<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.788.26480" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b0b8caba-aa6e-4a7b-aa2a-f2dce47a0c2c" ID-GBIF-Taxon="148657031" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-788-167" ID-ZBK="66FDB440E3EB455EB1F0EF6CF86E60BA" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-788-167" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 788" ModsDocTitle="A revision of Admetovis Grote, with the description of a new species from western North America (Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Hadenini)" checkinTime="1539050144519" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Crabo, Lars G. &amp; Schmidt, B. Christian" docDate="2018" docId="92E884B95FA1A1E1E2BCE1B198BB390B" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 788: 167-181" docOrigin="ZooKeys 788" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.788.26480" docTitle="Admetovis Grote 1873" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="172" masterDocId="FFE119434E62FFFAE06D3811FFBE222A" masterDocTitle="A revision of Admetovis Grote, with the description of a new species from western North America (Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Hadenini)" masterLastPageNumber="181" masterPageNumber="167" pageId="2" pageNumber="169" updateTime="1643470615174" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of Admetovis Grote, with the description of a new species from western North America (Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Hadenini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Crabo, Lars G.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Schmidt, B. Christian</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>788</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>167</mods:start>
<mods:end>181</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.788.26480</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.788.26480</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-788-167</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">66FDB440E3EB455EB1F0EF6CF86E60BA</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">66FDB440E3EB455EB1F0EF6CF86E60BA</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="148657031" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:92E884B95FA1A1E1E2BCE1B198BB390B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/92E884B95FA1A1E1E2BCE1B198BB390B" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="172" pageId="2" pageNumber="169">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="169" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="169">
<taxonomicName authority="Grote, 1873" authorityName="Grote" authorityYear="1873" class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="169" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis Grote, 1873</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="169" type="type species">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="169">Type species.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="169">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis oxymorus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="169" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oxymorus">Admetovis oxymorus</taxonomicName>
Grote, 1873 by monotypy.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="171" pageId="2" pageNumber="169" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="169">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="171" pageId="2" pageNumber="169">
Adults. Males and females similar in size and habitus, medium-sized (forewing length 17-21 mm) long-winged, stout noctuid moths; distinguished by combination of densely hairy eyes and gray forewing with a whitish, light tan, and reddish brown flame-like mark in both shape and colorfrom the medial reniform stigma to the jagged subterminal line. Head - Male antenna beaded weakly with slight constriction between segments, anterior, posterior, and ventral sides setose with innumerable short fine cilia; female antenna simple with few short lateral cilia. Scape whitish to gray tan, with ventral acute tuft. Eye normal size, densely setose. Labial palpus porrect, third segment length ~ ⅓ 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
second segment. Haustellum normal. Frons rounded, scales short, hair-like, forked, tan, brown, or gray brown. Dorsal head scales longer, forked, tan, gray, orange tan, sculpted weakly with paramedian dorsal and ventral protuberances. Thorax - Scales long, hair-like, forked, and scattered trifurcate, light tan, orange tan, and chestnut brown; appearing golden tan, with sculpted broad pale median tufts on mesothorax and metathorax and red-brown paramedian tufts on metathorax; prothoracic collar similar; appearing golden tan with pale-edged red-brown posterior band; tegula scales mostly white-tipped gray, forked; appearing gray with tan to red-brown medial edge. Legs: Lateral foretibia with row of 4-6 long, stout, slightly recurved, claw-like setae, proximal and distal longest; mid- and hindlegs lacking modified setae. Tarsal segments except apical segment with three rows of ventral spiniform setae. Wings: Forewing: Length 2.3-2.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width; apex pointed bluntly, outer margin slightly to moderately scalloped between veins; dorsal scales flat, fine toothed, elongate to triangular, white, gray, tan, and chestnut brown; ground color gray, darkest at costa and in cell, lightest at base; basal area posterior to vein 1A+2A light tan with anterior chestnut border; medial area distal to reniform spot and postmedial area whitish tan to tan, palest medially, forming with subterminal line and preceding chestnut shade a 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“flame”">&quot;flame&quot;</normalizedToken>
mark on distal ⅓ of wing; basal and antemedial lines double, gray with slightly lighter filling, undulating, perpendicular to wing axis; medial line dark gray, faint, diffuse; postmedial line thin, gray, faint, usually incomplete, scalloped strongly with points extended as thin dark lines and spots on veins, strongly oblique to wing axis from costa to posterior reniform stigma, less strongly to posterior margin; subterminal line thin, white to tan, bordered medially by prominent chestnut-brown and dark brown to black shade, darkest in fold, next darkest opposite reniform stigma, toothed to outer margin at apex and on M1, M3, CuA1, and 1A+2A, concave basad in fold; terminal line thin, black; fringe gray, striped, base pale tan or brown, pale transverse checkering at veins; claviform stigma dark gray to black, incomplete, apex darkest, short and broad, reaching mid-medial area, filling light gray; orbicular stigma black or chestnut brown, relatively large, ovoid to weakly figure-eight-shaped, filled variably with light gray, darker gray, light tan, and brown; reniform stigma moderately large, kidney shaped, usually with absent posterior and distal outline but evident due to whitish 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="170" start="start">filling</pageBreakToken>
that contributes to palest portion of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“flame”">&quot;flame&quot;</normalizedToken>
mark. Hindwing: Margin between M1 and M3 straight or concave; ground color pure white or slightly mottled light tan to brownish gray; veins, discal spot, and terminal line light to dark gray; fringe white to light gray with darker stripes, paler than ground. Abdomen. Male with or without basal coremata on segment I and pockets on ventrolateral segment III; when present weak, comprised of few filaments attached directly to base with pockets shallow, or strong, paint brush-like, filaments arising from rod with bulblike base, sometimes with very small medial accessory brushes, with pockets deep. Dorsal tufts on segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
. Female sternite VII sclerotized on distal half, with posterior median cleft 0.33-0.58 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
segment length, blunt posterolateral lobes on side of cleft cover ostium bursae and part of ventral segment VIII. Male genitalia: Uncus relatively short, curved ventrad, base cylindrical, distal half widened and flattened dorso-ventrally, slightly concave dorsally with flange-like raised edges, tapering to truncate apex with small ventral spine; dorsal edges and ventral apex with numerous short setae. Juxta broadly shield shaped, wider than tall, smooth (
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. similaris" pageId="3" pageNumber="170" rank="species" species="similaris">A. similaris</taxonomicName>
) or with median thorn-like spine directed posterodorsad (2 species). Valve length ~ 5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, S-shaped with slight curve dorsad near mid-point and 90° lateral bend distal to clasper at ⅔ distance from base to apex, tapered evenly from broad base to end of clasper, narrowing abruptly at bend to thin neck of cucullus, ventral margin of mid valve thickened with short blunt lateral projection ventral to distal clasper; sacculus length 0.4-0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
valve, sclerotized strongly, extending to or slightly above dorsal valve, distal costal margin near dorsal attachment of valve humped dorsad or anvil shaped, covered densely with minute setae; clasper strongly sclerotized, a bowl-like concavity dorsal and distal to sacculus, distal margin a narrow flange-like rim extended to blunt triangular dorsal and broad convex ventral projections, dorsal projection longer than (two species) or similar (one species) to ventral projection; digitus absent; cucullus triangular, 0.6-1.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
mid-valve width, with slightly rounded margin bearing simple corona of 15-25 claw-like setae. Phallus tubular, length 6-7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width. Vesica length (including right and left limbs) 1.0-1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
phallus, bent slightly ventrad at base then divided into nearly equal limbs directed 90° right and left to form with phallus a 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“T;”">&quot;T;&quot;</normalizedToken>
right limb comprised of distal vesica, tapered to ductus ejaculatorius at apex, with subapical broad short ventral diverticulum; left limb variable between species, tapering to conical or thin apical cornutus, bearing an additional thin acute cornutus at dorsal base (absent or diminutive in some specimens of all species) and anteriorly-directed broad conical subapical diverticulum (lacking in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. icarus" pageId="3" pageNumber="170" rank="species" species="icarus">A. icarus</taxonomicName>
). Female genitalia: Papilla analis asymmetrically conical, apex near dorsum, length 1-1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, covered sparsely on base and mid-portion by thin hair-like setae, more densely on apex by short setae. Abdominal segment VIII slightly longer than wide, venter length 2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
dorsum, covered sparsely by short hair-like setae; anterior apophyses length 0.57-0.77 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
abdominal segment VIII; posterior apophyses length 2.75-3.35 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
anterior apophyses. Ductus bursae length 1.14-1.32 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
abdominal segment VIII, strongly sclerotized, flattened dorsoventrally, length ~ 3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, ventral surface smooth, dorsum rugose; ostium bursae simple. Corpus bursae length 3.9-4.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
abdominal segment VIII, elongate, gourd shaped, anterior portion curved dorsad and leftward, membranous ovate anterior end widest, width 0.35-0.43 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
bursa length, 3-4 longitudinal irregular string- 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="171" start="start">of-beads</pageBreakToken>
signa evenly spaced on surface (left lateral signum absent in two species); appendix bursae projected ventrad and leftward from broad origin at junction with posterior corpus bursae at ductus bursae, length 0.12-0.25 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
total corpus bursae length, sclerotized lightly, apex blunt, ductus seminalis at dorsum anterior to apex.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="171" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="171">Distribution and ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="171">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
species occur in western North America, from the Rocky Mountains and Arizona-Mexico border west to the Pacific Coast and north to southern British Columbia. They undoubtedly occur in Mexico but the distribution there is unknown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="171">
The flight period of adults is from early spring (February or March) to as late as August depending on the species and locality. Based on limited information for 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis oxymorus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oxymorus">Admetovis oxymorus</taxonomicName>
the larvae feed on woody shrubs and are most likely climbing cutworms (
<bibRefCitation author="McFarland, N" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Lepidopterists' Society" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" pagination="112 - 125" title="Larval foodplant records for 106 species of North American moths." volume="29" year="1975">McFarland 1975</bibRefCitation>
). All species in the genus are nocturnal and are attracted readily to light.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="172" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" type="discussion">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="171">Discussion.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="171">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
was historically classified in the subfamily 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="subfamily" subfamily="Hadeninae">Hadeninae</taxonomicName>
, where it was placed since the early twentieth century (
<bibRefCitation author="Hampson, GF" journalOrPublisher="Taylor and Francis, London" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" title="Hadeninae. Catalogue of the Phalaenae Lepidoptera in the British Museum. Volume 5." year="1905">Hampson 1905</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="McDunnough, JH" journalOrPublisher="ZooKeys" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" url="https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.146941" year="1938">McDunnough 1938</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Hodges, RW et al." journalOrPublisher="Classey EW, London" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" title="Check List of the Lepidoptera of America north of Mexico." year="1982">Hodges et al. 1982</bibRefCitation>
). It was reassigned recently to the tribe 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="subfamily" subfamily="Noctuinae">Noctuinae</taxonomicName>
: 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Lafontaine, JD" journalOrPublisher="ZooKeys" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" pagination="1 - 239" title="Annotated check list of the Noctuoidea (Insecta, Lepidoptera) of North America north of Mexico." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.40.414" volume="40" year="2010">Lafontaine and Schmidt 2010</bibRefCitation>
) stemming from changes in the composition of the 
<taxonomicName family="Noctuidae" lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="family">Noctuidae</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Fibiger, M" journalOrPublisher="Esperiana" pageId="13" pageNumber="180" pagination="7 - 92" title="A review of the higher classification of the Noctuoidea (Lepidoptera) - with special reference to the Holarctic fauna." volume="11" year="2005">Fibiger and Lafontaine 2005</bibRefCitation>
). Although the higher classification, including the recognition of 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
as a tribe, is fairly recent (
<bibRefCitation author="Fibiger, M" journalOrPublisher="Esperiana" pageId="13" pageNumber="180" pagination="7 - 92" title="A review of the higher classification of the Noctuoidea (Lepidoptera) - with special reference to the Holarctic fauna." volume="11" year="2005">Fibiger and Lafontaine 2005</bibRefCitation>
) the relationship of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
to other genera in this tribe is not obvious and had not been recognized widely. More recent molecular approaches to noctuid classification based on mtDNA barcode sequence data (
<bibRefCitation author="Zahiri, R" journalOrPublisher="Entomological Press, Soro" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" url="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0178548" year="2017">Zahiri et al. 2017</bibRefCitation>
) support the current classification of North American 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
in that nearly all included genera cluster together, but with the exception of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
- this genus instead groups with genera in the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Hadenini">Hadenini</taxonomicName>
, which Godfrey also indicated as being the most closely related group to the orthosiine genera. This warrants a re-examination of 
<bibRefCitation author="Godfrey, GL" journalOrPublisher="United States Department of Agriculture, Technical Bulletin" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" pagination="1 - 265" title="A review and reclassification of larvae of the subfamily Hadeninae (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) of America north of Mexico." volume="1450" year="1972">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Godfrey’s">Godfrey's</normalizedToken>
(1972)
</bibRefCitation>
interpretation of larval hypopharynx structure, which forms the basis of the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
as currently defined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="171">
<bibRefCitation author="Godfrey, GL" journalOrPublisher="United States Department of Agriculture, Technical Bulletin" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" pagination="1 - 265" title="A review and reclassification of larvae of the subfamily Hadeninae (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) of America north of Mexico." volume="1450" year="1972">Godfrey (1972)</bibRefCitation>
included nine genera in the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Orthosia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthosia" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Orthosia</taxonomicName>
group (&quot;Group 8&quot;), noting that two other genus-groups were likely closely related based on the morphology of the hypopharynx, namely the spining pattern and especially the transverse cleft, the latter shared across the three groups. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Godfrey’s">Godfrey's</normalizedToken>
three 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“transverse-cleft”">&quot;transverse-cleft&quot;</normalizedToken>
groups comprise the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Anarta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Anarta" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Anarta</taxonomicName>
-group, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Polia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polia" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Nemertea" rank="genus">Polia</taxonomicName>
-group and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Orthosia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthosia" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Orthosia</taxonomicName>
-group, the first two now combined in the tribe 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Hadenini">Hadenini</taxonomicName>
and the third comprising the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
. Although Godfrey separated the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Hadenini">Hadenini</taxonomicName>
morphologically by two characters (lack of setae above the spinneret and larger spines on the proximolateral hypopharynx in 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
), exceptions occur in both tribes (
<bibRefCitation author="Godfrey, GL" journalOrPublisher="United States Department of Agriculture, Technical Bulletin" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" pagination="1 - 265" title="A review and reclassification of larvae of the subfamily Hadeninae (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) of America north of Mexico." volume="1450" year="1972">Godfrey 1972</bibRefCitation>
). 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
differs in the shape of the spinneret and the finely granular (vs. smooth) larval integument from all other 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
, but these characters appear to be autapomorphic because they also do not occur in the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Hadenini">Hadenini</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="172" pageId="4" pageNumber="171">
Importantly, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
is the sole constituent of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Godfrey’s">Godfrey's</normalizedToken>
Group 8 where adults do not emerge in early spring. Most species in the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
emerge very early in the season, and some, such as 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Orthosia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthosia praeses" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="praeses">Orthosia praeses</taxonomicName>
(Grote) and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Egira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Egira hiemalis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hiemalis">Egira hiemalis</taxonomicName>
(Grote), are the first non-overwintering moths to fly in late winter. While 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. similaris" pageId="4" pageNumber="171" rank="species" species="similaris">A. similaris</taxonomicName>
can be found as 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="172" start="start">early</pageBreakToken>
as February in the deserts of the Southwest, most 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
differ from other orthosiines in that they fly later in the year from late spring through summer.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
Finally, the male valves of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
, S-shaped with triangular cuculli, are more similar to those of most hadenine moths (e.g., as shown for European species in 
<bibRefCitation author="Hacker, H" journalOrPublisher="Entomological Press, Soro" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" title="Hadeninae I. Noctuidae Europaeae, volume 4." year="2002">Hacker et al. 2002</bibRefCitation>
) than they are to orthosiines (shown similarly in 
<bibRefCitation author="Ronkay, L" journalOrPublisher="Entomological Press, Soro" pageId="14" pageNumber="181" title="Hadeninae II. Noctuidae Europaeae, volume 5." year="2001">Ronkay et al. 2001</bibRefCitation>
), as are the everted vesicae. Females of both tribes are rather simple in genital structure and as a result are not highly diagnostic.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
The weight of evidence (barcodes, biology, and adult genitalia structure versus somewhat equivocal larva hypopharyngeal structure) suggests that 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
is better classified in the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rank="tribe" tribe="Hadenini">Hadenini</taxonomicName>
rather than the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rank="tribe" tribe="Orthosiini">Orthosiini</taxonomicName>
. A definitive phylogeny of the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rank="subfamily" subfamily="Noctuinae">Noctuinae</taxonomicName>
tribes, using multiple molecular and morphological markers, is still needed. As such, we recommend 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
as a fertile subject for further investigation.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="172" type="key to species of admetovis (adults)">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
Key to species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Admetovis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Admetovis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Admetovis</taxonomicName>
(adults)
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
<table pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. similaris" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rank="species" species="similaris">A. similaris</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rowspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. oxymorus" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rank="species" species="oxymorus">A. oxymorus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="172">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. icarus" pageId="5" pageNumber="172" rank="species" species="icarus">A. icarus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>