<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.678.12543" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2cadf614-c290-47bf-a7af-960209b2c21a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="131868945" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-678-97" ID-ZBK="4E52EF58511642F5B847531E0045B229" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:02A25235-8C44-4C3D-9270-AAD7BB9E9EC6" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-678-97" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 678" ModsDocTitle="Review of the species of Leptomias Faust from Sichuan, China (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae)" checkinTime="1496887656192" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Song, Zhenzhen, Ren, Li, Zhang, Runzhi &amp; Zhou, Chenggang" docDate="2017" docId="B5ED2388325FC8831757B72DEAA06747" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 678: 97-119" docOrigin="ZooKeys 678" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.678.12543" docTitle="Leptomias verticalis Ren, Zhang &amp; Song, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="02A25235-8C44-4C3D-9270-AAD7BB9E9EC6" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="98" masterDocId="FFFD6731FFDF7224DB49FFF0EC2BC611" masterDocTitle="Review of the species of Leptomias Faust from Sichuan, China (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae)" masterLastPageNumber="119" masterPageNumber="97" pageId="0" pageNumber="97" updateTime="1643569765036" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the species of Leptomias Faust from Sichuan, China (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Song, Zhenzhen</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ren, Li</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhang, Runzhi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhou, Chenggang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>678</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>97</mods:start>
<mods:end>119</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.678.12543</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.678.12543</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-678-97</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">4E52EF58511642F5B847531E0045B229</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">4E52EF58511642F5B847531E0045B229</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="131868945" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:02A25235-8C44-4C3D-9270-AAD7BB9E9EC6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B5ED2388325FC8831757B72DEAA06747" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="98" pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="97" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/02A25235-8C44-4C3D-9270-AAD7BB9E9EC6" authority="Ren, Zhang &amp; Song" class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Leptomias" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Leptomias verticalis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="97" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="verticalis">Leptomias verticalis Ren, Zhang &amp; Song</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="97">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-9, 10-23
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="97" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
This new species resembles 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. ochrolineatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="97" rank="species" species="ochrolineatus">L. ochrolineatus</taxonomicName>
Chen, 1987 but differs by the following characters: elytra in lateral view abruptly sloping posteriorly, dorsal edge of slope of declivity straight, almost parallel to anterior margin; elytra in dorsal view at apical 1/3 with symmetrical crescent-shaped dark brown patches.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="98" pageId="0" pageNumber="97" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Holotype, male. Measurements (mm): Standard length: 8.00; pronotal length: 3.00; pronotal width: 3.00; elytral length: 5.00; elytral width: 3.20; rostral length: 1.30; rostral width: 1.20.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Habitus and colour (Figs 1, 2): Body elongate-oval; integument dark reddish brown, antennae and legs reddish brown; with coppery to white to pale brown to brown scales, dorsal side of rostrum and apex of femora and tibiae with metallic turquoise scales; scales moderately dense, tessellate, contiguous but not overlapping, on dorsal side of rostrum moderately dense, oval to polygonal, behind epistome sparse, clearly different in colour from others, on lateral and ventral surfaces of rostrum moderately dense, around eyes penniform, elongate-oval, absent from anterior part of antennal scrobes but dense, penniform along posterior part, on pronotum dense, round to oval to polygonal, on elytra polygonal, moderately dense, at apical 1/3 forming symmetrical crescent-shaped dark brown patches, on ventrites dense, penniform, on legs dense, round to elongate-oval; body sparsely covered with recumbent to suberect, short and slightly fine, lanceolate setae, setae on rostrum subrecumbent, fine, lanceolate, sparse, on scapes and desmomeres 1-7 long, recumbent, fine, dense, on pronotum subrecumbent to erect, curved, on interstriae subrecumbent to erect, moderately thick, sparse, on tibiae long, moderately dense, lanceolate, on femora recumbent, short, fine, moderately dense.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Head (Fig. 3): Moderately convex; with small, sparse punctures and dense, tiny granules, each granule covered by a scale; eyes convex, moderately oval, with deep and fine circumocular sulcus along dorsal and anterior edge; between eyes moderately convex, higher than dorsal surface of rostrum in lateral view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
Rostrum (Fig. 3): In dorsal view 1.13
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, apex narrower than base; base slightly narrower than distance at midpoint between eyes; dorsal surface with narrow and deep median sulcus extending from posterior margin of frons to midpoint between eyes; epistome 
<normalizedToken originalValue="V–shaped">V-shaped</normalizedToken>
, posterior angle slightly less than 90°, posteriorly carinate; mandibular scars oval; ventral margin of scrobes visible in dorsal view from antennal insertion to base of rostrum; prementum with four setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
<taxonomicName genus="Antennae" lsidName="Antennae" pageId="0" pageNumber="97" rank="genus">Antennae</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 7): Scapes slender, subclavate, extending to region between midpoint and posterior margin of eyes at rest, 0.85
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as funicle; funicles with desmomere 1 1.38
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than 2, 1 and 2 elongate-clavate, 3.06
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than all others (compared with the shortest desmomere 5), 3 and 4 equal in length, shortly clavate, 0.63
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as 2, 5 elongate moniliform, 0.72
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as 4, 6 1.17
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than 5, shortly clavate, 7 as long as 3, shortly clavate; clubs with similar pubescence throughout, elongate-oval, 0.33
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as desmomeres, 3-segmented, basal segment 1.33
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than segment 2, this 0.89
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as 3, 3 with a marked annulus at midpoint.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
Figures 1-9. Habitus of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Leptomias" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Leptomias verticalis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="97" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="verticalis">Leptomias verticalis</taxonomicName>
sp. n.: 1 male paratype, dorsal view 2 male paratype, lateral view 3 male paratype, head and rostrum, anterior view 4 female paratype, dorsal view 5 female paratype, lateral view 6 female paratype, head and rostrum, anterior view 7 male paratype, antenna, anterior view 8 male paratype, right protibia, anterior view 9 female paratype, right protibia, anterior view. Scale bars 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Pronotum: subquadratic in dorsal outline, strongly convex; anterior margin truncate, posterior margin medially slightly produced caudad; sides strongly rounded, greatest width at midpoint, gradually narrowing towards both ends, anterior margin slightly shorter than posterior one; disc smooth, median sulcus absent; posterior margin narrowly and slightly carinate; dorsal surface with dense, small and round tubercles, each tubercle with 1 scale on top; postocular lobes absent, vibrissae blond, moderately long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Proventriculus (Fig. 17): Well developed, with eight sclerotized basal plates, each plate bearing two longitudinal rows of projecting setae, brush-like, apically ending with a trapezoidal zone covered with pointed inward denticles.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Scutellum: Not exposed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Elytra (Figs 4-5): In dorsal view elongate-ovate, anterior margin medially slightly produced and elevated as prominent flange, without humeral callus; lateral margins slightly diverging from base to basal 1/5, there widest apart, then evenly converging towards narrowly rounded apex; in lateral view with posterior declivity straight and not overhanging elytral apex; with ten complete, distinct, narrow, moderately deep, punctate striae; punctures minute, moderately dense, intervals between punctures narrow; interstriae wide, slightly eminent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">Abdomen (Fig. 10): Ventrite 1 depressed in middle, slightly convex at sides, in middle longer than 2, suture between 1 and 2 slightly curved forward in middle,; ventrite 2 moderately convex, as long as 3 and 4 combined; ventrite 5 as long as 1 in middle, moderately convex, broadly rounded at apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
Metendosternite (Fig. 11): Stalk 0.39
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as furcal arms, trapezoidal and transverse, anterior part of longitudinal flange slightly shorter than posterior part; hemiductus inconspicuous; anterior tendons positioned almost at apical 1/3 of furcal arms; furcal arms robust, apically not bifurcate, diverging at nearly 60°in relation to longitudinal flange.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
Legs: Procoxae situated close to front margin of prothorax; contiguous, inner side flat. Protibiae (Fig. 8) subcylindrical, slightly sinuate, bent inwards at apical 1/3; inner margin from basal 1/5 to apex arcuate, with 10 large, slightly curved, sharp teeth, each tooth with spiniform seta just behind it; Mesotibiae similar but teeth slightly smaller; metatibiae with inner margin adentate, apical 1/3 with much denser and longer setae. Tarsi slender, tarsomere 1 nearly 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than 2, much wider than 2, 3 wider than the others, deeply bilobed, 5 slender; claws connate in basal half.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="98" pageId="0" pageNumber="97">
Genitalia and terminalia: Sternite VIII (Fig. 12) divided into 2 transversely orientated, crescent-shaped hemisternites, each laterally acuminate, with anterior margin moderately sinuate and posterior margin arcuate. Sternite IX (Fig. 12) with basal plate bilobed, each lobe with inner margin almost straight and outer margin 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Σ–shaped">Σ-shaped</normalizedToken>
; spiculum gastrale 0.90
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as aedeagus, almost straight, strongly sclerotized, ante 
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="98" start="start">rior</pageBreakToken>
1/5 slightly curved. Penis (Figs 13, 14) in dorsal view 3.90 mm long and 0.50 mm wide, temones 1.15 mm long; lateral margins subparallel in middle, minimally expanded at ostium level, thereafter slightly rounded and triangularly converging, though very narrowly rounded apex; in lateral view curved, caudally of ostium strongly constricted towards apex. Tegmen (Fig. 15) 0.46
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as penis, ring narrow, parameroid lobes more sclerotized in basal half, separated from each other; tegminal apodeme slender, more sclerotized, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Y–shaped">Y-shaped</normalizedToken>
with basal piece, slightly curved at apex.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="98">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">
Figures 10-23. Abdominal and genital structures of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Leptomias" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Leptomias verticalis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="98" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="verticalis">Leptomias verticalis</taxonomicName>
sp. n.: 10 male paratype, ventrites, ventral view 11 male paratype, metendosternite, dorsal view 12 male paratype, sternites VIII and IX, dorsal view 13 male paratype, aedeagus, dorsal view 14 male paratype, aedeagus, lateral view 15 male paratype, tegmen, dorsal view 16 male paratype, pygidium, dorsal view 17 male paratype, proventriculus 18 female paratype, ventrites, ventral view (g - laterobasal groove) 19 female paratype, sternite VIII and genitalia, lateral view 20 female paratype, gonocoxites and styli, dorsal view 21 female paratype, bursal sclerites, dorsolateral view 22 female paratype, spermatheca, lateral view 23 female paratype, pygidium, dorsal view. Scale bars 10-19, 23: 1 mm; 20-22: 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="98" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">Male paratype. Measurements (in mm): Standard length: 8.20; pronotal length: 3.20; pronotal width: 3.20; elytral length: 5.00; elytral width: 3.30; rostral length: 1.35; rostral width: 1.20; inner margin of protibiae with eleven blunt teeth (apex worn out), mesotibiae with ten small sharp teeth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">
Female paratypes. Measurements (in mm): Standard length: 10.40-11.30; pronotal length: 3.00-3.20; pronotal width: 3.10-3.20; elytral length: 6.00-6.70; elytral width: 3.70-3.90; rostral length: 1.29-1.40; rostral width: 1.28-1.32. Pronotum with anterior and posterior margins not truncate, slightly curved; greatest width just behind midpoint. Elytra much longer and wider than in male; in lateral view with posterior declivity straight and overhanging elytral apex; ventrite 5 (Fig. 18) parabolic, apical 1/2 with median longitudinal ridge, slightly elevated, with basal longitudinal groove on each side close to lateral margins, extending from base to midpoint (Fig. 18, g). Inner margin of pro- and mesotibiae with 8-10 larger and sharper teeth than in male, inner margin of metatibiae with 10 small and sharp teeth. Sternite VIII (Fig. 19) with spiculum ventrale clavate, wide and straight; lamina tightly folded, in lateral view triangular, strongly sclerotized, ventral margin angular in middle. Ovipositor (Figs 19, 20) with gonocoxites shorter than sternite VIII, folded along middle, lateral margins strongly sclerotized, styli relatively small, cylindrical, with 2-3 long setae inserted apically, more strongly sclerotized than gonocoxites. Bursal sclerites (Fig. 21) near point of union of spermathecal duct and oviduct, with 1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="V–shaped">V-shaped</normalizedToken>
sclerite and 1 small sclerite on each side, dorsal surface of sclerites with small and sharp conical spines. Spermatheca (Fig. 22) with corpus short, trapezoidal; cornu elongate, strongly curved into a narrow 
<normalizedToken originalValue="U–shape">U-shape</normalizedToken>
, apically gradually narrowed, apex sinuate and acuminate; nodulus prominent, tube-like, apically gradually narrowed, subcontiguous with and angled at about 60°in relation to ramus; ramus prominent, elongate trapezoid, 2.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of nodulus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="98" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">
Holotype, ♂: (white, printed): 
<normalizedToken originalValue="四川九龙县南">四川九龙县南</normalizedToken>
[
<normalizedToken originalValue="Sìchuān">Sichuan</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Jǐulóngxiàn">Jǐulongxian</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="nán">nan</normalizedToken>
] J08 / 2120m 
<normalizedToken originalValue="核桃林">核桃林</normalizedToken>
[
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hétáolín">Hetaolin</normalizedToken>
] 
<normalizedToken originalValue="杯诱">杯诱</normalizedToken>
[
<normalizedToken originalValue="bēiyòu">bēiyou</normalizedToken>
] / 2001.VII.9-12 
<normalizedToken originalValue="于晓东">于晓东</normalizedToken>
[
<normalizedToken originalValue="Yú">Yu</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Xiǎodōng">Xiǎodōng</normalizedToken>
] / 
<normalizedToken originalValue="中科院动物所">中科院动物所</normalizedToken>
[
<normalizedToken originalValue="Zhōngkēyuàn">Zhōngkēyuan</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Dòngwùsuǒ">Dongwusuǒ</normalizedToken>
, printed]; (white, printed): IOZ(E) 1965001. Paratypes (1♂, 4♀): 1 ♂: (white, printed): same data as holotype except IOZ(E) 1965002; 2 ♀: (white, printed): same data as holotype except IOZ(E) 1965003, IOZ(E) 1965004; 2 ♀: (white, printed): same data as holotype except J09 / 2200m 
<normalizedToken originalValue="青冈灌丛">青冈灌丛</normalizedToken>
[
<normalizedToken originalValue="Qīnggāng">Qīnggang</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Guàncóng">Guancong</normalizedToken>
] and IOZ(E) 1965005, IOZ(E) 1965006.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="98" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">The specific epithet refers to the straight declivity of the elytra in lateral view.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="98" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="98">Sichuan (China).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>