<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.77.938" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4655c75d-7992-4f6d-b702-d5dd949bef15" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159361175" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-77-65" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-77-65" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 77" ModsDocTitle="Review of the genus Merulempista Roesler, 1967 (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) from China, with description of two new species" checkinTime="1451250820801" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Ren, Yingdang, Liu, Shurong &amp; Li, Houhun" docDate="2011" docId="360BEA0CAB64F455C43EAFFD9450DC85" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 77: 65-75" docOrigin="ZooKeys 77" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.77.938" docTitle="Merulempista rubriptera Li &amp; Ren, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="69" masterDocId="FF8E937D3C1CFFA2FD16686BED77FFFE" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Merulempista Roesler, 1967 (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) from China, with description of two new species" masterLastPageNumber="75" masterPageNumber="65" pageId="2" pageNumber="67" updateTime="1643553418572" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the genus Merulempista Roesler, 1967 (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) from China, with description of two new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ren, Yingdang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liu, Shurong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Houhun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>77</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>65</mods:start>
<mods:end>75</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.77.938</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.77.938</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-77-65</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="159361175" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:360BEA0CAB64F455C43EAFFD9450DC85" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/360BEA0CAB64F455C43EAFFD9450DC85" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="69" pageId="2" pageNumber="67">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="67" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="67">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:46528BF5-9166-41A0-87E8-BDD379022DDF" authority="Li &amp; Ren" class="Insecta" family="Pyralidae" genus="Merulempista" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Merulempista rubriptera" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rubriptera">Merulempista rubriptera Li &amp; Ren</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="67">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 3711
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="67" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="67">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="67">
Holotype ♂ - China,Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region: Erdaoqiao, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Eji’naqi">Eji'naqi</normalizedToken>
(41.56°N, 101.04°E), 927 m, 18.VII.2006, coll. Xinpu Wang and Xiangfeng Shi, genitalia slide no. LSR09083. Paratypes: 2 ♂♂, 2 ♀♀, same data as for holotype except dated 17-18.VII.2006.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="67" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="67">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="67">This species is characterized by the rosy-colored forewing with a longitudinal greyish black stripe at base below costa. It can be distinguished from its congeners by the costa with a triangular distal process arising from 2/3 length of valva, the stout phallus with three thornlike cornuti located at middle in the male genitalia; and the antrum angularly protruding backward posterolaterally in the female genitalia.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="2" pageNumber="67" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="67">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="2" pageNumber="67">
Adult (Fig. 3). Wingspan 23.5-24.5 mm. Head khaki in male, pale yellowish brown in female. Antenna with scape reddish brown dorsally, yellow ventrally; flagellum yellowish brown ringed with brown; male sinus with shining deep greyish brown mixed with rosy scales, somewhat shelllike, pale yellow on ventral surface. Labial palpus pale yellowish white, densely covered with rosy scales ventrally, in female third segment tinged with black ventrodistally, far exceeding vertex; second 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="68" start="start">segment</pageBreakToken>
shorter than diameter of eye, about 4 times length of third; third segment rather blunt apically. Patagium in male whitish yellowish tinged with pale yellowish brown, in female densely covered with greyish white-tipped rosy scales. Thorax and tegula in male rosy, in female greyish-brown tinged with rosy. Forewing rosy, with scattered greyish white and black scales in distal half, with a longitudinal greyish black stripe at base just below costa; posterior margin yellowish white at base; antemedian line yellowish white, straight, situated beyond basal 1/3, its posterior half tinged with black on inside, ocherous yellow on outside; postmedian and subterminal lines greyish white, slightly sinuate, nearly parallel; cilia rosy mixed with greyish brown, with a fine yellowish white basal line. Hindwing pale brown; cilia with basal 1/3 greyish brown, distal 2/3 greyish white. Legs rosy on outside, yellowish white on inside; tarsi brownish black, ringed with whitish yellow at apex of each segment, lined with short black spines on inside.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="69" pageId="3" pageNumber="68" type="male genitalia">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="68">Male genitalia</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="69" pageId="3" pageNumber="68">
(Fig. 7). Uncus somewhat trapezoid, with sparse setae laterally, blunt posteriorly. Gnathos slightly shorter than 1/2 length of uncus, heavily sclerotized, wide basally, tapering to hooked apex. Costa with distal process triangular, uprising obliquely outward from about 2/3 length of valva. Valva narrow basally, widened and arciform beyond middle ventrally, slightly narrowed toward bluntly rounded apex distally, densely setose; sacculus narrow, about 1/3 length of valva; clasper thumb-shaped. Vinculum large U-shaped, longer than valva, arciform anteriorly. Juxta slightly elliptical, concave deeply at middle on posterior margin. Phallus stout, about same length 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="69" start="start">as</pageBreakToken>
valva; three thornlike cornuti located at middle of phallus, median one longest and curved basally. Eighth sternite and culcita shown in figure 7a.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="69" type="female genitalia">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="69">Female genitalia</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="69">(Fig. 11). Papillae anales triangular, narrowed to bluntly rounded posterior margin. Eighth abdominal segment longer than wide, anterior margin roundly protruding, posterior margin straight. Apophyses anteriores about as long as apophyses posteriores, slightly dilated at base. Antrum weakly sclerotized, deeply concave at middle on posterior margin, angularly protruding backward posterolaterally. Ductus bursae membranous, with longitudinal rumples. Corpus bursae membranous, elongate ovate; large, more or less rectangular accessory sac arising from left side of corpus bursae posteriorly, densely covered with granules, ductus seminalis from its apex; signa comprised of two clusters of short spines, placed posteriorly.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="69" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="69">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="69">China (Inner Mongolia).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="69" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="69">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="69">The specific epithet is derived from the Latin ruber (= red)and the suffix -pteron (= wing), in reference to the color of forewing.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>