<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6292992" ID-GBIF-Dataset="620aac46-b4c8-42a1-a0a0-409792b70c2b" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100130616" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6292992" ModsDocID="3948" checkinTime="1243374478140" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Forel, A." docDate="1893" docId="7C14F30A84B098553741AB6BB5049EDD" docLanguage="en" docName="3948" docOrigin="Transactions of the Entomological Society of London 1893" docSource="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/social_insects/ants/publications/3948/3948.pdf" docTitle="Pheidole susannae subsp. obscurior , Forel" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="411" masterDocId="3C86B8CE88F3E20382761CE3CF3BA529" masterDocTitle="Formicides de l'Antille St. Vincent. Récoltées par Mons. H. H. Smith." masterLastPageNumber="418" masterPageNumber="333" pageNumber="410" updateTime="1645845610579" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Formicides de l'Antille St. Vincent. Récoltées par Mons. H. H. Smith.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Forel, A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1893</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1893</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>333</mods:start>
<mods:end>418</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://research.amnh.org/entomology/social_insects/ants/publications/3948/3948.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">3948</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5E6A481F-664E-428C-A636-08D4BD5A1EF0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6292992" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100130616" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6292992" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:7C14F30A84B098553741AB6BB5049EDD" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7C14F30A84B098553741AB6BB5049EDD" lastPageNumber="411" pageNumber="410">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="410">
6. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:151595" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Pheidole" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Pheidole susannae obscurior Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="410" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="susannae" subSpecies="obscurior">Pheidole susannae, Forel, r. obscurior, Forel</taxonomicName>
,
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="410">[[ worker ]] [[ soldier ]] [[ queen ]] [[ male ]]. (No. 31 a a 31 d et &quot; plantations de cocos &quot;).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="410">[[ queen ]] (inedite). L. 6, 2 mill. Tete plus reticulee que chez le [[ soldier ]], un peu echancree derriere; les rides de la tete se prolongent sur l'occiput. Mesonotum et cotes du metanotum rides en long; ces derniers en outre finement reticules-ponctues ainsi que les n oe uds du pedicule qui ont des rides transversales. Base de l'abdomen striee et mate (finement reticulee-ponctuee). Beste de l'abdomen presque lisse et luisant, avec des points piligeres. Epines du metanotum mediocres; entre elles quelques rides transversales; face basale et face declive du reste lisses et luisantes. Thorax et abdomen, plutot eleves, non deprimes; thorax-plus large que la tete; abdomen grand. D'un brun noiratre; mandibules, articulations et funicules roussatres; tarses jaunatres. Ailes subhyalines; nervures et tache marginale d'un brun jaunatre. Du reste comme le [[ soldier ]].</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="410">[[ male ]] (inedit). L. 3, 6 a 3, 7 mill. Mandibules triangulaires, bidentees. Un peu moins etroit que les precedents. Metanotum avec deux faibles bourrelets longitudinaux; face basale un peu plus longue que la face declive. Lisse et luisant. N'a pas la longue pubescence du [[ soldier ]] et de la [[ queen ]]. Pilosite dressee comme chez l'ouvriere.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="410">D'un jaune brunatre sale. ' Tete d'un brun noiratre; dos du thorax presque entierement brunatre. Pattes, antennes et mandibules pales. Ailes comme chez la [[ queen ]].</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageNumber="410">(31). A rare species, forming large colonies. Formicarium generally in rotten wood. When disturbed these ants are rather pugnacious. The workers minor are active; the workers major move about heavily. The latter are not numerous.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="411">(31 a). Wallilobo Valley (leeward), 500 ft.; forest near a stream. Formicarium in very rotten wood; the passages extended through six or eight inches of the log, with several chambers, each about 1 x 1 / 2 in. The colony probably contained over 1000 individuals. Immature males were numerous. Only a few females could be found. Nov. 8 th.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="411">(31 b). Hermitage Estate, Cumberland Valley, 1000 ft. Dec. 1 st. Open hill-side near forest. Formicarium in a rotten stick on the ground. It extended irregularly through about 15 in. of the stick, with several chambers, each about 3 / 4 in. long, and half as wide and high. The colony may have contained 500 individuals, the workers major being about one-tenth as numerous as the workers minor. There were many immature males in this nest,. but I could find no female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="411">(31 c). Same locality and situation as the last, in another log. The nest did not differ from No. 31 b, except that the chambers were rather larger; the community probably contained over 1000 individuals. About twenty winged females were seen, but no males.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="411">(31 d). Upper Richmond Valley, 1500 ft.; forest by a stream; under rubbish near the water. No nest could be found.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>