<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6191517" ID-GBIF-Dataset="56fb15f0-b55b-4ce9-a9ad-d8a2f5a95029" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119419948" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6191517" checkinTime="1460401525037" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Williams, Kevin A., Brothers, Denis J. &amp; Pitts, James P." docDate="2011" docId="03BF6217D832214006B648D9FDE4FBC0" docLanguage="en" docName="zt03064p068.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 3064" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@c555e1e" docStyleName="zootaxa.2007.monograph" docTitle="Tobantilla Casal 1965" docType="treatment" docVersion="8" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="44" masterDocId="FF861A6FD833214306214C5EFF9CFFBC" masterDocTitle="New species of Tobantilla Casal, 1965 and a new genus and species, Gogoltilla chichikovi gen. et sp. nov., from Argentina (Hymenoptera: Mutillidae)" masterLastPageNumber="68" masterPageNumber="41" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" updateTime="1645388412927" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species of Tobantilla Casal, 1965 and a new genus and species, Gogoltilla chichikovi gen. et sp. nov., from Argentina (Hymenoptera: Mutillidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Williams, Kevin A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Brothers, Denis J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Pitts, James P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3064</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>41</mods:start>
<mods:end>68</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.278958</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">56fb15f0-b55b-4ce9-a9ad-d8a2f5a95029</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">278958</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F876C14A-074F-4EA4-9BCE-37CB7B0894CB</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6191517" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119419948" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6191517" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03BF6217D832214006B648D9FDE4FBC0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BF6217D832214006B648D9FDE4FBC0" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="1.[151,424,1159,1218]" box="[151,424,1159,1185]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,424,1159,1185]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" reason="1">
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" box="[151,424,1159,1185]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,424,1159,1185]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,274,1159,1185]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Tobantilla</emphasis>
Casal, 
<number box="[365,424,1159,1185]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="1965.0">1965</number>
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[151,424,1159,1218]" box="[151,281,1194,1218]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,273,1194,1218]" captionStart-0="FIGURES 1 – 6" captionStart-1="FIGURES 7 – 14" captionStart-2="FIGURES 15 – 18" captionStart-3="FIGURES 19 – 38" captionStart-4="FIGURE 39" captionStartId-0="5.[151,264,1969,1992]" captionStartId-1="6.[151,264,1742,1765]" captionStartId-2="8.[151,264,1656,1679]" captionStartId-3="10.[151,264,1672,1695]" captionStartId-4="12.[151,250,1315,1338]" captionTargetBox-0="[151,1436,411,1944]" captionTargetBox-1="[151,1436,193,1719]" captionTargetBox-2="[151,1436,700,1634]" captionTargetBox-3="[176,1419,215,1644]" captionTargetBox-4="[195,1400,384,1293]" captionTargetId-0="figure@5.[151,1436,411,1945]" captionTargetId-1="figure@6.[151,1436,193,1721]" captionTargetId-2="figure@8.[151,1436,700,1636]" captionTargetId-3="figure@10.[157,1429,193,1651]" captionTargetId-4="figure@12.[180,1407,370,1294]" captionTargetPageId-0="5" captionTargetPageId-1="6" captionTargetPageId-2="8" captionTargetPageId-3="10" captionTargetPageId-4="12" captionText-0="FIGURES 1 – 6. Tobantilla species, females, habitus, dorsal view. 1. T. aleatrix sp. nov.; holotype; 2. T. charrasca Casal; 3. T. frigidula (Cresson); 4. T. kolasma sp. nov., holotype; 5. T. krima sp. nov., holotype; 6. T. montonera Casal." captionText-1="FIGURES 7 – 14. Tobantilla species, females. 7 - 12. Habitus, lateral view. 7. T. aleatrix sp. nov., holotype; 8. T. charrasca Casal; 9. T. frigidula (Cresson); 10. T. kolasma sp. nov., holotype; 11. T. krima sp. nov., holotype; 12. T. montonera Casal. 13, 14. Pygidium (T 6). 13. T. frigidula; 14. T. aleatrix." captionText-2="FIGURES 15 – 18. Tobantilla species, males, habitus, lateral view. 15. T. andrikos sp. nov., holotype; 16. T. drosos sp. nov., holotype; 17. T. ephemeros sp. nov.; 18. T. xouthos sp. nov., holotype." captionText-3="FIGURES 19 – 38. Tobantilla species. 19 – 34. Male genitalia: dorsal view (left), ventral view (middle), lateral view of penis valve (above), and lateral view with penis valve removed (right). 19 – 22. T. andrikos sp. nov.; 23 – 26. T. drosos sp. nov.; 27 – 30. T. ephemeros sp. nov.; 31 – 34. T. xouthos sp. nov. 35 – 36. Male clypeus. 28. T. andrikos sp. nov.; 29. T. ephemeros sp. nov. 37, 38. Female pygidium (T 6). 37. T. frigidula (Cresson); 38. T. kolasma sp. nov." captionText-4="FIGURE 39. Distribution of Tobantilla species." httpUri-0="https://zenodo.org/record/278959/files/figure.png" httpUri-1="https://zenodo.org/record/278960/files/figure.png" httpUri-2="https://zenodo.org/record/278961/files/figure.png" httpUri-3="https://zenodo.org/record/278962/files/figure.png" httpUri-4="https://zenodo.org/record/278963/files/figure.png" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
Figs 
<number box="[215,273,1194,1218]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="20.0" valueMax="39.0" valueMin="1.0">1–39</number>
</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[151,896,1266,1320]" box="[151,793,1266,1288]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" box="[151,383,1266,1288]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[151,254,1266,1288]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Tobantilla</emphasis>
Casal, 
<number box="[329,383,1266,1288]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="1965.0">1965</number>
</taxonomicName>
. Rev. Soc. Mex. Hist. Nat. 
<number box="[658,687,1266,1288]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="25.0">25</number>
: 
<number box="[697,789,1266,1288]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="212.0" valueMax="215.0" valueMin="209.0">209–215</number>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,896,1297,1320]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="1.[151,896,1266,1320]" box="[151,896,1297,1320]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,290,1297,1320]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<typeStatus box="[151,204,1298,1319]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Type</typeStatus>
species.
</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" box="[297,645,1297,1319]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="montonera">
<emphasis box="[297,517,1297,1319]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Tobantilla montonera</emphasis>
Casal, 
<number box="[592,645,1297,1319]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="1965.0">1965</number>
</taxonomicName>
, by original designation.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="1.[151,1437,1363,2036]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,273,1363,1388]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
FEMALE. Distinguished from all other New World mutillid genera by the following combination of characters: the mesosoma is dorsally flattened or concave in lateral view and has a well defined scutellar scale; the dorsal and posterior propodeal faces are more or less perpendicular and usually separated by lateral transverse carinae; the tibial spurs are white or yellow, being paler than the tibiae and tarsi; the first metasomal segment is clearly petiolate and posteriorly constricted.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="1.[151,1437,1363,2036]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
MALE. Distinguished from other New World mutillid genera by the following combination of characters: the clypeus is anteriorly produced into either a medial tooth or a shallowly emarginate plate; the axillae are impunctate and asetose postero-dorsally and truncate posteriorly; the first metasomal segment is petiolate and posteriorly constricted; S 
<number box="[262,277,1652,1676]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="2.0">2</number>
lacks a median seta-filled pit; the pygidium is margined with posterolateral carinae; and brachyplumose setae are present, especially obvious on the head, propodeum and basal metasomal segments.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[151,1437,1363,2036]" lastBlockId="2.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,342,1723,1748]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Description.</emphasis>
FEMALE. T 
<number box="[498,512,1724,1748]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="2.0">2</number>
with paired pale integumental spots. 
<emphasis box="[948,1008,1724,1748]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Head</emphasis>
. Broadly transverse, dull, vertex and gena shallowly and coarsely reticulate, mostly clothed with stout lanceolate decumbent setae and scattered slender finely brachyplumose erect setae. Occipital carina well developed dorsally. Vertex posterolaterally with a subtriangular glabrous tubercle merging with occipital carina. Eye circular, protruding, ommatidia distinct. Antennal tubercles smooth, basally contiguous. Antennal scrobe with lateral carina, without dorsal carina. Clypeus with complete strong setose transverse carina above short smooth transverse concave area, ventral margin straightish medially. Malar space almost as high as combined length of pedicel + flagellomere 
<number box="[976,991,1940,1964]" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" value="1.0">1</number>
. Genal carina weak, irregular, ventrally reaching hypostomal carina and dorsally not reaching vertex. Hypostomal carina distinct, even, ending laterally at posterior mandibular condyle. Proboscidal and mandibular fossae narrowly confluent anteriorly; proboscidal fossa about 
<number box="[223,258,151,175]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="0.6">0.6</number>
× length of ventral surface of head. Scape simple, punctate above. Pedicel slightly longer than wide, shorter than first flagellomere; first flagellomere much longer than wide, longer than second. Mandible nearly straight, tapering distad, unidentate apically, unarmed ventrally. Maxillary palp 
<number box="[1073,1086,223,247]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="6.0">6</number>
-segmented; labial palp 
<number box="[1366,1380,223,247]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="4.0">4</number>
-segmented; intermediate palpomeres slightly expanded apicad. Mentum smooth, weakly convex. 
<emphasis box="[1212,1332,261,284]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">Mesosoma</emphasis>
. Slightly elongate, coffin-shaped, widest at pronotal spiracle. Dorsum dull, shallowly and coarsely reticulate, clothed with stout lanceolate decumbent setae and scattered slender finely brachyplumose erect setae. Pronotal dorsal face (excluding anterior collar/flange) with anterior margin almost straight, weakly carinate, epaulet dentate, humeral angle blunt; anterior face and collar longitudinally striate. Posterodorsal margin of pronotum faintly indicated by very weak ridge, specially laterally. Scutellar scale strong, protruding, basally interrupting well developed metathoracic-propodeal suture. Propodeal disk short, posteriorly carinate on each side, distinct from and perpendicular to posterior declivity. Lateral face of pronotum densely and finely punctate, clothed with fine decumbent setae; pronotal-mesopleural suture scarcely discernible. Mesopleuron anteriorly finely and sparsely punctate, posteriorly reticulate, with fine decumbent setae. Metapleuron finely punctate, clothed with fine decumbent setae. Metapleural-propodeal suture obliterated dorsal to endophragmal pit. Lateral face of propodeum almost entirely smooth and shining, with a few fine decumbent setae ventrally; posterior face reticulate dorsally, smooth ventrally, with stout lanceolate decumbent setae near dorsal margin, scattered finely brachyplumose erect setae ventrally. Metasternal process triangular, unidentate acute apically, as long as metacoxal height. 
<emphasis box="[982,1035,729,752]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">Legs</emphasis>
. Tibial spur formula 
<number box="[1275,1312,727,751]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="1.5" valueMax="2.0" valueMin="1.0">1-2</number>
- 
<number box="[1322,1339,727,751]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="2.0">2</number>
. Foreleg with tarsal comb, a few long strong articulated spines on posterior/lateral margins of tarsomeres. Mid- and hind tibiae each with two rows of prominent spines, about 
<number box="[726,740,799,823]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="4.0">4</number>
spines in each row, apical spines not inserted on any process; subapically with small inconspicuous secretory pore near base of inner spur; apical spurs broad, finely and deeply pectinate. Metacoxa with weak irregular longitudinal carina on inner/posterior margin. 
<emphasis box="[1164,1281,873,896]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">Metasoma</emphasis>
. T 
<number box="[1319,1329,871,895]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="1.0">1</number>
about as wide as long, &lt;
<number box="[328,363,908,932]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="0.5">0.5</number>
× width of T 
<number box="[513,528,908,932]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="2.0">2</number>
, almost parallel-sided in dorsal view, oblique anterior and horizontal dorsal faces distinct, with fine decumbent pubescence and brachyplumose erect setae; anterior auricle prominent, dentate. T 
<number box="[1423,1437,943,967]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="2.0">2</number>
clothed with laterally flattened lanceolate setae medially between pale spots and in apical band; lateral felt line broad, about 
<number box="[297,332,1015,1039]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="0.3">0.3</number>
× as long as T 
<number box="[496,509,1015,1039]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="2.0">2</number>
laterally. T 
<number box="[638,679,1015,1039]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="4.0" valueMax="5.0" valueMin="3.0">3–5</number>
clothed with lanceolate decumbent setae. T 
<number box="[1169,1182,1015,1039]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="6.0">6</number>
with well defined longitudinally striate pygidial area. S 
<number box="[532,543,1052,1076]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="1.0">1</number>
with strong simple median carina. S 
<number box="[952,967,1052,1076]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="2.0">2</number>
without felt line.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastBlockId="3.[151,1436,151,1148]" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">
MALE. Without defined pubescent or integumental spots. 
<emphasis box="[856,925,1088,1112]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">Head.</emphasis>
Broadly transverse, at least as wide as mesosoma, surface shiny, densely punctate, clothed with simple decumbent and brachyplumose erect setae. Occipital carina distinct. Vertex weakly swollen and produced behind ocelli. Eye transversely ovate, protruding, ommatidia distinct. Ocelli small, but median ocellus distinctly larger than lateral ocelli. Antennal tubercles simple, mostly smooth, contiguous. Antennal scrobe broadly concave to eye margin, with prominent complete flangelike transverse carina above. Clypeus with anterior/ventral lobelike process medially. Malar space about half basal height of mandible, about as long as pedicel. Gena ecarinate. Hypostomal carina distinct but weak, even, ending laterally at posterior mandibular condyle. Proboscidal and mandibular fossae very narrowly confluent anteriorly; proboscidal fossa about 
<number box="[288,323,1376,1400]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="0.6">0.6</number>
× length of ventral surface of head. Scape strongly bicarinate anteriorly. Pedicel about as long as wide, shorter than first flagellomere, which much shorter than second flagellomere. Mandible tapering, bidentate apically, unarmed ventrally, in dorsal/anterior view with lateral margin broadly and obtusely angulate at midlength and almost straight basally and apically. Maxillary palp 
<number box="[795,808,1484,1508]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="6.0">6</number>
-segmented; labial palp 
<number box="[1084,1098,1484,1508]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="4.0">4</number>
-segmented; intermediate palpomeres slightly flattened and expanded apicad. Mentum smooth, with distinct median longitudinal carina. 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">Mesosoma.</emphasis>
Surface shiny, densely punctate except smooth on anterior face of pronotum, axillar tooth, metapleuron and lateral face of propodeum, and reticulate on remainder of propodeum; clothed with simple decumbent setae and brachyplumose erect setae. Pronotal dorsal face (excluding anterior collar/flange) with anterior margin almost straight, weakly carinate medially above depression on anterior face, epaulet scarcely evident, humeral angle blunt. Posterodorsal margin of pronotum broadly V-shaped. Tegula ovate, evenly convex, almost entirely smooth and glabrous. Mesoscutum with notaulus forming an elongate depression on posterior fifth at most, parapsis almost indistinguishable; posterolateral corner forming a raised lobe continuous with axilla. Scutellum pulvinate. Axilla laterally produced as a prominent obliquely projecting blunt tooth. Metanotum simple, transverse. Propodeum strongly convex, disk and declivity fairly distinct in lateral view. Metasternal process unidentate, acute, almost as long as metacoxal height. 
<emphasis box="[446,514,1881,1904]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">Wings</emphasis>
. Forewing with moderate ovate sclerotized pterostigma; marginal cell short, truncate apically; two closed submarginal cells. 
<emphasis box="[649,702,1917,1940]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="43">Legs</emphasis>
. Tibial spur formula 
<number box="[942,979,1916,1940]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="1.5" valueMax="2.0" valueMin="1.0">1-2</number>
- 
<number box="[989,1006,1916,1940]" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" value="2.0">2</number>
. Mid- and hind tibiae each with a few strong spines and several strong slender semi-erect macrosetae dorsally, apical spines not inserted on any process; subapically with small secretory pore near base of inner spur; apical spurs almost cylindrical, densely clothed with microsetae. Metacoxa with weak irregular longitudinal carina on inner/posterior margin, there with patch of erect plumose setae. 
<emphasis box="[326,451,189,212]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Metasoma.</emphasis>
T 
<number box="[479,489,188,212]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="1.0">1</number>
petiolate, longer than wide, &lt;
<number box="[843,878,188,212]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="0.5">0.5</number>
× width of T 
<number box="[1035,1050,188,212]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="2.0">2</number>
, posteriorly weakly constricted in dorsal view, oblique anterior and horizontal dorsal faces distinct, punctate with finely brachyplumose erect setae; anterior auricle moderate, forming rounded oblique flattened lobe. T 
<number box="[918,931,260,284]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="2.0">2</number>
punctate, with brachyplumose erect and narrowly lanceolate semi-decumbent setae; felt line broad and long. T 
<number box="[926,966,295,319]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="4.5" valueMax="6.0" valueMin="3.0">3–6</number>
punctate, with brachyplumose to simple erect and narrowly lanceolate semi-decumbent setae. T 
<number box="[773,786,333,356]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="7.0">7</number>
punctate with simple to brachyplumose narrowly lanceolate erect setae basally; pygidial area distinct, convex, with apical marginal carina. Sterna punctate with brachyplumose to simple erect to semi-decumbent setae. S 
<number box="[734,745,404,428]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="1.0">1</number>
with weak longitudinal carina. S 
<number box="[1141,1156,404,428]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="2.0">2</number>
simple, evenly convex, without felt line. S 
<number box="[362,376,439,463]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="7.0">7</number>
very short, almost entirely concealed. Hypopygium long with median lobe or tooth on posterior margin. 
<emphasis box="[293,399,476,500]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Genitalia</emphasis>
. Paramere and/or cuspis with long shaggy plumose erect setae. Paramere elongate, more or less cylindrical, acute, dorsally recurved apically. Parapenial lobe well developed. Cuspis deeply divided near base, both components cylindrical; digitus at least as long as cuspis. Penis valve asetose, bidentate apicoventrally, teeth separated.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="44" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1436,151,1148]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,350,619,644]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Distribution.</emphasis>
This genus likely occurs throughout South 
<collectingCountry box="[837,937,620,644]" name="United States of America" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">America</collectingCountry>
, except 
<collectingCountry box="[1028,1092,620,644]" name="Chile" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Chile</collectingCountry>
. It is recorded from 
<collectingCountry box="[1317,1431,620,644]" name="Argentina" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Argentina</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[151,222,655,679]" name="Brazil" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Brazil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[233,346,655,679]" name="Colombia" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Colombia</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[358,457,656,680]" name="Uruguay" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Uruguay</collectingCountry>
, and 
<collectingCountry box="[515,630,655,679]" name="Venezuela" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Venezuela</collectingCountry>
(
<figureCitation box="[646,730,655,679]" captionStart="FIGURE 39" captionStartId="12.[151,250,1315,1338]" captionTargetBox="[195,1400,384,1293]" captionTargetId="figure@12.[180,1407,370,1294]" captionTargetPageId="12" captionText="FIGURE 39. Distribution of Tobantilla species." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/278963/files/figure.png" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">
Fig. 
<number box="[698,730,655,679]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="39.0">39</number>
</figureCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="44" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1436,151,1148]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,313,692,716]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Remarks.</emphasis>
We agree with Casal’s (
<number box="[595,653,692,716]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="1969.0">1969</number>
) discussion regarding the males of 
<taxonomicName box="[1064,1178,692,716]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1064,1178,692,716]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. The 
<taxonomicName box="[1247,1361,692,716]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1247,1361,692,716]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
males described below were collected in countries where 
<taxonomicName box="[758,872,728,752]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[758,872,728,752]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
females occur, are similar in size to 
<taxonomicName box="[1322,1436,728,752]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1322,1436,728,752]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
females and, like 
<taxonomicName box="[349,463,764,788]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[349,463,764,788]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
females, have brachyplumose setae on the scape, clypeus, posterior head margin, posteroventral propodeal face and base of T 
<number box="[606,648,799,823]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="1.5" valueMax="2.0" valueMin="1.0">1–2</number>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1436,151,1148]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">
Currently, none of the 
<taxonomicName box="[454,568,836,860]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[454,568,836,860]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species is known from both sexes. When biological observations, molecular data, or large series become available, sex associations can be made and some species described below may need to be synonymized.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1436,151,1148]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">
Many members of 
<taxonomicName authority="Ashmead, 1899" authorityName="Ashmead" authorityYear="1899" box="[429,763,943,968]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Dasymutilla" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[429,566,944,968]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Dasymutilla</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Ashmead" box="[579,763,943,967]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" refString="Ashmead, W. H. (1899) Superfamilies in the Hymenoptera and generic synopses of the families Thynnidae, Myrmosidae, and Mutillidae. Journal of the New York Entomological Society, 7, 45 - 60." type="journal article" year="1899">
Ashmead, 
<number box="[704,763,943,967]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="1899.0">1899</number>
</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
, particularly those from the 
<taxonomicName box="[1108,1261,944,968]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Dasymutilla" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="monticola">
<emphasis box="[1108,1261,944,968]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">D. monticola</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species-group, closely resemble this genus. They are generally small bodied, have a well developed scutellar scale and orange head and mesosomal integument in females, and have at least T 
<number box="[865,878,1015,1039]" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" value="2.0">2</number>
reddish and the head and mesosoma clothed with silver and black setae in males. 
<taxonomicName box="[503,617,1052,1076]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[503,617,1052,1076]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
can be separated from 
<taxonomicName box="[875,1012,1052,1076]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Dasymutilla" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[875,1012,1052,1076]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Dasymutilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the male genitalic structure and by the dorsally flattened mesosoma in females. Additionally, none of the 
<taxonomicName box="[956,1093,1088,1112]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Dasymutilla" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[956,1093,1088,1112]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Dasymutilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
that could easily be confused with 
<taxonomicName box="[207,321,1124,1148]" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Tobantilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[207,321,1124,1148]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">Tobantilla</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is found in South 
<collectingCountry box="[527,628,1124,1148]" name="United States of America" pageId="3" pageNumber="44">America</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>