<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9cccfd73-da48-4ef6-be1b-1764337602de" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152062790" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-528-1" ID-ZBK="7BABDD295E484320B8964E8306B0ECE8" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:99015B2C-51C7-47AF-AEE7-7F171711F46D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1313-2970-528-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 528" ModsDocTitle="Phylogenetic revision of Minyomerus Horn, 1876 sec. Jansen &amp; Franz, 2015 (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) using taxonomic concept annotations and alignments" checkinTime="1451243880599" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Jansen, M. Andrew &amp; Franz, Nico M." docDate="2015" docId="2583CBF6786AAEE38957B4AFF2B15075" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 528: 1-133" docOrigin="ZooKeys 528" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001" docTitle="Minyomerus aeriballux [JF 2015] Jansen &amp; Franz sec. Jansen &amp; Franz 2015, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="99015B2C-51C7-47AF-AEE7-7F171711F46D" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" masterDocId="535DFFBEFFB3FFF3FFC56E31063DFF88" masterDocTitle="Phylogenetic revision of Minyomerus Horn, 1876 sec. Jansen &amp; Franz, 2015 (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) using taxonomic concept annotations and alignments" masterLastPageNumber="133" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" updateTime="1643511826791" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Phylogenetic revision of Minyomerus Horn, 1876 sec. Jansen &amp; Franz, 2015 (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) using taxonomic concept annotations and alignments</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jansen, M. Andrew</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Franz, Nico M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>528</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>133</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-528-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">7BABDD295E484320B8964E8306B0ECE8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">7BABDD295E484320B8964E8306B0ECE8</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152062790" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:99015B2C-51C7-47AF-AEE7-7F171711F46D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2583CBF6786AAEE38957B4AFF2B15075" lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<subSubSection pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<pageBreakToken pageId="41" pageNumber="42" start="start">Taxon</pageBreakToken>
classification Animalia Coleoptera Curculionidae
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/99015B2C-51C7-47AF-AEE7-7F171711F46D" authority="Jansen &amp; Franz sec. Jansen &amp; Franz (2015)" class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus aeriballux" order="Coleoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="symbols" species="aeriballux" symbols="[JF2015]">Minyomerus aeriballux [JF2015] Jansen &amp; Franz sec. Jansen &amp; Franz (2015)</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="41" pageNumber="42">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 23, 24
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus aeriballux" order="Coleoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aeriballux">Minyomerus aeriballux</taxonomicName>
[JF2015] is distinct from other congenerics in having irregular rows of setae on the elytra, where the setae do not form regular rows as in most other species. The setae are generally a lighter color, and are arranged in offset rows on the intervals. The elytra are strongly, distinctly punctate. The punctured elytral striae give this species a uniquely 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘pin-striped’">'pin-striped'</normalizedToken>
appearance (see Etymology). The pronotum is medially incurved on both the anterior and posterior margins. The head is distinctly conical in appearance, and is curved medially. The metatibiae are apically strongly convex and covered with setae similar in length to the surrounding setae, somewhat translucent, and slightly lamelliform. The spermatheca has the ramus elongate, annulate, and sub-apically situated on the corpus. The aedeagus is broad, and tapers to the apex. The aedeagal flagellum terminates in an apical sclerite that is irregularly sinuate and tortuous, and is nearly as large as the Aedeagal pedon itself.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="42" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="description – female">
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Description - female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Habitus. Length 5.25-6.49 mm, width 2.00-2.41 mm, shape sub-cylindrical to pyriform, length/width ratio 2.50-2.69, widest at posterior 1/2-2/5 of elytra. Integument dark reddish-brown to black. Scales with variously interspersed colors ranging from white to gold, in some specimens appearing semi-translucent (in others opaque) or with reddish or golden opalescent reflections; dorsal patterning fairly stable in this species, having alternating gold and white stripes on prothorax and elytra. Setae white.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Mandibles. Covered with white-opalescent scales, with 4-6 longer setae, and 1-3 shorter interspersed setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Maxillae. Cardo bifurcate at base with an inner angle of ca. 105°, inner (mesal) arm 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–3×">-3x</normalizedToken>
longer and 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
thicker than outer arm, inner arm of bifurcation equal in length to apically outcurved arm. Stipes nearly square, equilateral, roughly equal in length to inner arm of bifurcation of cardo. Galeo-lacinial complex membranous and setose in posterior 2/3, sclerotized and somewhat emarginate anteriorly; dorsally with 7 apicomesal lacinial teeth; ventrally with 3 reduced lacinial teeth. Palpiger with a transverse row of setae; anterior 1/2-1/3 membranous, posteriorly sclerotized. Maxillary palps. I with apical end facing mesally and forming a 45° angle with base, I and II each with 2 apical setae; II with 1 mesoventral seta in addition to 2 apical setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Labium. Prementum roughly pentagonal; apical margins sinuate, angulate, lateral margins broadly curved, posterior margin mesally incurved; each lateral region with 1 long seta. Labial palps 3-segmented, III with apical 1/3 projecting beyond margin of prementum, but not reaching apex of ligula; both with 2 apical setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Rostrum. Length 0.70-0.84 mm, anterior portion 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2.5×">-2.5x</normalizedToken>
broader than long, rostrum/pronotum length ratio 0.55-0.59, rostrum length/width ratio 1.16-1.34. Dorsal outline of rostrum sub-conical, posterior half of dorsal surface strongly rugose. Rostrum in lateral view sub-triangular; apical margin with 2 large vibrissae. Nasal plate weakly defined by Y-shaped, impressed lines, slightly convex, integument partially covered with white-opalescent scales. Margins of mandibular incision directed 15° outward dorsally in frontal view. Ventrolateral sulci weakly defined as a broad concavity dorsad of insertion point of mandibles, running parallel to scrobe, becoming flatter posteriorly and disappearing ventrally. Dorsal surface of rostrum with median sulcus running dorsally from fovea at posterior end of rostrum, equal in length to anterior-posterior length of nasal plate. Rostrum ventrally with integument between 2 converging sulci (beginning at corners of oral cavity) slightly elevated. Oral cavity with lateral margins feebly curved.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Antennae. Dorsal margin of scrobe overhanging slightly and forming a small tooth, anterior to margin of eye by 2/5 of length of eye. Funicle slightly longer than scape. Club similar in length to funicular antennomeres V-VII, nearly 2.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Head. Anterodorsal margin of each eye unimpressed, posterior margin very slightly elevated from lateral surface of head; eyes separated in dorsal view by 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
their anterior-posterior length, set off from anterior prothoracic margin by 1/3 of their anterior-posterior length.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Pronotum. Length/width ratio 0.83-0.89, sub-cylindrical to globular; widest between midpoint and anterior constriction; surface punctate, though punctures somewhat obscured by scales; median sulcus absent. Anterior margin nearly straight, subtly incurving mesally, lateral margins curved and widening into a bulge just anteriad of midpoint of pronotum, posterior margin incurved. Pronotum with scales forming 2 parenthesis-shaped, whitish stripes dorsally, laterally with a whitish stripe that continues onto elytron; in lateral view with setae that barely reach beyond anterior margin. Anterolateral margin with a greatly reduced tuft of 1-3 ocular vibrissae present, usually not emerging much beyond fringe of appressed scales, sometimes not apparent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Scutellum. Margins straight.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Pleurites. Metepisternum covered by elytron near posterior 1/4 of metasternum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Thoracic sterna. Anterior 1/4 of Mesosternum with a few plumose scales; mesocoxal cavities separated by distance 1/4x width of mesocoxal cavity. Metasternum without apparent transverse sulcus; metacoxal cavities separated by 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2×">-2x</normalizedToken>
their width.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Legs. Tibiae and trochanters of all legs with a single, hair-like, brown seta positioned on mesal surface, approximately 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2×">-2x</normalizedToken>
length of adjacent setae. Profemur/pronotum length ratio 0.93-1.00; profemur with distal 1/5 produced ventrally as a semicircular projection covering tibial joint. Protibia/profemur length ratio 0.89-0.95; protibia moderately stout, in cross section sub-circular, apically expanded; protibial apex with ventral setal comb recessed in a broadly concave groove, setal comb unbroken, but becoming thinner and sparser anteriorly; mucro present as a laterally projected tooth equal in length to nearby setae, triangular and equilateral. Protarsus with tarsomeres II and III equilateral; I-III jointly similar in length to V. Metatibial apex with almond shaped convex ity ringed by numerous longer, spiniform setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="42" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Elytra. Length/width ratio 2.94-3.32; widest at posterior 1/2-2/5; anterior margins jointly 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2×">-2x</normalizedToken>
wider than posterior margin of pronotum; lateral margins sub-parallel after anterior 1/4, more strongly rounded and converging in posterior 1/2. Posterior declivity angled at nearly 60° to main body axis. Elytral striae deeply and distinctly punctate, appearing pin-striped, 1/4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of intervals; punctures distinct, separated by 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–3×">-3x</normalizedToken>
their diameter; colors variously interspersed, dorsally with a median longitudinal whitish stripe, laterally with a white stripe continuing from pronotum, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="42" pageNumber="43" start="start">these</pageBreakToken>
stripes more or less defined on some specimens; each interval medially with 1-2 rows of setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Abdominal sterna. Ventrite III anteriorly concave, posterior margin elevated and set off from IV along lateral 1/4s of its length. Sternum VII mesally 1/2 as long as wide; anterior margin weakly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Tergum. Pygidium (tergum VIII) sub-conical, medial 1/2 of anterior 2/3 of pygidium less sclerotized.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Sternum VIII. Anterior laminar edges each incurved forming a 115° angle with lateral margin; lamina more sclerotized medially.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Ovipositor. Coxites 1/2 as broad as long in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
Spermatheca. Comma-shaped; collum short, apically with a large, hood-shaped projection perpendicular to ramus, nearly equal in length and contiously aligned with curvature of bulb of ramus; collum short, cylindrical, sub-contiguous with, and angled at 90° to ramus; ramus elongate, somewhat bulbous, 2/3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
thickness of corpus and collum; corpus swollen, slightly thicker than collum, 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
thickness of cornu; cornu elongate, apically, gradually narrowed, strongly recurved in basal 1/4, straight thereafter, extending nearly to extent of projection of collum, forming an inner angle of ca. 45° to collum and corpus.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
Figure 23. Habitus of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus aeriballux" order="Coleoptera" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aeriballux">Minyomerus aeriballux</taxonomicName>
[JF2015], female A lateral view B dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
Figure 24. Diagnostic features and terminalia of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus aeriballux" order="Coleoptera" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aeriballux">Minyomerus aeriballux</taxonomicName>
[JF2015] A aedeagus, dorsal view B aedeagus, lateral view C apical sclerite of aedeagal flagellum D labial prementum, ventral view E lamina of sternum VIII F spermatheca.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="42" pageNumber="43" type="male">
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Similar to female, except where noted. Length 4.74-4.97 mm, width 1.65-1.83 mm, length/width ratio 2.66-2.98. Rostrum length 0.63-0.74 mm, rostrum/pronotum length ratio 0.54-0.63, rostrum length/width ratio 1.14-1.41. Pronotum length/width ratio 0.85-0.95. Profemur/pronotum length ratio 0.92-1.03, protibia/profemur length ratio 0.91-0.97. Elytra length/width ratio 3.15-3.43.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Elytra. Elytral declivity more angulate, forming a 75° angle to main body axis, but otherwise as female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Abdomen. Sternum VII similar to female. Tergum VII with posterior margin straight. Pygidium (tergum VIII) with posterior 3/4 punctate; anterior 1/4 rugose. Posterior 1/4 constricted and depressed, with posterior margin flaring out and slightly projected dorsally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Aedeagus. Length/width ratio 3.09; lateral margins very slightly converging posteriorly, gradually, more strongly converging in region of ostium. Pedon in lateral view becoming gradually narrower posteriorly in anterior 1/2, ventral margins in posterior 1/2 becoming straight towards apex, then curving to meet dorsal margins at a sharp apical point. Flagellum with large, elonage, tortuous apical sclerite, sclerite nearly as long as pedon, with sinuate margins.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="42" pageNumber="43" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
Named in reference to the dorsal coloration of the scales and the propensity of living specimens to traverse the open sand habitat in which they can be found, thus appearing as moving pieces of gold in the desert; aeris = bronze, brass, or copper, ballux = gold-dust or gold-sand; aeriballux = bronzy gold-dust; Latin noun in apposition (
<bibRefCitation author="Brown, RW" journalOrPublisher="Smithsonian Institution Press, Washington, DC" pageId="106" pageNumber="107" title="Composition of Scientific Words, Revised Edition." year="1956">Brown 1956</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="42" pageNumber="43">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
Holotype - female &quot;TEX. Winkler Co., 4 mi. N.E. Kermit, X-I-1971, C.W.
<normalizedToken originalValue="O’Brien">O'Brien</normalizedToken>
/ on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Asteraceae" genus="Artemisia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Artemisia filifolia" order="Asterales" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="filifolia">Artemisia filifolia</taxonomicName>
[non-focal]&quot; (CWOB). Paratypes, same label information as female holotype (CWOB: 17 females, 19 males) [8 females, 8 males deposited at CMNC]; &quot;USA: NEW MEX: Lea Co., 7 mi. SE Jal, 2980 ft., 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="32.03275">
<pageBreakToken pageId="43" pageNumber="44" start="start">32.03275</pageBreakToken>
°N
</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-103.14474">103.14474°W</geoCoordinate>
, VIII-11-2012, E.G. Riley&quot; (TAMU: 1 female); &quot;USA: TEXAS: Winkler Co., Jct. TX hwy 115 &amp; TX FM, 874, 16 rd. km NE Kermit, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="31.953611">
31°57
<normalizedToken originalValue="’13’’">'13''</normalizedToken>
N
</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-102.97083">
102°58
<normalizedToken originalValue="’15’’">'15''</normalizedToken>
W
</geoCoordinate>
, X-6-7-2005, J.D. Oswald &amp; Field Ento. Class-393&quot; (TAMU: 1 female); &quot;NEW MEXICO: Eddy Co., 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="92" value="32.33">32° 19.8'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="92" value="-103.78833">103° 47.3'W</geoCoordinate>
, (Site 7) 23 Sept. 1979, R. R. Murray and J. C. Schaffner, sand dunes&quot; (TAMU: 3 females, 3 males); &quot;NEW MEXICO: Eddy Co., 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="92" value="32.34667">32° 20.8'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="92" value="-103.776665">103° 46.6'W</geoCoordinate>
, (Site 11) 24 April 1979, Burke, Selorme, Schaffner&quot; (TAMU: 1 female).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">This species has been found in western Texas as well as southeastern New Mexico (Fig. 51).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="natural history">
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Natural history.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
Associated with sagebrush (
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Asteraceae" genus="Artemisia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Artemisia filifolia" order="Asterales" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="filifolia">Artemisia filifolia</taxonomicName>
Torrey [non-focal]; 
<taxonomicName family="Asteraceae" genus="Tanymecina" lsidName="Tanymecina" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" rank="family">Asteraceae</taxonomicName>
[non-focal]).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>