<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2e39a8a5-7b47-46af-a42a-b9bc4ef05b38" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051665" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-390-1" ID-ZBK="5518417F69B745CC92C3C402055D5851" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:46A124DB-35CD-47FE-AB4B-708A18782B6F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-390-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 390" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the Neotropical bark mantis genus Liturgusa Saussure, 1869 (Insecta, Mantodea, Liturgusini)" checkinTime="1451246163705" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Svenson, Gavin J." docDate="2014" docId="B8D8AC704319B9987E0A6C23A78560BD" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 390: 1-214" docOrigin="ZooKeys 390" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661" docTitle="Liturgusa zoae Svenson, 2014, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="46A124DB-35CD-47FE-AB4B-708A18782B6F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="79" masterDocId="A2413846FFC2FFA59948CC63FFBF7E4D" masterDocTitle="Revision of the Neotropical bark mantis genus Liturgusa Saussure, 1869 (Insecta, Mantodea, Liturgusini)" masterLastPageNumber="214" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="74" pageNumber="75" updateTime="1643678993329" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the Neotropical bark mantis genus Liturgusa Saussure, 1869 (Insecta, Mantodea, Liturgusini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Svenson, Gavin J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>390</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>214</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-390-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">5518417F69B745CC92C3C402055D5851</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5518417F69B745CC92C3C402055D5851</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051665" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:46A124DB-35CD-47FE-AB4B-708A18782B6F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B8D8AC704319B9987E0A6C23A78560BD" lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="74" pageNumber="75">
<subSubSection pageId="74" pageNumber="75" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/46A124DB-35CD-47FE-AB4B-708A18782B6F" class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa zoae" order="Mantodea" pageId="74" pageNumber="75" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zoae">Liturgusa zoae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="74" pageNumber="75">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="74" pageNumber="75" type="type">
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Type.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Holotype Male, pinned. National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, DC, USA.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="74" pageNumber="75" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Guatemala, Alta V. Paz, Schwarz &amp; Barber Coll, 2.4 Cacao, Trece Aguas. (Lat. 15.592321, Long. -90.146392).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="75" pageNumber="76" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<pageBreakToken pageId="75" pageNumber="76" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa zoae" order="Mantodea" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zoae">Liturgusa zoae</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<table pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<tr pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<th colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">Sex</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">Type</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">Country</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">Label</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">Latitude Longitude</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">Code</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<td colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">15.592321, -90.146392</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<td colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">15.592321, -90.146392</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<td colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">8.274772, -82.865134</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<td colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">15.716539, -86.826280</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<td colspan="1" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" rowspan="1">16.195801, -89.043072</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
<pageBreakToken pageId="76" pageNumber="77" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
A medium sized species, is distinct from all other 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa" order="Mantodea" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Liturgusa</taxonomicName>
. Could be considered most similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa guyanensis" order="Mantodea" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guyanensis">Liturgusa guyanensis</taxonomicName>
based on the pronounced pronotal shape modifications compared to all other 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa" order="Mantodea" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Liturgusa</taxonomicName>
, but 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa zoae" order="Mantodea" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zoae">Liturgusa zoae</taxonomicName>
has a longer pronotum. The prothoracic femora lacks tubercles on the posterior (external) surface, unique to the species. The hindwings are dark black and highly opaque, appearing rounded.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Male. (Fig. 18A) N=3: Body length 23.28-25.87 (24.69); forewing length 15.09-17.00 (16.17); hindwing length 13.89; pronotum length 6.61-7.23 (6.85); prozone length 1.89-2.01 (1.96); pronotum width 2.47-3.00 (2.75); pronotum narrow width 1.89-1.98 (1.94); head width 4.95-5.52 (5.29); head vertex to clypeus 1.98-2.29 (2.18); frons width 1.66-2.00 (1.85); frons height 0.66-0.80 (0.75); prothoracic femur length 6.77-7.35 (7.01); mesothoracic femur length 8.02-9.37 (8.67); mesothoracic tibia length 6.37-7.08 (6.65); mesothoracic tarsus length 5.21-6.44 (5.82); metathoracic femur length 8.62-9.26 (8.94); metathoracic tibia length 8.84-9.81 (9.32); metathoracic tarsus length 9.47; pronotal elongation measure 0.28-0.29 (0.29); pronotal shape measure 0.37-0.41 (0.40); head shape measure 0.40-0.42 (0.41); frons shape measure 0.40-0.41 (0.40); anteroventral femoral spine count 14-15 (15); anteroventral tibial spine count 9; posteroventral tibial spine count 7.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Figure 18. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa zoae" order="Mantodea" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zoae">Liturgusa zoae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., dorsal habitus: A holotype male from Guatemala (USNM 062) B allotype female from Guatemala (USNM 045).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Head (Fig. 43C): Transverse, the juxta-ocular protuberances prominent, the apex in the lateral half; the vertex is concave, dipping just prior to the parietal sutures, even with the dorsal margin of the eyes. Frontal suture with a medial carina forming a continuous arc, the region just ventral and dorsal to the carina depressed, the carina within a trough. Ocelli small, all the same size, protruding and laterally angled on a pronounced, curved carina that connects all three. The carina on the frons pronounced, the medial region just ventral to the carina depressed. Clypeus transverse, the upper margin convex, the lower margin slightly convex, the lateral margins adjoining lower margins with rounded corners; the central, transverse carina pronounced and slightly curved, two small grooves symmetrically located just dorsal to the carina. Antennae scape pale, pedicel dark brown, the flagellum fading to dark brown just slightly distal to the base. Vertex and juxta-ocular protuberances mottled pale and brown; cuticle just adjacent to ocelli dark brown or black; pale centrally to the three ocelli. Frons, clypeus, labrum, mandibles and palpi pale.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Pronotum (Fig. 48E): A little less than three times long as wide with a defined supra-coxal bulge; dorsal surface without tubercles; the lateral margins expanded and slightly lamellar. Prozone slightly broader than long with pronounced convex lateral margins; the anterior margin round; the dorsal surface spherical or bulbous, raised higher than seen in other 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa" order="Mantodea" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Liturgusa</taxonomicName>
; lateral margins smooth or with very few blunt tubercles. Metazone with concave lateral margins, tapering rapidly posterior of the supra-coxal sulcus, the medial region bulging slightly outward before widening to a rounded posterior margin; posterior margin with a small emargination; lateral margins with disperse tubercles, mostly located in the anterior third; the dorsal surface of the posterior third of the metazone very depressed; symmetrical posterior bulges pronounced. Mostly pale with black markings, two prominent black marks near the posterior margin of the metazone and laterally just posterior of the supra-coxal sulcus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Prothoracic Legs: Femur robust with a slightly concave dorsal margin; strongly defined pale to dark banding on posterior (external) surface; anterior (internal) surface with a black band running medially from the base to terminus that may be thinned or interrupted medially, the band thicker near the femoral brush and connected to the dorsal margin; the ventral surface pale. Posterior surface of femur without tubercles. A femoral pit to accommodate terminal posteroventral tibial spine positioned medial to and in line with the first most proximal posteroventral spine, proximal to the most distal discoidal spine; pit is pigmented black. Posterior prothoracic femoral genicular spine smaller than posteroventral spines, originating distal to the beginning of the genicular lobe. Ventral surface with raised, blunt carina just medial to the posteroventral spines beginning at the femoral pit and fading to flat after the third most distal posteroventral spine. Prothoracic tibial posteroventral spines with the first (proximal) smallest, the fourth and fifth slightly longer and the second, third and sixth of similar length. Prothoracic coxae smooth, the anterior surface with a large black band medially in the proximal half as well as a small black spot medially towards the distal terminus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Meso- and Metathoracic Legs: Femora with ventral (posterior) carina; dorsal (anterior) carina present. Mesotarsi with first segment shorter or at most as long as the remaining segments combined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Wings: Forewings mottled with brown, whitish pale, and black coloration; the costal region mottled matching the discoidal region, some banding pattern present medially; the costal region widened; vein coloration across discoidal region pale or light brown; a large pale area is positioned centrally; most of the surface dark brown or black with whitish mottling across the surface, the distal tip more whitish. Forewings asymmetrically colored; one being mottled as described the other is darkened significantly with a rust tone, the mottled pattern still visible; extending just beyond the abdomen. Hindwings opaque black, the veins black; the terminus of the discoidal region projecting just beyond the distal margin of anal region, the wing appearing rounded.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="77" pageNumber="78">
<pageBreakToken pageId="77" pageNumber="78" start="start">Abdomen</pageBreakToken>
: Slightly widened in the middle, the fourth or fifth tergite the widest before a gradual posterior narrowing; a smooth, brown and black colored dorsal surface. Tergites with tiny triangular posterolateral tergal projections. Supra-anal plate transverse, an evenly rounded terminus. Subgenital plate irregularly rounded and without styli.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="77" pageNumber="78">Genital Complex (Fig. 52B.1): The main body of ventral left sclerite (L4A) elongate, an evenly rounded terminus with the margin rolled slightly along the terminus; the left side with an elongate depression on the surface; lacking a distal process (pda). The apofisis falloid (afa) of the main body of dorsal left sclerite (L4B) forming a very large triangular projection that evenly tapers to a point; the apical process (paa) elongate and thin, the terminus rounded. The right dorsal phallomere (fda) of the first sclerite of right phallomere (R1) tapers rapidly to a narrowed and rounded, membranous terminus; the ventral plate (pia) long, curved with a medial tooth projecting towards the pva, smooth surface; the ventral process (pva) long and smooth, but with a sharply bent terminus, creating a notch.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="77" pageNumber="78">Female. (Fig. 18B) N=2: Body length 27.92; forewing length 17.64; hindwing length 13.94; pronotum length 7.65-8.30 (7.97); prozone length 2.22-2.59 (2.40); pronotum width 3.23-3.26 (3.25); pronotum narrow width 2.16-2.44 (2.30); head width 6.00-6.22 (6.11); head vertex to clypeus 2.44-2.65 (2.54); frons width 2.23-2.31 (2.27); frons height 0.90-0.97 (0.94); prothoracic femur length 7.98-8.17 (8.07); mesothoracic femur length 8.83-9.54 (9.18); mesothoracic tibia length 6.94-7.09 (7.02); mesothoracic tarsus length 6.38-6.68 (6.53); metathoracic femur length 9.15; metathoracic tibia length 9.93; metathoracic tarsus length 9.93; pronotal elongation measure 0.29-0.31 (0.30); pronotal shape measure 0.39-0.43 (0.41); head shape measure 0.41-0.43 (0.42); frons shape measure 0.40-0.42 (0.41); anteroventral femoral spine count 14-15 (14); anteroventral tibial spine count 9-10 (9); posteroventral tibial spine count 7.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="77" pageNumber="78">Head (Fig. 43D): About as long as broad, the juxta-ocular protuberances prominent, the apex in the middle; the vertex is slightly concave, evenly sloping to a slightly depressed center, above the dorsal margin of the eyes. Region just ventral to the frontal suture slightly depressed. Ocelli very small, all the same size, the lateral ocelli widely positioned, almost in line with the middle of the antennal insertion. The carina on the frons present, but not strongly pronounced. Antennal scape pale, pedicel with black markings, the flagellum brown proximally, fading darker and darker distally. Cuticle just adjacent to ocelli pale or light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="77" pageNumber="78">Pronotum (Fig. 48F): Less than three times long as wide with a defined supra-coxal bulge. Posterior margin of metazone with flat posterolateral corners and with a small medial emargination; lateral margins with numerous, pronounced tubercles.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="77" pageNumber="78">Prothoracic Legs: Prothoracic tibial posteroventral spines with the first (proximal), third through fifth short, the second and sixth longer and similar length..</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="77" pageNumber="78">Meso- and Metathoracic Legs: Mesotarsi with first segment shorter than the remaining segments combined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<pageBreakToken pageId="78" pageNumber="79" start="start">Wings</pageBreakToken>
: Forewings with the costal region mottled matching the discoidal region, some banding pattern distally; the costal region widened and extending distally; vein coloration mostly matches surrounding coloration; two pale spots are positioned in the proximal quarter of the discoidal region just posterior to the first radial vein; a large pale area is positioned centrally; black with whitish pale spots in the distal half. Forewings asymmetrically colored; one being darker and less contrasting; extending short of the terminus of the abdomen.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Abdomen: Slightly widened, the fourth or fifth tergite the widest region before a gradual posterior narrowing. Tergites with posterolateral projections of varying size, but shaped like expanded triangles and not posteriorly oriented teeth. Supra-anal plate transverse, an evenly rounded terminus.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
A noun in the genitive case, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Liturgusa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liturgusa zoae" order="Mantodea" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zoae">Liturgusa zoae</taxonomicName>
is named for my daughter Zoey Kay Svenson.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>