<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5935051" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f4c53401-22d0-41f9-a5e5-cf19b6844663" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5935051" ID-ZooBank="C8FE29A7-B2E6-4EE7-81F6-D15B2641A2A7" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0A136401-7882-45BA-A92C-9D1FA76E08EA" checkinTime="1554323313477" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Neuhaus, Birger, Zotto, Matteo Dal, Yamasaki, Hiroshi &amp; Higgins, Robert P." docDate="2019" docId="03BA87CCFFA7675D2AB8EF61DC909012" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4561.1.1.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4561 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@4cce889e" docStyleName="zootaxa.2013.monograph" docTitle="Condyloderes shirleyi Neuhaus &amp; Zotto &amp; Yamasaki &amp; Higgins 2019, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docUuid="0A136401-7882-45BA-A92C-9D1FA76E08EA" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="7" lastPageNumber="63" masterDocId="FF83FFB4FF9967632A2FED49D9199678" masterDocTitle="Revision of Condyloderes (Kinorhyncha, Cyclorhagida) including description of Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov." masterLastPageNumber="91" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" updateTime="1643676442458" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of Condyloderes (Kinorhyncha, Cyclorhagida) including description of Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Neuhaus, Birger</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zotto, Matteo Dal</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Yamasaki, Hiroshi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Higgins, Robert P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2019-02-27</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4561</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>91</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4561.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">f4c53401-22d0-41f9-a5e5-cf19b6844663</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">2627892</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">C8FE29A7-B2E6-4EE7-81F6-D15B2641A2A7</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5935051" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5935051" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0A136401-7882-45BA-A92C-9D1FA76E08EA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BA87CCFFA7675D2AB8EF61DC909012" lastPageNumber="63" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1182,551,645]" box="[151,949,551,578]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,949,551,578]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,949,551,578]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
Description of 
<taxonomicName authority="Neuhaus &amp; Zotto &amp; Yamasaki &amp; Higgins, 2019" authorityName="Neuhaus &amp; Zotto &amp; Yamasaki &amp; Higgins" authorityYear="2019" box="[335,597,551,577]" class="Kinorhyncha" family="Centroderidae" genus="Condyloderes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Cyclorhagida" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Cephalorhyncha" rank="species" species="shirleyi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[335,597,551,577]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Condyloderes shirleyi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[603,697,552,578]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Neuhaus &amp; Higgins
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1182,551,645]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,289,586,611]" captionStart-0="FIGURE 33" captionStart-1="FIGURE 34" captionStart-10="FIGURE 43" captionStart-11="FIGURE 44" captionStart-2="FIGURE 35" captionStart-3="FIGURE 36" captionStart-4="FIGURE 37" captionStart-5="FIGURE 38" captionStart-6="FIGURE 39" captionStart-7="FIGURE 40" captionStart-8="FIGURE 41" captionStart-9="FIGURE 42" captionStartId-0="64.[151,250,1751,1773]" captionStartId-1="65.[151,250,1926,1948]" captionStartId-10="77.[151,250,1669,1691]" captionStartId-11="78.[151,250,1180,1202]" captionStartId-2="66.[151,250,1827,1849]" captionStartId-3="67.[151,250,1751,1773]" captionStartId-4="68.[151,250,1676,1698]" captionStartId-5="69.[151,250,1723,1745]" captionStartId-6="72.[151,250,244,266]" captionStartId-7="74.[151,250,213,235]" captionStartId-8="75.[151,250,1728,1750]" captionStartId-9="76.[151,250,1664,1686]" captionTargetBox-0="[156,1433,228,1684]" captionTargetBox-1="[239,1340,193,1888]" captionTargetBox-10="[162,1424,193,1647]" captionTargetBox-11="[163,1424,193,1159]" captionTargetBox-2="[164,1424,233,1750]" captionTargetBox-3="[163,1424,220,1721]" captionTargetBox-4="[184,1407,193,1661]" captionTargetBox-5="[162,1423,193,1702]" captionTargetBox-8="[162,1424,193,1707]" captionTargetBox-9="[173,1415,203,1623]" captionTargetId-0="figure@64.[156,1433,228,1684]" captionTargetId-1="figure@65.[239,1340,193,1900]" captionTargetId-10="figure@77.[162,1424,193,1647]" captionTargetId-11="figure@78.[163,1424,193,1159]" captionTargetId-2="figure@66.[164,1424,233,1753]" captionTargetId-3="figure@67.[163,1424,220,1721]" captionTargetId-4="figure@68.[184,1408,193,1661]" captionTargetId-5="figure@69.[162,1424,193,1702]" captionTargetId-8="figure@75.[162,1425,193,1707]" captionTargetId-9="figure@76.[173,1415,203,1623]" captionTargetPageId-0="64" captionTargetPageId-1="65" captionTargetPageId-10="77" captionTargetPageId-11="78" captionTargetPageId-2="66" captionTargetPageId-3="67" captionTargetPageId-4="68" captionTargetPageId-5="69" captionTargetPageId-8="75" captionTargetPageId-9="76" captionText-0="FIGURE 33. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov. A, B. Habitus of holotypic male (USNM 1480999). Placids not illustrated because of dirt particles hiding details. A. Ventral view. Sternal and tergal plate slightly separated on left side during mounting but still covered by interplate cuticle. Pachycyclus and cuticular hairs on surface indicated on segment 3. B. Dorsal view. Pores shown in segments 2 and 5. C. Segments 6–11 of paratypic female (USNM 1481025), ventral view. Variation of cuspidate spine of segment 7 in lateral accessory instead of ventrolateral position. Pores and cuticular hairs indicated on segment 9. Cuspidate spines highlighted by grey colour. Scale bar 100 µm, valid for A–C. Abbreviations: ac, acicular spine; amp, female-specific area of micropapillae; ap, female-specific appendage; cu, cuspidate spine; ff, free flap; gc, gland cell outlet of male; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; md7, middorsal spines of segment 7; mts, midterminal spine; ne, protonephridial openings; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot." captionText-1="FIGURE 34. Diagram of mouth cone, introvert, and placids of adult Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov. with indication of inner and outer oral styles as well as scalid and placid distribution. Placids symbolized by bold, bent bars around the introvert diagram. Abbreviation: is, introvert sector." captionText-10="FIGURE 43. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., females (USNM 1481166, A, D, E, G; 1481170—RH-2707.07SEM, B, C, F) and males (USNM 1481168—RH-2707.04SEM, H; 1481168—RH-2707.05SEM, I; 1481171, J) from ventral (A–D, H, J), ventrocaudal (F), right (E, G), and left side (I), SEM. A. Segments 4–6; arrows mark row of short cuticular projections on sternal plates. B. Segments 6–11; note lack of appendage on left sternal plate of segment 7. C. Segments 8 and 9. D. Segment 6, female-specific appendage. E. Segment 9, sublateral protonephridial openings and sensory spot. F. Segments 10 and 11, gonopores. G. Segments 4 and 5, bifid middorsal acicular spine of segment 5 (arrows). H. Segments 4 and 5, cuspidate spine on segment 4 in ventrolateral instead of lateral accessory position; arrows mark attachment sites of cuspidate spines; (after Neuhaus 2013, fig. 5.1.14D, © Walter de Gruyter). I. Segments 4–6; note lack of sublateral spine on segment 5 J. Segment 9, sensory spot doubled. Arrowheads in A–I mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bars in A, B, G, and I 40 µm. Scale bars in C–D, H, and J 10 µm. Scale bar in E 4 µm. Abbreviations: amp, female-specific area of micropapillae; ap, female-specific appendage; cu, cuspidate spine; ff, free flap; gp, gonopore; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; lv5, lateroventral spine of segment 5; md5, middorsal spine of segment 5; mts, midterminal spine; ne, protonephridial openings; s4, segment 4; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot." captionText-11="FIGURE 44. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., males (USNM 1481168—RH-2707.04SEM, A, B;1481167, C; 1481170—RH- 2707.08SEM, D) and female (USNM 1481166, E;) from right (AC, E), and left side (D), SEM. A. Segments 1–4; arrows mark reduced free flap. B. Segments 6 and 7; notice lack of sublateral sensory spot on segment 7. C. Segments 4–6, middorsal cuspidate spine of segment 5. D. Segments 8–11, middorsal and laterodorsal spine on segment 10 of male and sublateral sensory spot on segment 7. E. Segments 9 and 10, lack of middorsal and laterodorsal spine on segment 10 of female. Arrowheads in A–E mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bars in A–E 40 µm. Abbreviations: cu, cuspidate spine; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; lv1, lateroventral spine of segment 1; md1, middorsal spine of segment 1; ne, protonephridial openings; s4, segment 4; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot." captionText-2="FIGURE 35. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., holotypic male (USNM 1480999) in ventral (A, D–G) and dorsal view (B, C), DIC. A. Habitus, mouth cone and introvert withdrawn. B. Segments 6–8; notice middorsal cuspidate spines. C. Placids. D. Segments 1–3; arrows point to reduced free flap. E. Segments 4–6. F. Segments 7 and 8. G Segments 9–11; extended focus image of five images. Arrowheads in B and D–G mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bar in A 200 µm. Scale bar in F 50 µm, valid for B–G. Abbreviations: bpl, broader placid; cu, cuspidate spine; gc, gland cell outlet of male; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; lv5, lateroventral spine of segment 5; md6, middorsal spine of segment 6; npl, narrower placid; pl, placid; s1, segment 1; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot; tr, trichoscalid." captionText-3="FIGURE 36. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., paratypic females (ZMB 11603, A; USNM 1481022, B, C, E, F; USNM 1481040, D) and paratypic male (USNM 1480983, G) from right (A–F) and dorsal side (G), DIC. A–G. Segments 1 and 2 (A), 3 and 4 (B), 5 and 6 (C), 2–5 (D), 7 and 8 (E), 10 and 11 (F, G). White arrows mark reduced free flap (A). Black arrows indicate modified attachment sites of tergal plates for lateral accessory cuspidate spines (A, D), spine lost in A. Arrowheads in A–G mark type-6 sensory spots. Black arrowhead in A points to type-6 sensory spot located centrally on segment instead of posteriorly. Scale bar in G 50 µm, valid for A–G. Abbreviations: amp, female-specific area of micropapillae; ap, femalespecific appendage; cu, cuspidate spine; ld10, laterodorsal spine of segment 10; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; lv3, lateroventral spine of segment 3; md1, middorsal spine of segment 1; mts, midterminal spine; ne, protonephridial openings; pa, pachycyclus; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot; st, sternal plate; tp, tergal plate." captionText-4="FIGURE 37. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., paratypic females (ZMB 11606, A, C, D; USNM 1481025, B, F) and paratypic males (USNM 1480986, E; 1481000, G, H; 1481012, I; 1481003, J, K) in ventral (A–E, G–J) and dorsal view (F, K), DIC. A. Habitus, introvert and mouth cone protruded. B–E. Mouth cone; notice tapering tips of outer oral styles (C, D, arrows) and mouth cone weir (E). F–H, J, K. Variation of placids; notice broad instead of narrow middorsal placid (F), midventral placid fused with neighbouring right placid (G, H, same specimen at different focal levels), midventral placid neighboured by three instead of two narrow placids on right side (J), and middorsal placid neighboured by two narrow placids instead of a broad placid (K, arrowheads point to additional condyles). I. Trichoscalid plates and filamentous appendages. Notice association of a trichoscalid with a placid except for narrow placids neighbouring midventral placid (G–K). Scale bar in A 200 µm. Scale bar in D 50 µm, valid for B–E. Scale bar in G 50 µm, valid for F–K. Abbreviations: bpl, broader placid; fa, filamentous appendage; in, introvert; ios, inner oral style; ip, interstitial placid; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; mc, mouth cone; mdpl, middorsal placid; mts, midterminal spine; mvpl, midventral placid; npl, narrower placid; oos, outer oral style; tr, trichoscalid or its basal plate; we, mouth cone weir." captionText-5="FIGURE 38. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., paratypic females (ZMB 11604, A, B, H; ZMB 11607, C, E; USNM 1481038, D; 1481026, F; 1481032, G) in ventral view, DIC. A, B. Segments 6–8, same specimen, showing surface (A) and pores through trunk cuticle (B) of female-specific appendages. C. Segments 7–9 of recently moulted specimen with thickened cuticular structures anterior to free flap (arrows). D. Segment 6, appendage on right sternal plate only. E. Lateral terminal accessory spine with two thin areas (arrows). F, G. Segments 9–11, different extension of area of micropapillae; black arrowhead points to unusual type-6 sensory spot (F), arrows mark paraventral folds (G). H. Segment 11, sclerotization of gonopores. Arrowheads in A–D, F, and G mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bar in F 50 µm, valid for A–F. Scale bar in G 50 µm, valid for G and H. Abbreviations: amp, female-specific area of micropapillae; ap, female-specific appendage; cu, cuspidate spine; gp, gonopore; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; lv8, lateroventral spine of segment 3; s6, segment 6; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot; st, sternal plate; tp, tergal plate." captionText-6="FIGURE 39. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., paratypic males (ZMB 11598, A; 11600, B, D; USNM 1481006, C; 1481008, J; 1480993, M) and paratypic females (USNM 1481041, E; ZMB 11606, F; USNM 1481036, G; 1481022, H; 1481042, I; 1481040, K, L) in optical section (A, B, H), from ventral (C, D, I, J, M), dorsal (F, G), left (E, K), and right side (L), DIC. A. Segments 10 and 11, condyle (arrows) and socket articulation. B. Intracuticular cavity of protonephridial openings. C, D. Segment 11, anterior ventrolateral sclerotizations (arrows). E. Segments 5–7, attachments of cuspidate spines (arrows). F, G. Segments 6–8 (F) and 5–8 (G), specimen without middorsal cuspidate spine on segment 7 (F) or on segment 5 (G). H. Middorsal spines of segments 8 and 9 with two thin areas (arrows). I. Segment 2, right cuspidate spine paraventrally instead of ventrolaterally. J. Segment 5, no indication of right lateroventral spine. K, L. Right cuspidate spine on segment 7 in lateral accessory instead of ventrolateral position (K) and lack of right lateral accessory cuspidate spine on segment 6 (L), same specimen; arrows (K) mark attachment areas of cuspidate spines. M. Segments 4–6, left cuspidate spine of segment 5 lateral accessorily instead of ventrolaterally; arrows point to attachment areas of cuspidate spines. Arrowheads in C–E, I, J, and M mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bar in B 20 µm. Scale bar in H 50 µm, valid for A and C–L. Scale bar in M 100 µm. Abbreviations: cu, cuspidate spine; gc, gland cell outlet of male; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; lv5, lateroventral spine of segment 5; md6, middorsal spine of segment 6; mts, midterminal spine; ne, protonephridial openings; pa, pachycyclus; s2, segment 2; so, socket; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot; st, sternal plate; tp, tergal plate." captionText-7="FIGURE 40. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., paratypic males (USNM 1481012, A; ZMB 11600, B; USNM 1481005, C–E; 1480981, F; 1481013, J; 1481014, M; 1480984, N) and paratypic females (ZMB 11605, G; USNM 1481028, H; ZMB 11604, I; USNM 1481040, K; 1481041, L) from ventral (A–C, G–J, N), dorsal (D–F), right (K, M), and left side (L), DIC. A. Segments 6 and 7 lacking any cuspidate spine. B. Segment 4, left lateroventral spine small. C–E. Small spines lateroventrally on segments 8 and 9 (C, spines on right side) and middorsally on segment 9 (D) as well as laterodorsal spines of segment 10 not fully extended (E), same specimen. F. Right paradorsal sensory spot doubled. G, H. Segments 1 (G) and 2 (H), left ventromedial sensory spot doubled. I. Segments 9–11, right sensory spot ventromedially instead of lateroventrally. J. Segment 3, left ventromedial sensory spot doubled. K. Segment 6, sublateral sensory spot doubled on right side. L. Segment 9, left paradorsal sensory spot doubled, right organ missing. M. Segment 9, right side, laterodorsal sensory spot and nephridial openings, sublateral sensory spot missing. N. Segment 8, ventromedial sensory spot missing on left sternal plate. Arrowheads in A–N mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bar in C 50 µm. Scale bar in I 50 µm, valid for F–I and K–M. Scale bar in J 20 µm. Scale bar in N 50 µm, valid for A, B, D, E, and N. Abbreviations: amp, area of micropapillae; cu, cuspidate spine; ld10, laterodorsal spine of segment 10; lv2, lateroventral spine of segment 2; md9, middorsal spine of segment 9; ne, protonephridial openings; pa, pachycyclus; s1, segment 1; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot; st, sternal plate." captionText-8="FIGURE 41. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., males (USNM 1481164, A, G; 1481168—RH-2707.04SEM, B, F; 1481170— RH-2707.08SEM, H) and female (USNM 1481170—RH-2707.07SEM, C–E) from ventral (A, D, G, H), frontal (B, C), dorsolateral-right (E), and dorsal (F) side, SEM. A. Habitus, head and mouth cone protruded. B. Trunk triangular in crosssection; (after Neuhaus 2013, fig. 5.1.14B, © Walter de Gruyter). C, D. Mouth cone; note thin tips of outer oral styles. E. Introvert sectors 5 and 6. F, H. Neck; arrow in H marks broad placid with six condyles in basal row; (H after Neuhaus 2013, fig. 51.14C, © Walter de Gruyter). G. Trichoscalid with filamentous appendages. Arrowheads in E and G mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bar in A 100 µm. Scale bars in B–H 10 µm. Abbreviations: bpl, broader placid; d, dorsal side; fa, filamentous appendage; in, introvert; is5, introvert sector 5; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; mc, mouth cone; md1, middorsal spine of segment 1; mdpl, middorsal placid; mvpl, midventral placid; npl, narrower placid; oos, outer oral style; s5, segment 5; sc01, ring 01 primary spinoscalid; tr, trichoscalid; v, ventral side; we, cuticular weir." captionText-9="FIGURE 42. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., males (USNM 1481170—RH-2707.08SEM, A–D, F; 1481168—RH- 2707.04SEM, E) and female (USNM 1481166, G) in ventral (A–C, E–H) and ventrocaudal view (D, F), SEM. A. Segments 1– 4; arrows mark reduced free flap. B. Segments 5–8. C. Segments 9–11. D, F. Segments 10 and 11, ventral side up; arrows mark anterior ventrolateral unknown structures on segment 11. E. Placids and trichoscalids. G. Segments 1–3; arrows mark row of short cuticular projections on sternal plates. Arrowheads in A–D, F, and G mark type-6 sensory spots. Scale bars in A–C and G 40 µm. Scale bars in D–F 10 µm. Abbreviations: cu, cuspidate spine; ld10, laterodorsal spine of segment 10; ltas, lateral terminal spine; lv1, lateroventral spine of segment 1; md1, middorsal spine of segment 1; mts, midterminal spine; mvpl, midventral placid; pl, placid; s5, segment 5; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot; tr, trichoscalid." httpUri-0="https://zenodo.org/record/2627958/files/figure.png" httpUri-1="https://zenodo.org/record/2627960/files/figure.png" httpUri-10="https://zenodo.org/record/2627974/files/figure.png" httpUri-11="https://zenodo.org/record/2627978/files/figure.png" httpUri-2="https://zenodo.org/record/2627962/files/figure.png" httpUri-3="https://zenodo.org/record/2627964/files/figure.png" httpUri-4="https://zenodo.org/record/2627966/files/figure.png" httpUri-5="https://zenodo.org/record/2627968/files/figure.png" httpUri-8="https://zenodo.org/record/2627970/files/figure.png" httpUri-9="https://zenodo.org/record/2627972/files/figure.png" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Figs 33–44</figureCitation>
; 
<tableCitation box="[300,394,586,611]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="4.[147,228,526,547]" captionText="TABLE 1. Location and processing data of all known species of Condyloderes. Abbreviations: BMNH, British Museum of Natural History, London; ICHUM, Invertebrate Collection at the Hokkaido University; MIMB, Museum of A.V. Zhirmunsky Institute of Marine Biology, Vladivostok; NHMUK, Natural History Museum of the United Kingdom, London; USNM, Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (previously United States National Museum); ZMB, collection “Vermes” of Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (previously Zoological Museum Berlin); ZMUC-KIN, Natural History Museum of Denmark, Copenhagen (previously Zoological Museum of Copenhagen - collection Kinorhyncha)." pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Tables 1</tableCitation>
, 
<tableCitation box="[408,451,586,611]" captionStart-0="TABLE 5" captionStart-1="TABLE 6" captionStart-2="TABLE 7" captionStartId-0="79.[147,233,531,553]" captionStartId-1="80.[151,239,700,723]" captionStartId-2="83.[147,229,525,546]" captionText-0="TABLE 5. Characters of 28 female and 45 male Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov. present in the majority of specimens mounted for light microscopy (upper part of table) and variation of characters (lower part of table). Digits in brackets refer to number of specimens showing a variable character. Features appearing anteriorly on a segment do not show any background, features located centrally on a segment are indicated by a grey background, and characters occurring posteriorly on a segment are marked in black. Characters found in one gender only are indicated. Characters occupying an intermediate position to two reference positions are arranged right or left in a column (on segment 1: paradorsally to sublaterally, subdorsally to laterodorsally, and ventromedially to paraventrally). Positions of more frequent variation of organ (n ± 5) are highlighted by oblique hatching. Abbreviations: + or ‾, additional or lacking character in comparison with most frequent occurrence; ac, acicular spine; amp, area of micropapillae; ap, appendage; gc, gland cell outlet; la, lateral accessory; ld, laterodorsal; ltas, lateral terminal accessory spine; lv, lateroventral; md, middorsal; ml, midlateral; mts, midterminal spine; ne, nephridial openings; pd, paradorsal; sd, subdorsal; sl, sublateral; ssp3, type-3 sensory spot; vl, ventrolateral; vm, ventromedial." captionText-1="TABLE 6. Condyloderes shirleyi sp. nov., morphological data of the holotype, 10 additional males, and 10 females (length in µm). Holotype indicated by bold catalogue number; data given for left/right side if applicable. Abbreviations: ac, acicular spine; cu, cuspidate spine; ld10, length of laterodorsal spine of segment 10; ltas, length of lateral terminal accessory spine; lv1, length of lateroventral spine of segment 1; md1, length of middorsal spine on segment 1; mts, midterminal spine; n, number of specimens measured; s1, length of segment 1; sw8, standard width of segment 8; TL, trunk length; USNM, catalogue number of United States National Museum; vl2, length of ventrolateral spine of segment 2." captionText-2="TABLE 7. Comparison of selected characters of species of Condyloderes present in the majority of specimens mounted for light microscopy. + / –, character present / not present; [], indicates variation in few specimens. Characters unique within genus are underlain with grey background. Measurements taken from Higgins (1969), Adrianov et al. (2002), Martorelli &amp; Higgins (2004), Sørensen et al. (2010b), Adrianov &amp; Maiorova (2016), and this paper (Tables 2 6)." pageId="62" pageNumber="63">5–7</tableCitation>
) http://zoobank.org/ 
<uri box="[369,1182,620,645]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
<uuid box="[640,1182,620,645]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">0A136401-7882-45BA-A92C-9D1FA76E08EA</uuid>
</uri>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1144,686,708]" box="[151,1144,686,708]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Higgins" authorityYear="1969" box="[151,291,686,708]" class="Kinorhyncha" family="Centroderidae" genus="Condyloderes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Cyclorhagida" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Cephalorhyncha" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[151,291,686,708]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Condyloderes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
sp.—Neuhaus 2013: pp. 232, 239, 267, figs 
<date box="[744,809,686,708]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" value="14-01-05">5.1.14</date>
, 
<date box="[819,883,686,708]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" value="15-01-05">5.1.15</date>
.—Neuhaus 2017: p. 146.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1437,750,1642]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,273,750,775]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
Neck placids with condyles in two rows in narrower placids and three rows in broader placids; each narrower placid with one apical and two basal condyles except paraventral placid next to midventral placid revealing in majority of specimens one apical and one basal condyle; each broader placid usually with two apical condyles, two condyles in intermediate row, and four basal condyles; midventral placid always with three apical condyles and usually two in intermediate row and four in basal row; acicular spine middorsally on segments 1–9 (and on segment 
<quantity box="[371,437,917,942]" metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.54" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" unit="in" value="10.0">10 in</quantity>
male only), midterminally on segment 11, lateroventrally on segments 1–9, and laterodorsally on segment 10 (in male only); cuspidate spine ventrolaterally on segments 2, 5, 7 and 9, lateral accessorily on segments 2, 4, 6 and 8, and middorsally on segments 5 and 7; type-5 (?) sensory spot ventromedially on segment 11; type-6 sensory spot ventromedially on segments 1 (slightly more paraventrally) and 29, lateroventrally on segment 10, sublaterally on segments 1–3, 5-7 and 9, midlaterally on segments 1 and 2, laterodorsally on segments 1–9, subdorsally on segment 10, and paradorsally on segments 1 (almost subdorsally), 2 and 4–9; gland cell outlet ventromedially on segment 
<quantity box="[766,824,1117,1142]" metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.54" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" unit="in" value="10.0">10 in</quantity>
male only; ventromedial appendage on segments 6–8 and area of micropapillae ventromedially on segment 
<quantity box="[755,798,1150,1175]" metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.286" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" unit="in" value="9.0">9 in</quantity>
female only.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1437,750,1642]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,439,1183,1208]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Material examined.</emphasis>
Holotypic male (
<mcCollectionCode box="[655,738,1184,1208]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1480999), 44 paratypic males (
<mcCollectionCode box="[1127,1210,1184,1208]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1480980-1480998, 1481000-1481019; 
<accessionNumber box="[378,525,1217,1242]" httpUri="http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/ZMB11598" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<mcCollectionCode box="[378,439,1218,1241]" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/8syf-d21i" name="Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (Zoological Collections)" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">ZMB</mcCollectionCode>
11598
</accessionNumber>
-11602), 27 paratypic females (
<mcCollectionCode box="[900,983,1218,1242]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1481020-1481029, 1481031-1481042; 
<accessionNumber box="[151,292,1250,1275]" httpUri="http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/ZMB11603" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<mcCollectionCode box="[151,212,1251,1274]" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/8syf-d21i" name="Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (Zoological Collections)" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">ZMB</mcCollectionCode>
11603
</accessionNumber>
-11607), and one paratypic female exuvia (
<mcCollectionCode box="[782,865,1251,1275]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1481030), mounted for light microscope study; 
<specimenCount pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="male">6 males</specimenCount>
and 
<specimenCount box="[270,381,1284,1309]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="female">5 females</specimenCount>
, mounted for examination with the SEM (
<mcCollectionCode box="[851,933,1284,1308]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1481164, 1481166-1481172). All specimens originate from the same sample in 
<collectingRegion box="[540,618,1317,1342]" country="United States of America" name="Alaska" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Alaska</collectingRegion>
(
<figureCitation box="[633,700,1317,1342]" captionStart="FIGURE 1" captionStartId="8.[151,250,1158,1180]" captionTargetBox="[162,1425,198,1134]" captionTargetId="figure@8.[162,1426,195,1134]" captionTargetPageId="8" captionText="FIGURE 1. Map of locations of all known species of Condyloderes identified to species level; see Table 1 for location data. Filled symbols indicate specimens studied in this article, open symbols refer to specimens not investigated here." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2627894/files/figure.png" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Fig. 1</figureCitation>
; 
<tableCitation box="[714,796,1317,1342]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="4.[147,228,526,547]" captionText="TABLE 1. Location and processing data of all known species of Condyloderes. Abbreviations: BMNH, British Museum of Natural History, London; ICHUM, Invertebrate Collection at the Hokkaido University; MIMB, Museum of A.V. Zhirmunsky Institute of Marine Biology, Vladivostok; NHMUK, Natural History Museum of the United Kingdom, London; USNM, Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (previously United States National Museum); ZMB, collection “Vermes” of Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (previously Zoological Museum Berlin); ZMUC-KIN, Natural History Museum of Denmark, Copenhagen (previously Zoological Museum of Copenhagen - collection Kinorhyncha)." pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Table 1</tableCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1437,750,1642]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,480,1350,1375]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Deposition of material.</emphasis>
The 
<typeStatus box="[545,643,1350,1375]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">holotype</typeStatus>
and 
<specimenCount box="[705,851,1350,1375]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="generic" typeStatus="paratypes">62 paratypes</specimenCount>
are deposited at the National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, 
<collectingRegion box="[525,720,1383,1408]" country="United States of America" name="District of Columbia" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Washington D.C.</collectingRegion>
, catalogued under the numbers 
<mcCollectionCode box="[1078,1159,1384,1408]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1480999 (
<typeStatus box="[1279,1381,1383,1408]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">holotype</typeStatus>
) and 
<mcCollectionCode box="[151,232,1418,1442]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1480980-1480998, 1481000-1481042 (
<tableCitation box="[685,772,1417,1442]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="4.[147,228,526,547]" captionText="TABLE 1. Location and processing data of all known species of Condyloderes. Abbreviations: BMNH, British Museum of Natural History, London; ICHUM, Invertebrate Collection at the Hokkaido University; MIMB, Museum of A.V. Zhirmunsky Institute of Marine Biology, Vladivostok; NHMUK, Natural History Museum of the United Kingdom, London; USNM, Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (previously United States National Museum); ZMB, collection “Vermes” of Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (previously Zoological Museum Berlin); ZMUC-KIN, Natural History Museum of Denmark, Copenhagen (previously Zoological Museum of Copenhagen - collection Kinorhyncha)." pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Table 1</tableCitation>
). Also, all specimens mounted for SEM investigation are kept at the Smithsonian Institution (
<mcCollectionCode box="[561,643,1451,1475]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">USNM</mcCollectionCode>
1481164, 1481166-1481172). Ten additional 
<typeStatus box="[1165,1272,1451,1475]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">paratypes</typeStatus>
are located in the “worm” collection of the Museum für Naturkunde, 
<collectingRegion box="[785,855,1484,1509]" country="Germany" name="Berlin" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Berlin</collectingRegion>
and catalogued in the “Generalkatalog freilebende Würmer” under the numbers 
<accessionNumber box="[479,617,1517,1542]" httpUri="http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/ZMB11598" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<mcCollectionCode box="[479,540,1518,1541]" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/8syf-d21i" name="Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (Zoological Collections)" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="Museum">ZMB</mcCollectionCode>
11598
</accessionNumber>
-11607 (
<tableCitation box="[708,792,1517,1542]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="4.[147,228,526,547]" captionText="TABLE 1. Location and processing data of all known species of Condyloderes. Abbreviations: BMNH, British Museum of Natural History, London; ICHUM, Invertebrate Collection at the Hokkaido University; MIMB, Museum of A.V. Zhirmunsky Institute of Marine Biology, Vladivostok; NHMUK, Natural History Museum of the United Kingdom, London; USNM, Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (previously United States National Museum); ZMB, collection “Vermes” of Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (previously Zoological Museum Berlin); ZMUC-KIN, Natural History Museum of Denmark, Copenhagen (previously Zoological Museum of Copenhagen - collection Kinorhyncha)." pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Table 1</tableCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1437,750,1642]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<materialsCitation county="North Pacific Ocean" latitude="58.546665" location="Berg Bay" longLatPrecision="17" longitude="-136.15" municipality="Glacier Bay" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Alaska" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,357,1550,1575]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<typeStatus box="[199,258,1550,1575]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Type</typeStatus>
locality.
</emphasis>
<collectingCounty box="[363,595,1550,1575]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">North Pacific Ocean</collectingCounty>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[605,685,1550,1575]" country="United States of America" name="Alaska" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Alaska</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[696,832,1550,1575]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Glacier Bay</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03BA87CCFFA7675D2AB8EF61DC909012:8ECC6001FFA7675D2964EB46DAAC905F" box="[843,949,1551,1575]" county="North Pacific Ocean" latitude="58.546665" longLatPrecision="17" longitude="-136.15" municipality="Glacier Bay" name="Berg Bay" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" stateProvince="Alaska">Berg Bay</location>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03BA87CCFFA7675D2AB8EF61DC909012:8ECC6001FFA7675D29EFEB47DD71905F" box="[960,1128,1550,1575]" county="North Pacific Ocean" latitude="58.546665" longLatPrecision="17" longitude="-136.15" municipality="Glacier Bay" name="North Element" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" stateProvince="Alaska">North Element</location>
, 
<geoCoordinate box="[1139,1290,1550,1575]" direction="north" orientation="latitude" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" precision="15" value="58.546665">58°32’48’’ N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" precision="15" value="-136.15">136°09’00’’ W</geoCoordinate>
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[199,1417,1617,1642]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="62.[151,1437,750,1642]" box="[199,1417,1617,1642]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,334,1617,1642]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Etymology.</emphasis>
The species is named in honour of Prof. Dr Thomas Shirley, who supported sampling in 
<collectingRegion box="[1332,1414,1617,1642]" country="United States of America" name="Alaska" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Alaska</collectingRegion>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>