<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" ID-GBIF-Dataset="907713bd-c7f2-4f8e-a75e-b7f9c958865f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648680" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-689-1" ID-ZBK="2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-689-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 689" ModsDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" checkinTime="1502744367222" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lackner, Tomas &amp; Leschen, Richard A. B." docDate="2017" docId="7CCE42AE5D2F3ADA5D30ECE8556C16A2" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 689: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 689" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" docTitle="Saprinus (Saprinus) amethystinus Lewis 1900" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="79" masterDocId="D302FFB6FFA66345FFBAFF89311EFFDE" masterDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="72" pageNumber="73" updateTime="1643479489822" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lackner, Tomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Leschen, Richard A. B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>689</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-689-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648680" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:7CCE42AE5D2F3ADA5D30ECE8556C16A2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7CCE42AE5D2F3ADA5D30ECE8556C16A2" lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="72" pageNumber="73">
<subSubSection pageId="72" pageNumber="73" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="72" pageNumber="73">
<taxonomicName authority="Lewis, 1900" authorityName="Lewis" authorityYear="1900" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) amethystinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="72" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amethystinus" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) amethystinus Lewis, 1900</taxonomicName>
Figs 301, 302-310, 311-319, 759
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="73" pageNumber="74" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus amethystinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="73" pageNumber="74" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amethystinus">
<pageBreakToken pageId="73" pageNumber="74" start="start">Saprinus</pageBreakToken>
amethystinus
</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1900: 253.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="73" pageNumber="74" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Australia: Queensland: Taylor Range.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="73" pageNumber="74" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus amethystinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="73" pageNumber="74" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amethystinus">Saprinus amethystinus</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1900: Lectotype, present designation: ♂, side-mounted, terminalia and pygidium glued to the same card as the specimen, right antennal funicle missing, right mid-leg missing, right metatarsus missing, left protarsal claw missing, with the following labels: &quot;Taylor Range / Queens Land / (Janson)&quot; (written); followed by: &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="73" pageNumber="74" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="amethystinus" pageId="73" pageNumber="74" rank="species" species="amethystinus">amethystinus</taxonomicName>
/ Type Lewis&quot; (written); followed by: &quot;G. Lewis Coll. / B.M. 1926-369.&quot; (printed); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Type”">&quot;Type&quot;</normalizedToken>
(round, red-margined label); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“09-088”">&quot;09-088&quot;</normalizedToken>
(yellow, pencil-written label, added by the senior author); followed by: &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="73" pageNumber="74" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="amethystinus" pageId="73" pageNumber="74" rank="species" species="amethystinus">amethystinus</taxonomicName>
/ LEWIS, 1900 / LECTOTYPE / des. T. Lackner 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘011”">'011&quot;</normalizedToken>
(red label, written) (BMNH). This species was described from an unknown number of specimens and the lectotype designation fixes the species identity.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="73" pageNumber="74" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">AUSTRALIA. New South Wales: 1 ♂, Quirindi, G.E. Bryant, 2.xi.[19]08, G. Bryant Coll., 1919-147, Dahlgren det. (BMNH); 1 spec., Caragabal, 13.ix.1966, Z. Liepa (ANIC); 10 specs., Euglo ex., Humbug Creek, 12.xi.1972, D.A. Doolan leg. (AMS; 3 specs. in coll. TLAN). Queensland: 1 ♀, Urangan, Manski, collector unknown (ANIC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="73" pageNumber="74" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="73" pageNumber="74" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Australia: New South Wales and Queensland (Fig. 759).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="73" pageNumber="74" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">
This is a rare species of Australian 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="73" pageNumber="74" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
known from only a handful of specimens; the last ones were collected in 1972.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="74" pageNumber="75" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">
<pageBreakToken pageId="74" pageNumber="75" start="start">Re-description</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Body length: PEL: 3.25-3.85 mm; EL: 2.00-2.40 mm; APW: 1.25-1.60 mm; PPW: 2.25-2.75 mm; EW: 2.50-3.00 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Body (Fig. 301) rectangular oval, dorsally convex, ventrally rather flattened; cuticle dark brown, shining, pronotum darker, piceous black, with bronze metallic luster; elytra on basal third light brown, rest of elytra darker, elytra with dark blue metallic luster; legs, mouthparts and antennal scape castaneous brown; antennal club light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<pageBreakToken pageId="75" pageNumber="76" start="start">Antennal</pageBreakToken>
scape (Fig. 302) thickened and triangularly dilated, punctuate, with several setae; antennal club (Fig. 303) covered with dense short sensilla intermingled with sparse longer erect setae; lower third of club asetose; sensory structures of antennal club not examined.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
Figures 302-310. 302 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) amethystinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amethystinus" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) amethystinus</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1900 head, dorsal view 303 antennal club, dorsal view 304 pygidium 305 prosternum 306 mesoventrite 307 lateral disc of metaventrite + metepisternum 308 protibia, dorsal view 309 ditto, ventral view 310 metatibia, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">Mandibles carinate laterally, dorso-laterally densely and coarsely punctuate, rounded, mandibular apex acute; mentum square-shaped, anterior margin with deep conspicuous median notch; labrum finely and sparsely punctuate, convex, with shallow median depression; labral pits present, each with a single labral seta; other mouthparts not examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">Clypeus (Fig. 302) evenly densely punctuate; frontal stria weakened, but complete and outwardly arcuate medially, supra-orbital stria carinate; frontal disc (Fig. 302) coarsely and densely punctuate; eyes convex, well visible from above.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">Pronotal sides (Fig. 301) moderately narrowing anteriorly, apical angles acute, pronotal depressions absent, anterior incision for head shallow, semicircular; marginal pronotal stria complete, carinate, visible along its entire length from dorsal view; pronotal disc laterally with a band of deep dense elongate punctures, becoming finer and sparser behind head, median part of pronotal disc almost smooth, with only scattered microscopic punctation; double row of fine ovoid punctures present along pronotal base; pronotal hypomeron with short yellow setae; scutellum very small, but visible.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">Elytral epipleura with sparse fine punctures; marginal epipleural stria complete; marginal elytral stria well impressed and slightly carinate, continued as complete apical elytral stria. Humeral elytral stria well impressed on basal third, in most cases connected to inner subhumeral stria; variously long fragment of inner subhumeral stria present also laterad of humeral stria (in two of the three studied specimens); three dorsal elytral striae 1-3 well impressed, impunctate, carinate, apically slightly surpassing elytral half, fourth dorsal elytral stria strongly abbreviated, present as short basal fragment, basally not connected with sutural elytral stria; sutural elytral stria well-impressed, in punctures, abbreviated on basal fifth, apically connected with apical elytral stria; elytral disc on apical four-fifths punctuate, punctures becoming denser apically, forming almost elongate strioles near elytral apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">Propygidium with dense round deep punctures separated by less than their diameter intermingled with much finer and sparser punctures; pygidium (Fig. 304) with similar, if somewhat sparser punctation; punctures much larger than those of propygidium.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">Anterior margin of median portion of prosternum (Fig. 305) almost straight, rounded laterally; marginal prosternal stria present laterally and also as a rather long medial fragment; prosternal process flattened, surface between carinal prosternal striae depressed, with coarse punctures, apico-laterally substrigulate-punctate; carinal prosternal striae well-impressed, carinate, sub-parallel, slightly divergent anteriorly, forming a rounded loop, united in front (Fig. 305); lateral prosternal striae carinate, rather short, apically attaining carinal prosternal striae at about four-fifths of their length, surface around them with microscopic setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
Anterior margin of mesoventrite (Fig. 306) almost straight, slightly inwardly arcuate; discal marginal mesoventral stria well impressed, complete; disc with coarse and 
<pageBreakToken pageId="76" pageNumber="77" start="start">large</pageBreakToken>
punctation; meso-metaventral sutural stria largely absent, present only as two short lateral fragments; intercoxal disc of metaventrite flattened; disc of metaventrite for the most part almost smooth, only with scattered microscopic punctation, along posterior margin (especially in area behind hind coxae) denser and coarser punctation appears; lateral metaventral stria (Fig. 307) well impressed, carinate, almost straight, shortened; lateral disc of metaventrite (Fig. 307) slightly concave, with dense shallow large setigerous punctures; metepisternum (Fig. 307) with similar setigerous punctures, on basal two-thirds and on fused metepimeron punctures becoming much sparser, not setigerous; metepisternal stria present as short intermittent fragments.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Intercoxal disc of first abdominal ventrite completely striate laterally; disc along basal and lateral margins with deep round punctures becoming finer and sparser medio-apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Protibia (Fig. 308) slightly dilated, outer margin with three triangular teeth topped by large triangular denticle, second and third teeth conspicuously larger than first, fol 
<pageBreakToken pageId="77" pageNumber="78" start="start">lowed</pageBreakToken>
by two tiny low teeth topped by denticle; setae of outer row regular, moderately spaced; protarsal groove shallow; anterior protibial stria present on basal two-thirds, next obliterated; setae of median row shorter and sparser than those of outer row; two tarsal denticles present near tarsal insertion; protibial spur (Fig. 309) massive, bent, growing out from apical margin of protibia; outer part of posterior surface obscurely variolate, separated from glabrous median part of posterior surface by definite carinate boundary; posterior protibial stria complete, almost along entire length with dense row 
<pageBreakToken pageId="78" pageNumber="79" start="start">of</pageBreakToken>
long well sclerotized setae; inner row of setae single, setae sparse, shorter than those of posterior protibial stria.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Mesotibia moderately dilated, outer margin with a row of sparse long denticles growing in size apically, another row of much shorter sparser denticles situated on anterior surface of mesotibia; setae of outer row regular, thick, almost as long as denticles themselves; setae of median row irregular, shorter and finer; posterior mesotibial stria not examined; anterior surface of mesotibia sparsely punctuate; anterior mesotibial stria almost complete; mesotibial spur stout, moderately long; apical margin of mesotibia anteriorly with two short denticles; inner margin of mesotibia with sparse row of long setae; claws of apical tarsomere slightly bent, shorter than half its length; metatibia (Fig. 310) slenderer and longer than mesotibia, in all aspects similar to it, but denticles on outer margin much shorter and sparser.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
Male genitalia. Eighth sternite (Figs 311-312) strongly sclerotized, separated medially approximately on its apical half, apex with several microscopic setae, velum absent; eighth tergite and eighth sternite fused laterally (Fig. 313). Ninth tergite (Figs 314-315) typical for the subfamily; tenth tergite (Fig. 314) outwardly arcuate, rounded; spiculum gastrale (Figs 316-317) gradually dilated on most of its apical half; basal end slightly dilated. Aedeagus (Figs 318
<normalizedToken originalValue="––">--</normalizedToken>
319) with parameres separated almost on their entire length; basal piece of aedeagus short, ratio of its length: length of parameres 1: 5; aedeagus slightly curved from lateral view (Fig. 319).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
Figures 311-319. 311 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) amethystinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amethystinus" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) amethystinus</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1900 male terminalia: 8th sternite + 8th tergite, ventral view 312 ditto, dorsal view 313 ditto, lateral view 314 male terminalia: 9th + 10th tergites, dorsal view 315 ditto, lateral view 316 male terminalia: spiculum gastrale, ventral view 317 ditto, lateral view 318 male terminalia: aedeagus, dorsal view 319 ditto, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>