<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6491957" ID-GBIF-Dataset="642c683c-e358-47c6-a7b1-166873de29ee" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100122240" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6491957" ModsDocID="z01328p027" checkinTime="1247145408572" checkinUser="thomas" docAuthor="Lewis A. K. Barnett, Dominique A. Didier, Douglas J. Long &amp; David A. Ebert" docDate="2006" docId="39E82A968A8E1ED3AA730601487E6A8F" docLanguage="en" docName="2006_Barnett_Didier_Long_Ebert_gg1.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1328" docSource="http://www.zoobank.org/urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:682471C6-2C88-4399-B207-3716238191A6" docTitle="Hydrolagus mccoskeri Barnett, Didier, Long &amp; Ebert, 2006, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageNumber="36" masterDocId="34AD47331ECFAE2C71FFF3E87B84E2E8" masterDocTitle="Hydrolagus mccoskeri sp. nov., a new species of chimaeroid fish from the Galápagos Islands (Holocephali: Chimaeriformes: Chimaeridae)." masterLastPageNumber="38" masterPageNumber="27" pageNumber="30" updateTime="1650990557867" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Hydrolagus mccoskeri sp. nov., a new species of chimaeroid fish from the Galápagos Islands (Holocephali: Chimaeriformes: Chimaeridae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lewis A. K. Barnett</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Dominique A. Didier</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Douglas J. Long</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>David A. Ebert</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1328</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>27</mods:start>
<mods:end>38</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.zoobank.org/urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:682471C6-2C88-4399-B207-3716238191A6</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank-PUB">z01328p027</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">682471C6-2C88-4399-B207-3716238191A6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6491957" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100122240" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6491957" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:39E82A968A8E1ED3AA730601487E6A8F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/39E82A968A8E1ED3AA730601487E6A8F" lastPageNumber="36" pageNumber="30">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="30">
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="30" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">Hydrolagus mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="30">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Galápagos">Galapagos</normalizedToken>
Ghost Shark
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="30">(Figs. 1-3)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="30">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1058480686" country="Ecuador" stateProvince="Galapagos">
Holotype. CAS 86558, juvenile female, 381 mm TL, 274 mm PCL, 211 mm BDL, Southeast of San 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Cristóbal">Cristobal</normalizedToken>
Island, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Galápagos">
<collectingRegion>Galapagos</collectingRegion>
</normalizedToken>
, (
<geoCoordinate>01º5.981'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate>89º12.235'W</geoCoordinate>
), 396.24 m, coll. by John E. McCosker (CAS), R. Grant Gilmore (HBOI) &amp; Bruce Robison (MBARI), 17 Nov. 1995 (JSL dive 3934).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="30">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1058480680" country="Ecuador" stateProvince="Galapagos">
Paratype. CAS 223971, juvenile female, 227 mm TL, 138 mm PCL, 107 mm BDL, off Isla 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Española">Espanola</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Galápagos">
<collectingRegion>Galapagos</collectingRegion>
</normalizedToken>
, (
<geoCoordinate>01º18.5'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate>89º45.5'W</geoCoordinate>
), 505.97 m, coll. by John E. McCosker (CAS), and John Ross (Smithsonian Magazine), 6 Jul. 1998 (JSL dive 3094).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="30">
Diagnosis. A species of 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BCD2FA80-79F3-46AD-856C-5BE9DF05C735" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus Gill 1862:331" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="30" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Hydrolagus</taxonomicName>
distinguished from congeners by the following combination of characters: head small with short, blunt snout; second dorsal fin only slightly indented along its length; preopercular and oral lateral line canals branching from the same node off the infraorbital canal and sharing a short common branch; dorsum medium brown with numerous narrow, sharply delineated irregular circular and elongate white blotches; ventrum white to tan with extremely fine brown mottling.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="30">
Description. Holotype and paratype morphometric measurements are presented in Table 1. Head small (HDL 31-32 % BDL), with rounded, short snout and large eyes (EYL 9-13 % BDL). Body depth (dorso-ventral height of body at a given distance from snout tip) remains similar from head to origin of pelvic fins, from which point it rapidly tapers distally to pelvic fin tips (when depressed posteriorly), subsequently transitioning into a whiplike tail. Skin firm and robust, not deciduous as in some other 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BCD2FA80-79F3-46AD-856C-5BE9DF05C735" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus Gill 1862:331" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="30" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Hydrolagus</taxonomicName>
(Didier 2002). Post-anal pad present, but inconspicuous in the juvenile type specimens.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="30">Tooth plates light yellow in preserved specimens, with white tritors. Vomerine tooth plates small and incisor-like with 5 tritors visible on the right and 5-6 on the left. Palatine tooth plates with 2-3 tritors along the oral surface originating at the posterior edge and terminating prior to the anterior edge. Small protrusions are present along the anterior labial edge. Mandibular tooth plates incisor-like and large (three times wider than vomerine tooth plates), with 5 tritors per side.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="30">Lateral line canals on head are open grooves with especially wide dilation of canals on the snout. Preopercular and oral lateral line canals branch from the same node off the infraorbital canal and share a short common branch (Fig. 4). Lateral line of the trunk and tail is fairly straight, with very small asymmetrical undulations and a sigmoid curve at the point where it meets the canals of the head.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="31" pageNumber="30">First dorsal fin preceded by a highly robust dorsal spine, which is triangular in cross section. Two narrowly spaced columns of serrations are present on the posterolateral edges of the distal 2/3-3/4 of spine. Spine only slightly curved posteriorly, with the majority of curvature occurring in the distal 1/3 of spine. First dorsal fin nearly triangular, with a straight posterior margin and slightly convex anterior margin. Second dorsal fin slightly indented along its length with the anterior lobe higher than posterior lobe. Dorsal and ventral caudal fin lobes elongate, with a longer ventral caudal fin lobe extending anteriorly. Anterior portion of the ventral caudal fin lobe merges into a fleshy ridge. The ridge extends anteriorly an additional 26% of body length and is nearly aligned vertically with the midpoint of the second dorsal fin. Both caudal fin lobes are approximately equal in height. Caudal filament moderately stout. No anal fin present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="31">Anterior margin of pectoral fin slightly convex, with increasing curvature toward an acutely pointed distal tip. Posterior margin straight, becoming concave at distal 1/4 of length. Pectoral fins, when depressed posteriorly, reach past the pelvic fin insertion and distal tip of pelvic fin lobe. Pelvic fins large and nearly triangular. Anterior margin slightly convex, particularly at distal 1/3. Posterior margin nearly straight, but very slightly convex. Distal tip slightly rounded to acutely pointed.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="32" pageNumber="31">Coloration. Life color of the holotype is an overall medium gray on dorsal and lateral sides extending to near the ventrum, with slight superficial silvery sheen; snout and oral region slightly lighter gray; ventrum light gray to whitish, with underside of caudal region from the pelvic insertion to the terminal end of the tail whitish, except for the dark gray caudal filament; first dorsal fin dark gray with slightly lighter gray areas in membranes between proximal ceratotrichia; second dorsal fin with white proximal and distal margin bordering a medial dark gray stripe; pectoral and pelvic fins darkish gray on lateral portion, slightly lighter gray on medial portion, with whitish posterior margin; dorsum between the eyes and the anterior caudal region is profusely marked with irregular but well-defined spots, vermiculations, and stripes of a silvery white; pigment around the outer margins of the eye is dark grey and the tapetum lucidum reflects an emerald-green.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="32">Color of preserved holotype is medium brown on the dorsum with numerous irregular, finely delineated rounded to elongate white blotches. Rostrum is a uniform medium brown dorsally and uniform tan from snout tip to mouth. Coloration of the head and trunk ventral to the dorsal edge of gill opening is a uniform white to tan with fine brown mottling, with finer mottling at the head, creating a uniform light brown appearance. On the tail, this lighter ventral coloration begins below the lateral line.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="33" pageNumber="32">Medial portion of paired fin lobes uniform medium brown, fading to off-white with fine brown mottling at the fin bases and lateral portion of fin lobes. Paired fin webs light brown to grey-brown, darkest at anterior margin, fading to a translucent posterior margin. Second dorsal fin and dorsal caudal fin lobe are uniform medium brown, bordered by a light colored proximal margin and a translucent distal margin. Ventral caudal fin lobe is uniform medium brown, fading to tan anteriorly. Coloration of preserved paratype is similar to holotype, with a few exceptions: coloration of paired fin webs is uniform, without a darkened anterior margin; hue of the body is darker, particularly on the ventrum; color pattern of second dorsal fin and dorsal caudal fin lobe is much less distinct and the hue is light brown instead of medium brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="etymology">
<paragraph pageNumber="33">Etymology. The Latin name is designated in honor of Dr. John E. McCosker, a renowned ichthyologist who collected and graciously provided the type specimens. The common name is an allusion to the known distribution of the species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="33">
Distribution and Ecology. Nine specimens were observed from four sites in the 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1058480685" country="Ecuador" stateProvince="Galapagos">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Galápagos">
<collectingRegion>Galapagos</collectingRegion>
</normalizedToken>
archipelago: Cabo Douglas, Fernandina Island (
<geoCoordinate>01º17.534'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate>91º38.852'W</geoCoordinate>
)
</materialsCitation>
, 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1058480679" country="Ecuador" stateProvince="Galapagos">
Isla 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Española">Espanola</normalizedToken>
<geoCoordinate>(01º18.5335'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate>89º45.4037'W</geoCoordinate>
)
</materialsCitation>
, 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1058480668" country="Ecuador" stateProvince="Galapagos">
Marchena Island (
<geoCoordinate>00º24.0'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate>90º26.5'W</geoCoordinate>
)
</materialsCitation>
and 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1058480674" country="Ecuador" stateProvince="Galapagos">
San 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Cristóbal">Cristobal</normalizedToken>
Island (
<geoCoordinate>01º5.981'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate>89º12.235'W</geoCoordinate>
)
</materialsCitation>
, at 396.24-505.97 m depth.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageNumber="33">Individuals were found alone or in groups along steep slopes, within a few meters of the seafloor. Habitat was composed of igneous boulders, cobbles, and pebbles.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="33">
The observed bathymetric range is shallow compared to many other 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BCD2FA80-79F3-46AD-856C-5BE9DF05C735" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus Gill 1862:331" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="33" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Hydrolagus</taxonomicName>
, and may reflect incomplete deep-water sampling in the region. However, the two most similar congeners in morphology and distribution, 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="33" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="novaezealandiae">H. novaezealandiae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="33" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="colliei">H. colliei</taxonomicName>
, are also found in relatively shallow depths (Eschmeyer et al. 1983; Anderson et al. 1998), suggesting that the observed depth distribution of 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="33" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
may accurately represent its true bathymetric range.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="35">
We suggest 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
is likely endemic to the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Galápagos">Galapagos</normalizedToken>
archipelago. There is a high degree of endemism in this geographic region due to its isolation from the South American continent (Grove &amp; Lavenberg 1997; McCosker 1998). The 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Galápagos">Galapagos</normalizedToken>
archipelago has never been closer to the South American continent than today (Cox 1983). The expanse of deep water extending thousands of kilometers to the east and west, the East Pacific Barrier (Ekman 1953), has effectively contained many species within this small area. Given this species' apparently shallow bathymetric range and limited vagility, we hypothesize that this new species of 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BCD2FA80-79F3-46AD-856C-5BE9DF05C735" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus Gill 1862:331" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Hydrolagus</taxonomicName>
represents another of these species limited in its distribution.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="35">
Comparison. 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">Hydrolagus mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
is the third species of 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BCD2FA80-79F3-46AD-856C-5BE9DF05C735" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus Gill 1862:331" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Hydrolagus</taxonomicName>
described from the eastern Pacific. It is easily distinguished from its nearest geographic relatives, 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A9515375-350D-4C4B-B6BA-B58BE59BAC9B" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus macrophthalmus de Buen 1959:186" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="macrophthalmus">H. macrophthalmus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="colliei">H. colliei</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A9515375-350D-4C4B-B6BA-B58BE59BAC9B" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus macrophthalmus de Buen 1959:186" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="macrophthalmus">Hydrolagus macrophthalmus</taxonomicName>
is an even brown color with no distinct color pattern (de Buen 1959; Quaranta et al. in prep.). 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="colliei">Hydrolagus colliei</taxonomicName>
is characterized by a reddish-brown color with distinct white spots, a second dorsal fin that is deeply indented, almost separated into two parts, and oral and preopercular lateral line canals that originate separately from the infraorbital canal (Didier &amp; Rosenberger 2002). The body of 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="colliei">H. colliei</taxonomicName>
anterior to the external opening of the gastrointestinal tract is longer than in 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
(Table 1; SVL 67-93% BDL, and TRL 38-55% BDL).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="36" pageNumber="35">
An additional variant of 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BCD2FA80-79F3-46AD-856C-5BE9DF05C735" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus Gill 1862:331" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Hydrolagus</taxonomicName>
, collected from the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Galápagos">Galapagos</normalizedToken>
archipelago during this survey, is easily distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
by a longer trunk length (TRL), deeper body (D1P1, D2P1), shorter second dorsal fin (D2B) and caudal dorsal margin (CDM), shorter head length (HDL), and greater height of the anterior lobe of the second dorsal fin (D2AH) (Quaranta et al. in review). Coloration is dark brown to black, with a white blotch on the midpoint of the second dorsal fin, occasionally with a few large oval white blotches on the lateral sides of the body, but not as extensive as in 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
. This morphotype is likely a new species, however, its similarity to 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A9515375-350D-4C4B-B6BA-B58BE59BAC9B" class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Hydrolagus macrophthalmus de Buen 1959:186" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="35" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="macrophthalmus">H. macrophthalmus</taxonomicName>
is being addressed in a subsequent study (Quaranta et al. in review).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="36">
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">Hydrolagus mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
most closely resembles 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="novaezealandiae">H. novaezealandiae</taxonomicName>
, a species endemic to the coast of New Zealand. However, the white markings on the dorsum of 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
are more numerous, less continuous and more sharply delineated. The oral and preopercular lateral line canals of 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
branch from the same node off the infraorbital canal and share a short common branch, whereas in 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="novaezealandiae">H. novaezealandiae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="colliei">H. colliei</taxonomicName>
, they branch from separate nodes off the infraorbital canal. There are also distinct morphological differences that differentiate these species (Table 1). In particular, 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
has a shorter, blunter head and snout (POB 11-12% BDL), and the origin of the second dorsal fin is further anterior. Additionally, the majority (86%) of lateral line canals along the head are greater in length in 
<taxonomicName class="Holocephali" family="Chimaeridae" genus="Hydrolagus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Chimaeriformes" pageNumber="36" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="mccoskeri">H. mccoskeri</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="36">
Remarks. Determination of chimaeroid taxonomy is difficult because of extensive interspecific similarity in morphology and poor condition of type specimens captured by traditional fishing gear. This study demonstrates the benefits of using submersibles as a method of taxonomic research, allowing identification of a new species from limited type material while yielding accurate and precise information on live body color, behavior, distribution, and habitat associations that would be otherwise unavailable from deep waters. The condition of the type specimens facilitated the analysis of characters considered to be conservative and robust for the distinction of chimaeroid species. These characters include color pattern, shape of the fins and body (Didier 1998), and lateral line morphology (Didier &amp; Nakaya 1999). The type of branching of the oral and preopercular lateral line canals from the infraorbital canal has been found to be particularly useful in the taxonomy of chimaeras (Didier &amp; Nakaya 1999; Didier &amp; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Séret">Seret</normalizedToken>
2002).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>