<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280261" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120193" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280261" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="50DB9C35F7105ED0F09F2D041374CEE3" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys lura Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="691" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="690" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280261" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120193" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280261" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:50DB9C35F7105ED0F09F2D041374CEE3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/50DB9C35F7105ED0F09F2D041374CEE3" lastPageNumber="691" pageNumber="690">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="690">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155869" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys lura Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys lura Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="690" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lura">Strumigenys lura Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="690">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 1.8, HL 0.44, HW 0.33, CI 76, ML 0.22, MI 50, SL 0.27, SI 82, PW 0.22, AL 0.47. Characters of scotti-complex. Mandibles in full-face view short, outer margins shallowly and evenly convex, sharply narrowed at base. Upper scrobe margin evenly and shallowly convex in full-face view, not bordered by a rim or flange, the eyes visible. Maximum diameter of eye approximately equal to maximum width of scape, with 4 - 5 ommatidia in longest row. Scape subcylindrical, curved and narrowed near base; hairs on leading edge slender, slightly flattened or spoon-shaped apically. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with short, slender filiform ground-pilosity which is thickened apically. The upper scrobe margin fringed with sharply curved hairs which are flattened or spoonshaped apically and are similar in size to those on the leading edge of the scape. Cephalic dorsum with 6 standing filiform hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate and dorsum with usually two pairs of short suberect or erect hairs. Mesonotum with three pairs of hairs: a pair of standing filiform to narrowly remiform hairs on anterior margin, a shorter more posteriorly situated pair of erect filiform hairs, and an even shorter pair of erect fine hairs on posterior margin (pair on posterior margin absent in some paratypes). Hairs on promesonotal dorsum appear easily abraded and are broken or missing in many of the paratypes. Propodeum with one pair of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Ground-pilosity as on head but sparser. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and more or less flat posteriorly. Anterior mesonotum without a conspicuous carina above the mesothoracic spiracle; mesopleural gland set in a small circular notch. Propodeal tooth triangular, lamellate, pointed apically, and subtended by a very narrow lamella that is continuous down the declivity. Pronotal dorsum and sides longitudinally striolate with superficial punctulate sculpture; mesonotal and propodeal dorsa reticulate-punctate. Pleurae and side of propodeum smooth and peripherally punctulate. Anterior face of petiole with narrow lamellate, anteriorly projecting ridge at lateral margins. Postpetiole disc more or less smooth. In profile ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle a narrow irregular strip along the base of the peduncle, its deepest point approximately equal to or less than maximum diameter of eye. Ventral spongiform tissue of postpetiole moderately developed. Basigastral costulae well developed and sharply defined, radiating on each side of a central clear area. Dorsal surface of petiole, postpetiole, and gaster with standing filiform hairs which are slightly thickened apically. Colour light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="690">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 1.8 - 19, HL 0.43 - 0.45, HW 0.33 - 0.35, CI 75 - 79, ML 0.21 - 0.24, MI 48 - 53, SL 0.26 - 0.27, SI 75 - 80, PW 0.21 - 0.22, AL 0.45 - 0.50 (7 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="690">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 5.3 km. SSE Ambanizana, Andranobe, 15 Â° 40 ' S, 49 Â° 58 ' E, 425 m., 21. xi. 1993, sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood), rainforest, # 926 (27) - ll (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="690">Paratypes. 8 workers and 1 queen (dealate) with same data as holotype but coded: (5) - 5, (23) - 12, (28) - 12, (35) - ll, (40) - 17 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="690">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: Marojejy, 375 m. (G. D. Alpen); 6.5 km. SSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 875 m. (B. L. Fisher); 9.2 km. WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 1200 m. (B. L. Fisher); 19 km. ESE Maroantsetra, 350 m. (P. S. Vihrd); 1 km. W Andampibe, Cap Masoala, 125 m. (Alpen et at.); Fotodriana, Cap Masoala, 25 m. (Alpen el al.); 14 km. W Cap Est, Ambato, 100 m. (G. D. Alpen); 6.3 km. S Ambanizana, 25 m. (B. L. Fisher); Nosy Mangabe, 300 m. (P. S. Wjrd); S. F. Tampolo, 10 m. (B. L. Fisher); Vanjamanitra, 8 km. SE Anjozorobe, 1380 m. (J. - M. Betsch); Ankarongambe. 1050 m. (J. - M. Betsch); Andranobi, Route d'Andriamena, ca 25 km. W Morarano Sud, ca 1250 m. (A. Peyrieras); F. C. Sandranantitra, 450 m. (H. J. Ratsirarson); Ambohitantely, 1550 m. (J. - M. Betsch); F. C. Didy, 960 m. (H. J. Ratsirarson); F. C. Andrianantantely, 530 m. (H. J. Ratsirarson); P. N. Mantadia, 895 m. (H. J. Ratsirarson); Rte d'Anosibe, Km. 33 (A. Peyrieras); 6 km. ESE Andasibe, 900 m. (P. S. Vtord), Perinet (Noyes &lt;t Day).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="691">Measurements of these specimens extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.42 - 0.52, HW 0.33 - 0.39, CI 74 - 81, ML 0.20 - 0.27, MI 47 - 53, SL 0.25 - 0.32, SI 75 - 86 (20 measured). As in the typespecimens, the number of pairs of hairs on the mesonotum varies between 2 and 3 in the non-paratypic material.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="691">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155869" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys lura Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys lura Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="691" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lura">S. lura</taxonomicName>
is closely related to 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155868" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys lucomo Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys lucomo Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="691" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lucomo">lucomo</taxonomicName>
; see under the latter.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>