<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4659004" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bba7e28b-bb64-4be4-bc08-bd0f6e937832" ID-GBIF-Taxon="180784644" ID-ISSN="0067-1975" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4659004" checkinTime="1617232677864" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="McAlpine, David K." docDate="1997" docId="A04DD76CFFF84D4CF9B6CF5A4139F7B5" docLanguage="en" docName="RecAustMus.49.2.167-194.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Records of the Australian Museum 49 (2)" docSource="https://journals.australian.museum/mcalpine-1997-rec-aust-mus-492-167194/" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D3147822FB22E0797CFA40BA2FBFB595.2:RecAustMus.1986-1997.journal_article" docStyleId="D3147822FB22E0797CFA40BA2FBFB595" docStyleName="RecAustMus.1986-1997.journal_article" docStyleVersion="2" docTitle="Gobryidae McAlpine 1997, n.fam." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="183" masterDocId="5C74AF14FFF74D5CFFF0CA174670FFEC" masterDocTitle="Gobryidae, a new family of acalyptrate flies (Diptera: Diopsoidea), and a discussion of relationships of the diopsoid families." masterLastPageNumber="194" masterPageNumber="167" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" updateTime="1635482192647" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Gobryidae, a new family of acalyptrate flies (Diptera: Diopsoidea), and a discussion of relationships of the diopsoid families.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>McAlpine, David K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Records of the Australian Museum</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1997</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>1997-10-15</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>49</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>167</mods:start>
<mods:end>194</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>https://journals.australian.museum/mcalpine-1997-rec-aust-mus-492-167194/</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.3853/j.0067-1975.49.1997.1264</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">bba7e28b-bb64-4be4-bc08-bd0f6e937832</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0067-1975</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">4655129</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4659004" ID-GBIF-Taxon="180784644" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4659004" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A04DD76CFFF84D4CF9B6CF5A4139F7B5" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A04DD76CFFF84D4CF9B6CF5A4139F7B5" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="183" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">
<subSubSection box="[1606,1944,1357,1396]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="15.[1606,1944,1357,1396]" box="[1606,1944,1357,1396]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">
<heading box="[1606,1944,1357,1396]" centered="true" fontSize="10" level="2" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" reason="3">
<taxonomicName authority="McAlpine, 1997" authorityName="McAlpine" authorityYear="1997" box="[1606,1800,1357,1396]" class="Insecta" family="Gobryidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family" status="n.fam.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1606,1800,1357,1396]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">Gobryidae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1831,1944,1357,1396]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" rank="family">n.fam.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="183" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" type="type_taxon">
<paragraph blockId="15.[1285,1807,1450,1489]" box="[1285,1807,1450,1489]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">
<heading box="[1285,1807,1450,1489]" fontSize="10" level="2" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" reason="2">
<typeStatus box="[1285,1370,1450,1489]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">Type</typeStatus>
genus: 
<taxonomicName authority="Walker" authorityName="Walker" authorityYear="1860" box="[1539,1807,1450,1489]" class="Insecta" family="Gobryidae" genus="Gobrya" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="182" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1539,1663,1450,1489]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">Gobrya</emphasis>
Walker
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="15.[1282,2270,1543,3146]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1284,1695,1543,1583]" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">Diagnostic description.</emphasis>
Fully winged, moderately small, elongate flies, with reduced chaetotaxy and somewhat braconid-like habitus. Head large, somewhat depressed, much broader than thorax; postfrons oblong, its surface entirely occupied by a uniformly sclerotised plate apparently derived from ocellar plate or triangle, with fine setulae at orbital margins; frontal lunule largely concealed; ptilinal fissure short, its descending lateral arms undeveloped; facial region broad, uniformly sclerotised, convex in profile, its lower part extensively facing ventrally; parafacial suture obsolete; upper occiput concave; supracervical region with compact, convex setulose callosity; eye large, much broader than postfrons in dorsal view; ocelli well developed, posterior ones on ridge of vertex; inner and outer vertical bristles present, the former much, the latter slightly behind ridge of vertex; other cephalic bristles absent; membranous subcranial region small, broadly oval. Antenna: segment 1 short; segment 2 short, deeply slit dorsally, with distal surface facing forwards; segment 3 elongate, deflexed at angle to rest of antenna, with dorsobasal process inserted into cavity of segment 2; arista unsegmented, probably through desclerotisation of segments 4 and 5, so that segment 6 appears to arise from a gibbosity on segment 3 a little beyond basal process of latter; segment 6 irregularly bipectinate, with dorsal rays more numerous than ventral ones densely pubescent on basal part. Prelabrum (postclypeus) short and deep; palpus and proboscis moderately developed; labella well developed, reflexed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="15.[1282,2270,1543,3146]" lastBlockId="16.[1279,2270,399,2137]" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="183" pageId="15" pageNumber="182">
Thorax elongate, without neck-like anterior extension; pronotum very short; prosternal region with large basisternal plate, raised and medially grooved posteriorly, with very broad, largely ventrally facing precoxal bridges anteriorly; scutellum short; subscutellum distinct, convex, but not very prominent; prothoracic spiracle vertically elongate; narrow oblique sclerite (remnant ofkatepimeron) sharply demarcated from upper part of meron (meropleurite) by a well defined membranous strip; metathorax forming a prominent base for hind coxae, not cylindrically produced at attachment of abdomen (in contrast to 
<taxonomicName box="[436,718,675,714]" class="Insecta" family="Syringogastridae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Syringogastridae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="sensu Hennig" authorityYear="1965" box="[829,1003,675,714]" class="Insecta" family="Diopsidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Diopsidae</taxonomicName>
); postcoxal bridge deep, but deeply sinuate on dorsal side; apical scutellar, posterior notopleural (not on callosity), and sometimes anterior notopleural bristles present; postalar bristle either undifferentiated or small but distinct, located on angle of postalar callus and not dorsomedially displaced (i.e. located as in 
<taxonomicName box="[736,1018,950,989]" class="Insecta" family="Syringogastridae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Syringogastridae</taxonomicName>
, not as in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="sensu Hennig" authorityYear="1965" box="[224,400,995,1035]" class="Insecta" family="Diopsidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Diopsidae</taxonomicName>
); scutellar bristle inserted on very slight tubercle; other thoracic bristles absent or scarcely differentiated from setulae. Legs of moderate proportions, but markedly increasing in length in the order fore, mid, hind; fore coxa slightly longer than hind coxa, inserted far from anterior end of thorax (but less far than in 
<taxonomicName box="[224,427,1271,1310]" class="Insecta" family="Nothybidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Nothybidae</taxonomicName>
); hind femur with thickened, spinescent seriate anteroventral and posteroventral bristles; other femora often with less developed ventral spinescent bristles; mid tibia with large apical ventral spur; tibiae otherwise without bristles; fore and mid tarsi much more slender than hind one; basitarsi cylindrical, without series of short cuneate setulae (in contrast to 
<taxonomicName box="[226,538,1592,1631]" class="Insecta" family="Syringogastridae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Syringogastridae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="sensu Hennig" authorityYear="1965" box="[672,859,1592,1631]" class="Insecta" family="Diopsidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Diopsidae</taxonomicName>
). Wing narrow, attenuated basally; tegula very small; anterodorsal costagial bristle usually present but weak; costa extending to vein 4, without break or visible weakening at either humeral or subcostal position, with numerous fine setulae, but no stouter spines or spinules; subcosta complete, well sclerotised, terminating well before end of vein I so as to leave a clear subtriangular area of subcostal cell between the two veins; second basal, discal, and anal cells all elongate and complete; distal section of vein 6 well sclerotised but rather short, sometimes reaching approximately to wing margin; vein 7 indistinguishable beyond alular incision; alula much reduced, with incomplete marginal fringe; squama (lower calypter) quite undeveloped.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="16.[1279,2270,399,2137]" pageId="16" pageNumber="183">
Abdomen very slender, with anterior segments forming a slender petiole which is more pronounced in male; abdomen dorsoventrally compressed at its hinge-like articulation with thorax; tergite I and sternite I with deep membranous sinuation in anterior margin (as component of hinge mechanism, in contrast to that of 
<taxonomicName box="[1282,1575,812,851]" class="Insecta" family="Syringogastridae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Syringogastridae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="sensu Hennig" authorityYear="1965" box="[1702,1885,812,851]" class="Insecta" family="Diopsidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Diopsidae</taxonomicName>
); tergites I and 2 quite fused; other preabdominal tergites well separated by intersegmental membrane (in contrast to 
<taxonomicName box="[1282,1583,950,989]" class="Insecta" family="Syringogastridae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Syringogastridae</taxonomicName>
); sternites I to 5 all separate and well sclerotised; spiracles of segments I to 5 all located in pleural membrane, that of segment I well removed from margin of tergite.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="16.[1279,2270,399,2137]" pageId="16" pageNumber="183">Male postabdomen. Protandrium with single asymmetrical sclerite, apparently consisting of fused tergite 6 and sternites 6, 7, and 8, enclosing two pairs of spiracles (6 and 7). Epandrium large, asymmetrically subspherical; surstyli separated from margin of epandrium by membrane, very asymmetrical and of unequal size; a separate, undivided, plate-like subepandrial sclerite present between bases of surstyli; hypandrium desclerotised; aedeagus short and broad, with very complex, irregular, asymmetrical sclerotization; aedeagal apodeme absent; ejaculatory sclerite rather small, slender, bent near middle; cerci well developed, separate but attached to sides of proctiger, only slightly asymmetrical.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="16.[1279,2270,399,2137]" pageId="16" pageNumber="183">
Female postabdomen short, not markedly extensile. Segment 6 large, with tergite and sternite fused into a complete ring (its form suggesting that it consists very largely of tergite), enclosing spiracle laterally; segment 7 shorter, with separate tergite and sternite and spiracle enclosed in tergite; cerci separate, very broad; spermathecae 3, with pigmented cuticular lining to vesicles (at least in G. 
<emphasis box="[1727,1865,2098,2137]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="183">
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Enderlein" baseAuthorityYear="1920" box="[1727,1848,2098,2137]" class="Insecta" family="Gobryidae" genus="Gobrya" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cyanea">cyanea</taxonomicName>
).
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>