<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4645461" ID-GBIF-Dataset="645a7e49-5099-4d46-b6de-7c66d2b1475e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="180777975" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4645461" ID-ZooBank="57D92FE6-7516-4376-B251-49A40219EF69" checkinTime="1615993849445" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio &amp; Devesa, Sergio" docDate="2021" docId="03AC2D4B886BFFB1FF20FF2BB2EC4001" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4942.4.5.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4942 (4)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Paranisopodus thalassinus Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa 2021, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="581" masterDocId="FF9555338862FFBDFFB7FFBCB7704123" masterDocTitle="New species and new records in American Acanthocinini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="582" masterPageNumber="569" pageId="9" pageNumber="578" updateTime="1632016279623" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species and new records in American Acanthocinini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, SP, Brazil.</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Devesa, Sergio</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>La Iglesia, 4, San Vicente do Grove, 36988 Pontevedra, Galicia, Spain.</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2021</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2021-03-16</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4942</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>4</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>569</mods:start>
<mods:end>582</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4942.4.5</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">645a7e49-5099-4d46-b6de-7c66d2b1475e</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">4612807</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">57D92FE6-7516-4376-B251-49A40219EF69</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4645461" ID-GBIF-Taxon="180777975" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4645461" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03AC2D4B886BFFB1FF20FF2BB2EC4001" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03AC2D4B886BFFB1FF20FF2BB2EC4001" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="581" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
<subSubSection box="[151,577,151,178]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,577,151,213]" box="[151,577,151,178]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,577,151,178]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="578" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,577,151,178]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa, 2021" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,476,151,178]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="578" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thalassinus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,476,151,178]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">Paranisopodus thalassinus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[484,577,151,177]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="580" pageId="9" pageNumber="578" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,577,151,213]" box="[151,295,187,213]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,288,187,213]" captionStart="FIGURES 32–37" captionStartId="10.[151,264,1943,1967]" captionTargetBox="[202,1378,203,1909]" captionTargetId="figure-18@10.[185,1402,181,1919]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="FIGURES 32–37. Paranisopodus thalassinus, male holotype: 32) Dorsal habitus; 33) Lateral habitus; 34) Ventral habitus; 35) Oblique view; 36) Head, frontal view; 37) Centrobasal crest." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4612821" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4612821/files/figure.png" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">Figs 32–37</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,259,2014]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,488,259,285]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
Description. Male 
<typeStatus box="[378,483,259,285]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</emphasis>
Head mostly dark brown, almost black; parts of mouthparts dark reddish brown; anteclypeus testaceous except semicircular dark brown anterior region; apex of labrum testaceous; scape orangish brown except dark brown scape-ball and brownish apex; pedicel mostly brown; antennomeres III–VII brownish basally, dark brown apically (this area gradually wider from V, especially on VII), orangish brown on remaining surface; antennomeres VIII–XI brown. Pronotum mostly dark reddish brown, with posterior area more orangish brown. Sides of prothorax reddish brown, except dark brown macula under lateral tubercles; prosternum dark brown, except anterior margin of prosternum reddish brown; lateral tubercles of prothorax and apex of prosternal process orangish brown. Mesoventrite dark brown except irregular dark orangish-brown macula on each side of anterocentral area and sides of area close to mesocoxal cavities; mesanepisternum dark brown; mesepimeron orangish brown; metanepisternum dark brown; sides of metaventrite orangish brown, and remaining surface dark brown. Anterior 2/3 of elytra mostly green, with basal area and parts of sides testaceous; posterior third mostly greenish, with sides and area close to apex testaceous; sides of basal half with nearly black area close to epipleural margin (not reaching humerus), distinctly expanded, almost reaching dorsal surface on anterior third and middle, slightly reaching on middle; dorsal surface with subcircular, nearly black macula middle. Profemora dark orangish brown dorsally, dark brown ventrally; mesofemora orangish brown with ventral surface of peduncle of apex of club brownish; metafemora brownish on peduncle, orangish on club except brownish apex. Tibia brown with central area slightly dark reddish brown. Abdominal ventrites dark brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,259,2014]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,270,871,897]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">Head.</emphasis>
Frons minutely, abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument; with a few long, erect dark setae close to eyes. Central area between antennal tubercles and upper eye lobes depressed, glabrous. Remaining surface of vertex and area behind upper eye lobes minutely, somewhat sparsely punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, especially behind upper eye lobes; with a few long, erect dark setae close to eyes. Area behind lower eye lobes nearly smooth close to eye, somewhat rugose close to prothorax; with yellowish-brown pubescent band close to eye, glabrous close to prothorax, and another yellowish-brown pubescent band between the two areas; with a few long, erect dark setae close to eye. Genae finely punctate except smooth apex; with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, except glabrous apex, with a few long, erect dark setae interspersed. Wide central area of postclypeus with bristly yellowish-brown pubescence, and long, erect dark setae interspersed; sides glabrous. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior 2/3, inclined at anterior third; posterior 2/3 with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and brownish pubescence, and long, erect dark setae interspersed; anterior margin with fringe of yellowish pubescence. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous except area close to intermaxillary process depressed and with yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.37 times length of scape (0.35 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.68 times length of scape (0.65 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 1.7 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at the end of antennomere VIII; with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, appearing to be darker on dark areas due to the integument color; ventral surface of scape with long, erect dark setae; ventral surface of pedicel with a few short, erect dark setae; ventral surface of antennomere III with a few short, erect dark setae; ventral apex of antennomeres IV–X with a few short dark setae. Antennal formula based on antennomere III: scape = 0.86; pedicel = 0.14; IV = 0.77; V = 0.59; VI = 0.50; VII = 0.45; VIII = 0.41; IX = 0.41; X = 0.41; XI = 0.36.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,259,2014]" lastBlockId="11.[151,1437,151,1977]" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="580" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,295,1627,1653]" pageId="9" pageNumber="578">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax distinctly transverse, even excluding lateral tubercles; lateral tubercles, large, conical, starting in anterior third, ending near posterolateral angles, with its apex placed in posterior third. Pronotum with one elongate tubercle on each side of middle, from anterior fifth to posterior quarter, distinctly obliquely elevated from posterior to anterior area, and another smaller tubercle on center of posterior third (this later tubercle continuing toward anterior third as elongate, slightly distinct gibbosity); coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate, except smooth tubercles, central gibbosity, and anterocentral area; central area with light yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, except glabrous central tubercle and gibbosity, and sparse, brownish pubescence on lateral tubercles (absent centrally); with wide, dense yellowish-white pubescent macula close to outer side of lateral tubercles, widened anteriorly and reaching anterolateral angles, posteriorly curved toward posterolateral angles; area on lateral tubercles of prothorax with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument. Sides of prothorax coarsely punctate centrally, nearly smooth anteriorly and posteriorly; with yellowish-white pubescence, obscuring integument on some areas, except area close to coxae with brown pubescence, and glabrous anterior margin. Prosternum with yellowish-brown pubescence laterally, gradually yellowish white toward central area (pubescence not obscuring integument), except glabrous area close to anterior margin. Prosternal process gradually narrowed toward its posterior quarter, then strongly widened toward apex; posterior margin concave centrally; narrowest area 0.4 times width of procoxal cavity. Central area of mesoventrite and mesoventral process with dense yellowish-white pubescence; area on each side of central region nearly glabrous, and narrow lateral areas with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument; mesoventral process wide, moderately narrowed toward its posterior margin, which is 0.6 times as wide as mesocoxal cavity. Mesanepisternum and mesepimeron with yellowish-brown pubescence. Metanepisternum with yellowish-brown pubescence basally, gradually yellowish-white toward apex. Metaventrite with yellowish pubescence laterally, whitish centrally. Scutellum with dense yellowish-brown pubescence laterally, nearly glabrous centrally. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[540,623,511,537]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Eltyra.</emphasis>
Humerus rounded, slightly projected forward; centrobasal crest elongate, with three large tubercles dorsally; with another tubercle on center of dorsal surface slightly after middle; anterior 2/3 with sparse, small rounded tubercles; area before posterior dorsal tubercle depressed; coarsely, abundantly punctate on anterior 3/4, punctures finer, sparser on posterior quarter; apex obliquely truncate, with sutural angle slightly projected; anterior area with whitish pubescence, denser on humeral region; remaining anterior half with yellowishbrown pubescence not obscuring integument (pubescence dark on darkened lateral areas around all tubercles and near the apex), except oblique, wide white pubescent band close to posterior tubercle, not reaching suture, almost reaching epipleural margin; dorsal apex of lateral dark area and posterior tubercle with dark pubescence; area between posterior dorsal tubercle and apex mostly with yellowish-brown pubescence, with irregular white pubescent maculae interspersed, and decumbent, moderately sparse dark brown setae especially laterally. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1231,1294,835,861]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Legs.</emphasis>
Peduncle of meso- and metafemora arched basally; femora with yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument (pubescence more yellowish-brown depending on light intensity). Protibiae slightly arched, expanded inward apically; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, except posterior half of ventral surface with dark brown pubescence. Meso- and metatibiae with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument; metatibiae strongly arched posteriorly. Metatarsomere I distinctly longer than II–III together.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4612821" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4612821" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4612821/files/figure.png" pageId="10" pageNumber="579" startId="10.[151,264,1943,1967]" targetBox="[202,1378,203,1909]" targetPageId="10">
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1436,1943,2004]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,333,1943,1967]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">FIGURES 32–37</emphasis>
. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa" authorityYear="2021" box="[346,620,1944,1968]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="579" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thalassinus">
<emphasis box="[346,620,1944,1968]" italics="true" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">Paranisopodus thalassinus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, male holotype: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[791,824,1943,1967]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">32)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[992,1025,1943,1967]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">33)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1196,1230,1943,1967]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">34)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1402,1436,1943,1967]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">35)</emphasis>
Oblique view; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[302,335,1979,2003]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">36)</emphasis>
Head, frontal view; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[544,578,1979,2003]" pageId="10" pageNumber="579">37)</emphasis>
Centrobasal crest.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,323,1050,1076]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with light yellowish-brown pubescence laterally, gradually whitish toward central area (pubescence not obscuring integument); posterior area of ventrite V with erect, sparse black setae, and posterior margin concave.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,416,1158,1184]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Dimensions (mm).</emphasis>
Total length, 10.4; prothoracic length, 1.8; anterior prothoracic width, 2.4; posterior prothoracic width, 2.1; maximum prothoracic width, at lateral tubercles, 3.2; humeral width, 3.8; elytral length, 7.7.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="580" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,366,1230,1257]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Type material</emphasis>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3062302307" collectingDate="2000-02-26" collectionCode="MHNUSC, SDPC" collectorName="Km N San Isidro &amp; J. Prena" country="Costa Rica" elevation="1800" latitude="10.059167" location="Cerro Zurqui" longLatPrecision="21" longitude="-84.03306" municipality="Male" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Heredia" typeStatus="holotype">
<collectingMunicipality box="[381,439,1231,1257]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Male</collectingMunicipality>
<typeStatus box="[446,544,1231,1257]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">holotype</typeStatus>
from 
<collectingCountry box="[614,780,1231,1257]" name="Costa Rica" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">COSTA RICA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis box="[791,882,1231,1257]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<collectingRegion box="[791,882,1231,1257]" country="Costa Rica" name="Heredia" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Heredia</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
, 5 
<collectorName box="[918,1113,1231,1257]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Km N San Isidro</collectorName>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03AC2D4B886BFFB1FF20FF2BB2EC4001:8EDACA868869FFB6FBD2FB73B38845CA" box="[1125,1272,1231,1257]" country="Costa Rica" latitude="10.059167" longLatPrecision="21" longitude="-84.03306" municipality="Male" name="Cerro Zurqui" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" stateProvince="Heredia">Cerro Zurquí</location>
(
<geoCoordinate box="[1289,1426,1231,1257]" degrees="10" direction="north" minutes="03" orientation="latitude" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" precision="15" seconds="33" value="10.059167">10º03’33’’N</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate box="[151,299,1266,1293]" degrees="84" direction="west" minutes="01" orientation="longitude" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" precision="15" seconds="59" value="-84.03306">84º01’59’’W</geoCoordinate>
), 
<quantity box="[320,410,1267,1293]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.8" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" unit="m" value="1800.0">
<elevation box="[320,410,1267,1293]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.8" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" unit="m" value="1800.0">1800 m</elevation>
</quantity>
.s.n.m., 
<date box="[493,613,1267,1293]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" value="2000-02-26">
<collectingDate box="[493,613,1267,1293]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" value="2000-02-26">26.II.2000</collectingDate>
</date>
; 
<collectorName box="[624,713,1267,1293]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">J. Prena</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode box="[776,900,1267,1293]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">MHNUSC</collectionCode>
, temporarily in 
<collectionCode box="[1078,1153,1267,1293]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">SDPC</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[199,1037,1303,1329]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,151,1977]" box="[199,1037,1303,1329]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,328,1303,1329]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Etymology</emphasis>
. Latin, “thalassinus” (green); allusive to the color of the elytra.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="581" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,315,1339,1365]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa, 2021" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa" authorityYear="2021" box="[322,625,1339,1365]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thalassinus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[322,625,1339,1365]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Paranisopodus thalassinus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[633,723,1339,1365]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[633,723,1339,1365]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Monne &amp; Monne, 2007" authorityName="Monne &amp; Monne" authorityYear="2007" box="[871,1280,1339,1365]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peruanus">
<emphasis box="[871,1003,1339,1364]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. peruanus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Monne, M. L. &amp; Monne, M. A." box="[1010,1280,1339,1365]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" pagination="1057 - 1062" refId="ref9176" refString="Monne, M. L. &amp; Monne, M. A. (2007) Revis &quot; o dos generos Tropanisopodus Tippmann e Paranisopodus Monne &amp; Martins (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae). Revista Brasileira de Zoologia, 24 (4), 1057 - 1062. https: // doi. org / 10.1590 / S 0101 - 81752007000400024" type="journal article" year="2007">Monné &amp; Monné, 2007</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
. According to 
<bibRefCitation author="Monne, M. L. &amp; Monne, M. A." box="[151,429,1375,1401]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" pagination="1057 - 1062" refId="ref9176" refString="Monne, M. L. &amp; Monne, M. A. (2007) Revis &quot; o dos generos Tropanisopodus Tippmann e Paranisopodus Monne &amp; Martins (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae). Revista Brasileira de Zoologia, 24 (4), 1057 - 1062. https: // doi. org / 10.1590 / S 0101 - 81752007000400024" type="journal article" year="2007">Monné &amp; Monné (2007)</bibRefCitation>
, their species was described based on a single female from 
<collectingCountry box="[1094,1145,1375,1401]" name="Peru" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Peru</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion box="[1160,1235,1375,1401]" country="Peru" name="Cusco" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Cuzco</collectingRegion>
) and the 
<typeStatus box="[1338,1436,1375,1401]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">holotype</typeStatus>
was destroyed during the fire in 2018 at the MNRJ. According with the original description, 
<taxonomicName box="[1182,1281,1411,1437]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="viridis">
<emphasis box="[1182,1281,1411,1437]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. viridis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
differs as follows: centrobasal elytral crest long and tuberculate dorsally; circular dark brown pubescent macula near middle of the elytra positioned in an obliquely descending band from apex of nearly black lateral macula to the center of the dorsal area; mesofemora almost entirely yellowish-brown, and metafemora with most of club yellowish-brown. In 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Monne &amp; Monne" authorityYear="2007" box="[151,284,1555,1580]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peruanus">
<emphasis box="[151,284,1555,1580]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. peruanus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, elytra with subrounded centrobasal crest, with tubercles on top (translated from the original description), circular dark brown pubescent macula near middle of the elytra positioned in a slightly obliquely ascending band from the apex of the dark lateral macula to the center of the dorsal area, meso- and metafemora mostly dark brown (there is no information about the color of the legs in the original description, but the photographs of the 
<typeStatus box="[151,252,1699,1725]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">holotype</typeStatus>
, show them entirely dark). Additionally, the scape in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa" authorityYear="2021" box="[850,1003,1699,1725]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thalassinus">
<emphasis box="[850,1003,1699,1725]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. thalassinus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is slightly widened from base to apex, while it is distinctly widened in the 
<typeStatus box="[549,647,1735,1761]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">holotype</typeStatus>
of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Monne &amp; Monne" authorityYear="2007" box="[683,814,1735,1760]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peruanus">
<emphasis box="[683,814,1735,1760]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. peruanus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. In other species in which both sexes are known (
<emphasis box="[1369,1409,1735,1760]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">e.g.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Monne &amp; Martins, 1976" authorityName="Monne &amp; Martins" authorityYear="1976" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="heterotarsus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. heterotarsus</emphasis>
Monné &amp; Martins, 1976
</taxonomicName>
), the scape in male is narrower basally than in females. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa" authorityYear="2021" box="[1203,1356,1771,1797]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thalassinus">
<emphasis box="[1203,1356,1771,1797]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. thalassinus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
differs from males of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Monne &amp; Martins" authorityYear="1976" box="[315,482,1807,1833]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="heterotarsus">
<emphasis box="[315,482,1807,1833]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. heterotarsus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(see 
<bibRefCitation author="Nascimento, F. E. &amp; Santos-Silva, A." box="[541,918,1807,1833]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" pagination="195 - 210" refId="ref9353" refString="Nascimento, F. E. &amp; Santos-Silva, A. (2019) The &quot; Podus &quot; complex: New species and notes on some Acanthocinini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae). Zootaxa, 4629 (2), 195 - 210. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 4629.2.3" type="journal article" year="2019">Nascimento &amp; Santos-Silva 2019</bibRefCitation>
) especially by the distance between upper eye lobes about twice width of one upper lobe (larger than 2.5 times width of one upper lobe in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Monne &amp; Martins" authorityYear="1976" box="[1203,1371,1843,1869]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="heterotarsus">
<emphasis box="[1203,1371,1843,1869]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. heterotarsus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), and metafemora not surpassing elytral apex (distinctly surpassing in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Monne &amp; Martins" authorityYear="1976" box="[873,1039,1879,1905]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="heterotarsus">
<emphasis box="[873,1039,1879,1905]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">P. heterotarsus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa, 2021" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa" authorityYear="2021" box="[199,504,1915,1941]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thalassinus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[199,504,1915,1941]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">Paranisopodus thalassinus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[513,604,1915,1941]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[513,604,1915,1941]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
can be included in the alternative of couplet “5” from 
<bibRefCitation author="Monne, M. &amp; Monne, M. A." pageId="11" pageNumber="580" pagination="253 - 262" refId="ref9239" refString="Monne, M. L &amp; Monne, M. A. (2017) New species of Neotropical Acanthocinini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae). Zootaxa, 4299 (2), 253 - 262. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 4299.2.5" type="journal article" year="2017">Monné &amp; Monné (2017)</bibRefCitation>
modified:
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1438,2013,2035]" box="[151,1438,2013,2035]" pageId="11" pageNumber="580">5(1). Elytra with elongated centrobasal crest................................................................... 5’</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,291]" box="[151,1436,151,173]" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">- Elytra with subcircular centrobasal crest................................................................... 6</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,291]" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">
5’(5). Distance between upper eye lobes about twice width of one upper lobe; metatarsomere I dilated at apex, with acute spine directed upward. 
<collectingCountry box="[374,471,210,232]" name="Colombia" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">Colombia</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[481,561,210,232]" name="Ecuador" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">Ecuador</collectingCountry>
.......................................... 
<taxonomicName authority="Monne &amp; Martins, 1976" authorityName="Monne &amp; Martins" authorityYear="1976" box="[1072,1436,210,232]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="581" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="paradoxus">
<emphasis box="[1072,1197,210,232]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">P. paradoxus</emphasis>
Monné &amp; Martins, 1976
</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,291]" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">
- Distance between upper eye lobes larger than three times width of one upper lobe; metatarsomere I not dilated or with acute spine at apex. 
<collectingCountry box="[363,468,269,291]" name="Costa Rica" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">Costa Rica</collectingCountry>
.............................................................. 
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa, 2021" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Devesa" authorityYear="2021" box="[1222,1353,269,290]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Paranisopodus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="581" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thalassinus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[1222,1353,269,290]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">P. thalassinus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1360,1436,269,290]" pageId="12" pageNumber="581">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1360,1436,269,290]" pageId="12" pageNumber="581" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>