<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a503b11a-2446-4eb1-8c52-0be37806a642" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051545" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-387-33" ID-ZBK="462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:712E2AE1-2E06-4BD2-AA67-F557F425FEAA" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-387-33" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 387" ModsDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" checkinTime="1451246192135" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan F. &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2014" docId="56BA3A4C6BBAA607263CC1C7340C87B5" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 387: 33-49" docOrigin="ZooKeys 387" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827" docTitle="Cymatodera pueblae Burke, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="712E2AE1-2E06-4BD2-AA67-F557F425FEAA" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="41" masterDocId="FFBDFF91FFAAFF8DFFBA9E66E77FFFFD" masterDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" masterLastPageNumber="49" masterPageNumber="33" pageId="6" pageNumber="39" updateTime="1643670665773" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burke, Alan F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>387</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>33</mods:start>
<mods:end>49</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-387-33</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051545" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:712E2AE1-2E06-4BD2-AA67-F557F425FEAA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/56BA3A4C6BBAA607263CC1C7340C87B5" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="41" pageId="6" pageNumber="39">
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="39" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/712E2AE1-2E06-4BD2-AA67-F557F425FEAA" authority="Burke" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera pueblae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pueblae">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="39" start="start">Cymatodera</pageBreakToken>
pueblae Burke
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="6" pageNumber="39">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 2, 7, 12, 18, 19, 27
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="39" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">
Holotype: male, Mexico, Puebla, Highway 18, 6 miles S Esperanza, 14-V-1983, 8100 ft, L. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="O’Brien">O'Brien</normalizedToken>
and G. B. Marshall, printed red label, holotype deposited in CSCA. Paratypes: 2 males and 5 females. 1 male: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="México">Mexico</normalizedToken>
, Puebla, San Esteban Necoxcalco, 15-X-1992, C. Mayorga (CNIN); 1 male: Mexico, Mexico, km 41 highway Texcoco - Calpulalpan, 2685 m, 19 30 43 N 98 52 40 W, 3-VII-2001, beating oak, R. L. Westcott (JNRC); 1 female: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="México">Mexico</normalizedToken>
, Puebla, km 50 Plan de San Miguel, carretera Huajuapan de 
<normalizedToken originalValue="León">Leon</normalizedToken>
- Oaxaca, 14-VIII-1992, C. Mayorga and E. Barrera (CNIN); 1 female: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="México">Mexico</normalizedToken>
, Puebla, Nuevo Vicencio, km 50 Carretera El Seco - Amozoc, 20-V-1995, G. Ortega and E. Barrera (CNIN); 3 females: Mexico, Pachuca, H90, 8000 ft, 6, 9-VII-1937, M. A. Embury (WFBM).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="39" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera pueblae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pueblae">Cymatodera pueblae</taxonomicName>
is readily distinguished from similar species and other congeners by its small size, shape, sinuate midelytral fascia (Fig. 2), male terminalia (Figs 18-19), genitalia (Fig. 12), and geographic distribution (Fig. 34). No other species has this combination of characters.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="41" pageId="6" pageNumber="39" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">Holotype. Small, rather robust, posterior wings present, brachypterous, TL = 8.67 mm. Color: Head fuscous; pronotum, prosternum, mesosternum, mestasternum, legs and elytra brown; abdomen testaceous mesally, becoming brown toward sides; mouthparts pale testaceous. Each elytron bearing a pale testaceous, median fascia that extends from first stria to epipleuron (Fig. 2).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">Head: HL = 1.15 mm, HW = 1.88 mm. Measured across eyes conspicuously wider than pronotum; rugose; frons bi-impressed; strongly, coarsely punctate; clothed with short, semirecumbent setae intermixed with long, semierect and erect setae; eyes moderately large, subsinuate, longer than wide, moderately emarginate in front, feebly bulging laterally, separated by approximately 3.5 eye-widths. Antennae slender; loosely composed; extending slightly beyond posterior margin of elytra; antennomeres 2-3 subequal in length; fourth antennomere slightly longer than third antennomere; antennomeres 4-5 subequal in length; antennomeres 6-10 subequal in length, each slightly shorter than fifth antennomere; antennomeres 5-10 weakly serrate; last antennomere flattened apically, as long as tenth antennomere (Fig. 7).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="39">Thorax: PL = 2.35 mm, PW = 1.67 mm. Pronotum elongate; widest at middle; middle slightly broader than anterior margin; sides constricted subapically; somewhat more constricted behind middle; disc flat; very feebly impressed in front of middle; subbasal tumescence pronounced; surface rugose; moderately coarsely punctate; somewhat vested with short, recumbent setae, intermingled with less numerous, long erect setae. Prosternum wider than long, rugulose, puncticulate. Mesosternum coarsely, deeply punctate. Metasternum convex; reduced in length, rugulose, moderately shallowly punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="40">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="40" start="start">Legs</pageBreakToken>
: Femora clothed with short, recumbent setae interspersed with few erect and semierect setae; tibiae vested with short and long erect and semierect setae; femorae and tibiae transversely, moderately rugose.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="40">
Elytra: EL = 5.17 mm, EW = 2.8 mm. Anterior margin arcuately emarginate; narrower than widest portion of pronotum; humeri very feebly indicated; sides subovoid; widest behind middle; disc convex; apex rounded, broadly dehiscent; surface smooth, clothed with intermixed setae of three sizes; sixth tergite exposed dorsally; sculpturing consisting of regular, rather coarse and deep striae that gradually reduce in size after first third of elytral length, striae not reaching posterior 1/4 of elytral length; interstices about 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
the width of punctation at elytral base.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="41" start="start">Abdomen</pageBreakToken>
: Ventrites 1-5 rugulose, shallowly, moderately punctate; each segment with a pair of large, shallow impressions near sides; clothed with short, recumbent setae interspersed with less numerous, long, semi-erect setae. Fifth visible ventrite convex; sides oblique; posterior margin broadly, very deeply emarginate, emargination extends beyond first third of ventrite length (Fig. 18); sixth visible ventrite subquadrate; rugulose; surface strongly concave, excavated; moderately coarsely punctate; lateral margins subparallel; posterior margin broadly, very deeply emarginate, emargination extends to near base of segment; posterolateral angles arcuate, recurved ventrally. Fifth tergite moderately convex; rugulose; lateral margins subparallel; posterior margin broadly, shallowly, triangularly emarginate (Fig. 19). Sixth tergite subtriangular; surface strongly convex, smooth, shiny, shallowly punctate; lateral margin oblique; posterior margin subtruncate, narrowly, very shallowly, triangularly emarginate. Sixth tergite extending beyond sixth visible ventrite, fully covering it from dorsal view. Aedeagus: 1.4 mm long; ratio of length of parameres to whole tegmen 0.68: 1; tegmen robust, fully covering phallus; parameres robust, pointed at apex, lateral margins moderately oblique, procurved, posterior portion feebly curved ventrally; phallobase broad; phallus with copulatory piece somewhat acuminate distally; phallic plate armed with a row of long, posteriorly pointed denticles along dorsal margin; phallobasic apodeme short, robust, dilated distally; endophallic struts slender throughout their length (Fig. 12).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">Females differ from males by having the posterior margin of the fifth visible ventrite longitudinally truncate; the sixth visible ventrite is rather convex, rugose and broader than long, the lateral margins are strongly oblique, giving the appearance of a broadly rounded margin (Fig. 27); posterior margin of fifth tergite broadly, very shallowly, triangularly emarginate; sixth tergite subtriangular, rugulose, surface moderately convex, broader than long, lateral and posterior margins strongly oblique, forming a semicircular perimeter.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="41" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">Length of males 7.9-9.65 mm, length of females 8.85-10.2 mm; n = 5. Length to width ratio of head: males average 0.71, of females 0.83. Length to width ratio of thorax: males average 1.42, females average 1.6. Length to width ratio of elytra: males average 1.82, females average 1.94. One male and one female are darker than the rest of the type series; the mid-elytral fascia of one female is paler and the legs display a paler, yellowish coloration.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="41" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">
The type series of this species was collected at different localities in south-central Mexico, a high-altitude region characterized by various ranges surrounded by semiarid plateaus. Two males and two females were collected in the central and south region of the state of Puebla, Mexico; three females were collected in the vicinity of Pachuca, Hidalgo, Mexico; and one female was collected in km 41, highway Texcoco - Calpulalpan in the State of Mexico, a region that borders the central-western portion of the state of Puebla. The vegetation type in all collecting localities is predominantly a low to mid-altitude mixture of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus" order="Fagales" pageId="8" pageNumber="41" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Quercus</taxonomicName>
- 
<taxonomicName class="Pinopsida" family="Cupressaceae" genus="Juniperus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Juniperus" order="Pinales" pageId="8" pageNumber="41" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Juniperus</taxonomicName>
- 
<taxonomicName class="Pinopsida" family="Cupressaceae" genus="Cupressus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Cupressus" order="Pinales" pageId="8" pageNumber="41" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Cupressus</taxonomicName>
spp. in association with thorny species (Fig. 34).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="41" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="41">The specific epithet refers to Puebla, the Mexican state where the holotype was collected.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>