<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6297855" ID-GBIF-Dataset="dff18985-af15-4434-9040-aa1af94dbe76" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127476" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6297855" ModsDocID="4764" checkinTime="1243376452396" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Jerdon, T. C." docDate="1851" docId="D17C838F28D1E5168661AD509A380246" docLanguage="en" docName="4764" docOrigin="Madras Journal of Literature and Science 17" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/4764/4764.pdf" docTitle="Ocodoma providens" docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageNumber="108" masterDocId="6BFDDD950C9C483D99A6CBC6DB4FBED7" masterDocTitle="A catalogue of the species of ants found in southern India." masterLastPageNumber="127" masterPageNumber="103" pageNumber="108" updateTime="1645862547081" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A catalogue of the species of ants found in southern India.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jerdon, T. C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Madras Journal of Literature and Science</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1851</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>17</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>103</mods:start>
<mods:end>127</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/4764/4764.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">4764</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">FB264387-6556-4A30-B9E3-B490D5A1293A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6297855" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127476" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6297855" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:D17C838F28D1E5168661AD509A380246" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D17C838F28D1E5168661AD509A380246" lastPageNumber="108" pageNumber="108">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="108">
8. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:232155" authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Ocodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ocodoma providens" lsidName-HNS="Ocodoma providens" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="108" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="providens">Ocodoma providens</taxonomicName>
. (Sykes)?
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="108">Worker about 1 / 7 th of an inch long; head somewhat ovate bulging lightly at the sides, and narrowed behind, notched posteriorly and with two points, rough and granulous; eyes moderate, central, thorax slightly grooved with two small spines on its posterior angles; first abdominal pedicle pointed, second longer, broader and rounded; Warrior with jaws pointed and finely toothed; thorax very rough; length 1 / 4 inch, head large, otherwise similar.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="108">I am by no means certain if this be Sykes' species or not, and, indeed, without actual comparison, it would be very difficult to decide, so similar are the general features of these small Ants, of which I possess four very closely allied species from Southern India, and have only collected these from two or three localities, so that many other allied species may still exist.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="109" pageNumber="108">
The habits and manners of all are Very similar. They live under ground, making for their size a large series of excavations. Their common food I suspect to be animal matter, dead insects, &amp; c. &amp; c ,, which at all events they take readily, but they also carry of large quantities df seeds of various kinds, especially the small grass seeds and, as every gardener knows to his cost, more especially garden seeds. They will take off cabbage, celery, radish, carrot and tomato seeds, but are particularly partial to the light lettuce seeds, and in some gardens, unless the pots in which they are sown 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="109">be</pageStartToken>
suspended, or otherwise protected, the whole of the seeds sown will be removed in one night. I have also had many packets of seeds (especially lettuce) in my room completely emptied before I was aware that the Ants had discovered them. I do not know, how-ever, if they eat them or feed their larvre on them, though for what other purpose they carry them off I could not divine. I have often observed them bring the seeds outside their holes, as recorded by Col. Sykes, and this I think generally at the close of the rainy season, but in some cases I had reason to believe that it was merely the husks, of which I have seen quite heaps, and that the Ants did not take them back to their nests. If any of the forementioned seeds be sown out at once in a bed, most likely in the morning you will find the surface, of the whole spot covered over with little ridges, the works of these creatures, and the few seeds that perhaps remain, dug all round, and being carried off, sometimes above ground, at other times under ground. Their galleries and sub-terranean passages are often very extensive, and it is no easy matter [[ ... ]]] down to their nest to see what becomes of the seeds. I have [[ ... ]] procured the male or female of this species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>