<document ENCODING="Cp1252" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6191058" ID-GBIF-Dataset="070112ba-15a4-4f95-a391-625075ec7d0f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100115046" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6191058" ModsDocAuthor="Bolton, B. &amp; Fisher, B. L." ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="23490" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/23490/23490.pdf" ModsDocTitle="Taxonomy of Afrotropical and West Palaearctic ants of the ponerine genus Hypoponera Santschi (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." checkinTime="1308826820862" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B. &amp; Fisher, B. L." docDate="2011" docId="75093924AB7C8F6D0BF28B7DA8A1B2EC" docLanguage="en" docName="23490_gg0_temp5_treatmentstructure_lsid_dissolve.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2843" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/23490/23490.pdf" docTitle="Hypoponera faex Bolton &amp; Fisher, 2011, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageId="51" lastPageNumber="52" masterDocId="C7AFAB2882DB861B2AC799DC582E378E" masterDocTitle="Taxonomy of Afrotropical and West Palaearctic ants of the ponerine genus Hypoponera Santschi (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="118" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="50" pageNumber="51" updateTime="1645386978139" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Taxonomy of Afrotropical and West Palaearctic ants of the ponerine genus Hypoponera Santschi (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fisher, B. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2843</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>118</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/23490/23490.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">23490</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6191058" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100115046" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6191058" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:75093924AB7C8F6D0BF28B7DA8A1B2EC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/75093924AB7C8F6D0BF28B7DA8A1B2EC" lastPageId="51" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="50" pageNumber="51">
<subSubSection pageId="50" pageNumber="51" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="50" pageNumber="51">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:298347" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Hypoponera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Hypoponera faex Bolton &amp; Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="50" pageNumber="51" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="faex">Hypoponera faex Bolton &amp; Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="50" pageNumber="51" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="51" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="50" pageNumber="51" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="50" pageNumber="51">HOLOTYPE WORKER. Measurements: HL 0.88, HW 0.72, HS 0.800, SL 0.66, PrW 0.57, WL 1.30, HFL 0.72, PeNL 0.26, PeH 0.58, PeNW 0.44, PeS 0.427. Indices: CI 82, SI 92, PeNI 77, LPeI 45, DPeI 169.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="51" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="50" pageNumber="51">
Eyes present, of 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="–" pageId="50" pageNumber="51">-</normalizedToken>
6 small ommatidia. In full-face view apex of scape, when laid straight back from its insertion, just fails to touch the midpoint of the posterior margin; SL/HL 0.75. Cephalic dorsum coarsely and densely reticulate-punctate. Lateroventral surfaces of head completely covered with very coarse and conspicuous reticulate-punctate to punctate-rugulose sculpture, without discrete punctures separated by areas of smooth shining cuticle. Side of pronotum reticulate-punctate, strongly so but slightly less coarsely and densely than the head; this sculpture fades out dorsally and towards the midline the pronotum is almost entirely smooth. Mesonotum finely and densely 
<pageBreakToken pageId="51" pageNumber="52" start="start">punctate</pageBreakToken>
dorsally; the propodeal dorsum with disorganised punctate sculpture anteriorly, but this fades out posteriorly so that the mid-dorsal area just before the declivity is smooth. Metanotal groove absent on dorsum of mesosoma but a slight change of slope is present between mesonotum and propodeum. In profile the anterior margination of the mesopleuron is merely obtusely angled behind base of anterior coxa; without a projecting acute angle or tooth. Propodeum narrowly marginate between declivity and sides. Posterior face of petiole node with a series of short cuticular ridges that arise from the base of the peduncle. Petiole node with weak sculpture present on sides, and more weakly so on dorsum, fading out towards the midline. Maximum width of first gastral tergite in dorsal view is greater than the width of the second tergite at its midlength. Base of cinctus of second gastral tergite with cross-ribs conspicuous in dorsal view. Posttergite of second gastral segment, from posterior margin of cinctus to apex, very slightly broader than long. Disc of second gastral tergite with sharply incised punctures that are separated by areas of smooth cuticle; distance between punctures averages distinctly greater than diameters of the punctures.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
Holotype worker, Ethiopia (Abyssinia on main label): Gamo Prov., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Bonghé" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Bonghe</normalizedToken>
valley, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Gughé" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Gughe</normalizedToken>
highlands, c. 9500
<normalizedToken originalValue="–" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">-</normalizedToken>
10000 ft, 8.xii.1948, Ethiopia 1948-49, BM 1949-184, sifted humus under bamboo, near waterfall, south side of valley (H. Scott) (BMNH). Right funiculus is missing from holotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="51" pageNumber="52">This is a large, conspicuous and coarsely sculptured species, the only known Afrotropical species that combines the presence of radiating cuticular ridges at the base of the posterior face of the petiole node with relatively well-developed eyes. The condition of the metanotal groove is between absent and vestigially present. There is no strong, deep groove that cuts across and interrupts the surface, but a slight change of slope and vague hint of a depression remains.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>