<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153" ID-GBIF-Dataset="248dd503-13d6-4dae-a0aa-d7d5fdc867a2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127871323" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-657-93" ID-ZBK="199B466C0D1C4E2D81331C0D77FCBD3F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B1D49BEA-B845-4047-BF0E-396CB099CD09" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-657-93" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 657" ModsDocTitle="Descriptions of three new carbonaria-group species of Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy from China, with a key to the carbonaria-group species (Diptera, Fanniidae)" checkinTime="1487401264803" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Wang, Ming-fu, Li, Wei, Zhao, Yu-wan, Wu, Jie &amp; Zhang, Dong" docDate="2017" docId="C2FD8D23220D772BA4D91DA1C21B435D" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 657: 93-107" docOrigin="ZooKeys 657" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153" docTitle="Fannia nitidiventris Wang &amp; Zhang, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="B1D49BEA-B845-4047-BF0E-396CB099CD09" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="100" masterDocId="FF85FFD5FF9BFFAFC117966BD410FFC8" masterDocTitle="Descriptions of three new carbonaria-group species of Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy from China, with a key to the carbonaria-group species (Diptera, Fanniidae)" masterLastPageNumber="107" masterPageNumber="93" pageId="5" pageNumber="98" updateTime="1643572775644" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Descriptions of three new carbonaria-group species of Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy from China, with a key to the carbonaria-group species (Diptera, Fanniidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wang, Ming-fu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Wei</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhao, Yu-wan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wu, Jie</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhang, Dong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>657</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>93</mods:start>
<mods:end>107</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-657-93</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">199B466C0D1C4E2D81331C0D77FCBD3F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">199B466C0D1C4E2D81331C0D77FCBD3F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127871323" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B1D49BEA-B845-4047-BF0E-396CB099CD09" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C2FD8D23220D772BA4D91DA1C21B435D" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="100" pageId="5" pageNumber="98">
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="98" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="98">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/B1D49BEA-B845-4047-BF0E-396CB099CD09" authority="Wang &amp; Zhang" class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia nitidiventris" order="Diptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="98" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nitidiventris">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="98" start="start">Fannia</pageBreakToken>
nitidiventris Wang &amp; Zhang
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="5" pageNumber="98">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Fig. 2
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="99" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="99">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="99" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="99">This species is characterized as follows: frontal setae five or six; posterior acr biserial; calypters yellowish; haltere yellow; fore tibia all black; hind femur with three or four av; abdomen black and shining, without pollinosity or stripe; sternite 5 slightly concave on posterior margin; from ventral view, cercal plate slightly rounded, the hook-like projection on its lower margin curved outward; surstylus slightly broad.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="99">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="99">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia nitidiventris" order="Diptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nitidiventris">Fannia nitidiventris</taxonomicName>
Wang &amp; Zhang, sp. n., male, holotype (specimen from Ningxia, deposited in IESNU). A Terminalia, ventral view B Terminalia, lateral view C Sternite 5, ventral view. Scale bars 0.25 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="100" pageId="6" pageNumber="99" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="99">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="100" pageId="6" pageNumber="99">
MALE. Body length 4.8 mm. The whole body shining black. Eye bare and large; postocular setae in one row, short and neatly arranged, without occipital seta; fronto-orbital plate and parafacial with gray pollinosity; at narrowest point frons 2/3 of the distance between outer margins of two posterior ocelli, 2/3 of the width of postpedicel; frontal stripe linear at narrowest point; frontal setae five or six, nearly reaching 2/3 of frons, the gaps filled with numerous fine setulae, orbital setae absent; parafacial bare and narrow, at middle as wide as 2/5 of the width of postpedicel; antenna black, postpedicel 2.0 times longer than wide, arista yellow in basal half, haired, the longest hair equal to basal aristal width; epistoma not projecting beyond vibrissal angle, vibrissal angle behind frontal angle in profile; subvibrissal setulae in one row, lateral of subvibrissal setulae row with a row of short setae; gena and genal dilation with black setulae, upper margin of gena without upcurved seta; proboscis stout, labella large; prementum shining, with thin grayish yellow pollinosity, 1.2 times longer than wide; palpus black, claviform, as long as prementum. Thorax black in ground color, shining, notum with thin grayish yellow pollinosity; acr biserial, hair-like, only prescutellar pairs stout, the distance between acr rows narrower than the distance between acr row and dc row, dc 2+3, ia 0+2, pra 1, 2/3 of the length of posterior notopleural seta, notopleuron without setula; proepisternal setae 2, proepimeral seta 1, lower part with one slender setula; basisternum, proepisternum, anepimeron, meron and katepimeron bare; katepisternal setae 1+1, katepisternum without ventral spine, with only some fine hair; anterior spiracle yellowish and small, posterior one brownish yellow; calypters yellowish, the lower one slightly projecting beyond the upper one. Wing brownish; veins brown; wing base being similar color as rest of wing; tegula black; basicosta brownish; costal spine inconspicuous; node of Rs bare on ventral and dorsal surfaces; vein R4+5 straight, veins R4+5 and M1+2 parallel to each other distally; crossveins without obvious cloud; haltere yellow. Legs entirely black; fore coxa without anterior spine on ventral surface, fore femur with complete pv row, fore tibia without ad and median p, with only one d in preapical part, fore first tarsomere with several longish basal setae on ventral surface; mid coxa without a hook-like spine or spine-like seta, mid femur with complete av row, short and strong, at middle the longest seta shorter than the width of mid femur, without gap, comb-like in distal 1/3, with complete pv row, biserial in median part, the longest one is shorter than the width of mid femur, with one fine p row, the longest one is equal to the width of mid femur, mid tibia slightly swollen towards apex, with three ad, two pd, and with numerous slender setulae on ventral surface, the longest one 2/3 of mid tibial width in distal half, mid first tarsomere without basal 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="100" start="start">tooth-like</pageBreakToken>
spine on ventral surface; hind coxa bare on posterior surface, hind femur not curved, with three or four stout av only in distal 2/5, without pv, hind tibia with two av, two ad and one median d. Abdomen oval and flattened, black in ground color, shining, without stripe and pollinosity; sternite one bare, sternite 5 broad, concave on posterior margin (Fig. 2C); from ventral view, cercal plate slightly rounded, the hook-like projection on its lower margin curved outward (Fig. 2A); surstylus slightly broad, not separated into two branches (Fig. 2A, B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">FEMALE. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="100" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">
The new species is distinguished from its likely closest relative 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia fuscitibia" order="Diptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="100" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fuscitibia">Fannia fuscitibia</taxonomicName>
Stein, 1920 by having five or six frontal setae; posterior acr biserial; calypters yellowish; haltere yellow; fore tibia all black; hind femur with three or four av; abdomen black and shining, without stripe; sternite 5 slightly concave on posterior margin (Fig. 2C); from ventral view, cercal plate slightly rounded, the hook-like projection on its lower margin curved outward (Fig. 2A); surstylus slightly broad (Fig. 2B).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="100" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">This specific name refers to a characteristic of the species that the abdomen is black and shiny.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="100" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Male: China, Ningxia, Jingyuan, Lvyuan, 1700 m, 29.V.2008, Coll. M.F. Wang (IESNU).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="100" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Known only from the type locality in Ningxia, China.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>