<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6271083" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8b7f91fc-871f-4eda-a481-b5def7620b41" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100124842" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6271083" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E7DA85A9-DDF7-44BF-BD07-1F567EE506ED" ModsDocID="z00707p001" checkinTime="1246973006595" checkinUser="thomas" docAuthor="Wilson J. E. M. Costa" docDate="2004" docId="00D3CDEB0F26121A989BDAF2FA193B91" docLanguage="en" docName="2004_Costa5_gg1.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 707" docSource="http://www.zoobank.org/urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:9D4BF84D-0FDC-4C56-B4C7-C3B237E2C038" docTitle="Moema apurinan Costa, 2004, new species" docType="treatment" docUuid="E7DA85A9-DDF7-44BF-BD07-1F567EE506ED" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="13" lastPageNumber="7" masterDocId="E904F00E7C1B1D262298406FBF5DE0B7" masterDocTitle="Moema apurinan sp. n. and Aphyolebias boticarioi sp. n. (Teleostei: Cyprinodontiformes: Rivulidae): two new annual killifishes from the Rio Purus basin, Brazilian Amazon." masterLastPageNumber="12" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="3" updateTime="1645761972696" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Moema apurinan sp. n. and Aphyolebias boticarioi sp. n. (Teleostei: Cyprinodontiformes: Rivulidae): two new annual killifishes from the Rio Purus basin, Brazilian Amazon.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wilson J. E. M. Costa</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2004</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>707</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>12</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.zoobank.org/urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:9D4BF84D-0FDC-4C56-B4C7-C3B237E2C038</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank-PUB">z00707p001</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">EFD7A94F-D68A-4A04-801C-C6B2E9DF76B8</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6271083" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100124842" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6271083" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E7DA85A9-DDF7-44BF-BD07-1F567EE506ED" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/00D3CDEB0F26121A989BDAF2FA193B91" lastPageNumber="7" pageNumber="3">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="3">
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E7DA85A9-DDF7-44BF-BD07-1F567EE506ED" class="Actinopterygii" family="Rivulidae" genus="Moema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Moema apurinan Costa 2004:3" order="Cyprinodontiformes" pageNumber="3" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="apurinan">Moema apurinan</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="3">(Figs. 1-2)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="3">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923899155" country="Brazil" stateProvince="Estado do Acre">
<typeStatus>Holotype</typeStatus>
. 
<collectionCode collectionName="UFRJ">UFRJ</collectionCode>
5980, male, 52.5 mm SL; 
<collectingCountry>Brazil</collectingCountry>
: 
<collectingRegion>Estado do Acre</collectingRegion>
: Porto Acre, temporary pool within forest, Rio Acre floodplains, Rio Purus drainage, Rio Amazonas basin (9o35’12.2”S 67o31’50.6”W; altitude 132 m); W. J. E. M. Costa, S. Lima and A. Pinto, 
<date day="10" month="06" value="2003-06-10" year="2003">10 June 2003</date>
.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph country="Brazil" pageNumber="3">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923899153" country="Brazil" stateProvince="Estado do Acre">
<typeStatus>Paratypes</typeStatus>
. 
<collectionCode collectionName="UFRJ">UFRJ</collectionCode>
5981, 4 males, 50.2-55.4 mm SL, 5 females, 42.7-51.1 mm SL
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923899152" country="Brazil" stateProvince="Estado do Acre">
<collectionCode collectionName="UFRJ">UFRJ</collectionCode>
5982, 4 males, 48.2-54.4 mm SL, 3 females, 46.8-47.9 mm SL (c&amp;s); collected with 
<typeStatus>holotype</typeStatus>
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="3">
Diagnosis: The new species differs from all other species of the genus in having fewer caudal-fin rays (30-31, vs. 32-35). It is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Rivulidae" genus="Moema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Cyprinodontiformes" pageNumber="3" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="staecki">M. staecki (Seegers)</taxonomicName>
, and distinguished from all other congeners by possessing contact organs on scales of the flank of the male (vs. contact organs absent), caudal fin acuminate (vs. rounded to subtruncate), fewer pectoral-fin rays (14, vs. 15-17), fewer vertebrae (33-35, vs. 36-39), and narrower rostral cartilage (width about 75-80% of rostral cartilage length, vs. 90-100% in the remaining species of the genus, except in 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:07C0B958-A31B-47C3-9BF1-4D91025A23FA" class="Actinopterygii" family="Rivulidae" genus="Moema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Moema ortegai Costa 2003:7" order="Cyprinodontiformes" pageNumber="3" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="ortegai">M. ortegai Costa</taxonomicName>
, about 145%). The new species differs from 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Rivulidae" genus="Moema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Cyprinodontiformes" pageNumber="3" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="staecki">M. staecki</taxonomicName>
by having a longer pectoral fin (tip reaching between the base of 8th and 13th anal fin rays, vs. reaching urogenital papilla), and wider basihyal (width about 75% of basihyal length, vs. 55 %).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="4">Description: Morphometric data given in Table 1. Male larger than female, largest male 55.4 mm SL. Dorsal profile gently convex from snout to end of dorsal-fin base, approximately straight to slightly concave on caudal peduncle. Ventral profile slightly convex on head, almost straight from anterior portion of venter to end of anal-fin base, nearly straight on caudal peduncle. Body slender, subcylindrical anteriorly, deeper than wide, to compressed posteriorly. Greatest body depth at level of pelvic-fin base. Jaws long, snout pointed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="4">Tip of dorsal fin pointed, with short filamentous ray in male, rounded to slightly pointed in female. Anal fin approximately rectangular, longer than deep; tip pointed, long, reaching vertical through middle of caudal fin in male, rounded and short in female. Caudal fin long, acuminate, with short posterior filamentous rays in male, short and elliptical in female. Pectoral fin lanceolate, terminating in long tip, reaching between base of 8th and 13th anal fin rays in male, slightly pointed and short, reaching between pelvic-fin base and anus in female. Pelvic fin rounded, tip reaching between base of 1st and 3rd anal-fin rays in male, and between anus and urogenital papilla in female. Pelvic-fin bases in close proximity. Dorsal-fin origin on vertical through base of 9th or 10th anal-fin ray, and between neural spines of 20th and 22nd vertebrae. Anal-fin origin between pleural ribs of 16th and 17th vertebrae. Dorsal-fin rays 10-11; anal-fin rays 16-17; caudal-fin rays 30- 31; pectoral-fin rays 14; pelvic-fin rays 7.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="5" pageNumber="4">Scales large, cycloid. Body and head entirely scaled, except anterior ventral surface of head. Body scales extending over caudal-fin base; no scales on dorsal and anal fins. Frontal squamation E-patterned; E-scales not overlapping medially; scales arranged in irregular circular pattern around A-scale without exposed margins. Longitudinal series of scales 34- 35; transverse series of scales 8; scale rows around caudal peduncle 16. Ctenii-like contact organ on each scale of median ventral portion of male flank. Supraorbital neuromasts 3 + 3.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="5">Interhyal vestigial, not ossified. Rostral cartilage longer than wide, width 75-80% length. Basihyal subtriangular, width 75% length; basihyal cartilage 45% basihyal length. Six branchiostegal rays. Second pharyngobranchial with no, one or two small teeth. Gillrakers of first branchial arch 1 + 10. Vomerine teeth 4-11. Ventral process of posttemporal present. Total vertebrae 33-35.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="6" pageNumber="5">Coloration: Male: Side of body greenish golden, with three purplish brown stripes alternating with narrow dark golden stripes; dark red crimson dots simultaneously arranged both in longitudinal rows, on two dorsalmost purplish brown stripes, and in oblique rows crossing flank. Dorsum light brown with brown dots, venter white. Side of head greenish golden with dark brown blotches. Jaws light brown. Infraorbital region and ventral surface of head white. Iris yellowish green, with dark brown bar crossing center of eye. Dorsal fin pale greenish yellow with small dark reddish brown spots. Anal fin light greenish yellow, basal region light blue, with small dark reddish brown spots. Caudal fin pale greenish yellow with small dark reddish brown spots on dorsal portion and short brown stripes or dots parallel to fin rays on median portion; broad light orange stripe with bright yellow dorsal contour, dorsally outlined by dark brown stripe, on ventral margin of fin. Pelvic fin light greenish yellow, with transverse rows of small brown spots. Pectoral fin yellowish hyaline.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Female: Side of body light metallic green, with six longitudinal rows of brown dots. Dorsum light brown with brown dots, venter white. Side of head pale metallic green with faint brown spots. Jaws gray. Infraorbital region and ventral surface of head white. Iris yellow, with pale brown bar crossing center of eye. Dorsal and anal fins pale greenish yellow with small dark brown spots. Caudal fin pale greenish yellow with small dark brown spots on dorsal portion, and faint small gray spots on middle. Paired fins hyaline.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Distribution: Known only from the type locality, Rio Acre floodplains, Rio Purus drainage, Rio Amazonas basin, northwestern Brazil (Fig. 3).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageNumber="7">Habitat notes: The type series was collected in a temporary pool within the forest. The pool was small, about 7 m of long and about 3 m wide, shallow, about 0.40-0.60 m deep. The water was dark brown. No aquatic vegetation.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="etymology">
<paragraph pageNumber="7">
Etymology: The specific name apurinan (
<normalizedToken originalValue="Apurinã">Apurina</normalizedToken>
) is the Portuguese name of an indigenous tribe of people, also known as 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ipurinã">Ipurina</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Popingaré">Popingare</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kangitê">Kangite</normalizedToken>
, with own language derived from the linguistic group Aruak, inhabiting lands drained by the Rio Purus basin in the region of the type locality of the new species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>