<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5940988" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8c3d903d-6d82-45d1-a1c0-b29f5b97d0c1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157145399" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5940988" ID-ZooBank="8A6746BE-616B-4FEC-AA37-E274F8508255" approvalRequired="12" approvalRequired_for_matCits="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="11" checkinTime="1557922264577" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Zhang, Chun-Tian, Shima, Hiroshi, Liang, Hou-Can &amp; Li, He-Nan" docDate="2019" docId="03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4603.1.1.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4603 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Estheria cristata Meigen 1826" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" masterDocId="FFCDA47DFFC3C87F6C11DD1A5025827F" masterDocTitle="Four new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from China and Nepal, with a review of the East Palearctic and Oriental species" masterLastPageNumber="38" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" updateTime="1643736677199" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Four new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from China and Nepal, with a review of the East Palearctic and Oriental species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhang, Chun-Tian</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Shima, Hiroshi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liang, Hou-Can</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, He-Nan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2019-05-08</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4603</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>38</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4603.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">8c3d903d-6d82-45d1-a1c0-b29f5b97d0c1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">2841928</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8A6746BE-616B-4FEC-AA37-E274F8508255</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5940988" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157145399" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5940988" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<subSubSection box="[151,542,1936,1962]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,588,1936,1996]" box="[151,542,1936,1962]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,542,1936,1962]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" reason="1">
<taxonomicName authority="(Meigen, 1826)" authorityName="Meigen" authorityYear="1826" baseAuthorityName="Meigen" baseAuthorityYear="1826" box="[151,542,1936,1962]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cristata">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,542,1936,1962]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,350,1936,1962]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Estheria cristata</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Meigen" box="[365,534,1936,1962]" firstAuthor="Meigen" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" pagination="42 - 54" refId="ref33117" refString="Meigen, J. W. (1826) Systematische Beschreibung der bekannten europaischen zweiflugeligen Insekten. Funfter Theil. Schulz, Hamm, xii + 412 pp., pls. 42 - 54." type="book chapter" year="1826">Meigen, 1826</bibRefCitation>
)
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,588,1971,1996]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,588,1936,1996]" box="[151,588,1971,1996]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,231,1971,1996]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–12" captionStartId="27.[151,264,1739,1762]" captionTargetBox="[265,1314,205,1697]" captionTargetId="figure@27.[256,1327,195,1710]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURES 1–12. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in caudal view. 1. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 2. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 3. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 4. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 5. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 6. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 7. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 8. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 9. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 10. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 11. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 12. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841934/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Figs 6</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[243,273,1971,1995]" captionStart="FIGURES 13–24" captionStartId="28.[151,264,1735,1758]" captionTargetBox="[275,1294,206,1693]" captionTargetId="figure@28.[249,1320,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="28" captionText="FIGURES 13–24. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in lateral view. 13. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 14. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 15. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 16. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 17. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 18. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 19. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 20. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 21. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 22. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 23. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 24. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841940/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">18</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[285,315,1971,1995]" captionStart="FIGURES 25–36" captionStartId="29.[151,264,1733,1756]" captionTargetBox="[270,1317,224,1702]" captionTargetId="figure@29.[255,1326,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="29" captionText="FIGURES 25–36. Estheria spp., phallic complexes in lateral view. 25. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 26. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 27. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 28. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 29. E. acuta (Portschinsky), speciumen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 30. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 31. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 32. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 33. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 34. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 35. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 36. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841948/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">30</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[327,357,1971,1995]" captionStart="FIGURES 37–52" captionStartId="30.[151,264,1665,1688]" captionTargetBox="[281,1301,213,1612]" captionTargetId="figure@30.[281,1301,193,1636]" captionTargetPageId="30" captionText="FIGURES 37–52. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. 37–48, 52. Sternite 5 in ventral view. 49–50. Epandrial complex in caudal (49) and lateral (50) views. 51. Phallic complex in lateral view. 37. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 38. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 39. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 40. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 41. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU); 42. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 43. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 44. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 45. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 46. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 47. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 48. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). 49–52. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841952/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">42</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[369,399,1971,1996]" captionStart="FIGURES 53–64" captionStartId="31.[151,264,1742,1765]" captionTargetBox="[319,1255,193,1713]" captionTargetId="figure@31.[319,1255,193,1713]" captionTargetPageId="31" captionText="FIGURES 53–64. Estheria spp., male heads in anterior view. 53. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 54. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 55. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 56. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 57. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 58. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 59. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 60. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 61. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 62. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 63. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 64. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841962/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">58</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[411,442,1971,1996]" captionStart="FIGURES 65–73" captionStartId="32.[151,264,1753,1776]" captionTargetBox="[206,1374,193,1722]" captionTargetId="figure@32.[206,1374,193,1722]" captionTargetPageId="32" captionText="FIGURES 65–73. Estheria spp., female heads in anterior view. 65. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Duoxiongla Mountain, Paizhen, Milin to Médog, Tibet, China (SYNU). 66. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Xuekagou, Milin, Tibet, China (SYNU). 67. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 68. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Xuekagou, Milin, Tibet, China (SYNU). 69. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 70. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Huanren, Laotudingzi Mountains, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 71. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 72. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 73. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS). Scale bars = 0.5 mm (Figs 65–66, 69–72); 1.0 mm (Figs 67–68, 73)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841970/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">69</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[454,484,1971,1995]" captionStart="FIGURES 83–91" captionStartId="34.[151,264,1795,1818]" captionTargetBox="[270,1275,215,1733]" captionTargetId="figure@34.[234,1351,193,1773]" captionTargetPageId="34" captionText="FIGURES 83–91. Estheria spp., male heads in lateral view. 83. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 84. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 85. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 86. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 87. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 88. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 89. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 90. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS). 91. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars: 0.5 mm (Figs 87–89); 1 mm (Figs 90–91)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841988/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">84</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[495,525,1971,1995]" captionStart="FIGURES 92–106" captionStartId="35.[151,264,1719,1742]" captionTargetBox="[267,1298,254,1691]" captionTargetId="figure@35.[258,1309,211,1697]" captionTargetPageId="35" captionText="FIGURES 92–106. Estheria spp., male habitus in dorsal (92–104) and lateral (106) view; head in anterior view (105). 92. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 93. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 94. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 95. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 96. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 97. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden- Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 98. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 99. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 100. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 101. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 102. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 103. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS). 104–106. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841996/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">97</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[537,579,1971,1995]" captionStart="FIGURES 107–118" captionStartId="36.[151,264,1749,1772]" captionTargetBox="[239,1323,246,1694]" captionTargetId="figure@36.[239,1341,193,1751]" captionTargetPageId="36" captionText="FIGURES 107–118. Estheria spp., male habitus in lateral view. 107. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 108. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 109. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 110. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 111. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 112. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 113. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 114. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 115. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 116. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 117. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 118. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2842000/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">112</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,152,327]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<treatmentCitationGroup pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<taxonomicName authority="Meigen, 1826: 41" authorityName="Meigen" authorityPageNumber="41" authorityYear="1826" box="[151,486,152,174]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Dexia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cristata">
<emphasis box="[151,295,153,174]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Dexia cristata</emphasis>
<treatmentCitation author="Meigen, J. W." box="[303,486,152,174]" page="41" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" year="1826">
<bibRefCitation author="Meigen" box="[303,448,152,174]" firstAuthor="Meigen" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" pagination="42 - 54" refId="ref33117" refString="Meigen, J. W. (1826) Systematische Beschreibung der bekannten europaischen zweiflugeligen Insekten. Funfter Theil. Schulz, Hamm, xii + 412 pp., pls. 42 - 54." type="book chapter" year="1826">Meigen, 1826</bibRefCitation>
: 41
</treatmentCitation>
</taxonomicName>
. Type locality: 
<collectingCountry box="[644,738,152,174]" name="Germany" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Germany</collectingCountry>
(Stolberg). 
<typeStatus box="[861,962,153,174]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Lectotype</typeStatus>
<specimenCount box="[969,988,153,174]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="male">♂</specimenCount>
and one female 
<typeStatus box="[1158,1294,152,174]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">paralectotype</typeStatus>
(
<collectionCode box="[1308,1389,152,174]" country="France" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34988" name="Museum National d'Histoire Naturelle" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">MNHN</collectionCode>
) not examined. References: 
<treatmentCitation author="Herting, B. &amp; Dely-Draskovits, A." box="[435,831,182,204]" page="363" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" year="1993">
<bibRefCitation author="Herting &amp; Dely-Draskovits" box="[435,780,182,204]" firstAuthor="Herting" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" pagination="118 - 458" refId="ref32837" refString="Herting, B. &amp; Dely-Draskovits, A. (1993) Family Tachinidae. In: Soos, A. &amp; Papp, L. (Eds.), Catalog of Palaearctic Diptera. Fol. 13. Anthomyiidae-Tachinidae. Hungarian Natural HistoryMuseum, Budapest, pp. 118 - 458." type="book chapter" year="1993">Herting &amp; Dely-Draskovits (1993</bibRefCitation>
: 363
</treatmentCitation>
; Palearctic catalog); 
<treatmentCitation author="Cerretti, P. &amp; Tschorsnig, H. - P." box="[1042,1380,182,204]" page="272" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" year="2012">
<bibRefCitation author="Cerretti &amp; Tschorsnig" box="[1042,1331,182,204]" firstAuthor="Cerretti" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" pagination="271 - 286" refId="ref32552" refString="Cerretti, P. &amp; Tschorsnig, H. - P. (2012) Three new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from the Mediterranean, with a key to the European and Mediterranean species of the genus. Stuttgarter Beitrage zur Naturkunde A, Neue Serie, 5, 271 - 286." type="journal article" year="2012">Cerretti &amp; Tschorsnig (2012</bibRefCitation>
: 272
</treatmentCitation>
, 284; species, key); 
<treatmentCitation author="Zhang, C. - T. &amp; Cui, L. &amp; Zheng, G. &amp; Hou, P. &amp; Xu, W. - J." box="[343,584,213,235]" page="139" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" year="2013">
<bibRefCitation author="Zhang" box="[343,533,213,235]" etAl="et al." firstAuthor="Zhang" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" pagination="136 - 142" refId="ref34325" refString="Zhang, C. - T., Cui, L., Zheng, G., Hou, P. &amp; Xu, W. - J. (2013) Checklist of subfamily Dexiinae (Diptera, Tachinidae) from the National Zoological Museum of China, Part 1. Journal of Shenyang Normal University (Natural Science), 31, 136 - 142." type="journal article" year="2013">
Zhang 
<emphasis box="[414,458,213,235]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">et al</emphasis>
. (2013
</bibRefCitation>
: 139
</treatmentCitation>
; checklist).
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,152,327]" box="[151,1073,244,266]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<treatmentCitationGroup box="[151,1073,244,266]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<taxonomicName authority="Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830: 306" authorityName="Robineau-Desvoidy" authorityPageNumber="306" authorityYear="1830" box="[151,700,244,266]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="imperatoriae">
<emphasis box="[151,375,244,266]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Estheria imperatoriae</emphasis>
<treatmentCitation author="Robineau-Desvoidy, J. B." box="[381,700,244,266]" page="306" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" year="1830">
<bibRefCitation author="Robineau-Desvoidy" box="[381,649,244,266]" firstAuthor="Robineau-Desvoidy" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" pagination="1 - 813" refId="ref33638" refString="Robineau-Desvoidy, J. B. (1830) Essai sur les myodaires. Memoires Presentes par Divers Savans a l'Academie Royale des Sciences de l'Institut de France. Sciences Mathematiques et Physiques, Series 2, 2, 1 - 813." type="journal article" year="1830">Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830</bibRefCitation>
: 306
</treatmentCitation>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<typeStatus box="[709,759,245,266]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Type</typeStatus>
locality: St.-Sauveur (
<collectingCountry box="[987,1062,244,266]" name="France" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">France</collectingCountry>
).
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,152,327]" box="[151,1014,274,296]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<treatmentCitationGroup box="[151,1014,274,296]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<taxonomicName authority="Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830: 306" authorityName="Robineau-Desvoidy" authorityPageNumber="306" authorityYear="1830" box="[151,640,274,296]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="floralis">
<emphasis box="[151,316,274,296]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Estheria floralis</emphasis>
<treatmentCitation author="Robineau-Desvoidy, J. B." box="[322,640,274,296]" page="306" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" year="1830">
<bibRefCitation author="Robineau-Desvoidy" box="[322,590,274,296]" firstAuthor="Robineau-Desvoidy" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" pagination="1 - 813" refId="ref33638" refString="Robineau-Desvoidy, J. B. (1830) Essai sur les myodaires. Memoires Presentes par Divers Savans a l'Academie Royale des Sciences de l'Institut de France. Sciences Mathematiques et Physiques, Series 2, 2, 1 - 813." type="journal article" year="1830">Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830</bibRefCitation>
: 306
</treatmentCitation>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<typeStatus box="[650,700,275,296]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Type</typeStatus>
locality: St.-Sauveur (
<collectingCountry box="[928,1003,274,296]" name="France" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">France</collectingCountry>
).
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,152,327]" box="[151,753,305,327]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<treatmentCitationGroup box="[151,753,305,327]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<taxonomicName authority="Walker, 1849: 832" authorityName="Walker" authorityPageNumber="832" authorityYear="1849" box="[151,522,305,327]" class="Insecta" family="Sarcophagidae" genus="Sarcophaga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="edax">
<emphasis box="[151,326,305,327]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Sarcophaga edax</emphasis>
<treatmentCitation author="Walker, F." box="[332,522,305,327]" page="832" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" year="1849">
<bibRefCitation author="Walker" box="[332,471,305,327]" firstAuthor="Walker" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" pagination="689 - 1172" refId="ref34281" refString="Walker, F. (1849) List of the specimens of dipterous insects in the collection of the British Museum. Part IF. British Museum (Natural History), London, 484 pp. [pp. 689 - 1172]" type="book chapter" year="1849">Walker, 1849</bibRefCitation>
: 832
</treatmentCitation>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<typeStatus box="[531,581,306,327]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Type</typeStatus>
locality: 
<collectingCountry box="[677,749,306,327]" name="France" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">France</collectingCountry>
.
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,273,372,397]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
Frons of male about 1/7 of head width; facial carina indistinct; prementum 5–6 times as long as wide. Three strongest postpronotal setae arranged in a straight line; 3 postsutural dorsocentral setae; wing cell r 
<subScript attach="left" box="[1335,1359,422,436]" fontSize="6" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">4+5</subScript>
with a petiole at most 0.20 times as long as postangular section of M; costal spine about as long as crossvein r-m.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" box="[199,688,482,507]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,372,482,507]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Redescription.</emphasis>
Body length: 9.0– 
<quantity box="[583,684,482,507]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.05" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" unit="mm" value="10.5">10.5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis box="[199,264,518,543]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Male.</emphasis>
Head covered with yellowish-white pruinosity (fronto-orbital plate, parafacial, face gena and occiput); frontal vitta dark brown; lunule reddish-brown; 1 
<taxonomicName box="[696,869,554,579]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
, pedicel and palpus reddish-yellow. Frons about 1/ 7 of head width; parafacial about 3 times as wide as 1 
<taxonomicName box="[773,950,590,615]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
; genal height 0.6–0.7 of eye height; facial carina indistinct or weakly developed; occiput usually with two rows of black setulae below postocellar seta row. First flagellomere about 2.2 times as long as pedicel; arista plumose, aristal hairs about as long as width of 1 
<taxonomicName pageId="13" pageNumber="14" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
; prementum 5–6 times as long as wide.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Thorax black, covered with yellowish gray-white pruinosity, with 5 longitudinal dark vittae on presutural scutum and 4 vittae on anterior half of postsutural scutum; scutellum reddish-brown at least apically; 5–6 postpronotal setae, the strongest three arranged in a straight line; 2 presutural and 2 postsutural acrostichal setae; 3 presutural and 3 postsutural dorsocentral setae; 3 postsutural intra-alar setae; 3 supra-alar setae, the first one short; 3 katepisternal setae; scutellum with 3 pairs of marginal setae and a pair of discal setae. 
<emphasis box="[1160,1216,880,903]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Wing</emphasis>
hyaline, brownish; calypter milk-white, margin yellowish, lower calypter with short fringes on outer margin. Costal spine about as long as crossvein r-m, relative lengths of 2nd, 3rd and 4th costal sections approximately 1.1:2.3:1, radial node with 2–3 setulae dorsally and ventrally; cell r 
<subScript attach="left" box="[599,623,1001,1015]" fontSize="6" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">4+5</subScript>
closed near apex, with a petiole slightly shorter than crossvein r-m. 
<emphasis box="[1383,1436,988,1011]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Legs</emphasis>
dark except for middle part of tibiae reddish-yellow. Fore tibia with 4 anterodorsal and 2 posterior setae; Fore claws and pulvilli longer than 5th tarsomere; mid femur with 4 strong anterior setae, mid tibia with 3 anterodorsal (upper two shorter), 2 posterior and 1 ventral setae; hind tibia with 1 upper (short) and 2 lower (long) anterodorsal setae, 1 upper (short) and 2 lower (long) posterior setae and 1 ventral seta, 2 apical dorsal setae, 1 long apical anteroventral and 1 short apical posteroventral setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Abdomen long-ovate, black, covered with dense and entirely grayish-white pruinosity on tergites; syntergite 1+2 medially excavated to posterior margin, without median marginal setae, with 1 lateral marginal seta and 2 lateral discal setae; tergite 3 with 2 median marginal setae, 1 lateral marginal seta and 2 median discal setae; tergite 4 with 2 median discal setae and a row of marginal setae, tergite 5 with rows of marginal and discal setae. Sternite 1 with black hairs. 
<emphasis box="[364,546,1349,1374]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Male terminalia</emphasis>
as in 
<figureCitation box="[612,683,1349,1374]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–12" captionStartId="27.[151,264,1739,1762]" captionTargetBox="[265,1314,205,1697]" captionTargetId="figure@27.[256,1327,195,1710]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURES 1–12. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in caudal view. 1. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 2. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 3. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 4. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 5. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 6. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 7. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 8. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 9. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 10. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 11. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 12. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841934/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Figs 6</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[695,725,1350,1374]" captionStart="FIGURES 13–24" captionStartId="28.[151,264,1735,1758]" captionTargetBox="[275,1294,206,1693]" captionTargetId="figure@28.[249,1320,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="28" captionText="FIGURES 13–24. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in lateral view. 13. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 14. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 15. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 16. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 17. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 18. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 19. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 20. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 21. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 22. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 23. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 24. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841940/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">18</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[737,767,1350,1374]" captionStart="FIGURES 25–36" captionStartId="29.[151,264,1733,1756]" captionTargetBox="[270,1317,224,1702]" captionTargetId="figure@29.[255,1326,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="29" captionText="FIGURES 25–36. Estheria spp., phallic complexes in lateral view. 25. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 26. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 27. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 28. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 29. E. acuta (Portschinsky), speciumen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 30. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 31. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 32. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 33. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 34. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 35. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 36. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841948/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">30</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[779,810,1350,1374]" captionStart="FIGURES 37–52" captionStartId="30.[151,264,1665,1688]" captionTargetBox="[281,1301,213,1612]" captionTargetId="figure@30.[281,1301,193,1636]" captionTargetPageId="30" captionText="FIGURES 37–52. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. 37–48, 52. Sternite 5 in ventral view. 49–50. Epandrial complex in caudal (49) and lateral (50) views. 51. Phallic complex in lateral view. 37. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 38. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 39. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 40. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 41. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU); 42. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 43. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 44. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 45. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 46. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 47. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 48. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). 49–52. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841952/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">42</figureCitation>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis box="[199,290,1385,1410]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Female.</emphasis>
As male, except as follows: head covered with grayish-yellow pruinosity. Frons narrowed posteriorly, about 3/5 of head width at narrowest point; parafacial about 4 times as wide as 1 
<taxonomicName box="[1054,1228,1421,1446]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
; gena about 3/4 of eye height; three proclinate outer orbital setae, 1 prevertical seta; ocellar seta strong, about as long as upper frontal setae; inner vertical seta about twice as long as outer vertical seta; occiput with 2 black setae below postocellar setae; 1 
<taxonomicName box="[231,403,1529,1554]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
about twice as long as pedicel. Fore claws pulvilli and shorter than 5th tarsomere. Abdomen ovate, tergite 5 with a pair of discal setae and 1–2 weak lateral discal setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,435,1601,1626]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Material examined.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2242324177" collectingDate="1971-08-22" collectionCode="IZCAS" collectorName="Y. - S. Shi" country="China" location="Wulagai" municipality="Dong Ujimqin Qi" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-female="1" stateProvince="Inner Mongolia">
<collectingCountry box="[445,512,1601,1626]" name="China" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">China</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[529,711,1601,1626]" country="China" name="Nei Mongol" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Inner Mongolia</collectingRegion>
: 
<specimenCount box="[725,770,1602,1626]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="female">1 ♀</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[787,994,1601,1626]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Dong Ujimqin Qi</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596:8E823BC8FFCEC8726FE1DB5B54748425" box="[1008,1105,1601,1626]" country="China" municipality="Dong Ujimqin Qi" name="Wulagai" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" stateProvince="Inner Mongolia">Wulagai</location>
, 
<collectingDate box="[1119,1268,1602,1626]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1971-08-22">
<date box="[1119,1268,1602,1626]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1971-08-22">22.VIII.1971</date>
</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName box="[1282,1384,1601,1626]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Y.-S. Shi</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode box="[159,246,1638,1662]" country="China" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/crjh-4ne1" name="Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">IZCAS</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2242324171" box="[264,1177,1637,1662]" collectingDate="1957-07-12" collectionCode="IZCAS" collectorName="C. - P. Hong" country="China" elevation="470" location="Shuiding" municipality="Jitai" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" stateProvince="Xinjiang">
<collectingRegion box="[264,367,1637,1662]" country="China" name="Xinjiang Uygur" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Xinjiang</collectingRegion>
: 
<specimenCount box="[376,420,1638,1662]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="male">1 ♂</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[431,481,1637,1662]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Jitai</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596:8E823BC8FFCEC8726DFADB7F52768401" box="[491,595,1637,1662]" country="China" municipality="Jitai" name="Shuiding" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" stateProvince="Xinjiang">Shuiding</location>
, 
<elevation box="[606,735,1637,1662]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.7" metricValueMax="4.8" metricValueMin="4.6" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" unit="m" value="470.0" valueMax="480.0" valueMin="460.0">
<quantity box="[606,735,1637,1662]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.7" metricValueMax="4.8" metricValueMin="4.6" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" unit="m" value="470.0" valueMax="480.0" valueMin="460.0">460–480 m</quantity>
</elevation>
, 
<collectingDate box="[746,885,1637,1662]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1957-07-12">
<date box="[746,885,1637,1662]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1957-07-12">12.VII.1957</date>
</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName box="[896,1019,1638,1662]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">C.-P. Hong</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode box="[1082,1169,1638,1662]" country="China" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/crjh-4ne1" name="Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">IZCAS</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2242324174" collectingDate="2015-08-06" collectionCode="IZCAS" collectorName="H. - B. Liang" country="China" elevation="3760" location="Songlinkou" municipality="Milin" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" stateProvince="Xizang">
<collectingRegion box="[1187,1268,1637,1662]" country="China" name="Xizang" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Xizang</collectingRegion>
(= 
<collectingRegion box="[1306,1370,1637,1662]" country="China" name="Xizang" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Tibet</collectingRegion>
): 
<specimenCount box="[1388,1431,1638,1662]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="male">1 ♂</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[151,216,1673,1698]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Milin</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596:8E823BC8FFCEC8726CF6DB93514E84DD" box="[231,363,1673,1698]" country="China" municipality="Milin" name="Songlinkou" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" stateProvince="Xizang">Songlinkou</location>
, 
<elevation box="[378,469,1673,1698]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="3.76" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" unit="m" value="3760.0">
<quantity box="[378,469,1673,1698]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="3.76" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" unit="m" value="3760.0">3760 m</quantity>
</elevation>
, 
<collectingDate box="[485,619,1673,1698]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="2015-08-06">
<date box="[485,619,1673,1698]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="2015-08-06">6.VIII.2015</date>
</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName box="[634,773,1673,1698]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">H.-B. Liang</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode box="[844,931,1674,1698]" country="China" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/crjh-4ne1" name="Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">IZCAS</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2242324180" collectingDate="1954-07-22" collectionCode="ZMHB" country="Germany" determinerName="J. Ziegler" location="Wald au Teisnach" municipality="Bayer" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1">
<collectingCountry box="[953,1057,1674,1698]" name="Germany" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Germany</collectingCountry>
: 
<specimenCount box="[1076,1124,1674,1698]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="male">1 ♂</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[1139,1208,1674,1698]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Bayer</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596:8E823BC8FFCEC87268D6DB9355BD84DD" box="[1223,1432,1673,1698]" country="Germany" municipality="Bayer" name="Wald au Teisnach" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Wald au Teisnach</location>
, 
<collectingDate box="[151,291,1709,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1954-07-22">
<date box="[151,291,1709,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1954-07-22">22.VII.1954</date>
</collectingDate>
, [no collector], (
<collectionCode box="[478,564,1710,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">ZMHB</collectionCode>
; det. 
<determinerName box="[625,737,1709,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">J. Ziegler</determinerName>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2242324267" collectingDate="1997-07-07" collectionCode="SMNS" collectorName="H. - P. Tschorsnig" country="Germany" determinerName="H. - P. Tschorsnig" location="Willingen" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="2" specimenCount-female="1" specimenCount-male="1" stateProvince="Baden-Wurttemberg">
<specimenCount box="[757,801,1710,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="male">1 ♂</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount box="[814,857,1710,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="female">1 ♀</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[872,1105,1709,1734]" country="Germany" name="Baden-Wuerttemberg" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Baden-Württemberg</collectingRegion>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFCFC8726C86DA8A525B8596:8E823BC8FFCEC872684CDBB754EA84B9" box="[1117,1231,1709,1734]" country="Germany" name="Willingen" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" stateProvince="Baden-Wurttemberg">Willingen</location>
, 
<collectingDate box="[1242,1368,1710,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1997-07-07">
<date box="[1242,1368,1710,1734]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="1997-07-07">7.VII.1997</date>
</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName pageId="13" pageNumber="14">H.-P. Tschorsnig</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode box="[336,417,1746,1770]" country="Germany" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34840" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34840" name="Staatliches Museum fuer Naturkund Stuttgart" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">SMNS</collectionCode>
; det. 
<determinerName box="[477,668,1745,1770]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">H.-P. Tschorsnig</determinerName>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,352,1781,1806]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Distribution.</emphasis>
<collectingCountry box="[365,432,1781,1806]" name="China" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">China</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion box="[453,640,1781,1806]" country="China" name="Nei Mongol" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Inner Mongolia</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[657,758,1781,1806]" country="China" name="Xinjiang Uygur" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Xinjiang</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[776,861,1781,1806]" country="China" name="Xizang" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Xizang</collectingRegion>
), Europe (northwards to 
<collectingCountry box="[1165,1258,1781,1806]" name="United Kingdom" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">England</collectingCountry>
and 
<collectingCountry box="[1326,1432,1782,1806]" name="Germany" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Germany</collectingCountry>
, Transcaucasus).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[199,1237,1853,1878]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" box="[199,1237,1853,1878]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,273,1853,1878]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Hosts.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authorityName="" authorityYear="1758" box="[280,406,1853,1878]" class="Insecta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="order">Coleoptera</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Latreille" authorityYear="1802" box="[417,565,1853,1878]" class="Insecta" family="Scarabaeidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Scarabaeidae</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Linnaeus" baseAuthorityYear="1758" box="[580,836,1853,1878]" class="Insecta" family="Rutelidae" genus="Phyllopertha" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="horticola">
<emphasis box="[580,836,1853,1878]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Phyllopertha horticola</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
) (Ziegler &amp; Tschorsnig 2016: 346).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,372,2025]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,315,1889,1914]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Remarks.</emphasis>
We have examined identified specimens from Europe and confirm that our specimens are conspecific with these. This species appears to be similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="(Portschinsky)" authorityName="Portschinsky" baseAuthorityName="Portschinsky" box="[842,1112,1925,1950]" class="Insecta" family="Pteromalidae" genus="Syntomocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">
<emphasis box="[842,936,1927,1950]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">E. acuta</emphasis>
(Portschinsky)
</taxonomicName>
, but differs in having longer prementum, 3 presutural and 3 postsutural dorsocentral setae, wing cell r 
<subScript attach="left" box="[968,992,1976,1990]" fontSize="6" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">4+5</subScript>
closed, with a petiole, wing not brownclouded around crossveins r-m and dM-Cu.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>