<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.598.7983" ID-GBIF-Dataset="abd221f1-79a2-45ab-8228-fc395abb9cb7" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127874082" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-598-113" ID-ZBK="2ADA598CCEC14EFF8AD07431B9E17B36" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C3089E00-6329-40D5-B852-ECBF3D1F70BB" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-598-113" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 598" ModsDocTitle="Review of the Fanniapostica-group Chillcott, 1961 of the genus Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830, with description of two new species from the Palearctic and Oriental regions (Diptera, Fanniidae)" checkinTime="1465974289187" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Wang, Ming-fu, Li, Wei, Zhu, Wei-bing &amp; Zhang, Dong" docDate="2016" docId="35C8B9778B40EBC83B77DE3F62AE86B1" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 598: 113-128" docOrigin="ZooKeys 598" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.598.7983" docTitle="Fannia ningxiaensis Wang &amp; Zhang, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="C3089E00-6329-40D5-B852-ECBF3D1F70BB" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="121" masterDocId="C308FFA0FF8BFFDB2972FFF2772F717E" masterDocTitle="Review of the Fanniapostica-group Chillcott, 1961 of the genus Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830, with description of two new species from the Palearctic and Oriental regions (Diptera, Fanniidae)" masterLastPageNumber="128" masterPageNumber="113" pageId="5" pageNumber="118" updateTime="1643598358636" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the Fanniapostica-group Chillcott, 1961 of the genus Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830, with description of two new species from the Palearctic and Oriental regions (Diptera, Fanniidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wang, Ming-fu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Wei</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhu, Wei-bing</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhang, Dong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>598</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>113</mods:start>
<mods:end>128</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.598.7983</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.598.7983</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-598-113</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">2ADA598CCEC14EFF8AD07431B9E17B36</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2ADA598CCEC14EFF8AD07431B9E17B36</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127874082" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C3089E00-6329-40D5-B852-ECBF3D1F70BB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/35C8B9778B40EBC83B77DE3F62AE86B1" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="121" pageId="5" pageNumber="118">
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="118" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="118">Taxon classification Animalia Diptera Fanniidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="118" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="118">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/C3089E00-6329-40D5-B852-ECBF3D1F70BB" authority="Wang &amp; Zhang" class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia ningxiaensis" order="Diptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="118" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ningxiaensis">Fannia ningxiaensis Wang &amp; Zhang</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="5" pageNumber="118">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Fig. 2
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="120" pageId="6" pageNumber="119" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="119">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="119" start="start">Description</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="120" pageId="6" pageNumber="119">
MALE. Body length 4.0 mm. Eye bare; postocular setae in one row, slender and curved anteriorly, occipital setae situated behind the postocular setae on vertex and in one row; fronto-orbital plate and parafacial with grayish-silvery pollinosity; frons at narrowest point slightly narrower than the distance between outer margins of posterior ocelli, about 2/3 as wide as postpedicel; frontal vitta black, linear at narrowest point; frontal setae 7 to 9, stout, nearly reaching ocellar triangle, the gaps between them without setulae; orbital setae absent; parafacial bare and narrow, at middle about 2/5 of width of postpedicel; antenna black, postpedicel about 1.5x as long as wide, arista black and ciliated, slightly swollen in basal part, the longest individual hairs shorter than aristal base; epistoma not projecting beyond vibrissal angle, vibrissal angle behind frontal angle in profile; subvibrissal setulae in one row, lateral of it with 2 or 3 fine setae; gena and genal dilation with black setulae, upper margin of gena without upcurved setae; prementum with thin grayish pollinosity, slightly shining, about 2.3x as long as wide; palpus black, claviform, about as long as prementum. Thorax ground-color black, notum with thin dark brown pollinosity, without a distinct vitta; presutural acr biserial, slightly stout, prescutellar pairs stout, the distance between the 2 rows of acr narrower than the distance between rows of acr and dc; dc 2+3, ia 0+2, pra 2, the anterior one about 3/5 as long as posterior notopleural seta; notopleuron bare; proepisternal setae 2, proepimeral seta 1, with about 10 slender setulae around it; basisternum, proepisternum, anepimeron, meron and katepimeron bare; katepisternal setae 1+1, katepisternum without a ventral spine, with only some fine and curved setae; anterior spiracle brown, posterior spiracle dark brown; calypters brownish with yellow-brownish margin, the lower calypter slightly smaller than the upper one and not projecting beyond the upper one. Wing brownish; veins brown; wing-base of similar color to other parts of wing; tegula black; basicosta brown; costal spine inconspicuous; node of Rs bare on ventral and dorsal surfaces; vein R4+5 straight, parallel to vein M1+2 distally; crossveins not distinctly clouded; haltere brownish-yellow. Legs entirely black; fore coxa without a spine on anterior ventral surface; fore femur with a complete row of pv; fore tibia 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="120" start="start">without</pageBreakToken>
ad and median p, and with only one stout preapical d; fore first tarsomere with several longish basal setae on ventral surface; mid coxa without a hook-like spine or spine-like seta; mid femur with 6 to 8 stout av in basal part, becoming gradually shorter and denser towards apex, with a gap in preapical part, 2 to 4 comb-like setae in distal part, and with a row of stout pv, slightly biserial in median part, with a gap in preapical part, with 4 or 5 comb-like setae in distal part, and with a row of slender p; mid tibia slightly swollen in distal half, with one ad and one pd in distal half, and with numerous slender setulae on ventral surface, the longest one about 3/4 of mid tibial width in distal part; mid first tarsomere without a basal tooth-like spine on ventral surface, and with only short basal clustered setulae; hind coxa bare on posterior surface; hind femur with only one stout av in preapical part, with 8 to 10 stout pv in distal half; hind tibia with one av, one ad, and one median d, and with 8 or 9 slightly erect median setae on posterior surface. Abdomen oval and flattened, ground-color black, with dense grayish-blue pollinosity; syntergite 1+2 and tergites 3-4 each with one dark broad median triangular vitta, tergite 5 with one dark median stripe in basal part; sternite 1 with setulae, sternite 5 broad (Fig. 2C); cercal plate longish, from ventral view, apex of cercal plate projecting, large and rounded, as broad as middle part of cercal plate and slightly broader than the basal part (Fig. 2A); bacilliform process twisted (Fig. 2B); surstylus slender, hook-like at apex and pointed posteriorly (Fig. 2A, B).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="120">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="120">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia ningxiaensis" order="Diptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ningxiaensis">Fannia ningxiaensis</taxonomicName>
Wang &amp; Zhang, sp. n., male, holotype: (specimen from Ningxia, deposited in IESNU). A. Terminalia, ventral view B Terminalia, lateral view C Sternite 5, ventral view. Scale for A−C = 0.25 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="120">FEMALE. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="121" pageId="7" pageNumber="120" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="120">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="121" pageId="7" pageNumber="120">
The new species is attributed to the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="spathiophora" pageId="7" pageNumber="120" rank="species" species="spathiophora">spathiophora</taxonomicName>
-subgroup of the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="postica" pageId="7" pageNumber="120" rank="species" species="postica">postica</taxonomicName>
-group. It can be distinguished from a similar European species, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia stigi" order="Diptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="stigi">Fannia stigi</taxonomicName>
Rognes, 1982, by the following character states: mid first tarsomere with only short basal clustered setulae on ventral surface; hind femur with 8 to 10 stout pv in distal half; abdominal syntergite 1+2 and tergites 3-4 each with one dark broad median triangular vitta; apex of cercal plate projecting, large and rounded in ventral view (Fig. 2A); bacilliform process twisted (Fig. 2B), while 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia stigi" order="Diptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="stigi">Fannia stigi</taxonomicName>
Rognes mid first tarsomere with a basal 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="121" start="start">tooth-like</pageBreakToken>
spine; hind femur with 4 or 5 stout pv in distal half; abdominal syntergite 1+2 and tergites 3-4 each with a dark median stripe; apex of ceral plate not projecting, half round in ventral view; bacilliform process not twisted.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="121" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="121">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="121">The specific name is derived from name of the type locality, Ningxia.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="121" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="121">Types material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="121">Holotype male: China, Ningxia, Guyuan, Jingyuan, Dongshanpo, 2200 m, 27.VI.2008, Coll. M.F. Wang (IESNU). Paratype: 1 male, China, Ningxia, Guyuan, Jingyuan, Dongshanpo, 2000 m, 27.VI.2008, Coll. M.F. Wang (IESNU).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="121" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="121">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="121">Palearctic: China (Ningxia).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>