<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6289129" ID-GBIF-Dataset="da733677-6530-4a1b-b657-6c8861e011c4" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100135032" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6289129" ModsDocAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." ModsDocID="20597" checkinTime="1243372031551" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." docDate="1922" docId="6D465383A375E6B189F340F568B38934" docLanguage="en" docName="20597_3" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 45" docSource="http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097" docTitle="Pseudolasius gowdeyi Wheeler, 1922, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="223" masterDocId="A3DBBB852C51D8D8BF05CD746529E30A" masterDocTitle="The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition." masterLastPageNumber="269" masterPageNumber="39" pageNumber="222" updateTime="1645827484690" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wheeler, W. M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1922</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>45</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>39</mods:start>
<mods:end>269</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">20597</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6289129" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100135032" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6289129" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6D465383A375E6B189F340F568B38934" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6D465383A375E6B189F340F568B38934" lastPageNumber="223" pageNumber="222">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="222">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:35699" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Pseudolasius" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Pseudolasius gowdeyi Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="222" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gowdeyi">Pseudolasius gowdeyi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="222">Text Figure 57</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="222">Worker major.- Length 2.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="223" pageNumber="222">Head as broad as long, subrectangular, as broad in front as behind, with straight sides and feebly but distinctly excised posterior border. Eyes absent. Mandibles with five acute teeth on their oblique apical borders, the median tooth small, the apical twice as long as the other three. Clypeus convex but not carinate, its anterior border nearly straight. Antennae slender, the scapes extending about one-fifth their length beyond the posterior corners of the head; the second funicular joint not longer than broad, the succeeding joints slightly longer than broad. Thorax short and robust, the pro- and mesonotum forming together an evenly rounded convexity; mesopleura. somewhat compressed; epinotum short, nearly horizontal, lower than the mesonotum, passing through a curve into the sloping, flat declivity. Petiolar scale narrowed above, its sides curved, its superior border rather blunt, truncated, entire. Gaster elliptical. Legs rather short.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="223">Whole body smooth and shining, except the mandibles, which are opaque and very finely and densely striated. Integument of the body and appendages apparently, microscopically but not densely punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="223">Hairs and pubescence white, the former sparse, conspicuous only on the clypeus, thorax, and gaster, the appendages being without erect hairs. Pubescence short, rather dense on the head and gaster, longer on the latter, slightly oblique on the scapes and legs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="223">Pale yellow, the head and thorax a little darker, mandibular teeth dark brown. Worker minor.- Length l.8 to 2 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="223">Differing from the major worker in its smaller head, which is elongate and with very feeble occipital excision. Antennal scapes reaching nearly one-fourth their length beyond the posterior corners of the head; joints 2 to 6 of the funiculus as broad as long.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="223">Described from two major and sixteen minor workers taken by Mr. C. C. Gowdey at Entebbe, Uganda. They were found attending subterranean coccids(Pseudococcus citri Risso) about the roots of coffee.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="223">This is readily distinguished from all the preceding species by its smaller size, paler color, the complete absence of eyes even in the major workers, the shape of the head and thorax, and the pilosity.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>