<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.776.26308" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e8e2e290-1373-4d85-be88-b1c1e3816de3" ID-GBIF-Taxon="146727263" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-776-13" ID-ZBK="FA4C4AA2006440AA848DC76C7ADFC828" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FA4C4AA2-0064-40AA-848D-C76C7ADFC828" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-776-13" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 776" ModsDocTitle="Searching for shelter in a ferruginous cave? A new species of Pasipha from a plateau in the Brazilian savanna (Platyhelminthes, Tricladida)" checkinTime="1532776092836" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Leal-Zanchet, Ana &amp; Marques, Alessandro" docDate="2018" docId="FAEF173E629810ADD10615B55DB118B1" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 776: 13-25" docOrigin="ZooKeys 776" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.776.26308" docTitle="Pasipha ferrariaphila Leal-Zanchet &amp; Marques, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="FA4C4AA2-0064-40AA-848D-C76C7ADFC828" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="13" masterDocId="FF88FFD5FF86FFAE1A1EFFE48060B809" masterDocTitle="Searching for shelter in a ferruginous cave? A new species of Pasipha from a plateau in the Brazilian savanna (Platyhelminthes, Tricladida)" masterLastPageNumber="25" masterPageNumber="13" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" updateTime="1643535252543" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Searching for shelter in a ferruginous cave? A new species of Pasipha from a plateau in the Brazilian savanna (Platyhelminthes, Tricladida)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Leal-Zanchet, Ana</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Marques, Alessandro</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>776</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>13</mods:start>
<mods:end>25</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.776.26308</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.776.26308</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-776-13</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">FA4C4AA2006440AA848DC76C7ADFC828</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">FA4C4AA2006440AA848DC76C7ADFC828</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="146727263" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FA4C4AA2-0064-40AA-848D-C76C7ADFC828" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FAEF173E629810ADD10615B55DB118B1" lastPageNumber="13" pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/FA4C4AA2-0064-40AA-848D-C76C7ADFC828" family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="13">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Holotype MZUSP PL 2141: leg. Carste 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ciência">Ciencia</normalizedToken>
e Ambiente, 16 January 2014, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Conceição">Conceicao</normalizedToken>
do Mato Dentro (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-18.917276">18°55'02.2&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-43.428444">43°25'42.4&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
; altitude 931 m a.s.l.), state of Minas Gerais (MG), Brazil - anterior tip: transverse sections on 8 slides; anterior region at the level of the ovaries: sagittal sections on 7 slides; pre-pharyngeal region in two fragments: transverse sections on 4 slides and sagittal sections on 6 slides; pharynx: sagittal sections on 5 slides; copulatory apparatus: sagittal sections on 8 slides.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="type-locality">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Type-locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Conceição">Conceicao</normalizedToken>
do Mato Dentro, state of Minas Gerais (MG), Brasil.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
is characterised by almost homogeneous dorsal pigmentation pattern, eyes spreading over the dorsal surface, collar-shaped pharynx, prostatic vesicle with two portions separated by a canal, ejaculatory duct long and spacious, male and female atria separated by a constriction and female atrium spacious, long and with a strongly developed circular musculature in its proximal part, resembling a sphincter.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Body elongate with parallel margins; anterior tip rounded and posterior tip pointed (Figs 2-3). After fixation, length of 22 mm, maximal width of 2 mm, and maximal height 0.7 mm. Mouth at 77% of body length and gonopore at 82% of body length.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Figures 2-3. 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, dorsal view, 2 general view of preserved specimen 3 schematic drawing of the anterior region of body. The arrow indicates the anterior extremity. Eyes were drawn based on observations carried out under both stereomicroscope and microscope.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Fixed specimen with dorsal surface covered by fine, almost homogeneous dark brown pigmentation over light brown ground colour, which is discernible under stereomicroscope on a thin, almost imperceptible median stripe (Fig. 3). Ventral surface pale yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Eyes, initially monolobate (pigment cups of 15-25 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
) and disposed in an irregular row, surround anterior tip (Fig. 3). After that, some eyes become bilobed (pigment cups of 10-15 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
) and spread onto dorsal surface of body. Towards posterior end, eyes gradually becoming sparser.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Sensory pits, as simple invaginations (20-40 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
deep), contour anterior tip and occur ventro-marginally in a single row (Fig. 4) in approximately the anterior 1/6 of body. Creeping sole occupies almost whole body width.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Figures 4-8. 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype. 4 anterior region, transverse section 5-7 pre-pharyngeal region, transverse sections 8 pharynx, sagittal section.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Four gland types discharge through dorsal epidermis and body margins of pre-pharyngeal region: abundant rhabditogen cells with xanthophil secretion (Figs 5-7), numerous erythrophil glands with coarse granular secretion of two types (with ovoid or rounded granules), and sparse cyanophil glands with amorphous secretion. Creeping sole receives three types of glands: cyanophil glands with amorphous secretion, rhabditogen cells with small rhabdites, as well as scarcer glands with rounded erythrophil granules. Glandular margin absent (Fig. 5). Glands discharging through anterior tip of body similar to those of pre-pharyngeal region.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Cutaneous musculature with usual three layers (circular, oblique, and longitudinal layers), longitudinal layer with small bundles (Figs 6-7). Mc:h 10%. Thickness of cutaneous musculature similar to that of epidermis. Ventral musculature (about 30 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
) two times thicker than dorsal musculature (about 15 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
) at sagittal plane in pre-pharyngeal region. Thickness of cutaneous musculature gradually diminishes towards anterior tip.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Mesenchymal musculature (Figs 6-7) poorly developed, mainly composed of three layers: (1) dorsal subcutaneous with oblique decussate fibres (about 2 fibres thick); (2) supra-intestinal transverse (about 2 fibres thick); (3) sub-intestinal transverse (about 3-4 fibres thick). Mesenchymal musculature thicker in cephalic region than in pre-pharyngeal region, especially sub-intestinal transverse layer (Fig. 4); thickness gradually diminishes towards anterior tip.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Pharynx collar-shaped, nearly 8% of body length, occupies almost all length of pharyngeal pouch. Pharyngeal dorsal insertion posteriorly shifted next to end of pharyngeal pouch. Mouth in median third of pharyngeal pouch (Fig. 8). Oesophagus absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Testes in two irregular rows on either side of body, located close to dorsal cutaneous musculature (Fig. 7). Testes begin at the same transversal level as ovaries, about 3.5 mm from anterior tip (16% of body length), and extend to near root of pharynx. Sperm ducts dorsal to ovovitelline ducts, laterally displaced, forming spermiducal vesicles laterally to pharynx. Behind pharynx, spermiducal vesicles well developed and sinuous, extending laterally to penis bulb. These vesicles recurve, ascend, and, subsequently, open through lateral walls of proximal portion of prostatic vesicle (Fig. 9). Large prostatic vesicle extrabulbar and not forked, close to pharyngeal pouch. This vesicle shows two portions united by a narrow canal: proximal portion oval-elongate, with a spacious lumen; distal portion globose with a narrower lumen (Figs 9-11). Ejaculatory duct sinuous, with irregular contour and ample lumen, arising from posterior region of prostatic vesicle and thereafter ascending to open into proximal portion of male atrium. Male atrium long with folded walls (Figs 9-10). Proximal region of male atrium, about anterior 1/4 of male atrium length, with narrower lumen (Figs 9-10; 12). Distal region of male atrium communicates with female atrium through a constriction (Figs 9-10).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, sagittal composite reconstruction of copulatory apparatus. The arrow indicates the strong musculature in female atrium. Anterior to the left.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Epithelial lining of prostatic vesicle ciliated and columnar, receiving coarse granular erythrophil or probably mixed secretion (erythrophil core and a chromophobic peripheral part), more abundant in its proximal portion. Distal portion of prostatic vesicle receives numerous amorphous, slightly cyanophil secretions. Muscularis of prostatic vesicle thick (20-35 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
thick), constituted of interwoven longitudinal, circular and some oblique fibres (Fig. 11). Canal uniting both portions of prostatic vesicle receives few coarse granular erythrophil secretions. Ejaculatory duct lined with ciliated, columnar epithelium, receiving openings from finely granular, cyanophil glands. Muscle coat of ejaculatory duct relatively thick (about 20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
), mainly constituted of circular fibres. Male atrium lined with non-ciliated and erythrophil epithelium in distal region, ciliated and cyanophil in proximal region. Glands of distal region of two types: with coarse granular, erythrophil secretion and with amorphous, cyanophil secretion, whereas proximal region receives a third type with finely granular, erythrophil secretion. Muscularis of male atrium thick (50-60 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
), mainly comprised of circular fibres followed by some longitudinal fibres, diminishing in thickness and number of fibres in proximal region (20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Figures 10-14. 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, copulatory apparatus in sagittal sections. 10 general view 11 proximal region of prostatic vesicle 12 ejaculatory duct and proximal portion of male atrium 13 proximal portion of female atrium 14 gonoduct. Arrows indicate the strong musculature in female atrium; the arrow head indicates the canal separating proximal and distal regions of prostatic vesicle. Anterior to the left.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Vitelline follicles, situated between intestinal branches, well-developed (Figs 5-7). Ovaries oval-elongate, measuring about 0.3 mm in length; they are situated dorsally to ventral nerve plate, about 3.5 mm from anterior tip (16% of body length). Ovovitelline ducts emerge dorsally from median third of ovaries and run posteriorly, close to median plane, immediately above ventral nerve plate. Distal sections of ovovitelline ducts run medially lateral to female atrium, with a slight asymmetry, the left ovovitelline duct contouring the atrial coat ventrally dislocated. They unite posteriorly to female atrium to form a C-shaped, ascending common glandular ovovitelline duct (Fig. 9). Female canal, horizontal, penetrates female muscle coat and opens into posterior-most part of female atrium. Female atrium ovoid with folded walls and narrow lumen (Figs 9-10; 13). Length of female atrium about 4/5 of male atrial length.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Female canal and atrium lined with columnar epithelium, sparsely ciliated in female canal. Glands of female atrium of two types: numerous glands with cyanophil, amorphous secretion and few glands with coarse granular erythrophil secretions. Female canal receives scant glands with coarse granular erythrophil secretion. Musculature of female atrium well developed, especially in proximal half (120 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
thick), composed mainly of circular fibres intermingled with some oblique fibres (Fig. 13).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Male and female atria with independent muscle coats (Figs 9-10), comprising longitudinal, oblique, and circular fibres. A constriction separates male and female atria (Figs 9-10). Gonoduct large and inclined backward at the sagittal plane (Figs 9; 14).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="ecology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Ecology and distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
is known only from its type locality. It was sampled in an area situated in the eastern margin of Serra do 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Espinhaço">Espinhaco</normalizedToken>
Plateau, in southeastern Brazil. The area is covered by Brazilian savanna on rocky outcrops, also known as rupestrian complexes (
<bibRefCitation author="Rapini, AA" journalOrPublisher="Megadiversidade" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="16 - 24" title="A flora dos campos rupestres quartziticos da Cadeia do Espinhaco." volume="4" year="2008">Rapini et al. 2008</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Oliveira, PA" journalOrPublisher="Acta Botanica Brasilica" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="141 - 149" title="Phytosociology of the herbaceous-subshrub layer of a rupestrian complex in Serra do Espinhaco, Brazil." url="https://doi.org/10.1590/0102-33062017abb0225" volume="32" year="2018">Oliveira et al. 2018</bibRefCitation>
), which occur associated with quartzite, sandstone, and itabirite above 900 m of altitude along the Serra do 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Espinhaço">Espinhaco</normalizedToken>
(
<bibRefCitation pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Giulietti et al. 2000</bibRefCitation>
). The sampling site is the entrance zone of a ferruginous cave, representing 80% of the cave area. The sampling place is a low cavity (1.6 m high) with an area of 37 m2 and sandy soil covered by crushed ferruginous rocks. It is located in an area planned for mining activities, which is constituted by itabirite profoundly affected by such activities. Caves within iron formations are small and narrow, being formed by chemical, physical, and biological processes (
<bibRefCitation pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Auler 2015</bibRefCitation>
). Ten samplings were conducted in the area between December 2010 and September 2014, but a single specimen of 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
was collected. Since this specimen shows no troglomorphic features and was collected only once in the entrance zone of the cave, we consider that its occurrence in the cave is probably occasional, using it as a temporary shelter.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">The holotype, directly fixed in 70% ethanol during field work, showed a coiled body with some artefacts (Fig. 2), such as loss of the epidermis in some body parts, numerous lacunae in the mesenchyme and ovaries. In spite of that, the anatomy and most histological aspects were relatively well preserved. Nevertheless, the specimen may have some distortion in its anatomical features. The flatworm was parasitised by helminths (Figs 6; 8; 11).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="comparative discussion">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Comparative discussion.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
The new species herein described shows characteristics that match the diagnosis of the genus 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="genus">Pasipha</taxonomicName>
, such as a body shape with parallel margins and prostatic vesicle with two portions receiving different secretions (
<bibRefCitation pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Ogren and Kawakatsu 1990</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Carbayo, F" journalOrPublisher="Zoologica Scripta" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="508 - 528" title="Molecular phylogeny of Geoplaninae (Platyhelminthes) challenges current classification: proposal of taxonomic actions." url="https://doi.org/10.1111/zsc.12019" volume="42" year="2013">Carbayo et al. 2013</bibRefCitation>
). 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
also shows a folded male atrium and the female canal presenting a post-flex condition with ventral approach, i.e., the ovovitelline ducts join behind the female atrium and the female canal arises from posterior region of the female canal.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
With eyes spreading over the dorsal surface of the body and a collar-shaped pharynx, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
resembles five other species of 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="genus">Pasipha</taxonomicName>
, namely 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="plana">P. plana</taxonomicName>
(Schirch, 1929), 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. penhana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="penhana">P. penhana</taxonomicName>
(Riester, 1938), 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. velutina" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="velutina">P. velutina</taxonomicName>
(Riester, 1938), 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rosea" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="rosea">P. rosea</taxonomicName>
(E.M. Froehlich, 1955) and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. hauseri" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="hauseri">P. hauseri</taxonomicName>
(Froehlich, 1959). Hence, we discuss 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
in relation to these five species in the following comparative discussion.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
With respect to colour pattern, by having an almost homogeneous dorsal pattern with a thin, nearly imperceptible median stripe, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
differs from the five species mentioned above. 
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha penhana" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="penhana">Pasipha penhana</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. hauseri" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="hauseri">P. hauseri</taxonomicName>
show a quite distinct median stripe, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="plana">P. plana</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rosea" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="rosea">P. rosea</taxonomicName>
a light median stripe and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. velutina" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="velutina">P. velutina</taxonomicName>
a marbled appearance (
<bibRefCitation author="Schirch, PF" journalOrPublisher="Boletim do Museu Nacional" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="27 - 38" title="Sobre as planarias terrestres do Brasil." volume="5" year="1929">Schirch 1929</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Riester, A" journalOrPublisher="Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="1 - 88" title="Beitraege zur Geoplaniden-Fauna Brasiliens." volume="441" year="1938">Riester 1938</bibRefCitation>
, E.M. 
<bibRefCitation author="Froehlich, EM" journalOrPublisher="Zoologia" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="289 - 369" title="Sobre especies brasileiras do genero Geoplana. Boletim da Faculdade de Filosofia, Ciencias e Letras da Universidade de Sao Paulo, Ser." volume="19" year="1955">Froehlich 1955</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Froehlich, CG" journalOrPublisher="Boletim da Faculdade de Filosofia, Ciencias e Letras da Universidade de Sao Paulo, Ser Zoologia" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="201 - 265" title="On geoplanids from Brazil." volume="22" year="1959">Froehlich 1959</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
Concerning internal anatomy, four of these species, namely 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="plana">P. plana</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. penhana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="penhana">P. penhana</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. velutina" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="velutina">P. velutina</taxonomicName>
, and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rosea" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="rosea">P. rosea</taxonomicName>
, present a not-forked prostatic vesicle with two distinct regions separated by a constriction or canal (
<bibRefCitation author="Riester, A" journalOrPublisher="Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="1 - 88" title="Beitraege zur Geoplaniden-Fauna Brasiliens." volume="441" year="1938">Riester 1938</bibRefCitation>
, E.M. 
<bibRefCitation author="Froehlich, EM" journalOrPublisher="Zoologia" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="289 - 369" title="Sobre especies brasileiras do genero Geoplana. Boletim da Faculdade de Filosofia, Ciencias e Letras da Universidade de Sao Paulo, Ser." volume="19" year="1955">Froehlich 1955</bibRefCitation>
) similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
. In contrast, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. hauseri" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="hauseri">P. hauseri</taxonomicName>
stands apart in this group by having a forked proximal portion in its prostatic vesicle (
<bibRefCitation author="Froehlich, CG" journalOrPublisher="Boletim da Faculdade de Filosofia, Ciencias e Letras da Universidade de Sao Paulo, Ser Zoologia" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="201 - 265" title="On geoplanids from Brazil." volume="22" year="1959">Froehlich 1959</bibRefCitation>
). The new species shows a large and richly folded female atrium and, as usual in 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="subfamily" subfamily="Geoplaninae">Geoplaninae</taxonomicName>
, testes distributed pre-pharyngeally, differing from 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="plana">P. plana</taxonomicName>
, which has a small, almost unfolded female atrium and testes almost reaching the level of the copulatory organs (E.M. 
<bibRefCitation author="Froehlich, EM" journalOrPublisher="Zoologia" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="289 - 369" title="Sobre especies brasileiras do genero Geoplana. Boletim da Faculdade de Filosofia, Ciencias e Letras da Universidade de Sao Paulo, Ser." volume="19" year="1955">Froehlich 1955</bibRefCitation>
). By having a horizontal female canal and an almost C-shaped common glandular ovovitelline duct, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rosea" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="rosea">P. rosea</taxonomicName>
, which shows a female canal with a C-shaped appearance and an almost horizontal common glandular ovovitelline duct (E.M. 
<bibRefCitation author="Froehlich, EM" journalOrPublisher="Zoologia" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="289 - 369" title="Sobre especies brasileiras do genero Geoplana. Boletim da Faculdade de Filosofia, Ciencias e Letras da Universidade de Sao Paulo, Ser." volume="19" year="1955">Froehlich 1955</bibRefCitation>
). In addition, the sperm ducts open anteriorly displaced into the proximal region of the prostatic vesicle of 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rosea" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="rosea">P. rosea</taxonomicName>
, whereas in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
, the openings of the sperm ducts occur into the posterior part of the proximal region of the prostatic vesicle. 
<bibRefCitation author="Froehlich, EM" journalOrPublisher="Zoologia" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="289 - 369" title="Sobre especies brasileiras do genero Geoplana. Boletim da Faculdade de Filosofia, Ciencias e Letras da Universidade de Sao Paulo, Ser." volume="19" year="1955">Froehlich (1955)</bibRefCitation>
describes the occurrence of a distinct circular musculature in the distal portion of the male atrium, similar to a sphincter, in both 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="plana">P. plana</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rosea" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="rosea">P. rosea</taxonomicName>
, which does not occur in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
. In contrast, a strong circular musculature, resembling a sphincter, occurs in the proximal part of the female atrium of 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
<taxonomicName family="Geoplanidae" genus="Pasipha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pasipha ferrariaphila" order="Tricladida" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" phylum="Platyhelminthes" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">Pasipha ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
shows a prostatic vesicle presenting pear-shaped proximal and distal regions of similar lengths with the distal part located above the proximal, differing from 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. penhana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="penhana">P. penhana</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. velutina" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="velutina">P. velutina</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Riester, A" journalOrPublisher="Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="1 - 88" title="Beitraege zur Geoplaniden-Fauna Brasiliens." volume="441" year="1938">Riester 1938</bibRefCitation>
). In 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. penhana" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="penhana">P. penhana</taxonomicName>
, the prostatic vesicle is tubular-shaped with an elongate distal region (= 
<normalizedToken originalValue="drüsiger">druesiger</normalizedToken>
Teil des Ductus ejaculatorius according to 
<bibRefCitation author="Riester, A" journalOrPublisher="Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="1 - 88" title="Beitraege zur Geoplaniden-Fauna Brasiliens." volume="441" year="1938">Riester 1938</bibRefCitation>
) and a shorter proximal region (= Ductus seminalis according to 
<bibRefCitation author="Riester, A" journalOrPublisher="Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="1 - 88" title="Beitraege zur Geoplaniden-Fauna Brasiliens." volume="441" year="1938">Riester 1938</bibRefCitation>
). In 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. velutina" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="velutina">P. velutina</taxonomicName>
, both distal and proximal regions are tubular, giving an inverted U-shape to the prostatic vesicle (
<bibRefCitation author="Riester, A" journalOrPublisher="Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" pagination="1 - 88" title="Beitraege zur Geoplaniden-Fauna Brasiliens." volume="441" year="1938">Riester 1938</bibRefCitation>
). In addition, besides the occurrence of a highly developed circular musculature in the proximal part of the female atrium, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. ferrariaphila" pageId="0" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="ferrariaphila">P. ferrariaphila</taxonomicName>
differs from all species in this group by showing a longer and more spacious ejaculatory duct, as well as male and female atria separated by a constriction.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="13" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="13">
The specific name is a composite of the Latin noun ferraria (iron mine) and a suffix from the Greek adjective 
<normalizedToken originalValue="phílos">philos</normalizedToken>
(affinity), referring to its sampling site.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>