<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744" ID-GBIF-Dataset="dce6ec3b-3df0-419f-955d-e877c8f32fa6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152048865" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-343-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5DCA0360-4458-4F5E-82BE-5D465A6C277C" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-343-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 343" ModsDocTitle="A systematic revision of Baconia Lewis (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Exosternini)" checkinTime="1451246799544" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Caterino, Michael S. &amp; Tishechkin, Alexey K." docDate="2013" docId="B189A41351F0F350515E5E0AE92BBFE9" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 343: 1-297" docOrigin="ZooKeys 343" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744" docTitle="Baconia chatzimanolisi Caterino &amp; Tishechkin, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="5DCA0360-4458-4F5E-82BE-5D465A6C277C" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="190" lastPageNumber="191" masterDocId="FFCEFFE1717FD230FF94FFCEFF9CE450" masterDocTitle="A systematic revision of Baconia Lewis (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Exosternini)" masterLastPageNumber="297" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="189" pageNumber="190" updateTime="1643701416415" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A systematic revision of Baconia Lewis (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Exosternini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Caterino, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tishechkin, Alexey K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>343</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>297</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-343-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">541A802C-21F2-4A14-9428-F5F46FFE4760</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152048865" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5DCA0360-4458-4F5E-82BE-5D465A6C277C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B189A41351F0F350515E5E0AE92BBFE9" lastPageId="190" lastPageNumber="191" pageId="189" pageNumber="190">
<subSubSection pageId="189" pageNumber="190" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="189" pageNumber="190">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/5DCA0360-4458-4F5E-82BE-5D465A6C277C" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Baconia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Baconia chatzimanolisi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="189" pageNumber="190" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="chatzimanolisi">Baconia chatzimanolisi</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="189" pageNumber="190">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 52
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–D53D–G">C-D53D-G</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="J–KMap">J-KMap</normalizedToken>
16
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="189" pageNumber="190" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="189" pageNumber="190">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="189" pageNumber="190">
NICARAGUA: Granada: Volcan Mombacho [
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="555" value="11.83">11.83°N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="555" value="-85.98">85.98°W</geoCoordinate>
].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="189" pageNumber="190" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="189" pageNumber="190">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="189" pageNumber="190">
Holotype male: &quot;NICARAGUA: Granada Dept. Res. Nat. Volcan Mombacho, entrance rd, 910m 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="11.834167">11°50.05'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="-85.9805">85°58.83'W</geoCoordinate>
1-50-VI-2002, R.Brooks, Z.Falin, S.Chatzimanolis ex. flight intercept trap, NIC1BFC02 189&quot; / &quot;SM0537395 KUNHM-ENT&quot; (SEMC). Paratypes (1): same data as type (SEMC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="190" lastPageNumber="191" pageId="189" pageNumber="190" type="diagnostic description">
<paragraph pageId="189" pageNumber="190">Diagnostic description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="190" lastPageNumber="191" pageId="189" pageNumber="190">
Length: 1.4-1.5mm, width: 0.8-0.9mm; body narrowly elongate, cylindrical, glabrous; color rufescent, shining; head with frons slightly elevated between antennal bases, weakly convex, with distinct small punctures sparsely but evenly scattered throughout, frontal stria present only along upper half of eye, absent across front, supraorbital stria present but fragmented; antennal scape short, club broadly oval, subtruncate apically; epistoma faintly emarginate; labrum about 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×wider">xwider</normalizedToken>
than long, apical margin shallowly emarginate on upper edge, slightly produced beneath; mandibles short, each with small, acute basal tooth; pronotum with sides subparallel in basal two-thirds, rounded to apex, lateral marginal stria descending to ventral edge of margin behind antennal cavity, merging with lateral submarginal stria, continued around anterior corner but detached from median part of anterior marginal stria, which diverges from margin behind eye, pronotal disk with ground punctation fine, very sparse, with small secondary punctures more or less evenly scattered throughout, somewhat sparser in prescutellar area; elytra with single, fine epipleural stria, outer subhumeral stria absent, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="190" pageNumber="191" start="start">inner</pageBreakToken>
subhumeral stria barely impressed at extreme base, dorsal stria 1 present in basal half, striae 2-3 progressively slightly longer, 4th stria absent, 5th and sutural striae present in basal two-thirds, joined in narrow basal arch; elytral disk with small secondary punctures in apical one-fourth; prosternal keel narrow, flat, base produced, with carinal striae joined along basal margin, subparallel or converging slightly to front; prosternal lobe about two-thirds keel length, apical margin broadly rounded, slightly deflexed, marginal stria obsolete at sides; mesoventrite emarginate at middle, with complete marginal stria; mesometaventral stria absent from middle, inner lateral metaventral stria continuing from marginal mesoventral stria, extending posterad toward inner corner of metacoxa, outer lateral metaventral stria very short, curving behind mesocoxa; metaventral disk sparsely punctate at sides, impunctate at middle; abdominal ventrite 1 with single complete lateral stria, central portion of disk impunctate, ventrites 2-5 with fine punctures at sides, sparser across middle; protibiae distinctly tridentate, margin only very finely serrulate between teeth; mesotibia with two marginal and one subapical spines; outer metatibial margin smooth; propygidium lacking basal stria, with fine, sparse ground punctation interspersed with small secondary punctures separated by slightly more than their diameters, propygidial gland openings inconspicuous; pygidium similarly punctate to propygidium, slightly sparser. Male genitalia (Figs 53
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–G">D-G</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="J–K">J-K</normalizedToken>
): T8 slightly wider than long, deeply, arcuately emarginate at base, sides weakly converging apicad, ventrolateral apodemes with inner apices opposing, separated by about two-thirds T8 width, projecting beneath to about ventral midpoint, strongly narrowed apically, apical margin shallowly, narrowly emarginate; S8 with halves fused, basal emargination broad, shallow, sides diverging to apex, apical guides well developed, widest apically, bearing a dense fringe of setae along outer margin; T9 with dorsal plates broad to base, proximal apodemes strongly reduced, sides weakly diverging to obliquely truncate apices bearing several conspicuous setae, ventrolateral apodemes strong, nearly meeting at midline about one-third from apex; S9 stem more or less evenly tapered to very narrow base, head bluntly subquadrate, apices divergent, apical emargination narrow; tegmen widest in basal two-thirds, sides sinuate, narrowed in apical third, apex narrowly rounded, tegmen weakly curved ventrad in apical half; median lobe simple, about one-half tegmen length; basal piece basally bulbous, about one-third tegmen length.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="190" pageNumber="191" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="190" pageNumber="191">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="190" pageNumber="191">
As discussed above, the two species in this group are very similar. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Baconia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Baconia chatzimanolisi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="190" pageNumber="191" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="chatzimanolisi">Baconia chatzimanolisi</taxonomicName>
can be recognized by its larger body size and strongly reduced 4th elytral stria (Fig. 52C).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="190" pageNumber="191" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="190" pageNumber="191">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="190" pageNumber="191">We name this species for staphylinid specialist Dr. Stylianos Chatzimanolis, a former SBMNH postdoctoral fellow, now at University of Tennessee Chattanooga, and co-collector of the types of this species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>