<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.513.9935" ID-GBIF-Dataset="13a07ef7-5c4a-4e39-bced-826a9e344ba5" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152060661" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-513-105" ID-ZBK="734F689911BD44CD85ECD845A47C7760" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:27646149-9E6B-4397-ACD2-DB7E55F37A7C" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1313-2970-513-105" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 513" ModsDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from central and southern Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" checkinTime="1451244134553" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan F., Rifkind, Jacques &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2015" docId="F0CAAF3B8A4B7FBAD81D0A28F7C09029" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 513: 105-121" docOrigin="ZooKeys 513" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.513.9935" docTitle="Cymatodera ortegae Burke, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="27646149-9E6B-4397-ACD2-DB7E55F37A7C" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="114" masterDocId="DB3C1121FFD2E57DFFEDFF9D431B6055" masterDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from central and southern Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" masterLastPageNumber="121" masterPageNumber="105" pageId="3" pageNumber="108" updateTime="1643637345542" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from central and southern Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burke, Alan F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Rifkind, Jacques</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>513</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>105</mods:start>
<mods:end>121</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.513.9935</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.513.9935</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-513-105</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">734F689911BD44CD85ECD845A47C7760</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">734F689911BD44CD85ECD845A47C7760</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152060661" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:27646149-9E6B-4397-ACD2-DB7E55F37A7C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F0CAAF3B8A4B7FBAD81D0A28F7C09029" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="114" pageId="3" pageNumber="108">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="108" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="108">Taxon classification Animalia Coleoptera Cleridae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="108" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="108">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/27646149-9E6B-4397-ACD2-DB7E55F37A7C" authority="Burke" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera ortegae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="108" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ortegae">Cymatodera ortegae Burke</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="3" pageNumber="108">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 2, 7, 12, 17, 21, 22, 24
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="110" pageId="4" pageNumber="109" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="109">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="109" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
material
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="110" pageId="4" pageNumber="109">
(n = 30). Holotype red labeled, male: Jalisco, road to microondas Los Mazos, Sierra 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Manantlán">Manantlan</normalizedToken>
, 1425-1610 m, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="19.7">19°42'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-104.4">104°24'W</geoCoordinate>
, 12 km SSD Autlan, mixed hardwood forest 15-VII-1993, R. L. Westcott; holotype deposited in CASC. Paratypes yellow labeled: 1 male: same data as holotype (WFBM); 1 female: Mexico: 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="110" start="start">Jalisco</pageBreakToken>
, 81 km E of El Grullo, 6-X-1992, R. Turnbow (RHTC); 2 males, 1 female: Mex: Jalisco, N slope Nevado de Colima, 8000', 17-VII-1990, J. Wappes (JEWC); 1 male, Jalisco, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Autlán">Autlan</normalizedToken>
, Res. de la Biosfera 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Manantlán">Manantlan</normalizedToken>
, Est. Cientifica Las Joyas, 19°35'443&quot;N, 104°16'468&quot;W, 30-VIII-2001, Col. V. H. Toledo (CIUM); 1 male, 2 females: Mexico, Jalisco, 2 km S La Manzanilla, 12-X-2001, F. Hovore (JNRC); 1 female: Mexico, Jalisco, Nevado de Colima, 8200', Parque Nacional, 10.7 mi N Hwy 54, 17-IX-1986, [no collector data] (KSUC); 1 male: Mexico, Jalisco, 24.8 km SW Ciudad Guzman, 2286 m, 2-VII-1988, R. S. Anderson, pine-oak forest (JNRC); 1 male: Mexico: Sierra de Manantlan, Jalisco, Las Joyas, 1870 m, 18-VII-1985, J. Doyen, black and white light (EMEC); 1 male, 1 female: Mexico, Sierra de Manantlan, Jalisco, 1800-1900 m, 17-VII-1985, J. Doyen (EMEC); 4 females: Mexico, Jalisco, 5.4 km NE de Apango, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="19.8">19 48 N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-103.683334">103 41 W</geoCoordinate>
, 20-X-1996, beating dead leaf clumps of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus" order="Fagales" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Quercus</taxonomicName>
sp., R. L. Westcott (WFBM); 1 female: Mexico, Jalisco, Manantlan, Lab. Nat. Las Joyas, 8-VII-1988, F. A. Noguera and Y. A. Rodriguez (CNIC); 1 female: Mexico, Jalisco, 19 km E El Jazmin, (SW Ciudad Guzman), 2005 m, 19-VII-1993, pine-oak forest, R. L. Westcott, collected on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus" order="Fagales" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Quercus</taxonomicName>
sp. (WFBM); 2 males, 2 females: Mexico, Jalisco, km 3.5-4 Nevado de Colima, 24-VII-2011, R. Turnbow (RHTC); 1 female: Mex: Colima, nr El Terrero, 7800', 18-VII-199, J. E. Wappes (JEWC); 1 male: Mexico, on elderberry stems, lot 72-11927, 27-VII-1972, Racine and Turk (WFBM); 1 male: Mexico, Colima, NW slope Nevado de Colima, 17-VII-1990, E. Giesbert (JNRC); 1 female: Colima, W rd. to El Terrero, 5000', 3-5-X-1992, J. E. Wappes (JEWC); 1 male: Mexico, Michoacan, 2 km N Tancitaro, 2700-800 m, 26-I-1947, 53, T. H. Hubbell (JNRC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="110" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="110">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
The undulate fascia pattern on the elytral ground, the testaceous to slightly greenish integumental color, general body shape, and geographic distribution of the new species will, in combination, serve to separate it from other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Cymatodera</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera ortegae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ortegae">Cymatodera ortegae</taxonomicName>
appears to be allied to several Mexican congeners that share similar body shape, integumental color, brachypterous condition, and a reduced anterior elytral margin. Of these, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera barri" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="barri">Cymatodera barri</taxonomicName>
Rifkind, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera maculifera" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculifera">Cymatodera maculifera</taxonomicName>
Barr, and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera monticola" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="monticola">Cymatodera monticola</taxonomicName>
Rifkind are most similar. Unlike 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera ortegae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ortegae">Cymatodera ortegae</taxonomicName>
, however, the males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera barri" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="barri">Cymatodera barri</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera maculifera" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculifera">Cymatodera maculifera</taxonomicName>
possess a distinct pair of feebly to moderately developed tubercles on the median posterior portion of the metasternum. Both sexes of these species lack the irregular, infuscate elytral pattern of the new species. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera monticola" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="monticola">Cymatodera monticola</taxonomicName>
possesses distinctly different terminalia from 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera ortegae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ortegae">Cymatodera ortegae</taxonomicName>
, as well as sinuate elytral apices.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="114" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="110">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
Holotype male. Medium sized, moderately slender anteriorly, rather robust posteriorly; brachypterous, TL = 13.1 mm. Color: Head, pronotum, thorax, femora and anterior portion of tibiae brunneous; posterior portion of femora and tarsomeres testaceous; antennae and mouthparts fuscous; abdomen fuscous, slightly darker than thorax, distal portion of abdominal segments with a depressed testaceous mark; elytral ground light testaceous, with a slight greenish tinge. Each elytron bearing a pair of irregular, sinuate, darkened fasciae: the first fascia located on anterior third, extending from the elytral suture to the epipleural fold, conspicuously slender proximal to elytral suture then abruptly widening before epipleural fold; the second fascia 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="111" start="start">located</pageBreakToken>
at the elytral mid-length, moderately wide, extending from the elytral suture to before the epipleural fold. Punctation on elytral ground infuscate (Fig. 2).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="112" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">
Head: HL = 2.9 mm, HW = 2.5 mm. Large, measured across eyes wider than pronotum; surface rugose; frons bi-impressed; surface moderately punctate; clothed with short, fine, recumbent setae intermixed with long, semierect and erect setae; eyes mod 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="112" start="start">erately</pageBreakToken>
small, form subsinuate, longer than wide, moderately emarginate in front, very feebly bulging laterally, separated by approximately 3 eye-widths. Antennae slender; loosely composed; extending beyond posterior margin of elytra; antennomeres 2-3 subequal in length; fourth antennomere slightly longer than third; fifth antennomere very slightly longer than fourth, antennomeres 5-10 subequal in length, antennomeres 4-10 weakly serrate; last antennomere flattened apically, somewhat acuminate distally, approximately the same length as ninth antennomere (Fig. 7).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="112">Thorax: PL = 4.05 mm, PW = 2.1 mm. Pronotum elongate; widest at middle; middle slightly broader than anterior margin; sides constricted subapically; more constricted behind middle; moderately impressed in front of middle; subbasal tumescence pronounced; surface rugose, moderately punctate, punctation rather coarse; clothed with short, pale, semirecumbent setae, intermingled with long, stiff, semierect pale setae. Prosternum convex; wider than long; surface rugose, shining, very feebly punctate. Mesosternum feebly convex; surface rugulose, moderately, deeply punctate, vested with fine, pale, recumbent setae. Metasternum convex; shortened longitudinally; surface rugulose, devoid of tubercles or carinae, moderately, shallowly punctate. Scutellum conspicuously wider than long; moderately setose.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="112">Legs: Femora clothed with short, recumbent setae intermingled with less numerous erect and semierect setae; tibiae vested with short and long erect and semierect setae; femora and tibiae transversely rugose; metathoracic legs with tarsomeres longer than those of pro- and mesothoracic legs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="112">
Elytra: EL = 7.7 mm, EW = 3.2 mm. Form: subovate (brachypterous type). Anterior margin arcuately emarginate; narrower than widest portion of pronotum; humeri very feebly indicated; sides widest on posterior fourth; disc convex; apex rounded, broadly dehiscent, not covering sixth ventrite; surface smooth, moderately clothed with short, fine, pale, recumbent setae intermixed with long, pale, fine, erect setae; sculpturing consisting of small, coarse punctures and larger punctation irregularly arranged from base to apex, punctures becoming less numerous behind anterior third, interstices about 3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
the diameter of punctures at elytral base.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="112">Abdomen: Ventrites 1-5 rugulose; shallowly, moderately punctate; each segment with a pair of large, shallow impressions near sides; surface clothed with short, recumbent setae intermixed with less numerous, long, semi-erect setae. Fifth ventrite (Fig. 12) moderately convex; sides oblique, moderately arcuate; posterior margin broadly, very deeply emarginate. Sixth ventrite (Fig. 12) subquadrate; protruding laterally (visible in dorsal view); rugose; surface moderately concave; somewhat punctate; lateral margins oblique, feebly arcuate; posterior margin broadly, very deeply emarginate; posterolateral angles somewhat blunt, slightly procurved inwardly. Fifth tergite (Fig. 21) convex, rugulose; lateral margins slightly oblique; posterior margin narrowly, shallowly emarginate. Sixth tergite (Fig. 21) subquadrate; moderately convex; surface rugulose; lateral margins moderately oblique; posterolateral angles rounded; posterior margin broadly, shallowly, triangularly emarginate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="114" pageId="7" pageNumber="112">
Aedeagus 2.3 mm long; ratio of length of parameres to whole tegmen 0.4:1; tegmen fully covering phallus; parameres subparallel, pointed at apex, lateral margins fee 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="113" start="start">bly</pageBreakToken>
oblique; phallobase moderately broad; phallus with copulatory piece feebly tapered distally; phallic plate armed with a row of moderately long denticles along the dorsal margin, these denticles increasing in size toward distal end; phallobasic apodeme short, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="114" start="start">robust</pageBreakToken>
, dilated distally; phallobasic struts slender throughout their length, each as long as phallobasic apodeme (Fig. 24).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Females of the type series differ from males by having the sixth ventrite (Fig. 17) with lateral margins moderately oblique, feebly arcuate, and posterior margin very feebly, shallowly, narrowly emarginate, rather than broadly, deeply, semicircularly emarginate, as observed in males (Fig. 12); additionally, females have the sixth tergite (Fig. 22) subquadrate, with the lateral margins oblique and the posterior margin very feebly, shallowly, narrowly emarginate. Females closely resemble males in other respects.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="114" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Length of males range from 7.9-13.1 mm, females from 7.6-13.3 mm. Specimens examined have considerable variation in body size, and also in the shape of the fasciate pattern on the elytral ground, which ranges from almost incomplete and very narrow, to conspicuously wide, covering most part of the elytral ground. The color of these fasciae is also somewhat variable, ranging from dark testaceous to dark greenish. The elytral ground color ranges from light testaceous to light greenish.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="114" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Available specimens were collected in the central-occidental part of Mexico, in the states of Colima, Jalisco and Michoacan. Distribution appears limited to the southern tip of the Sierra Madre Occidental (Fig. 29).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="114" type="note">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Note.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">This new species appears to be confined to mid-to-high altitude mountainous environments in the central-west portion of Mexico: specimens were collected on the slopes of Volcan Nevado de Colima in the states of Colima and Jalisco, and Cerro Tancitaro, in the northwestern region of the Mexican state of Michoacan. These mid and high altitude areas are dominated by pine and pine-oak forest stands.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="114" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="114">The specific epithet is a patronymic honoring Cristina Ortega, a friend of the first author.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>