<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5683222" ID-GBIF-Dataset="96332a33-78e1-45f7-af15-666eb30c9e0e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119344982" ID-ISSN="1175­5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5683222" checkinTime="1459761453211" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Conle, Oskar V." docDate="2006" docId="03A4A860FFEBA75AFECFF9F86C83F9BB" docLanguage="en" docName="zt01231p051.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1231" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@599a9cb2" docStyleName="zootaxa.0000.journal_article" docTitle="Hennobrimus hennemanni Conle, 2006, n. sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="48" masterDocId="FF9DD018FFE9A75FFFC7FF946846FFE5" masterDocTitle="Hennobrimus hennemanni n. gen. n. sp., a remarkable new genus and species of the tribe Obrimini from the Philippine Islands. (Phasmatodea: Heteropterygidae: Obriminae: Obrimini)" masterLastPageNumber="51" masterPageNumber="43" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" updateTime="1636738247508" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Hennobrimus hennemanni n. gen. n. sp., a remarkable new genus and species of the tribe Obrimini from the Philippine Islands. (Phasmatodea: Heteropterygidae: Obriminae: Obrimini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Conle, Oskar V.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1231</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>51</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.172761</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">96332a33-78e1-45f7-af15-666eb30c9e0e</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175­5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">172761</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">237AEEBB-A391-4285-9680-373E8835398E</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5683222" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119344982" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5683222" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03A4A860FFEBA75AFECFF9F86C83F9BB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03A4A860FFEBA75AFECFF9F86C83F9BB" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="2.[264,666,1644,1705]" box="[264,666,1644,1670]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
<heading bold="true" box="[264,666,1644,1670]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[264,666,1644,1670]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
<taxonomicName box="[264,592,1644,1670]" class="Insecta" family="Heteropterygidae" genus="Hennobrimus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Phasmida" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hennemanni" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[264,592,1644,1670]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Hennobrimus hennemanni</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[600,666,1644,1670]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[264,666,1644,1705]" box="[264,385,1679,1705]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
(figs. 
<number box="[332,377,1679,1705]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="3.5" valueMax="6.0" valueMin="1.0">1–6</number>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="2.[264,1322,1759,1905]" box="[264,1164,1759,1785]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
<typeStatus box="[264,376,1759,1785]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Holotype</typeStatus>
, male: 
<collectingCountry box="[460,595,1759,1785]" name="Philippines" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Philippines</collectingCountry>
, Mindanao, 0 
<number box="[754,838,1759,1785]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="8.2004">8.2004</number>
, ex coll. O. Conle (
<collectionCode box="[1065,1151,1759,1785]" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/a6ms-py1z" name="Zoologische Staatssammlung" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">ZSMC</collectionCode>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[264,1322,1759,1905]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
<typeStatus box="[312,426,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Paratypes</typeStatus>
(
<specimenCount box="[445,542,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="male">
<number box="[445,460,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="6.0">6</number>
males
</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount box="[558,669,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="female">
<number box="[558,573,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="1.0">1</number>
female
</specimenCount>
): 
<specimenCount box="[691,778,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="male">
<number box="[691,706,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="1.0">1</number>
male
</specimenCount>
: 
<collectingCountry box="[793,928,1799,1825]" name="Philippines" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Philippines</collectingCountry>
, Mindanao, 0 
<number box="[1094,1178,1799,1825]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="8.2004">8.2004</number>
, ex coll. O. Conle (FH 0600­ 
<number box="[477,487,1839,1865]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="1.0">1</number>
); 
<specimenCount box="[510,594,1839,1865]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="male">
<number box="[510,525,1839,1865]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="1.0">1</number>
male
</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount box="[608,717,1839,1865]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="female">
<number box="[608,622,1839,1865]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="1.0">1</number>
female
</specimenCount>
: 
<collectingCountry box="[730,865,1839,1865]" name="Philippines" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Philippines</collectingCountry>
, Leyte Island, Mt. Balocaue, 0 
<number box="[1234,1318,1839,1865]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="2.2005">2.2005</number>
, (OC); 
<specimenCount box="[340,435,1879,1905]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="male">
<number box="[340,355,1879,1905]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="4.0">4</number>
males
</specimenCount>
: 
<collectingCountry box="[446,581,1879,1905]" name="Philippines" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Philippines</collectingCountry>
, Mindanao, 0 
<number box="[740,824,1879,1905]" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" value="8.2004">8.2004</number>
, (OC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="46" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="3.[264,1323,284,470]" box="[264,389,284,309]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
<emphasis box="[264,389,284,309]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">Etymology</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[264,1323,284,470]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
This striking and colourful new species is dedicated to Mr. Frank H. Hennemann (Kaiserslautern, 
<collectingCountry box="[469,583,364,390]" name="Germany" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">Germany</collectingCountry>
), one of the world’s leading specialists in 
<taxonomicName box="[1168,1323,364,390]" class="Insecta" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" order="Phasmatodea" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="order">Phasmatodea</taxonomicName>
taxonomy, for many years of best friendship and good cooperation during the past fifteen years.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="3.[264,1325,524,1870]" box="[264,402,524,549]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
<emphasis box="[264,402,524,549]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">Description</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[264,1325,524,1870]" box="[312,914,564,590]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">The colouration is described from dried specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[264,1325,524,1870]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
Female: Medium sized to large (body length including supraanal plate 
<quantity box="[1142,1251,604,630]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="9.01" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" unit="mm" value="90.1">90.1 mm</quantity>
), very robust 
<taxonomicName box="[347,458,644,670]" class="Insecta" family="Heteropterygidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Phasmida" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="tribe" tribe="Obrimini">Obrimini</taxonomicName>
, with moderately long and robust legs. Armature of body and legs very poorly developed when compared with the other genera of the tribe. Body surface smooth, except for elements of armament and minute tubercles on the thorax, and slightly shiny. Complete dorsal body surface and supraanal plate, except head and pronotum, with a fine but distinct longitudinal median carina. Abdomen entirely unarmed and smooth. General colouration of body and legs pale to drab green, ventral body surface pale to reddish mid brown. Thoracic armature and teeth on legs bright green. Subgenital plate and anal segment brown. Eyes brown. Antennae greenish brown in basal third, otherwise dark brown. Tibiae and tarsi greenish brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[264,1325,524,1870]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
Head: Slightly wider than long, vertex strongly convex and slightly conically elevated; armature consisting of small occipital spines and small, simple lateral and medial coronals. Eyes roughly circular, convex and slightly projecting from head capsule. Antennae at least reaching to anterior margin of tergite IV, consisting of at least 
<number box="[1026,1055,1124,1150]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" value="28.0">28</number>
segments; all densely setose. Scapus slightly compressed dorsoventrally and 
<number box="[922,958,1164,1190]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" value="1.5">1.5</number>
x longer than wide. Pedicellus cylindrical, roughly half the length of scapus. Third antennomere longer than pedicellus and almost as long as scapus. Remaining antennomeres cylindrical, first increasing then decreasing in length towards apices of antennae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[264,1325,524,1870]" lastBlockId="4.[264,1325,284,1870]" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="47" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
Thorax: Meso­ and metathorax each strongly broadened towards the posterior. Pronotum transverse, slightly wider than long, gently broadened towards the posterior and indistinctly shorter and narrower than head. Transverse median depression indistinct and broadly V­shaped. Anterior margin slightly raised, with an oval lateral excavation and bearing a pair of distinct but simple posterior and anterior pronotals. Sensory areas of prosternum indistinct, gently convex. Mesonotum 
<number box="[875,911,1524,1550]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" value="1.5">1.5</number>
x longer than wide and 
<date box="[1207,1237,1524,1550]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
<number box="[1207,1221,1524,1550]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" value="2.0">2</number>
x
</date>
longer than pronotum, parallel sided. Complete surface of mesonotum covered with minute, rounded granules, these become less distinct towards the posterior. Otherwise armed with a distinct pair of flat, blunt posterior mesonotals connected by a transverse carina and a pair of small anterior mesonotals. Posterior mesonotals with several small granules on a common base. Metanotum slightly wider than long, 
<number box="[946,983,1724,1750]" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" value="0.7">0.7</number>
x as long and as wide as mesonotum, parallel sided. Armed with a pair of flat, blunt posterior metanotals connected by a transverse carina, and a few small granules, otherwise smooth. Posterior mesonotals with several small granules on a common base. Metanotum and median segment combined about the same length as mesonotum and 
<number box="[803,839,284,310]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" value="1.5">1.5</number>
x longer than wide. Transverse fissure between metanotum and median segment distinct, straight in the centre and back­curving laterally. Lateral mesopleurals and metapleurals produced as small spines. Lower margin of both pleurae armed with a longitudinal row of distinct spines. Prosternum unarmed; meso­ and metasternum with a longitudinal row of prominent mesosternals and metasternals along lateral margins and a few minute granules.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[264,1325,284,1870]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
Abdomen: 
<number box="[450,537,524,550]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" value="1.65" valueMax="1.7" valueMin="1.6">1.6–1.7</number>
x longer than head and thorax combined, bulgy and gradually tapered towards the apex, III–IV widest, anal segment narrowest. Surface entirely unarmed and smooth. Median segment half as long as metanotum, slightly trapezoidal and transverse. Tergites II–VII of about equal length, II–VII transverse being 
<number box="[1129,1173,644,670]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" value="4.5" valueMax="5.0" valueMin="4.0">
4– 
<date box="[1160,1173,644,670]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47">5</date>
</number>
x wider than long, VIII 
<date box="[397,427,684,710]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
<number box="[397,410,684,710]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" value="3.0">3</number>
x
</date>
wider than long, IX anal segment hardly wider than long. VIII strongly convex and narrowed towards posterior margin. IX distinctly narrower than VIII, strongly convex and tapered towards the posterior. Anal segment slightly longer than IX, narrowed towards the posterior margin which is notched. Cerci very small, laterally compressed and finely bristled. Supraanal plate very elongate and slender, about as long as tergite IX and X combined, straight, tectiform and very gently tapered towards a truncate apex which reaches to the tip of the subgenital plate. Sternites II–VII simple and smooth, VII possessing a very small praeopercular organ, forming a V­shaped incision. Subgenital plate strongly keeled, elongated, straight and gently tapered towards a pointed apex. The supraanal and subgenital plate form a conspicuous beak­like ovipositor.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[264,1325,284,1870]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
Legs: All of moderate length, rather stout and robust, femora conspicuously thickened. Mesofemora only slightly longer than mesonotum, metafemora almost reaching to posterior margin of tergite V, hind legs slightly projecting over apex of abdomen. Femora and tibiae slightly trapezoidal in cross­section. All carinae indistinct and blunt, bearing several minute saw­like teeth. Profemora very indistinctly curved basally. No prominent spines on ventral carinae of femora and tibiae. Basitarsus 
<date box="[936,966,1284,1310]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
<number box="[936,949,1284,1310]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" value="3.0">3</number>
x
</date>
longer than second tarsomere.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[264,1325,284,1870]" pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
Male: Much more slender than female. Moderately sized (body length 47.0–51.0 mm) but very robust 
<taxonomicName box="[452,563,1364,1390]" class="Insecta" family="Heteropterygidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Phasmida" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="tribe" tribe="Obrimini">Obrimini</taxonomicName>
, abdominal segments II–V parallel­sided, legs robust. Armature of body and legs poorly developed when compared with the other genera of the tribe, although prominent posterior mesonotals and posterior metanotals present. Body surface, except for elements of armament and a few minute tubercles on the thorax, smooth and shiny. Abdomen entirely unarmed, smooth and shiny. Head, pronotum, prosternum, legs and coxae pale to drab green. Meso­, metanotum, median segment, meso­ and metasternum, meso­ and metaepisternum yellowish green to drab orange. Posterior mesonotals and posterior metanotals green. Ventral membrane of cervix bright orange. Dorsal surface of abdomen green with reddish band alog lateral margins and a glossy yellow longitudinal dorsomedian stripe running along the complete abdomen. Ventral surface of abdomen bright green, each sternite with a yellow transverse bands at posterior margin. Eyes yellowish brown to dark brown. Antennae green in basal third, otherwise dark brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[264,1325,284,1630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
Head: Generally as in female, but eyes relatively larger and projecting hemispherically from head capsule. Antennae very robust and conspicuously thickened, consisting of 
<number box="[1293,1322,324,350]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="26.0">26</number>
segments and almost reaching apex of abdomen.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[264,1325,284,1630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
Thorax: Meso­ and metathorax strongly broadened towards the posterior. Pronotum transverse, slightly wider than long, slightly shorter and narrower than head and gently broadened towards the posterior. Transverse median depression indistinct and broadly Vshaped. Anterior margin slightly raised, with an oval lateral excavation and bearing a pair of distinct but simple posterior and anterior pronotals. Sensory areas of prosternum small and gently convex, forming two small yellow humps. Mesonotum 
<date box="[1046,1076,604,630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
<number box="[1046,1060,604,630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="2.0">2</number>
x
</date>
longer than wide, 
<date box="[1295,1325,604,630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
<number box="[1295,1309,604,630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="2.0">2</number>
x
</date>
longer than pronotum, broadened towards the posterior. Complete surface covered with minute, rounded granules and otherwise armed with a pair of prominent and conical, blunt posterior mesonotals and a pair of small anterior mesonotals. Metanotum about as wide as long, 
<number box="[331,368,764,790]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="0.7">0.7</number>
x as long as and of the same width as posterior margin of mesonotum, broadened towards the posterior. Armed with a pair of prominent, conical blunt posterior metanotals and many small granules. Metanotum and median segment combined about the same length as mesonotum, at least 
<number box="[671,707,884,910]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="1.5">1.5</number>
x longer than wide. Transverse fissure between metanotum and median segment distinct, straight in the centre and down curving at the lateral edges. Lateral mesopleurals and metapleurals produced as small spines and round tubercles. Lower margin of both pleurae armed with a longitudinal row of distinct spines. Prosternum unarmed; meso­ and metasternum with a longitudinal row of prominent mesosternals and metasternals along lateral margins and a few minute granules. Metasternum irregularly covered with minute granules.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[264,1325,284,1630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
Abdomen: Sub­cylindrical in cross section, hardly longer than head and thorax combined. Segments II–V parallel­sided, VI–VIII broadened towards the posterior, IX and X narrowed towards the posterior. Median segment half as long as metanotum, trapezoidal and transverse. Tergites II–V longest, VII and VIII widest and shortest, anal segment narrowest. All segments except anal segment transverse, II–V 
<number box="[1039,1127,1324,1350]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="1.35" valueMax="1.5" valueMin="1.2">1.2–1.5</number>
x long, 
<date pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
VI–VIII 
<number box="[264,277,1364,1390]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="3.25" valueMax="3.5" valueMin="3.0">3</number>
</date>
–3.5x, IX 
<date box="[397,428,1364,1390]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
<number box="[397,413,1364,1390]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="2.0">2</number>
x
</date>
, anal segment 
<number box="[601,637,1364,1390]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" value="1.5">1.5</number>
x wider than long. Anal segment strongly tapered and with a bold triangular posteromedian notch; posterolateral angles rounded. Supraanal plate small, roughly triangular and slightly projecting over anal segment. Vomer broad, triangular, pointed towards the apex. Cerci small and laterally compressed. Poculum very bulgy, strongly convex, cup­like and prominently keeled, reaching the apex of the anal segment. Sternites simple and smooth.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[264,1325,284,1630]" box="[312,1221,1604,1630]" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">Legs: As in female, but hind legs projecting distinctly over apex of abdomen.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>