<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3942c2db-fdc5-4428-bc87-0a337edc07d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="142664141" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-747-1" ID-ZBK="74DC1895C13148E6B0C28A2BF42FAFE3" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9ACD4C39-16EC-47AF-A3B0-C32C3BA8EAC3" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-747-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 747" ModsDocTitle="Four new Gammarus species from Tibetan Plateau with a key to Tibetan freshwater gammarids (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)" checkinTime="1522305661575" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Hou, Zhonge &amp; Li, Shuqiang" docDate="2018" docId="02D62806CFCAA788739030C0FA6F315A" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 747: 1-40" docOrigin="ZooKeys 747" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999" docTitle="Gammarus limosus Hou &amp; Li, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="9ACD4C39-16EC-47AF-A3B0-C32C3BA8EAC3" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="16" masterDocId="FFE0FFCB0045FF9EFF9D381EFF99FFED" masterDocTitle="Four new Gammarus species from Tibetan Plateau with a key to Tibetan freshwater gammarids (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)" masterLastPageNumber="40" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" updateTime="1643519075925" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Four new Gammarus species from Tibetan Plateau with a key to Tibetan freshwater gammarids (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Hou, Zhonge</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Shuqiang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>747</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>40</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-747-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">74DC1895C13148E6B0C28A2BF42FAFE3</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">74DC1895C13148E6B0C28A2BF42FAFE3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="142664141" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9ACD4C39-16EC-47AF-A3B0-C32C3BA8EAC3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/02D62806CFCAA788739030C0FA6F315A" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="16" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/9ACD4C39-16EC-47AF-A3B0-C32C3BA8EAC3" class="Malacostraca" family="FAMILIA" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="ORDO" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="11" pageNumber="12">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="13" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="13" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
Holotype: male (IZCAS-I-A0063-1), 8.6 mm, Baxoi County (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="5555" value="30.2">30.2°N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="5555" value="97.2">97.2°E</geoCoordinate>
), Tibet, altitude 4400 m, August 21, 2001, collected by Xianjin Peng. Paratype: female (IZCAS-I-A0063-2), 5.5 mm; paratypes: five males and five females (IZCAS-I-A0063-3), same data as holotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="13" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">This specific name alludes to its living environment, living silt beside a polluted river; adjective.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Diagnosis. Antenna I accessory flagellum with three articles; antenna II calceoli present; pereopods III and IV with few setae on posterior margin; inner ramus of uropod III reaching 0.6 times the length of outer ramus, terminal article of outer ramus longer than adjacent spines, both inner and outer rami with few marginal setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="15" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Description of holotype male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">(IZCAS-I-A0063-1), 8.6 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Head. (Fig. 17A): cephalic lateral lobe truncated, inferior antennal sinus deep, eyes ovate.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
Figure 17. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. A head B epimeral plates 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
C urosomites 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
(dorsal view) D lower lip E upper lip F maxilliped G palp of left mandible H incisor of left mandible I left maxilla I J palp of right maxilla I K incisor of right mandible L maxilla II.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
Antenna I (Fig. 18A): peduncle articles 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
in length ratio 1.0: 0.7: 0.4, each article with distal setae, article II with two groups of setae on inner face; primary flagellum with 21 articles, most with aesthetascs; accessory flagellum with three articles, the distal article tiny.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Antenna II (Fig. 19A): gland cone shorter than peduncle article III, article IV approximately as long as article V, both with two or three groups of short setae along anterior and posterior margins; flagellum with 12 articles, proximal six articles with calceoli.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Upper lip (Fig. 17E): convex, with minute setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="14" start="start">Mandible</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 17G, H, K): asymmetrical, left incisor with five teeth; lacinia mobilis with four teeth; spine row with nine plumose setae; second article of palp with ten setae on medial margin, third article 0.7 times the length of second article, with four A-setae on outer face, five B-setae on inner face, a row of 22 D-setae and four E-setae. Incisor of right mandible with four teeth; lacinia molibis bifurcate, with small teeth; molar with one long seta.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Lower lip (Fig. 17D): inner lobes lacking, outer lobes covered with thin setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Maxilla I (Fig. 17I, J): asymmetrical, left inner plate with 15 plumose setae on medial margin; outer plate with eleven serrated spines; second article of palp with seven slender spines. Second article of right palp broad, with five blunt spines and one stiff seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Maxilla II (Fig. 17L): inner plate with 14 plumose setae on inner face; inner and outer plates with apical setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Maxilliped (Fig. 17F): inner plate with three apical and one subapical spines, and 17 plumose setae; outer plate with 13 blade spines on medial margin and five apical plumose setae; palp with four articles, terminal article unguis-form.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Pereon. Gnathopod I (Fig. 18C, D): coxal plate weakly dilated distally, lower margin with short setae; basis with long setae on anterior and posterior margins; carpus triangular, posterior margin with setae; propodus oval, palm oblique, with one median spine, seven spines on posterior margin and seven spines on inner face; dactylus longer than half of posterior margin, with one seta on outer margin.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figure 18. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. A antenna I B gnathopod II C gnathopod I D propodus of gnathopod I (medial view) E propodus of gnathopod II (medial view) F pleopod I G pleopod II H pleopod III.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Gnathopod II (Fig. 18B, E): coxal plate slightly narrowing distally, with short setae on lower margin; basis with long setae on anterior and posterior margins; carpus a little shorter than propodus, with sub-parallel margins, bearing setae on posterior margin; propodus subrectangular, palm transverse, with one median spine and four spines on posterior corner; dactylus beyond the palm margin, with one seta on outer margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Pereopod III (Fig. 19B, G): coxal plate with one seta on anterodistal and posterodistal corners each; basis with long setae on anterior and posterior margins; merus to propodus with few setae on posterior margin; merus with two spines on anterior margin and three clusters of setae on posterior margins; carpus and propodus with three groups of spines accompanied by setae on posterior margins; dactylus with one plumose seta on anterior margin and one simple and one stiff setae at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figure 19. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. A antenna II B pereopod III C pereopod IV D pereopod V E pereopod VI F pereopod VII G dactylus of pereopod III H dactylus of pereopod IV I dactylus of pereopod V J dactylus of pereopod VI K dactylus of pereopod VII.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Pereopod IV (Fig. 19C, H): coxal plate concave, with one seta on anterior corner and five setae on posterior margin; basis with long setae on posterior margin; merus with one spine on anterior margin, posterior margin with two pairs of setae; carpus and propodus with two to four groups of spines accompanied by setae on posterior margins; dactylus with one plumose seta on anterior margin and a seta at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="15" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Pereopod V (Fig. 19D, I): coxal plate with one seta on anterior lobe and three setae on posterior lobe; basis nearly straight on posterior margin, with three setae and four spines on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with two spines accompanied by setae; posterior margin with a row of nine setae; merus and carpus with two groups of spines accompanied with few setae on anterior margins and one group of spines on posterior margins; propo 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="15" start="start">dus</pageBreakToken>
with three groups of spines on anterior margin and a pair of setae on posterior margin; dactylus with one plumose seta on posterior margin and two setae at hinge of unguis.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Pereopod VI (Fig. 19E, J): coxal plate with two setae on posterior margin; basis elongated, anterior margin with four setae and four spines on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with one spine, posterior margin with a row of eight setae; merus and carpus with two groups of spines on anterior margins and a group of spines on posterior margins; propodus with three groups of spines on anterior margin and a seta on posterior margin; dactylus with two setae at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Pereopod VII (Fig. 19F, K): coxal plate with four setae on posterior margin; basis elongated, with five setae and four spines on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with two spines; posterior margin with a row of ten setae; merus and carpus with one or two groups of spines on anterior margins, and two or one spine on posterior margins; propodus with three groups of spines on anterior margin and a seta on posterior margin; dactylus with one seta at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">
Coxal gills (Figs 18B, 19B, C, E, F): present on gnathopod II and pereopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
, sac-like.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Pleon. Epimeral plates (Fig. 17B): plate I ventrally rounded, with six setae on anteroventral margin and two setae on posterior margin; plate II with two spines on ventral margin, posterior margin blunt, with one seta; plate III with two spines on ventral margin, posterior margin acute, with two setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">
Pleopods (Fig. 18
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
): subequal, peduncle with some long setae, bearing two retinacula accompanied by two setae; rami with approximately 18 segments, fringed with plumose setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Urosome. Urosomites (Fig. 17C): non-humped, urosomite I with two-one-one-two spines on dorsal margin; urosomite II with three-one-one-two spines on dorsal margin; urosomite III with two and one spine on lateral margins respectively, and two setae on dorsal margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Uropod I (Fig. 20D): peduncle with one basofacial spine, outer margin with one spine on outer margin, two spines on outer distal corner, one spine on inner margin, and one spine on inner distal corner; outer ramus with one spine on inner and outer margins each; inner ramus with one mid-lateral spine, both inner and outer rami with five distal spines.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="15">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">
Figure 20. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–G">D-G</normalizedToken>
male, holotype; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
female, paratype. A oostegite of gnathopod II B oostegite of pereopod III C uropod III D uropod I E uropod II F telson G uropod III.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Uropod II (Fig. 20E): peduncle with one spine on outer margin, and one spine on outer and inner corners each; outer ramus with one spine on outer margin; inner ramus with one spine on inner margin, both rami with five distal spines.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Uropod III (Fig. 20G): peduncle with one marginal spine and three distal spines; inner ramus 0.6 times the length of outer ramus, with two marginal and two distal spines; proximal article of outer ramus with three pairs of spines on outer margin, one spine on inner margin and four distal spines; terminal article of outer ramus longer than adjacent spines; both rami with few marginal setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Telson (Fig. 20F): cleft, each with three or four distal spines accompanied by few short setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="16" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">Description of paratype female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="15">(IZCAS-I-A0063-2), 5.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="16" start="start">Pereon</pageBreakToken>
. Gnathopod I (Fig. 21A, C): palm of propodus not oblique as that of male, with eight spines on posterior corner.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
Figure 21. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female paratype. A gnathopod I B gnathopod II C propodus of gnathopod I (medial view) D propodus of gnathopod II (medial view).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">Gnathopod II (Fig. 21B, D): carpus approx. as long as propodus, propodus subrectangular, palm truncated, with four spines on posterior corner.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
Figure 22. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female paratype. A pereopod III B pereopod IV C pereopod V D pereopod VII E pereopod VI F dactylus of pereopod III G dactylus of pereopod IV H dactylus of pereopod V I dactylus of pereopod VII J dactylus of pereopod VI.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
Pereopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
(Fig. 22
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–J">A-J</normalizedToken>
): similar to those of male. Pereopods III and IV with more setae on posterior margins; pereopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="V–VII">V-VII</normalizedToken>
stouter, basis broader than those of male.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">Oostegites (Figs 20A, B, 22B, C): progressively decreasing in size, with long marginal setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">Urosome. Uropod III (Fig. 20C): stouter than that of male, inner ramus less than half the length of outer ramus; both rami with few setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="16" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">This species was collected along a riverside with altitude 4400 m, water polluted.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="16" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. altus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="altus">G. altus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. in antenna II having calceoli; pereopod V having few setae on posterior margin; and bases of pereopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="V–VII">V-VII</normalizedToken>
elongated. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. altus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="altus">G. altus</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. altus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="altus">G. altus</taxonomicName>
in parentheses) by pereopod III with few setae on posterior margin (merus with four groups of setae on posterior margin); epimeral plate III acute on posterodistal corner (blunt); and uropod III inner ramus longer than half of outer ramus length (inner ramus 0.3 times the length of outer ramus).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus limosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limosus">Gammarus limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is very similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. balcanicus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="balcanicus">G. balcanicus</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Schäferna">Schaeferna</normalizedToken>
, 1922 (widespread in Europe). It differs from the latter by pereopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–IV">III-IV</normalizedToken>
and uropod III having few setae; bases of pereopods VI and VII slender.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="16">
The species of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Gammarus</taxonomicName>
recorded from the Tibetan Plateau can be classified into four groups based on morphological comparison: (1) 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. lacustris" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="lacustris">G. lacustris</taxonomicName>
group, is characterized by uropod III inner ramus longer than half of outer ramus length, both rami fringed with plumose setae, and includes five species: 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. lacustris" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="lacustris">G. lacustris</taxonomicName>
Sars, 1863, 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. lasaensis" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="lasaensis">G. lasaensis</taxonomicName>
Barnard &amp; Dai, 1988, 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. hongyuanensis" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="hongyuanensis">G. hongyuanensis</taxonomicName>
Barnard &amp; Dai, 1988, 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. frigidus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="frigidus">G. frigidus</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, 2004, and 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. jaspidus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="jaspidus">G. jaspidus</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, 2004; (2) cave species with no eyes, including 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. abstrusus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="abstrusus">G. abstrusus</taxonomicName>
Hou, Platvoet &amp; Li, 2006, and 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. praecipuus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="praecipuus">G. praecipuus</taxonomicName>
Li, Hou &amp; An, 2013; (3) 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. sinuolatus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="sinuolatus">G. sinuolatus</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, 2004 with long simple setae on uropod III; and (4) 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. kangdingensis" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="kangdingensis">G. kangdingensis</taxonomicName>
group is characterized by uropod III having a few simple or plumose setae, and includes 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. emeiensis" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="emeiensis">G. emeiensis</taxonomicName>
Hou, Li &amp; Koenemann, 2002, 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. sichuanensis" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="sichuanensis">G. sichuanensis</taxonomicName>
Hou, Li &amp; Zheng, 2002, 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. glaber" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="glaber">G. glaber</taxonomicName>
Hou, 2017, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus altus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="altus">Gammarus altus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. kangdingensis" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="kangdingensis">G. kangdingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. gonggaensis" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">G. gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., and 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. limosus" pageId="15" pageNumber="16" rank="species" species="limosus">G. limosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A key to these species is presented as follows.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>