<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.173.2314" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5903a675-a795-4922-9f4b-61887c281390" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152033454" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-173-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FAEAFDD4-6AE6-44BC-B733-B9274D16CF21" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-173-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 173" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Halacarsantia Wolff, 1989 (Crustacea, Isopoda, Asellota, Santiidae) from Wistari Reef, southern Great Barrier Reef, Australia" checkinTime="1451249316544" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Shimomura, Michitaka &amp; Bruce, Niel L." docDate="2012" docId="9522A0D258170722E5E932DB3E25C046" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 173: 1-9" docOrigin="ZooKeys 173" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.173.2314" docTitle="Halacarsantia acuta Shimomura &amp; Bruce, 2012, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="FAEAFDD4-6AE6-44BC-B733-B9274D16CF21" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" masterDocId="7731FFD5FFDB70691C79FFBE0656FFB8" masterDocTitle="A new species of Halacarsantia Wolff, 1989 (Crustacea, Isopoda, Asellota, Santiidae) from Wistari Reef, southern Great Barrier Reef, Australia" masterLastPageNumber="9" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" updateTime="1643710495481" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of Halacarsantia Wolff, 1989 (Crustacea, Isopoda, Asellota, Santiidae) from Wistari Reef, southern Great Barrier Reef, Australia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Shimomura, Michitaka</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bruce, Niel L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>173</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>9</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.173.2314</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.173.2314</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-173-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">37DACB80-384B-4D2F-9F39-0B70C8C5CFB1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152033454" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FAEAFDD4-6AE6-44BC-B733-B9274D16CF21" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9522A0D258170722E5E932DB3E25C046" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FAEAFDD4-6AE6-44BC-B733-B9274D16CF21" class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia acuta" order="Isopoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">Halacarsantia acuta</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="3">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 13
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Holotype. ♀ (0.83 mm, with 4 eggs), Wistari Reef, Great Barrier Reef, Australia, 23 November 2009, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-23.454283">23°27.257'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="151.88066">151°52.840'E</geoCoordinate>
, northern side of reef, rubble on bommie, 3 m, stn HI09-084F, coll. N. L. Bruce &amp; K. Schnabel (MTQ W34048).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Paratype. 1♀ (0.83 mm), same data as holotype (MTQ W31550).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Description of the holotype female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Body (Fig. 1A) 1.9 times as long as maximum width, with dark reddish brown pigment in patches. Head 1.4 times as broad as long, narrower than pereonite 1, with 1 robust seta on anterior part of eyes; frontal lobe broad and long, 0.32 times as wide as maximum width of head, with 6 long robust setae on anterior margin; lateral margins of head, each with 1 slender and 3 robust setae; posterior margin of head convex. Eyes each with 7 ommatidia. Pereonites laterally rounded; pereonites 1, 4 and 7 with 2 long robust setae near lateral margin on each side; pereonite 2 with 2 short slender setae on each side of lateral margins and 2 long robust setae near lateral margin on each side; pereonites 3, 5 and 6 with 1 short slender setae on each side of lateral margins and 3 robust setae near lateral margin on each side. Pereonites 1 to 3 increasing in length; pereonites 3 and 4 subequal in length; pereonites 5-7 subequal in length. Pereonites 1 to 3 increasing in width; pereonite 4 slightly narrower than pereonite 3; pereonites 4 to 7 decreasing in width. Coxal plates dorsally visible on all pereonites, laterally rounded; coxal plate of pereonite 1 with 1 short seta; coxal plates of pereonites 2 and 3 each with 1 robust seta; coxal plates of pereonites 4-6 each with 2 robust setae; coxal plate of pereonite 7 with 1 short seta. Pleotelson (Figs 1A, 3E, 3F) pyriform, about 1.3 times as long as wide, with 7 robust setae near dorsolateral margin on each side and 4 robust setae near ventrolateral margin on each side.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Antennula (Figs 1B, 1C) composed of 5 articles. Article 1 broadest, with 1 simple seta mediodistally and 1 broom seta laterodistally; article 2 slightly shorter than article 1, with 1 simple seta and 4 broom seta distally; article 3 with 1 simple seta mediodistally; article 4 as long as article 3, without setae; article 5 twice as long as article 4, with 3 simple setae, 1 broom seta and 1 aesthetasc apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Antenna (Fig. 1D): peduncle composed of 4 short stout and 2 long slender articles, and flagellum of 8 short slender articles. Article 1 with 1 simple seta laterodistally; article 2 without setae; article 3 with 1 simple seta mediodistally and 1 stout seta on lateral protrusion; article 4 with 3 simple setae mediodistally; article 5 shorter than articles 1-4 combined, with 1 simple and 1 biramous setae laterally and medially; article 6 longer and slender than article 5, with 1 lateral and 1 medial simple setae, and 3 simple and 2 broom setae; flagellar articles 1-7, each with 2 or 3 simple setae distally; flagellar article 8 with 6 simple setae apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Left mandible (Fig. 1E) palp article 1 with seta distally; article 2 longest, laterally with 2 setae; article 3 as long as article 1, with 2 apical setae and few short setae; molar process with 2 setae; lacinia mobilis with 2 teeth; setal row with 4 setae. Right mandible (Fig. 1F) palp article 1 with seta distally, article 2 longest, laterally with 2 setae, article 3 as long as article 1, with 2 apical setae and few short setae; incisor with 4 cusps, setal row with 4 setae; molar process stout, with 2 setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Maxilla 1 (Fig. 1G) with inner lobe bearing 4 apical and 2 medial setae; outer lobe with 11 irregular and 1 simple setae distally. Maxilla 2 (Fig. 1H) with inner lobe bearing 16 setae on margin; outer 2 lobes each with 4 apical setae
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">.</pageBreakToken>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Maxilliped (Fig. 1I) palp slender: article 1 shortest, with 1 seta mediodistally; article 2 about 1.9 times as long as article 1, with 1 medial seta; article 3 slightly longer than article 2, with 1 seta laterodistally and 2 setae medially; article 4 as long as article 3, with 1 seta laterodistally and 2 setae medially; article 5 narrowest, with 2 slender and 2 stout setae apically; endite broad, bearing 2 simple setae ventrally, with 8 pectinate setae distally, 1 simple and 2 fan-shaped setae on subdistal margin, and 2 coupling hooks medially; epipod lanceolate, moderately broad, with acute apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Pereopod 1 (Fig. 2A): basis the longest article, with short projection ventrally, and with 3 ventral and 1 dorsal setae; ischium 0.8 as long as basis, bearing 1 ventral and 1 dorsal setae; merus trapezoidal, with 4 ventral and 2 dorsal setae; carpus trapezoidal, 0.8 as long as merus, wider than merus, ventrally with 2 stout and 6 slender setae, dorsally with 1 slender seta; propodus ovate, with 8 ventral and 3 dorsal setae; dactylus shorter than propodus, with 1 curved unguis and 1 short accessory claw.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Pereopods 2-3 (Fig. 2B, C) subequal in shape and length; bases with 2-3 ventral and 1 dorsal setae; ischia as long as bases, with 0-1 ventral and 2 dorsal setae; meri as long as ischia, with 2 setae ventrally, 1-2 simple and 1 robust setae dorsodistally; carpi 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="5" start="start">shorter</pageBreakToken>
than meri, with 3-4 simple, 1 broom and 5-7 robust setae; propodi shorter than carpi, with 3-5 simple and 1 robust setae; dactyli with 1 short setae, 1 curved unguis and 1 curved accessory claw. Pereopods 4-6 (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
) decreasing in length posteriorly; bases with 2 short and 1 long setae ventrally, and with 0-1 short seta dorsally; ischia with 0-1 short seta; meri with 2 short distal setae, and with 1-3 robust setae and row of short setae dorsodistally; carpi with 2-3 robust setae ventrally and 3-6 robust setae distally; propodi with 1-2 short setae and 0-1 robust seta; dactyli with 1 short seta, 1 curved unguis and 1 curved accessory claw. Pereopod 7: basis shorter than those of pereopods1-6, with 1 long and 2 short setae ventrally and 1 short seta dorsally; ischium with 1 dorsal and 1 ventral setae; merus with 2 short setae ventrodistally and 3 robust setae and row of spinules dorsodistally; carpus with 4 robust setae ventrally and 1 robust seta dorsodistally; propodus with 2 short setae; dactylus with 1 short seta, 1 curved unguis and 1 curved accessory claw.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Operculum (Fig. 3A) 1.2 times as broad as long, with 2 lateral, 2 subapical setae, and many fine marginal setae. Pleopod 3 (Fig. 3B) with endopod bearing 3 stout, plumose setae distally; exopod narrower than endopod, bearing 1 lateral, 1 apical long simple setae, and many fine setae on convex lateral margin. Pleopod 4 (Fig. 3C) with ovate endopod; exopod uniramous, narrow, with 1 plumose seta distally, and many fine setae on lateral margin. Pleopod 5 (Fig. 3D) ovate, uniramous, about 2.8 times as long as broad, without setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Halacarsantia</taxonomicName>
acuta sp. n. may be distinguished from its congeners in having long robust setae on the pereonites. The body shape of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Halacarsantia</taxonomicName>
acuta is similar 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia kussakini" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kussakini">Halacarsantia kussakini</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Müller">Mueller</normalizedToken>
, 1992 from the Society Islands, French Polynesia (type locality), but 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">H</taxonomicName>
. acuta can be separated from 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia kussakini" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kussakini">Halacarsantia kussakini</taxonomicName>
by the (those of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia kussakini" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kussakini">Halacarsantia kussakini</taxonomicName>
in parentheses): 3 robust setae on each side of the head (2 setae); antenna flagellum composed of 8 articles (11 articles); maxilliped epipod apically acute, without setae (apically blunt, with 2 slender setae); maxilliped endite broad (moderately narrow); and pereopod 1 basis with a conspicuous short projection (without conspicuous projections).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">The species is named after the apically acute maxilliped epipod.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia acuta" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">Halacarsantia acuta</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–I">A-I</normalizedToken>
holotype female: A habitus, dorsal B right antennula, ventral C articles 1-3 of right antennula, dorsal D right antenna, ventral E left mandible, dorsal F right mandible, dorsal G right maxilla 1, ventral H right maxilla 2, ventral I left maxilliped, dorsal. Scales = 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia acuta" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">Halacarsantia acuta</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–G">A-G</normalizedToken>
holotype female: A right pereopod 1, medial B right pereopod 2, dorsal C right pereopod 3, dorsal D right pereopod 4, dorsal E right pereopod 5, dorsal F right pereopod 6, dorsal G right pereopod 7, dorsal. Scale = 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Santiidae" genus="Halacarsantia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Halacarsantia acuta" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">Halacarsantia acuta</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
holotype female: A operculum, ventral B right pleopod 3, dorsal C right pleopod 4, ventral D right pleopod 5, ventral E pleotelson, ventral F pleotelson, lateral. Scales = 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>