<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5321854" ID-ISSN="1175­5334" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5321854" approvalRequired="48" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="4" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="36" approvalRequired_for_treatments="8" checkinTime="1629674756648" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Oláh, János &amp; Johanson, Kjell Arne" docDate="2010" docId="2B7E87E4FF8CFFB4F5A6FC9AFEDAFA33" docLanguage="en" docName="zt02457p128.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2457 (1)" docSource="https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.2457.1.1" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1.1:Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleId="D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Anisocentropus (Anisocentropus) mjoebergi Oláh &amp; Johanson 2010, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="36" masterDocId="D747FF9CFFADFF97F531FFFDFFD9FFE9" masterDocTitle="Description of 33 new species of Calamoceratidae, Molannidae, Odontoceridae and Philorheithridae (Trichoptera), with detailed presentation of their cephalic setal warts and grooves 2457" masterLastPageNumber="128" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" updateTime="1630239817089" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Description of 33 new species of Calamoceratidae, Molannidae, Odontoceridae and Philorheithridae (Trichoptera), with detailed presentation of their cephalic setal warts and grooves 2457</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Oláh, János</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johanson, Kjell Arne</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2010-05-14</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2457</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>128</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.2457.1.1</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.2457.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5313709</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5321854" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5321854" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2B7E87E4FF8CFFB4F5A6FC9AFEDAFA33" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2B7E87E4FF8CFFB4F5A6FC9AFEDAFA33" lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="36" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<subSubSection box="[151,842,871,897]" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="33.[151,842,871,932]" box="[151,842,871,897]" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,842,871,897]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,842,871,897]" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName authority="Oláh &amp; Johanson, 2010" authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[151,683,871,897]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mjoebergi" status="new species" subGenus="Anisocentropus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,340,871,897]" italics="true" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Anisocentropus</emphasis>
(
<emphasis bold="true" box="[357,546,871,897]" italics="true" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Anisocentropus</emphasis>
) 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[563,683,871,897]" italics="true" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">mjoebergi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[698,842,871,897]" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="36" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="33.[151,842,871,932]" box="[151,282,906,932]" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<figureCitation box="[151,282,906,932]" captionStart="FIGURES 68–72" captionStartId="34.[151,269,1344,1368]" captionTargetBox="[153,1425,207,1304]" captionTargetId="figure-250@34.[151,1436,197,1316]" captionTargetPageId="34" captionText="FIGURES 68–72. Anisocentropus mjoebergi, new species, holotype. 68 — genitalia, lateral; 69 — genitalia, dorsal; 70 — genitalia, ventral; 71 — phallus, lateral; 72 — phalus, ventral." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5313751" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5313751/files/figure.png" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Figs 68–72</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="33.[151,1437,986,2012]" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
This medium-sized, brown species with bicoloured forewings, is most similar to 
<emphasis box="[1107,1319,986,1011]" italics="true" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName authorityName="McLachlan" authorityYear="1863" box="[1107,1288,986,1011]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Anisocentropus</taxonomicName>
io
</emphasis>
Kimmins from New 
<collectingCountry box="[277,365,1026,1052]" name="Guinea-Bissau" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Guinea</collectingCountry>
, especially in the genitalia. The 2 species are easily separated in that the forewing pattern is less colourfully in 
<emphasis box="[372,428,1066,1091]" italics="true" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">A. io</emphasis>
. In the genitalia, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[635,786,1066,1091]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mjoebergi">
<emphasis box="[635,786,1066,1091]" italics="true" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">A. mjoebergi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
differs by having a posterad-protruding tergum IX and having the lateral flank of segment X stretched more laterad and with bilobed apices.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="33.[151,1437,986,2012]" lastBlockId="35.[151,1437,152,1498]" lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="36" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
Male (in alcohol). Body medium-sized, small-eyed, brown; legs, antennae and palps lighter; wings brown with darker apical half, visible even in alcohol. Head rectangular in dorsal view, almost as long as broad. Ocelli absent. Tentorium not examined. Facial groove pattern modified, with plate-like flange or rim connecting anterior tentorial pits, separating frons and clypeus; frontogenal vertical grooves forming oblique, dorsal continuations from anterior tentorial pits, almost horizontally merging with broad antennal grooves; clypeogenal vertical grooves located ventrally of anterior tentorial pits, short, running slightly mesoventrad; conspicuous pattern of plate-like flanges and frontogenal and clypeogenal sutures forming frontogenal septum (complex of anterior tentorial arms). Small, inconspicuous subantennal grooves sinuous, running almost horizontally between large frontogenal compact warts and palpifers, forming proximal articulation of palpi on stipes; subocular grooves not visible; short, pronounced frontal groove present on compressed frons between antennae and joining to vertexal medioantennal compact setose wart. Vertexal groove pattern reduced; large, anterad-directed, rounded elevation dominating anterior half of vertex, reaching interantennal area, delineated laterally by extremely large membranous antennal sockets with corrugated or granulous surfaces near frontogenal compact setose warts; stem of epicranial groove (coronal groove) vestigial, only posterior end remaining; usually permanent antennal and ocular grooves accompanied by occipito-postgenal grooves, partly merging anteriorally with, or tangential to, very large occipital compact setal warts. Labrum vertically long, quadrangular, with narrow, rounded apex, freely hanging, sparsely setose. Mandibles long, slightly pigmented, beside lateral margins of labrum; laciniae narrow, elongated, bearing few setae. Frontal setal warts absent on face, frontal interantennal warts absent due to forward-directed vertexal elevation and compressed narrow frons between antennae. Pair of large, nearly triangular frontogenal compact setal warts present on posterior pregenae, extending obliquely or almost horizontally from frontogenal grooves; no other warts visible on face. Forward-directed, rounded triangular elevation on vertex bearing fused vertexal medioantennal compact setose warts anteriorly; vertexal lateroantennal compact setal warts absent; antennal sockets enlarged; pair of small, rounded, vertexal ocellar compact setose warts, and scattered, vertexal, medioocellar, diffuse setose warts present, with 1 or 2 setae in middle of vertex; obliquely located and elongated ovoid pair of large occipital compact setose warts dominating posterior half of vertex; small pair of postgenal compact warts visible between posterior section of ocular grooves and large occipital compact setose warts. Maxillary palps apparently 6-segmented; maxillary palp formula II-VI-IV-I-V-III, labial palps apparently 4-segmented, maxillary palp segments filiform, with long, mesad-directed setae. Scapes rounded, long, about half as long as head; pedicels 2/5ths as long as scapes. Minute, rounded setose wart located proximally above articulation of each cervical sclerite on proepisternum. Large, compact setal warts present mainly on membranous part of cervix, touching anterior arms of cervical sclerites. Lateral cervical sclerites forming narrow anterior arms articulating anteriorly to back of head with occipital condyles above posterior tentorial pits and fusing with posterior cervical sclerites. Posterior cervical sclerites forming narrow, elongate plates reaching prothoracic episternum, articulating to weakly sclerotized anteromedian band of prothoracic eusternum by thin ventral intercervical sclerites. Two pairs pronotal warts present: large-sized, transverse, ovoid dorsal pair widely separate mesally; second setal wart pair, small, rounded, located deep laterally, visible in lateral view. One pair of mesoscutal, diffused warts present, arranged in longitudinal lines along full length of mesoscutum, composed mostly of single, double and maximum triple setae in groups visible as more weakly pigmented alveoli. Pair of mesoscutellar warts forming small, rounded less-pigmented areas with few setal alveoli. Legs with symmetrical claws; spur formula 2,?, 3, middle legs broken; foreleg spurs equally long; hind leg anteroapical spur half as long as posteroapical spur. Forewings: length 11.0 mm, membrane brown with dark brown apical half speckled with small, lighter dots; R1 running separately to C; base of discoidal cell located proximally of wing middle; forks I, II, III, IV, V present; crossveins 
<emphasis box="[797,812,432,457]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">h</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[828,872,432,458]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">sc -r</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[888,898,432,457]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">r</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[914,925,432,457]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">s</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[942,983,432,458]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">r -m</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[999,1020,432,457]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">m</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[1036,1096,432,458]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">m -cu</emphasis>
, and 
<emphasis box="[1162,1204,432,457]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">cu2</emphasis>
present, crossveins 
<emphasis box="[151,261,472,498]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">cu1, cu -a</emphasis>
and postanal vein absent. Hind wings: R1 meeting R2; forks I, II, III, V present; fork I longer than fork II.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5313751" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5313751" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5313751/files/figure.png" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" startId="34.[151,269,1344,1368]" targetBox="[153,1425,207,1304]" targetPageId="34">
<paragraph blockId="34.[151,1435,1344,1403]" pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,350,1344,1368]" pageId="34" pageNumber="35">FIGURES 68–72.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Oláh &amp; Johanson, 2010" authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[357,636,1344,1367]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mjoebergi" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[357,636,1344,1367]" italics="true" pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Anisocentropus mjoebergi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[650,782,1344,1367]" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
, holotype. 68 — genitalia, lateral; 69 — genitalia, dorsal; 70 — genitalia, ventral; 71 — phallus, lateral; 72 — phalus, ventral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="35.[151,1437,152,1498]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">Male genitalia. Abdominal segment IX fused annularly, without longitudinal groove separating dorsal and ventral parts; tergum little shorter than venter, elevated dorsum produced into protruding triangular posterior corner in lateral view; anterior margins of segment IX triangular in ventral half; posterior margins produced into apical lobe at base of each inferior appendage, additional flank present on each side below its preanal appendage, apical half of flank glabrous and shining, transparent. Antecosta weakly developed, forming narrow, marginal rim, equally thin along its full width, without conspicuous external groove of antecostal suture; elevated tergum regularly triangular in dorsal view; spine row on posterior margin of segment IX modified, concentrated as small setose patches of dorsopleural setose areas composed of 3–4 setae on each side and larger ventropleural setose area on each side. Intersegmental depression between segments IX and X forming deep step or excision. Segment X longer than gonocoxites and preanal appendages, forming broad hood with ventrad- and laterad-directed apical flanks, each with slightly bilobed apex; apicoventral setose lobes represented by these flanks; apicodorsal setose lobe with few tiny setae above middle of segment X. Dorsal interlobular gap parallel-sided, very narrow and deep. Preanal appendages short, compressed, plate-like in lateral view; digitiform to clavate in dorsal view. Gonocoxites without harpagones, triangular, each with bare digitiform apex in lateral view, more elongate and broad mesally in ventral view; dorsomesal surface armed with short stout peg-like setae, ventral surface with long setae. Phallic apparatus forming slightly ventrad-curving tube with elongate, sclerotized ventral apical lobe, only part of phallicata visible above ventral lobe while retracted; pair of phallotremal sclerites scarcely visible in lateral view as dorsad-curving structure inside membranous phallicata. Phallotremal sclerite complex in ventral view, U-shaped with laterad-curving ends; slender ejaculatory duct indistinctly reaching phallotremal sclerite complex.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[199,947,1351,1378]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="35.[151,1437,152,1498]" box="[199,947,1351,1378]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">
<materialsCitation box="[199,947,1351,1378]" collectorName="O. Borneo" location="Pajau River" pageId="35" pageNumber="36" specimenCount="1" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,380,1351,1377]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">
<typeStatus box="[199,313,1351,1377]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">Holotype</typeStatus>
male
</emphasis>
: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[396,523,1351,1377]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">BORNEO</emphasis>
: 
<collectorName box="[538,663,1352,1378]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">O. Borneo</collectorName>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2B7E87E4FF8CFFB4F5A6FC9AFEDAFA33:A6086029FF8EFFB4F792FAB5FCF5FA8B" box="[675,812,1352,1378]" name="Pajau River" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">Pajau River</location>
[Mjöberg].
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[199,463,1391,1418]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="35.[151,1437,152,1498]" box="[199,463,1391,1418]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,361,1391,1417]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">Distribution:</emphasis>
Borneo.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="35" pageNumber="36" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="35.[151,1437,152,1498]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,343,1431,1457]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">Etymology:</emphasis>
<emphasis box="[356,477,1432,1457]" italics="true" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">Mjoebergi</emphasis>
, named after the Swedish zoologist and collector of the 
<typeStatus box="[1193,1243,1432,1458]" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">type</typeStatus>
specimen, Eric Mjöberg.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>