<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280267" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120206" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280267" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="45FFE3ADF95DB68D5AF986415C0737E3" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys ravola Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="693" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="693" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280267" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120206" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280267" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:45FFE3ADF95DB68D5AF986415C0737E3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/45FFE3ADF95DB68D5AF986415C0737E3" lastPageNumber="693" pageNumber="693">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="693">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155872" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys ravola Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys ravola Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="693" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ravola">Strumigenys ravola Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="693">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 2.3, HL 0.54, HW 0.44, CI 81, ML 0.22, MI 41, SL 0.33, SI 76, PW 0.28, AL 0.56. Characters of scotti-complex. Mandibles in full-face view with outer margins shallowly and evenly convex, the width gradually decreasing from near the base to the apicodorsal tooth. Upper scrobe margin evenly and shallowly convex in fullface view, not bordered by a rim or flange. Eyes small, not visible in full-face view; maximum diameter of eye less than maximum width of scape, with 2 - 3 ommatidia in longest row. Scape short and stout, shallowly and gently curved; hairs on leading edge spatulate or spoon-shaped. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with curved narrow spatulate to spoon-shaped ground-pilosity, the upper scrobe margin fringed with hairs which are the same shape and size as those on the dorsum. Cephalic dorsum with 6 clavate standing hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Reticulate-punctate sculpture of cephalic dorsum with superimposed longitudinal or oblique rugulae; the top surface of the rugulae with a beaded appearance due to the presence of aligned punctulation. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate. Mesonotum with 2 pair of erect clavate hairs. Propodeum with 2 pairs of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Dorsal alitrunk with ground-pilosity as on head. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline more or less flat. Anterior mesonotum with a narrow carina above mesothoracic spiracle. Propodeal tooth broadly triangular, lamellate, pointed apically, subtended by a moderate lamella. Alitrunk dorsum and sides of pronotum densely reticulate-punctate, dorsal pronotum also with short rugulose sculpture. Pleurae mostly smooth and shiny with reticulate-punctate sculpture peripherally. Postpetiole disc smooth and shining. In profile the petiole with a straight ventral spongiform strip, its depth approximately equal to maximum diameter of eye. Postpetiole with moderately developed ventral and lateral spongiform lobes. Basigastral costulae arising on each side of a narrow, central clear area. Dorsal surfaces of petiole, postpetiole and gaster with standing clavate to remiform hairs. First gastral sternite, including anterior half, with numerous short suberect filiform hairs. Colour light brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="693">Holotype worker, Madagascar: Prov. Toamasina, P. N. Mantadia, 18 Â° 47.5 ' S, 48 Â° 25.6 ' E, 895 m., 25. xi. - l. xii. 1998, ground forager (s), rainforest ,, # 25 - 2 (H. J. Ratsirarson) (MCZ).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="693">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155872" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys ravola Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys ravola Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="693" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ravola">S. ravola</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from other species in the scorn-complex by having the cephalic dorsum reticulate-punctate with superimposed longitudinal or oblique rugulae, the top surface of the rugulae with a beaded appearance due to the presence of aligned punctulation. See 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155865" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys langrandi Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys langrandi Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="693" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="langrandi">langrandi</taxonomicName>
for further discussion.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>