<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" ID-GBIF-Dataset="92d38eff-94a4-404e-a09c-d535155922c8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043328" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-292-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BF3D2E8D-3434-4B3B-88AA-70122522496D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-292-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 292" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" checkinTime="1451247388242" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="EE85EA15DEF791920408C1D7E0D1DAF8" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 292: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 292" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" docTitle="Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="BF3D2E8D-3434-4B3B-88AA-70122522496D" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="103" lastPageNumber="104" masterDocId="FFB8FF92FF98D87CFFAE2F6B1E57FFC8" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" updateTime="1643694823285" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>292</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-292-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043328" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BF3D2E8D-3434-4B3B-88AA-70122522496D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EE85EA15DEF791920408C1D7E0D1DAF8" lastPageId="103" lastPageNumber="104" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
<subSubSection pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BF3D2E8D-3434-4B3B-88AA-70122522496D" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dermatoglyphes">Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="102" pageNumber="103">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 172-177Morphbank57
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="103" lastPageNumber="104" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Female. Body length 4.25-4.7 mm (n=12).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Radicle color: darker than scape. Scape color: Yellowish. A4: longer than broad. A5: longer than broad; as long as broad. Antennal club: formed, segments compact.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Interantennal process: not elongate. Median longitudinal elevation in frontal depression: absent. Frontal depression: concave. Frontal depression sculpture: without transverse or oblique carinae below submedian carina. Submedian carina: indicated by multiple weak carinae. Submedian carina medially: without peak. Concavity across dorsal part of frontal depression: absent. Depression extending ventrally from median ocellus: absent. Upper frons: not hood-like. Malar area near antennal foramen: without carina or expansion. Malar area at mouth corner: with radiating striae. Smooth strip along posterior side of malar sulcus: absent or not consistently broad. Middle genal carina: present. Direction of middle genal carina dorsally: parallel to eye margin. Major sculpture of gena anteriorly: rugose; umbilicate-punctate. Major sculpture of gena posteriorly: rugose; umbilicate-punctate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent. Median carina extending posteriorly from hyperoccipital carina: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by rugae. Lateral connection between hyperoccipital and occipital carinae: absent. Area between vertex and occipital carina: umbilicate-foveate. Occipital carina medially: uniformly rounded. Lateral corners of occipital carina: not protruding.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="103" lastPageNumber="104" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
Lateral pronotal area: without bulge projecting towards anterior pit. Epomial corner: weak. Netrion surface anteriorly: not inflexed. Mesoscutum anteriorly: not steep. Mesoscutal median carina: present and complete. Longitudinal carina between median carina and notauli: absent. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum: umbilicate-foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum medially: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum laterally: absent. Mesoscutellar apex: convex or straight. Setae along anterior limit of femoral depression: arising from tiny pits. Number of carinae crossing speculum above femoral depression: 4. Number of carinae crossing femoral depression: more than 5. Mesepimeral sulcus pits: more than 5. Metascutellum dorsally: concave. Metascutellar sculpture 
<pageBreakToken pageId="103" pageNumber="104" start="start">dorsally</pageBreakToken>
: with scattered rugae. Median carina of metascutellum: absent or branched. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellar apex: convex or straight. Metapleuron above ventral metapleural area: crossed by carinae. Metasomal depression setae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae anteromedially: strongly diverging. Anterior areoles of metasomal depression: absent. Anterior longitudinal carinae in metasomal depression: absent. Lateral propodeal areas: separated medially. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex: reaching middle of T5.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1: with small rounded anterior bulge, not reaching metascutellum. T2: with straight longitudinal striae or rugae. T6: longer than broad. Apical flange of T6: exposed apically. Metasomal apex: rounded. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate-punctate; longitudinally striate or rugose. Microsculpture of T6: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Male.Body length 3.55-4.5 mm (n=20). A5 tyloid: carina-like, not expanded. A11: longer than broad. Median tooth of frontal depression: absent. Median lobe of T1: with 6 longitudinal carinae. Metasomal apex: with tiny rounded tubercles.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Both sexes: Upper frons with extra carinae present parallel to submedian carina, all these carinae of about equal height. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by rugae. Mesoscutellum without granulate sculpture. Mesopleuron along anteroventral edge of femoral depression without row of foveae, setae arising from tiny pits. Female: A4 longer than broad. Metascutellum subrectangular, with scattered weak rugae. T1 midlobe with long anterior bulge. T6 longer than broad, tapering to a rounded apex. Male: A11 longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. T7 with sharp and protruding posterolateral corners.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
Compound noun based on Greek, intended to mean 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“fingerprint.”">&quot;fingerprint.&quot;</normalizedToken>
Refers to the pattern formed on the frons near the submedian carina.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=275502]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
Holotype, female: TAIWAN: Taiwan Prov., Nantou Co., Lugu (Luku) Twp., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hsi-t’ou">Hsi-t'ou</normalizedToken>
(Chito) Experimental Forest, 1100m, 20.IX.1997, B. J. Sinclair, OSUC 368835 (deposited in CNCI). Paratypes: TAIWAN: 13 females, 22 males, OSUC 368834, 368838 (CNCI); OSUC 368832 (OSUC); OSUC 439680-439681, 439683, 439687-439688, 439700-439715, 439717-439718, 439720-439727 (TARI); OSUC 442263 (WINC). Other material: TAIWAN: 1 unknown [consists only of mesosoma], OSUC 439686 (TARI).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dermatoglyphes">Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes</taxonomicName>
is part of a species complex occurring also in Japan and Korea. This complex can be characterized by the elongate body, dark antennal radicle, weak occipital carina without protruding lateral corners, subrectangular flat metascutellum (reduced in males), and very strong T1 horn in females.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
<paragraph pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
Figures 172-177. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dermatoglyphes">Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 368835) 172 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 173 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 174 Head, anterior view 175 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 368838) 176 Antenna 177 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank57
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>