<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886426" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2c2b0f81-dcfb-4ae5-8d57-be3d9f2fe8f1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="192495243" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5886426" ID-ZooBank="DC9F2DA8-DC30-454A-BAE8-D311DFEF958D" checkinTime="1642751139630" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2022" docId="03F12B6304700D627591F9787995FA82" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.5092.4.1.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 5092 (4)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Bebelis skillmani Santos-Silva 2022, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="413" masterDocId="FFC8531B04790D6E7506FF89785AFFFB" masterDocTitle="New species, revalidation, synonymies, and new records in Bebelis Thomson (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Apomecynini)" masterLastPageNumber="428" masterPageNumber="401" pageId="9" pageNumber="410" updateTime="1642777679909" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species, revalidation, synonymies, and new records in Bebelis Thomson (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Apomecynini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2022</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2022-01-21</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>5092</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>4</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>401</mods:start>
<mods:end>428</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.5092.4.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">2c2b0f81-dcfb-4ae5-8d57-be3d9f2fe8f1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5886400</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DC9F2DA8-DC30-454A-BAE8-D311DFEF958D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886426" ID-GBIF-Taxon="192495243" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5886426" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F12B6304700D627591F9787995FA82" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F12B6304700D627591F9787995FA82" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="413" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<subSubSection box="[151,460,1777,1804]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,460,1777,1840]" box="[151,460,1777,1804]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,460,1777,1804]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="410" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,460,1777,1804]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva, 2022" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2022" box="[151,359,1777,1804]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="410" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="skillmani" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,359,1777,1804]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Bebelis skillmani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[366,460,1778,1804]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="413" pageId="9" pageNumber="410" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,460,1777,1840]" box="[151,295,1814,1840]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,287,1814,1840]" captionStart="FIGURES 31–39" captionStartId="11.[151,264,1893,1917]" captionTargetBox="[205,1384,184,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-18@11.[202,1385,181,1869]" captionTargetPageId="11" captionText="FIGURES 31–39. Bebelis spp. 31–34) B. skillmani sp. nov., holotype male: 31) Dorsal habitus; 32) Ventral habitus; 33) Lateral habitus; 34) Head, frontal view. 35–36) B. cuprina (Belon, 1903), male from Brazil (Entre Rios, no state reported): 35) Dorsal habitus; 36) Lateral habitus. 37–38) B. cuprina, male from Brazil (Acre, Rio Branco): 37) Lateral habitus; 38) Head, frontal view. 39) B. cuprina, holotype, dorsal habitus, by Jesus Santiago Moure." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886414" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886414/files/figure.png" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Figs 31–34</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,1886,2020]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,482,1886,1912]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
Description. 
<typeStatus box="[302,411,1886,1912]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Holotype</typeStatus>
male.
</emphasis>
Integument mostly dark brown; anterior region of labrum partially brown with central area of apex dark yellowish-brown; palpomeres dark reddish brown except yellowish-brown apex of labial palpomere III and maxillary palpomere IV; base of antennomeres III–VIII dark reddish brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,1886,2020]" lastBlockId="10.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="411" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,270,1994,2020]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Head.</emphasis>
Frons moderately coarsely and abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and white setae interspersed; with one long, erect brown seta on each side close to eyes. Area between antennal tubercles and upper eye lobes coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence, and white setae interspersed (pubescence dense close to antennal tubercles and upper eye lobes). Remaining surface of vertex coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with sparse brownish pubescence and short white seta on some punctures. Area behind upper eye lobes with narrow, longitudinal yellowish-brown pubescent band close to vertex, wide brownish pubescent band almost obscuring integument on central region, narrow, longitudinal yellowish-brown pubescent band close to lower eye lobes, and transverse yellowish-brown pubescent band close to prothorax, connecting the two longitudinal yellowish-brown pubescent bands; all pubescence with short, thick white setae interspersed. Area behind lower eye lobes and genae coarsely, sparsely punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and short, thick white setae interspersed; genae distinctly longer than lower eye lobe. Wide central area of postclypeus with yellowish-brown pubescence directed to central region close to frons, and white setae interspersed, and yellowish-white setae directed forward close to anteclypeus; with one long, erect brown setae on each side. Sides of postclypeus glabrous. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior half, inclined at anterior half; moderately finely, densely punctate on posterior half, smooth on anterior half; with long, erect, both brown and yellowish setae on posterior half, and short fringe of golden setae on anterior margin. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.23 times distance between outer margins of eyes; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.63 times distance between outer margins of eyes. Antennae 1.6 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex near apex of antennomere X. Scape cylindrical, moderately finely rugose-punctate; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and short, thick white setae interspersed; with a few long, erect, thick dark setae ventrally. Pedicel with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, more yellowish apically, and short, thick white setae interspersed; ventral surface with a long erect dark seta. Antennomeres III and IV with yellowish pubescence basally, yellowish-brown, not obscuring integument on remaining surface, and short, thick white setae throughout; ventral surface with long, erect, thick dark setae. Antennomeres V–XI with white pubescence basally, and yellowish-brown pubescence with white setae interspersed on remaining surface (white basal pubescent region gradually narrowed toward XI); with long, erect thick dark setae ventrally (erect setae gradually sparser toward XI); with short, erect yellowish setae interspersed throughout. Antennal formula based on length of antennomere III: scape = 1.00; pedicel = 0.29; IV = 1.04; V = 0.81; VI = 0.73; VII = 0.73; VIII = 0.63; IX = 0.59; X = 0.54; XI = 0.68.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastBlockId="12.[151,1437,151,1401]" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="413" pageId="10" pageNumber="411">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,295,1159,1185]" pageId="10" pageNumber="411">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax slightly longer than wide; sides slightly tumid centrally, subparallel-sided anteriorly and posteriorly. Pronotum coarsely, abundantly punctate; with narrow, longitudinal, white pubescent band laterally from posterior margin to anterior third, slightly inclined inward from its middle to anterior region, narrow, longitudinal white pubescent band laterally on anterior third, longitudinal white pubescent band on center of lateral area (tumid area of prothorax), oblique, narrow white pubescent band on each side of center of anterior third, and white pubescent macula on each side of middle of central region; with dense yellowish-brown pubescence on center of anterior fifth, sides of anterior 2/3, and small tuft centrally close to posterior margin, sparse yellowish-brown pubescence on center of posterior 3/4, and abundant brownish pubescence not obscuring integument on remaining surface; sides with short, thick white setae interspersed. Sides of prothorax coarsely, abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, and short, thick white setae interspersed, except postcoxal process mostly with white pubescence; with a few long, erect dark setae. Prosternum coarsely, abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, denser laterally. Prosternal process with abundant whitish pubescence not obscuring integument, except central area with yellowish pubescence; narrowest area 0.29 times procoxal width; apex 1.10 times procoxal width. Mesoventrite coarsely, sparsely punctate, except smooth sides; with sparse yellowish-brown pubescence on anterocentral region, dense on remaining surface, and white setae interspersed, except glabrous apex of sides. Mesanepisternum coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and short, thick white setae interspersed. Mesepimeron with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and a few short white setae interspersed. Mesoventral process with abundant white pubescence not obscuring integument. Metanepisternum with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and white setae interspersed. Metaventrite coarsely, abundantly punctate; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, more yellowish and sparser toward central region, and white setae interspersed. Scutellum with yellowish-brown pubescence laterally, glabrous on wide central area. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[580,663,1951,1977]" pageId="10" pageNumber="411">Elytra.</emphasis>
Coarsely, abundantly punctate on anterior half, punctures gradually sparser and slightly finer toward apex; anterior half with irregular white pubescent maculae, together forming wide, oblique V-shaped band; sutural region with short, longitudinal white pubescent bands, from apex of V-shaped band to near apex; posterior third with abundant, irregular white pubescent maculae, part of them forming slightly distinct inverted V-shaped band; circum-scutellar region, are inside anterior V-shaped white pubescent macula, and sides of anterior quarter with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument; sides of dorsal surface on middle with dense, irregular, large yellowish-brown pubescent macula; area between anterior V-shaped white pubescent macula and surrounding the yellowish-brown central pubescent macula with brownish pubescence; sutural region between white bands with brownish pubescence not obscuring integument; posterior quarter of dorsal surface with oblique brownish pubescent band; remaining surface of posterior quarter with sparse yellowish-brown pubescence; with abundant, short, erect, thick white setae interspersed throughout; apex slightly obliquely truncate. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1278,1341,439,465]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence and short, thick white setae interspersed. Tibiae with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence and short, thick white setae interspersed, except posterior 2/3 of ventral surface of protibiae with dense, bristle brown pubescence, posterior third of ventral surface of meso- and metatibiae with bristly brownish pubescence, and posterior third of dorsal surface of meso- and metatibiae with long, abundant, erect, thick brown setae. Tarsomeres I–III with brownish pubescence not obscuring integument, and whitish setae interspersed; tarsomeres IV–V with sparse brownish pubescence.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886414" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5886414" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886414/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" startId="11.[151,264,1893,1917]" targetBox="[205,1384,184,1869]" targetPageId="11">
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,1893,2025]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,339,1893,1917]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">FIGURES 31–39.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName box="[345,467,1893,1917]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="undetermined">
<emphasis box="[345,420,1893,1917]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">Bebelis</emphasis>
spp.
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[472,544,1893,1917]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">31–34)</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva, 2022" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2022" box="[549,670,1893,1917]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="skillmani" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[549,670,1893,1917]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">B. skillmani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[675,755,1894,1918]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[675,755,1894,1918]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, holotype male: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[923,956,1893,1917]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">31)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1121,1155,1893,1917]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">32)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1325,1359,1893,1917]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">33)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[238,263,1929,1953]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">34</emphasis>
) Head, frontal view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[480,552,1929,1953]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">35–36)</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="(Belon, 1903)" baseAuthorityName="Belon" baseAuthorityYear="1903" box="[558,816,1929,1954]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cuprina">
<emphasis box="[558,666,1930,1953]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">B. cuprina</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Belon, P. M." box="[680,808,1929,1954]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" pagination="47 - 76" refId="ref18989" refString="Belon, P. M. (1903) Materiaux pour l'etude des longicornes de Bolivie. Revue d'Entomologie, 22, 47 - 76." type="journal article" year="1903">Belon, 1903</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
, male from Brazil (Entre Rios, no state reported): 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1328,1362,1929,1953]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">35)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[239,273,1965,1989]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">36)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[449,520,1965,1989]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">37–38)</emphasis>
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Belon" baseAuthorityYear="1903" box="[528,637,1966,1989]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cuprina">
<emphasis box="[528,637,1966,1989]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">B. cuprina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, male from Brazil (Acre, Rio Branco): 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1049,1083,1965,1989]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">37)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1259,1293,1965,1989]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">38)</emphasis>
Head, frontal view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[211,245,2001,2025]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">39)</emphasis>
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Belon" baseAuthorityYear="1903" box="[252,359,2002,2025]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cuprina">
<emphasis box="[252,359,2002,2025]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">B. cuprina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, holotype, dorsal habitus, by Jesus Santiago Moure.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,1401]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,323,690,716]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and white setae interspersed, gradually more abundant from 1 to 5 (white setae forming irregular tufts on some areas).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,1401]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,416,798,824]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Dimensions (mm).</emphasis>
Total length, 6.95; prothoracic length, 1.45; anterior prothoracic width, 1.10; posterior prothoracic width, 1.15; maximum prothoracic width, 1.30; humeral width, 1.55; elytral length, 4.80.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="413" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,1401]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,373,870,897]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3450093355" collectingDate="2012-12-05" collectingDateMax="2012-12-10" collectingDateMin="2012-12-05" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="Skillman &amp; Wappes &amp; Bonaso" country="Bolivia" elevation="1250" latitude="-19.866667" location="Eyti" longLatPrecision="1270" longitude="-63.483334" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Santa Cruz" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[381,485,871,897]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry box="[616,734,871,897]" name="Bolivia" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">BOLIVIA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis box="[746,871,871,897]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<collectingRegion box="[746,871,871,897]" country="Bolivia" name="Santa Cruz" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Santa Cruz</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<locationDeviation box="[887,1075,871,897]" location="Camiri" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<quantity box="[887,959,871,897]" metricMagnitude="4" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.0" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" unit="km" value="20.0">20 km</quantity>
N Camiri
</locationDeviation>
, road to 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F12B6304700D627591F9787995FA82:8E87CCAE04750D627192FCEE7C9FFC7A" box="[1172,1221,871,897]" country="Bolivia" latitude="-19.866667" longLatPrecision="1270" longitude="-63.483334" name="Eyti" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" stateProvince="Santa Cruz">Eyti</location>
, 
<quantity box="[1234,1321,870,897]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.25" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" unit="m" value="1250.0">
<elevation box="[1234,1321,870,897]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.25" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" unit="m" value="1250.0">1250 m</elevation>
</quantity>
, 
<locationDeviation location="Hwy" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<quantity box="[1333,1412,871,897]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="6.8" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" unit="km" value="6.8">6.8 km</quantity>
E Hwy
</locationDeviation>
9, 
<geoCoordinate box="[241,332,906,933]" degrees="19" direction="south" minutes="52" orientation="latitude" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" precision="925" value="-19.866667">19º52’S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate box="[344,444,907,933]" degrees="63" direction="west" minutes="29" orientation="longitude" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" precision="925" value="-63.483334">63º29’W</geoCoordinate>
, 
<date box="[456,624,906,933]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" value="2012-12-05" valueMax="2012-12-10" valueMin="2012-12-05">
<collectingDate box="[456,624,906,933]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" value="2012-12-05" valueMax="2012-12-10" valueMin="2012-12-05">5–10.XII.2012</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName box="[635,739,907,933]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Skillman</collectorName>
, 
<collectorName box="[750,838,907,933]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Wappes</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName box="[873,957,907,933]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Bonaso</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode box="[1020,1096,907,933]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="413" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,1401]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,334,943,969]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Etymology.</emphasis>
The new species is named in honor of Frederick W. Skillman Jr. (FWSC), one of the collectors of the 
<typeStatus box="[192,294,979,1005]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="413" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,1437,151,1401]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,315,1015,1041]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva, 2022" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2022" box="[321,513,1015,1041]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="skillmani" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[321,513,1015,1041]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Bebelis skillmani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[519,608,1015,1041]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[519,608,1015,1041]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="(Belon, 1903)" baseAuthorityName="Belon" baseAuthorityYear="1903" box="[752,1031,1015,1041]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cuprina">
<emphasis box="[752,869,1015,1040]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">B. cuprina</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Belon, P. M." box="[884,1022,1015,1041]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" pagination="47 - 76" refId="ref18989" refString="Belon, P. M. (1903) Materiaux pour l'etude des longicornes de Bolivie. Revue d'Entomologie, 22, 47 - 76." type="journal article" year="1903">Belon, 1903</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation box="[1045,1174,1014,1041]" captionStart="FIGURES 31–39" captionStartId="11.[151,264,1893,1917]" captionTargetBox="[205,1384,184,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-18@11.[202,1385,181,1869]" captionTargetPageId="11" captionText="FIGURES 31–39. Bebelis spp. 31–34) B. skillmani sp. nov., holotype male: 31) Dorsal habitus; 32) Ventral habitus; 33) Lateral habitus; 34) Head, frontal view. 35–36) B. cuprina (Belon, 1903), male from Brazil (Entre Rios, no state reported): 35) Dorsal habitus; 36) Lateral habitus. 37–38) B. cuprina, male from Brazil (Acre, Rio Branco): 37) Lateral habitus; 38) Head, frontal view. 39) B. cuprina, holotype, dorsal habitus, by Jesus Santiago Moure." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886414" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886414/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Figs 35–39</figureCitation>
), but differs as follows: dorsal surface with short and thick white setae interspersed, which are distinctly erect on the elytra; anterior and posterior white pubescent bands on the pronotum not aligned on anterior third; anterior half of the pronotum with oblique white pubescent bands and maculae centrally; lower eye lobes shorter than genae (
<figureCitation box="[1157,1241,1123,1149]" captionStart="FIGURES 31–39" captionStartId="11.[151,264,1893,1917]" captionTargetBox="[205,1384,184,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-18@11.[202,1385,181,1869]" captionTargetPageId="11" captionText="FIGURES 31–39. Bebelis spp. 31–34) B. skillmani sp. nov., holotype male: 31) Dorsal habitus; 32) Ventral habitus; 33) Lateral habitus; 34) Head, frontal view. 35–36) B. cuprina (Belon, 1903), male from Brazil (Entre Rios, no state reported): 35) Dorsal habitus; 36) Lateral habitus. 37–38) B. cuprina, male from Brazil (Acre, Rio Branco): 37) Lateral habitus; 38) Head, frontal view. 39) B. cuprina, holotype, dorsal habitus, by Jesus Santiago Moure." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886414" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886414/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Fig. 34</figureCitation>
); and pubescence on the sides of the metaventrite not forming dense yellowish-brown band (
<figureCitation box="[997,1082,1159,1185]" captionStart="FIGURES 31–39" captionStartId="11.[151,264,1893,1917]" captionTargetBox="[205,1384,184,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-18@11.[202,1385,181,1869]" captionTargetPageId="11" captionText="FIGURES 31–39. Bebelis spp. 31–34) B. skillmani sp. nov., holotype male: 31) Dorsal habitus; 32) Ventral habitus; 33) Lateral habitus; 34) Head, frontal view. 35–36) B. cuprina (Belon, 1903), male from Brazil (Entre Rios, no state reported): 35) Dorsal habitus; 36) Lateral habitus. 37–38) B. cuprina, male from Brazil (Acre, Rio Branco): 37) Lateral habitus; 38) Head, frontal view. 39) B. cuprina, holotype, dorsal habitus, by Jesus Santiago Moure." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886414" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886414/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Fig. 32</figureCitation>
). In 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Belon" baseAuthorityYear="1903" box="[1134,1253,1159,1184]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cuprina">
<emphasis box="[1134,1253,1159,1184]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">B. cuprina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, the white setae on dorsal surface are sparse, fine, and decumbent, anterior and posterior white pubescent bands on the pronotum aligned, central area of the anterior half of the pronotum without white pubescent bands and maculae, lower eye lobes longer than genae (
<figureCitation box="[432,516,1267,1293]" captionStart="FIGURES 31–39" captionStartId="11.[151,264,1893,1917]" captionTargetBox="[205,1384,184,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-18@11.[202,1385,181,1869]" captionTargetPageId="11" captionText="FIGURES 31–39. Bebelis spp. 31–34) B. skillmani sp. nov., holotype male: 31) Dorsal habitus; 32) Ventral habitus; 33) Lateral habitus; 34) Head, frontal view. 35–36) B. cuprina (Belon, 1903), male from Brazil (Entre Rios, no state reported): 35) Dorsal habitus; 36) Lateral habitus. 37–38) B. cuprina, male from Brazil (Acre, Rio Branco): 37) Lateral habitus; 38) Head, frontal view. 39) B. cuprina, holotype, dorsal habitus, by Jesus Santiago Moure." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886414" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886414/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Fig. 38</figureCitation>
), and pubescence on the sides of the metaventrite forming dense yellowish-brown band (
<figureCitation box="[223,309,1303,1329]" captionStart="FIGURES 31–39" captionStartId="11.[151,264,1893,1917]" captionTargetBox="[205,1384,184,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-18@11.[202,1385,181,1869]" captionTargetPageId="11" captionText="FIGURES 31–39. Bebelis spp. 31–34) B. skillmani sp. nov., holotype male: 31) Dorsal habitus; 32) Ventral habitus; 33) Lateral habitus; 34) Head, frontal view. 35–36) B. cuprina (Belon, 1903), male from Brazil (Entre Rios, no state reported): 35) Dorsal habitus; 36) Lateral habitus. 37–38) B. cuprina, male from Brazil (Acre, Rio Branco): 37) Lateral habitus; 38) Head, frontal view. 39) B. cuprina, holotype, dorsal habitus, by Jesus Santiago Moure." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886414" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886414/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Fig. 37</figureCitation>
). 
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva, 2022" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2022" box="[331,525,1303,1329]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="skillmani" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[331,525,1303,1329]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Bebelis skillmani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[534,626,1303,1329]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[534,626,1303,1329]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
differs from 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Breuning" authorityYear="1942" box="[780,975,1303,1329]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pseudolignosa">
<emphasis box="[780,975,1303,1329]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">B. pseudolignosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation box="[992,1122,1303,1329]" captionStart="FIGURES 16–25" captionStartId="6.[151,264,1847,1871]" captionTargetBox="[205,1382,184,1822]" captionTargetId="figure-24@6.[205,1383,181,1823]" captionTargetPageId="6" captionText="FIGURES 16–25. Bebelis spp. 16–20) B. nearnsi sp. nov., holotype male: 16) Dorsal habitus; 17) Ventral habitus; 18) Lateral habitus; 19) Head, frontal view; 20) Lower eye lobe, lateral view. 21–23) B. pseudolignosa Breuning, 1942, female from Argentina (Salta, Rosario de Lerma): 21) Lower eye lobe, lateral view; 22) Dorsal habitus; 23) Lateral habitus. 24) B. pseudolignosa, holotype, by Jesus Santiago Moure. 25) Dorcasta prolongata Fisher, 1947 (= B. lignea (Bates, 1866)), holotype male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886408" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886408/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Figs 21–24</figureCitation>
) mainly by the presence of erect white setae on the elytra (absent in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Breuning" authorityYear="1942" box="[615,809,1339,1365]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pseudolignosa">
<emphasis box="[615,809,1339,1365]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">B. pseudolignosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), and the elytral apex not projected at outer angle (projected in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Breuning" authorityYear="1942" box="[254,447,1375,1401]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pseudolignosa">
<emphasis box="[254,447,1375,1401]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">B. pseudolignosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>