<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280270" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120208" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280270" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="F759D52780DB25925C41AA1902EEDDA1" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys rubigus Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="694" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="693" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280270" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120208" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280270" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F759D52780DB25925C41AA1902EEDDA1" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F759D52780DB25925C41AA1902EEDDA1" lastPageNumber="694" pageNumber="693">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="693">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155873" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys rubigus Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys rubigus Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="693" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rubigus">Strumigenys rubigus Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="694" pageNumber="693">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 2.9, HL 0.63, HW 0.48, CI 76, ML 0.32, MI 50, SL 0.40, SI 83, PW 0.34, AL 0.71. Characters of scotti-complex. Mandibles in full-face view with outer margins shallowly and evenly convex, the width gradually decreasing from near the base to the apicodorsal tooth. Upper scrobe margin evenly and shallowly convex in fullface view, not bordered by a rim or flange, the eyes visible. Maximum diameter of eye slightly smaller than maximum width of scape, with 3 - 4 ommatidia in longest row. Scape short and stout, shallowly and gently curved; hairs on leading edge spatulate or spoonshaped. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with curved narrow spatulate to spoon-shaped ground-pilosity, the upper scrobe margin fringed with hairs which are the same shape and size as those on the dorsum. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate hair (absent on left humerus of holotype). Mesonotum with 1 pair of erect clavate hairs, located at anterior margin; shorter hairs which are curved toward the midline present posterior to this pair. Propodeum with 2 pairs of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior ofpropodeal spines. Dorsal alitrunk with ground-pilosity as on head. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline very shallowly convex anteriorly and more or less flat posteriorly; posterior portion of mesonotum only slightly depressed below the anterior margin of propodeum. Anterior mesonotum without a carina above mesothoracic spiracle. Propodeal tooth broadly triangular, lamellate, pointed apically, and subtended by a moderate lamella. Alitrunk dorsum densely reticulate-punctate. Side of alitrunk mostly with punctate sculpture, except for katepisternum which is smooth and shiny. Postpetiole disc smooth and shining. In profile the petiole with a straight ventral spongiform strip that is slightly less deep than maximum diameter of eye. Postpetiole with moderately developed ventral spongiform lobes. Basigastral costulae arising on each side of a narrow, central clear area. Dorsal surfaces of petiole, postpetiole and gaster with standing clavate to remiform hairs. First gastral sternite, including anterior half, with numerous short suberect filiform hairs. Colour light brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="694">Holotype worker, Madagascar: Prov. Toamasina, F. C. Andrianantantely, 18 Â° 41.7 ' S, 48 Â° 48.8 ' E, 530 m., 4 - 10. xii. 1998, ex rotten log, rainforest, # 49 - 2 (H. J. Ratsirarson) (MCZ).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="694">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155873" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys rubigus Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys rubigus Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="694" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rubigus">S. rubigus</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from other species in the scotti-complex which have the dorsum of petiole node reticulate-punctate by having the following combination of characters:
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="694">1 Mesonotum with only a single pair of erect hairs, located at anterior margin; shorter decumbent hairs may be present posterior to this pair.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="694">2 In full-face view hairs on upper scrobe margin decumbent and sharply bent at basal third, not projecting well beyond the scrobe margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="694">3 Anterior half of first gastral sternite with numerous short suberect hairs.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>