<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bcdbe5f4-2f0e-4240-8727-64b6c91db94a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886268" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-591-1" ID-ZBK="DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-591-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 591" ModsDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" checkinTime="1463833188709" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Monckton, Spencer K." docDate="2016" docId="614148BC4C43B1C77BE9149999874363" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 591: 1-144" docOrigin="ZooKeys 591" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" docTitle="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) mavida Toro &amp; Moldenke 1979" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="77" masterDocId="FFFED84DD544452EFFC446356171FFFD" masterDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" masterLastPageNumber="144" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="70" pageNumber="71" updateTime="1643492814039" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Monckton, Spencer K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>591</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>144</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-591-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886268" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:614148BC4C43B1C77BE9149999874363" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/614148BC4C43B1C77BE9149999874363" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="70" pageNumber="71">
<subSubSection pageId="70" pageNumber="71" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="70" pageNumber="71">
<pageBreakToken pageId="70" pageNumber="71" start="start">Taxon</pageBreakToken>
classification Animalia Hymenoptera Colletidae
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="70" pageNumber="71" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="70" pageNumber="71">
<taxonomicName authority="Toro &amp; Moldenke, 1979" authorityName="Toro &amp; Moldenke" authorityYear="1979" class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) mavida" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="70" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mavida" subGenus="Heteroediscelis">Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) mavida Toro &amp; Moldenke, 1979</taxonomicName>
Figs 5A; 6C; 9
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
; 21B; 23A; 24
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–D">C-D</normalizedToken>
; 41
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–J">A-J</normalizedToken>
; 49
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="71" pageNumber="72" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="71" pageNumber="72">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola mavida" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="71" pageNumber="72" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mavida">
<pageBreakToken pageId="71" pageNumber="72" start="start">Chilicola</pageBreakToken>
mavida
</taxonomicName>
Toro &amp; Moldenke, 1979: 122-124 (male holotype, female allotype, AMNH [examined]). 
<bibRefCitation author="Michener, CD" journalOrPublisher="Scientific Papers, Natural History Museum, The University of Kansas" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" pagination="1 - 47" title="The Bee Genus Chilicola in the Tropical Andes, with Observations on Nesting Biology and a Phylogenetic Analysis of the Subgenera (Hymenoptera: Colletidae, Xeromelissinae)." url="10.5962/bhl.title.8449" volume="26" year="2002">Michener 2002</bibRefCitation>
: 5-7 (phylogeny). 
<bibRefCitation author="Packer, L" journalOrPublisher="Systematic Entomology" pageId="125" pageNumber="126" pagination="72 - 96" title="Phylogeny and classification of the Xeromelissinae (Hymenoptera: Apoidea, Colletidae) with special emphasis on the genus Chilicola." url="10.1111/j.1365-3113.2007.00398.x" volume="33" year="2008">Packer 2008</bibRefCitation>
: 77. Montalva and Ruz 2010: 28 (checklist). 
<bibRefCitation author="Moure, JS" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="125" pageNumber="126" title="Catalogue of Bees (Hymenoptera, Apoidea) in the Neotropical Region - online version" url="http://www.moure.cria.org.br/catalogue" year="2012">Moure et al. 2012</bibRefCitation>
(catalogue). 
<bibRefCitation author="Monckton, SK" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of Zoological Nomenclature" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" pagination="234 - 236" title="Case 3670: Chilicolavicugna Toro &amp; Moldenke, 1979 (Insecta, Hymenoptera, COLLETIDAE): proposed replacement of the holotype by a neotype." volume="71" year="2014">Monckton 2014</bibRefCitation>
: 234. 
<bibRefCitation author="Ascher, JS" journalOrPublisher="Annals of the Missouri Botanical Garden" pageId="122" pageNumber="123" title="Discover Life Bee Species Guide and World Checklist (Hymenoptera: Apoidea: Anthophila)" url="http://www.discoverlife.org/mp/20q?guide=Apoidea_species" year="2015">Ascher and Pickering 2015</bibRefCitation>
(checklist).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="71" pageNumber="72" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="71" pageNumber="72">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="71" pageNumber="72">
Males are diagnosable by the combination of first flagellomere longer than wide (≥1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
), malar space longer than clypeal lateral (1.05
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.1×">-1.1x</normalizedToken>
), and S1 process with anterior apical angle acute in lateral view. Females are diagnosable by the combination of malar space subequal in length to the clypeal lateral (0.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1×">-1x</normalizedToken>
) and leg colouration as follows: apicodorsal spot on mesotibia yellow-brown, apicodorsal rim of metafemur yellow, wide basal ring of metatibia yellow, posterior apical rim of metatibia yellow-brown. Females of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola curvapeligrosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="71" pageNumber="72" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="curvapeligrosa">Chilicola curvapeligrosa</taxonomicName>
are most similar, but have darker leg colouration (following parts brown: apicodorsal spot on mesotibia, apicodorsal rim of metafemur, basidorsal spot on metatibia; apex of metatibia black-brown).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="75" lastPageNumber="76" pageId="71" pageNumber="72" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="71" pageNumber="72">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="71" pageNumber="72">Male. Length 5.3-5.8mm, forewing length 3.4-3.5mm, head width 1.1-1.2mm, thorax width 1.1-1.2mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.13mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="71" pageNumber="72">Colouration: Black-brown, following parts yellow: labrum; clypeus except broadly dark along epistomal suture; lower paraocular area, extending ~1OD above transverse portion of epistomal suture and not reaching lower tangent of antennal socket; apicoventral spot on scape; apicoventral surface of pedicel; protrochanter apical rim posteriorly; apex of profemur broadly on anterior surface, narrowly on posterior surface; protibia except dark medioventrally; probasitarsus dorsally, at least in basal half; apex of mesofemur broadly on anterior surface, narrowly on posterior surface; broad basal and apical rings on mesotibia, the latter widened to apical half anteriorly; at least basoventral spot on mesobasitarsus; apicoventral rim of metacoxa and metatrochanter, the latter sometimes yellow-brown; narrow apical ring on metafemur; metatibia in basal one-third, in apical quarter of anterior surface, apical one-third of posterior surface and along ventral varina, yellow colouration continuous along ventral surface, sometimes continuous or nearly so along dorsal surface; metabasitarsus in basal one-third dorsally, basal two-thirds ventrally; anterior spot on tegula; apex of T7. Ventral surface of flagellum yellow-brown, flagellomeres suffused with brown basally. Apical half of prodistitarsus and apical one-third of mesodistitarsus brown. Posterior metatibial carina black. Metasoma black, T1-T6 marginal zones translucent yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="72" lastPageNumber="73" pageId="71" pageNumber="72">
Pubescence: White, hairs generally short (0.5OD) and sparse, not especially plumose; on lower paraocular area and around antennal base moderately long and moderately dense (1OD); genal beard long and dense (0.5-3OD) longest at midlength; discs of mesoscutum, scutellum, and metanotum mostly bare, few short hairs (0.5OD), longer and denser toward lateral margin as follows: mesoscutum (0.5-1OD), scutellum (1-2OD) also on posterior margin, longest posteromedially, metanotum (≤2OD); 
<pageBreakToken pageId="72" pageNumber="73" start="start">propodeal</pageBreakToken>
hairs moderately long and dense dorsolaterally (0.5-1.5OD); T1-T3 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD); S2 hairs long and dense (1.5OD basolaterad, 0.5OD distilaterad, shorter mesad).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="73" pageNumber="74">
<pageBreakToken pageId="73" pageNumber="74" start="start">Surface</pageBreakToken>
sculpture: Microsculpture imbricate, integument generally dull; punctures generally small and deep. Clypeus and lower paraocular area moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) except clypeus irregularly punctate in upper half (i=1-3d); supraclypeal area irregularly punctate (i=1-4d) densely punctate toward lateral margin (i≤d); frontal area very densely punctate (i≤0.5d), densely punctate around ocelli (i≤d); ocellocular space densely punctate adjacent to compound eye (i≤d) becoming impunctate adjacent to lateral ocellus; vertexal area rugose and very densely punctate (i≤0.5d); scape shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) densely punctate apicoventrally (i≤d); genal area microstriate and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); hypostomal area weakly imbricate to glossy apically and densely punctate (i=d); pronotum densely punctate (i=0.5-1d), lateral surface coarsely imbricate; mesoscutum densely punctate (i=0.5-1d) except moderately densely punctate laterally (i=1-2d); scutellum moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) punctures crowded around median (i≤d); mesepisternum irregularly punctate, sparse below scrobe (i=2-3d), sparser anterior of episternal groove (i≥3d), impunctate just dorsad of scrobe, otherwise moderately dense on hypoepimeral area (i=1-2d); metanotum moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) punctures crowded around median and anteriorly (i≤0.5d); metepisternum densely punctate (i≤d) distinctly longitudinally striate anterodorsally; metapostnotum rugose, fewer transverse lineations posteriorly; propodeum coarsely imbricate, rugulose posteriorly, moderately densely punctate throughout (i=1-2d); T1-T5 coarsely imbricate; T1 sparsely punctate basally (i≥2d) moderately densely punctate apically (i=1-2d); T2-T5 moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); T6 moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) and coarsely imbricate posteriorly; T7 sparsely puncticulate; marginal zones of terga weakly imbricate and shiny, punctate to impunctate at margins.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="74" lastPageNumber="75" pageId="73" pageNumber="74">
Structure: Labrum 2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (23:10); malar space subequal in length to clypeal lateral (9:8.5); LOT at level of anterior tentorial pits; clypeus subequal in length to maximum width in frontal view (31:30) extending for more than half of its length beyond LOT; median longitudinal groove present on clypeus, weak apically; subantennal sutures ~1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as the shortest distance between them (17:12); IAD ~2.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
AOD (13:6); scape 2.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (24:10); pedicel shorter than wide (8:9); F1 longer than wide (10:8.5); F2 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F1 and shorter than F3 (F2:F3 - 13:14); UOD ~1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 50:54:35); frontal line carinate in lower two-fifths, flat just below median ocellus for a length of ~1OD, otherwise roughly defined; MOC subequal to width of head (89:90); OOC ~0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (11:18); genal area ~0.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as compound eye in lateral view (17:33); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 63:23:9:15; probasitarsus 3.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (26:8); length of prodistitarsus subequal to that of preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V - 7:5:5:16); metafemur ~1.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (70:37); summit of metatibial ventral convexity rounded and near tibial apex; metatibia ~1.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (56:31); in apical view apical lamina of metatibia broad and thick, length 0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
OD (8:10); ventral metatibial carina bowed ventrad and absent basally, originating at midpoint of weakly sigmoid posterior carina; metabasitarsus ~3.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (43:12); S1 process apical surface with longitudinal median 
<pageBreakToken pageId="74" pageNumber="75" start="start">ridge</pageBreakToken>
, in lateral view anterior and posterior margins convergent apically and median ridge projecting posteriorly from apex. S7 apodemal arm sclerotized margin terminating laterally at arm midlength; ventral lobe narrow, almost linear; dorsal lobe roughly triangular, wide at base and narrow apically, with row of setae long basally and shorter apically; apex of disc disinctly emarginate. S8 lateral process ~0.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, anteromedial sclerotized margin following marginal contour. Gonobase apicoventral truncate process biconvex and distinctly notched by ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of one convexity.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Female. Length 4.2-4.8mm, forewing length 2.6-3.0mm, head width 1.0mm, thorax width 1.0-1.1mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.10mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Colouration: Black to black-brown except as follows: mandible with yellow basal spot, translucent yellow in apical half except apex translucent brown; antenna variable (scape entirely dark; pedicel to F2 dark, or apicoventral rim brown; ventral surface of F3 to penultimate flagellomere yellow-brown, narrowing basally on F3, flagellomeres suffused with brown basally; terminal flagellomere yellow-brown in basal half, brown in apical half). Following parts yellow: dorsal surface of protibia; apical two-thirds of prodistitarsus, sometimes yellow-brown; narrow basal ring on mesotibia; apicodorsal rim on metafemur; wide basal ring on metatibia, narrow ventrally; anterior spot on tegula. Following parts yellow-brown: apicodorsal spot on mesotibia; posterior apical rim on metatibia. Apical half of mesodistitarsus brown. Metasoma black, T1-T5 yellow-brown beyond premarginal line to translucent yellow at margins.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Pubescence: As in male except as follows: clypeal hairs short and sparse (0.5OD); genal beard sparse (0.5-2.5OD); discs of mesoscutum and scutellum with sparse short hairs (≤0.5OD), longer and denser toward lateral margin of mesoscutum (0.5-1OD), and toward lateral and posterior margins of scutellum (1-1.5OD) longest posteromedially; scopae on metafemur and metatibia (1-1.5OD); T1-T3 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD); S1 hairs long and moderately dense (≤2OD); S2 scopal hairs (1-2OD).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Surface sculpture: As in male except as follows: clypeus sparsely punctate (i=2-3d) moderately densely punctate toward lateral margin (i=1-2d); supraclypeal area irregularly punctate (i=1-2d) densely punctate toward lateral margin (i≤d); lower paraocular area densely punctate (i=d); frontal area densely punctate (i≤d), moderately densely punctate around ocelli (i=1-2d); vertexal area moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); scape shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); genal area weakly imbricate and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); hypostomal area weakly imbricate to glossy apically and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); mesoscutum and scutellum densely punctate; metanotum moderately densely punctate (i=0.5-2d); metepisternum densely punctate (i≤d) distinctly longitudinally striate anterodorsally (weak in some specimens); metapostnotum rugose, fewer transverse lineations posteriorly (posterior half to two-thirds longitudinally carinate in some specimens); propodeum moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); T1-T5 moderately puncticulate; T6 moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d).</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="75" lastPageNumber="76" pageId="74" pageNumber="75">
Structure: Labrum 2.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (20:8); malar space subequal in length to clypeal lateral (6:6.5); LOT at level of anterior tentorial pits; clypeus ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width in frontal view (29:26) extending for approximately half of its length 
<pageBreakToken pageId="75" pageNumber="76" start="start">beyond</pageBreakToken>
LOT; median longitudinal groove weak on clypeus; subantennal sutures subequal in length to the shortest distance between them (11:11); IAD ~1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
AOD (11.5:8); scape ~3.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (22:6.5); pedicel longer than wide (8:6.5); F1 longer than wide (6.5:5.5); F2 shorter than F1 and shorter than F3 (F2:F3 - 4:5); UOD ~1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 44:47:34); frontal line carinate in lower third, flat above; MOC ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as width of head (77:71); OOC ~0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (11:16); genal area ~0.65
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as eye in lateral view (15:23); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 51:20:9:12.5; probasitarsus ~3.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (21:6.5); length of prodistitarsus ~1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
that of preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V - 4:4:3:14); metafemur ~2.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (43:15); metatibia ~4.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (53:11.5); metabasitarsus 4.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (34:8).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
Figure 41. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola mavida" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mavida">Chilicola mavida</taxonomicName>
: A male habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm B male head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm C female habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm D female head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm E male metatibia, posterior view, scale bar 0.25 mm F male S1 process, lateral view†, scale bar 0.25 mm G male S1 process, apical view, scale bar 0.25 mm H male S7, scale bar 0.25 mm I male S8, scale bar 0.25 mm J male genital capsule, scale bar 0.25 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="75" pageNumber="76" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">Material studied</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
(21 males &amp; 19 females): Holotype (male): Region IV, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Baños">Banos</normalizedToken>
del Toro, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-29.838">S 29.838°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.026">W 70.026 °</geoCoordinate>
, 3202m, i.1970, Toro (AMNH); Allotype (female): same data as holotype (AMNH); Region IV: one paratype male, same data as holotype (AMNH); five paratype males, Laguna Dam, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-30.206">S 30.206°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.042">W 70.042°</geoCoordinate>
, 3170m, 5.xii.1950, Ross &amp; Michelbacher (AMNH); one paratype male, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Río">Rio</normalizedToken>
Laguna, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-30.191">S 30.191°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.047">W 70.047°</geoCoordinate>
, 3000m, i.1970, Dazarola (AMNH); one female, same locality as holotype, 1970, collector unknown (AMNH); one male, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Río">Rio</normalizedToken>
Laguna, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-30.191">S 30.191°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.047">W 70.047°</geoCoordinate>
, 3000m, 1970, H. Toro (AMNH); one male, same locality, 8.i.1970, H. Toro (PUCV); one male, CH-41 km 165, S of La Laguna, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-30.1479">S 30.1479°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.0518">W 70.0518°</geoCoordinate>
, 2767m, 15.xii.2013, L. Packer (PCYU); one male, 41-CH km km 171, N of Emb La Laguna, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-30.1787">S 30.1787°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.0473">W 70.0473°</geoCoordinate>
, 2942m, 15.xii.2013, J. Postlethwaite, CCDB-19989 D05 (PCYU); two females, W of Junta Toro, 41-CH km 146, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-29.9675">S 29.9675°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.1285">W 70.1285°</geoCoordinate>
, 1977m, 8.xi.2013, S. Monckton, pan traps, CCDB-19989 D01 // PCYU 0021694, CCDB-19989 D02 // PCYU 0021695 (PCYU); one male, 41-CH km, 137.8, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-29.967">S 29.9670°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.1936">W 70.1936</geoCoordinate>
, 800m, 8.xi.2013, S. Monckton, pan trap, CCDB-19989 B10 // PCYU 0021684 (PCYU); one male, E of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Vicuña">Vicuna</normalizedToken>
, 127.8 km, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-29.9777">S 29.9777°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.2293">W 70.2293°</geoCoordinate>
, 1711m, 12-19.ix.2010, L. Packer (PCYU); one female, Elqui Prov., Pangue, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-30.1539">S 30.1539°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.6639">W 70.6639°</geoCoordinate>
, 1686m, 11-30.ix.2004, A. Ugarte (PCYU); two males, Elqui: El Pangue, 24 km S of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Vicuña">Vicuna</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-30.168">S 30.168°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.663">W 70.663°</geoCoordinate>
, 1711m, 31.x.1992, Snyder &amp; Sharkov (AMNH); one male and one female, Elqui Prov., 26 km S of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Vicuña">Vicuna</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="555" value="-30.19">S 30.19°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.661">W 70.661°</geoCoordinate>
, 1691m, 29.x.1992, Rozen, Sharkov, Snyder (AMNH); three females, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Limarí">Limari</normalizedToken>
Prov., Las Mollacas, E Monte Patria, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-30.753">S 30.753°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.657">W 70.657°</geoCoordinate>
, 1142m, 13.x.1994, Rozen, Quinter, Ascher, on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Oxalidaceae" genus="Oxalis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Oxalis" order="Oxalidales" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Oxalis</taxonomicName>
(AMNH); Region V: one female, Portillo Aduanas, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-32.8304">S 32.8304°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.0905">W 70.0905°</geoCoordinate>
, 3210m, 10.i.2009, L. Packer, on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Hydrophyllaceae" genus="Phacelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Phacelia" order="Boraginales" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Phacelia</taxonomicName>
, CHI09-13-2-011 (PCYU); two males and six females, Portillo, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-32.8372">S 32.8372°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.1296">W 70.1296°</geoCoordinate>
, 2870m, 11.i.2009, L. Packer, on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Hydrophyllaceae" genus="Phacelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Phacelia" order="Boraginales" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Phacelia</taxonomicName>
, CHI09-13-1-003, CHI09-13-1-005, CHI09-13-1-004, CHI09-13-1-009 (PCYU); two females, same data (BBSL); two females, same data (CTMI); one female, same locality, 30.xii.2008, L. Packer, CHI09-2-1-018 (PCYU); one female, Portillo, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-32.8507">S 32.8507°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.1339">W 70.1339°</geoCoordinate>
, 2612m, 30.xii.2009, L. Packer, CHI09-2-2-031 (PCYU); one male and one female, same data, on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Lamiaceae" genus="Stachys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Stachys" order="Lamiales" pageId="75" pageNumber="76" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Stachys</taxonomicName>
, CHI09-2-2-039, CHI09-2-2-0398 (PCYU); one male, Guardia Vieja mountain, Aconcagua Prov., 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-32.904">S 32.904°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.272">W 70.272°</geoCoordinate>
, 1600m, 17.ix.1964, L. E. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
<pageBreakToken pageId="76" pageNumber="77" start="start">Variation</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Some females have a yellow-brown or yellow spot on the lower paraocular area below the anterior tentorial pit.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Central Andean Cordillera and upper Coquimban Desert, just extending into Southern Andean Cordillera, from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Baños">Banos</normalizedToken>
del Toro &amp; Embalse La Laguna west to El Pangue (Region IV) and south to Portillo (Region V); 1142-3210m a.s.l.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="ecology">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Collected on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Oxalidaceae" genus="Oxalis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Oxalis" order="Oxalidales" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Oxalis</taxonomicName>
L. (3 records), 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Hydrophyllaceae" genus="Phacelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Phacelia" order="Boraginales" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Phacelia</taxonomicName>
(9 records), and 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Lamiaceae" genus="Stachys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Stachys" order="Lamiales" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Stachys</taxonomicName>
L. (2 records). Recorded September to January.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>