<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C84168AD53FF7531CAB3A0A57F" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Diphyus amatorius" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="662" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>597</mods:start>
<mods:end>711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C84168AD53FF7531CAB3A0A57F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C84168AD53FF7531CAB3A0A57F" lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="662" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">
<subSubSection box="[178,601,738,760]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,601,738,760]" box="[178,601,738,760]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">
<heading box="[178,601,738,760]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,601,738,760]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">
<taxonomicName authority="(MULLER)" baseAuthorityName="MULLER" box="[178,492,738,760]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Diphyus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amatorius">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,376,738,760]" italics="true" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">Diphyus amatorius</emphasis>
(MÜLLER)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 10)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="63" pageNumber="660" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,924,778,876]" box="[178,745,778,798]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">
<taxonomicName authority="MULLER 1776" authorityName="MULLER" authorityYear="1776" box="[178,514,778,798]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amatorius">
<emphasis box="[178,377,778,798]" italics="true" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">Ichneumon amatorius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="MULLER F" box="[383,514,778,798]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" pagination="151 - 160" refId="ref60926" refString="MULLER F. (1776): Zoologiae Danicae prodromus, seu animalium Daniae et Norvegiae indigenarum characters, nomina et synonyma imprimis popularium. - Hafniae: 1 - 282 (Ichnneumon 151 - 160)." type="book chapter" year="1776">MÜLLER 1776</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Zool. Dan. prodr.: 151.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,924,778,876]" box="[178,902,804,824]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">
<taxonomicName authority=": WESMAEL 1844" authorityName="WESMAEL" authorityYear="1844" box="[178,535,804,824]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amatorius">
<emphasis box="[178,375,804,824]" italics="true" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">Amblyteles amatorius</emphasis>
: WESMAEL 1844
</taxonomicName>
- Nouv. Mém. Acad. Sc. Brux. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[826,849,804,824]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">18</emphasis>
: 123.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,924,778,876]" box="[178,924,830,850]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">
<taxonomicName authority=": PERKINS 1959" authorityName="PERKINS" authorityYear="1959" box="[178,519,830,850]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="amatorius">
<emphasis box="[178,375,830,850]" italics="true" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">Amblyteles amatorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="PERKINS J" box="[387,519,830,850]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" pagination="1 - 116" refId="ref61033" refString="PERKINS J. F. (1959 - 1960): Handbooks for the indentification of British insects. Hymenoptera: Ichneumonoidea. Ichneumonidae, key to subfamilies and Ichneumoninae-I. - Royal Entomological Society of London 7 (2): 1 - 116; 117 - 213." type="journal article" year="1959">PERKINS 1959</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Roy. Ent. Soc. London 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[753,764,830,850]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">7</emphasis>
,2 (aii): 193, 198.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,924,778,876]" box="[178,855,856,876]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">
<taxonomicName authority=": RASNITSYN 1981" authorityName="RASNITSYN" authorityYear="1981" box="[178,530,856,876]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Diphyus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armatorius">
<emphasis box="[178,360,856,876]" italics="true" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">Diphyus armatorius</emphasis>
: RASNITSYN 1981
</taxonomicName>
- Opr. Faun. SSSR 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[713,724,856,876]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">3</emphasis>
(3): 613, 616.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="662" pageId="63" pageNumber="660" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,292,893,915]" box="[178,292,893,915]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,1086,930,1069]" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, with 41-42 segments, moderately thick, first segment short, only 1,3 times longer than width at apex, with white annulus on segments (6)7-12, beyond white annulus only just flattened ventrally; already segment 3 square from lateral, other segments transverse. Flagellum almost 2 times shorter than the front wing and 3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,1086,1084,1604]" lastBlockId="64.[178,1085,219,416]" lastPageId="64" lastPageNumber="661" pageId="63" pageNumber="660">H e a d: Head contour from front quite slightly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, only 1,3 times wider than height; genae from front (malar space) 3,8 times shorter than height of an eye (0,3); head contour from above transverse, 2,2 times wider than length in middle and 1,6 times along an external contour, almost linearly narrowed backwards behind eyes. Vertex from lateral straightly sloping from hind borders of ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, in the middle 1,4 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye, parallel to hind margin of an eye, behind eyes from above rather slightly almost straightly narrowed behind eyes; occipital carina sharp all round, from above rather strongly roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina almost not visible from lateral, occipital carina meeting with hypostomal carina before base of mandible; abscissula 2 times shorter than mandible base width; malar space 1,2 times shorter than the mandible base width; mandibles normal, evenly narrowed from base to apex, upper tooth considerably longer than lower one; clypeus only just convex, 1,8 times wider than length, with straight front margin and distinctly expressed lateral corners, separated from face, by impression; clypeal foveae big, deep; labrum usually distinctly protrude from under clypeus, equal by breadth to front margin, roundlytriangular; middle field of face slightly elevated, narrow, in middle 2 times narrower than lateral fields; antennal cavities very deeply impressed, not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, laterally above antennal fossae without tubercles and with distinct interantennal tubercle; margins of antennal fossae rather slightly elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, slightly convex, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,3 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle practically not expressed. Surface of clypeus with big punctures, without microsculpture; upper part of face wrinklypunctured, lateral fields with big punctures; frons roughly wrinkly-punctured; temples densely punctured, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1086,431,980]" pageId="64" pageNumber="661">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum from above long with straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum deep, narrow; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp; pronotal base gradually curved; lateral surface of pronotum roughly-wrynkled in middle. Mesonotum only just convex, practically with equal length and width; notauli only in a form of very slight impressions at base; surface of mesonotum densely punctured, median lobe to slightly wrinkled, without microsculpture; axillary tongue developed, but weak; subalarum high, thick, not sharpened; speculum densely punctured; mesopleural fovea sharp, area around it narrow, deep; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs; mesopleurae at bottom with distinct but gradual bend; sternauli absent; lower part of mesopleurae at back part roughly wrinkly-punctured; scutellum from lateral moderately elevated above postscutellum, from above flat, laterally not carinated. Hind margin of metanotum with triangular projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral with angular break, length of horizontal part 1,7 times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum, with exception of costulae, sharp; basal area short and deep; area superomedia square; carinae of apical part of propodeum high; areae dentiparae at apices without teeth, but with strong lamelliform broadenings on theirs place; spiracles long, slit-shaped, along external contour 4 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum, including metapleurae, roughly wrinkly-punctured shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1085,996,1047]" pageId="64" pageNumber="661">L e g s: Long, stumpy. Hind coxae without scopa. Tibiae and tarsi of all legs with strong sparse spinules. Claws normal, sharply curved in middle.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1086,1062,1201]" pageId="64" pageNumber="661">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, almost symmetrical, external vein of apex longer than internal one; stigma normal, short, light; radial cell narrow, long, radius very slightly sinuous, almost straight; nervulus slightly postfurcal; ramulus expressed; all veins light, reddish-brown; membrane of wing yellowish. Front wing considerably longer than length of flagellum and shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1086,1217,1561]" pageId="64" pageNumber="661">A b d o m e n:Amblypygous, from above broadly-oval, tergite 7 from above only just visible; second tergite transverse, at apex 1,3 times wider than length; sheath of ovipositor not protrude. First tergite from lateral with gradual bend between petiolus and postpetiolus, from lateral sharply bordered by carinae and with strong transversal ribs between them; from above petiolus gradually but sharply broadened to postpetiolus; distance between spiracles many more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus distinctly elevated, 1,7 times wider than lateral fields, its surface longitudinally striated. Gastrocoeli small, square, only just impressed, short; thyridia small, distinct; lunulae small, but distinct; surface of second tergite up to apex very densely punctured by small superficial punctures, without microsculpture; tergites 3-4 densely superficially punctured by very small punctures, apical tergites shagreen. Hypopygium not compressed from sides; only sternites 2-3 with fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1085,1576,1598]" lastBlockId="65.[178,1085,219,299]" lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="662" pageId="64" pageNumber="661">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black with reach yellow-white pattern: internal orbits broadly, collar and hind corners of pronotum, tegulae, subalarum and scutellum completely, apical bands on tergites 2-6th and spot on 7th; tergite 2 of abdomen yellow-red; tibiae and tarsi of all the legs and apices of front and middle femora yellow-red.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,920,314,336]" box="[178,920,314,336]" pageId="65" pageNumber="662">
S i z e: Body length: 16,5 (13-17); front wing: 10,7; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[836,916,314,336]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.5" pageId="65" pageNumber="662" unit="mm" value="5.5">5,5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,254,352,374]" box="[178,254,352,374]" pageId="65" pageNumber="662">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,1085,389,616]" pageId="65" pageNumber="662">Flagellum of male thin, bristle-shaped with only just visible tyloides (almost not expressed), black, often rust-colored ventrally, without white annulus; labrum rounded, far protrude from under clypeus; hypopygium apically with triangularly extended and pointed central part. Yellow coloration more expanded: face, as a rule, completely, frontal orbits, collar and hind corners of pronotum, tegulae, subalarum, scutellum, second and third tergites of abdomen entirely, narrow apical bands on forth and fifth, rarely on seventh; most part of femora of front and middle legs, tibiae and tarsi of all the legs with exception of darkened apices of hind tibiae yellow.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>