<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C84149AD32FF753774B537A35B" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Limerodes arctiventris" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="629" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>597</mods:start>
<mods:end>711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C84149AD32FF753774B537A35B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C84149AD32FF753774B537A35B" lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="629" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">
<subSubSection box="[178,586,1116,1138]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="30.[178,586,1116,1138]" box="[178,586,1116,1138]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">
<heading box="[178,586,1116,1138]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,586,1116,1138]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">
<taxonomicName authority="(BOIE)" baseAuthorityName="BOIE" box="[178,488,1116,1138]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Limerodes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="arctiventris">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,412,1116,1138]" italics="true" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">Limerodes arctiventris</emphasis>
(BOIE)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 1)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="627" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="30.[178,987,1156,1228]" box="[178,792,1156,1176]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">
<taxonomicName authority="BOIE 1841" authorityName="BOIE" authorityYear="1841" box="[178,492,1156,1176]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="arctiventris">
<emphasis box="[178,390,1156,1176]" italics="true" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">Ichneumon arctiventris</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="BOIE F" box="[395,492,1156,1176]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" pagination="315 - 324" refId="ref59970" refString="BOIE F. (1841): Entomologische Beitrage. - Naturhistorisk Tidskrift. 3: 315 - 324." type="journal article" year="1841">BOIE 1841</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Naturh. Tidsskr. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[668,679,1156,1176]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">3</emphasis>
: 319,,.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="30.[178,987,1156,1228]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">
<taxonomicName authority=": WESMAEL 1844" authorityName="WESMAEL" authorityYear="1844" box="[178,568,1182,1202]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Limerodes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ophioniventris">
<emphasis box="[178,410,1182,1202]" italics="true" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">Limerodes ophioniventris</emphasis>
: WESMAEL 1844
</taxonomicName>
- Nouv. Mém. Acad. Sci., 
<collectingRegion box="[818,905,1182,1202]" country="Belgium" name="Region de Bruxelles-Capitale" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">Bruxelles</collectingRegion>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[912,935,1182,1202]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">18</emphasis>
: 112. 
<taxonomicName authority=": RASNITSYN 1981" authorityName="RASNITSYN" authorityYear="1981" box="[178,554,1208,1228]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Limerodes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="arctiventris">
<emphasis box="[178,384,1208,1228]" italics="true" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">Limerodes arctiventris</emphasis>
: RASNITSYN 1981
</taxonomicName>
- Opr. Faun. SSSR 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[739,750,1208,1228]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">3</emphasis>
(3): 623.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="629" pageId="30" pageNumber="627" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="30.[178,292,1245,1267]" box="[178,292,1245,1267]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="30.[178,1086,1282,1450]" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, with 45 segments, not flattened ventrally and practically not widened beyond middle, with traces of white annulus on segments 8- 10(11) dorsally; first segment approximately 3 times longer than the width at apex, segment 13 square from lateral; segments of flagellum distinctly differentiated; flagellum of dried samples coiled. Flagellum 1,2 times longer than the front wing and 1,6 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="30.[178,1085,1465,1601]" lastBlockId="31.[178,1086,218,809]" lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="628" pageId="30" pageNumber="627">H e a d: Head contour from front slightly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, only 1,1 times wider than height; malar space from front 4,3 times shorter than height of an eye (0,2); temples from front visible some higher of eye’s base, genae from front narrowed almost straightly; head contour from above thick, 1,9 times wider than length in middle, slightly roundly narrowed backwards. Vertex from lateral rather straightly sloping from hind border of ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, in the middle equal to longitudinal diameter of an eye, from middle parallel to hind margin of an eye, from above slightly, roundly narrowed behind eyes (convex); occipital carina sharp all round, from above slightly roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral, occipital carina meeting with hypostomal carina before base of mandible; abscissula 1,3 times shorter than mandible base width; malar space equal to mandible base width; mandibles rather broad, upper tooth considerably longer than lower one, impression between teeth narrow; clypeus only just convex, 3,2 times wider than length, with slightly emarginated and thinned front margin, middle denticle and distinctly expressed lateral corners, slightly impressed at apex, separated from middle field of face by slight broad impression; clypeal foveae big, deep; labrum short, triangle, narrower than front margin of clypeus; middle field of face distinctly elevated, narrower than lateral fields, separated by slight impressions; antennal cavities not big, moderately impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, without tubercles laterally and with slight interantennal tubercle; margins of antennal fossae distinctly elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, distinctly convex, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,4 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle almost not expressed. Surface of face and clypeus with exception of apical part in middle with big punctures, upper part of face wrinkly-punctured between middle and lateral fields, face and clypeus shining without microsculpture; frons punctured, temples smoothly, superficially punctured, polished.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="31.[178,1085,824,1529]" pageId="31" pageNumber="628">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum rather long, from above with rounded front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum rather deep; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp, high; pronotal base sharply and gradually curved; lateral surface of pronotum wrinklypunctured, polished. Mesonotum slightly convex, 1,2 times longer than width; notauli only in a form of only just visible impressions at base; lateral furrow of mesonotum behind tegulae very deep; surface of mesonotum densely punctured, punctures almost merge, with microsculpture between punctures, with slight shine; axillary tongue not developed; prepectal carina upwardly not reach front margin of mesopleurae; subalarum high, narrow, but not sharpened; speculum smooth on the larger part, shining; mesopleural fovea sharp, area around it narrowly impressed; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs in lower third; mesopleurae at bottom without distinct bend; sternauli in a form of very slight impressions up to middle of mesopleurae; mesopleurae densely punctured by big punctures, shining; scutellum slightly elevated above postscutellum, from above almost flat, gradually slanted to postscutellum, not carinated laterally. Hind margin of metanotum with triangular projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral convex without distinct break, length of horizontal part 1,3 times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum except costulae and lateral carinae of area posteromedia, sharp; basal area deep; area superomedia indistinctly hexagonal, elongated, narrowed and rounded in front; costulae weak, situated in middle or behind middle of area superomedia; external carina of area dentipara parallel to metapleural carina, apices of areae dentiparae without teeth; spiracles long, narrow, along external contour 2,7 times longer than width. Horizontal surface of propodeum, except area superomedia, with big punctures, shining; surface of area superomedia with very slight indistinct wrinkling; metapleurae densely punctured by big punctures; propodeum shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="31.[178,718,1545,1567]" box="[178,718,1545,1567]" pageId="31" pageNumber="628">L e g s: Slender. Claws gradually uniformly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="31.[178,1085,1582,1604]" lastBlockId="32.[178,1086,219,299]" lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="629" pageId="31" pageNumber="628">W i n g s: Areolet big, pentagonal, with wide base, symmetrical; stigma narrow, light; radial cell narrow, long; radius very slightly sinuous; nervulus postfurcal; ramulus only just marked; all veins moderately dark to light in hind wing; membrane of wing hyaline. Front wing shorter than length of flagellum and considerably less than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1086,314,717]" pageId="32" pageNumber="629">A b d o m e n:Amblypygous, from above narrow, long, compressed from sides, tergite 7 from above protrude on length of scutellum; second tergite long, at apex 1,7 times narrower than length in middle; sheath of ovipositor visible from above. First tergite from lateral with gradual transform of petiolus to postpetiolus, narrow at base, from lateral not bordered by carinae; from above petiolus gradually widened to rounded postpetiolus; distance between spiracles 1,5 times more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus not expressed, only just marked at apex; surface of first tergite not sculptured, polished. Gastrocoeli in a form of indistinct narrow longitudinal lateral impression, sometimes with thyridia in a form of only just marked rounded punctiform impressions at theirs apices; lunulae big, in a form of unsculptured impression in the middle of lateral surface of tergite; surface of second tergite densely punctured by superficial punctures, polished; other tergites with very delicate superficial punctures, shining. Hypopygium from lateral with sharp apex, strongly compressed from sides; sternites, except fifth, strongly unsclerotized.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1085,732,842]" pageId="32" pageNumber="629">C o l o r a t i o n: Head black with narrowly reddish frontal orbits; thorax entirely black except brownish collar and white scutellum; tergites 1-2 of abdomen and tergite 3, except apex, red, other tergites black or brownish black; legs, except coxae and trochanters 1, red, hind femora and tibiae darkened at apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,822,857,879]" box="[178,822,857,879]" pageId="32" pageNumber="629">S i z e: Body length: 12,5; front wing: 6,9; flagellum: 8,0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,254,895,917]" box="[178,254,895,917]" pageId="32" pageNumber="629">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1086,932,1100]" pageId="32" pageNumber="629">Flagellum of male with long row of narrow bacilliform tyloides on segments 6-16(17), very slightly ribbed on side opposite tyloides, without white annulus, brownish-red; scutellum more elevated; hypopygium with short apical process. White coloration more rich: scapus ventrally, mandibles, labrum, face entirely, frontal orbits up to middle, collar of pronotum, tegulae, subalarum, scutellum and postscutellum. Tergite 4 of abdomen red on the larger part. Front coxae with white spot; hind femora darkened on the larger part.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>