<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C84163AD24FF7531AAB05AA33A" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Spilichneumon occisor" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="54" lastPageNumber="651" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>597</mods:start>
<mods:end>711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C84163AD24FF7531AAB05AA33A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C84163AD24FF7531AAB05AA33A" lastPageId="54" lastPageNumber="651" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<subSubSection box="[178,650,642,664]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,650,642,664]" box="[178,650,642,664]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<heading box="[178,650,642,664]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,650,642,664]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<taxonomicName authority="(FABRICIUS)" baseAuthorityName="FABRICIUS" box="[178,554,642,664]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Spilichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="occisor">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,417,642,664]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">Spilichneumon occisor</emphasis>
(FABRICIUS)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 7)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="52" pageNumber="649" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,828,682,806]" box="[178,766,682,702]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<taxonomicName authority="FABRICIUS 1793" authorityName="FABRICIUS" authorityYear="1793" box="[178,508,682,702]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="occisor">
<emphasis box="[178,352,682,702]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">Ichneumon occisor</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="FABRICIUS J" box="[357,508,682,702]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" pagination="1 - 519" refId="ref60193" refString="FABRICIUS J. C. (1793): Entomologia systematica emendata et aucta. - 2: 1 - 519." type="journal article" year="1793">FABRICIUS 1793</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Entom. System. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[674,685,682,702]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">2</emphasis>
: 142,.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,828,682,806]" box="[178,724,708,728]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<taxonomicName authority=": FABRICIUS 1804" authorityName="FABRICIUS" authorityYear="1804" box="[178,540,708,728]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="occisorius">
<emphasis box="[178,378,708,728]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">Ichneumon occisorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="FABRICIUS J" box="[390,540,708,728]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" pagination="1 - 439" refId="ref60215" refString="FABRICIUS J. C. (1804): Systema Piezatorum. - Carolum Reichard, Brunsviga: 1 - 439." type="book chapter" year="1804">FABRICIUS 1804</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Syst. Piez: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[665,688,708,728]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">61</emphasis>
,.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,828,682,806]" box="[178,702,734,754]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<taxonomicName authority=": WESMAEL 1844" authorityName="WESMAEL" authorityYear="1844" box="[178,534,734,754]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="occisorius">
<emphasis box="[178,376,734,754]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">Amblyteles occisorius</emphasis>
: WESMAEL 1844
</taxonomicName>
- Tent.: 122,.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,828,682,806]" box="[178,787,760,780]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<taxonomicName authority=": THOMSON 1894" authorityName="THOMSON" authorityYear="1894" box="[178,568,760,780]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Spilichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="occisorius">
<emphasis box="[178,412,760,780]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">Spilichneumon occisorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="THOMSON C" box="[424,568,760,780]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" pagination="2080 - 2137" refId="ref61382" refString="THOMSON C. G. (1894): Anmarkningar ofver Ichneumoner sarskildt med hansyn till nagra af A. E. Holmgrens typer. - Opuscula Entomologica. Lund. 19: 2080 - 2137." type="journal article" year="1894">THOMSON 1894</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Opusc. Ent. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[700,723,760,780]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">19</emphasis>
: 2089.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,828,682,806]" box="[178,828,786,806]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
<taxonomicName authority=": RASNITSYN 1981" authorityName="RASNITSYN" authorityYear="1981" box="[178,556,786,806]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Spilichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="occisor">
<emphasis box="[178,386,786,806]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">Spilichneumon occisor</emphasis>
: RASNITSYN 1981
</taxonomicName>
- Opr. Faun. SSSR 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[737,748,786,806]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">3</emphasis>
(3): 622.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="54" lastPageNumber="651" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,292,823,845]" box="[178,292,823,845]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,1085,860,1029]" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped with 35-37 segments, moderately stout, first segment short, with equal length and width at apex from lateral, with weak white semiannulus on segments 8-11(12), not widened and only just visible flattened ventrally; all segments not longer than width. Segments of flagellum sharply differentiated. Coloration of flagellum mainly reddish-brown. Flagellum short, 2,1 times shorter than front wing and 3,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="52.[178,1086,1044,1593]" lastBlockId="53.[178,1086,219,533]" lastPageId="53" lastPageNumber="650" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">
H e a d: Head contour from front slightly and roundly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, 1,1 times wider than height; genae and temples visible almost up to middle of an eye, genae length (malar space) 5,5 times shorter than height of eye; head contour from above rounded, 1,8 times wider than length in middle and 1,7 times along an external contour, roundly narrowed behind eyes. Vertex from lateral straightly sloping from ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, 1,8 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye at middle, broadened downwards, from above behind eyes roundly narrowed; occipital carina sharp all round, from above broadly and roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina from lateral only just visible at very lower part, merged with occipital carina far from mandible base; abscissula long, 1,7 times shorter than mandible base width; genae above abscissula with impression; malar space 2 times shorter than mandible base width; mandibles strong, long and broad, narrowed in middle and broadened at the apical half (spatulate), at apex with flat broad teeth divided by rather narrow impression, lower tooth broader and longer than upper one; clypeus flat, slightly convex at base, sharply impressed relative to middle and lateral fields of face (similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH. There" authorityYear="1936" box="[748,966,1483,1505]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Bureschias" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="649" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[748,859,1483,1505]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="649">Bureschias</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
), 2,4 times wider than length with thinned front margin and slightly projected medially; clypeal foveae distinct; labrum rounded, slightly protrude from under clypeus with very long pubescence along front margin; middle and lateral fields overhang under clypeus (like 
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH. There" authorityYear="1936" box="[178,395,219,241]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Bureschias" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="53" pageNumber="650" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[178,289,219,241]" italics="true" pageId="53" pageNumber="650">Bureschias</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
); middle field strongly elevated, convex and separated from lateral fields by deep and broad impressions, 1,8 times wider than lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities very deep, not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, without lateral tubercles and with very strong and sharp tooth compressed from sides between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae rather strongly elevated above face surface; frons below front ocellus broadly impressed; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,5 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle expressed. Face and clypeus with big smoothed punctures, frons medially roughly wrinkly-punctured, temples with big smoothed punctures; surface of face without microsculpture. Frons, clypeus and lateral fields of face with long reddish-brown pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="53.[178,1087,549,1185]" pageId="53" pageNumber="650">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long with straight front margin (from above); transverse furrow of pronotum shallow, broad, not interrupted by keel; upper margin of pronotum not swollen, only slightly thickened above epomiae; epomiae sharp, high; pronotal base gradually curved. Mesonotum only just convex, 1,2 times longer than width; notauli only as a very slight impressions at the same base; surface of mesonotum finely punctured by smoothed punctures more densely at the base, without microsculpture, shining; axillary tongue only just expressed; prepectal carina in middle with a strong bend backwards so, that considerable part of epicnemiae visible from side; subalarum thick, not sharpened; speculum shining with sparse punctures; area of mesopleural fovea narrowly impressed; mesopleural suture straight, interrupted by weak smoothed ribs; mesopleurae at bottom without sharp bend; sternauli broadly and slightly impressed up to middle of mesopleurae; lover half of mesopleurae sharply longitudinally striated by smoothed wrinkles, shining, without microsculpture, upper one wrinkly-punctured; scutellum not elevated, almost flat, not carinated laterally. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangular projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral elongated with convex horizontal part, length of horizontal part 1,3 times longer than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum expressed with exception of costulae and carina closed area superomedia from backwards; basal area rather short; area superomedia rectangular, elongated, 1,4 times longer than width; areae dentiparae with weak teeth or broadenings at apices; spiracles of propodeum long, slit-shaped, along external contour 3 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum, including metapleurae, wrinkled, shining, without microsculpture. Thorax with long reddish-brown pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="53.[178,1086,1201,1281]" pageId="53" pageNumber="650">L e g s: Strong. Tibiae of front and middle legs with strong spinules; first segment of hind tarsi (metatarsus) slightly flattened. Hind coxae without scopa. Claws long, slightly uniformly curved. Coxae of all legs with long reddish-brown pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="53.[178,1085,1297,1406]" pageId="53" pageNumber="650">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, symmetrical; stigma quite short, light; radius slightly sinuous, particularly at apex; nervulus very slightly postfurcal; ramulus expressed; all veins light; membrane of wing hyaline. Length of front wing 2,1 times longer than length of flagellum and 1,5 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="53.[178,1085,1421,1585]" lastBlockId="54.[178,1086,218,439]" lastPageId="54" lastPageNumber="651" pageId="53" pageNumber="650">A b d o m e n:Amblypygous, fusiform from above, apical tergites not retracted; second tergite only just transverse, at apex 1,1 times wider than length. First tergite from lateral with distinct gradual bend between petiolus and postpetiolus; laterally sharply carinated; dorsolateral carinae weak, between them and ventrolateral carinae with strong transversal ribs; from above petiolus gradually broadened to triangle postpetiolus; distance between spiracles many more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus only just elevated, broad, delicately longitudinally striated, 3,9 times wider than lateral fields. Gastrocoeli small, slightly impressed and approached to the base of second tergite, 2-2,3 times narrower than interval between them; thyridiae expressed but weak, parallel to front margin of tergite; lunulae in a form of distinct impressions; surface of second tergite up to apex superficially longitudinally wrinklypunctured, shining; tergite 3 superficially punctured by small punctures, apical tergites with indistinct punctures. Hypopygium from below pointed, not compressed from sides; only sternites 2-4 with longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="54.[178,1085,454,561]" pageId="54" pageNumber="651">C o l o r a t i o n: Head black with reddish frontal orbits. Thorax black with white scutellum and subalarum. Tergites 2-3 red, 2nd with yellowish base, other tergites black; tergites 4-6 with white stripes at apex, 7th with white spot. All trochanters, coxae and femora on the larger part black; tibiae and tarsi of all legs red-yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="54.[178,822,576,598]" box="[178,822,576,598]" pageId="54" pageNumber="651">
S i z e: Body length: 13,5; front wing: 9,0; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[738,818,576,598]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.2" pageId="54" pageNumber="651" unit="mm" value="4.2">4,2 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="54.[178,254,612,634]" box="[178,254,612,634]" pageId="54" pageNumber="651">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="54.[178,1085,649,1069]" pageId="54" pageNumber="651">Flagellum of male moderately thick, bristle-shaped, gradually narrowed to apex with closely merged segments up to middle, segments 4-20 with long, narrow almost bacilliform tyloides, black, often ferruginous ventrally, without white annulus; mandibles normal, with long upper tooth and short lower one, gradually narrowed to apex, the most part parallel-sided. Scutellum from side more high. Propodeum not elongated. with horizontal surface high elevated at area of area superomedia; area superomedia not elongated, square. Middle field of postpetiolus high elevated and sharply striated as well as lateral fields. Gastrocoeli small, triangle, thyridia not developed. Sternites 2-3 with longitudinal fold; hypopygium with long narrow process apically. Yellow coloration more expanded: scapus from front, face and clypeus completely, frontal orbits at lower part, collar, hind corners of pronotum, tegulae, subalarum, scutellum, postscutellum partially, second tergite predominantly and third tergite of abdomen entirely, narrow apical bands on tergites 4-6, tergite 7 broadly apically (with spot); most part of femora of front and middle legs, tibiae and tarsi of all the legs, with exception of darkened apices of hind tibiae, yellow.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>