<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C84167AD23FF7533F0B22FA31C" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Bureschias subcylindricus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="49" lastPageNumber="646" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>597</mods:start>
<mods:end>711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C84167AD23FF7533F0B22FA31C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C84167AD23FF7533F0B22FA31C" lastPageId="49" lastPageNumber="646" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">
<subSubSection box="[178,723,216,238]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="48.[178,723,216,238]" box="[178,723,216,238]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">
<heading box="[178,723,216,238]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,723,216,238]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">
<taxonomicName authority="(GRAVENHORST)" baseAuthorityName="GRAVENHORST" box="[178,625,216,238]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Bureschias" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subcylindricus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,453,216,238]" italics="true" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">Bureschias subcylindricus</emphasis>
(GRAVENHORST)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 6)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="48" pageNumber="645" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="48.[178,981,256,328]" box="[178,975,256,276]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">
<taxonomicName authority="GRAVENHORST 1829" authorityName="GRAVENHORST" authorityYear="1829" box="[178,616,256,276]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subcylindricus">
<emphasis box="[178,417,256,276]" italics="true" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">Ichneumon subcylindricus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="GRAVENHORST I" box="[423,616,256,276]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" pagination="1 - 827" refId="ref60294" refString="GRAVENHORST I. L. C. (1829): Ichneumonologia Europea. - Vratislaviae, Sum. Auct. 1: 1 - 827." type="journal article" year="1829">GRAVENHORST 1829</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ichneumonologia europaea 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[882,893,256,276]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">2</emphasis>
: 321,.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="48.[178,981,256,328]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">
<taxonomicName authority=": HEINRICH 1936" authorityName=": HEINRICH" authorityYear="1936" box="[178,538,282,302]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Bureschias" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="balcanicus">
<emphasis box="[178,383,282,302]" italics="true" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">Bureschias balcanicus</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[395,538,282,302]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" pagination="81 - 88" refId="ref60385" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1936): Die von mir in Bulgarien gesammelten Ichneumoninae und Cryptinae (Insecta, Hymenoptera). - Mitt. Konigl. Naturwiss. Inst. Sofia 9: 81 - 88." type="journal article" year="1936">HEINRICH 1936</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mitt. Königl. Naturwiss. Inst. 
<collectingRegion box="[840,889,282,302]" country="Bulgaria" name="Sofiya-Grad" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">Sofia</collectingRegion>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[896,907,282,302]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">9</emphasis>
: 82-84. 
<taxonomicName authority=": RASNITSYN 1981" authorityName="RASNITSYN" authorityYear="1981" box="[178,587,308,328]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Bureschias" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subcylindricus">
<emphasis box="[178,417,308,328]" italics="true" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">Bureschias subcylindricus</emphasis>
: RASNITSYN 1981
</taxonomicName>
- Polsk. Pismo. Entomol 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[820,843,308,328]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">51</emphasis>
(1): 114, syn.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="48.[178,292,345,367]" box="[178,292,345,367]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">F e m a l e</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="49" lastPageNumber="646" pageId="48" pageNumber="645" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="48.[178,1085,382,521]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped with 36 segments, moderately stout, first segment short, only 1,5 times longer than width at apex from lateral, with white annulus on segments 9- 12, only just visible widened and flattened ventrally; only segments 1-4 slightly elongated. Segments of flagellum up to white annulus sharply differentiated. Flagellum short, 1,6 times shorter than front wing and 2,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="48.[178,1086,536,1232]" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">H e a d: Head contour from front almost not narrowed downwards, transverse, 1,4 times wider than length; genae and temples visible almost up to middle of eye, genae (malar space) very short, 7,8 times shorter than height of eye (0,1 of height of an eye); head contour from above rounded, slightly transverse, only 2,1 times wider than length in middle and 1,6 times along an external contour, roundly narrowed behind eyes. Vertex from lateral straightly sloping to occipital carina; temples long 1,5 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye at middle, parallel to hind margin of an eye, from above behind eyes swollen and roundly narrowed; occipital carina sharp all round, from above very slightly and roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina from lateral only just visible at very lower part, merged with occipital carina far from mandible base; abscissula very long, equal by length to mandible base width; malar space 1,2 times shorter than mandible base width; mandibles large, long, slightly swollen at middle, at apex with equal teeth; clypeus flat, extremely impressed relative to middle and lateral fields of face, from lateral practically parallel to longitudinal axis of a body, 2,5 times wider than length with thinned front margin and slight projection apically, in a shape of arch; clypeal foveae not expressed; labrum not protrude from under clypeus; middle and lateral fields overhang under clypeus; middle field strongly elevated and separated from lateral fields by deep and broad impressions, wider than lateral field in middle; antennal cavities deep, not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, without lateral tubercles and with strong and sharp tooth between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae slightly elevated above face surface; ocelli very small, diameter of lateral ocellus 2,5 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle almost not expressed. Surface of a head wrinkled, without microsculpture, only middle field of face with big smoothed punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="48.[178,1085,1246,1604]" lastBlockId="49.[178,1086,217,379]" lastPageId="49" lastPageNumber="646" pageId="48" pageNumber="645">
T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long with straight front margin (from above); transverse furrow of pronotum shallow, very narrow; upper margin of pronotum not swollen; epomiae sharp, short; pronotal base gradually curved. Mesonotum only just convex (flattened), slightly (1,2 times) longer than width; notauli only as a very slight impressions at same base; surface of mesonotum densely punctured by big punctures, without microsculpture, shining; subalarum narrow; speculum densely wrinkly-punctured, only just slightly than other part of mesopleurae; mesopleural fovea sharp, deep, area around it narrowly and deeply impressed; mesopleural suture straight, interrupted by delicate ribs; mesopleurae at bottom without sharp bend; sternauli developed up to middle of mesopleurae; lover half of mesopleurae sharply longitudinally striated, shining, without microsculpture, upper one wrinkly-punctured; scutellum only just elevated above postscutellum, almost flat, not carinated laterally. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangular projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral of broken 
<typeStatus box="[256,302,218,239]" pageId="49" pageNumber="646">type</typeStatus>
, length of horizontal part 1,2 times longer than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum expressed with exception of costulae and coxal carina (indistinct); basal area rather deep, of moderate length; area superomedia rectangular, elongated, 1,3 times longer than width; areae dentiparae without teeth at apices; spiracles of propodeum long, slit-shaped, along external contour 3,8 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum, including metapleurae, wrinkled, shining, without microsculpture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="49.[178,1023,393,415]" box="[178,1023,393,415]" pageId="49" pageNumber="646">L e g s: Strong. Hind coxae without scopa. Claws long, uniformly slightly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="49.[178,1085,429,563]" pageId="49" pageNumber="646">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, with broad base, slightly asymmetrical, external vein of apex shorter than internal one; stigma short, light, radius slightly sinuous, particularly at apex; nervulus interstitial; ramulus only just marked; all veins light; membrane of wing hyaline. Length of front wing 1,6 times longer than length of flagellum and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="49.[178,1085,577,907]" pageId="49" pageNumber="646">A b d o m e n: Amblypygous, fusiform from above, apical tergites not retracted; second tergite transverse, at apex 1,3 times wider than length. First tergite from lateral with distinct bend between petiolus and postpetiolus; laterally sharply carinated with sharp transversal ribs between carinae; from above petiolus gradually broadened to triangle postpetiolus; distance between spiracles many more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus slightly elevated, sharply longitudinally striated, 1,7 times wider than lateral fields. Gastrocoeli small, only just impressed, short, oblique, 1,6 times narrower than interval between them; thyridia practically not developed; lunulae weak, situated approximately at middle of second tergite; surface of second tergite superficially wrinkly-punctured up to middle, shining. Hypopygium from below not pointed, not compressed from sides, not fully overlap slit of ovipositor; sternites 2-4 with longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="49.[178,1085,921,999]" pageId="49" pageNumber="646">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black; scutellum yellow, tergites 1-2 of abdomen red; all trochanters and coxae black; tibiae and tarsi of all legs, front femora fully and middle at apex red.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="49.[178,822,1013,1035]" box="[178,822,1013,1035]" pageId="49" pageNumber="646">S i z e: Body length: 13,8; front wing: 9,7; flagellum: 6,0 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>