<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047626" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="2C917AEE56F9017D4EBEE811B3B95863" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="142" lastPageNumber="142" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" updateTime="1643530488545" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047626" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2C917AEE56F9017D4EBEE811B3B95863" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2C917AEE56F9017D4EBEE811B3B95863" lastPageId="142" lastPageNumber="142" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<subSubSection pageId="138" pageNumber="139" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/B769D0CF-1DF0-4AB5-A6F1-2EEBF39B874A" authority="Dodd" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Oxyscelio nigricoxa (Dodd)</taxonomicName>
Figures 213-218; Morphbank69
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="138" pageNumber="139" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Sceliomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sceliomorpha nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Sceliomorpha nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
Dodd, 1913: 165 (original description); 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieffer, JJ" journalOrPublisher="Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co., Berlin" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" title="Scelionidae. Das Tierreich. Vol. 48." year="1926">Kieffer 1926</bibRefCitation>
: 302, 307 (description, keyed). 
<taxonomicName authority="Kieffer, 1908" authorityName="Kieffer" authorityYear="1908" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Dicroteleia" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dicroteleia nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Dicroteleia nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
(Dodd): 
<bibRefCitation author="Dodd, AP" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="91 - 140" title="Further new genera and species of Australian Proctotrypoidea." volume="26" year="1914">Dodd 1914</bibRefCitation>
: 107 (generic transfer).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Oxyscelio nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
(Dodd): 
<bibRefCitation author="Dodd, AP" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="71 - 81" title="The genus Oxyscelio Kieffer, its synonymy and species, with a description of one new genus (Hymenoptera: Proctotrypoidea)." volume="42" year="1931">Dodd 1931</bibRefCitation>
: 76 (generic transfer); 
<bibRefCitation author="Galloway, ID" journalOrPublisher="Queensland Journal of Agricultural and Animal Sciences" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="83 - 114" title="The types of Australian species of the subfamily Scelioninae (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae)." volume="33" year="1976">Galloway 1976</bibRefCitation>
: 99 (type information).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="141" lastPageNumber="142" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Female. Body length 2.35-3.45 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape; at least partially darker than scape. A3: shorter than pedicel. A4: longer than broad. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="140" lastPageNumber="141" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">
<pageBreakToken pageId="139" pageNumber="140" start="start">Ventral</pageBreakToken>
clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: absent. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="140" pageNumber="141" start="start">Hyperoccipital</pageBreakToken>
carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: uniformly rounded dorsally. Occiput sculpture: umbilicate foveate medially, becoming smooth laterally. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="140" pageNumber="141">Lateral pronotal area sculpture: with shallow irregular carinae, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent; punctate. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally; smooth. Metascutellum shape: deeply emarginate, with the resulting pair of posterior processes subtriangular and directed dorsally. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="140" pageNumber="141">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: slightly emarginate, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: densely setose, setal pits between very weak longitudinal rugae. S5 sculpture: densely setose, setal pits between very weak longitudinal rugae. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
<pageBreakToken pageId="141" pageNumber="142" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Body length 2.15-3.4 mm (n=20). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: broader than long; as long as broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: weakly emarginate.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
Figures 213-218. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Oxyscelio nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
(Dodd), female (OSUC 462599) 213 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 214 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 215 Metasoma, dorsal view. Female (QDPC 0-165685) 216 Head, anterior view. Paratype male (OSUC 438140) 217 Antenna 218 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank69
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="141" pageNumber="142" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
Both sexes: Frontal depression shallow, transverse carinae absent or broadly interrupted ventrally, no carinae present above dorsal separator; submedian carina absent medially. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by weak rugae. Occipital carina complete, weakly convex medially. Metascutellum deeply concave, emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein absent. Coxa darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4 about as long as broad, A5 broader than long. Mesoscutellum without granulate sculpture. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. T6 without metasomal flanges, emarginate apically. Fore wing long enough to exceed metasomal apex. Male: A4 broader than long, A11 longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach beyond T7. T7 emarginate apically. The smaller-bodied 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio exiguitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exiguitatis">Oxyscelio exiguitatis</taxonomicName>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Oxyscelio nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
, but has a deep frontal depression and even deeper T6 emargination.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="141" pageNumber="142" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=5031]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="141" pageNumber="142" type="associations">
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Associations.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
On sticky seed of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Nyctaginaceae" genus="Pisonia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Pisonia brunoniana" order="Caryophyllales" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="brunoniana">Pisonia brunoniana</taxonomicName>
Endl.: [
<taxonomicName genus="Caryophyllales" lsidName="Caryophyllales" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" rank="genus">Caryophyllales</taxonomicName>
: 
<taxonomicName genus="Nyctaginaceae" lsidName="Nyctaginaceae" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" rank="genus">Nyctaginaceae</taxonomicName>
]
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="142" lastPageNumber="143" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="142" lastPageNumber="143" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
Holotype, male, S. nigricoxa: AUSTRALIA: QLD, summit of mountain range, grass / forest, Gordonvale (Nelson), 1500ft, 30.V.1913, sweeping, A. A. Girault, SAMA DB 32-001587 (deposited in SAMA). Other material: AUSTRALIA: 62 females, 152 males, ANIC DB 32-020124, 32-020125, 32-020144, OSUC 359709, OSUC 359710, OSUC 359711, OSUC 438058, OSUC 438059, OSUC 438060, OSUC 438061, OSUC 438062, OSUC 438063, OSUC 438064, OSUC 438067, OSUC 438069, OSUC 438072, OSUC 438093, OSUC 438094, OSUC 438095, OSUC 438096, OSUC 438097, OSUC 438098, OSUC 438099, OSUC 438100, OSUC 438102, OSUC 438103, OSUC 438110, OSUC 438111, OSUC 438112, OSUC 438113, OSUC 438114, OSUC 438115, OSUC 438116, OSUC 438117, OSUC 438118, OSUC 438119, OSUC 438120, OSUC 438121, OSUC 438122, OSUC 438123, OSUC 438133, OSUC 438134, OSUC 438135, OSUC 438136, OSUC 438137, OSUC 438138, OSUC 438139, OSUC 438140, OSUC 438141, OSUC 438142, OSUC 438143, OSUC 438152 (ANIC); OSUC 449022, 451335, 451359 (BMNH); OSUC 462598-462601 (CNCI); OSUC 438068, 438104, 438108, 438182, QDPC 0-165634, QDPC 0-165641, QDPC 0-165645, QDPC 0-165651, QDPC 0-165662, QDPC 0-165668, QDPC 0-165670, QDPC 0-165680, QDPC 0-165681, QDPC 0-165683, QDPC 0-165685, QDPC 0-165689, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="142" pageNumber="143" start="start">QDPC</pageBreakToken>
0-165697, QDPC 0-165700, QDPC 0-165710, QDPC 0-165712, QDPC 0-165716, QDPC 0-165717, QDPC 0-165722, QDPC 0-165733, QDPC 0-165742, QDPC 0-165743, QDPC 0-165744, QDPC 0-165748, QDPC 0-165755, QDPC 0-165763, QDPC 0-165764, QDPC 0-165766, QDPC 0-165767, QDPC 0-165783 (QDPC); OSUC 438073, 438092, 438101 (QMBA); OSUC 448607 (QPIM); OSUC 438070, 449028, 451329-451334, 451339-451340 (UQIC); OSUC 359704-359708, 359712, 436936, 438039-438057, 438065-438066, 438071, 438074-438091, 438105-438107, 438109, 438124-438132, 438144-438147, 438149-438151, 438153-438181, 438183-438186, 449029, 451336-451338, 451357-451358, 451360 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>