<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047589" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7FC6E9B1-A5F3-4877-B4B0-A1E428550121" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="6E31A5135CCBF90C2355F4EE2711E447" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio bellariorum Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="7FC6E9B1-A5F3-4877-B4B0-A1E428550121" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="32" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="28" pageNumber="29" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047589" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7FC6E9B1-A5F3-4877-B4B0-A1E428550121" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6E31A5135CCBF90C2355F4EE2711E447" lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="32" pageId="28" pageNumber="29">
<subSubSection pageId="28" pageNumber="29" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/7FC6E9B1-A5F3-4877-B4B0-A1E428550121" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio bellariorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bellariorum">Oxyscelio bellariorum Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="28" pageNumber="29">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 15-18; Morphbank29
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="30" lastPageNumber="31" pageId="28" pageNumber="29" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Female. Body length 4.5-4.9 mm (n=12).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="29" lastPageNumber="30" pageId="28" pageNumber="29">
Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="29" pageNumber="30" start="start">Median</pageBreakToken>
longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: with some transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, medially incomplete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="30" lastPageNumber="31" pageId="29" pageNumber="30">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: with shallow irregular carinae, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: with large smooth areas. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Micro 
<pageBreakToken pageId="30" pageNumber="31" start="start">sculpture</pageBreakToken>
of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent; punctate. Mesoscutellar rim: expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: with notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching base of T5. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: present. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: present as slightly protruding sharp corners. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: present, blade-like with rounded margins. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: longitudinally striate; umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: with deep emargination that is V-shaped medially, separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: present, very broadly rounded, with rounded apices. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: present, posteriorly complete. S6 apex in relation to T6: exposed to dorsal view by T6 emargination. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Male. unknown.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
Figures 15-18. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio bellariorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bellariorum">Oxyscelio bellariorum</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype female (OSUC 435954) 15 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 16 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 17 Head, anterior view 18 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank29
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
Both sexes: Frontal depression deep, all carinae except dorsal separator interrupted medially, carinae present above dorsal separator; submedian carina weakly defined or absent medially. Hyperoccipital carina absent. Occipital carina complete, medially sinuate. Mesoscutal midlobe weakly sculptured with some smooth areas near midlength. Mesoscutellar rim not expanded, with median notch. Metascutellum scoop-like, projecting dorsally. Coxa darker than rest of leg. Postmarginal vein absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4 not longer than broad, A5 broader than long. T4 with weak metasomal flanges. T5 with lobe-like metasomal flanges. T6 with broad, wavy lateral metasomal flanges. T6 broadly and deeply emarginate, roundly concave medially. S6 exposed to dorsal view, rounded apically. This species is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio incisurae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incisurae">Oxyscelio incisurae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio funis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funis">Oxyscelio funis</taxonomicName>
, but has a shorter antenna than in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio funis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funis">Oxyscelio funis</taxonomicName>
and weaker sculpture than in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio incisurae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incisurae">Oxyscelio incisurae</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“confectioneries.”">&quot;confectioneries.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307064]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="32" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
<pageBreakToken pageId="31" pageNumber="32" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: NSW, Pilliga, 1.II.1931, A. P. Dodd, OSUC 435957 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 11 females, OSUC 435950-435956, 435958-435960 (ANIC); OSUC 449096 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>