<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.429.7949" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d876d832-141c-4025-8cb3-cb7cfb46ffa5" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152054621" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-429-101" ID-ZBK="" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-429-101" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 429" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the genus Hemisaprinus Kryzhanovskij, 1976 (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Saprininae)" checkinTime="1451245553400" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lackner, Tomas" docDate="2014" docId="BA10B00FB6C231856147C113C9A83C17" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 429: 101-130" docOrigin="ZooKeys 429" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.429.7949" docTitle="Hemisaprinus lutshniki Reichardt 1941" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="116" masterDocId="FFCFFFBF940DFFCEF807FFB3DF528074" masterDocTitle="Revision of the genus Hemisaprinus Kryzhanovskij, 1976 (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Saprininae)" masterLastPageNumber="130" masterPageNumber="101" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" updateTime="1643517939224" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the genus Hemisaprinus Kryzhanovskij, 1976 (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Saprininae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lackner, Tomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>429</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>101</mods:start>
<mods:end>130</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.429.7949</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.429.7949</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-429-101</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">237EB0D4-12AF-4856-89C5-5E2AA52C4CEA</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152054621" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BA10B00FB6C231856147C113C9A83C17" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BA10B00FB6C231856147C113C9A83C17" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="116" pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Taxon classification Animalia Coleoptera Histeridae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
<taxonomicName authority="Reichardt, 1941" authorityName="Reichardt" authorityYear="1941" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki (Reichardt, 1941)</taxonomicName>
Figs 13-25
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus cribellatus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribellatus">Saprinus cribellatus</taxonomicName>
ab. lutshniki Reichardt, 1941: 257, 392.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Hemisaprinus) lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki" subGenus="Hemisaprinus">Saprinus (Hemisaprinus) lutshniki</taxonomicName>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="Kryzhanovskij, OL" journalOrPublisher="Nauka, Leningrad" pageId="22" pageNumber="123" title="Zhuki Nadsemeystva Histeroidea (semeystva Sphaeritidae, Histeridae, Synteliidae). [Beetles of the superfamily Histeroidea (families Sphaeritidae, Histeridae, Syntelidae)]. Fauna SSSR, Zhestokrylye, Vyp. 4." year="1976">Kryzhanovskij and Reichardt (1976)</bibRefCitation>
: 183; 
<bibRefCitation author="Mazur, S" journalOrPublisher="Polskie Pismo Entomologiczne" pageId="23" pageNumber="124" pagination="1 - 376" title="A world catalogue of Histeridae." volume="54" year="1984">Mazur (1984)</bibRefCitation>
: 62; 
<bibRefCitation author="Mazur, S" journalOrPublisher="Genus, Supplement" pageId="23" pageNumber="124" title="A world catalogue of the Histeridae (Coleoptera: Histeridae)." year="1997">Mazur (1997)</bibRefCitation>
: 231; 
<bibRefCitation author="Mazur, S" journalOrPublisher="Apollo Books, Stenstrup" pageId="23" pageNumber="124" title="Family Histeridae. Pp. 68 - 102. In: Loebl I, Smetana A (Eds) Catalogue of Palaearctic Coleoptera, Vol. 2, Hydrophiloidea-Histeroidea-Staphylinoidea." year="2004">Mazur (2004)</bibRefCitation>
: 96.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="Mazur, S" journalOrPublisher="Warsaw University of Life Sciences, SGGW Press, Warsaw" pageId="23" pageNumber="124" title="A concise catalogue of the Histeridae (Coleoptera)." year="2011">Mazur (2011)</bibRefCitation>
: 188.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Russia: Totskiy Rayon, near Samara.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="type material examined">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus cribellatus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="111" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribellatus">
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="111" start="start">Saprinus</pageBreakToken>
cribellatus
</taxonomicName>
ab. lutshniki: Lectotype, sex unidentified, left mesotarsus missing, with following labels: circle, gold label, followed by: &quot;Totskij lag / Samarsk. g. / 26.iv. 1917&quot; (hand-written label in Russian); followed by: &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus cribell" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="111" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribell">Saprinus cribell</taxonomicName>
. / a. lutshniki nov. / A. Reichardt det.&quot; (printed-written); followed by: &quot;Lectotypus / 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="111" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Saprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
Rchdt. / Kryzhanovskij det., 66&quot; (red label, printed-written). Paratypes: 1 ♂, with following labels: &quot;Saratov / N.L. Sacharov&quot; (black-margined label, written-printed); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Paratypus”">&quot;Paratypus&quot;</normalizedToken>
(red label, printed). 1 spec., with the following labels: &quot;O.B. Don 15.iv.[1]912 / Persianovka / B. Kizeritskij&quot; (printed-written); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Paratypus”">&quot;Paratypus&quot;</normalizedToken>
(red label, printed). 1 ♀, with following labels: &quot;G. Temir Ural Obl. / 15.iv.[19]07 / D. Borodin &amp; V. Uvarov&quot; (printed-written in Russian); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Paratypus”">&quot;Paratypus&quot;</normalizedToken>
(red label, printed); followed by: &quot;Zoological / Institute RAS / St. Petersburg&quot; (yellow label, printed); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“lutshniki”">&quot;lutshniki&quot;</normalizedToken>
(yellow, pencil-written label) and: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“09-063”">&quot;09-063&quot;</normalizedToken>
(yellow, pencil-written label) added by myself. 2 specs., with following labels: &quot;Peremezhnoe, / okr. Uralska / Lyubishev 1.v.[19]33&quot; (hand-written label in Russian); followed by red label, printed: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Paratypus”">&quot;Paratypus&quot;</normalizedToken>
(all exs. ZIN).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="112" pageId="10" pageNumber="111" type="additional material examined">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="112" pageId="10" pageNumber="111">
KAZAKHSTAN: 1 ♂, River Ural near Kharkin, 14.v.1951, L. Arnoldi leg. (NCB); 56 exs., Ural River, near Kharkin, 14.v.1951, L. Arnoldi, under desert plants 
<taxonomicName genus="Atraphaxys" lsidName="Atraphaxys" pageId="11" pageNumber="112" rank="genus">
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="112" start="start">Atraphaxys</pageBreakToken>
</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName genus="Polygonaceae" lsidName="Polygonaceae" pageId="11" pageNumber="112" rank="genus">Polygonaceae</taxonomicName>
) (ZIN); 1 spec., Ganibek nat. reserve, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="49.383335">49°23' N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="46.783333">46°47' E</geoCoordinate>
, 1.v.2003, O. Khrulyova leg. (CAS); 2 specs., Ural River, Kharkin, 14.v.1951, L. Arnoldi leg. (MNHN). RUSSIA: 1 ♂, Orenburskaya oblast, 3 km NW Pervomaiskij, Donguz, steppe, 1.v.-28.vi.2009, Kozminykh V.O. leg. (TLAN). 1 spec., Volgograd, ovrag (=ravine) of the Tsaritsa River, 23.iv.1986, Matveev leg.; 2 specs., Samarskaya gubernia, Nikolaevskij distr., Bostanyhoglo leg., 1917; 1 spec., Samara, no date, Dr. Volz leg.; 1 spec., Kalmytskaya ASSR, Priozernij rayon, Tugtyn, 11.v.1976, Iviliev leg.; 1 spec., Petrovsk-port, N. Caucasus, 4.v.1931, M. Ryabov leg.; 1 spec., Tverskaya obl., Pokhot'-Krugloe, Zubtsovskij uezd, 30.v.1925, collector unknown; 3 exs., Kuybyshevskaya obl., Pestravskij rayon, kolkhoz 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Rodina”">&quot;Rodina&quot;</normalizedToken>
, 14-15.v.1960, collector unknown; 4 specs., idem, but selo 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Mosty”">&quot;Mosty&quot;</normalizedToken>
, 14.v.1960, under 
<taxonomicName class="Liliopsida" family="Poaceae" genus="Agropyron" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Agropyron" order="Poales" pageId="11" pageNumber="112" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Agropyron</taxonomicName>
plants in a ditch (all exs. ZIN); 1 spec., Kuybyshiev distr., 14.v.1960, Alejnikova leg. (BMNH); 1 spec., Astrakhan reg., 10 km S Upper Baskunchak vill., &quot;Shikli&quot; sands, 4.v.1995, I. Melnik leg. (CAS); 2 specs. Astrakhan reg., Palass distr., N side Elton lake, right side Khara River, 20-31.v.2006, A. Matalin leg. (CAS).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="116" pageId="11" pageNumber="112" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="112">Re-description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="112">
Body length: PEL= 2.75-3.35 mm, APW= 1.00-1.25 mm, PPW= 2.00-2.35 mm, EW= 2.25-2.60 mm, EL= 1.90-2.20 mm. Body (Fig. 13) rectangular oval, convex, elytra widest at humeri; cuticle of elytra on impunctate 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘mirror’">'mirror'</normalizedToken>
dark brown to black, on punctate part reddish-brown, shining, pronotum dark, almost black; body ventrally dark brown to almost black; abdominal ventrites (except for first visible) rufescent; legs, mouthparts and antennae rufo-castaneous; antennal club somewhat darker.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="112">Antennal scape (Fig. 14) slightly thickened, substrigulate, finely punctate, lower margin carinate, with few short setae; club (Figs 14, 15) round, pointed apically, without visible articulation, entire surface with dense short sensilla intermingled with sparser longer erect sensilla; sensory structures of antennal club in form of four ovoid sensory areas on ventral side (Fig. 15); vesicle(s) not examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="113">
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="113" start="start">Mouthparts</pageBreakToken>
: mandibles (Fig. 14) stout, densely punctate, mandibular apex pointed; sub-apical tooth of left mandible not examined; labrum convex, densely punctate, with slight median concavity interrupted by semi-globular convexity; labral pits deep, each with two well-sclerotized long setae; terminal labial palpomere elongated, about twice as long as pen-ultimate, its width about one-third its length; mentum sub-trapezoid, anterior margin medially with deep notch surrounded with sparse rather long setae, lateral margins with single row of sparse shorter ramose setae; cardo of maxilla with few short setae; stipes triangular, with three short setae; terminal maxillary palpomere elongated, pointed apically, about three times as long as pen-ultimate; its width about one-third its length.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="114" pageId="12" pageNumber="113">
Clypeus (Fig. 14) flat, gradually sloping down laterally, rugulose-lacunose; frontal stria broadly interrupted medially, for short distance prolonged onto clypeus, supraor 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="114" start="start">bital</pageBreakToken>
stria well impressed, carinate; frontal disc (Fig. 14) very coarsely and densely punctate; eyes convex, well visible from above.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="114">Pronotal sides (Fig. 13) on basal half moderately narrowing anteriorly, strongly narrowing on apical half; apical angles obtuse; median emargination for head shallow; pronotal depressions absent; marginal pronotal stria complete, somewhat weakened behind head; pronotal disc shining on most part, with sparse punctures separated by several times their diameter, laterally and behind head more coarse and dense punctures appear, punctures form a depressed band of confluent punctuation, between it and pronotal margin a narrow band with simple punctuation present; several rows of ovoid punctures present along pronotal base; pronotum with faint ante-scutellar depression; pronotal hypomeron asetose, in fine scattered punctures; scutellum well visible.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="115" pageId="13" pageNumber="114">
Elytral epipleura glabrous; marginal epipleural stria fine, complete; marginal elytral stria straight, well impressed and slightly carinate, continued as weakened complete apical elytral stria. Humeral elytral stria weakly impressed on basal fourth, doubled, surface between it and second dorsal elytral stria in longitudinal irregular strioles; inner subhumeral stria present as short median fragment; elytra with thin striae 1-4; striae with weak punctures within, except for first stria which is shorter than the others reaching approximately elytral half apically; fourth dorsal elytral stria basally connected with sutural elytral stria by broad arch; sutural elytral stria well-impressed and 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="115" start="start">complete</pageBreakToken>
, fine punctures within, apically connected with apical elytral stria, between it and elytral suture a row of fine punctures present; elytral humeri and flanks almost impunctate, elytral disc along sutural elytral stria on apical two-fifths with dense, almost confluent punctation, forming longitudinal rugae; weakened punctuation slightly enters elytral intervals, apically punctuation weakens, leaving an impunctate band before extreme elytral apex; rest of elytral disk with large impunctate 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘mirror’">'mirror'</normalizedToken>
, most prominent on 2-4 elytral intervals; this mirror occasionally bears fine scattered punctures, in most cases limited to second elytral interval.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="115">Propygidium and pygidium densely and coarsely punctate, punctures separated by about half to their own diameter; interspaces with microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="115">Anterior margin of median portion of prosternum (Fig. 16) rounded; marginal prosternal stria present laterally and as short anterior fragment; prosternal process on apical sixth distinctly elevated in respect to the remaining part; surface between carinal prosternal striae slightly convex, with scattered fine punctation, punctures surrounded by microsculpture; carinal prosternal striae well-impressed, parallel on prosternal apophysis, thence divergent anteriorly, terminating in deep and large prosternal foveae; lateral prosternal striae carinate, sub-parallel, apically terminating near the point where carinal prosternal striae enter prosternal foveae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="115">Anterior margin of mesoventrite broadly, but shallowly inwardly arcuate; discal marginal mesoventral stria well impressed, carinate; disc of mesoventrite with dense deep large punctures intermingled with much smaller microscopic punctuation; meso-metaventral sutural stria marked as straight row of punctures; intercoxal disc of metaventrite slightly convex with scattered microscopic punctures, becoming coarser and denser along basal margin; lateral metaventral stria well impressed, carinate, almost straight, shortened; lateral disc of metaventrite concave, with regular shallow large setigerous punctures; metepisternum with denser and coarser punctation, punctures almost confluent; fused metepimeron with somewhat sparser punctures; metepisternum + fused metepimeron with metepisternal stria.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="115">Intercoxal disc of first abdominal ventrite incompletely striate laterally; on basal third with irregular scattered fine punctures separated by several times their own diameter; rest of first visible abdominal ventrite with scattered microscopic punctuation.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="116" pageId="14" pageNumber="115">
Protibia slightly dilated, outer margin apically with single low tooth topped by tiny denticle, in proximal direction three low triangular teeth topped by short rounded denticle appear, all three approximately of the same size, followed by another low tooth (occasionally bearing two tiny denticles), followed by a single tiny denticle growing out directly from outer margin of protibia; setae of outer row regular, rather short; protarsal groove rather deep; anterior protibial stria very shortened (absent?); setae of intermedian row situated on ridge delimiting proximal margin of protarsal groove; single tarsal denticle present near tarsal insertion; protibial spur short, bent, growing out from apical margin of protibia; apical margin of protibia posteriorly with three tiny denticles almost abutting each other; outer part of posterior surface obscurely variolate, punctate, separated from imbricate median part of posterior surface by vague boundary and row of short sclerotized setae; posterior protibial stria complete, bearing a row 
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="116" start="start">of</pageBreakToken>
fine sparse setae along its length, terminating in two tiny inner denticles; inner row of setae double, setae dense and short.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">Mesotibia slender, outer margin with a single row of short denticles situated on low teeth; setae of outer row regular, sparse, about as long as denticles themselves; setae of intermedian row shorter and finer than those of outer row, regular; posterior mesotibial stria almost complete; anterior surface of mesotibia imbricate, with another row of approximately seven shorter denticles than those of outer row; anterior mesotibial stria complete, terminating in single tiny inner anterior denticle; mesotibial spur short; apical margin of mesotibia anteriorly with three short denticles; claws of apical tarsomere slightly bent, shorter than half its length; metatibia slenderer and longer than mesotibia, outer margin with approximately five short denticles situated on even lower teeth than those of mesotibia; apical-most tooth bearing two denticles; setae of outer row distinctly longer than denticles themselves; anterior face of metatibia punctate, with a row of approximately five tiny denticles; claws of apical-most metatarsomere longer than half of its length; metatibia otherwise similar to mesotibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
Male genitalia: Eighth sternite (Figs 17-18) longitudinally medially separated, apically with medially-sized velum covered with dense micro-pores and several larger pseudopores medially; eighth tergite inwardly arcuate; eighth tergite and sternite fused laterally (Fig. 19). Ninth tergite (Fig. 20) medially with strong longitudinal sclerotization, apically inwardly slightly arcuate; tenth tergite outwardly arcuate apically, basally slightly inwardly arcuate. Spiculum gastrale (Figs 22-23) basally strongly dilated, outwardly arcuate; apically slightly triangularly dilated, without typical inwardly-turned apical 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“tails”">&quot;tails&quot;</normalizedToken>
. Aedeagus (Figs 24-25) sub-parallel, parameres fused approximately on their apical halves, apex of aedeagus blunt. Basal piece of aedeagus rather short, ratio to parameres approximately 1:6; aedeagus curved laterally (Fig. 25).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="116" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
This species is very similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus cyprius" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cyprius">Hemisaprinus cyprius</taxonomicName>
, differing from it chiefly by the presence of a second dorsal elytral stria, absent with 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus cyprius" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cyprius">Hemisaprinus cyprius</taxonomicName>
and aciculate elytral punctuation, as well as shining pronotum (matt in cyprius).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
Figure 13. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
Figure 14. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, head, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
Figure 15. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, antennal club, ventro-lateral view showing sensory structures of the antenna.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
Figure 16. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, prosternum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="116">
Figures 17-25. 17 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, 8th sternite and tergite, ventral view 18 ditto, dorsal view 19 ditto, lateral view 20 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, 9th + 10th tergites, dorsal view 21 ditto, lateral view 22 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, spiculum gastrale, ventral view 23 ditto, lateral view 24 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hemisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hemisaprinus lutshniki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lutshniki">Hemisaprinus lutshniki</taxonomicName>
(Reichardt, 1941) paratype, aedeagus, dorsal view 25 ditto, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>