<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6202b897-11c1-4686-99d8-94b8174ac809" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359746" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-55-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-55-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 55" ModsDocTitle="Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) – review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America" checkinTime="1451251020634" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gary A. P., Gibson" docDate="2010" docId="63D9E08B2158942B8373312FC642F2A0" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 55: 1-75" docOrigin="ZooKeys 55" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490" docTitle="Calosota setosa P., 2010, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="48" lastPageNumber="49" masterDocId="FF9456530D10AC187F08FFB0FC42FFD0" masterDocTitle="Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) - review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America" masterLastPageNumber="75" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="45" pageNumber="46" updateTime="1643559592688" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) - review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gary A. P., Gibson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>55</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>75</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-55-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359746" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:63D9E08B2158942B8373312FC642F2A0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/63D9E08B2158942B8373312FC642F2A0" lastPageId="48" lastPageNumber="49" pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
<subSubSection pageId="45" pageNumber="46" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B4AE6AAE-8687-42B9-81D8-1BA6CED60E19" class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota setosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="45" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="setosa">Calosota setosa</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="45" pageNumber="46">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 104347, 5177
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="45" pageNumber="46" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
From the Latin word setosus, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘bristly’">'bristly'</normalizedToken>
, in reference to the comparatively conspicuously setose body of females, including the metacoxae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="46" lastPageNumber="47" pageId="45" pageNumber="46" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="46" lastPageNumber="47" pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
HOLOTYPE ♀ (CNC no. 23927). BAHAMAS, W.I. [West Indies], Eleuthera, Rainbow Bay, 16-26.X.85, J.R. Wiley, MT; CNC Photo 2009-32; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="46" pageNumber="47" start="start">Holotype</pageBreakToken>
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota setosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="46" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="setosa">Calosota setosa</taxonomicName>
Gibson. ALLOTYPE♂ (CNC). Same data as holotype except collected 1.X.86; CNC Photo 2009-3; Allotype 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota setosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="46" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="setosa">Calosota setosa</taxonomicName>
Gibson.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="46" pageNumber="47">
Additional paratypes: BAHAMAS. Same data as holotype (1♀, 1♂ CNC); same data except 1.VII.87, D.B. &amp; R.W. Wiley (1♀ FSCA). DOMINICAN REPUBLIC. Prov. Pedernales, Sierra Bahoruco, 9.5 km. N Cabo Rojo, VII.90, L. Masner, desert (1♂ CNC); 21 km. N Cabo Rojo, 19-20.VI.76, R.E. Woodruff &amp; E.E. Grissell (1♀ FSCA). USA. Florida: Monroe Co., Big Pine Key, S1, T67S, R29E, 30.
<normalizedToken originalValue="VIII–">VIII-</normalizedToken>
17.XI.85, S&amp;J Peck, Cactus Hammock, malaise &amp; FIT, forest (1♀ CNC, CNC Photo 2009-1); Middle Torch Key, 1-30.XI.86, S&amp;J Peck, hammock forest edge, malaise, 86-95 (1♀ CNC, CNC SEM 2009-39); No Name Key, 23.
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–">II-</normalizedToken>
3.VI.86, S&amp;J Peck, hammock forest, malaise &amp; FIT (1♂ CNC, CNC Photo 2009-2); Sugarloaf Key, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kitching’s">Kitching's</normalizedToken>
, NW 1/4, SE 1/4, S25, R27E, T66S, 14.XI.85-25.II.86, S&amp;J Peck, FIT malaise (1♂ CNC, CNC SEM 2009-40).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="47" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="46" pageNumber="47" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="46" pageNumber="47">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="46" pageNumber="47">FEMALE (Fig. 43). HOLOTYPE: length 2.25 mm. Color. Head (Fig. 10) greenish to greenish-blue under most angles of light except scrobal depression and parascrobal region brown or with coppery luster under some angles of light, and with less distinct coppery-brown band extending dorsally from scrobal depression on either side of anterior ocellus. Maxillary and labial palpi white (Fig. 10). Antenna with about basal fifth of scape white (Fig. 10), otherwise dark brown except scape with bluish-purple lusters under some angle of light. Tegula whitish-yellow. Mesoscutum mostly green similar to head but with reddish-coppery medial region anterior to scutellum, the region fading with ill-defined margins anteriorly but extending to about level of posterior margin of notauli; scutellar-axillar complex mostly green but with very slight and limited indication of reddish-coppery luster under some angles of light. Acropleuron (Fig. 51) brown with variably distinctly greenish to purple lusters under different angles of light. Legs (Fig. 43) with front leg whitish-yellow beyond coxa except posterior surface of femur partly light brown and tibia more distinctly brown subbasally; middle leg whitish-yellow beyond coxa except anterodorsal margin of femur with tiny brown spot and tibia subbasally with tiny, almost complete brown band; hind leg whitish-yellow beyond coxa except anterior surface of femur very slightly darker, brownish-yellow basally. Fore wing hyaline; setae uniformly brown. Gaster variably extensively brown to slightly greenish to blue dorsally under different angles of light, but extreme base of Gt1, syntergum except apically, and terga laterally more distinctly bluish-green.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="47" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="46" pageNumber="47">
Structure/setation. Head in dorsal view about 1.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, with IOD about 0.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
head width; IOD: MPOD: OOL: POL: LOL = 38: 7: 6: 14: 10; in frontal view about 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high, with dorsal margin of torulus slightly above level of lower orbits; malar space about 0.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
eye height. Head (Fig. 10) with frontovertex, dorsal most part of scrobal depression and most of parascrobal region finely meshlike coriaceous; scrobal depression mostly and interantennal region dorsally smooth and shiny, interantennal region ventrally finely coriaceous-alutaceous; clypeal region microcoriaceous and paraclypeal region obliquely coriaceous-alutaceous, the sculpture only slightly finer narrowly along inner orbit. Head with whitish seta except for bare 
<pageBreakToken pageId="47" pageNumber="48" start="start">scrobal</pageBreakToken>
depression. Antenna (Fig. 43) with flagellum clavate; length of flagellum + pedicel about 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
head width; scape: pedicel: fu1-fu8: clava = 37(10): 14(7): 5(4), 14(4), 14(5), 13(6), 12(6), 11(6), 10(6), 9(7): 36(10). Mesoscutum (Fig. 77) more or less uniformly reticulate, the flat-bottomed, meshlike reticulations slightly but not conspicuously larger medially than laterally, and with sparse, white setae; notaulus extending from spiracle as shallow furrow on inclined anterior surface; anteroadmedian line not evident; parapsidal line inconspicuous, a short microsculptured region. Axillae elongate-slender, separated by about 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
own width (Fig. 77). Scutellum low convex, about 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; elongate reticulate-strigose (Fig. 77); with inconspicuous white setae. Mesopleuron with reduced lower mesepimeron, but narrow vertical surface under convex acropleuron above base of mesocoxa with 2 setae projecting between bases of meso- and metacoxae (cf. Fig. 81); acropleuron without distinct microsculptured region, coriaceous to obliquely coriaceous-alutaceous anteriorly longitudinally elongate coriaceous-alutaceous to coriaceous-aciculate over about posterior half. Fore wing with cc: mv: stv: pmv = 42: 46: 10: 14; basal cell entirely setose; cubital area bare except closed by setae along posterior margin over about apical third; disc setose except for small bare region at juncture of base of basal and mediocubital folds. Metacoxa with outer surface completely setose (Fig. 51). Propodeum with callus setose to posterior margin (Fig. 51); bare anteriorly between spiracle and foramen. Gaster (Fig. 43) about 1.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as mesosoma, with sparse, inconspicuous white setae dorsally and much denser and more conspicuous, slightly lanceolate white setae laterally; penultimate tergum with posterior margin extending to level of cerci; syntergum about 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as transcercal width, evenly convex, and about 1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of penultimate tergum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="47" pageNumber="48">MALE (Fig. 47). ALLOTYPE: length 2.1 mm. Similar to female except as follows. Color. Head with brownish-coppery region of scrobal depression extending completely to anterior ocellus and mesoscutum and scutellar-axillar complex more extensively though diffusely reddish-coppery, including scutellum and mesoscutal lateral lobes anteriorly; legs almost completely whitish-yellow beyond coxae except for distinct brown region dorsally on protibia and slight brownish tinge posteriorly on profemur and subbasal brownish spot on mesotibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="47" pageNumber="48">
Structure/setation. Head in dorsal view about 1.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, with IOD about 0.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
head width; IOD: MPOD: OOL: POL: LOL = 41: 11: 5: 15: 9; in frontal view about 1.28
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high, with ventral margin of torulus about at level of lower orbits; malar space about 0.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
eye height. Antenna (Fig. 47) with flagellum elongate-filiform and conspicuously setose, the setae somewhat longer than width of respective flagellomere and curved; length of flagellum + pedicel about 2.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of head; scape: pedicel: fu1-fu11 = 31(10): 16(8): 2(5): 24(7): 25(7): 25(7): 23(7): 20:(7): 19(7): 18(7): 16(7): 14(7): 15(6) (including very small apical subsegment). Fore wing cc: mv: stv: pmv = 55: 60: 10: 18. Mesopleuron without projecting setae from slender region below acropleuron above base of mesocoxa. Metacoxa with outer surface more extensively bare mediolongitudinally.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="48" lastPageNumber="49" pageId="47" pageNumber="48" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="47" pageNumber="48">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="48" lastPageNumber="49" pageId="47" pageNumber="48">
Females range in length from about 2.1-3.4 mm and males from about 2.1-2.6 mm. One exceptionally large female (FL: Cactus Hammock, Fig. 51) has the 
<pageBreakToken pageId="48" pageNumber="49" start="start">head</pageBreakToken>
mostly dark brown except for slight coppery or greenish lusters under some angles of light and the mesosoma and gaster more or less uniformly reddish-coppery except for small greenish regions on the gastral terga dorsolaterally. The legs are almost completely yellow beyond the coxae, though with a similar color pattern to the holotype, and the outer surface of the metacoxa is much more densely and conspicuously setose. The mesoscutum is also more strongly reticulate with smaller reticulations so that they are more concave than flat-bottomed. The acropleuron is very shallowly reticulate-coriaceous anteriorly below the tegula and five curved setae project from under its posteroventral margin between the meso- and metacoxae (Fig. 51). The head also has the scrobal depression much more deeply concave; this apparently is because the face is collapsed below the anterior ocellus, but the vertex is not collapsed and the IOD is only one-third the width of the head. The ocelli are also relatively larger, with the IOD: MPOD: OOL: POL: LOL = 43: 13: 5: 14: 10. Additional specimens from Florida are necessary to better access variation, but I currently consider the Cactus Hammock female to be conspecific with the other female from Florida and those from the West Indies. Also, the single female and male from Dominican Republic differ from other type specimens in having a strongly bluish-green to purple mesosoma. The female has about the anterior third of the mesoscutum bright greenish (region narrowly blue posteriorly) and the posterior two-thirds violaceous to purple, the regions abruptly delimited posteriorly, whereas the scutellar-axillar complex is greenish-blue. The male has a more extensively bluish-green mesoscutum, including medially and very narrowly posteriorly, but the lateral lobes are partly violaceous to purple as for the female. The female has only the extreme base of the scape white, whereas the male lacks a distinct basal white region from the scape; the male also has the posterior surface of the profemur darker than for other males and with a slight purple luster. I interpret these differences as intraspecific variation, but additional specimens from Dominican Republic are required to better evaluate the color differences.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="48" pageNumber="49" type="biology">
<paragraph pageId="48" pageNumber="49">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="48" pageNumber="49">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="48" pageNumber="49" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="48" pageNumber="49">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="48" pageNumber="49">
Florida Keys and West Indies (Map 5). One of four New World species that may have had a Neotropical origin (see further under distribution for 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota albipalpus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="48" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="albipalpus">Calosota albipalpus</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="48" pageNumber="49" type="recognition">
<paragraph pageId="48" pageNumber="49">Recognition.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="48" pageNumber="49">
Individuals of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota setosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="48" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="setosa">Calosota setosa</taxonomicName>
are most similar to those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota albipalpus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="48" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="albipalpus">Calosota albipalpus</taxonomicName>
, as discussed under the latter species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>