<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280168" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120169" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280168" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="52CA17876E056AABC4A036AECA77C2D2" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys dora Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="653" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="652" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280168" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120169" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280168" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:52CA17876E056AABC4A036AECA77C2D2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/52CA17876E056AABC4A036AECA77C2D2" lastPageNumber="653" pageNumber="652">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="652">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155834" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys dora Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys dora Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="652" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dora">Strumigenys dora Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="653" pageNumber="652">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 3.2, HL 0.73, HW 0.57, CI 79, ML 0.37, MI 52, SL 0.46, SI 81, PW 0.36, AL 0.75. Characters of (fora-complex. Mandibles almost straight and at full closure parallel. Apical fork of mandible with 2 spiniform teeth, without intercalary teeth or denticles. Mandible with 2 preapical teeth, situated in the apical third of the length; proximal preapical tooth longer than the distal. Upper scrobe margin ends, or at least becomes extremely indistinct, at about the level of the eye. Eye large, convex, and plainly visible in full-face view. Scape stout, curved near base, widest at about the midlength, the leading edge with a row of hairs which are slightly flattened or spoon-shaped apically. Cephalic dorsum with curved remiform to narrowly clavate ground-pilosity; the upper scrobe margin fringed with a row of hairs which are the same shape and size as those on the dorsum. Cephalic dorsum with 6 simple standing hairs arranged in a transverse row close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Dorsum of head reticulatepunctate. Pronotal humeri rounded, the humeral hair stiffly projecting. Alitrunk dorsum with numerous standing simple hairs. Propodeal declivity with one pair of simple hairs situated at centre of lateral margin. Alitrunk dorsum with small curved narrowly clavate ground-pilosity. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline shallowly convex anteriorly and more or less flat posteriorly; posterior portion of mesonotum slightly depressed below the anterior margin of the propodeum, the metanotal groove represented by a distinct impression. Anterior mesonotum without a distinct carina above the mesothoracic spiracle. Propodeal spines triangular, spongiform; propodeal lamella narrow. Alitrunk dorsum and sides reticulate-punctate, katepisternum smooth and shiny. Petiole node in dorsal view reticulatepunctate and approximately as long as broad. Postpetiole disc reticulate-punctate. Spongiform appendages of petiole and postpetiole absent, except for a spongiform collar on posterior margin of postpetiole. First gastral tergite and sternite densely punctate over anterior half or more of the sclerites; basigastral costulae short and obscured by the punctate sculpture. Dorsum of petiole with at least 3 pairs of standing hairs. Dorsal surfaces of postpetiole and gaster with stout standing hairs which are weakly swollen apically. Colour chocolate brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="653">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 18 km. NW Betroka, 23 Â° 9 ' 48 &quot; S, 45 Â° 58 ' 7 &quot; E, 825 m., 24 - 29. xi. 1994, savanna #. 17216 (hie &amp; Pollock) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="653">Paratypes. 2 queens (alate and dealate) with same data as holotype but coded. 15822, 16453 (BMNH, MCZ).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="653">
Among species of the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="653" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandidieri-group">grandidieri-group</taxonomicName>
with a 2 - dentate apical fork, 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155834" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys dora Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys dora Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="653" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dora">dora</taxonomicName>
is the only one that has the first gastral tergite and sternite densely punctate over the anterior halves or more of the sclerites, coupled with at least 3 pairs of hairs on the petiole dorsum.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>