<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4390878" ID-GBIF-Dataset="cd615cd7-ecb8-4cc3-b074-5ddfab94649a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127598808" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4390878" checkinTime="1484571130511" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Ivan Löbl &amp; Ryo Ogawa" docDate="2016" docId="0C70F70CD743FFEFFF7BABDFDFE7406D" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.48.2.1339-1492.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 48 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle{}" docTitle="Scaphisoma transversale Löbl &amp; Ogawa, 2016, nov.sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageId="77" lastPageNumber="1416" masterDocId="F0498F74D70FFFA2FFC9AB07DD0F4264" masterDocTitle="On the Scaphisomatini (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Scaphidiinae) of the Philippines, IV: the genera Sapitia ACHARD and Scaphisoma LEACH" masterLastPageNumber="1492" masterPageNumber="1339" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415" updateTime="1643500627434" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>On the Scaphisomatini (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Scaphidiinae) of the Philippines, IV: the genera Sapitia ACHARD and Scaphisoma LEACH</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ivan Löbl</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ryo Ogawa</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>48</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1339</mods:start>
<mods:end>1492</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.247206</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">cd615cd7-ecb8-4cc3-b074-5ddfab94649a</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">247206</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4390878" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127598808" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4390878" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:0C70F70CD743FFEFFF7BABDFDFE7406D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0C70F70CD743FFEFFF7BABDFDFE7406D" lastPageId="77" lastPageNumber="1416" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">
<subSubSection box="[178,829,216,238]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="76.[178,1086,216,1606]" box="[178,829,216,238]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,829,216,238]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">
5.2.18.12. 
<taxonomicName box="[286,545,216,238]" class="Insecta" family="Staphylinidae" genus="Scaphisoma" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="transversale">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[286,545,216,238]" italics="true" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">Scaphisoma transversale</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[552,628,217,238]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Figs 37, 178, 179)
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="1415" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="76.[178,1086,216,1606]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">T y p e m a t e r i a l: Holotype 6: Luzon: Lagunas Mt. Makiling (summit rd) 600m, 21- 22.XI.1995 I. Löbl, fungi on logs (MHNG). Paratypes: Luzon, with the same data as the holotype, 4 66, 3 ♀♀ (MHNG); with the same data but moss, epiphytes, bark on logs, 4 ex. (MHNG); with the same data but 21.XI. leaf litter, 1 6 (MHNG); with the same data as the holotype but 28.XI, fungi on large logs, 4 66, 1 ♀ (MHNG); Mt. Makiling, 4 km SE Los Banos, 9 and 12.IV.1977, leg. L.E. Watrous, 13 ex. (MHNG); Lagunas Prov., Mt. Banashaw ca 1 km from Kinabuhayan, 500-700 m, 24.XI.1995, degraded rainforest floor litter, leg. I. Löbl, 1 6 (MHNG); same data but 500 m, 26.XI., 1♀ (MHNG); Mountain Prov., Mt. Data 2250 m, 13.VII.1985, leg. M. Sakai, 1 6, 3♀♀ (EUMJ); same data as preceding but 25.VII., 3♀♀ (EUMJ); same data but 2300 m, 26.VII., 10 ex. (EUMJ, MHNG); Mountain Prov., Mt. Pugui 1800-1900 m, 17.VII.1985, leg. M. Sakai, 2♀♀ (EUMJ); Mountain Prov., Palopal, 2300 m, 30.V.1977, leg. M. Satô, 1 ex. (MHNG); Ifugao Prov., Mt. Polis, 1900 m, 4, 5.VI.1977, leg. M. Satô, 1 ex. (MHNG); with the same data but 5.VI., leg. Y. Kurosawa, 1 ex. (MHNG); Ifugao Prov., Mt. Pangao 2350 m nr. Data 14.VII.1985, leg. M. Sakai, 10 ex. (EUMJ, MHNG).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="77" lastPageNumber="1416" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="76.[178,1086,216,1606]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">D e s c r i p t i o n: Length 1.05-1.35 mm, width 0.74-0.92 mm. Head, pronotum and most of elytra ochreous. Basal margin of pronotum somewhat darkened. Elytra each with darkened, brown transversal band situated anterior apical fourth to third, touching lateral margins but not extending up to sutural stria. Hypomera ochreous, mesoventrite, metaventrite and sternite 1 brown, sternite 2 as sternite 1 or lighter. Apical fifth to fourth of elytra, apical abdominal segments and appendages yellowish. Pronotum and elytra not microsculptured and not iridescent. Length/width ratio of antennomeres as: III 12/6: IV 20/5: V 35/7: VI 32/7: VII 42/11: VIII 34/8: IX 46/10: X 40/13: XI 55/13. Pronotum very finely and fairly densely punctate, with lateral contours evenly rounded, lateral margin carinae usually visible in dorsal view, lateral striae distinctly punctate. Exposed tip of scutellum minute. Elytra with lateral margin carinae usually entirely visible in dorsal view, apical margins truncate, inner apical angles not prominent, situated somewhat posterior level of outer angles; sutural margin raised, sutural striae deep, often starting somewhat posterior level of scutellum, parallel toward apical third of sutural length, converging toward apices, coarsely punctate; adsutural areas narrow, flat, densely and finely punctate, lateral striae distinctly punctate. Elytral disc with punctation dense and coarse from bases to apical third or fourth, puncture rows distinct, puncture intervals mostly about as large to twice as large as puncture diameters; apical fourth to third very finely and sparsely punctate, surface near apices impunctate. Hind wings fully developed. Hypomera and mesanepisterna smooth. Mesepimera about twice as long as intervals to mesocoxae, about four times as long as wide. Median part of metaventrite convex, lacking mesal or apicomesal impressions or striae, with strigulate microsculpture expanded onto areas between mesocoxae and metacoxae but absent from lateral parts of metaventrite; with punctation distinct and dense in middle, very fine and sparse on sides; antecoxal puncture rows present, in impressed lines. Submesocoxal areas 0.03 mm, about as fourth of intervals to metacoxae, submesocoxal lines convex, coarsely punctate. Metanepisternum convex, hardly narrowed anteriad, inner margin rounded, impressed below margin of metaventrite. Tibiae straight. Abdomen with strigulate microsculpture, very finely punctate; sternite 1 with punctation sparse except on basomedian area; submetacoxal areas 0.04 mm, about as third of intervals to apical margin of sternite 1, submetacoxal lines convex, coarsely punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="76.[178,1086,216,1606]" lastBlockId="77.[178,1085,219,521]" lastPageId="77" lastPageNumber="1416" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">
M a l e: Protarsomeres 1 to 3 weakly widened. Aedeagus (
<figureCitation box="[821,970,1496,1518]" captionStart="Figs 177 - 183" captionStartId="139.[178,218,1482,1504]" captionTargetBox="[213,1062,222,1439]" captionTargetId="figure@139.[178,1085,212,1471]" captionTargetPageId="139" captionText="Figs 177 - 183: Aedeagi of Scaphisoma; (177), S. surigaosum (PIC), in lateral view, scale 0.2 mm; (178, 179), S. transversale nov. sp., in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.1 mm; (180, 181), S. acutulum nov. sp., in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.2 mm; (182, 183), S. apomontanum nov. sp., in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/247228/files/figure.png" pageId="76" pageNumber="1415">Figs 178, 179</figureCitation>
) 0.32-0.41 mm long, symmetrical, weakly sclerotized. Apical process of median lobe short, moderately inflexed, with rounded apex, weakly narrowed in dorsal view; articular process small, not prominent. Parameres with small membranous inner lobes, narrowed toward mid-length, in dorsal view evenly broad in apical halves, in lateral view gradually narrowed toward apices. Internal sac tubular, lacking sclerotized pieces, with elongate spine-like structures becoming shorter in apical section.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="77" pageNumber="1416" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="77.[178,1085,219,521]" pageId="77" pageNumber="1416">
E t y m o l o g y: The species epithet refers to the transverse darkened elytral band. Comparative notes: The aedeagal characters of this species suggest relationships with 
<emphasis box="[380,527,381,403]" italics="true" pageId="77" pageNumber="1416">S. banguiense</emphasis>
LÖBL. These species share in particular the comparatively short apical process of the median lobe, the small parameral lobes and the tubular internal sac lacking sclerotized pieces. However, 
<taxonomicName box="[777,930,440,461]" pageId="77" pageNumber="1416">
<emphasis box="[777,930,440,461]" italics="true" pageId="77" pageNumber="1416">S. transversale</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
may be easily distinguished by its colour pattern and by the apical halves of parameres broader in dorsal view and more narrowed apically in lateral view.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>