<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4390896" ID-GBIF-Dataset="cd615cd7-ecb8-4cc3-b074-5ddfab94649a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127598781" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4390896" checkinTime="1484571130511" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Ivan Löbl &amp; Ryo Ogawa" docDate="2016" docId="0C70F70CD75EFFF0FF7BA829DEF341AD" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.48.2.1339-1492.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 48 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle{}" docTitle="Scaphisoma disparides Löbl &amp; Ogawa, 2016, nov.sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="1421" masterDocId="F0498F74D70FFFA2FFC9AB07DD0F4264" masterDocTitle="On the Scaphisomatini (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Scaphidiinae) of the Philippines, IV: the genera Sapitia ACHARD and Scaphisoma LEACH" masterLastPageNumber="1492" masterPageNumber="1339" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420" updateTime="1643500627434" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>On the Scaphisomatini (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Scaphidiinae) of the Philippines, IV: the genera Sapitia ACHARD and Scaphisoma LEACH</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ivan Löbl</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ryo Ogawa</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>48</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1339</mods:start>
<mods:end>1492</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.247206</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">cd615cd7-ecb8-4cc3-b074-5ddfab94649a</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">247206</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4390896" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127598781" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4390896" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:0C70F70CD75EFFF0FF7BA829DEF341AD" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0C70F70CD75EFFF0FF7BA829DEF341AD" lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="1421" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420">
<subSubSection box="[178,791,813,836]" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="81.[178,1086,813,1583]" box="[178,791,813,836]" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,791,813,836]" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420">
5.2.19.6. 
<taxonomicName box="[273,512,813,835]" class="Insecta" family="Staphylinidae" genus="Scaphisoma" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="disparides">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[273,512,813,835]" italics="true" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420">Scaphisoma disparides</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[518,594,814,835]" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Figs 11, 196-198)
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="81" pageNumber="1420" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="81.[178,1086,813,1583]" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420">T y p e m a t e r i a l: Holotype 6: Palawan (central) Conception, sea level, I. Löbl, 6.- 7.XII.1995, fungi on logs, bark (MHNG). Paratypes: Palawan, with the same data as the holotype, 6 66, 2 ♀♀ (MHNG); Palawan, Olanguan [sic], 0-50 m, between Puerto Princesa and Roxas, 1.IX.1985, leg. M. Sakai, 5 66, 10 ♀♀ (EUMJ, MHNG, BZLA); Palawan, Olangoan, sea level, 18 km N San Rafael, 5-6-XII.1995, leg. I. Löbl, 2 66, 1♀ (MHNG); Palawan, Binaluan, 1 6 (SMTD); Palawan, Tigoplan River, Brook’s Pt., near sea level, IV.1947, leg. F.G. Werner, 2 66, 3 ♀♀ (FMNH, MHNG); Palawan, Mantalingajan Range, S. slope of Mt. Balabag, 2800 ft., 4-17.V.1947, forest, leg. F.G. Werner, 1 6, 2♀♀ (FMNH, MHNG); Mindanao, 30 km E of Malaybalay, Busdi, 5-9.V.1996, leg. Bolm, 1 6, 1♀ (SMNS, MHNG).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="1421" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="81.[178,1086,813,1583]" lastBlockId="82.[178,1086,219,969]" lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="1421" pageId="81" pageNumber="1420">Description: Length 1.20-1.25 mm, width 0.82-0.85 mm. Head, thorax and most of elytra brown to blackish-brown, often with somewhat reddish shine. Apical fifth to tenth of elytra light brown to yellowish. Abdomen reddish-brown, lighter than thorax. Appendages light, reddish-brown. Pronotum and elytra not microsculptured and not iridescent. Length/width ratio of antennomeres as: III 12/6: IV 14/5: V 25/5: VI 26/8: VII 36/9: VIII 25/7: IX 33/12: X 30/12: XI 48/12. Pronotum finely and densely punctate, with lateral contours evenly rounded, lateral margin carinae not or hardly visible in dorsal view, lateral striae impunctate. Exposed tip of scutellum minute. Elytra with lateral margin carinae partly or almost entirely visible in dorsal view, apical margins weakly rounded, inner apical angles not prominent, situated somewhat posterior level of outer angles; sutural margin raised, sutural striae deep, bent at base, not extending along basal margin, strongly converging toward apices, distinctly punctate; adsutural areas conspicuously broad anteriad, about twice as wide at level of scutellar tip than at level of midlength, flat, densely and fairly finely punctate anterior mid-length, with punctures usually larger than those on elytral disc, very finely punctate posterior mid-length, lateral striae very finely punctate. Elytral disc with punctation fairly dense and fine, puncture intervals mostly about twice to four times as large as puncture diameters. Hind wings fully developed. Hypomera and mesanepisterna smooth. Mesepimera about as long as intervals to mesocoxae, three times as long as wide. Median part of metaventrite inconspicuously microsculptured, slightly convex, lacking mesal or apicomesal impressions or striae, punctation on prevailing surface of metaventrite very fine and sparse; antecoxal puncture rows absent. Submesocoxal areas 0.05-0.06 mm, about as third of intervals to metacoxae, submesocoxal lines convex, almost impunctate. Metanepisternum flat, narrowed anteriad, inner margin straight, rounded near angles, not impressed below margin of metaventrite. Tibiae straight. Abdomen with strigulate microsculpture, very finely punctate, submetacoxal areas 0.05-0.06 mm, about as half of intervals to apical margin of sternite 1, submetacoxal lines convex, distinctly punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="82.[178,1086,219,969]" pageId="82" pageNumber="1421">
M a l e: Protarsomeres 1 to 3 hardly widened. Aedeagus (
<figureCitation box="[788,926,491,513]" captionStart="Figs 194 - 200" captionStartId="141.[178,218,1458,1480]" captionTargetBox="[198,1059,212,1448]" captionTargetId="figure@141.[178,1085,212,1448]" captionTargetPageId="141" captionText="Figs 194 - 200: Aedeagi of Scaphisoma; (193), S. dispar LÖBL, in lateral view, without proximal part of basal bulb, scale = 0.05 mm; (195), ditto, internal sac in dorsal view, scale = 0.05 mm; (196), S. disparides nov. sp., in dorsal view, scale = 0.1 mm; (197), ditto, in lateral view, without proximal part of basal bulb, scale = 0, 0 5 mm; (198), ditto, internal sac in dorsal view, scale = 0.05 mm; (199, 200), S. distinctum nov. sp., in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/247230/files/figure.png" pageId="82" pageNumber="1421">Figs 196-198</figureCitation>
) 0.35-0.40 mm long, symmetrical, with basal bulb weakly sclerotized, except for its oblique, strongly sclerotized apical side. Articular processes small, not prominent. Apical process of median lobe trifid. Ventral branch of apical process narrow, weakly inflexed, tapering dorsal view, even in lateral view, lacking tubercles. Dorsal branches of apical process tapering. Parameres in lateral view sinuate, widest in middle part and strongly narrowed apically, in dorsal view almost straight in basal halves, curved and gradually narrowed in apical halves. Internal sac with central membranous vesicle covered by scale-like structures, partly overlapping long and fairly sclerotized admesal spines.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="82" pageNumber="1421" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="82.[178,1086,219,969]" pageId="82" pageNumber="1421">
E t y m o l o g y: The species epithet derives from 
<emphasis box="[747,841,763,784]" italics="true" pageId="82" pageNumber="1421">S. dispar</emphasis>
; the Greek suffix ides means descendent.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="82" pageNumber="1421" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="82.[178,1086,219,969]" pageId="82" pageNumber="1421">
C o m p a r a t i v e n o t e s: This species shares most diagnostic characters with 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="82" pageNumber="1421">S. dispar</emphasis>
. It may be distinguished by the much darker colour of the body, the coarser punctures on anterior parts of adsutural areas, the hardly visible microsculpture on the median part of the metaventrite, the ventral branch of apical process tapering in lateral view, and the longer narrow apical section of the parameres as seen in lateral view.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>