<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4390829" ID-GBIF-Dataset="cd615cd7-ecb8-4cc3-b074-5ddfab94649a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127598787" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4390829" checkinTime="1484571130511" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Ivan Löbl &amp; Ryo Ogawa" docDate="2016" docId="0C70F70CD74FFFE0FF7BAE50DC4B4387" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.48.2.1339-1492.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 48 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle{}" docTitle="Scaphisoma werneri Löbl &amp; Ogawa, 2016, nov.sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="1405" masterDocId="F0498F74D70FFFA2FFC9AB07DD0F4264" masterDocTitle="On the Scaphisomatini (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Scaphidiinae) of the Philippines, IV: the genera Sapitia ACHARD and Scaphisoma LEACH" masterLastPageNumber="1492" masterPageNumber="1339" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403" updateTime="1643500627434" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>On the Scaphisomatini (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Scaphidiinae) of the Philippines, IV: the genera Sapitia ACHARD and Scaphisoma LEACH</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ivan Löbl</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ryo Ogawa</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>48</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1339</mods:start>
<mods:end>1492</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.247206</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">cd615cd7-ecb8-4cc3-b074-5ddfab94649a</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">247206</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4390829" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127598787" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4390829" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:0C70F70CD74FFFE0FF7BAE50DC4B4387" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0C70F70CD74FFFE0FF7BAE50DC4B4387" lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="1405" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">
<subSubSection box="[178,765,1367,1389]" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1086,1367,1593]" box="[178,765,1367,1389]" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">
<heading bold="true" box="[178,765,1367,1389]" fontSize="9" level="3" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403" reason="6">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,765,1367,1389]" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">
5.2.14.8. 
<taxonomicName box="[273,486,1367,1389]" class="Insecta" family="Staphylinidae" genus="Scaphisoma" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="werneri">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[273,486,1367,1389]" italics="true" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">Scaphisoma werneri</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[493,569,1367,1388]" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(
<figureCitation box="[582,662,1367,1389]" captionStart="Figs 41 - 45" captionStartId="116.[178,218,1426,1448]" captionText="Figs 41 - 45: Habitus of Scaphisoma; (41), S. tricoloripennne nov. sp.; (42), S. trifurcatum nov. sp.; (43), S. trilobum nov. sp., male; (44), ditto, female; (45), S. werneri nov. sp. Scale: 1.0 mm." pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">Figs 45</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[673,758,1367,1389]" captionStart="Figs 151 - 156" captionStartId="135.[178,218,1498,1520]" captionTargetBox="[206,1059,220,1478]" captionTargetId="figure@135.[178,1069,212,1487]" captionTargetPageId="135" captionText="Figs 151 - 156: Aedeagi of Scaphisoma; (151), S. iridescens nov. sp., aedeagus in dorsal view, internal sac extruded; (152), ditto, paramere in dorsal view, scale = 0.2 mm; (153, 154), S. werneri nov. sp., aedeagus in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.2 mm; (155, 156), S. dissymmetricum nov. sp., aedeagus in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.1 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/247224/files/figure.png" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">153-154</figureCitation>
)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="1404" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1086,1367,1593]" lastBlockId="65.[178,1086,219,1577]" lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="1404" pageId="64" pageNumber="1403">T y p e m a t e r i a l: Holotype 6: Burungkot, Upi, Cotabato Prov., Mindanao Elev. 1500 ft. I, 1-9, 1947 / Lot 154 taken on polypores /CNHM-Philippine Zool. Exped. (1946-47) F.G. Werner leg. (FMNH). Paratypes: with the same data as the holotype, 5 66, 3♀♀ (FMNH, MHNG); 1 6 with the same data but under bark of smooth barked soft log (FMNH); Mindanao, Cotabato Prov., 50 km N of Parang, 500 ft., 6.XII.1946, on encrusting polypore, leg. F.G. Werner, 2 66, 1 ♀ (FMNH, MHNG); with the same data but 20 km N. of Parang, 200 ft., 1 6 (FMNH); Leyte, Visca N Baybay, sec. forest, 100-200 m, 27.II.1991, leg. W. Schawaller et al., 2 66 (SMNS; MHNG). Description: Length 1.55-1.95 mm, width 1.23-1.35 mm. Head, pronotum, hypomera, large parts of elytra, apical abdominal segments and appendages ochreous to yellowish, or pronotum narrowly darkened along basal margin. Elytra at bases, on adsutural areas, along sutural striae from bases about to apical third, and on transverse band anterior apical third darkened, darken elytral areas usually surrounding more or less distinct ochreous discal spot. Mesoventrite, metaventrite, metanepisterna, metanepisterna and sternite 1 darkened, brown to blackish. Pronotum and elytra not microsculptured and not iridescent. Length/width ratio of antennomeres as: III 16/8: IV 40/6: V 70/8: VI 60/9: VII 68/14: VIII 56/9: IX 73/14: X 68/14: XI 77/14. Pronotum finely and densely punctate, with lateral margins evenly rounded, lateral margin carinae usually visible in dorsal view, lateral striae impunctate. Exposed tip of scutellum minute. Elytra with lateral margin carinae usually entirely visible in dorsal view, with apical margins sexually dimorphic; sutural margin raised, sutural striae deep, not bent at base and not extending along basal margin, strongly converging toward apices, coarsely punctate; adsutural areas conspicuously broad anteriad, about twice as wide at level of scutellar tip as at mid-length, flat, densely and coarsely punctate, with punctures usually largest and more dense near base; lateral striae very finely punctate. Elytral disc with punctation dense, coarse on inner half, in particular near base, becoming fine laterally. Hind wings fully developed. Hypomera and mesanepisterna smooth. Mesepimera shorter than intervals to mesocoxae, about three times as long as wide. Metaventrite with strigulate microsculpture covering entire sides. Median part of metaventrite convex between mesocoxae, deeply impressed apically, punctation on prevailing surface of metaventrite extremely fine and sparse; antecoxal puncture rows present, in impressed striae. Submesocoxal areas 0.03 mm, about as sixth of intervals to metacoxae, submesocoxal lines parallel, coarsely punctate, punctures not extended by striae. Metanepisternum flat, not or slightly narrowed anteriad, inner margin straight, suture conspicuously deep. Protibiae straight, mesotibiae and metatibiae sexually dimorphic. Abdomen with strigulate microsculpture, very finely and sparsely punctate; submetacoxal areas 0.02- 0.03 mm, about as sixth to ninth of intervals to apical margin of sternite 1, submetacoxal lines parallel, coarsely punctate.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="65" pageNumber="1404" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,1086,219,1577]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1404">
M a l e: Elytra with apical margins rounded, inner apical angles not prominent, finely crenulated, situated in level with outer angles. Mesotibiae robust, thicker than metatibiae, distinctly curved, metatibiae slightly curved. Protarsomeres 1 to 3 and mesotarsomeres 1 and 2 strongly widened, tarsomeres 1 wider than apices of tibiae. Aedeagus (
<figureCitation captionStart="Figs 151 - 156" captionStartId="135.[178,218,1498,1520]" captionTargetBox="[206,1059,220,1478]" captionTargetId="figure@135.[178,1069,212,1487]" captionTargetPageId="135" captionText="Figs 151 - 156: Aedeagi of Scaphisoma; (151), S. iridescens nov. sp., aedeagus in dorsal view, internal sac extruded; (152), ditto, paramere in dorsal view, scale = 0.2 mm; (153, 154), S. werneri nov. sp., aedeagus in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.2 mm; (155, 156), S. dissymmetricum nov. sp., aedeagus in dorsal and lateral views, scale = 0.1 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/247224/files/figure.png" pageId="65" pageNumber="1404">Figs 153, 154</figureCitation>
) 1.15-1.28 mm long, symmetrical, strongly sclerotized. Articular processes robust, not prominent. Apical process of median lobe bifid, long, weakly inflexed. Ventral branch of apical process robust and gradually narrowed in proximal two thirds, narrow in apical third, truncate and rather hook-like at apex, sinuate in lateral view. Dorsal branch of median lobe gradually narrowed. Parameres in lateral view strongly bent posterior bases, strongly widened toward large apical section covered by dense pores. Parameres in dorsal view almost straight posterior bases, with evenly arcuate outer margin in apical halves, inner margin membranous and lobed in apical halves. Internal sac complex, with large, strongly sclerotized teeth, spines and scale-like structures, narrowed apically, and with large apical plate extended by strong tooth.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,1086,219,1577]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1404">F e m a l e: Elytra with apical margins oblique, inner apical angles acute and prominent, situated posterior level of outer angles. Meso- and metatibiae straight, similar.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="66" pageNumber="1405" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,1085,219,483]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1405">E t y m o l o g y: The species is named in honour of one of its collector, Floyd G. Werner.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="66" pageNumber="1405" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,1085,219,483]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1405">
C o m p a r a t i v e n o t e s: The species resembles 
<emphasis box="[761,908,285,307]" italics="true" pageId="66" pageNumber="1405">S. biplagiatum</emphasis>
, and its aedeagal characters suggest close relationships of these species. The females of 
<emphasis box="[899,912,315,336]" italics="true" pageId="66" pageNumber="1405">S</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis box="[925,1004,315,336]" italics="true" pageId="66" pageNumber="1405">werneri</emphasis>
may be readily distinguished by the shape of the elytral apices. The males possess a unique shape of the apex of the median lobe. In addition, the shape of the parameres, in particular in lateral view, is diagnostic for this new species. The presence of strigulate microsculpture on the entire lateral parts of the metaventrite and the longer antennae are also diagnostic for 
<emphasis box="[214,227,462,483]" italics="true" pageId="66" pageNumber="1405">S</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis box="[239,317,462,483]" italics="true" pageId="66" pageNumber="1405">werneri</emphasis>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>