<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F8468BC7D7DAC6FEBDF579C37F" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Pagarenes erythropus CAMERON" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="160" lastPageNumber="1477" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F8468BC7D7DAC6FEBDF579C37F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F8468BC7D7DAC6FEBDF579C37F" lastPageId="160" lastPageNumber="1477" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">
<subSubSection box="[178,635,320,342]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="159.[178,635,320,342]" box="[178,635,320,342]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">
<heading box="[178,635,320,342]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,596,320,342]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">
<taxonomicName authority="CAMERON" authorityName="CAMERON" box="[178,527,320,342]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pagarenes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erythropus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,405,320,342]" italics="true" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">Pagarenes erythropus</emphasis>
CAMERON
</taxonomicName>
(Plate
</emphasis>
37
<emphasis bold="true" box="[627,635,320,342]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">)</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="159.[178,933,361,410]" lastBlockId="159.[178,291,424,445]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">
<taxonomicName authority="CAMERON, 1903" authorityName="CAMERON" authorityYear="1903" box="[178,537,360,380]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pagarenes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erythropus">
<emphasis box="[178,378,360,380]" italics="true" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">Pagarenes erythropus</emphasis>
CAMERON, 1903
</taxonomicName>
- Ztchr. Hym. Dipt. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[726,737,360,380]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">3</emphasis>
: 184, 
<specimenCount box="[795,807,364,385]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. 
<taxonomicName authority=": HEINRICH, 1974" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1974" box="[178,539,386,406]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pagarenes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erythropus">
<emphasis box="[178,378,386,406]" italics="true" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">Pagarenes erythropus</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[391,539,386,406]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" pagination="103 - 197" refId="ref142818" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1974): Burmesische Ichneumoninae IX. Tribus Platylabini. - Annales Zoologici Wars. 32, 8: 103 - 197." type="journal article" year="1974">HEINRICH, 1974</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ann. Zool. Wars. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[723,746,386,406]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">32</emphasis>
(8): 168-169, 
<specimenCount box="[877,889,390,411]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="159.[178,1085,460,599]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">F l a g e l l u m. Slender bristle-shaped with 34 segments and white annulus (semiannulus) dorsally on 7-10(11) segments, behind white annulus widened and flattened ventrally, basal segment long, thin, from lateral 3,7 times longer than width at apex, all segments elongated. Flagellum 1,2 times longer than front wing and body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="160" lastPageNumber="1477" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="159.[178,1085,614,1251]" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">H e a d. Head contour from front strongly narrowed downwards with large eyes; genae from front straightly narrowed to mandible base, short, 4,8 times shorter than height of an eye. Vertex straightly slanted down to occipital carina; temples from above strongly and roundly narrowed behind eyes, from lateral parallel to hind margin of eye, short, in middle 1,3 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye; occipital carina roundly impressed, reach level of eyes but not reach level of hind ocelli, sharp on all distance, meeting with hypostomal carina far from mandible base; length of genae 1,5 times shorter than mandible base width; mandibles at base sharply narrowed and place of narrowing concavely-parallel sided to apex with long upper tooth and short lower considerably moved inside; second segment of maxillary palps normal, not swollen, palps long, thin; clypeus strongly convex, transversal with straight thinned front margin and oblique lateral ones, rather sharply separated from face by deep impression; clypeal foveae small, deep, roundish; labrum triangle, rather stronlly protrude from under clypeus, equal by width to front margin of clypeus; middle field of face only just elevated and approximately equal by width to lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities slightly impressed, polished, laterally reach to margins of eyes, but not reah front ocellus level, with sharp lateral tubercles but without tubercle between antennal fossae, at its place margin of antennal cavities sharply elevated above middle field of face; front margins of antennal fossae sharply elevated; ocelli rather strongly convex, of moderate size, diameter of lateral ocellus only just lesser than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle distinctly elevated. Surface of face and clypeus densely punctured by small punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="159.[178,1085,1266,1581]" lastBlockId="160.[178,1085,219,563]" lastPageId="160" lastPageNumber="1477" pageId="159" pageNumber="1476">T h o r a x. Collar of pronotum short, pronotal furrow shallow, pronotal base smoothly rounded, strongly sharpened backwards; lateral surface with distinct punctures at upper half; epomiae sharp. Mesonotum strongly convex, only just longer than width; notauli only in form of broad impressions at base; surface of mesonotum with dense rough punctures (punctures almost merged), without microsculpture, with slight shine; subalarum moderately thick, not sharpened; speculum with sparse shining; area of mesopleural fovea deeply and broadly impressed; sternauli in form of only just visible impressions at base; lover part of mesopleurae without distinct bend; surface of mesopleurae at lover half distinctly wrinkle-punctured, without microsculpture; scutellum from lateral distinctly convex and smoothly slanted backwards, laterally sharply carinated up to apex, carinae from behind practically close and scutellum thus practically carinated from behind; horizontal surface moderately convex with dense smoothed punctures; without microsculpture. Hind margin metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral weakly angular, short, length of horizontal part two times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum, with exception of most part of costulae and hind part of coxal carina sharp, costula marked only at base; area superomedia square, slightly rounded in front, high elevated above lateral fields; areae dentiparae with strong flat teeth, carina closing areae dentiparae backwards also strongly broadened; spiracles very small, roundish, 1,4 times longer than width (length of spiracle equal 0,4 breadth of field at place of spiracle). Horizontal part of propodeum irregularly roughly-wrinkled; metapleurae roughly densely-punctured by large punctures; surface of propodeum with slight shine.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="160.[178,1014,578,600]" box="[178,1014,578,600]" pageId="160" pageNumber="1477">L e g s. Long, slender; claws of hind tarsi rather long and thin, gradually curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="160.[178,1085,615,696]" pageId="160" pageNumber="1477">W i n g s. Areolet quadrangular, symmetrical; radius strongly sinuous, long; nervulus intersticial; ramulus only just marked; pterostigma rather broad, light; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Front wing only 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="160.[178,1086,712,1035]" pageId="160" pageNumber="1477">A b d o m e n. From above longish-oval; tergites 6-7 not retracted, ovipositor sheath not protrude; second tergite at apex 1,2 times wider than length. Petiolus distinctly wider than height, from above gradually broadened to postpetiolus with distinct but slight lateral carinae, dorsomedian carina merged with median one at middle of petiolus; middle field of postpetiolus slightly elevated, some wider than lateral fields; distance between spiracles more than distance from spiracles to apex; surface of postpetiolus only just wrinkled. Gastrocoeli distinctly impressed, moderately long; thyridia distinct, slightly oblique, somewhat wider than interval between them; interval wrinkled; lunulae expressed, small; surface of tergites 2-3 densely punctured, interspaces narrower than punctures, without microsculpture, slightly shining, third punctured by superficial punctures, others slightly shagreen. Hypopygium pointed with longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="160.[178,1085,1051,1253]" pageId="160" pageNumber="1477">C o l o r a t i o n: Body with rich yellow-white pattern: genae, mandibles, most part of clypeus and face and fronto-vertical orbits broadly and stripes on outer ones, scutellum and postsculellum completely, apical part of propodeum, apical band of first tergite, interrupted bands on tergites 2-3, 5-th narrowly on apex, 6-th at most part, 7-th completely; front coxae completely, middle at most part, hind at apex, trochanteres 1 of front and middle legs completely and first segment of hind tarsi. Front and middle legs mainly light-red, hind ones mainly reddish black.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="160.[178,809,1269,1291]" box="[178,809,1269,1291]" pageId="160" pageNumber="1477">
S i z e: Body length: 7,1; front wing: 6,2; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[725,805,1269,1291]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="8.4" pageId="160" pageNumber="1477" unit="mm" value="8.4">8,4 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>