<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846BBC7C7DAC6FD89F4DDC289" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Platybirmania acutinota HEINRICH" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="176" lastPageNumber="1493" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846BBC7C7DAC6FD89F4DDC289" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846BBC7C7DAC6FD89F4DDC289" lastPageId="176" lastPageNumber="1493" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">
<subSubSection box="[178,653,629,651]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="175.[178,653,629,651]" box="[178,653,629,651]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">
<heading box="[178,653,629,651]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,653,629,651]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,545,629,651]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Platybirmania" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acutinota">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,431,629,651]" italics="true" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">Platybirmania acutinota</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 43)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="175.[178,942,669,692]" lastBlockId="175.[178,253,707,727]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH 1974" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1974" box="[178,548,669,689]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Platybirmania" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acutinota">
<emphasis box="[178,400,669,689]" italics="true" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">Platybirmania acutinota</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[406,548,669,689]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" pagination="103 - 197" refId="ref142818" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1974): Burmesische Ichneumoninae IX. Tribus Platylabini. - Annales Zoologici Wars. 32, 8: 103 - 197." type="journal article" year="1974">HEINRICH 1974</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ann. Zool. Wars. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[732,755,669,689]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">32</emphasis>
(8): 192-193, 
<specimenCount box="[887,899,673,694]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. M a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="175.[178,1086,743,823]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">F l a g e l l u m: With 39 segments, bristle-shaped with white semiannulus on segments 11-18; basal segments moderately long, first segment 3 times longer than width at apex. Flagellum with narrow tyloides on segments 11-18.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="176" lastPageNumber="1493" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="175.[178,1086,838,1417]" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">H e a d: Head contour from front roundly narrowed downwards, only 1,1 times wider than height; malar space almost 7 times lesser than height of an eye; from above head contour transversal, 1,9 times wider than length; contour of head triangle from lateral, angle between face surface and frons from side almost right. Vertex from lateral gradually slanting down to occipital carina directly behind hind ocelli; temples from above convex, roundly narrowed backwards, moderately long, in middle 1,5 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye, from lateral slightly widened downwards from middle, at the base of mandible with slight impression; occipital carina from above almost straight, practically not impressed to ocelli, low, meeting with hypostomal carina on mandible base, at the base of mandible slightly widened; malar space approximately 2 times shorter than mandible base width; mandibles very wide at base, in middle strongly curved (almost at right angle), immediately from base uniformly narrowed, lower tooth small, slightly moved inside; clypeus flat, widely gradually curved in form of arch, 1,2 times wider than height, only just visible separated from face; clypeal foveae small, rounded; middle field of face only just expressed, wider than lateral fields; antennal cavities of moderate size, deep, not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, without rounded tubercles and with small tooth between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae high elevated; frons under front ocellus with slight impression; ocelli rather large, convex, diameter of lateral ocellus equal to distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle high elevated. Surface of clypeus and face densely superficially punctured, without microsculpture, frons smooth, polished.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="175.[178,1085,1432,1600]" lastBlockId="176.[178,1086,219,651]" lastPageId="176" lastPageNumber="1493" pageId="175" pageNumber="1492">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum short, transverse furrow shallow; pronotal ridge sharply thickened (swollen), especially in front, thus, that pronotal ridge from above from the front almost perpendicular to longitudinal axis of a body. Mesonotum strongly convex, of equal length and breadth, notauli only just marked at base, practically not developed; external margin of mesonotum between tegula and scuto-scutellar groove with projecting triangle process; surface of mesonotum rather densely punctured, shining, without microsculpture; prepectus behind front coxae strongly impressed; prepectal carina at lower part high elevated, thick; subalarum normal, moderately thick, not sharpened; speculum smooth, shining, area of mesopleural fovea deep; sternauli absent or only just marked in front third in form of very slight impression; mesopleurae densely punctured; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, sharply divided on horizontal and vertical parts, sharply carinated laterally and at apex, lateral carinae high, horizontal part slightly convex, roughly wrinklypunctured, slightly shining; foveae of postscutellum practically merged. Hind margin of metanotum with small narrow triangular projections. Propodeum short, horizontal part considerably shorter than area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum developed, with exception of carina, limiting area superomedia from front; area superomedia hexagonal, narrowed in front, approximately of equal length and breadth, costulae beyond middle; areae dentiparae with short, but distinct teeth; spiracles of moderate size, longish-oval (0,6 breadth of area spiraculifera at place of spiracle), 1,9-2,2 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture; metapleurae with superficial punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="176.[178,777,666,688]" box="[178,777,666,688]" pageId="176" pageNumber="1493">L e g s: Quite long and slender. Claws thin, sharply curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="176.[178,1086,703,813]" pageId="176" pageNumber="1493">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, petiolate, asymmetrical, external vein of apex longer than internal; stigma broad, dark; radius practically straight; nervulus interstitial; ramulus distinct; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Front wing 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="176.[178,1087,828,1172]" pageId="176" pageNumber="1493">A b d o m e n Elongated, from above from middle of tergite 3 uniformly narrowed backwards, apical tergites far protrude, second tergite transversal, apex of abdomen compressed from sides. Petiolus at base only just wider than height; place of transform of petiolus to postpetiolus (from lateral) with gradual, but distinct bend, lateral carinae sharp, surface between them slightly wrinkled; postpetiolus from above strongly and sharply broadened; spiracles of postpetiolus roundish, small, distance between them equal to distance to apex; middle field of postpetiolus high elevated and distinctly carinated, lateral fields narrower than middle field; postpetiolus wrinkly-punctured, slightly shining. Gastrocoeli deep and broad, transverse; thyridia sharp, closed to base of tergite, interval many narrower than breadth of thyridia, with longitudinal impression almost to apex of second tergite; lunulae large, distinctly expressed; tergites 2-4 densely and roughly punctured, other tergites smooth, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="176.[178,1086,1188,1239]" pageId="176" pageNumber="1493">C o l o r a t i o n: Black with reach yellow coloration on head, thorax and abdomen. All tergites with white band at apex. Tarsi of hind legs yellow-white.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="176.[178,653,1254,1276]" box="[178,653,1254,1276]" pageId="176" pageNumber="1493">
S i z e: Body length: 9,8; front wing: 
<quantity box="[569,649,1254,1276]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="7.3" pageId="176" pageNumber="1493" unit="mm" value="7.3">7,3 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>