<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F8460BC756DAC6FCF3F545C77B" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Ctenocalus schizoaspis HEINRICH" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="33" lastPageNumber="1349" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F8460BC756DAC6FCF3F545C77B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F8460BC756DAC6FCF3F545C77B" lastPageId="33" lastPageNumber="1349" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">
<subSubSection box="[178,627,783,806]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="31.[178,627,783,806]" box="[178,627,783,806]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">
<heading box="[178,627,783,806]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,627,783,806]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,531,783,806]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ctenocalus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="schizoaspis">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,416,783,805]" italics="true" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">Ctenocalus schizoaspis</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 6)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="31.[178,953,823,847]" lastBlockId="31.[178,268,861,882]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH 1967" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1967" box="[178,537,823,843]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ctenocalus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="schizoaspis">
<emphasis box="[178,388,823,843]" italics="true" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">Ctenocalus schizoaspis</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[394,537,823,843]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" pagination="1 - 1258" refId="ref142685" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1967 - 1968): Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of the Sahara. - Monograph. Farmington State College Press 1 - 5: 1 - 1258." type="book chapter" year="1967">HEINRICH 1967</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ichn. Stenop. of Africa 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[772,783,823,843]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">2</emphasis>
: 381, 394, 
<specimenCount box="[896,908,827,848]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. M a l e:
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="31.[178,1085,897,1007]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, with 36 segments and with white annulus on segments 13-18; all segments longer than wide, without constriction between segments, first segment 4 times longer than width at apex; tyloides absent. Flagellum almost equal by length to front wing and slightly shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="33" lastPageNumber="1350" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="31.[178,1086,1022,1600]" pageId="31" pageNumber="1348">H e a d: Head contour from front roundly-square, slightly transversal (1,3 times wider than height) with strongly swollen long genae; length of genae equal 0,4 of eye height; surface of face flat, but distinctly separated from genae, clypeus also separated from face by distinct clypeal foveae and lateral sutures; head contour from above transversal, 1,5 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral convex, roundly curved to occipital carina; temples long, longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, temples from above swollen behind eyes, slightly and roundly narrowed backwards, from side parallel to hind margin of eye; occipital carina from above strongly roundly impressed but far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, sharp with the exception lower quarter, erased before place of confluence with hypostomal carina; malar space almost equal to mandible base width; mandible sickle-shaped, gradually curved, lower tooth moved inside and situated practically in same (horizontal) plane with upper tooth; clypeus flat with gradually rounded front margin and slightly impressed in middle, clypeus transversal, two times wider than height, not separated from face; clypeal foveae small, but distinct and quite deep; labrum long, triangular; middle field of face only just visible elevated (practically not elevated) in upper half above lateral fields; antennal cavities deeply impressed, reach level of front ocellus and laterally borders of eyes, laterally above antennal fossae without tubercles, with only just visible tubercle between antennal fossae; ocelli small, diameter of lateral ocellus equal 0,7 distance to eye. Only surface of face and clypeus with superficial punctures, other part of head not sculpturated, smooth, polished.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1086,219,885]" pageId="32" pageNumber="1349">T h o r a x: Collar long with leaf-like broadened front margin (lamelliform); pronotal base slightly and uniformly curved; epomiae very slightly expressed, only just marked; pronotal ridge not thickened. Mesonotum moderately convex, only just wider than length, middle field slightly elevated above lateral fields; notauli marked just only at base as slight impressions; surface of mesonotum punctured by big punctures, more small on lateral fields, shining, without microsculpture; subalarum thin, sharp, high elevated; speculum with big punctures, shining; mesopleural fovea small, deep, area of mesopleural fovea slightly impressed; sternauli absent; surface of mesopleurae at upper half punctured by big punctures, at lower wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture; mesopleural suture not interrupted by distinct ribs, almost smooth; scutellum high elevated, laterally carinated by leaf-like broadened at horizontal part carinae; horizontal part with weak (pyramidal) elevation, its surface with sparse big smoothed punctures, shining; lateral foveae on postscutellum practically not developed. Hind margin of metanotum smooth, without projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae of propodeum. Propodeum from lateral short, convex, without sharp bend between horizontal and vertical surfaces; length of horizontal part equal to length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of horizontal part of propodeum slightly expressed, front branches of carinae, limiting area superomedia not expressed up to costulae and presented only by rugosity, costulae distinct; apical branch of lateral longitudinal carina and carina dentipara interiores of area dentipara absent; coxal carina absent, area of area coxalis marked by sharp longitudinal ribs; spiracles long, but not slit-shaped. Surface of propodeum wrinkled, shining, without microsculpture; metapleurae very densely and roughly wrinklypunctured.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1085,900,951]" pageId="32" pageNumber="1349">L e g s: Slender, thin; front coxae comparatively small; claws small, smooth, slightly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1085,967,1076]" pageId="32" pageNumber="1349">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal with very narrow base, almost symmetrical, intercubital veins of equal length; stigma narrow, dark; radius strongly curved; nervulus slightly postfurcal and reclival; ramulus expressed. Veins of both wings dark, membrane of wings hyaline. Length of front wing 1,4 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1085,1092,1407]" pageId="32" pageNumber="1349">A b d o m e n: From above broadly-oval with very sharp constrictions between segments. First tergite from lateral almost straight, without break at place of transition of petiolus to postpetiolus, lateral carinae of petiolus absent, petiolus from lateral smooth; from above petiolus very narrow, sharply and roundly transform into broad postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus only just marked and not limited by carinae, surface of postpetiolus with superficial elongated punctures. Gastrocoeli short, deep, oblique relatively longitudinal axis of а body and almost reach to lateral borders of tergite; thyridia distinct, three times wider than interval between them; surface of interval delicate wrinkled; lunulae absent; surface of second and third tergites very roughly wrinkly-punctured; forth tergite densely and roughly punctured, with slight rugosity, fifth tergite with traces of punctures, other tergites smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,1085,1422,1561]" pageId="32" pageNumber="1349">C o l o r a t i o n: Head black, face dark-brown; thorax ferruginous; abdomen black with ferruginous base and white spots on 5th, stripe at apex on 6th and completely white tergite 7; legs black (front and middle dark-brown), front and middle coxae, stripes on front surface of femora and tibiae of front and middle legs and third segment of hind tarsi white.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="32.[178,822,1576,1598]" lastBlockId="33.[178,1085,219,270]" lastPageId="33" lastPageNumber="1350" pageId="32" pageNumber="1349">
S i z e: Body length: 12,0; front wing: 8,4; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[737,818,1576,1598]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="9.2" pageId="32" pageNumber="1349" unit="mm" value="9.2">9,2 mm</quantity>
. F e m a l e (according to 
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[452,615,219,241]" pageId="33" pageNumber="1350" pagination="1 - 1258" refId="ref142685" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1967 - 1968): Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of the Sahara. - Monograph. Farmington State College Press 1 - 5: 1 - 1258." type="book chapter" year="1967">HEINRICH 1967</bibRefCitation>
): «abdomen semiamblypygous, claws of tarsi of all legs strongly pectinate, frontal orbits narrowly white».
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>