<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84650C732DAC6FF24F5FEC5CF" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Hoplismenus pica WESMAEL" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="1386" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84650C732DAC6FF24F5FEC5CF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84650C732DAC6FF24F5FEC5CF" lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="1386" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">
<subSubSection box="[178,589,216,239]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="68.[178,589,216,239]" box="[178,589,216,239]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">
<heading box="[178,589,216,239]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,589,216,239]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">
<taxonomicName authority="WESMAEL" authorityName="WESMAEL" box="[178,481,216,239]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hoplismenus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pica">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,366,216,238]" italics="true" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">Hoplismenus pica</emphasis>
WESMAEL
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 18)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="68.[178,900,257,306]" lastBlockId="68.[178,291,320,341]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">
<taxonomicName authority="WESMAEL 1855" authorityName="WESMAEL" authorityYear="1855" box="[178,493,256,276]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hoplismenus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pica">
<emphasis box="[178,341,256,276]" italics="true" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">Hoplismenus pica</emphasis>
WESMAEL 1855
</taxonomicName>
- Bull. Acad. Sc. 
<collectingCountry box="[657,739,256,276]" name="Belgium" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">Belgique</collectingCountry>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[745,768,256,276]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">22</emphasis>
(2): 406, 
<specimenCount box="[857,869,260,281]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. 
<taxonomicName authority=": CEBALLOS 1924" authorityName="CEBALLOS" authorityYear="1924" box="[178,503,282,302]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hoplismenus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pica">
<emphasis box="[178,341,282,302]" italics="true" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">Hoplismenus pica</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="CEBALLOS G" box="[353,503,282,302]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" pagination="1 - 335" refId="ref141942" refString="CEBALLOS G. (1924): Estudios sobre Ichneumonidos de Espana. I. Subfamilia Joppinae (Tribus Joppini, Amblytelini, Listrodromini). - Trabajos del Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales, Serie Zoologia. 50: 1 - 335." type="journal article" year="1924">CEBALLOS 1924</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Trab. Mus. Nac. Cien. Nat. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[775,798,282,302]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">50</emphasis>
: 32-33, 
<specimenCount box="[875,887,286,307]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="68.[178,1085,356,495]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, very long and slender, not widened beyond middle and slightly flattened ventrally, with 41 segments and white annulus on segments 7-12; segments of flagellum clearly separated (differentiated); first segment 3 times longer than width at apex; approximately segment 15 square from lateral. Flagellum 1,1 times shorter than the front wing and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="1386" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="68.[178,1087,510,1147]" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">H e a d: Head contour from front sharply, almost straightly narrowed downwards, transversal, 1,3 times wider than height; genae from front very long, 3,4 times shorter than height of eye; head from above transversal, 1,6 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral straightly abrupt after the ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, equal to longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, from lateral slightly narrowed downwards, from above sharply and almost straightly narrowed behind eyes; occipital carina high, sharp, from above quite deeply and roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina visible from lateral, meeting with occipital carina far before base of mandible; length of abscissula equal 0,7 breadth of mandible base width; malar space 1,5 times longer than the mandible base width; mandibles narrow, sharply narrowed just behind base, with small weak teeth, lower tooth moved inside relative to upper; clypeus convex in longitudinal and transverse directions, transversal, approximately 1,8 times wider than length, separated from face by slight broad impression, with straight front margin and rounded lateral corners; clypeal foveae small, but sharp and deep; labrum protrude from under clypeus, equal by breadth to clypeus front margin, long, roundish; middle field of face distinctly elevated, in middle equal to lateral fields; antennal cavities deeply impressed, reach borders of eyes, without distinct upper border, laterally above antennal fossae without tubercles and with only just visible interantennal tubercle; front margins of antennal fossae high elevated above face surface; ocelli small, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,9 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle distinct, but slightly elevated. Surface of head wrinkly-punctured with microsculpture, dull, except face and clypeus.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="68.[178,1085,1163,1595]" lastBlockId="69.[178,1085,219,299]" lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="1386" pageId="68" pageNumber="1385">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum rather long with rounded front margin (from above); transverse furrow deep, not interrupted by keel; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp, short; pronotal base gradually curved. Mesonotum moderately convex, 1,2 times longer than width; notauli only as slight impressions at base; axillary tongue developed; surface of mesonotum with confluent punctures, matt with strongly developed microsculpture; subalarum high, not sharpened; speculum roughly wrinkly-punctured without microsculpture; area of mesopleural fovea sharply impressed with transversal wrinkles; prepectal carina almost reach pronotum, sharp all round; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs; border between vertical and horizontal parts of mesopleurae expressed; sternauli absent; lower surface of mesopleurae roughly wrinkly-punctured, matt, upper third without microsculpture; scutellum very sharply elevated above postscutellum, gradually convex, laterally not carinated. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangular projections. Horizontal part of propodeum 1,3 times shorter than area posteromedia in middle; carinae of apical half of area dentipara reduced, basal area short and deep, area superomedia high elevated above lateral fields and carinated by high sinuous carinae, carina metapleuralis sharp and high all round, coxal carina in form of separate interrupted carinae; spiracles long, slit-shaped; propodeum with strong apophysises. Surface of propodeum cellular-wrinkled, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="69.[178,1084,314,366]" pageId="69" pageNumber="1386">L e g s: Very long and slender. At dried samples hind tibiae with dorsal impression at base. Claws thin, smooth, gradually curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="69.[178,1085,381,491]" pageId="69" pageNumber="1386">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, with wide base, symmetrical; stigma rather narrow, dark brown, radial cell long, radius almost straight, slightly curved only at apex; nervulus interstitial; ramulus long; all veins of hind wing pigmented; membrane of wing yellowish. Length of front wing of female 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="69.[178,1085,506,821]" pageId="69" pageNumber="1386">A b d o m e n: Abdomen from above longish-oval; second tergite transversal, 1,3 times shorter than breadth at apex; ovipositor not protrude behind apex, tergite 7 long; abdomen oxypygous, at apex compressed from sides. First tergite from lateral gradually curved to postpetiolus, with very narrow petiolus at base, from lateral with sharp transversal ribs, carinated by sharp carinae; from above petiolus gradually, but sharply broadened to triangle postpetiolus; middle field distinctly elevated, its surface with sparse irregular punctures; lateral fields of postpetiolus wrinkly-punctured. Gastrocoeli moderately impressed, thyridia sharp and perpendicular to longitudinal axis of body, closed to base and reach to borders of tergite; lunulae distinct; surface of second tergite with small deep merging punctures, matt, puncturation of other tergites more superficial retrad, tergites 5-7 only just shagreen, slightly shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="69.[178,1085,836,917]" pageId="69" pageNumber="1386">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black. White or yellowish: small spots on internal orbits, upper corners of pronotum, subalarum, scutellum and spots at corners of first and second tergites; sometimes spots on collar and narrow band at apex of second tergite.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="69.[178,942,932,954]" box="[178,942,932,954]" pageId="69" pageNumber="1386">
S i z e: Body length: 13,5 (13-15); flagellum: 10,0; front wing: 
<quantity box="[850,942,932,954]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.1199999999999999" pageId="69" pageNumber="1386" unit="mm" value="11.2">11,2 mm</quantity>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>