<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84688C7E9DAC6FD0EF546C7C5" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Cratolaboides palpalis A.M 2009, nov.sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="158" lastPageNumber="1475" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84688C7E9DAC6FD0EF546C7C5" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84688C7E9DAC6FD0EF546C7C5" lastPageId="158" lastPageNumber="1475" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">
<subSubSection box="[178,602,754,776]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="156.[178,602,754,776]" box="[178,602,754,776]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">
<heading box="[178,602,754,776]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,602,754,776]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">
<taxonomicName authority="A.M, 2009" authorityName="A.M" authorityYear="2009" box="[178,410,754,776]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cratolaboides" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="palpalis" status="nov.sp.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,410,754,776]" italics="true" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">Cratolaboides palpalis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[416,493,754,776]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" rank="species">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Plate 36)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="158" lastPageNumber="1475" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="156.[178,1086,794,862]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">
<materialsCitation collectorName="D. Kasparyan. The" country="Russia" location="Zoologycal Institute" municipality="Ussurijskiy Reserve" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-female="1" stateProvince="Saint Petersburg" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[178,266,794,814]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">Holotype</typeStatus>
. 
<specimenCount box="[275,287,798,819]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[307,370,794,814]" name="Russia" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">Russia</collectingCountry>
, Far East, Primorskyi Kray, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[638,824,794,814]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">Ussurijskiy Reserve</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<emphasis box="[837,963,794,814]" italics="true" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">Pinus sibirica</emphasis>
, 15.07.198 1, 
<collectorName box="[230,412,818,838]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">D. Kasparyan. The</collectorName>
<typeStatus box="[422,501,818,838]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">holotype</typeStatus>
is deposited in the collection of 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84688C7E9DAC6FD0EF546C7C5:8E8360354688C7EBD934FCCEF5ACC533" box="[832,1020,818,838]" country="Russia" municipality="Ussurijskiy Reserve" name="Zoologycal Institute" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473" stateProvince="Saint Petersburg">Zoologycal Institute</location>
of 
<collectingRegion country="Russia" name="Saint Petersburg" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">St. Petersburg</collectingRegion>
.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="156.[178,307,878,900]" box="[178,307,878,900]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">F e m a l e:</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="156.[178,1085,916,1055]" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, with 32 segments and with white semiannulus on segments (8)-12 dorsally, beyond middle widened and flattened ventrally, basal segment long, slender, 3,7 times longer than width at apex laterally, segment 13 and last but one square laterally. Flagellum 1,2 times longer than the front wing and practically equal to body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="156.[178,1086,1070,1590]" lastBlockId="157.[178,1085,219,299]" lastPageId="157" lastPageNumber="1474" pageId="156" pageNumber="1473">H e a d: Head contour from front rather strongly narrowed downwards with large eyes; genae from front roundly narrowed to mandibles base, short, 5 times shorter than height of eye. Vertex from lateral gradually slanting down to occipital carina; temples from above strongly and roundly narrowed behind eyes, from side parallel to hind margin of eye, short, at middle 1,6 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye; occipital carina slightly, but angularly impressed to hind ocelli but not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, sharp all round, meeting with hypostomal carina far from mandible base; malar space equal to mandible base width; mandibles sharply narrowed at base, from place of constriction convexly-parallel to apex, with long upper tooth and short lower one rather strongly moved inside; second segment of maxillary palps of extraordinary large size, swollen; clypeus strongly convex, transversal, with straight thinned front margin and oblique corners, rather sharply separated from face by deep impression; clypeal foveae small, deep, roundish; labrum rounded, rather far protrude from under clypeus, equal by breadth to clypeus front margin; middle field of face distinct, but slightly elevated and approximately equal by width to lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities slightly impressed, polished, laterally reach margins of eyes, but not reach front ocellus level, without lateral tubercles, but with tubercle between antennal fossae; front margins of antennal fossae high elevated; ocelli rather strongly convex, of moderate size, diameter of lateral ocellus equal to distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle slightly and gradually elevated. Surface of face and clypeus densely punctured by big smoothed punctures, without microsculpture, shine; frons polished.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="157.[178,1086,314,1010]" pageId="157" pageNumber="1474">
<collectionCode box="[178,193,315,336]" name="Tavera, Department of Geology and Geophysics" pageId="157" pageNumber="1474">T</collectionCode>
h o r a x: Collar of pronotum short, transverse furrow shallow; lateral surface practically not sculptured, without ribs, only with slight, superficial punctures dorsally, with very short sharp epomiae and with only just expressed ribs at hind corners. Mesonotum slightly convex, longer than width, laterally bordered by rather sharp and deep furrow from level of epomiae; notauli not developed; surface of mesonotum with dense punctures (punctures almost merging), without microsculpture, slightly shining; subalarum thin, but not sharpened; speculum with sparse big smoothed punctures, shining; area of mesopleural fovea deeply and broadly impressed; sternauli slightly and broadly impressed up to middle of mesopleurae; lower part of mesopleurae without distinct bend; surface of mesopleurae at lower half wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture; scutellum from lateral moderately convex and gradually slanting backwards, laterally carinated up to apex; horizontal part moderately convex, with sparse big punctures, without microsculpture. Hind margin of metanotum with sharply developed triangle-bacilliform projections, reaching of level of lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral long, slightly angle-shaped, length of horizontal part 1,2 times longer than area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum, with exception of transversal carina between area superomedia and basal area sharp; costulae and most part of coxal carina, with exception of base, atrophied; area superomedia rectangular, slightly narrowed backwards, 1,5 times longer than width, practically not elevated above lateral fields; areae dentiparae with strong teeth, carina closed it from behind not broadened; spiracles very small, roundish, 1,4 times longer than width (length of spiracles equal 0,3 breadth of field at place of spiracle). Horizontal part of propodeum shining, with irregular wrinkles, surface of area superomedia smooth, metapleurae densely uniformly punctured by big punctures, shining.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="157.[178,1085,1025,1076]" pageId="157" pageNumber="1474">L e g s: Long, slender, hind rather strong; claws of hind tarsi rather long and thin, curved almost at right angle.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="157.[178,1085,1092,1202]" pageId="157" pageNumber="1474">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, roundly pointed in front, almost symmetrical (external vein of apex some longer than internal); stigma narrow, dark; radius slightly sinuous, long; nervulus interstitial; ramulus distinct; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Front wing only 1,1 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="157.[178,1085,1217,1590]" pageId="157" pageNumber="1474">A b d o m e n: From above broadly-oval, not flattened; tergites 6-7 strongly hidden and only just protrude from above, ovipositor slightly protrude; second tergite at apex 1,2 times wider than length. Petiolus distinctly wider than height, gradually broadened to postpetiolus (from above); first tergite from lateral without sharp transform to postpetiolus, with distinct, but slight lateral carinae, dorsolateral carina merge with dorsomedian carina below middle of petiolus; middle field of postpetiolus distinct, but slightly carinated, slightly wider than lateral fields; distance between spiracles more than distance from spiracles to apex; surface of postpetiolus very slightly wrinkled, shining. Gastrocoeli deeply impressed, short, triangle; thyridia distinct, equal by breadth to interval between them; interval punctured; lunulae distinct, small; surface of tergites 2-3 densely punctured to wrinkled, intervals narrower than punctures, with microsculpture, slightly shining, third tergite with very sparse shallow punctures, other tergites only slightly shagreen. Hypopygium pointed, compressed from sides, but not unsclerotized medially.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="158.[178,1085,227,395]" pageId="158" pageNumber="1475">C o l o r a t i o n: Body with reach yellow-white pattern: genae, mandibles, margins of clypeus, internal orbits and stripes on external, spots on vertex, slight spot on scutellum and postscutellum, teeth of propodeum and apical pleural area, apical stripes on all tergites of abdomen, front and middle coxae richly, trochanters of front and middle legs completely and first segment of hind tarsi. Front and middle legs mainly light-red, hind mainly brownish black.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="158.[178,790,410,432]" box="[178,790,410,432]" pageId="158" pageNumber="1475">
S i z e: Body length: 6,8; front wing: 6,0; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[725,786,411,432]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="7.0" pageId="158" pageNumber="1475" unit="mm" value="7.0">7 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>