<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846C1C7A1DAC6FE0CF579C36C" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Spanophatnus bicinctorius" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="214" lastPageNumber="1531" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846C1C7A1DAC6FE0CF579C36C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846C1C7A1DAC6FE0CF579C36C" lastPageId="214" lastPageNumber="1531" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">
<subSubSection box="[178,708,496,518]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="213.[178,708,496,518]" box="[178,708,496,518]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">
<heading box="[178,708,496,518]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,708,496,518]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">
<taxonomicName authority="(THUNBERG)" baseAuthorityName="THUNBERG" box="[178,598,496,518]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Spanophatnus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicinctorius">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,458,496,518]" italics="true" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">Spanophatnus bicinctorius</emphasis>
(THUNBERG)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 56)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="213.[178,1008,537,585]" lastBlockId="213.[178,291,599,620]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">
<taxonomicName authority="THUNBERG 1822" authorityName="THUNBERG" authorityYear="1822" box="[178,553,536,556]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicinctorius">
<emphasis box="[178,392,536,556]" italics="true" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">Ichneumon bicinctorius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="THUNBERG C" box="[398,553,536,556]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" pagination="249 - 281" refId="ref143999" refString="THUNBERG C. P. (1822): Ichneumonidea, Insecta Hymenoptera illustrata. - Mem. Acad. St. Petersburg 8: 249 - 281." type="journal article" year="1822">THUNBERG 1822</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. 
<collectingRegion box="[780,907,536,556]" country="Russia" name="Saint Petersburg" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">St. Pétersburg</collectingRegion>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[913,924,536,556]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">8</emphasis>
: 278, 
<specimenCount box="[982,994,539,560]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. 
<taxonomicName authority=": HEINRICH 1967" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1967" box="[178,578,562,582]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Spanophatnus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicinctorius">
<emphasis box="[178,420,562,582]" italics="true" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">Spanophatnus bicinctorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[432,578,562,582]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" pagination="1 - 1258" refId="ref142685" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1967 - 1968): Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of the Sahara. - Monograph. Farmington State College Press 1 - 5: 1 - 1258." type="book chapter" year="1967">HEINRICH 1967</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ichn. Stenop. of Africa 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[815,826,562,582]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">2</emphasis>
: 428-429, 432, 
<specimenCount box="[983,995,565,586]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="213.[178,1085,636,775]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, beyond middle slightly flattened ventrally and practically not widened, with 32 segments, gradually attenuated toward apex, with white annulus on segments 8-11; segments of flagellum distinctly differentiated; basal segments moderately long, first segment 3,3 times longer than width at apex. Flagellum 1,2 times shorter than front wing and 1,5 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="214" lastPageNumber="1531" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="213.[178,1086,790,1515]" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">H e a d: Head contour from front strongly, almost straightly narrowed downwards; 1,5 times wider than length; internal margins of eyes parallel, genae almost linearly oblique, malar space 3 times shorter than height of eye; from above head contour transversal, 2 times wider than length. Vertex behind ocelli from lateral gradually oblique to moderately high occipital carina; temples from above behind eyes sharply roundly narrowed, from lateral at upper part short, temples length at middle 2,7 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye, widened downwards; occipital carina from above only just impressed to hind ocelli, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, meeting with hypostomal carina not reaching mandible base, abscissula approximately 2-3 times longer than mandible base width and distinctly lamellate, but only moderately high; genae at place of meeting occipital and hypostomal carinae (carinal junction) forming not great impression; genae longer than mandible base width; mandibles narrowed behind base with small lower tooth strongly moved inside; clypeus moderately convex, transversal, 2,3 times wider than length, with impressed and thinned, almost straight front margin and oblique lateral margins, distinctly separated from middle field of face by impression; clypeal foveae deep, rounded; labrum not protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face very narrow, in middle 1,5 times narrower than lateral fields, slightly elevated above lateral fields; antennal cavities moderately deep, small, not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, with wrinkled surface, without visible lateral tubercles and with sharp narrow tooth between antennal fossae; ocelli of small size, diameter of lateral ocellus 2 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle only just elevated. Surface of clypeus roughly wrinkly-punctured, surface of face roughly-wrinkled; frons and vertex densely and roughly wrinkly-punctured; head surface, with exception of malar space, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="213.[178,1085,1530,1581]" lastBlockId="214.[178,1085,219,592]" lastPageId="214" lastPageNumber="1531" pageId="213" pageNumber="1530">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum moderately long, transverse furrow deep. Mesonotum strongly convex, of equal length and breadth; notauli practically absent; surface of meso- notum roughly and densely punctured (intervals narrower than punctures), slightly shining; subalarum thick not sharpened; area of speculum also sculpturated practically as other part of mesopleurae, only just expressed; front part of mesopleurae opposite mesopleural fovea convex in form of knoll; area of mesopleural fovea slightly impressed; sternauli not expressed; surface of mesopleurae roughly wrinkly-punctured; scutellum strongly roundly convex, laterally carinated up to apex, its surface with big rough punctures. Hind margin of metanotum smooth, without prominences. Propodeum from lateral rounded; horizontal and declivous surfaces divided by apical transversal carina, other transverse carinae not developed; from longitudinal carinae only carina metapleuralis developed, thus coxal area not limited; spiracles of propodeum large, almost slit-shaped (2,5-3 times longer than width), equal by length approximately 0,8 of breadth of area spiraculifera at place of spiracle. Horizontal and lateral parts of propodeum roughly reticulate-rugose, area posteromedia roughly punctured.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="214.[178,986,607,629]" box="[178,986,607,629]" pageId="214" pageNumber="1531">L e g s: Slender, moderately long. Claws small, narrow, strongly bend at apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="214.[178,1085,645,754]" pageId="214" pageNumber="1531">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, narrow at base almost symmetrical (external vein of base only slightly longer than internal); stigma broad, dark; radius straight, at apex strongly curved, long; nervulus interstitial or very slightly antefurcal; ramulus long; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Front wing 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="214.[178,1086,770,1172]" pageId="214" pageNumber="1531">A b d o m e n Broadly-oval from above, from forth tergite sharply narrowed backwards and pointed, sixth and seventh tergites only just visible from above, second tergite transversal, shorter than breadth at apex; ovipositor not protrude behind apex of abdomen. Petiolus flattened, in middle approximately two times wider than height, from lateral with only ventrolateral carina expressed and slightly developed only at base dorsolateral carina, with slightly wrinkly-punctured lateral surface (without expressed ribs), from lateral gradually transform to postpetiolus; from above uniformly broadened to postpetiolus; dorsal carinae of postpetiolus of first tergite not expressed same as middle field, its surface slightly uniformly convex, irregularly superficially wrinkly-punctured. Gastrocoeli slightly impressed and short, small, triangle, thyridia expressed, narrow, two times narrower than interval between them, situated near base of second tergite; spiracles in middle of second tergite, lunulae distinct, large; tergites 2-4 strongly sclerotized, densely longitudinally wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture. Hypopygium compressed from sides, with longitudinal fold and membranous apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="214.[178,1085,1188,1268]" pageId="214" pageNumber="1531">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black with white pattern: subalarum, scutellum, broad white stripes (bands) on apex of tergites 1-3 of abdomen and small spot at apex of 4th; external orbits of eyes dark-red; legs with exception of coxae and trochanters brown-red.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="214.[178,809,1283,1305]" box="[178,809,1283,1305]" pageId="214" pageNumber="1531">
S i z e: Body length: 8,5; front wing: 6,6; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[725,805,1283,1305]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.7" pageId="214" pageNumber="1531" unit="mm" value="5.7">5,7 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>