<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846B8C7DADAC6FCF3F53EC066" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Acantholabus malaisei HEINRICH" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="173" lastPageNumber="1490" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846B8C7DADAC6FCF3F53EC066" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846B8C7DADAC6FCF3F53EC066" lastPageId="173" lastPageNumber="1490" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">
<subSubSection box="[178,638,783,806]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="172.[178,638,783,806]" box="[178,638,783,806]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">
<heading box="[178,638,783,806]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,638,783,806]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,530,783,806]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Acantholabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="malaisei">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,416,783,805]" italics="true" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">Acantholabus malaisei</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 42)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="172.[178,927,823,847]" lastBlockId="172.[178,291,861,882]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH 1974" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1974" box="[178,534,823,843]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Acantholabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="malaisei">
<emphasis box="[178,385,823,843]" italics="true" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">Acantholabus malaisei</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[391,534,823,843]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" pagination="103 - 197" refId="ref142818" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1974): Burmesische Ichneumoninae IX. Tribus Platylabini. - Annales Zoologici Wars. 32, 8: 103 - 197." type="journal article" year="1974">HEINRICH 1974</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ann. Zool. Wars. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[718,741,823,843]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">32</emphasis>
(8): 158-160, 
<specimenCount box="[872,884,827,848]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="172.[178,1085,897,1036]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, [with 36 segments (acc. to G.H.)], not widened beyond middle and not flattened ventrally, with white semiannulus dorsally; basal segments long, first segment 6 times longer than width at apex [apical segments longer than wide (acc. to G.H.)]. Flagellum approximately equal by length to front wing and body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="173" lastPageNumber="1490" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="172.[178,1086,1051,1600]" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489">
H e a d: Head contour from front rounded with very large eyes, only 1,2 times wider than height, narrowed downwards, only malar space visible from front; genae from front 7,4 times sorter than height of eye; head from above strongly transversal, 1,8 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral abrupt to occipital carina just after the ocelli; temples short, behind eyes from above sharply, strongly and roundly narrowed backwards and from lateral downwards; temples length at middle 5,2 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye; occipital carina from above angularly impressed, but not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, from lateral, before mandible base erased and not reach hypostomal carina; malar space equal to mandible base width; mandibles with form character to 
<taxonomicName box="[178,288,1315,1337]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="172" pageNumber="1489" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="tribe" tribe="Platylabini">Platylabini</taxonomicName>
strongly and gradually narrowed to apex, sharply carinated dorsally and ventrally; clypeus narrow, but wider than length, strongly convex, with rounded front margin, slightly separated from middle field of face; clypeal foveae deeply impressed, of moderate size; labrum protrude from under clypeus, triangle, but rather broad; middle field of face slightly elevated, narrower than lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities very slightly impressed, with rounded tubercles laterally and distinct tubercle between antennal fossae, margins of antennal cavities laterally reach eyes, but far not reach front ocellus level; ocelli large, strongly convex, diameter of lateral ocellus equal to distance from ocellus to eye. Surface of face and clypeus with dense fine punctures, with dull shine (interspaces between punctures sculpturated), frons above antennal cavities shagreen.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,1085,219,738]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum short, transverse furrow deep. Mesonotum very strongly convex, slightly longer than width, notauli marked only at basal third; surface of mesonotum with very dense punctures and strongly developed microsculpture, matt; subalarum thickened, but sharpened; speculum with wrinkled sculpture, mesopleural fovea deep with sharp enveloping impression; sternauli slightly impressed at front half; surface of mesopleurae densely wrinkly-punctured, matt; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, carinated laterally and at apex by high sharp carina, at apex carina interrupted, forming something like teeth; surface of scutellum flat, with dense punctures and microsculpture, matt; postscutellum with strong longitudinal wrinkles. Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral slanted, horizontal part of propodeum considerably shorter than area posteromedia in middle; all fields of propodeum developed; basal area very long; area superomedia hexagonal, approximately of equal length and breadth, costulae present or indistinct, situated before middle of area superomedia; area dentipara short with very long bend upwards apophysis at apex; coxal carina distinct; spiracles rather large, longish-oval, 1,6-2-times longer than width (equal 0,6 breadth of area spiraculifera at place of spiracle). Horizontal part of propodeum and metapleurae wrinkly-punctured, slightly shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,1085,754,805]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">L e g s: Very long and slender; segments of all tarsi long and thin; claws long, slightly curved, hind coxae elongated.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,1085,820,930]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">W i n g s: Areolet big, quadrangular, symmetrical (veins of base of equal length); stigma broad, dark; radius almost straight, long; nervulus interstitial; ramulus absent; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Length of front wing approximately equal to body length or only just shorter.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,1085,945,1289]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">A b d o m e n: Abdomen from above longish-oval (drop-shaped), flattened dorsoventrally; second tergite longer than width at apex; apical tergites not hidden, visible from above; sheath of ovipositor slightly protrude behind apex of abdomen. Petiolus of first tergite rather thick, sharply flattened only at base; petiolus from lateral and from above with gradual passage to postpetiolus; lateral carinae distinct; middle field of postpetiolus high elevated and distinctly limited, lateral fields of postpetiolus narrower than middle field, its surface sinuously-wrinkled. Gastrocoeli slightly impressed, superficial, long, thyridia strongly removed from base of second tergite, wider than interval between them; interspace between thyridia with slight longitudinal impression, wrinkled; lunulae distinct, comparatively large and elevated; second and third tergites from delicate to very delicate punctured or with coriaceous sculpture; tergites 6-7 slightly membranous. Hypopygium from below triangle, without distinct longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,1085,1305,1385]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black-brown; yellow: spots on vertex, internal orbits, front and upper margins of pronotum, subalarum, scutellum, apophysises. Apical margin of sixth and seventh tergites completely white.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,817,1401,1423]" box="[178,817,1401,1423]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">
S i z e: Body length - 6,7; front wing: 6,1; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[733,813,1401,1423]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.9" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490" unit="mm" value="4.9">4,9 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,547,1438,1460]" box="[178,547,1438,1460]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">M a l e (according to G. HEINRICH)</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="173.[178,1085,1475,1556]" pageId="173" pageNumber="1490">Flagellum of male with 38 segments, with distinct longish-oval tyloides on segments 8- 12 and white semiannulus on segments 11-15. Face and clypeus broadly white, tergites 5th and 6th with white membranous apex, 7th with white apical spot.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>