<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846C5C7A5DAC6FC26F566C031" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Lissolaboides flavorufus HEINRICH" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="210" lastPageNumber="1527" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846C5C7A5DAC6FC26F566C031" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846C5C7A5DAC6FC26F566C031" lastPageId="210" lastPageNumber="1527" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">
<subSubSection box="[178,654,986,1008]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="209.[178,654,986,1008]" box="[178,654,986,1008]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">
<heading box="[178,654,986,1008]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,654,986,1008]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,546,986,1008]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Lissolaboides" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavorufus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,432,986,1008]" italics="true" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">Lissolaboides flavorufus</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 55)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="209.[178,913,1028,1049]" lastBlockId="209.[178,291,1064,1084]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH 1974" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1974" box="[178,550,1026,1046]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Lissolaboides" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavorufus">
<emphasis box="[178,401,1026,1046]" italics="true" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">Lissolaboides flavorufus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[407,550,1026,1046]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" pagination="103 - 197" refId="ref142818" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1974): Burmesische Ichneumoninae IX. Tribus Platylabini. - Annales Zoologici Wars. 32, 8: 103 - 197." type="journal article" year="1974">HEINRICH 1974</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ann. Zool. Wars. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[734,757,1026,1046]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">32</emphasis>
(8): 184-185, 
<specimenCount box="[888,900,1030,1051]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="209.[178,1086,1100,1239]" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">F l a g e l l u m: Of female slender, bristle-shaped, with 42 segments, slightly widened beyond middle and flattened ventrally, strongly attenuated and pointed toward apex, with white annulus on segments 8-12; basal segments moderately long, first segment 3,7 times longer than width at apex. Flagellum approximately equal by length to front wing and 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="210" lastPageNumber="1527" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="209.[178,1085,1253,1583]" lastBlockId="210.[178,1086,218,436]" lastPageId="210" lastPageNumber="1527" pageId="209" pageNumber="1526">H e a d: Head contour from front moderately narrowed downwards, transversal, 1,3 wider than height; genae strongly and gradually roundly oblique, long from front; head contour from above transversal, 2 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral straightly and gradually sloping to not high but sharp occipital carina; temples long, in middle 1,4 times sorter than longitudinal diameter of eye, from above gradually narrowed behind eyes with slightly curved contour, from lateral relatively wide, downwards only just visible widened, practically parallel to hind margin of eye; occipital carina slightly angularly impressed to hind ocelli, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina meeting with occipital carina on some distance from mandible base; malar space some more than mandible base width; mandibles uniformly narrowed from base to apex, lower tooth strong; clypeus transversal, 2,5 times wider than height, not strongly convex, with straight thinned front margin and rounded lateral corners, separated from face by impression, clypeus more elevated than lateral fields (see from lateral); clypeal foveae deep, of moderate size; labrum short, broad, only just protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face only just expressed, narrow, narrower than lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities moderately impressed, laterally reach margins of eyes, but not reach front ocellus level, with lateral tubercles and slight tubercle between antennal fossae; ocelli large, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,3 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle distinctly elevated. Face and clypeus with dense punctures, without microsculpture; antennal cavities and frons polished; face slightly shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="210.[178,1086,450,948]" pageId="210" pageNumber="1527">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum moderately long, transverse furrow deep. Mesonotum strongly convex, longer than width, notauli marked at base; surface of mesonotum with dense punctures, with slightly shining lateral lobes; subalarum thick, not sharpened; mesopleural fovea deep, area around it broadly impressed, comparatively of area of speculum; mesopleurae densely superficially wrinkly-punctured, including area of speculum, without microsculpture; lower part of mesopleurae with angular bend; sternauli absent; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, from lateral strongly slanting backwards, laterally carinated, horizontal part strongly convex with sparse punctures, apical part of scutellum with longitudinal wrinkles. Hind margin of metanotum with strong triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum short, angleshaped; horizontal part, including area basalis approximately equal to length of area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum, with exception of coxal (presented by transversal ribs), developed; area basalis long, area superomedia hexagonal, narrowed in front and from costulae backwards, its surface smooth, costulae at middle of area superomedia; areae dentiparae with expressed teeth at apices; area spiraculifera with transversal ribs; spiracles large, elongated, 2-3 times longer than width (equal 0,6 breadth of area spiraculifera at place of spiracle). Surface of propodeum shining; metapleurae punctured, intervals wider than punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="210.[178,1085,962,1012]" pageId="210" pageNumber="1527">L e g s: Moderately slender, rather long. Claws long, narrow, slightly and gradually curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="210.[178,1085,1026,1132]" pageId="210" pageNumber="1527">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, asymmetrical (external intercubitus considerably longer than internal); stigma narrow, dark; radius slightly sinuous; nervulus interstitial; ramulus only just marked; membrane of wing hyaline. Front wing 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="210.[178,1086,1146,1504]" pageId="210" pageNumber="1527">A b d o m e n:Fromabove elongated, broadened to apex of second tergite and from it uniformly narrowed backwards; second tergite with equal length to width at apex; apices of ovipositor sheath visible from above. Petiolus only just wider than height at base, from lateral gradually curved; lateral carinae distinct, surface between them wrinkled; from above petiolus gradually broadened to postpetiolus, middle field of postpetiolus practically not expressed, smooth, shining, lateral fields narrower than middle field, with very slight superficial rugosity; distance between spiracles equal to distance from spiracles to apex, or only just less. Gastrocoeli slightly impressed, thyridia distinct, far removed from base of tergite, oblique; interval many wider than thyridia; lunulae practically not expressed, only in form of trace some different by sculpture; tergites 2-3 shining with coriaceous sculpture, without punctures; other tergites smooth, shining; lateral margins of apical tergites bent-under. Hypopygium slightly pointed, practically without longitudinal fold, not overlap ovipositor.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="210.[178,1085,1518,1568]" pageId="210" pageNumber="1527">C o l o r a t i o n: Main color of head, thorax and abdomen light-red (brown) with very reach yellow and slight black pattern.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="210.[178,822,1583,1605]" box="[178,822,1583,1605]" pageId="210" pageNumber="1527">
S i z e: Body length: 11,5; front wing: 9,0; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[738,818,1583,1605]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="8.5" pageId="210" pageNumber="1527" unit="mm" value="8.5">8,5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>