<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846D8C7BADAC6FF25F761C24A" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Pristiceros serrarius GRAVENHORST" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="205" lastPageNumber="1522" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846D8C7BADAC6FF25F761C24A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846D8C7BADAC6FF25F761C24A" lastPageId="205" lastPageNumber="1522" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">
<subSubSection box="[178,663,217,239]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="204.[178,663,217,239]" box="[178,663,217,239]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">
<heading box="[178,663,217,239]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,663,217,239]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">
<taxonomicName authority="GRAVENHORST" authorityName="GRAVENHORST" box="[178,555,217,239]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pristiceros" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="serrarius">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,389,217,238]" italics="true" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">Pristiceros serrarius</emphasis>
GRAVENHORST
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 53)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="204.[178,1000,256,306]" lastBlockId="204.[178,253,320,341]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">
<taxonomicName authority="GRAVENHORST 1829" authorityName="GRAVENHORST" authorityYear="1829" box="[178,564,256,276]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pristiceros" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="serrarius">
<emphasis box="[178,366,256,276]" italics="true" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">Pristiceros serrarius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="GRAVENHORST I" box="[371,564,256,276]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" pagination="1 - 827" refId="ref142250" refString="GRAVENHORST I. L. C. (1829): Ichneumonologia Europea. - Vratislaviae, Sum. Auct. 1: 1 - 827." type="journal article" year="1829">GRAVENHORST 1829</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ichneum. Eur. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[719,730,256,276]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">1</emphasis>
: 635, 
<specimenCount box="[788,800,260,281]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
,Ƌ. 
<taxonomicName authority=": HEINRICH 1934" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1934" box="[178,521,282,302]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pristiceros" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="serrarius">
<emphasis box="[178,366,282,302]" italics="true" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">Pristiceros serrarius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[378,521,282,302]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" pagination="1 - 263" refId="ref142350" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1934): Die Ichneumoninae von Celebes. - Mitt. Zool. Mus. Berlin 20: 1 - 263." type="journal article" year="1934">HEINRICH 1934</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
(1936) - Polskie Pismo Entomol. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[831,854,282,302]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">13</emphasis>
(1-4): 41, 
<specimenCount box="[951,963,286,307]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
,Ƌ. M a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="204.[178,1085,356,495]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">F l a g e l l u m: Long, with 40 segments, with white annulus (semiannulus) on segments (11)12-(16)18, sharply serrate from segment 8; apically segments deeply cut with broad cavity between segments; first segment 2,6 times longer than width at apex laterally; white segments with large oval tyloides. Flagellum 1,2 times shorter than the front wing and 1,6 times shorter than the body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="205" lastPageNumber="1522" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="204.[178,1085,510,1060]" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">H e a d: Head contour from front transversal, 1,4 times wider than height, gradually narrowed downwards; lower part of temples from the front visible almost to middle of eye; genae from front 5,2 times sorter height of eye; from above head contour slightly narrowed backwards, 1,9 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral gradually sloping to sharp and rather high occipital carina; temples from above roundly and moderately narrowed behind eyes, long, equal to longitudinal diameter of eye at middle, from side parallel to hind margin of eye; occipital carina from above gradually impressed to hind ocelli, far not reach level of eyes, at bottom meeting with hypostomal carina before mandible base; malar space shorter than mandible base width; mandibles gradually narrowed behind base; clypeus sharply separated from face by suture, with strongly convex and uniformly rounded front margin, 2,6 times wider than length; clypeal foveae deep, narrow; labrum very short, wide, with straight front margin; middle field of face only just elevated, rather wide, 1,6 times narrower than lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities deep, but short, not reach front ocellus level and margins of eyes, without rounded tubercles laterally and slight tooth between antennal fossae; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus equal to distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle expressed, but slightly elevated. Surface of clypeus punctured by big punctures, lateral fields very densely punctured, middle field wrinkly-punctured, head surface shining, only middle field partially with microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="204.[178,1086,1075,1595]" lastBlockId="205.[178,1085,219,270]" lastPageId="205" lastPageNumber="1522" pageId="204" pageNumber="1521">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long, from above with straight front margin, transverse furrow shallow; epomiae only just marked. Mesonotum strongly convex, only just longer than width; notauli only just marked at base; lateral margin of mesonotum behind tegulae strongly widened; surface of mesonotum very densely punctured, shining, without microsculpture; subalarum high, thick, not sharpened; speculum practically not expressed, wrinkly-punctured; area of mesopleural fovea narrowly and deeply impressed; mesopleural suture deep, straight, interrupted by sharp ribs; sternauli practically absent; lower part of mesopleurae without sharp bend; surface of mesopleurae very densely punctured to slightly wrinkled, shining, without microsculpture, with slight white pubescence at area of speculum and mesopleural carina; scutellum rather high elevated, laterally sharply carinated; its horizontal part uniformly convex, punctured by sparse punctures, shining. Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral rather short, without sharp division to horizontal and vertical parts, almost triangle; horizontal part 2 times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum developed, including coxal carina; basal area short and deep; area superomedia rectangular (hexagonal), transversal, costulae before middle; area dentipara at apex without tooth (or very slight tooth-like projection); spiracles large, equal 0,7 breadth of field at place of spiracle, slit-shaped, three and more times longer than width. Surface of propodeum wrinkled, without microsculpture; metapleurae densely punctured, shining; propodeum of male with white pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[178,1015,285,307]" box="[178,1015,285,307]" pageId="205" pageNumber="1522">L e g s: Long and slender. Claws thin, at upper third curved almost at right angle.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[178,1085,322,432]" pageId="205" pageNumber="1522">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular almost symmetrical; stigma narrow with wide base, dark; radius slightly sinuous, almost straight, long; nervulus interstitial; ramulus from short to long; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Length of front wing 1,4 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[178,1086,448,821]" pageId="205" pageNumber="1522">A b d o m e n From above narrow, longish-oval, in middle almost parallel sided; second tergite of equal length and breadth. First tergite long, without distinct bend on border of petiolus and postpetiolus; petiolus at base slightly flattened; laterally carinated by strong carinae, interspace between them with sharp transverse ribs; from above petiolus gradually and uniformly broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus sharply elevated, wider than lateral fields; its surface slightly irregularly wrinkled. Gastrocoeli moderately deep, rather short; thyridia distinct, almost perpendicular to longitudinal axis of a body, laterally reach to borders of tergite; interval only just visible less than breadth of thyridia; lunulae not big, distinct; surface of interval and front third of tergite cellular, other part of second tergite, with exception of smooth stripe at apex densely wrinkly-punctured slightly shining; tergites 3-4 very densely punctured and with developed microsculpture; other tergites with more sharp punctures, shining. Hypopygium of male with straight, only just rounded apex, without longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[178,1085,836,917]" pageId="205" pageNumber="1522">C o l o r a t i o n: Uniformly black with yellowish internal orbits, traces of white or yellowish pattern along front margin and at hind corners of pronotum, yellowish spot on scutellum, often with spots at hind corners of propodeum. Legs mainly dark-brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[178,822,932,954]" box="[178,822,932,954]" pageId="205" pageNumber="1522">S i z e: Body length: 11,5; front wing: 8,4; flagellum: 7,0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[178,291,969,991]" box="[178,291,969,991]" pageId="205" pageNumber="1522">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[178,1085,1007,1087]" pageId="205" pageNumber="1522">Flagellum of females bristle-shaped, long and slender, flattened ventrally beyond middle and slightly widened, sharply attenuated toward apex. Female with red-brown basic color of abdomen.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>