<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F8462DC74DDAC6FF25F566C505" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Hymenura nigra" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="58" lastPageNumber="1375" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F8462DC74DDAC6FF25F566C505" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F8462DC74DDAC6FF25F566C505" lastPageId="58" lastPageNumber="1375" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">
<subSubSection box="[178,593,217,239]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,593,217,239]" box="[178,593,217,239]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">
<heading box="[178,593,217,239]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,593,217,239]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">
<taxonomicName authority="(HEINRICH)" baseAuthorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,483,217,239]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hymenura" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigra">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,352,217,238]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">Hymenura nigra</emphasis>
(HEINRICH)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 14)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,816,256,302]" box="[178,806,256,281]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">
<emphasis box="[178,259,256,276]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">Neopyga</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH 1930" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1930" box="[264,462,256,276]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hymenura" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigra">
<emphasis box="[264,313,256,276]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">nigra</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[319,462,256,276]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" pagination="545 - 555" refId="ref142316" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1930): Einige neue genera und species der Subfam. Ichneumoninae Ashm. - Mitt. Zool. Mus. Berlin 15: 545 - 555." type="journal article" year="1930">HEINRICH 1930</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mitt. Zool. Mus. Berlin 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[700,723,256,276]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">15</emphasis>
: 546, 
<specimenCount box="[781,793,260,281]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,816,256,302]" box="[178,816,282,302]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">
<taxonomicName authority=": TOWNES et al. 1965" authorityName="TOWNES" authorityYear="1965" box="[178,521,282,302]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hymenura" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigra">
<emphasis box="[178,328,282,302]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">Hymenura nigra</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="TOWNES H &amp; MOMOI S" box="[340,521,282,302]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" pagination="1 - 661" refId="ref144266" refString="TOWNES H. K., MOMOI S. &amp; M. TOWNES (1965): A catalogue and reclassification of the eastern Palaearctic Ichneumonidae. - Mem. American Ent. Inst. 5: 1 - 661." type="journal article" year="1965">TOWNES et al. 1965</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mem. Amer. Ent. Inst. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[752,763,282,302]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">5</emphasis>
: 426.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,291,319,341]" box="[178,291,319,341]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">F e m a l e</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="58" lastPageNumber="1375" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,1085,356,495]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">F l a g e l l u m: Of females bristle-shaped (almost filiform), with 36 segments and white annulus on segments (7)8-13(14), slightly flattened beyond white annulus. First segment three times longer than width at apex, already segment 15 transverse from lateral, last but one segment square. Flagellum practically equal by length to front wing and 1,6 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,1085,510,1089]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">H e a d: Head contour from front roundish, narrowed downwards, only just transversal, 1,2 times wider than height; genae from front short, equal 0,2 height of eye. Vertex from lateral roundly slanting down after the ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, equal to longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, from above roundly narrowed behind eyes, from side parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina, from above gradually impressed, not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, meeting with hypostomal carina on mandible base; malar space equal 0,7 mandible base width; mandibles almost sickleshaped, lower tooth in form of only just visible tubercle moved inside; clypeus transverse, two times wider than length, with straight front margin and rounded lateral corners, practically flat with thickened lateral sides, only just visible separated from middle field of face by very slight impression (practically confluent); clypeal foveae large, deep; labrum not protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face only just visible elevated above lateral fields and in middle equal to lateral fields by width; antennal cavities moderately impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, laterally above antennal fossae without tubercles and any interantennal tubercle; diameter of lateral ocellus approximately equal to distance from ocellus to eye, ocellar triangle not expressed. Surface of face shining, practically without microsculpture; surface of clypeus, except lateral corners, and also lateral fields densely punctured by big superficial punctures; middle field very densely, practically wrinklypunctured; upper part of frons and vertex dull, coriaceous.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,1086,1104,1565]" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">T h o r a x: Pronotal ridge not thickened; pronotal base gradually uniformly curved. Mesonotum moderately convex, only just longer than width; notauli sharp in front third; surface of mesonotum very densely punctured, matt; subalarum moderately thick, not sharpened; speculum smooth, shining, area of mesopleural fovea broadly and deeply impressed; sternauli absent; surface of mesopleurae wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture; scutellum from lateral convex, gradually slanting to postscutellum, laterally carinated to middle, surface of scutellum densely punctured. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral with break, distinctly divided on horizontal and declivous parts; horizontal part approximately two times shorter than area posteromedia in middle; propodeum with complete set of carinae, lateral carinae of basal area only just expressed; basal area with distinct knoll; area superomedia hexagonal, only just longer than width, costulae at middle of area superomedia; area dentipara at apex with wide tooth; spiracles large, long, almost slit-shaped, 2,5 times, longer than width (equal 0,6 breadth of field at place of spiracle). Surface of propodeum wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture, metapleurae very densely wrinkly-punctured.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="57.[178,881,1581,1603]" lastBlockId="58.[178,1085,218,352]" lastPageId="58" lastPageNumber="1375" pageId="57" pageNumber="1374">L e g s: Rather strong, but slender. Claws smooth, gradually curved. W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, asymmetrical, external vein of apex considerably shorter than internal; stigma broad, dark, radius only just visible curved only at base and apex; nervulus interstitial, sharply inclival; ramulus distinct; veins strongly darkened, membrane of wing hyaline. Front wing almost equal by length to flagellum and 1,4 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="58.[178,1085,366,752]" pageId="58" pageNumber="1375">
A b d o m e n Abdomen from above elongated, parallel sided, second tergite with equal length and breadth; abdomen with truncate apex and cut out from above apical tergites (remind one of 
<taxonomicName authority="HOLMGR." authorityName="HOLMGR." box="[428,641,422,443]" class="Hexanauplia" family="Notodelphyidae" genus="Notopygus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Cyclopoida" pageId="58" pageNumber="1375" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[428,536,422,443]" italics="true" pageId="58" pageNumber="1375">Notopygus</emphasis>
HOLMGR.
</taxonomicName>
), amblypygous; apex of ovipositor sheath visible from above. Petiolus of first tergite not flattened at base, thin, from lateral with sharp passage to postpetiolus, dorsal and ventral lateral carinae sharp, interspace between them with slight rugosity; from above petiolus sharply broadened to postpetiolus, middle field of postpetiolus expressed, but not carinated by carinae, wider than lateral fields, its surface with irregular rugosity, aciculated; spiracles of postpetiolus roundish. Gastrocoeli short, rather deep, very slightly oblique; thyridia sharp, approached to base of second tergite, broad, 1,5 times wider than interval between them, interval densely wrinklypunctured; lunulae very distinct, of moderate size, situated in middle of tergite; surface of tergites 2-4 very densely punctured, matt, with exception of narrow apical stripe, only tergites 6th and 7th with slight microsculpture. Sternites 2-3 not sclerotized, with longitudinal fold; hypopygium roundly pointed, without longitudinal fold.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="58.[178,1085,766,844]" pageId="58" pageNumber="1375">C o l o r a t i o n: Black with white or light-yellow pattern: broad spots on frontal orbits, stripes at upper corners of pronotum, subalarum, scutellum, band at apex of tergites 5-6 and membranous part of apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="58.[178,822,859,881]" box="[178,822,859,881]" pageId="58" pageNumber="1375">S i z e: Body length: 11,0; flagellum: 7,0; front wing: 8,0 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>