<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846B3C7DFDAC6FE41F561C21C" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Rhyssolabus bassicus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="168" lastPageNumber="1485" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846B3C7DFDAC6FE41F561C21C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846B3C7DFDAC6FE41F561C21C" lastPageId="168" lastPageNumber="1485" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">
<subSubSection box="[178,642,445,468]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="167.[178,642,445,468]" box="[178,642,445,468]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">
<heading box="[178,642,445,468]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" reason="2">
<taxonomicName authority="(TISCHBEIN)" baseAuthorityName="TISCHBEIN" box="[178,532,445,468]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Rhyssolabus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bassicus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,416,445,468]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,401,445,467]" italics="true" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">Rhyssolabus bassicus</emphasis>
(
</emphasis>
TISCHBEIN
<emphasis bold="true" box="[524,532,446,468]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">)</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[539,642,446,468]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">(Plate 40)</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="167.[178,907,485,531]" box="[178,780,485,505]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">
<emphasis box="[178,295,485,505]" italics="true" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">Platymischus</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="TISCHBEIN 1868" authorityName="TISCHBEIN" authorityYear="1868" box="[300,534,485,505]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Rhyssolabus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bassicus">
<emphasis box="[300,377,485,505]" italics="true" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">bassicus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="TISCHBEIN P" box="[383,534,485,505]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" pagination="248 - 258" refId="ref144028" refString="TISCHBEIN P. (1868): Hymenopterologische Beitrage. - Stettiner Entomologische Zeitung 29: 248 - 258." type="journal article" year="1868">TISCHBEIN 1868</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ent. Ztg. Stettin 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[704,727,485,505]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">29</emphasis>
: 257.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="167.[178,907,485,531]" box="[178,907,511,531]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">
<taxonomicName authority=": BERTHOUMIEU 1896" authorityName="BERTHOUMIEU" authorityYear="1896" box="[178,576,511,531]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Rhyssolabus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bassicus">
<emphasis box="[178,374,511,531]" italics="true" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">Rhyssolabus bassicus</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="BERTHOUMIEU G" box="[386,576,511,531]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" pagination="285 - 418" refId="ref141644" refString="BERTHOUMIEU G. V. (1896): Ichneumonides d'Europe et des pays limitrophes. - Ann. Soc. Ent. France. 65: 285 - 418." type="journal article" year="1896">BERTHOUMIEU 1896</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ann. Soc. Ent. Fr. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[765,788,511,531]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">65</emphasis>
(1896): 306.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="167.[178,291,548,570]" box="[178,291,548,570]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">F e m a l e</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="168" lastPageNumber="1485" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="167.[178,1085,585,724]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, with 40 segments, slightly widened and flattened ventrally beyond middle, gradually attenuated toward apex, with white semiannulus on segments (6)7-10(11); basal segments moderately long, first segment 2,8 times longer than width at apex. Flagellum equal by length to front wing and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="167.[178,1085,739,1318]" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">H e a d: Head contour from front almost straightly narrowed downwards, 1,4 times wider than height; head contour from above transversal, 2,3 times wider than length; genae from front long, equal 0,3 height of eye; lower part of middle field of face from lateral strongly protrude above clypeus. Vertex from lateral gradually slanting down after the ocelli to moderately high occipital carina; temples from above strongly roundly narrowed backwards, long, from lateral at middle only just shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye; occipital carina from above gradually impressed to hind ocelli, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, from lateral parallel to hind margin of eye, meeting with hypostomal carina not reaching mandible base; genae some longer than mandible base width, with impression from place of meeting occipital and hypostomal carinae to lower angle of mandible; mandibles with form character to tribe, sharply narrowed behind base; clypeus convex with straight front margin and expressed corners, transversal, 1,8 times wider than length, sharply separated from middle field of face by narrow impression; clypeal foveae rounded, strongly impressed; labrum rather short, wide, rounded in front; middle field of face high elevated above lateral fields and clypeus, narrower than lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities moderately impressed with lateral tubercles and small tubercle between antennal fossae, reach margins of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level; ocelli of normal size, cross diameter of lateral ocellus equal 0,6 distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle distinct, but slightly elevated. Surface of head roughly wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="167.[178,1086,1333,1589]" lastBlockId="168.[178,1085,219,475]" lastPageId="168" lastPageNumber="1485" pageId="167" pageNumber="1484">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum short, transverse furrow shallow, only just marked. Mesonotum moderately convex, longer than width, notauli distinct in front third and only just marked towards apex; surface of mesonotum densely punctured, shining, without microsculpture; subalarum moderately thin, but not sharpened; speculum densely punctured, shining; mesopleural fovea deep, area around it only just impressed; sternauli distinct up to middle of mesopleurae, but slightly impressed; mesopleurae very densely wrinkly-punctured with microsculpture, matt with exception of parts of speculum and upper part adjoin to prepectal carina; scutellum high elevated, almost from base gradually slanting to postscutellum, lateral carinae developed up to middle, horizontal part slightly convex with distinct punctures, shining. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral shortened and slanted, horizontal part of propodeum shorter than area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum developed, with exception of costulae and coxal carina; area superomedia longer than width, laterally and from front limited by sinuous carinae, rounded in front, high elevated above lateral fields, its surface cellular; area dentipara with strong tooth at apex; spiracles large, longish-oval, 1,5 times longer than width, equal 0,6 breadth of area spiraculifera at place of spiracle. Horizontal part of propodeum and metapleurae roughly cellular-wrinkled.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="168.[178,1084,490,541]" pageId="168" pageNumber="1485">L e g s: Moderately slender. Claws rather broad at two third, curved slightly at apical third.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="168.[178,1085,557,637]" pageId="168" pageNumber="1485">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal symmetrical with wide base; stigma narrow, long, dark; radius almost straight, slightly sinuous, long; nervulus postfurcal; ramulus distinct; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Front wing 1,4 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="168.[178,1086,653,1026]" pageId="168" pageNumber="1485">A b d o m e n: From above longish-oval, second tergite transversal, shorter than breadth at apex, apical tergites not hidden, distinctly visible from above; apex of ovipositor sheath slightly protrude. Petiolus from lateral angularly separated from postpetiolus almost at right angle, lateral carinae of first tergite sharp, interspace between them with rough sculpture; from above petiolus very strongly gradually broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus slightly elevated above lateral fields, not carinated, roughly wrinkled, considerably wider than lateral fields. Gastrocoeli deep and short, thyridia distinct, transverse, parallel to front margin of tergite, interval some narrower each of them; lunulae large, distinct, approximately in middle of tergite; interval and front half of tergite roughly-wrinkled, apical half with dense punctures with microsculpture; second tergite with very dense punctures with microsculpture, matt with exception of apically parts; other tergites with superficial punctures, slightly shining. Hypopygium from below triangle without longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="168.[178,1085,1041,1092]" pageId="168" pageNumber="1485">C o l o r a t i o n: Black with exception of red femora, tibiae and tarsi of front and middle legs and hind femora.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="168.[178,817,1108,1130]" box="[178,817,1108,1130]" pageId="168" pageNumber="1485">S i z e: Body length: 9,7; front wing: 7,1; flagellum: 7,0 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>