<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846DDC7BDDAC6FEA2F25CC333" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Pristicerops infractorius" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="202" lastPageNumber="1519" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846DDC7BDDAC6FEA2F25CC333" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846DDC7BDDAC6FEA2F25CC333" lastPageId="202" lastPageNumber="1519" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">
<subSubSection box="[178,671,350,372]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="201.[178,671,350,372]" box="[178,671,350,372]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">
<heading box="[178,671,350,372]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,671,350,372]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">
<taxonomicName authority="(LINNAEUS)" baseAuthorityName="LINNAEUS" box="[178,560,350,372]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pristicerops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="infractorius">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,431,350,372]" italics="true" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">Pristicerops infractorius</emphasis>
(LINNAEUS)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 52)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="201.[178,876,389,435]" box="[178,727,389,409]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">
<taxonomicName authority="LINNAEUS 1761" authorityName="LINNAEUS" authorityYear="1761" box="[178,543,389,409]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="infractorius">
<emphasis box="[178,391,389,409]" italics="true" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">Ichneumon infractorius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="LINNAEUS C" box="[397,543,389,409]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" pagination="1 - 578" refId="ref143155" refString="LINNAEUS C. (1761): Fauna Svecica. Editio altera. - Laurentii Salv Stockholmiae, 1 - 578." type="book chapter" year="1761">LINNAEUS 1761</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Fauna Svec.: 398.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="201.[178,876,389,435]" box="[178,876,415,435]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">
<taxonomicName authority=": RASNITSYN 1981" authorityName="RASNITSYN" authorityYear="1981" box="[178,571,415,435]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pristicerops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="infractorius">
<emphasis box="[178,401,415,435]" italics="true" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">Pristicerops infractorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="RASNITSYN A" box="[413,571,415,435]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" pagination="505 - 636" refId="ref143316" refString="RASNITSYN A. (1981): [A guide to the insects of the European part of the USSR. Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae. Subfamily Ichneumoninae]. - Opredeliteli po Faune SSSR 3 (3): 505 - 636 [in Russ]." type="journal article" year="1981">RASNITSYN 1981</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Opred. Faune SSSR 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[779,790,415,435]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">3</emphasis>
(3): 552.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="201.[178,291,452,474]" box="[178,291,452,474]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">F e m a l e</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="202" lastPageNumber="1519" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="201.[178,1085,489,658]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">F l a g e l l u m: Long and slender, with 37 segments, not widened or slightly widened and slightly flattened ventrally beyond middle, gradually attenuated toward apex with white annulus on segments (8)9-12; basal segments moderately long, first segment 3,7 times longer than width at apex laterally, segments up to white annulus distinctly differentiated. Flagellum 1,1 times longer than the front wing and 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="201.[178,1086,673,1251]" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">H e a d: Head contour from front narrowed downwards (genae moderately strongly narrowed toward mandibles base), 1,3 times wider than height; malar space 4 times shorter height of eye; head considerably large, transversal, 2 times wider than length. Vertex straightly slanting from ocelli to sharp, low occipital carina; temples from above behind eyes sharply roundly narrowed backwards, from lateral almost parallel to hind margin of eye, temples length at middle 1,3 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye; occipital carina gradually concave to hind ocelli, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, meeting with hypostomal carina on considerable distance from mandible base, before place of meeting curved anteriad, so, that part of hypostomal carina visible from lateral; malar space equal to mandible base width; mandibles gradually narrowed from base to apex, lower tooth slightly move inside; clypeus convex with straight front margin and rounded lateral corners, moderately convex, separated from middle field by slight impression, two times wider than length; clypeal foveae deep, narrow; labrum rather long and wide, rounded in front; middle field of face only just protrude, narrow, in middle 1,5 times shorter lateral fields; antennal cavities deep, far not reach front ocellus level, but almost reach margins of eyes, without roundish tubercles laterally and with distinct, but slight tooth between antennal fossae; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus equal to distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle only just elevated. Clypeus with big punctures, face wrinkly-punctured, face and clypeus strongly shining without microsculpture, frons smooth, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="201.[178,1085,1266,1581]" lastBlockId="202.[178,1086,219,504]" lastPageId="202" lastPageNumber="1519" pageId="201" pageNumber="1518">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum rather long with straight front margin, transverse furrow shallow, narrow. Mesonotum moderately convex, approximately of equal length and breadth; notauli only just marked at base; surface of mesonotum densely punctured (intervals narrower than punctures), shining, without microsculpture; apices of prepectal carinae reach front margin of mesopleurae; subalarum rather high and thick, not sharpened; speculum with rather big punctures; area of mesopleural fovea rather broadly and deeply impressed; mesopleural suture rather deeply impressed, straight, interrupted by thin transversal ribs; sternauli not developed, only just marked at base in form of slight impressions; lower part of mesopleurae with distinct, but not sharp bend; surface of mesopleurae densely punctured, to wrinkled at lower half, shining, with white pubescence; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, strongly slanted, from lateral trian- gle, carinated laterally up to apex, its horizontal part with distinct uniform punctures. Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral gradually slanting backwards, horizontal part approximately 1,8 times shorter than area posteromedia in middle; set of propodeum carinae complete; area superomedia of equal length and breadth or wider than length, rounded in front and narrowed backwards, hexagonal, costulae at middle of area superomedia; carinae of areae dentiparae at apex widened, but not forming distinct apophysises or teeth; spiracles elongated, 2,2-3,3 times longer than width, of moderate size, equal 0,5 of breadth of field at place of spiracle. Surface of propodeum wrinkly-punctured, shining, with white pubescence; metapleurae with big punctures, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="202.[178,994,519,541]" box="[178,994,519,541]" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">L e g s: Long and slender. Claws thin, not great, slightly and uniformly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="202.[178,1086,557,667]" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, asymmetrical (external veins longer than internal); stigma normal, light; radius slightly sinuous, long; radial cell long and broad; nervulus interstitial; ramulus developed, but slightly; membrane of wing slightly yellowish, veins light. Length of front wing only 1,1 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="202.[178,1086,682,1026]" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">A b d o m e n Abdomen from above longish-oval; second tergite at apex 1,2 times wider than length; apical tergites not hidden; ovipositor from above slightly protrude. First tergite from lateral gradually curved, without sharp bend; petiolus flattened at base, laterally carinated by sharp carinae, interspace between them with slight wrinkles; from above petiolus uniformly, but distinctly broadened to postpetiolus; middle field slightly elevated, not carinated, broad with sparse smoothed punctures and smooth shining surface. Gastrocoeli not deep, rather long; thyridia distinct, oblique, considerably narrower than interval (breadth of interval vary in considerably extent); lunulae not big, but distinct; tergites 2 and 3 densely punctured, surface of second tergite strongly, of third dully shining with developed microsculpture, 4th tergite with slight microsculpture, other smooth. Hypopygium of female from lateral triangle, slightly compressed from sides, practically without longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="202.[178,1086,1041,1122]" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black, with reach yellow-white pattern on head, thorax and apical stripes on tergites of abdomen. Legs, with exception of hind coxae, of reddishbrown color.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="202.[178,809,1137,1159]" box="[178,809,1137,1159]" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">S i z e: Body length: 7,8; front wing: 7,0; flagellum: 7,0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="202.[178,253,1174,1196]" box="[178,253,1174,1196]" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="202.[178,1085,1212,1351]" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">
Flagellum without white annulus with distinct longish-oval light tyloides on segments 10-16, in front at apical part with slight notches between segments, but not serrate as 
<taxonomicName authorityName="GRAVENHORST. Unusually" authorityYear="1829" box="[178,289,1271,1292]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Pristiceros" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[178,289,1271,1292]" italics="true" pageId="202" pageNumber="1519">Pristiceros</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, not flattened ventrally and not widened beyond middle; legs more slender than of females; scutellum more gradually slanted; abdomen of male more narrow and long. Males more reachly marked by light-colored (white or slightly yellow) pattern.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>