<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F8462AC737DAC6FD06F5E4C718" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Amblyteles armatorius" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="64" lastPageNumber="1381" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F8462AC737DAC6FD06F5E4C718" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F8462AC737DAC6FD06F5E4C718" lastPageId="64" lastPageNumber="1381" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">
<subSubSection box="[178,643,762,784]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="62.[178,643,762,784]" box="[178,643,762,784]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">
<heading box="[178,643,762,784]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,643,762,784]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">
<taxonomicName authority="(FORSTER)" baseAuthorityName="FORSTER" box="[178,533,762,784]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armatorius">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,413,762,784]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">Amblyteles armatorius</emphasis>
(FÖRSTER)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 16)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="62.[178,996,801,852]" lastBlockId="62.[178,291,866,887]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">
<emphasis box="[178,288,802,822]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">Ichneumons</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="FORSTER 1771" authorityName="FORSTER" authorityYear="1771" box="[293,535,802,822]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armatorius">
<emphasis box="[293,394,802,822]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">armatorius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="FORSTER J" box="[400,535,802,822]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" pagination="81 - 85" refId="ref142153" refString="FORSTER J. R. (1771): Novae species insectorum. Centuria I. - London, 1 - 100 (Ichneumonidae: 81 - 85)." type="book chapter" year="1771">FÖRSTER 1771</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Novae species insectorum, Centula 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[879,890,802,822]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">1</emphasis>
: 82, Ƌ. 
<taxonomicName authority=": HOLMGREN 1856" authorityName="HOLMGREN" authorityYear="1856" box="[178,555,828,848]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armatorius">
<emphasis box="[178,384,828,848]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">Amblyteles armatorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="HOLMGREN A" box="[396,555,828,848]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" pagination="1 - 104" refId="ref142994" refString="HOLMGREN A. E. (1856): Entomologiska antecknigar under en resa i sodra Sverige ar 1854. - Kongliga Svenska Vetenskapsakademiens Handlingar 75 (1854): 1 - 104." type="journal article" year="1856">HOLMGREN 1856</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Svenska Vetensk. Akad. Handl. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[870,893,828,848]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">75</emphasis>
: 39, 
<specimenCount box="[939,951,832,853]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="62.[178,1085,902,1041]" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, with 50 segments, moderately thick, first segment rather short, only three times longer than the width at apex, without white annulus, scarcely widened, very slightly flattened ventrally beyond middle; segments slightly elongated, already segment 14 square from lateral. Flagellum 1,3 times shorter than the front wing and 1,4-1,5 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="64" lastPageNumber="1381" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="62.[178,1085,1056,1605]" lastBlockId="63.[178,1085,219,299]" lastPageId="63" lastPageNumber="1380" pageId="62" pageNumber="1379">H e a d: Head contour from front quite slightly narrowed downwards, only just transversal, only 1,2 times wider than height; genae from front 3,2 times shorter than height of eye; head contour from above strongly transversal, 1,8 times wider than length, strongly, almost linearly narrowed backwards behind eyes. Vertex from lateral sloping nearly perpendicularly from hind borders of ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, in the middle 1,2 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye at middle, parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina sharp all round, from above slightly roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral, occipital carina meeting with hypostomal carina far before base of mandible; malar space 1,3 times longer than the mandible base width; mandibles narrow, evenly narrowed from base to apex, upper tooth considerably longer than lower; clypeus two times wider than length, with straight front margin and distinctly expressed lateral corners, separated from face, by slight impression; clypeal foveae small, deep; labrum equal by breadth to front margin of clypeus, rounded, moderately long; middle field of face slightly expressed, in middle slightly narrower than lateral fields; antennal cavities quite deeply impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, laterally above antennal fossae without tubercles and with slight but distinct interantennal tubercle; margins of antennal fossae slightly elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,7 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle practically not elevated. Surface of clypeus with big punctures, lateral fields wrinkly-punctured, frons roughly wrinkly-punctured, temples densely punctured; surface of head without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,1086,314,864]" pageId="63" pageNumber="1380">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum from above long with straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum deep, narrow, not interrupted by keel; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp; pronotal base gradually curved. Mesonotum moderately convex, only just (1,1 times) longer than width; notauli in form of very slight impressions, with slightly different sculpture; surface of mesonotum densely wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture; axillary tongue not developed; subalarum high, thick; speculum densely wrinkly-punctured, same as other part of upper third of mesopleurae; mesopleural fovea sharply expressed, deep; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs; mesopleurae at bottom without sharp bend; sternauli in a form of indistinct impressions in front third; lower part of mesopleurae wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture; scutellum slightly convex, almost flat, laterally not carinated. Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Length of horizontal part of propodeum 2 times less than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum expressed, with exception of costulae and coxal carina (indistinct), but indistinct because of general roughly-wrinkled sculpture of surface; basal area short and deep; area superomedia rectangular, transversal, two times wider than length; areae dentiparae at apices with apophysises; spiracles long, slit-shaped, along external contour 4 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum, including metapleurae, roughlywrinkled to cellular, shining, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,1009,879,901]" box="[178,1009,879,901]" pageId="63" pageNumber="1380">L e g s: Slender. Hind tibiae with sparse spinules. Claws long, uniformly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,1085,916,1026]" pageId="63" pageNumber="1380">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, practically symmetrical, front veins longer than hind one; stigma broad, light, radial cell broad, radius very slightly sinuous, almost straight; nervulus sharply postfurcal; ramulus long; all veins light; membrane of wing slightly yellowish. Front wing longer than length of flagellum and shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,1085,1041,1415]" pageId="63" pageNumber="1380">A b d o m e n Amblypygous, from above broadly-oval, apical tergites not hidden; second tergite transversal, at apex 1,4 times wider than length; sheath of ovipositor not protrude. First tergite from lateral with sharp bend between petiolus and postpetiolus, not flattened at base, from lateral sharply bordered by carinae and with strong transversal ribs between them; from above petiolus sharply broadened to triangle postpetiolus; distance between spiracles many more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus sharply expressed and high elevated, 1,5 times wider than lateral fields, its surface irregularly roughly longitudinally-striated. Gastrocoeli small, only just impressed, short, oblique; thyridia not developed; lunulae very distinct, elongated; surface of second tergite up to apex very densely punctured to slightly wrinkled, shining; tergites 3-4 densely superficially punctured by very small punctures, apical tergites shagreen. Hypopygium triangle from lateral, without longitudinal fold; sternites 2-3 completely unsclerotized medially.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,1085,1430,1540]" pageId="63" pageNumber="1380">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black with reach yellow pattern: internal orbits, collar and hind corners of pronotum, subalarum and scutellum completely, bands along front margin of 2nd and 3rd and apically of other tergites; all trochanters and partially femora and tibiae of all legs; tarsi of basic color.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[178,834,1555,1577]" box="[178,834,1555,1577]" pageId="63" pageNumber="1380">
S i z e: Body length: 14,0; flagellum: 8,0; front wing: 
<quantity box="[737,830,1555,1577]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.1199999999999999" pageId="63" pageNumber="1380" unit="mm" value="11.2">11,2 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,253,219,241]" box="[178,253,219,241]" pageId="64" pageNumber="1381">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="64.[178,1086,256,366]" pageId="64" pageNumber="1381">Flagellum of male with yellow bacilliform tyloides on segments 4-19; interspace between dorsal and ventro-lateral carinae of petiolus punctured, without transversal ribs. Hypopygium with slightly elongated, rounded apex. Yellow coloration more expanded: face completely, front half of second and third tergite completely and so on.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>