<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846A3C7CEDAC6FA40F7E1C221" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Neolevansa hirsuta GAULD" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="185" lastPageNumber="1502" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846A3C7CEDAC6FA40F7E1C221" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846A3C7CEDAC6FA40F7E1C221" lastPageId="185" lastPageNumber="1502" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">
<subSubSection box="[178,571,1468,1490]" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="183.[178,571,1468,1490]" box="[178,571,1468,1490]" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">
<heading box="[178,571,1468,1490]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,571,1468,1490]" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">
<taxonomicName authority="GAULD" authorityName="GAULD" box="[178,461,1468,1490]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Neolevansa" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hirsuta">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,379,1468,1490]" italics="true" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">Neolevansa hirsuta</emphasis>
GAULD
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 46)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="184" lastPageNumber="1501" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="183.[178,961,1507,1531]" lastBlockId="183.[178,291,1545,1566]" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">
<taxonomicName authority="GAULD 1984" authorityName="GAULD" authorityYear="1984" box="[178,478,1507,1527]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Neolevansa" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hirsuta">
<emphasis box="[178,353,1507,1527]" italics="true" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">Neolevansa hirsuta</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="GAULD I" box="[359,478,1507,1527]" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" pagination="216 - 217" refId="ref142183" refString="GAULD I. D. (1984): An introduction to the Ichneumonidae of Australia. - British Museum (Natural History). Publication 895: 216 - 217." type="journal article" year="1984">GAULD 1984</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- British Mus. (Nat. Hist.) Publ. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[779,813,1507,1527]" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">895</emphasis>
: 216-217, 
<specimenCount box="[912,924,1511,1532]" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
,Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="183.[178,1085,1581,1603]" lastBlockId="184.[178,1085,219,328]" lastPageId="184" lastPageNumber="1501" pageId="183" pageNumber="1500">F l a g e l l u m: Long and slender, [27]-segments, not widened beyond middle, gradu- ally attenuated toward apex, with white annulus on segments 8-14, beyond annulus only just visible flattened ventrally; basal segments long with oblique apex, first segment from lateral 4 times longer than width at apex laterally. Flagellum 1,5 times shorter than front wing and 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="185" lastPageNumber="1502" pageId="184" pageNumber="1501" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="184.[178,1086,344,951]" pageId="184" pageNumber="1501">H e a d: Head contour from front gradually narrowed downwards, transversal, 1,3 times wider than height; genae from front long, 4,5 times sorter than height of eye; head contour from above transversal, 2 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral straightly slanting to occipital carina; temples from above strongly roundly narrowed behind eyes, rather long, in middle 1,4 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye, laterally from upper third parallel to hind margin of eye; occipital carina from above gradually impressed to hind ocelli, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, sharp, high, meeting with hypostomal carina not reaching mandible base; length of abscissula equal to mandible base width; malar space 1,2 times longer than mandible base width; mandibles with form character to tribe, gradually narrowed from base to apex, from above rather sharply curved; clypeus convex, transversal, two times wider than length with straight front margin and rounded lateral corners, with thinned apex, separated from middle field of face by suture; clypeal foveae moderately large, deep; labrum long, triangle, rounded in front, equal by breadth to front margin of clypeus; middle field of face only just elevated above lateral fields, but sharply limited, narrow, in middle considerably narrower than lateral fields; antennal cavities sharp, deep, but not big, not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level with strong tooth between antennal fossae; frons before front ocellus with strong impression; ocelli of normal size, moderately convex, diameter of lateral ocellus equal to distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle distinctly limited. Clypeus and face with slight superficial punctures, without microsculpture; temples with superficial punctures, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="184.[178,1085,967,1545]" pageId="184" pageNumber="1501">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum moderately long with shallow and narrow furrow, from above with straight front margin. Mesonotum convex, of equal length and breadth, notauli in form of slight impression in front third; axillary tongue not developed; surface densely punctured without microsculpture, shining; subalarum thick, not sharpened; speculum punctured by big punctures, shining; area of mesopleural fovea slightly broadly impressed; mesopleural suture deep, interrupted by sharp transversal ribs; mesopleurae without sharp bend at lower part; sternauli only just marked in form of slight impressions in front third; hind corner of mesopleurae strongly protrude above middle coxae; surface densely punctured, shining between punctures, without microsculpture; scutellum high elevated, laterally and at apex carinated, horizontal part strongly convex with sparse punctures, without microsculpture, shining. Hind margin of metanotum with sharp triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral with distinct division on horizontal and vertical parts approximately equal by length; all carinae of horizontal part developed, except front branches of lateral longitudinal carinae; area posteromedia and third lateral field merged; coxal carina not developed; area basalis long, area superomedia regularly hexagonal; costulae some before middle of area superomedia; areae dentiparae at apices with transversal lamellar broadenings (teeth); spiracles slit-shaped, long, 2,8 times longer than width, high elevated above surface of area spiraculifera. Surface of area superomedia smooth, shining, other areas wrinkled, shining, metapleurae strongly shining with big smoothed punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="184.[178,1085,1560,1582]" box="[178,1085,1560,1582]" pageId="184" pageNumber="1501">L e g s: Strong, stumpy, tarsi of all legs thickened with flattened area of all segments as</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="185.[178,1085,219,270]" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">
of 
<taxonomicName authority="CAMERON" authorityName="CAMERON" box="[208,400,219,241]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Abzaria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[208,288,219,241]" italics="true" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">Abzaria</emphasis>
CAMERON
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicName authority="GAULD" authorityName="GAULD" authorityYear="1984" box="[410,610,219,241]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Neolevansa" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[410,528,219,241]" italics="true" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">Neolevansa</emphasis>
GAULD
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authority="RATZEBURG." authorityName="RATZEBURG." box="[666,946,219,241]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Poecilostictus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[666,808,219,241]" italics="true" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">Poecilostictus</emphasis>
RATZEBURG.
</taxonomicName>
Segments of hind tarsi shortened. Claws strong, smooth, strongly curved.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="185.[178,1085,285,395]" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular with blunted base, almost pentagonal, slightly asymmetrical; stigma broad, dark; radius slightly sinuous, almost straight at most part, long; radial cell long, broad; nervulus slightly postfurcal; ramulus rather long; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Front wing 1,4 times longer than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="185.[178,1086,410,725]" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">A b d o m e n:Abdomen from above elongated, drop-shaped, dorsally flattened, second tergite slightly transversal, at apex 1,2 times wider than length; sheath of ovipositor only just protrude behind apex of abdomen, apex of abdomen cut. Petiolus at base distinctly wider than height, from lateral uniformly curved without sharp bend to postpetiolus, from above also gradually broadened to postpetiolus; from carinae of first tergite distinctly expressed only ventrolateral carina and base of dorsolateral carina; lateral surface of petiolus slightly wrinkled; middle field of postpetiolus not developed, surface of postpetiolus smooth, shining. Gastrocoeli broadly impressed, with weak thyridia, interval 1,2 times wider than gastrocoeli; lunulae completely absent; all tergites of abdomen smooth, polished, without sculpture. Hypopygium of females broad, flat with slight longitudinal fold and with fascicle of long hairs at apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="185.[178,1085,740,909]" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">C o l o r a t i o n: Head and thorax black with yellow and red pattern. Yellow: genae, margins of clypeus, internal orbits broadly, upper margin and base of pronotum, subalarum, spots on mesopleurae, scutellum, postscutellum, spots on metapleurae. Red: apex of clypeus, external orbits, abdomen entirely red, with exception of narrow, slightly expressed yellow apical stripes on apical tergites. Legs with exception of apices of hind femora and tibiae red. Scapus and some basal segments of flagellum mainly red.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="185.[178,847,924,946]" box="[178,847,924,946]" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">S i z e: Body length: 11,5; flagellum: 10,0; front wing: 16,0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="185.[178,253,961,983]" box="[178,253,961,983]" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="185.[178,1085,999,1108]" pageId="185" pageNumber="1502">Flagellum of male with big broadly-oval light-brown tyloides on segments 12-18 at place of white annulus. In contrast to females legs slender and hind tarsi slightly thickened and their segments not shortened. Yellow coloration more expanded on coxae. In other respects similar to females.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>