<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84655C735DAC6FD89F4C3C3FF" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Aethioplites madagascariensis HEINRICH" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="1383" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84655C735DAC6FD89F4C3C3FF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84655C735DAC6FD89F4C3C3FF" lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="1383" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">
<subSubSection box="[178,714,629,651]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,714,629,651]" box="[178,714,629,651]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">
<heading box="[178,714,629,651]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,714,629,651]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,607,629,651]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Aethioplites" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="madagascariensis">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,492,629,651]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">Aethioplites madagascariensis</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 17)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,1024,669,718]" lastBlockId="65.[178,291,733,753]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH 1938" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1938" box="[178,604,669,689]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Aethioplites" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="madagascariensis">
<emphasis box="[178,456,669,689]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">Aethioplites madagascariensis</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="HEINRICH G" box="[461,604,669,689]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" pagination="7 - 139" refId="ref142508" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1938. Les Ichneumonides de Madagascar, part 3, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae. - Extr. Mem. Acad. Malgache 25: 7 - 139." type="journal article" year="1938">HEINRICH 1938</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mém. Acad. Malgache 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[838,861,669,689]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">25</emphasis>
: 75, 
<specimenCount box="[907,919,673,694]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. 
<taxonomicName authority="HEINRICH 1969" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1969" box="[178,606,695,715]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Aethioplites" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="madagascariensis">
<emphasis box="[178,456,695,715]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">Aethioplites madagascariensis</emphasis>
HEINRICH 1969
</taxonomicName>
- Ichn. Stenop. of Africa 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[843,854,695,715]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">4</emphasis>
: 701, 785, 
<specimenCount box="[967,979,699,720]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,1085,769,908]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, very long, not widened beyond middle but flattened ventrally, with 40-43 segments, with white semiannulus dorsally on segments 7- 12 or 5-(13); first segment long, 5,4 times longer than width at apex, approximately segment 17 square. Flagellum 1,2 times shorter than the front wing and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="1383" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,1086,923,1501]" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">H e a d: Head contour from front sharply, almost straightly narrowed downwards, only just transversal, only 1,2 times wider than height; genae from front very long, 4 times shorter than height of eye; head from above transversal, 2 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral straightly slanting down after the ocelli to occipital carina; temples 1,6 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, from side parallel to hind margin of an eye, from above sharply narrowed behind eyes; occipital carina high, sharp, from above deeply and roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and level of hind ocelli; hypostomal carina not visible from side, meeting with occipital carina far from mandible base; malar space approximately equal to mandible base width, or 1,3 times more; mandibles narrow, with small weak apical teeth, lower tooth moved inside relative to upper; clypeus flat, transversal, approximately 1,9 wider than height, not separated from middle field by impression, front margin of clypeus slightly concave, lateral corners distinct; clypeal fovea small, but sharp; labrum protrude from under clypeus, roundish, equal by breadth to clypeus front margin; middle field of face only just elevated, wider than lateral fields; antennal cavities slightly impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, laterally above antennal fossae with distinct tubercles but with only just visible tubercle between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae high elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus equal to distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle expressed. Surface of head dull with only just visible superficial punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[178,1085,1517,1597]" lastBlockId="66.[178,1086,219,651]" lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="1383" pageId="65" pageNumber="1382">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum rather long with straight front margin (from above); transverse furrow of pronotum moderately deep, not interrupted by keel; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp, short; pronotal base gradually curved. Mesonotum moder- ately convex, 1,2 times longer than width; notauli only as slight impressions at base (middle lobe only just elevated in front third); surface of mesonotum with confluent punctures, matt; axillary tongue not developed; subalarum high, thin, sharpened; speculum matt, as well as other part of mesopleurae and as thorax in whole; area of mesopleural fovea broadly, but slightly impressed; prepectal carina reach pronotum, sharp all round; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by only just expressed transversal ribs; sharp border between vertical and horizontal parts of mesopleurae not expressed; sternauli absent (only as slight impressions at base); surface of mesopleurae slightly wrinkly-punctured, matt; scutellum very sharply elevated above postscutellum, carinated laterally up to apex by high lamelliform carinae, its horizontal part slightly convex. Hind margin of metanotum with small triangular projections. Horizontal part of propodeum almost two times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle; areas and carinae of propodeum reduced, only carina metapleuralis and slightly marked apical transverse carina developed; spiracles long, slit-shaped; propodeum with strong apophysises. Surface of propodeum wrinkled, matt.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,1085,666,717]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383">L e g s: Very long and slender; hind coxae without scopa. Claws massive, smooth, gradually curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,1085,732,872]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, pointed in front, almost petiolate, symmetrical; stigma narrow, light brown; radial cell narrow and long; radius almost straight, slightly curved only at apex; nervulus slightly postfurcal; ramulus practically absent; all veins of hind wing pigmented. Membrane of wing yellowish. Length of front wing of female 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,1085,886,1160]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383">A b d o m e n: From above long, fusiform; second tergite longer than width at apex; ovipositor considerably protrude behind apex; abdomen oxypygous, at apex compressed from sides. First tergite from lateral gradually curved to postpetiolus, with very narrow petiolus at base, from lateral smooth, without traces of lateral carinae and any sculpture; from above petiolus gradually broadened to postpetiolus; middle field only just marked and not limited by dorsal carinae, its surface smooth, only lateral fields of postpetiolus with slight rugosity. Gastrocoeli slightly impressed, long; thyridia small, far removed from base of tergite and reach its lateral margins, perpendicular to longitudinal axis of a body; lunulae very small; surface of second and third tergites with small punctures, matt, other tergites, slightly shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,1085,1174,1252]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383">C o l o r a t i o n: Body mainly rusty-red. Head mainly whitely-yellow with black pattern on ocellar triangle and vertex. Apex of abdomen black with white pattern: tergites 5-6 with broad white band at apex, seventh practically completely white.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,851,1267,1289]" box="[178,851,1267,1289]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383">
S i z e: Body length: 12,8; front wing: 10,5; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[765,848,1267,1289]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="8.9" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383" unit="mm" value="8.9">8,9 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,253,1304,1326]" box="[178,253,1304,1326]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="66.[178,1085,1340,1418]" pageId="66" pageNumber="1383">Similar on morphology and coloration to female. Segments of males flagellum with transversal ridges and bacilliform tyloides on segments 10-15. Black coloration of abdomen more expanded, tergite 4 completely black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>