<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84681C7E0DAC6FABCF579C04B" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Notoplatylabus podolicus subsp. conterranius TERESHKIN" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="151" lastPageNumber="1468" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84681C7E0DAC6FABCF579C04B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84681C7E0DAC6FABCF579C04B" lastPageId="151" lastPageNumber="1468" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">
<subSubSection box="[178,819,1344,1366]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="149.[178,819,1344,1366]" box="[178,819,1344,1366]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">
<heading box="[178,819,1344,1366]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,819,1344,1366]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">
<taxonomicName authority="TERESHKIN" authorityName="TERESHKIN" box="[178,709,1344,1366]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Notoplatylabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="podolicus" subSpecies="conterranius">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,580,1344,1366]" italics="true" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">Notoplatylabus podolicus conterranius</emphasis>
TERESHKIN
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 34)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="149.[178,1062,1384,1407]" lastBlockId="149.[178,291,1422,1442]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">
<taxonomicName authority="TERESHKIN 1993" authorityName="TERESHKIN" authorityYear="1993" box="[178,694,1384,1404]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Notoplatylabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="podolicus" subSpecies="conterranius">
<emphasis box="[178,532,1384,1404]" italics="true" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">Notoplatylabus podolicus conterranius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="TERESHKIN A" box="[537,694,1384,1404]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" pagination="477 - 488" refId="ref143712" refString="TERESHKIN A. (1993): New and little known species of Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of the genera Ulesta CAMERON 1903, Notoplatylabus HEINRICH 1934, and Neischnus HEINRICH 1952 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae). - Entomofauna 14 (29): 477 - 488." type="journal article" year="1993">TERESHKIN 1993</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Entomofauna 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[842,865,1384,1404]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">14</emphasis>
(29): 477-488, 
<specimenCount box="[1007,1019,1388,1409]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="149.[178,1085,1458,1568]" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">
Morphologically it is similar to female of 
<taxonomicName authority="podolicus HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" box="[613,1085,1458,1480]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Notoplatylabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="149" pageNumber="1465" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="podolicus" subSpecies="podolicus">
<emphasis box="[613,979,1458,1480]" italics="true" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">Notoplatylabus podolicus podolicus</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
being different by more sharp sculpture of body, more small size and by saturated black coloration. The characters, only differing it from European 
<taxonomicName authority="podolicus HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Notoplatylabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="149" pageNumber="1465" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="podolicus" subSpecies="podolicus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">Notoplatylabus podolicus podolicus</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
are given below.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="151" lastPageNumber="1468" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="149.[178,845,1583,1605]" lastBlockId="150.[178,1085,219,358]" lastPageId="150" lastPageNumber="1467" pageId="149" pageNumber="1466">F l a g e l l u m: Flagellum 1,3 times longer than the front wing. H e a d: Malar space 7 times shorter than height of eye from front; head contour from above more sharply transversal, 2,9 times wider than length. Clypeus more convex, slightly transversal, 1,6 times wider than length; lateral margins of antennal cavities less raised above margins of eyes and practically not striated longitudinally, high raised only in lower part; ocellar triangle distinctly elevated.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,1086,373,541]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">T h o r a x: Pronotal ridge not thickened and with cellular impression along margin; front part of pronotum to epomiae with sharp longitudinal wrinkles; pronotal base with more sharp angular projection above front coxae than of European subspecies. Surface of mesonotum around notauli with sharp transversal wrinkles; subalarum more low. Costulae at middle of area superomedia. Metapleurae slightly convex, very densely irregularly wrinkled.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,1085,557,667]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">A b d o m e n:Abdomen from above rather broad, longish-oval to drop-shaped, broadening up to apex of third tergite. Gastrocoeli some narrower than interval between them; lunulae only just expressed; third tergite with impression at base, often sharp. Second sternite almost completely unsclerotized.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,838,682,704]" box="[178,838,682,704]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">
S i z e: Body length: 5,7; front wing: 4,6; f l a g e l l u m: 
<quantity box="[754,834,682,704]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.9" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467" unit="mm" value="5.9">5,9 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,565,719,741]" box="[178,565,719,741]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">
Variation of body length: 
<quantity box="[441,561,719,741]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.65" metricValueMax="5.8" metricValueMin="5.5" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467" unit="mm" value="5.65" valueMax="5.8" valueMin="5.5">5,5-5,8 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,253,756,778]" box="[178,253,756,778]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,391,794,816]" box="[178,391,794,816]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">M o r p h o l o g y:</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,1085,831,882]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">Surface of body of males in contrast to that of females with variable, very rough sculpture from moderately, to vastly expressed.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,1085,898,1007]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, with 31-34 segments, not widened beyond middle and not flattened ventrally, basal segments scarcely elongated, first segment three times longer than width at apex laterally, with long row very poorly visible (indistinctly limited) short-oval tyloides (to practically full absence), without traces of white annulus.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="150.[178,1085,1023,1601]" pageId="150" pageNumber="1467">H e a d: Head contour from front sharply narrowed downwards, with large eyes, from above sharply narrowed behind eyes; occiput abrupt just after the ocelli, from above deeply impressed to ocelli; temples from lateral sharply narrowed downwards, 2,4 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye at middle. Occipital carina from above absent, from lateral sharp, at bottom angularly curved forward, opposite of projection of pronotal base, lower of fracture slightly widened; hypostomal carina visible from lateral on considerable length, meeting with occipital carina on mandible base; malar space 1,2 times shorter than mandible base width; mandibles as of female very narrow and thin with small lower tooth strongly moved inside; clypeus separated from face by deep groove, strongly elevated at the base, with thin straight apical margin, slightly impressed at middle; clypeal foveae sharp, deep; labrum equal by breadth to clypeus front margin, rectangular, rather long; internal margins of eyes parallel, face transversal; middle field of face convex, narrower than lateral fields; antennal cavities slightly impressed, not reach front ocellus level, theirs lateral margins only just elevated above margins of eyes, with only just visible tubercle between antennal fossae; ocelli very large, high elevated; distance from hind ocellus to eye approximately equal to 0,7 diameter of an ocellus; ocellar triangle sharply elevated. Middle field of face wrinkly-punctured; lateral fields punctured, shining, with indistinct microsculpture; clypeus with sparse punctures, more dense at base, its surface without microsculpture, shining; malar surface with strong microsculpture, matt.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="151.[178,1086,219,973]" pageId="151" pageNumber="1468">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum very short with straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum shallow, narrow, interrupted keel and laterally from it by ribs; pronotal ridge with deep longitudinal impression with cellular sculpture; pronotal base above front coxae with angulate projection; epomiae strongly developed, reach pronotal ridge; surface of pronotum smooth, polished. Mesonotum strongly convex, wider than length; middle lobe of mesonotum high elevated, roughly-wrinkled, matt, laterally slightly shining; notauli very deep and long, almost reach to scuto-scutellar groove, with strong transversal carinae; lateral lobes of mesonotum densely wrinkly-punctured, slightly shining; mesonotum bordered by deep furrow with transversal carinae; scuto-scutellar groove very deep with polished surface; prepectus behind front coxae strongly impressed up to margin of prepectus; subalarum thin, low; speculum smooth, shining, not sculptured; area of mesopleural fovea very deeply impressed; sternauli deep, long with transversal carinae, reach two third of mesopleurae; mesopleurae, with exception of speculum, with strong longitudinal sinuous carinae; longitudinal furrow of mesosternum very deep, with transversal ribs and strongly broadened backwards; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, laterally carinated by high carinae, dorsal surface cellular in different degree; postscutellum more often trapeziform, with cellular sculpture, sharply carinated. Metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral shortened and slanted, horizontal part of propodeum almost two times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle. All fields of propodeum distinct; area basalis very deep, its surface from smooth, polished, to with transversal projection (rib); area superomedia hexagonal, transversal, costulae at middle; carinae, bordering area superomedia and costulae very high; spiracles of propodeum very small, circular, equal 0,25 breadth of field at place of spiracle; area dentipara at apex with strong tooth. Surface of propodeum roughly cellular-wrinkled with numerous strong sinuous carinae; metapleurae cellular, or with strong sinuous ribs.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="151.[178,1085,988,1068]" pageId="151" pageNumber="1468">L e g s: Legs moderately slender, hind stumpy; hind femora strongly widened, with very slight impression on external surface; claws very small, thin, sharply curved at upper third.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="151.[178,1085,1084,1164]" pageId="151" pageNumber="1468">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, almost symmetrical; stigma very broad, dark; radius short, practically straight; nervulus interstitial; ramulus developed. Front wing 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="151.[178,1085,1180,1465]" pageId="151" pageNumber="1468">A b d o m e n:Fromabove rather broadly-oval; second tergite transversal. First tergite flattened, from lateral with gradual, but distinct bend to postpetiolus; lateral carinae sharp, surface between them wrinkled; dorsomedian carinae of first tergite not developed; dorsally petiolus gradually broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus convex, not carinated by carinae, its surface from smooth, to slightly irregularly-wrinkled. Gastrocoeli moderately impressed, rectangular; thyridia distinct, short, transverse, wider or equal to interval between them; lunulae distinct; base of second tergite often impressed in different degree; surface of second and third tergites densely punctured, other tergites with slight superficial punctures. Second and third sternites almost completely unsclerotized.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="151.[178,1085,1480,1561]" pageId="151" pageNumber="1468">C o l o r a t i o n: Completely black, with exception of white apex of sixth tergite and seventh tergite completely; paramerae black; legs from light to dark-brown; hind tibiae at apex darkened.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="151.[178,809,1576,1598]" box="[178,809,1576,1598]" pageId="151" pageNumber="1468">
S i z e: Body length: 5,8; front wing: 4,0; flagellum: 
<quantity box="[725,805,1576,1598]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.6" pageId="151" pageNumber="1468" unit="mm" value="4.6">4,6 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>