<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846A9C7C8DAC6FBE2F5E6C7A3" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Asthenolabus vitratorius" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="191" lastPageNumber="1508" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1317</mods:start>
<mods:end>1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846A9C7C8DAC6FBE2F5E6C7A3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846A9C7C8DAC6FBE2F5E6C7A3" lastPageId="191" lastPageNumber="1508" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">
<subSubSection box="[178,727,1054,1076]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="189.[178,727,1054,1076]" box="[178,727,1054,1076]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">
<heading box="[178,727,1054,1076]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,727,1054,1076]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">
<taxonomicName authority="(GRAVENHORST)" baseAuthorityName="GRAVENHORST" box="[178,617,1054,1076]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Asthenolabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitratorius">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,434,1054,1076]" italics="true" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">Asthenolabus vitratorius</emphasis>
(GRAVENHORST)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 48)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="189.[178,935,1092,1165]" box="[178,817,1092,1113]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">
<taxonomicName authority="GRAVENHORST 1829" authorityName="GRAVENHORST" authorityYear="1829" box="[178,580,1093,1113]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Mesoleptus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitratorius">
<emphasis box="[178,382,1093,1113]" italics="true" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">Mesoleptus vitratorius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="GRAVENHORST I" box="[388,580,1093,1113]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" pagination="1 - 827" refId="ref142250" refString="GRAVENHORST I. L. C. (1829): Ichneumonologia Europea. - Vratislaviae, Sum. Auct. 1: 1 - 827." type="journal article" year="1829">GRAVENHORST 1829</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ichneum. Eur. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[735,746,1093,1113]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">2</emphasis>
: 34, Ƌ.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="189.[178,935,1092,1165]" box="[178,935,1118,1144]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">
<taxonomicName authority=": SCHMIEDEKNECHT 1930" authorityName="SCHMIEDEKNECHT" authorityYear="1930" box="[178,612,1119,1139]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Platylabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitratorius">
<emphasis box="[178,376,1119,1139]" italics="true" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">Platylabus vitratorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="SCHMIEDEKNECHT O" box="[388,612,1119,1139]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" pagination="1 - 28" refId="ref143512" refString="SCHMIEDEKNECHT O. (1930): Opuscula Ichneumonologica. - Supplement-Band. Fsc. IX. - Blankenburg Thuringen, 5 - 55, 1 - 28." type="journal article" year="1930">SCHMIEDEKNECHT 1930</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Opusc. Ichneum. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[792,803,1119,1139]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">9</emphasis>
: 39-40, Ƌ, 
<specimenCount box="[910,922,1123,1144]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="189.[178,935,1092,1165]" box="[178,906,1145,1165]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">
<taxonomicName authority=": HEINRICH 1951" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1951" box="[178,556,1145,1165]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Asthenolabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitratorius">
<emphasis box="[178,401,1145,1165]" italics="true" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">Asthenolabus vitratorius</emphasis>
: HEINRICH 1951
</taxonomicName>
- Bonn. Zool. Beitr. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[748,759,1145,1165]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">2</emphasis>
(3-4): 240, syn.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="191" lastPageNumber="1508" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="189.[178,1085,1182,1351]" box="[178,291,1182,1204]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">F e ma l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="189.[178,1085,1182,1351]" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">F l a g e l l u m: Long and very slender, with 37-38 segments, not widened beyond middle, slightly flattened ventrally and strongly attenuated toward apex, with white annulus on segments 8-12; basal segments long; first segment 5 times longer than width at apex laterally, all segments longer than wide. Flagellum 1,3 times longer than the front wing and approximately equal to body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="189.[178,1085,1367,1594]" lastBlockId="190.[178,1086,219,533]" lastPageId="190" lastPageNumber="1507" pageId="189" pageNumber="1506">H e a d: Head contour from front roundish, 1,2 times wider than height; genae from front roundly narrowed, 3,8 times sorter than height of eye; head contour from above transversal, two times wider than length. Vertex from lateral roundly oblique to occipital carina; temples from above gradually roundly narrowed behind eyes, long, in middle only just shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye, from lateral temples narrowed downwards; occipital carina from above gradually impressed to hind ocelli, not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, sharp, before mandible base reduced; malar space equal to mandible base width; mandibles with form character to tribe, gradually narrowed from base to apex; clypeus convex, transversal, with straight front margin oblique lateral margins and rounded lateral corners, thinned along apex, separated from middle field of face by impression; clypeal foveae moderately large, deep; labrum short, broad, rounded in front; middle field of face only just elevated above lateral fields and slightly differentiated, in middle some shorter than lateral fields; antennal cavities deep, but not big, not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, with roundish tubercle laterally and strong tooth (tubercle) between antennal fossae; ocelli of normal size, moderately convex, diameter of lateral ocellus only just less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle not elevated. Clypeus punctured, middle field of face wrinkly-punctured, lateral fields of face with slight, superficial punctures; head surface slightly shining with microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="190.[178,1085,549,1039]" pageId="190" pageNumber="1507">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum short with shallow and narrow transverse furrow, from above rounded from front. Mesonotum moderately convex, of equal length and breadth, notauli not developed; axillary tongue not developed; surface of mesonotum densely punctured with developed microsculpture, matt; subalarum thin, sharp; speculum punctured by big punctures, shining; area of mesopleural fovea slightly impressed; mesopleurae with gradual bend at lower part; sternauli only just marked at base, practically not expressed; surface wrinkly-punctured, at lower half roughly longitudinally-wrinkled, shining between punctures; scutellum comparatively slightly elevated, laterally carinated up to apex, horizontal part slightly convex with sparse shallow punctures, without microsculpture. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral strongly and gradually slanting backwards, horizontal part 1,7 times shorter than area posteromedia in middle; all carinae with exception of costulae developed; area basalis rather long, area superomedia square; area dentipara without tooth at apex; spiracles large, long, 2,5 times longer than width (equal 0,6 breadth of area at level of spiracle). Propodeum shining, punctured by big punctures, surface of area superomedia slightly irregularly-wrinkled, metapleurae strongly shining with big punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="190.[178,1085,1054,1106]" pageId="190" pageNumber="1507">L e g s: Slender; hind femora thickened. Claws thin, strongly curved at apex, almost at right angle.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="190.[178,1085,1121,1202]" pageId="190" pageNumber="1507">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, symmetrical; stigma not broad, light; radius slightly sinuous, especially at apical part, long; nervulus interstitial; ramulus only just marked; membrane of wing hyaline, veins light. Front wing 1,4 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="190.[178,1086,1217,1590]" pageId="190" pageNumber="1507">A b d o m e n:Abdomen from above longish-oval, dorsally flattened, second tergite at apex only just wider than length; sheath of ovipositor protrude behind apex of abdomen. Petiolus at base slightly wider than height, from lateral gradually transform to postpetiolus (without sharp bend), from above also slightly broadened to postpetiolus; dorsomedian carina of petiolus slightly expressed only to spiracles, dorsolateral carina developed, ventrolateral carina only just expressed; lateral carinae merge before base of petiolus; surface between lateral carinae not sculptured, smooth, shining; middle field of postpetiolus not developed, surface of middle field superficially-wrinkled. Gastrocoeli only just impressed, thyridia atrophied, interval many wider than gastrocoeli; lunulae small, distinct, but not elevated and distinct only by not sculpturated surface; middle surface of tergites 2 and 3 superficially-wrinkled, with dull shine, other tergites smooth, shining; tergites 6 and 7 with membranous apex. Hypopygium with sharpened apex and slight longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="191.[178,1085,219,328]" pageId="191" pageNumber="1508">C o l o r a t i o n: Head and thorax black with slight white pattern on frontal orbits (narrowly), often spot on subalarum, scutellum and often postscutellum white. Abdomen red with darkening on tergites 4 and 5-7; (5)-6th tergites with white membranous apex, 7th with large membranous spot. Legs with exception of coxae and trochanters red.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="191.[178,809,344,366]" box="[178,809,344,366]" pageId="191" pageNumber="1508">S i z e: Body length: 7,8; front wing: 5,6; flagellum: 7,0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="191.[178,253,381,403]" box="[178,253,381,403]" pageId="191" pageNumber="1508">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="191.[178,1085,418,470]" pageId="191" pageNumber="1508">White pattern of males more reach: margins of clypeus and internal orbits broadly, subalarum, spot on tegulae, scutellum, spots at apex of tergites 5-7 of abdomen.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>