<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6235398" ID-GBIF-Dataset="062987ea-d4b2-4e44-a8da-43e0b4d50708" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100122594" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6235398" ModsDocID="21682" checkinTime="1249509580828" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Yamane, S., Bui, T. V. &amp; Eguchi, K." docDate="2008" docId="44C3C2E8336E317FD75E9D62DB115F12" docLanguage="en" docName="21682.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1767" docSource="http://hol.osu.edu/reference-full.html?id=21682" docTitle="Opamyrma Yamane, Bui &amp; Eguchi, 2008, gen. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="56" masterDocId="0092243E4637E4D075B1A81F971BC8B1" masterDocTitle="Opamyrma hungvuong, a new genus and species of ant related to Apomyrma (Hymenoptera: Formicidae: Amblyoponinae)" masterLastPageNumber="63" masterPageNumber="55" pageNumber="56" updateTime="1645586640780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Opamyrma hungvuong, a new genus and species of ant related to Apomyrma (Hymenoptera: Formicidae: Amblyoponinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Yamane, S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bui, T. V.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Eguchi, K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2008</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1767</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>55</mods:start>
<mods:end>63</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hol.osu.edu/reference-full.html?id=21682</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">21682</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6235398" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100122594" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6235398" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:44C3C2E8336E317FD75E9D62DB115F12" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/44C3C2E8336E317FD75E9D62DB115F12" lastPageNumber="56" pageNumber="56">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="56">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:238041" authority="Yamane, Tuan Viet Bui &amp; Eguchi, 2008" authorityName="Yamane, Tuan Viet Bui &amp; Eguchi" authorityYear="2008" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Opamyrma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Opamyrma Yamane, Bui &amp; Eguchi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Opamyrma</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="genus">gen. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Figs. 1-12)
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="56">
Type species. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:238042" authority="Yamane, Tuan Viet Bui &amp; Eguchi, 2008" authorityName="Yamane, Tuan Viet Bui &amp; Eguchi" authorityYear="2008" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Opamyrma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Opamyrma hungvuong Yamane, Bui &amp; Eguchi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hungvuong">Opamyrma hungvuong</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="56">Worker description. Preoccipital carina complete, almost encircling the head slightly before its posterior margin (&quot;poc&quot; in Fig. 4). Venter of head with a distinct and complete median furrow, with each anterolateral corner forming a process (&quot;alc&quot; in Fig. 3). Clypeus posteriorly margined with a distinct continuous carina (&quot;pcc&quot; in Fig. 3); median part of clypeus rather clearly divided into posterior horizontal portion and anterior steep slope; the posterior portion broadly inserted between antennal sockets, extending anteriorly to the level of posterior margin of the sockets; lateral part of clypeus narrow from front to back. Mandibular base with closed trulleum (&quot;trl&quot; in Fig. 3). Labrum on its outer face with at least two rows of peg-like denticles, each with more than 10 denticles (&quot;lpd&quot; in Fig. 3). Eye absent. Frontal lobe absent. Antennal sockets completely exposed in full-face view, directing almost dorsad, located in a large, roundly excavated area whose anterior wall is steep just behind the posterior margin of clypeus; the area not clearly defined posteriorly. Antenna 12- segmented, gradually incrassate from segment II to XII.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="56">Mesosoma elongate, with a single furrow (&quot;msf&quot; in Figs. 6 &amp; 7) which is deep and flexible and separates pronotum from the remaining part of mesosoma. Metapleural gland bulla round, occupying posterior twofifths of ventrolateral part of the pleuron; metapleural trench running below the bulla. Junction of dorsal and posterior faces of propodeum round without any transverse carina; posterior face of propodeum laterally without spines/carinae. Propodeal spiracle situated relatively low on the side of propodeum, near the weak furrow separating metapleuron from lateral side of propodeum. Propodeal lobe present, low and round.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="56">Mid- and hind tibiae each with a reduced barbulate anterior spur (&quot;ats&quot; in Fig. 8) and a well-developed pectinate posterior spur (&quot;pts&quot; in Fig. 8). Pretarsal claws simple, without teeth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="56">Waist consisting of a single segment (petiole); petiole elongate, narrowly attached to abdominal segment III (gastral segment I), virtually without anterior peduncle; tergo-sternal sutures of petiole present as longitudinal furrows on ventrolateral edges that meet medially at 1/3 length of petiole from the base (&quot;tss&quot; in Fig. 10); the sternite of petiole reduced to a small posteroventral sclerite, bounded by the conspicuous tergo-sternal sutures; petiolar spiracle located anteriorly on the lateral face of petiole at its mid-height.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="56">Gaster very long, laterally compressed, especially in posterior portion, in profile highest at the posterior end of abdominal segment VI (&quot;absg-VI&quot; in Fig. 11). Segment III (&quot;absg-III&quot; in Fig. 11) seen from above longer than broad, narrowed basally, longer than segments IV, V and VI, having a free anterior face above the helcium; anteriormost part of abdominal sternite III (&quot;abs-III&quot; in Fig.11) produced anteriad to the same level as the anteriormost part of tergite III (&quot;abt-III&quot; in Fig. 11). Segment IV with differentiated presternite (&quot;ps-IV&quot; in Fig. 11). Spiracles on segments V-VII concealed by the preceding segments. Segment VII (&quot;absg-VII&quot; in Fig. 11) longest among the segments III-VII. Pygidium (&quot;abt-VII&quot; in Fig. 11) and hypopygium (&quot;abs-VII&quot; in Fig. 11) unarmed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="56">56 • Zootaxa 1767 © 2008 Magnolia Press</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="56">YAMANE ET AL.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>