<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047597" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:70513FD4-F630-4E90-B766-1FD74195425D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="6060ECC00C11AD5964A5DA6F03520E14" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio exiguitatis Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="70513FD4-F630-4E90-B766-1FD74195425D" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="77" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="74" pageNumber="75" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047597" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:70513FD4-F630-4E90-B766-1FD74195425D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6060ECC00C11AD5964A5DA6F03520E14" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="74" pageNumber="75">
<subSubSection pageId="74" pageNumber="75" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/70513FD4-F630-4E90-B766-1FD74195425D" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio exiguitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="74" pageNumber="75" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exiguitatis">Oxyscelio exiguitatis Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="74" pageNumber="75">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 97-100; Morphbank46
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="74" pageNumber="75" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Female. Body length 2.3-3.05 mm (n=15).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: shorter than pedicel. A4: longer than broad. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="74" pageNumber="75">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: with some transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: granulate. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by a set of irregular elevations. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: omicron-shaped, with sharp corners where median portion meets lateral portions. Occiput sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; absent. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: granulate. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="75" lastPageNumber="76" pageId="74" pageNumber="75">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: with shallow irregular carinae, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum periph 
<pageBreakToken pageId="75" pageNumber="76" start="start">erally</pageBreakToken>
: absent; punctate. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T5. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="75" pageNumber="76">
T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: with medially truncate emargination, sloping down to apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: present as tiny apical sharp projections. T6 
<pageBreakToken pageId="76" pageNumber="77" start="start">raised</pageBreakToken>
peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Male. unknown.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Figures 97-100. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio exiguitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exiguitatis">Oxyscelio exiguitatis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 359682) 97 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 98 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 99 Head, anterior view 100 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank46
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Both sexes: Frontal depression deep, carinae present above dorsal separator; submedian carina weak or absent medially. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by rugae. Occipital carina complete, medially sinuate. Metascutellum concave dorsally, weakly emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Coxa darker than rest of leg. Postmarginal vein absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4, A5 broader than long. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T5 or to metasomal apex. T4, T5 without metasomal flanges. T6 abruptly narrower than T5. Main body of T6 raised above apical rim, medially sloping down to it. T6 with broadly rounded apical lobes. S6 not exposed to dorsal view. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio exiguitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exiguitatis">Oxyscelio exiguitatis</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="76" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Oxyscelio nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
, but with much shorter fore wings and a deeper frontal depression.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“smallness.”">&quot;smallness.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307077]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="76" pageNumber="77" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="76" pageNumber="77">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, 7km S Batavia Downs, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-12.716666">12°43'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="142.7">142°42'E</geoCoordinate>
, 23.
<normalizedToken originalValue="XI–">XI-</normalizedToken>
11.XII.1992, malaise trap, P. Zborowski &amp; W. Dressler, OSUC 359682 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 14 females, ANIC DB 32-020148, OSUC 359684, OSUC 359685, OSUC 359686, OSUC 359687, OSUC 359688, OSUC 359689, OSUC 359690, OSUC 359691, OSUC 359692, OSUC 359693, OSUC 359694, OSUC 359695 (ANIC); OSUC 359683 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>