<document ID-ISBN="978-84-16728-04-6" approvalRequired="12443" approvalRequired_for_illustrations="47" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="11727" approvalRequired_for_treatments="666" checkinTime="1656696812616" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="Don E. Wilson, Russell A. Mittermeier &amp; Thomas E. Lacher, Jr" docDate="2017" docId="1E30E275344DFFFCE16E2E0C7F088078" docLanguage="en" docName="hbmw_7_Muridae_0536.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II, Barcelona: Lynx Edicions" docTitle="Muridae" docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageNumber="707" masterDocId="E2099A0D3426FF97E1372C0977498313" masterDocTitle="Muridae" masterLastPageNumber="884" masterPageNumber="536" pageNumber="707" updateTime="1656696851240" updateUser="carolina">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Muridae</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Don E. Wilson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Russell A. Mittermeier</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Thomas E. Lacher, Jr</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2017</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:dateOther type="pubDate">2017-11-30</mods:dateOther>
<mods:publisher>Lynx Edicions</mods:publisher>
<mods:place>
<mods:placeTerm>Barcelona</mods:placeTerm>
</mods:place>
</mods:originInfo>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>536</mods:start>
<mods:end>884</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>book chapter</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISBN">978-84-16728-04-6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1E30E275344DFFFCE16E2E0C7F088078" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1E30E275344DFFFCE16E2E0C7F088078" lastPageNumber="707" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<heading pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<subSubSection box="[89,172,517,563]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="107.[88,1276,517,641]" box="[89,172,517,563]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<figureCitation box="[89,172,517,563]" captionStart="Plate 42: Muridae" captionStartId="101.[90,119,3137,3158]" captionTargetBox="[11,2719,14,3649]" captionTargetPageId="100" captionText="278. Southern Groove-toothed Shrew Mouse (Microhydromys argenteus), 279. Northern Groove-toothed Shrew Mouse (Macrohydromys richardsoni), 280. Mirza’s Western Moss Rat (Mirzamys louiseae), 281. Mirza’s Eastern Moss Rat (Mirzamys norahae), 282. New Guinea Waterside Rat (Parahydromys asper), 283. Northern Water Rat (Paraleptomys rufilatus), 284. Short-haired Water Rat (Paraleptomys wilhelmina), 285. Gressitt’s Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys gressitti), 286. Papuan Lowland Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys levipes), 287. Lorentz’s Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys lorentzii), 288. Montane Soft-furred Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys mollis), 289. Monckton’s Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys moncktoni), 290. Long-nosed Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys naso), 291. Common Lowland Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys platyops), 292. Mountain Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys rubex), 293. Stein’s Mosaic-tailed Rat (Paramelomys steini), 294. Brass’s Brush Mouse (Pogonomelomys brassi), 295. Bruyn’s Brush Mouse (Pogonomelomys bruni), 296. Shaw Mayer’s Brush Mouse (Pogonomelomys mayeri), 297. Champion’s Tree Mouse (Pogonomys championi), 298. D’Entrecasteaux Archipelago Tree Mouse (Pogonomys fergussoniensis), 299. Chestnut Tree Mouse (Pogonomys macrourus), 300. Gray-bellied Tree Mouse (Pogonomys sylvestris), 301. Loria’s Tree Mouse (Pogonomys loriae), 302. Papuan Mosaic-tailed Rat (Protochromys fellowsi), 303. Bishop Moss Mouse (Pseudohydromys berniceae), 304. Huon Small-toothed Moss Mouse (Pseudohydromys carlae), 305. Laurie’s Moss Mouse (Pseudohydromys eleanorae), 306. Shaw Mayer’s Shrew Mouse (Pseudohydromys ellerman), 307. Mottled-tailed Shrew Mouse (Pseudohydromys fuscus), 308. German’s One-toothed Moss Mouse (Pseudohydromys germani), 309. Eastern New Guinea Shrew Mouse (Pseudohydromys murinus), 310. Torricelli Mountains Shrew Mouse (Pseudohydromys mussert), 311. Western New Guinea Shrew Mouse (Pseudohydromys occidentalis), 312. Woolley’s Moss Mouse (Pseudohydromys patriciae), 313. Southern Small-toothed Moss Mouse (Pseudohydromys pumehanae), 314. White-bellied Moss Mouse (Pseudohydromys sandrae)" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">299.</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[189,636,517,563]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="107.[88,1276,517,641]" box="[189,636,517,563]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<vernacularName box="[189,636,517,563]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Chestnut Tree Mouse</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[708,1106,517,563]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="107.[88,1276,517,641]" box="[708,1106,517,563]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis box="[708,1106,517,563]" italics="true" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Pogonomys macrourus</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="107.[88,1276,517,641]" box="[89,1276,581,602]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[89,161,581,602]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">French:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[170,438,581,602]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Pogonomys a longue queue</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[456,545,581,602]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">German:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[554,894,581,602]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Kastanienbraune Greifschwanzratte</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[913,1001,581,602]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Spanish:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1010,1276,581,602]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Raton arboricola de castano</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="107.[88,1276,517,641]" box="[88,1193,620,641]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[88,335,620,641]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Other common names:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[345,561,620,641]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Chestnut Pogonomys</vernacularName>
, 
<vernacularName box="[576,818,620,641]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Prehensile-tailed Mouse</vernacularName>
, 
<vernacularName box="[832,1064,620,641]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Soft-haired Tree Mouse</vernacularName>
, 
<vernacularName box="[1074,1193,620,641]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Tree Mouse</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</heading>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="107.[697,1295,690,1114]" box="[702,1295,690,719]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[702,857,690,719]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Taxonomy.</emphasis>
Mus (Pogonomys) macrourus
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="107.[697,1295,690,1114]" box="[703,1293,725,759]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
Milne-Edwards, 1877, 
<materialsCitation pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
Amberbaki, Arfak 
<paragraph blockId="107.[697,1295,690,1114]" box="[703,1291,768,797]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Mountains, Vogelkop, Province of Papua,</paragraph>
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="107.[697,1295,690,1114]" box="[702,1255,808,837]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">West Papua (= Irian Jaya), New Guinea.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="107.[697,1295,690,1114]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Although more studies of the relation-ships within Hydromyini are needed, Po-</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="107.[697,1295,690,1114]" lastBlockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">gonomys was found in S. J. Steppan and J. J. Schenk’s 2017 analysis to form a genetic clade with Hyomys (to which it is sister taxon), Chiruromys, Macruromys, Lorentzimys, and Anisomys, although with relatively low support. P. macrourus as currently defined almost certainly represents a species complex. The Australian populations have been treated by most Australian authorities as a distinct species under the name mollipilosus, although this name is represented by a New Guinea specimen of uncertain taxonomic affinities (included in P. macrourus by some, and treated as distinct species by others). The name mollipilosus is included here under P. macrourus, although it may represent a distinct taxon. North Australian populations thus do not have an applicable name, although they are almost certainly a distinct species. There is also a possibly undescribed species in Foja Mountains. P. macrourus, as well as the whole genus,is in need of revision. Tentatively treated as monotypic.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="distribution">
<caption inLine="true" pageId="107" pageNumber="707" targetBox="[2109,2113,850,875]" targetPageId="107">
<paragraph blockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[89,266,1474,1508]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Distribution.</emphasis>
Throughout various mountainous areas of New Guinea, Yapen I, New Britain I, and extreme NE Australia (NE Queensland: Iron Range, and from Shiptons Flat to Koombooloomba).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[90,344,1592,1626]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Descriptive notes.</emphasis>
New Guinea: head-body 92-150 mm, tail 126-187 mm, ear 11-15-5 mm, hindfoot 19-1-22-5 mm; weight 28-60 g. Australia: head—body 120-165 mm, tail 160-208 mm, ear 14-16 mm, hindfoot 22-27 mm; weight 42-83 g. The Chestnut Tree Mouse is a small to mid-sized species of Pogonomys with pelage soft and dense. Dorsal pelage is reddish brown in New Guinea and grayish brown in Australia, all populations with distinctive and thin dark eye-ring; ventral pelage is pure white and sharply demarcated from dorsal pelage. Feet are pinkish, sparsely furred dorsally, broad and short. Ears are small, dark around edges, and rounded; vibrissae relatively long. Tail is long (c.130% of head—body length), prehensile, thin, naked, and gray brown in color, commonly blotched with white in at least Australian populations. Skull is short and broad. Various species of cestode and nematode (Odilia, Pogonomystrongylus, etc.), as well as some fleas, have been recorded from New Guinea populations of this species. There are three pairs of mammae, one pectoral and two inguinal. Chromosomal complement for New Guinea populations is 2n = 46, FN = 42.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[90,201,2144,2178]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Habitat.</emphasis>
Tropical moist primary and secondary forest in New Guinea and recorded in rainforests and monsoonal forests in Australia.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="food_feeding">
<paragraph blockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[90,357,2223,2257]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Food and Feeding.</emphasis>
Chestnut Tree Mice are known to feed only on fruits and leaves, being strictly herbivorous. All information regarding feeding habits of this species is from Australia. Fruits of red-leaved figs (Ficus congesta, Moraceae), Rhodomyrtus trineura (Myrtaceae), Amoora ferruginea (Meliaceae), Pandanus monticola (Pandanaceae), bananas, and wild tobacco bush (Solanum mauritianum, Solanaceae) are eaten, as well as leaves of yellow passionfruit vine (Passiflora edulis flavicarpa, Passifloraceae). Some fruits are carried elsewhere for consumption (figs, tobacco bush, Rhodomyrtus), while others, because of their size, are eaten without being taken off the plant (Pandanus and bananas). The outer surfaces of Pandanus fruits and bananas are bitten off and discarded to allow access to the inner fruit. Leaves of passionfruit vine are bitten offat the stalk and held in the forefeet when eaten, although the mouse may not completely finish them, dropping them on ground under the plant, where they will litter the floor (a useful clue for locating the animals). Chestnut Tree Mice generally forage alone, but up to three individuals have been seen eating together from a passionfruit.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="breeding">
<paragraph blockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[92,226,2774,2808]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Breeding.</emphasis>
In New Guinea, breeding generally occurs in October—January and litter size is usually 2-3. In Telefomin area a female with two nearly independent young was captured in July, while a female with a single young was captured in Arfak Mountains in October. Reproductive activity of Australian populations is less known, but a female with two embryos was captured in September in Ordon Creek and two females (not breeding) were captured in July and February in Lake Barrine and Kuranda, respectively. Males with scrotal testes were captured during June-September, indicating that they were able to breed.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="activity">
<paragraph blockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[91,326,3089,3123]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Activity patterns.</emphasis>
The Chestnut Tree Mouse is strictly nocturnal. During day it rests in burrows on the ground, and in Australia has been reported to emerge at around 21:50 h. This species is arboreal and forages in trees, rarely coming to ground. Nests are built in burrows on ground, with nest chamber packed with leaves, usually with an escape hole hidden under leaves.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="107.[89,1303,1124,3477]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[93,791,3286,3320]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Movements, Home range and Social organization.</emphasis>
Males are probably solitary, but 3-5 individuals (usually females) usually share a burrow, and up to 15 have been taken from a single burrow in New Guinea. In Australia, they move between trees and shrubs over pathways apparently used regularly, relying on their body weight to lower branches in order to bridge gaps. When disturbed, the tree mouse may hide among dense
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="107.[1364,2569,297,875]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">leaves, as observed in a Pandanus in Australia, but it may also just continue moving throughout understory. Chestnut Tree Mice use the prehensile tail as support when moving through understory, grasping on sticks and twigs by curling the tail around them in a corkscrew pattern.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="conservation">
<paragraph blockId="107.[1364,2569,297,875]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1364,1712,446,480]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Status and Conservation.</emphasis>
Classified as Least Concern on The IUCN Red List. The Chestnut Tree Mouse has a wide but scattered distribution, and is considered common but hard to see because of its arboreal nature. It is potentially found in various protected areas throughout New Guinea, and in Australia is found in the Wet Tropics World Heritage Area. It is apparently hunted for food in New Guinea. Although the Chestnut Tree Mouse is well known in Australia, there is a need for further research into the species in New Guinea, and into the taxonomy of the speciesitself, in order fully to understand its natural history and evolution, and any potential threats to it.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="107" pageNumber="707" type="bibRefCitation_list">
<paragraph blockId="107.[1364,2569,297,875]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1365,1518,771,796]" pageId="107" pageNumber="707">Bibliography.</emphasis>
Breed &amp; Aplin (1995), Dennis &amp; Menzies (1979), Dwyer (1975), Flannery (1995a, 1995b), Hastriter &amp; Easton (2013), Jackson &amp; Groves (2015), Leary, Singadan, Menzies, Wright, Aplin &amp; Helgen (2016), Musser &amp; Carleton (2005), Smales (2014), Steppan &amp; Schenk (2017).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>