<document ID-ISBN="978-84-16728-04-6" approvalRequired="12443" approvalRequired_for_illustrations="47" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="11727" approvalRequired_for_treatments="666" checkinTime="1656696812616" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="Don E. Wilson, Russell A. Mittermeier &amp; Thomas E. Lacher, Jr" docDate="2017" docId="1E30E275346BFFD9E46129F4757087B4" docLanguage="en" docName="hbmw_7_Muridae_0536.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II, Barcelona: Lynx Edicions" docTitle="Muridae" docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageNumber="678" masterDocId="E2099A0D3426FF97E1372C0977498313" masterDocTitle="Muridae" masterLastPageNumber="884" masterPageNumber="536" pageNumber="677" updateTime="1656696851240" updateUser="carolina">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Muridae</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Don E. Wilson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Russell A. Mittermeier</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Thomas E. Lacher, Jr</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2017</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:dateOther type="pubDate">2017-11-30</mods:dateOther>
<mods:publisher>Lynx Edicions</mods:publisher>
<mods:place>
<mods:placeTerm>Barcelona</mods:placeTerm>
</mods:place>
</mods:originInfo>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>536</mods:start>
<mods:end>884</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>book chapter</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISBN">978-84-16728-04-6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1E30E275346BFFD9E46129F4757087B4" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1E30E275346BFFD9E46129F4757087B4" lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="678" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<heading pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<subSubSection box="[1366,1448,1533,1583]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1365,2449,1533,1662]" box="[1366,1448,1533,1583]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<figureCitation box="[1366,1448,1533,1583]" captionStart="Plate 40: Muridae" captionStartId="75.[90,119,3225,3250]" captionTargetBox="[12,2716,14,3649]" captionTargetPageId="74" captionText="214. Mount Banahaw Shrew Rat (Rhynchomys banahao), 215. Mount Isarog Shrew Rat (Rhynchomys isarogensis), 216. Mount Data Shrew Rat (Rhynchomys soricoides), 217. Mount Tapulao Shrew Rat (Rhynchomys tapulao), 218. Kalinga Shrew Mouse (Soricomys kalinga), 219. Leonardo Shrew Mouse (Soricomys leonardocor), 220. Mountain Shrew Mouse (Soricomys montanus), 221. Sierra Madre Shrew Mouse (Soricomys musseri), 222. Sundaic Ranee Mouse (Haeromys pusillus), 223. Margaret's Ranee Mouse (Haeromys margaretlae), 224. Lowland Sulawesi Ranee Mouse (Haeromys minahassae), 225. Papuan Highland Brush Mouse (Abeomelomys sevia), 226. Uneven-toothed Rat (Anisomys imitator), 228. Shaw Mayer’s Water Rat (Baiyankamys shawmayeri), 229. White-toothed Mouse (Brassomys albidens), 230. Forbes’s Tree Mouse (Charuromys forbesi), 231. Broad-headed Tree Mouse (Chiruromys lama), 232. Lesser Tree Mouse (Chiruromys vates), 233. Tawny Brush Mouse (Coccymys kirrhos), 234. Rimmler’s Brush Mouse (Coccymys ruemmleri), 235. Central Cordillera Brush Mouse (Coccymys shawmayer), 236. Earless New Guinea Water Rat (Crossomys moncktoni), 237. Common Water Rat (Hydromys chrysogaster), 238. Husson’s Water Rat (Hydromys hussoni), 239. New Britain Water Rat (Hydromys neobritannicus), 240. Ziegler’s Water Rat (Hydromys ziegleri), 241. Western White-eared Giant Rat (Hyomys dammerman), 242. Eastern White-eared Giant Rat (Hyomys goliath), 243. Arfak Water Rat (Leptomys arfakensts), 244. Elegant Water Rat (Leptomys elegans), 245. Ernst Mayr’sWater Rat (Leptomys ernstmayri), 246. Small Water Rat (Leptomys paulus), 247. Fly River Water Rat (Leptomys signatus)" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">223.</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[1465,1981,1533,1583]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1365,2449,1533,1662]" box="[1465,1981,1533,1583]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<vernacularName box="[1465,1981,1533,1583]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Margaret's Ranee Mouse</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[2053,2449,1533,1583]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1365,2449,1533,1662]" box="[2053,2449,1533,1583]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<emphasis box="[2053,2449,1533,1583]" italics="true" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Haeromys margaretlae</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="77" pageNumber="677" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1365,2449,1533,1662]" box="[1366,2408,1601,1622]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1366,1441,1601,1622]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">French:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1450,1681,1601,1622]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Haeromys de Margaret</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1701,1792,1601,1622]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">German:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1803,2056,1601,1622]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Borneo-Zwergbaummaus</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[2076,2168,1601,1622]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Spanish:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[2178,2408,1601,1622]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Raton rani de Margaret</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1365,1612,1641,1662]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1365,2449,1533,1662]" box="[1365,1425,1641,1662]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Other</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="77.[1365,2449,1533,1662]" box="[1433,1990,1641,1662]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
common names: 
<vernacularName box="[1622,1838,1641,1662]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Margaret's Haeromys</vernacularName>
, 
<vernacularName box="[1852,1990,1641,1662]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Ranee Mouse</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</emphasis>
</subSubSection>
</heading>
<subSubSection pageId="77" pageNumber="677" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1977,2571,1714,2133]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1977,2132,1714,1739]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Taxonomy.</emphasis>
Mus margarettae Thomas, 1893, 
<materialsCitation box="[1978,2338,1753,1778]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">“Penrisen Hills, Sarawak,”</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="77.[1977,2571,1714,2133]" lastBlockId="77.[1366,2574,2139,3472]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Malaysia. This is the type species of Haeromys. In describing Mus margarettae, O. Thomas noted the mosaic of similarities to “Mus chiropus” [= Chiromyscus chiropus, a substantially larger arboreal animal] and to other, diminutive, arboreal murines of genera Chiropodomys and Vandeleuria. Subsequently, Thomas concluded that, while margarettae and some closely related species were externally similar to species of Chiropodomys, they were too different in molarcusp arrangement and warranted erection of a distinct genus. G. H. H. Tate in 1936 suggested a possible derivation of Haeromys from his cremoriventer group within “Rattus” (now Nwviventer cremoriventer). J. R. Ellerman at first agreed, but by 1949he favored a relationship with Lorentzimys of New Guinea. X. Misonne wrote in 1969 that Haeromys is “extremely difficult to classify” on cranio-dental criteria, while G. G. Musser and C. Newcomb cited cranio-dental evidence in 1983 to align Haeromys more closely to Chiropodomys than to any other genus. Karyotype of Haeromys (H. minahassae), described by Musser in 1990, conforms closely with putative ancestral arrangementfirst identified among Australo-Papuan members of tribe Hydromyini and also identifiable among Philippine members ofthis phylogenetic lineage. Unpublished cranio-dental studies by K. P. Aplin also point to likely relationship of Haeromys to the Hydromyini, and it is classified as such here, on basis of these converging lines of evidence. Molecular confirmation is required. Taxon pusillus was described as a subspecies by Thomas in 1893, but listed as a full species in 1911 when he specified the content of Haeromys. It was treated as a subspecies by Ellerman in 1941, but returned to species level by Lord Medway in 1965, an action endorsed by Musser and all subsequent authors. A specimen from East Kalimantan reported as H. margarettae by Medway in 1977 was discounted by Musser and Carleton in 1993. Monotypic.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[1368,2257,2848,2882]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677" type="distribution">
<caption box="[1368,2257,2848,2882]" inLine="true" pageId="77" pageNumber="677" targetBox="[565,569,1166,1191]" targetPageId="78">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1366,2574,2139,3472]" box="[1368,2257,2848,2882]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1368,1544,2848,2882]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Distribution.</emphasis>
Known only from two localities in N &amp; SE Borneo.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="78" lastPageNumber="678" pageId="77" pageNumber="677" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="77.[1366,2574,2139,3472]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1368,1616,2892,2921]" pageId="77" pageNumber="677">Descriptive notes.</emphasis>
Head-body 76 mm, tail 144 mm, ear 13 mm, hindfoot 19-7 mm (measurements from type description). No specific data are available for body weight. Margaret's Ranee Mouseis the second smallest native rodent on Borneo; only the Sundaic Ranee Mouse (H. pusillus) is smaller. It has abroad head with short snout and moderately large eyes. Body proportions are unexceptional, but tail is very long and slender, rather whip-like in appearance. Fur on upperparts is soft, dense, and moderately long, lacking distinct spines. Color described in 1893 by Thomas as “deep rufous chestnut, mixed on the back with the gray of the bases of the hairs, but clearing on the sides where it seems to form a rufous lateral band. Chin, chest, and belly white.” Vibrissae “numerous and prominent, black.” Ears “small, oval, practically naked.” Feet brown but with white skin and hairs on digits. Forefeet with nail on first digit, and “short and curved claws” on remaining digits. Hindfeet are moderately elongate but broad, with six “large rounded pads.” First digit moderately long, and with minute claw rather than a nail; remaining digits all with “very short and curved” claws. Tail is long and slender (190% of head-body length in holotype), and color a “sort of pale greenish gray, the same above as below.”
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="78.[160,1367,289,1191]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Basal portion of tail thinly furred but remainderfinely haired, almost naked in appearance, and with small scales, averaging c.17 rows per cm. Cranium has globular braincase, with veryshort, narrow rostrum and delicate zygomatic arches. Three molars present in each series, all very reduced but with cuspidate crown morphology. Mammae three on each side, one post-axillary and two inguinal.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="678" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="78.[160,1367,289,1191]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[162,273,487,521]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Habitat.</emphasis>
The two records are from areas that would have originally supported evergreen tropical rainforest. The lower to middle slopes of Penrisen Hills support dipterocarp hill forest, while upper slopes support lower montane rainforest.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<paragraph blockId="78.[160,1367,289,1191]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">
<subSubSection box="[162,1231,605,639]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678" type="food_feeding">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[162,424,605,639]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Food and Feeding.</emphasis>
Margaret's Ranee Mouse islikely to be a “seed predator.”
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[161,535,644,678]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678" type="breeding">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[161,296,644,678]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Breeding.</emphasis>
No information.
</subSubSection>
</paragraph>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="678" type="activity">
<paragraph blockId="78.[160,1367,289,1191]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[160,396,684,718]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Activity patterns.</emphasis>
Body form suggests a highly arboreallifestyle. Some terrestrial activity is indicated by J. Payne and coworkers’ report of a Haeromys (either this species or the Sundaic Ranee Mouse) captured in a pitfall trap in Sabah, Malaysia.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[161,1101,802,836]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="78.[160,1367,289,1191]" box="[161,1101,802,836]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[161,862,802,836]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Movements, Home range and Social organization.</emphasis>
No information.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="678" type="conservation">
<paragraph blockId="78.[160,1367,289,1191]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[162,510,846,875]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Status and Conservation.</emphasis>
Classified as Data Deficient on The IUCN Red List. Type locality is now included within Gunung Niut Penrisen Nature Reserve. In the four decades leading up to 2014, more than 30% of the original tropical rainforest cover of Borneo was lost to habitat conversion, much ofit to oil palm plantations. The range of Margaret’s Ranee Mouse is no doubt both strongly reduced and highly fragmented.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="678" type="bibRefCitation_list">
<paragraph blockId="78.[160,1367,289,1191]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[163,312,1047,1072]" pageId="78" pageNumber="678">Bibliography.</emphasis>
Chasen &amp; Kloss (1932), Corbet &amp; Hill (1992), Donnellan (1989), Ellerman (1941, 1949), Gaveau et al. (2014), Gerrie &amp; Kennerley (2016i), Medway (1965, 1977), Misonne (1969), Musser (1979, 1990), Musser &amp; Carleton (1993, 2005), Musser &amp; Newcomb (1983), Rickart &amp; Heaney (2002), Rickart &amp; Musser (1993), Tate (1936), Thomas (1893d, 1893e, 19111).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>