<document ID-ISBN="978-84-16728-04-6" approvalRequired="12443" approvalRequired_for_illustrations="47" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="11727" approvalRequired_for_treatments="666" checkinTime="1656696812616" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="Don E. Wilson, Russell A. Mittermeier &amp; Thomas E. Lacher, Jr" docDate="2017" docId="1E30E2753480FF30E1682B8674D68074" docLanguage="en" docName="hbmw_7_Muridae_0536.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II, Barcelona: Lynx Edicions" docTitle="Muridae" docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageNumber="770" masterDocId="E2099A0D3426FF97E1372C0977498313" masterDocTitle="Muridae" masterLastPageNumber="884" masterPageNumber="536" pageNumber="769" updateTime="1656696851240" updateUser="carolina">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Muridae</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Don E. Wilson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Russell A. Mittermeier</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Thomas E. Lacher, Jr</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2017</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:dateOther type="pubDate">2017-11-30</mods:dateOther>
<mods:publisher>Lynx Edicions</mods:publisher>
<mods:place>
<mods:placeTerm>Barcelona</mods:placeTerm>
</mods:place>
</mods:originInfo>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>536</mods:start>
<mods:end>884</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>book chapter</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISBN">978-84-16728-04-6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1E30E2753480FF30E1682B8674D68074" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1E30E2753480FF30E1682B8674D68074" lastPageId="167" lastPageNumber="770" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<heading pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<subSubSection box="[95,178,1935,1981]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="166.[94,1230,1935,2061]" box="[95,178,1935,1981]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<figureCitation box="[95,178,1935,1981]" captionStart="Plate 48: Muridae" captionStartId="166.[98,128,3175,3200]" captionTargetBox="[11,2727,14,3650]" captionTargetPageId="165" captionText="469. Barbary Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys barbarus), 470. Typical Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys striatus), 471. [MISSING], 473. Senegal Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys linulus), 474. Mittendorf’s Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys Ts), 475. Hoogstraal’s Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys hoogstraali), 476. Buffoon Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys macculus), 477. Griselda Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys griselda), 478. Single-striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys rosalia), 479. Rosevear’s Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys roseveart), 480. West African Rufous-nosed Rat (Oenomys ornatus), 481. Common Rufous-nosed Rat (Oenomys hypoxanthus), 482. East African Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys fallax), 483. Hopkins’s Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys hopkinst), 484. Lake Victoria Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys isseli), 485. Angolan Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys campanae), 486. Least Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys minor), 487. Target Rat (Stochomys longicaudatus), 488. Kemp's Thicket Rat (Thamnomys kempr), 489. Hatt’s Thicket Rat (Thamnomys major), 490. Schouteden’s Thicket Rat (Thamnomys schoutedeni), 491. Thomas's Thicket Rat (Thamnomys venustus), 492. Namaqua Rock Rat (Micaelamys namaquensis), 493. Grant's Rock Rat (Micaelamys granti), 494. Mesic Four-striped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys dilectus), 495. West-Central South African Four-striped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys bechuanae), 496. KwaZulu Natal Four-striped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys chakae), 497. [MISSING], 499. Loring’s Thallomys (Thallomys loringi), 500. Black-tailed Thallomys (Thallomys nigricauda), 501. Sundevall’s Thallomys (Thallomys paedulcus), 502. Shortridge’s Thallomys (Thallomys shortridgei)" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">470.</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[194,782,1935,1981]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="166.[94,1230,1935,2061]" box="[194,782,1935,1981]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<vernacularName box="[194,782,1935,1981]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Typical Striped Grass Mouse</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[854,1230,1935,1981]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="166.[94,1230,1935,2061]" box="[854,1230,1935,1981]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<emphasis box="[854,1230,1935,1981]" italics="true" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Lemniscomys striatus</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="166.[94,1230,1935,2061]" box="[95,1179,2000,2021]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[95,171,2000,2021]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">French:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[180,353,2000,2021]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Rat-rayé d'Afrique</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[375,465,2000,2021]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">German:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[476,766,2000,2021]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Eigentliche Streifengrasmaus</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[788,879,2000,2021]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Spanish:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[889,1179,2000,2021]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Raton de hierba listado tipico</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[94,1230,1935,2061]" box="[94,573,2040,2061]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[94,341,2040,2061]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Other common names:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[351,573,2040,2061]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Striated Lemniscomys</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</heading>
<subSubSection pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="166.[708,1299,2104,2532]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[708,863,2104,2138]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Taxonomy.</emphasis>
Mus striatus Linnaeus, 1758, 
<materialsCitation box="[709,815,2143,2177]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">“India.”</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[708,1299,2104,2532]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Corrected by O. Thomas in 1911 to “Sierra Leone,” West Africa.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<paragraph blockId="166.[708,1299,2104,2532]" box="[709,806,2222,2256]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Recent</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[708,1299,2104,2532]" box="[826,1062,2222,2256]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">phylogeographic</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[708,1299,2104,2532]" lastBlockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">studies suggest that L. striatus as presently constituted contains at least four lineages which may constitute cryptic species within a species complex. Some of these entities correspond roughly with geographical limits of five subspecies proposed by E. Van der Straeten and W. N. Verheyen in 1980. Further research required. Distribution. Widespread in tropical Africa in Guinea-Bissau and from Sierra Leone and Guinea E to S South Sudan and W Kenya, and S to N Angola, S DR Congo, NE Zambia, SW Tanzania, and extreme N Malawi; isolated populations occur in SW Sudan</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[96,148,2696,2730]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">and</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[158,204,2696,2730]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">SW</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[213,335,2696,2730]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Ethiopia</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">. Descriptive notes. Head—body 97139 mm, tail 96-153 mm, ear 12-21 mm, hindfoot</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[97,351,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">22-29 mm; weight</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[359,395,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">28</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[395,441,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">-67</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[449,467,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">g</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[467,530,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">. Fur</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[538,568,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">of</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[574,617,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">the</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[626,724,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Typical</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[733,833,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Striped</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[843,917,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Grass</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[926,1017,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Mouse</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[1026,1045,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">is</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[1054,1141,2774,2808]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">coarse</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">and brown above, often flecked with ocher, contrasting with white below. Single well-marked</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[97,170,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">black</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[185,333,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">mid-dorsal</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[348,424,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">stripe</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[440,548,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">extends</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[563,630,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">from</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[646,752,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">neck to</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[768,828,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">base</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[843,929,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">of tail</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[929,1002,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">, and</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" box="[1018,1082,2853,2887]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">each</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[95,1301,2539,3083]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">of fourlateral pale yellow stripes on flank is broken into spots; additional spots occur below, not arranged in lines. Ears are large, rounded, and covered with short rufous hairs. Eye-ring is rufous. Tail is long (c.125% of head-body length), dark above, pale below, sparsely haired. Forefeet have three functional digits. Females have 2+2 = 4 pairs of nipples. Chromosomal complement has 2n = 44, FN = 68-74 (West Africa).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[1364,2572,288,875]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Habitat. Variety of grasslands with good grass cover, as well as agricultural areas. Often trapped on forest edges or clearings in forest, but neverin forest itself. Food and Feeding. Typical Striped Grass Mice eat grass stems and inflorescences, fruits, leaves, and seeds. Breeding. Breeding is seasonal and linked to rainfall. Where rain occurs in all months (e.g. Uganda), there are two breeding periods annually and females can have 1-3 litters per year. Gestation lasts 23 days. Littersize is 2-8. Activity patterns. Typical Striped Grass Mice are terrestrial and crepuscular, with some nocturnal activity around midnight. Population cycles are strongly controlled by annual early-ssummerfires in grasslands. Movements, Home range and Social organization. Typical Striped Grass Mice build nests of shredded grass on ground surface in dense vegetation. Status and Conservation. Classified as Least Concern on The IUCN Red List. Bibliography. Cheeseman &amp; Delany (1979), Happold (2013a), Monadjem etal. (2015), Neal (1970, 1977), Nicolas, Mboumba et al. (2008), Thomas (1911c¢), Van der Straeten &amp; Verheyen (1980).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[1367,2574,947,2174]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">471. Heuglin’s Striped Grass Mouse Lemniscomys zebra French: Rat-rayé de Heuglin / German: Heuglin-Streifengrasmaus / Spanish: Raton de hierba listado de Heuglin Other common names: Heuglin's Lemniscomys, Zebra Grass Mouse, Zebra Lemniscomys Taxonomy. Mus zebra Heuglin, 1864, Bahr el Ghazal, South Sudan. Lemniscomys zebra was previously included within L. barbarus, but M. D. Carleton and E. Van der Straeten in 1997 demonstrated that the two species can be distinguished morphometrically. Poorly defined L. hoogstraali may be conspecific with L. zebra. Monotypic. Distribution. Widespread in arid Sahelo-Sudanian savannas from Senegal E to Eritrea, extending into much of E Africa S to S Tanzania. Descriptive notes. Head—body 96-119 mm, tail 110-133 mm, ear 13-16 mm, hindfoot 22-27 mm; weight 24-60 g. Heuglin’s Striped Grass Mouse has coarse fur yellowish brown to brown above, contrasting with white below. Single black mid-dorsal stripe extends from neck to base oftail, and there are 67 unbroken yellowish or cream stripes on each flank. Ears are large, rounded, and covered with short rufous hairs. Tail is long (c.1 10% of head— body length), dark above, pale below, sparsely haired. Forefeet have three functional digits. Females have 2+2 = 4 pairs of nipples. Chromosomal complement has 2n = 54, FN = 58. Habitat. Drier grasslands and woodland savannas with adequate cover of grass, herbs, or bushes. Food and Feeding. No information. Breeding. No information. Activity patterns. Heuglin’s Striped Grass Mice are terrestrial and crepuscular. Movements, Home range and Social organization. No information. Status and Conservation. Classified as Least Concern on The IUCN Red List. Bibliography. Carleton &amp; Van der Straeten (1997), Happold (2013a), Monadjem et al. (2015), Rosevear (1969).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="166.[1370,2575,2248,3081]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
472. Bellier’s Striped Grass Mouse Lemniscomys bellier: French: Rat-rayé de Bellier / German: BellierStreifengrasmaus / Spanish: Ratén de hierba listado de Bellier Other common names: Bellier's Lemniscomys 
<subSubSection pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="reference_group">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1982,2137,2417,2451]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Taxonomy.</emphasis>
Lemniscomys belliert Van der Straeten, 1975, 
<materialsCitation pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Ayeremou (= Lamto), Ivory Coast. Lemniscomys bellieri, previously included in L. striatus, was elevated to species rank on basis of its unbroken lower lateral stripes (broken into spots in L. striatus) combined with chromosomal and moleculargenetic differences. It is genetically close to (cytochrome-b divergence 3-3%) and shares chromosomal and morphological characters with L. macculus, and the two may be conspecific. Monotypic.</materialsCitation>
</subSubSection>
</paragraph>
<subSubSection pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="distribution">
<caption inLine="true" pageId="166" pageNumber="769" targetBox="[923,927,846,871]" targetPageId="167">
<paragraph blockId="166.[1370,2575,2248,3081]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1371,1547,2889,2923]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Distribution.</emphasis>
W of the Dahomey Gap in W Africa, from Guinea and Sierra Leone to extreme S Burkina Faso and NW Ghana.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="167" lastPageNumber="770" pageId="166" pageNumber="769" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="166.[1370,2575,2248,3081]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1372,1621,2968,3002]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">Descriptive notes.</emphasis>
Head-body 91-127 mm,tail 94-134 mm, ear 13-19 mm, hindfoot 23-27 mm; weight 26-46 g. Bellier’s Striped Grass Mouse has fur buffy brown above contrasting with pure white below, with narrow dark mid-dorsal stripe, and eight pale
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="166" pageNumber="769" startId="166.[98,128,3175,3200]" targetBox="[11,2727,14,3650]" targetPageId="165">
<paragraph blockId="166.[96,2566,3150,3483]" pageId="166" pageNumber="769">On following pages: 473. Senegal Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys linulus); 474. Mittendorf's Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys mittendorfi); 475. Hoogstraal's Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys hoogstraali), 476. Buffoon Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys macculus); 477. Griselda Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys griselda); 478. Single-striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys rosalia); 479. Rosevear’s Striped Grass Mouse (Lemniscomys roseveari); 480. West African Rufous-nosed Rat (Oenomys ornatus); 481. Common Rufous-nosed Rat (Oenomys hypoxanthus); 482. East African Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys fallax); 483. Hopkins's Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys hopkinsi); 484. Lake Victoria Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys isseli); 485. Angolan Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys campanae); 486. Least Groove-toothed Swamp Rat (Pelomys minor); 487. Target Rat (Stochomys longicaudatus); 488. Kemp's Thicket Rat (Thamnomys kempi); 489. Hatt's Thicket Rat (Thamnomys majon; 490. Schouteden's Thicket Rat (Thamnomys schoutedeni); 491. Thomas's Thicket Rat (Thamnomys venustus); 492. Namaqua Rock Rat (Micaelamys namaquensis); 493. Grant's Rock Rat (Micaelamys granti); 494. Mesic Four-striped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys dilectus); 495. West-Central South African Fourstriped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys bechuanae); 496. KwaZulu Natal Four-striped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys chakae); 497. Karoo Four-striped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys intermedius); 498. Xeric Four-striped Grass Rat (Rhabdomys pumilio), 499. Loring's Thallomys (Thallomys loringi); 500. Black-tailed Thallomys (Thallomys nigricauda); 501. Sundevall’s Thallomys (Thallomys paedulcus); 502. Shortridge’s Thallomys (Thallomys shortridgei).</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">buffy lateral stripes on each flank (some broken into spots). Tail is long (c.100% of head-body length), dark brown above and whitish below, sparsely haired and ringed with scales. Feet are buffy-colored, forefeet with threefunctional digits, first digit vestigial and fifth digit highly reduced (with nail instead of claw). Females have 2+2 = 4 pairs of nipples. Chromosomal complement has 2n = 56.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[171,1179,483,517]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" box="[171,1179,483,517]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[171,282,483,517]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">Habitat.</emphasis>
Grasslands in moist savannas, avoiding forests and forest edges.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="167" pageNumber="770" type="food_feeding">
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[171,435,523,557]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">Food and Feeding.</emphasis>
Bellier’s Striped Grass Mouse is mostly or exclusively herbivorous, feeding close to burrows.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[171,545,601,635]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770" type="breeding">
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" box="[171,545,601,635]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[171,306,601,635]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">Breeding.</emphasis>
No information.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="167" pageNumber="770" type="activity">
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[169,403,641,675]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">Activity patterns.</emphasis>
Bellier’s Striped Grass Mouseis terrestrial, and nocturnal and crepuscular, with activity peaks before sunrise, after sunset, and in middle of night.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[171,1111,720,754]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" box="[171,1111,720,754]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[171,872,720,754]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">Movements, Home range and Social organization.</emphasis>
No information.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[171,1222,759,793]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770" type="conservation">
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" box="[171,1222,759,793]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[171,521,759,793]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">Status and Conservation.</emphasis>
Classified as Least Concern on The IUCN Red List.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="167" pageNumber="770" type="bibRefCitation_list">
<paragraph blockId="167.[169,1380,286,871]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[172,324,808,833]" pageId="167" pageNumber="770">Bibliography.</emphasis>
Bernard (1969), Chéneti &amp; Sani (1989), Ducroz et al. (2001), Happold (2013a), Monadjem etal. (2015), Van der Straeten (1975), Van der Straeten &amp; Verheyen (1978a).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>