<document ID-ISBN="978-84-16728-04-6" approvalRequired="12443" approvalRequired_for_illustrations="47" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="11727" approvalRequired_for_treatments="666" checkinTime="1656696812616" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="Don E. Wilson, Russell A. Mittermeier &amp; Thomas E. Lacher, Jr" docDate="2017" docId="1E30E2753461FFDFE47929D272048746" docLanguage="en" docName="hbmw_7_Muridae_0536.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II, Barcelona: Lynx Edicions" docTitle="Muridae" docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageNumber="672" masterDocId="E2099A0D3426FF97E1372C0977498313" masterDocTitle="Muridae" masterLastPageNumber="884" masterPageNumber="536" pageNumber="671" updateTime="1656696851240" updateUser="carolina">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Muridae</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Don E. Wilson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Russell A. Mittermeier</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Thomas E. Lacher, Jr</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2017</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:dateOther type="pubDate">2017-11-30</mods:dateOther>
<mods:publisher>Lynx Edicions</mods:publisher>
<mods:place>
<mods:placeTerm>Barcelona</mods:placeTerm>
</mods:place>
</mods:originInfo>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 7 Rodents II</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>536</mods:start>
<mods:end>884</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>book chapter</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISBN">978-84-16728-04-6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1E30E2753461FFDFE47929D272048746" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1E30E2753461FFDFE47929D272048746" lastPageId="72" lastPageNumber="672" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<heading pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<subSubSection box="[1358,1440,1499,1545]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="71.[1357,2414,1499,1624]" box="[1358,1440,1499,1545]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<figureCitation box="[1358,1440,1499,1545]" captionStart="Plate 39: Muridae" captionStartId="61.[92,122,3192,3213]" captionTargetBox="[11,2715,13,3648]" captionTargetPageId="60" captionText="182. Indomalayan Pencil-tailed Tree Mouse (Charopodomys gliroudes), 183. Palawan Pencil-tailed Tree Mouse (Charopodomys calamianensis), 184. Koopman' ’ s Pencil-tailed Tree Mouse (Charopodomys karlkoopmani), 185. Greater Pencil-tailed Tree Mouse (Chiropodomys major), 186. Gray-bellied Pencil-tailed Tree Mouse (Charopodomys muroides), 187. Lesser Pencil-tailed Tree Mouse (Chuwropodomys pusillus), 188. Luzon Cordillera Forest Mouse (Apomys abrae), 189. Aurora Forest Mouse (Apomys aurorae), 190. Banahaw Forest Mouse (Apomys banahao), 191. Brown's Forest Mouse (Apomys brownorum), 192. Camiguin Forest Mouse (Apomys camiguinensis), 193. Northern Luzon Forest Mouse (Apomys datae), 194. Large Mindoro Forest Mouse (Apomys gracilirostris), 195. Mindanao Mossy Forest Mouse (Apomys hylocoetes), 196. Mindanao Montane Forest Mouse (Apomys insignis), 197. Mount Irid Forest Mouse (Apomys iridensis), 198. Mindanao Lowland Forest Mouse (Apomys lttoralis), 199. Lubang Forest Mouse (Apomys lubangensis), 200. Large Forest Mouse (Apomys magnus), 201. Small Luzon Forest Mouse (Apomys microdon), 202. Mount Mingan Forest Mouse (Apomys minganensis), 203. Least Philippine Forest Mouse (Apomys musculus), 204. Long-nosed Luzon Forest Mouse (Apomys sacobianus), 205. Sierra Madre Forest Mouse (Apomys sierrae), 206. Zambales Forest Mouse (Apomys zambalensis), 207. Isarog Shrew Mouse (Archboldomys luzonensis), 208. Large Cordillera Shrew Mouse (Archboldomys maximus), 209. Isarog Striped Shrew Rat (Chrotomys gonzalesi), 210. Lowland Striped Shrew Rat (Chrotomys mindorensis), 211. Sibuyan Striped Shrew Rat (Chrotomys sibuyanensis), 212. Blazed Luzon Striped Shrew Rat (Chrotomys silaceus), 213. Montane Striped Shrew Rat (Chrotomys whiteheadi)" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">209.</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[1458,1974,1499,1545]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="71.[1357,2414,1499,1624]" box="[1458,1974,1499,1545]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<vernacularName box="[1458,1974,1499,1545]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Isarog Striped Shrew Rat</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[2047,2396,1499,1545]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="71.[1357,2414,1499,1624]" box="[2047,2396,1499,1545]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<emphasis box="[2047,2396,1499,1545]" italics="true" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Chrotomys gonzalesi</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="vernacular_names">
<paragraph blockId="71.[1357,2414,1499,1624]" box="[1357,2414,1563,1584]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1357,1433,1563,1584]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">French:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1442,1661,1563,1584]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Chrotomys de |'lsarog</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1682,1773,1563,1584]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">German:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1783,1973,1563,1584]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Isarog-Streifenratte</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1994,2085,1563,1584]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Spanish:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[2095,2414,1563,1584]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Rata musarana listada de Isarog</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="71.[1357,2414,1499,1624]" box="[1357,2251,1603,1624]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1357,1604,1603,1624]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Other common names:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1614,1791,1603,1624]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">sarog Chrotomys</vernacularName>
, 
<vernacularName box="[1806,1985,1603,1624]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Isarog Striped Rat</vernacularName>
, 
<vernacularName box="[1999,2251,1603,1624]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Mount Isarog Striped Rat</vernacularName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</heading>
<subSubSection pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="reference_group">
<subSubSection pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="71.[1969,2562,1672,2096]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1969,2124,1672,1701]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Taxonomy.</emphasis>
Chrotomys gonzales Rickart &amp; Heaney, 1991, 
<materialsCitation pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
“Western slope of Mount Isarog, 4 km N, 21 km E Naga, Camarines Sur Province, Luzon Island, Philippines
<paragraph blockId="71.[1969,2562,1672,2096]" lastBlockId="71.[1358,2566,2102,3473]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">, 1350 m elevation, 13°40’N, 123°22°E.” Chrotomys and Rhynchomys of the Philippines were typically allied in the past with the Australo-Papuan water rats (Hydromys etc.), mainly on account of dental similarities. Their closest phylogenetic affinities, as revealed by molecular studies, are with other, recently discovered Philippine shrew rats and mice of genera Archboldomys and Soricomys, and with the less specialized Philippine murines of genus Apomys. C. gonzales appears to be most closely related to C. whiteheadi and C. mindorensis. It is geographically isolated from other Chrotomys. Monotypic.</paragraph>
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="distribution">
<caption inLine="true" pageId="71" pageNumber="671" targetBox="[1353,1357,1084,1109]" targetPageId="72">
<paragraph blockId="71.[1358,2566,2102,3473]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1358,1533,2260,2294]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Distribution.</emphasis>
Slopes of Mt Isarog, SE Luzon I, Philippines; recently collected specimen from Saddle Peak, S Sierra Madre, and a photographic record from Mt Malinao, SE Luzon, suggest possibility of two addtional populations.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="72" lastPageNumber="672" pageId="71" pageNumber="671" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="71.[1358,2566,2102,3473]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1358,1601,2382,2411]" pageId="71" pageNumber="671">Descriptive notes.</emphasis>
Head-body 160-190 mm, tail 83-105 mm, ear 20-23 mm, hindfoot 34-39 mm; weight 70-190 g. According to L.. R. Heaney and coworkers, adult males are probably larger, on average, than females. Chrotomys species are stout-bodied, semi-fossorial murines with short, strong limbs, and thick tail considerably shorter than head-body length; relatively small eyes; rounded and relatively short ears; forefeet proportionally large and with strong digits and heavy, nearly straight claws on second to fourth digits; hindfeet long and narrow with small plantar pads and claws on all digits; cranium robust, with flaskshaped outline, forward-projecting upper incisors that are probably used for digging, short nasal bones that terminate well behind level of incisors, and molars small, with occlusal pattern consisting of shallow “basins.” The Isarog Striped Shrew Rat is one of the larger members of genus and has fur on upperparts soft, dense, and fluffy, hair length 17-18 mm on middle of back; mid-dorsalstripe pale yellowish buff (individual hairs blackish brown, tipped with buff), narrow, typically running from forehead to base of tail but sometimes confined to head and upper back; lateral zone is blackish brown, merging into yellowish buff on flanks, and underparts are dark gray withfaint grayish-buff wash; transitions between lateral zone, flank, and underparts all gradual; white blaze sometimes present on chest or upper abdomen; top of head is blackish to snout,lipssilvery gray and merging with yellowish buff on cheeks and side of head; no eye-ring; vibrissae blackish gray, reaching just past ears; ears pale gray and sparsely furred. Feet have upper surface dark gray and well furred, except for digits that are unpigmented and nearly naked, palmar surface unpigmented; plantar surface of hindfeet pigmented pale gray to base of digits, usually with five pads,less often with six (addition ofvery small inner posterior pad). Tail is relatively short (55-60% of head-body length), skin pale gray above and nearly white below, sometimes with short all-white tip, scales small, in 16-18 rows per cm, each scale with three short, dark hairs. Cranium has relatively broad, low braincase, relatively narrow rostrum, and three molars in each series, the last strongly reduced. Females have two pairs of mammae, both inguinal. Chromosomal complement has 2n = 44 and FN = 52, and includes two pairs of small metacentric, one pair of large submetacentric, one pair
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">of large subacrocentric, and 18 pairs of acrocentric chromosomes, the last grading from large to small. The X and Y chromosomes cannot be distinguished from the autosomes and must be among the acrocentric series. This karyotype is shared with theLowland Striped Shrew Rat (C. mindorensis) and the Blazed Luzon Striped Shrew Rat (C. silaceus).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="72" pageNumber="672" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[175,286,445,479]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">Habitat.</emphasis>
Evergreen tropical forest, including montane and mossy forest types distinguished by ecologists in Philippines. Recorded elevational range of 1350-1750 m.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="72" pageNumber="672" type="food_feeding">
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[175,445,528,557]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">Food and Feeding.</emphasis>
The Isarog Striped Shrew Rat is reported as foraging for earthworms and other soil invertebrates by digging in leaf litter and humus. Individuals consumed earthworms when kept briefly in captivity. Large forefeet and heavy claws are consistent with foraging mode that involves frequent digging in humus and soil.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[175,1092,681,715]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672" type="breeding">
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" box="[175,1092,681,715]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[175,309,681,715]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">Breeding.</emphasis>
Little is known, but one adult female had two embryos.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="72" pageNumber="672" type="activity">
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[173,408,721,755]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">Activity patterns.</emphasis>
Heaney and coworkers reported that the Isarog Striped Shrew Rat it is active primarily during day but also at night.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="72" pageNumber="672" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[175,896,803,832]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">Movements, Home range and Social organization.</emphasis>
Heaney and coworkers reported that Isarog Striped Shrew Rats kept briefly in captivity were docile.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="72" pageNumber="672" type="conservation">
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[175,527,878,912]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">Status and Conservation.</emphasis>
Classified as Near Threatened on The IUCN Red List. At the time of its discovery, in 1988, primary forest was present on Mount Isarog down to ¢.900 m elevation; extensive trapping effort at each of 475 m, 900 m, and 1125 m failed to yield captures ofthe Isarog Striped Shrew Rat. At higher elevations it was not common, with only eight captures out of 4900 trap-nights at or above 1350 m.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[175,1357,1084,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672" type="bibRefCitation_list">
<paragraph blockId="72.[173,1380,287,1109]" box="[175,1357,1084,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[175,327,1084,1109]" pageId="72" pageNumber="672">Bibliography.</emphasis>
Balete, Heaney, Alviola &amp; Rickart (2013), Balete, Rickart et al. (2012), Rickart &amp; Heaney (1991).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>