<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bcdbe5f4-2f0e-4240-8727-64b6c91db94a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886272" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-591-1" ID-ZBK="DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D6EA94C8-BED2-4A7F-8019-7F9A70BA2996" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-591-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 591" ModsDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" checkinTime="1463833188709" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Monckton, Spencer K." docDate="2016" docId="560D68A2C21E6CD7E09A2E5FBC1C64A2" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 591: 1-144" docOrigin="ZooKeys 591" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" docTitle="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) guanicoe Monckton, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="D6EA94C8-BED2-4A7F-8019-7F9A70BA2996" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="61" masterDocId="FFFED84DD544452EFFC446356171FFFD" masterDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" masterLastPageNumber="144" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" updateTime="1643603351127" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Monckton, Spencer K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>591</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>144</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-591-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886272" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D6EA94C8-BED2-4A7F-8019-7F9A70BA2996" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/560D68A2C21E6CD7E09A2E5FBC1C64A2" lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<subSubSection pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Colletidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/D6EA94C8-BED2-4A7F-8019-7F9A70BA2996" authority="Monckton" class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) guanicoe" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guanicoe" subGenus="Heteroediscelis">Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) guanicoe Monckton</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="56" pageNumber="57">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 6A; 7B; 21A; 38
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–J">A-J</normalizedToken>
; 49
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
Males are diagnosable by the combination of malar space 1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2×">-2x</normalizedToken>
as long as the clypeal lateral, and apical surface of S1 process with a longitudinal median ridge. Males share many characters with 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola vicugna" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vicugna">Chilicola vicugna</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola mavida" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mavida">Chilicola mavida</taxonomicName>
, but are differentiable by the longer face and weakly toothed posterior carina on the metatibia. Females are diagnosable by the combination of malar space 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.7×">-1.7x</normalizedToken>
as long as the clypeal lateral, and dorsal surface of the protibia yellow along its entire length.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="59" lastPageNumber="60" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Male (Holotype). Length 5.5mm, forewing length 3.3mm, head width 1.1mm, thorax width 1.2mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.14mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Colouration: Black-brown, following parts yellow: labrum; clypeus except narrowly dark brown along epistomal suture and apex yellow along entire width; lower paraocular area extending more than 1OD above transverse epistomal suture, nearly reaching lower tangent of antennal socket; apicoventral surface of scape; apex of profemur broadly on anterior surface, narrowly on posterior surface; dorsal surface of protibia, including anterior surface in dorsal half, with ventral half translucent yellow; probasitarsus; apicodorsal rim of mesofemur, wider anteriorly; wide basal and apical rings on mesotibia, as well as apical half of anterior surface; mesobasitarsus, suffused with brown distad; apicoventral rim of metacoxa; wide apical ring on metafemur; metatibia except black posterior carina, medial dark patch on posterior surface, dark medial quadrangle on anterior surface covering approximately half of total length; basal half of metabasitarsus and ventrally in apical half; anterior spot on tegula; apex of T7. Following parts yellow-brown: apicoventral surface of pedicel; ventral surface of F1, narrowing basally; ventral surface of antenna from F2 to terminal flagellomere, suffused with darker brown; protrochanter apical rim posteriorly; apical half of prodistitarsus; apicoventral rim of mesocoxa; apical half of mesodistitarsus; apicoventral rim of metatrochanter. Metasoma black, T1-T6 marginal zones amber to translucent yellow at margins.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Pubescence: White, hairs generally short (0.5OD) and sparse, not especially plumose; on lower paraocular area and around antennal base moderately long and moderately dense (1OD); genal beard long and dense (0.5-2OD) longest at midlength; mesoscutal hairs moderately long and sparse, denser toward lateral margin (0.5-1OD); discs of scutellum and metanotum mostly bare, few short hairs (0.5OD), longer and denser toward lateral and posterior margins of scutellum (1-1.5OD) longest posteromedially, and toward lateral margin of metanotum (≤2OD); propodeal hairs moderately long and dense dorsolaterally (0.5-1.5OD); T1-T3 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD); S2 hairs long and dense (1.5OD basolaterad, 0.5OD distilaterad, shorter mesad).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Surface sculpture: Microsculpture imbricate, integument generally dull; punctures generally small and deep. Clypeus and lower paraocular area moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) except clypeus sparsely punctate medially (i≥2d); supraclypeal area irregularly punctate (i=1-3d) densely punctate toward lateral margin (i≤d); frontal area very densely punctate (i≤0.5d); ocellocular space densely punctate adjacent to compound eye (i≤d) becoming impunctate adjacent to lateral ocellus; vertexal area densely punctate (i≤d); scape shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); genal area microstriate and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); hypostomal area rough, weakly imbricate and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); pronotum moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d), lateral surface coarsely imbricate; mesoscutum densely punctate (i=0.5-1d) punctures crowded around median (i≤d); scutellum moderately densely punctate (i=0.5-2d) punctures crowded around median (i≤d); mesepisternum irregularly punctate, moderately dense to sparse below scrobe (i=1-2d), sparser anterior of episternal groove (i=1-3d), impunctate just dorsad of scrobe, otherwise moderately dense on hypoepimeral area (i≤2d); metanotum moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) punctures crowded around median and anteriorly (i≤d); metepisternum densely punctate (i≤d); metapostnotum rugose, fewer transverse lineations and more weakly microsculptured posteriorly; propodeum rugulose posteriorly, moderately densely punctate throughout (i=1-2d); T1-T5 coarsely imbricate and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d on T1-T4; i=1-3d on T5); T2-T5 basal depressed area more coarsely microsculptured but punctures distinct; T6 moderately densely punctate (i=1-3d) and coarsely imbricate posteriorly; T7 moderately densely punctate (i=1-3d); marginal zones of terga weakly imbricate and shiny, minutely punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="58" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
Structure: Labrum ~2.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (22:9); malar space ~1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as clypeal lateral (11:8); LOT just above anterior tentorial pits; clypeus ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width in frontal view (34:30) extending for more than half of its length beyond LOT; median longitudinal groove on clypeus weakly present in dorsal half, absent ventrad; subantennal sutures ~1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as the shortest distance between them (16:11.5); IAD 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
AOD (12:6); scape 2.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (24:10); pedicel shorter than wide (7.5:8.5); F1 slightly shorter than wide (8.5:9); F2 ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F1 and shorter than F3 (F2:F3 - 12.5:14); UOD ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 48:52:33); frontal line carinate between antennal bases for a length less than 0.5OD, flat just below median ocellus for less than 1OD, otherwise 
<pageBreakToken pageId="57" pageNumber="58" start="start">undefined</pageBreakToken>
; MOC longer than width of head (88:83); OOC ~0.67
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (12:18); genal area ~0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as compound eye in lateral view (18:29); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 60:21:9:14; probasitarsus 
<pageBreakToken pageId="58" pageNumber="59" start="start">~</pageBreakToken>
3.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (25:6.5); length of prodistitarsus subequal to that of preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V - 6:5:4:14); metafemur almost twice as long as maximum depth (59:30); summit of metatibial ventral convexity at approximately two-thirds tibial length and rounded; metatibia ~2.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (53:25); in apical view apical lamina of metatibia short and thick, length 0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
OD (7:10); ventral metatibial carina bowed ventrad and absent basally, originating at midpoint of posterior carina, the latter sharply inflected near base and somewhat concave apicad of inflection; metabasitarsus ~4.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (38:9); S1 process apical surface with a longitudinal median ridge, in lateral view anterior and posterior margins convergent apically and median ridge projecting posteriorly from apex. S7 apodemal arm sclerotized margin recurved mesad, dividing membranous portion of arm; ventral lobe narrow, almost linear; dorsal lobe roughly triangular, wide at base and narrow apically, with row of setae long basally and shorter apically; apex of disc disinctly emarginate. S8 lateral process ~0.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, anteromedial sclerotized margin wide and weakly convex. Gonobase apicoventral truncate process biconvex and distinctly notched by ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of one convexity.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="58" pageNumber="59">Female (Allotype). Length 5.0mm, forewing length 3.1mm, head width 1.0mm, thorax width 1.1mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.12mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="58" pageNumber="59">Colouration: Black to black-brown except as follows: labrum pale to translucent yellow along basal margin; mandible with yellow basal spot and pale to translucent yellow except apex translucent brown. Following parts yellow-brown: apicoventral surface of pedicel and F1; ventral surface of antenna from F2 to terminal flagellomere, narrowing basally on F2; mesobasitarsus ventrally; apical half of mesodistitarsus; wide apical ring on metatibia; posterior surface of metabasitarsus. Following parts yellow: dorsal surface and narrow apical ring on protibia; anterior surface of probasitarsus and second to fourth tarsomeres; apical half of prodistitarsus; wide basal and narrow apical ring on mesotibia; narrow apical ring on metafemur; wide basal ring on metatibia; anterior spot on tegula. Apical one-third of metadistitarsus brown. Metasoma brown, T1-T5 marginal zones amber to translucent yellow at margins.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="58" pageNumber="59">Pubescence: As in male except as follows: clypeal hairs short and sparse (0.5OD); genal beard sparse (0.5-2OD); discs of mesoscutum, scutellum, and metanotum with sparse short hairs (≤0.5OD), longer and denser toward lateral margin as follows: mesoscutum (0.5-1.0OD), scutellum (1-1.5OD) also on posterior margin, longest posteromedially, metanotum (≤2OD); propodeal hairs moderately long and dense dorsolaterally (0.5-1.5OD); scopae on metafemur and metatibia (1-1.5OD); T1-T3 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD); S1 hairs long and moderately dense (≤2OD); S2 scopal hairs (1-2.5OD).</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="59" lastPageNumber="60" pageId="58" pageNumber="59">
Surface sculpture: As in male except as follows: clypeus moderately densely punctate throughout (i=1-2d); supraclypeal area irregularly punctate (i=1-2d) densely punctate toward lateral margin (i≤d); frontal area densely punctate (i≤d); ocellocular space moderately densely punctate adjacent to compound eye (i=1-2d) becoming impunctate adjacent to lateral ocellus; vertexal and genal areas moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); hypostomal area weakly imbricate to glossy apically and moderately densely punctate (i=1- 
<pageBreakToken pageId="59" pageNumber="60" start="start">3</pageBreakToken>
d); mesoscutum and scutellum densely punctate (i=0.5-1d); metepisternum irregularly punctate, sparse below scrobe (i=1-3d), sparser anterior of episternal groove (i≥3d), impunctate just dorsad of scrobe, otherwise irregularly spaced on hypoepimeral area (i≤2d); metanotum moderately densely punctate (i=0.5-2d); metapostnotum rugose to longitudinally striate posteriorly; propodeum coarsely imbricate, moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); T1-T5 moderately puncticulate; T6 moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="60">
Structure: Labrum ~2.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (23.5:9.5); malar space ~1.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as clypeal lateral (9.5:7.5); LOT just above anterior tentorial pits; clypeus ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width in frontal view (32:28) extending for more than half of its length beyond LOT; median longitudinal groove weak on clypeus; subantennal sutures ~1.4 longer than shortest distance between them (15:11); IAD ~1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
AOD (11.5:8); scape ~3.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (23:7); pedicel longer than wide (8:7); F1 as long as wide (6.5:6.5); F2 ~0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F1 (4.5) and 0.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F3 (6); UOD ~1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 45:48.5:34.5); frontal line carinate in lower third, flat just below median ocellus for a length of ~1OD, otherwise roughly defined; MOC ~1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as width of head (86:73); OOC ~0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (11:19); genal area ~0.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as eye in lateral view (17:23); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 57:20:11:14; probasitarsus ~3.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (24:7); length of prodistitarsus ~0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
that of preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V - 6:5:4.5:13); metafemur 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (45:15); metatibia ~4.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (58:13); metabasitarsus ~4.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (38:9).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="59" pageNumber="60">
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="60">
Figure 38. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola guanicoe" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="59" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guanicoe">Chilicola guanicoe</taxonomicName>
: A male habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm B male head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm C female habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm D female head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm E male metatibia, posterior view†, scale bar 0.25 mm F male S1 process, lateral view, scale bar 0.25 mm G male S1 process, apical view†, scale bar 0.25 mm H male S7 (C.gnco.007), scale bar 0.25 mm I male S8 (C.gnco.007), scale bar 0.25 mm J male genital capsule (C.gnco.007), scale bar 0.25 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="59" pageNumber="60" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="60">Type material</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="59" pageNumber="60">
(9 males &amp; 26 females): Holotype (male): Region III, C-453 km 22, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-28.1816">S 28.1816°</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-69.8261">W 69.8261°</geoCoordinate>
, 1625m, 6.xi.2013, fl. yellow pan trap, S. Monckton, CCDB-19989 B08 // PCYU 0021682 (PCYU); Allotype (female): Region III, C-35 km 51.5, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-27.8237">S 27.8237°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.1227">W 70.1227°</geoCoordinate>
, 875m, 29.ix.2013, S. Monckton, CCDB-19989 A12 // PCYU 0021674 (PCYU); Paratypes: Region III: one male, Las Juntas, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-28.003">S 28.003°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-69.976">W 69.976°</geoCoordinate>
, 1160m, 5.x.1982, C. Tobar (PUCV); one female, same locality and date, R. Aldunate (PUCV); one male and three females, Rd to Pastos Largos, km 4, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-28.1643">S 28.1643°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-69.7913">W 69.7913°</geoCoordinate>
, 2127m, 11.xi.2013, S. Monckton &amp; J. Postlethwaite (PCYU); one male and one female, same data (AMNH); one female, same data (BBSL); one female, same data (CTMI); one female, Rd to Pastos Largos, km 0.5, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-28.1802">S 28.1802°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-69.8047">W 69.8047°</geoCoordinate>
, 1863m, 6.xi.2013, S. Monckton (PCYU); one female, same locality, 6.xi-11.xii.2013, J. Postlethwaite &amp; S. Monckton, pan trap (PCYU); four females, Fundo La Semilla, 125 km SE 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Copiapó">Copiapo</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-28.2507">S 28.2507°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-69.741">W 69.741°</geoCoordinate>
, 2358m, 17.x.2004, F.D. Parker, M.E. Irwin, pan traps, CHL-14509-54 // FDP52511, CHL-14509-55 // FDP52599, CHL-14509-56 // FDP52403, CHL-14509-03 // FDP4749 // USDA Native Bee Survey BBSL699121 (BBSL); two females, E of El Maray, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-27.63363">S27.63363°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-70.00784">W70.007844°</geoCoordinate>
, 1316m, 3.xi.2015- 4.ii.2016, L. Packer, pan traps (PCYU); one male and four females, Cuesta 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Castaño">Castano</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-27.69314">S27.69314°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-69.75387">W69.75387°</geoCoordinate>
, 2975m, 3.xi.2015- 4.ii.2016, L. Packer, pan traps (PCYU); one male and three females, Cuesta 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Castaño">Castano</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-27.68156">S27.68156°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-69.75493">W69.75493°</geoCoordinate>
, 2672m, 3.xi.2015- 4.ii.2016, L. Packer, pan traps (PCYU); one female, Finca las Herrera, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-27.66756">S27.66756°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-69.79012">W69.79012°</geoCoordinate>
, 2315m, 3.xi.2015- 4.ii.2016, L. Packer, pan trap (PCYU); one male and one female, E of Potrerillos, C-177, km 24, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-26.4585">S 26.4585°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-69.3272">W 69.3272°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="60" pageNumber="61" start="start">2839</pageBreakToken>
m, 28.ix-16.xi.2013, J. Postlethwaite, pan traps (PCYU); one male, same locality, 16.xi.2013, J. Postlethwaite, blue pan, CCDB-22789 F02 (PCYU); one male, Hwy C-269, km 0.5, E of Potrerillos, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-26.4763">S 26.4763°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-69.3214">W 69.3214°</geoCoordinate>
, 3000m, 28.
<normalizedToken originalValue="iii–">iii-</normalizedToken>
24.iv.2013, J. Postlethwaite &amp; S. Monckton, yellow cup (PCYU); Region IV: one female, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Limarí">Limari</normalizedToken>
Prov., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Chañar">Chanar</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-30.2804">S 30.2804°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.6402">W 70.6402°</geoCoordinate>
, 1564m, 4.ix.2004, L. Packer (PCYU).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="60" pageNumber="61" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Some females have a yellow-brown or yellow spot on the lower paraocular area below the anterior tentorial pit.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="60" pageNumber="61" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Upper Intermediate Desert and northern Central Andean Cordillera, from Fundo La Semilla west to Last Juntas and north to E of Potrerillos (Region III); 875-3000m a.s.l.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="60" pageNumber="61" type="ecology">
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Recorded September to December and March to April.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="60" pageNumber="61" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">
This species is named after the guanaco - 
<taxonomicName class="Mammalia" family="Camelidae" genus="Lama" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lama guanicoe" order="Artiodactyla" pageId="60" pageNumber="61" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="guanicoe">Lama guanicoe</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken originalValue="Müller">Mueller</normalizedToken>
, 1776) - a camellid native to South America and found throughout Chile. The specific epithet is identical to that of the guanaco and is treated as a noun in apposition.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>