<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.378.6695" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8cf312b6-d145-4039-b72e-eafbc4c9aa17" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152050835" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-378-1" ID-ZBK="55F1E62259B24761B58C445498320C87" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B6610CBE-C007-4B2A-A2B6-3EE5ADF4BDD6" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-378-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 378" ModsDocTitle="A new subspecies of Nitokra affinis Gurney, 1927 (Copepoda, Harpacticoida) from the Caribbean coast of Colombia" checkinTime="1451246340710" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Fuentes-Reines, Juan M. &amp; Suarez-Morales, Eduardo" docDate="2014" docId="A90462ACEF5B45F804E025D981F7E0B5" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 378: 1-15" docOrigin="ZooKeys 378" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.378.6695" docTitle="Nitokra affinis subsp. colombiensis Fuentes-Reines &amp; Suarez-Morales, 2014, ssp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="B6610CBE-C007-4B2A-A2B6-3EE5ADF4BDD6" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="8" masterDocId="FF8A592AFF85FFC43456FFA4FFAFFFCE" masterDocTitle="A new subspecies of Nitokra affinis Gurney, 1927 (Copepoda, Harpacticoida) from the Caribbean coast of Colombia" masterLastPageNumber="15" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" updateTime="1643523014400" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new subspecies of Nitokra affinis Gurney, 1927 (Copepoda, Harpacticoida) from the Caribbean coast of Colombia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fuentes-Reines, Juan M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Suarez-Morales, Eduardo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>378</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>15</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.378.6695</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.378.6695</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-378-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">55F1E62259B24761B58C445498320C87</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">55F1E62259B24761B58C445498320C87</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152050835" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B6610CBE-C007-4B2A-A2B6-3EE5ADF4BDD6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A90462ACEF5B45F804E025D981F7E0B5" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="8" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/B6610CBE-C007-4B2A-A2B6-3EE5ADF4BDD6" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ameiridae" genus="Nitokra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nitokra affinis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="affinis" subSpecies="colombiensis">Nitokra affinis colombiensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="1" pageNumber="2">ssp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
One female holotype (UARC133M) and one male allotype (UARC134M), ethanol-preserved. Paratypes: one female (UARC142M-147M) and one male (UARC136M-141M), plus two females and two males (UARC135M). Additional material: Six adult females, four adult males in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="authors’">authors'</normalizedToken>
(JF-R) personal collection. Two adult females, two adult males from same locality and date (ECO-CHZ-09088).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Laguna 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Navío">Navio</normalizedToken>
Quebrado, La Guajira, Colombia (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="11.416667">11°25'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-73.083336">73°5'W</geoCoordinate>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="8" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="female">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Female.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="3" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Habitus in lateral view as in Figure 1A. Body subcylindrical, tapering posteriorly, total body length measured from tip of rostrum to posterior margin of caudal rami ranging from 588 to 714 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(average 660 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="3" start="start">n</pageBreakToken>
= 6; holotype: 700 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
). Rostrum subtriangular with 2 sensilla and apical rostral projection which is about half the length of rostrum (Fig. 3H). Genital double-somite distinct dorsally and laterally, with partial ventral suture (Fig. 2A, B). Anterior ventral surface of genital somite with incomplete rows of spinules on medial outer surface, distal row of spinules and pair of sensilla. Succeeding urosomite with dorsal incomplete row of spinules on medial surface and distal row of spinules covering lateral margin and only part of ventral margin (Fig. 2A, B); same somite with ventral curved row of minute spinules on central surface, incomplete row on medial outer margin and 2 sensilla on posterior margin. Preanal somite with similar ornamentation pattern except for spinules encircling posterior margin of somite, absence of curved row on ventral surface and additional row of minute spinules. Anal somite with ventral and dorsal rows of spinules along posterior margin bordering insertion of caudal rami; anal operculum semicircular, ornamented with 14-20 large spinules, flanked by 2 sensilla and rows of minute spinules (Figs 1C, 2B). Caudal ramus short, subquadrate, with rounded margins, armed with 6 setae, seta I small, seta II as long as seta I, seta III on distal outer position, about 1.5 times as long as setae I and II. Setae IV and V thick, long, the former being longest; seta VI slightly longer than seta III. Dorsal seta VII uniarticulate at base. Ramus ornamented with spinules at insertion of setae (Figs 1F, 2A, B).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ameiridae" genus="Nitokra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nitokra affinis subsp. colombiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="affinis" subSpecies="colombiensis">Nitokra affinis colombiensis</taxonomicName>
ssp. n., from northern Colombia. A adult female, habitus, lateral view B adult male, habitus, lateral view C female, anal somite showing ornamentation of anal operculum D male, urosome, ventral view E male, third urosomite, ventral view F male, caudal rami, ventral view. Scale bars: A, B = 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, C, E, F = 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, D = 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ameiridae" genus="Nitokra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nitokra affinis subsp. colombiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="affinis" subSpecies="colombiensis">Nitokra affinis colombiensis</taxonomicName>
ssp. n., from northern Colombia. A female, urosome, ventral view showing genital field and P6 B same, dorsal view, showing genital field and sixth leg plate, arrowed C male, urosome, lateral view showing P5 and P6 plate D same, ventral view E male, detail of ornamentation of anal operculum. Scale bars: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
= 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, E = 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">Antennule</pageBreakToken>
. 8-segmented, second segment about 1.5 longer than first and third segments, aesthetasc on fourth segment reaching well beyond distal end of terminal segment (Fig. 3A). Second segment longest, about 1.5 times as long as third segment and 2.1 times longer than preceding first segment. Fourth segment about as long as third segment. Armature as follows: 1(1), 2(7), 3(7), 4(3+aes), 5(2), 6(3), 7(3), 8(7).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ameiridae" genus="Nitokra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nitokra affinis subsp. colombiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="affinis" subSpecies="colombiensis">Nitokra affinis colombiensis</taxonomicName>
ssp. n., adult female from northern Colombia. A antennule B antenna C mandible blade D mandibular palp E maxillule F maxilla G maxilliped H rostrum with rostral process. Scale bars: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–G">A-G</normalizedToken>
= 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, H = 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="5" start="start">Antenna</pageBreakToken>
. Basis with group of 5 unequal spiniform setae, first endopodal segment subrectangular, smooth, second endopodal segment with subdistal row of spinules on inner margin, with 2 lateral inner spines and 6 distal elements, outermost two of them basally fused at insertion. Exopod one-segmented with 3 setae, 2 pinnate and 1 smooth seta (Fig. 3B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="6" start="start">Mandible</pageBreakToken>
. Gnathobase with 5 large teeth, and long dorsal seta ornamented with short spinules (Fig. 3C). Mandibular palp 2-segmented, first segment (basis) with 2 setae. Endopodal segment with 1 short lateral and 4 long apical setae (Fig. 3D).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Maxillule. Arthrite of praecoxa ornamented with group of subequal spinules, arthrite armed with 2 subdistal setae and 4 distal elements. Coxal endite with 2 setae. Basis with 4 setae; exopod 1-segmented, with 2 setae, one slender, the other thicker, distally serrate (Fig. 3E).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Maxilla. Syncoxa naked, with 2 endites, proximalmost with single, slender modified element with distal tuft of setules and with short proximal seta; second endite with 2 unequal setae. Allobasis forming strong serrate claw with 2 accessory setae on proximal position (Fig. 3F).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Maxilliped. Subchelate. Syncoxa with single seta on inner distal corner, basis unarmed, with longitudinal patch of spinules. Endopod drawn into long and slender lightly serrate claw with 2 short accessory setae (Fig. 3G).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">P1. Coxa with outer row of slender spinules. Basis with spinules bordering insertion of exopodal and endopodal rami, inner basipodal spine short, stout, reaching 1/3 of length of first endopodal segment. Outer basipodal spine short, stout, spinulated. EXP and ENP 3-segmented. Exopodal ramus shorter than first endopodal segment. Third exopodal segment with 2 apical geniculate setae. First endopodal segment about 2.9 longer than its width; third endopodal segment with terminal claw, the latter about 1.5 times as long as segment (Fig. 4A).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ameiridae" genus="Nitokra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nitokra affinis subsp. colombiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="affinis" subSpecies="colombiensis">Nitokra affinis colombiensis</taxonomicName>
ssp. n., adult female from northern Colombia. A first swimming leg (P1) B second swimming leg (P2) C third swimming leg (P3) D fourth swimming leg (P4) showing modified pectinate element (arrowed). Scale bars: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
= 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="7" start="start">P</pageBreakToken>
2. Coxa with outer row of slender spinules. Basipod with 2 groups of spinules, as figured. Exopod and endopod 3-segmented. Exopod endopod equally long. First exopodal segment without inner seta, second and third exopodal segments with inner seta. Exopod without modified setae, outer margin of exopodal segments spinulated. Endopod 3-segmented, outer margin of segments ornamented with spinules (Fig. 4B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">P3. Coxa with outer row of slender spinules. Basipod with spinules only at insertion of outer basipodal seta. Exopodal and endopodal rami as in P2 except for shorter apical spiniform element (arrowed in Fig. 4C) and endopod slightly shorter than exopod (Fig. 4C).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">P4. Coxa with outer row of slender spinules. Basipod as in P3. EXP longer than ENP (Fig. 4D). Middle inner seta of EXP3 thicker and longer than adjacent setae (arrowed in Fig. 4D).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">P5. EXP subrectangular, about 1.66 longer than it is width, with 6 setae. Relative length of exopodal setae from inner to outer element as follows: 0.81, 1.00, 0.18, 0.38, 0.18, 0.56. Endopodal lobe quadrate, reaching almost halflength of EXP, with 5 spinulose setae, outermost being longest; relative length of setae from inner to outer elements as follows: 0.32, 0.37; 0.43, 1, 0.46 (Fig. 6A).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Armature formula of female P1-P5 as follows:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<table pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<tr pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<th colspan="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" rowspan="1">P1</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" rowspan="1">P2</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" rowspan="1">P3</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" rowspan="1">P4</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" rowspan="1">P5</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="8" start="start">P</pageBreakToken>
6. Represented by narrow plate with subdistal lobe-like process marked by a notch (arrowed in Fig. 2A); plate bearing 3 elements, 2 equal slender setae and outer small spinulated seta (Fig. 6B).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="male">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
Smaller than female, habitus in lateral view as in figure 1B. Total body length ranging from 518 to 574 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(mean, 546 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; n = 4; allotype: 518 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
). Ornamentation of urosomites resembling that of female except for position of rows of minute spinules on ventral surface of genital and preanal somites (Fig. 2C, D). Anal somite with row of small spinules on posterior margin at insertion of caudal rami. (Figs 1D, E, 2C, D). Rostrum, antennae and mouthparts as in female.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">P1. As in female except for an additional row of spinules on the coxa, presence of small slender seta and 1 geniculate apical seta (arrowed in Fig. 5A), instead of 2 on ENP3, slenderer ENP1, and dimorphic modified inner basipodal spine (Fig. 5A, B).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ameiridae" genus="Nitokra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nitokra affinis subsp. colombiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="affinis" subSpecies="colombiensis">Nitokra affinis colombiensis</taxonomicName>
ssp. n., adult male from northern Colombia. A first swimming leg (P1) B modified inner basipodal spine of P1 C second swimming leg (P2) D third swimming leg (P3) E fourth swimming leg (P4). Scale bars: A, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–E">C-E</normalizedToken>
= 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, B = 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">P2-P4. As in female (Fig. 5C-E), including thickened middle inner seta of EXP3 (arrowed in Fig. 5E) which is relatively shorter than in female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">P5. EXP subquadrate, armed with 6 setae, distal innermost being longest, reaching midlength of fourth urosomite (Fig. 2C, D). Baseoendopod with 3 unequally long setae, middle one longest, about twice as long as the other two (Fig. 6C).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ameiridae" genus="Nitokra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nitokra affinis subsp. colombiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="affinis" subSpecies="colombiensis">Nitokra affinis colombiensis</taxonomicName>
ssp. n. from northern Colombia. Adult female: A fifth leg B sixth leg. Male: C fifth leg D sixth leg. Scale bars: A, C = 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; B, D = 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">P6. With 2 unequal seta, inner one three times longer than outer seta (Figure 6D). Caudal rami as in female (Fig. 2C, D).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Variability. One male with 2 elements (instead of3) on ENP3 of P1.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">The new subspecies is named after Colombia, the country from which it was first discovered.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
The estuary Laguna 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Navío">Navio</normalizedToken>
Quebrado has a surface area of 10.7 km2; it is characterized by the presence of an oyster bank in the limnetic area and vegetation (mangrove and beds of macrophytes) in the littoral zone. Water temperature ranged between 28 and 31 °C, salinity between 0-28 psu, and pH values were 7.8-8.3.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>