<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287418" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a79bfa9b-f103-4186-9d1f-add9ef6b2b3a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116835" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287418" ModsDocAuthor=" &amp; Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota" ModsDocDate="1936" ModsDocID="3011" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf" ModsDocTitle="The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1" checkinTime="1258815363179" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota" docDate="1936" docId="3102C5FD58B202C8BF45CC22EFB73445" docLanguage="en" docName="3011_tx.xml" docOrigin="Revista de Entomologia 7" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf" docTitle="Myrmicocrypta unidentata Weber, 1936, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="385" masterDocId="62511D09FB353213B214D7BBDF9210C0" masterDocTitle="The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1" masterLastPageNumber="409" masterPageNumber="378" pageNumber="384" updateTime="1645821295722" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revista de Entomologia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1936</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>7</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>378</mods:start>
<mods:end>409</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="">3011</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287418" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116835" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287418" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:3102C5FD58B202C8BF45CC22EFB73445" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3102C5FD58B202C8BF45CC22EFB73445" lastPageNumber="385" pageNumber="384">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="384">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:32720" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Myrmicocrypta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Myrmicocrypta unidentata Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="384" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="unidentata">Myrmicocrypta unidentata</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="385" pageNumber="384">
Worker: Length 1.8 mm. - Head, excluding mandibles, 1.1 times as long as wide, occipital margin broadly convex, with rounded and shallow medial impression, sides sub-parallel, feebly convex in front of and behind eyes, anterior clypeal margin convex, posterior sides raised as acute teeth. Eyes small, convex, situated in middle of sides. Frontal lobes moderately large, reflected. Frontal region shallowly concave in middle, not distinctly marginate. Cutting margin of mandibles without distinct teeth, apical tooth well developed. Antennal scapes of moderate proportions, inflated and slightly curved distally, exceeding posterior margin by a distance equal to less than their distal diameter. Joints 2-9 of funiculus about 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="385">as</pageStartToken>
broad as long, terminal joint equal in length to joints 4-9 taken together.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="385">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="385">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="385">Pronotum</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
lacking the anterior and dorso-lateral pair of tubercles, sides with low carinae ending dorsally where the tubercles are in other species. Mesonotum, in profile, high arid convex, with three pairs of blunt tubercles of which the anterior is largest; from the posterior tubercle the mesonotum drops abruptly to the mesoepinotal impression except for a single stout and pointed tubercle on this declivous surface which is larger than any preceding. Basal surface of epinotum carinate on margins and produced behind as small but distinct teeth.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="385">Peduncle of petiole shorter than node, the latter rising smoothly and convexly to a posteriorly descending dorsal surface. Postpetiole in profile with evenly convex dorsal and ventral surfaces, slightly shorter in length than petiole; from above trapezoidal, anterior and posterior margins parallel, feebly impressed postero-medially. First gastric segment slightly longer than wide, anterior and posterior margins straight. Legs of moderate length.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="385">Opaque finely shagreened, mandibles finely striate. - Hairs of head numerous, narrow squamate; sparse on thorax, being confined to. projections, squamate; sparse on pedicel and gaster, squamate; more numerous on antennal scapes and legs but not greatly obscuring integument, narrow squamate. Pale ferruginous, darker on head, mandibles brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="385">Described from one worker taken by myself August 23, 1935, in virgin greenheart (Nectandra Rodei Schomb.) forest near the Forest Settlement, Mazaruni River, British Guiana.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="385">
This species is noteworthy in small size, single large tooth or tubercle on declivous surface of mesonotum above the mesoepinotal impression, reduced spinulation and sparse pilosity of thorax. It cannot belong to 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:32705" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Myrmicocrypta" genus.bestMatchDistance="946" genus.bestMatchVote="2" genus.innerRound="1" genus.outerRound="1" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Myrmicocrypta elisabethae Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="385" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elisabethae">M. elisabethae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
here described because of the very different frontal lobes, pronotal spines, and postpetiole.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>