<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.24351" ID-GBIF-Dataset="154ba0a6-ce19-472e-a0c2-1c03e204b570" ID-GBIF-Taxon="143461795" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-747-87" ID-ZBK="BBCA7929F53F45F5803956B7D3BB2575" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:11847BE7-9D54-4145-9242-14B868FCF6F6" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-747-87" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 747" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the Afrotropical genus Ivondrovia Shenefelt &amp; Marsh, 1976 with description of a new species (Hymenoptera: Braconidae: Doryctinae)" checkinTime="1522737855468" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Belokobylskij, Sergey, Zaldivar-Riveron, Alejandro &amp; Castaneda-Osorio, Ruben" docDate="2018" docId="9DD299DD8A42B211AB387ABF852E4AB5" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 747: 87-100" docOrigin="ZooKeys 747" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.24351" docTitle="Ivondrovia grangeri Belokobylskij, Zaldivar-Riveron &amp; Castaneda-Osorio, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="11847BE7-9D54-4145-9242-14B868FCF6F6" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="92" masterDocId="452FFFB4FFB9FFC1FFA440640A56FFCD" masterDocTitle="Revision of the Afrotropical genus Ivondrovia Shenefelt &amp; Marsh, 1976 with description of a new species (Hymenoptera: Braconidae: Doryctinae)" masterLastPageNumber="100" masterPageNumber="87" pageId="4" pageNumber="91" updateTime="1643523239263" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the Afrotropical genus Ivondrovia Shenefelt &amp; Marsh, 1976 with description of a new species (Hymenoptera: Braconidae: Doryctinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Belokobylskij, Sergey</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zaldivar-Riveron, Alejandro</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Castaneda-Osorio, Ruben</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>747</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>87</mods:start>
<mods:end>100</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.24351</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.24351</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-747-87</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">BBCA7929F53F45F5803956B7D3BB2575</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">BBCA7929F53F45F5803956B7D3BB2575</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="143461795" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:11847BE7-9D54-4145-9242-14B868FCF6F6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9DD299DD8A42B211AB387ABF852E4AB5" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="92" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="91" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/11847BE7-9D54-4145-9242-14B868FCF6F6" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ivondrovia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ivondrovia grangeri" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grangeri">Ivondrovia grangeri</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="4" pageNumber="91">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-11, 12-20
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="91" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
Holotype: female, &quot;Kenya: Nyanza Prov., Gembe Hills in dry gallery woodland 
<taxonomicName class="Gastropoda" family="Limapontiidae" genus="Olea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="ssp." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Olea europaea" order="Lamiales" pageId="4" pageNumber="91" phylum="Mollusca" rank="subspecies" species="europaea" subspecies="cuspidata">Olea europaea ssp. cuspidata</taxonomicName>
common, 1362 m, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-0.48933333">0°29.36'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="34.26">34°15.60'E</geoCoordinate>
, 22-29.i.2005, R. Copeland&quot;, &quot;CNIN 3090&quot; (ZISP). Paratypes. 1 female, with same first label, &quot;CNIN 3326&quot; (UNAM); 1 female, with same first label, but 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“8–15.i.2005”">&quot;8-15.i.2005&quot;</normalizedToken>
, &quot;CNIN 3609&quot; (UNAM); 1 female, Kenya, &quot;Nyanza Prov. Gembe Hills in dry gallery woodland 
<taxonomicName class="Gastropoda" family="Limapontiidae" genus="Olea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="ssp." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Olea europaea" order="Lamiales" pageId="4" pageNumber="91" phylum="Mollusca" rank="subspecies" species="europaea" subspecies="cuspidata">Olea europaea ssp. cuspidata</taxonomicName>
common, 1362 m, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-0.48933333">0°29.36'S</geoCoordinate>
- 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="34.26">34°15.60'E</geoCoordinate>
, R. Copeland&quot; (MNHN).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="91" type="comparative diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Comparative diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
This new species is very similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="I." lsidName="I. seyrigi" pageId="4" pageNumber="91" rank="species" species="seyrigi">I. seyrigi</taxonomicName>
; the differences between both species are indicated in the foregoing key.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="92" pageId="4" pageNumber="91" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Female. Body length 7.3-7.9 mm; fore wing length 5.7-5.8 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Head width 1.60-1.75 times its median length, 1.15-1.20 times width of mesoscutum. Occiput distinctly concave. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) slightly convex anteriorly and weakly roundly narrowed posteriorly. Transverse diameter of eye 1.2-1.3 times longer than temple. Ocelli enlarged, in triangle with base 1.1-1.2 times its sides, situated on median line of eyes. POL 1.10-1.25 times Od, 0.30-0.35 times OOL. Eye without emargination opposite antennal sockets, 1.1-1.2 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.4 times as high as eye, 0.75-0.80 times as high as basal width of mandible. Face width 1.3-1.4 times height of eye and 1.50-1.65 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeus almost flat (lateral view). Width of hypoclypeal depression 0.8-0.9 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.4-0.5 times width of face. Hypostomal flange narrow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Antenna thickened, almost filiform, 51-segmented. Scape 1.5-1.7 times longer than its maximum width. First flagellar segment 2.4-2.6 times longer than its apical width, 0.90-0.95 times as long as second segment. Submedian segments 1.5 times longer than their widths.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Mesosoma. Length 1.7 times its height. Lateral side of pronotum without longitudinal carina, mainly smooth. Median lobe of mesoscutum distinctly convex, protruding forwards and weakly rounded anteriorly. Notauli entirely deep and distinct, rather wide, smooth. Prescutellar depression (scutellar sulcus) deep, long, only with strong median carina, smooth, 0.3-0.4 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum 1.15-1.20 times longer than its maximum width. Subalar depression shallow, entirely smooth. Precoxal sulcus (sternaulus) shallow, narrow, smooth, connected anteriorly with prepectal carina, running along all lower part of mesopleuron. Metapleural lobe without dense pubescence along posterior margin. Propodeum (lateral view) distinctly and evenly convex.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Wings. Fore wing 3.4-3.5 times longer than its maximum width. Pterostigma 3.5-4.2 times longer than width. Metacarpus (R1a) 1.1-1.2 times longer than pterostigma, 1.5-2.0 times longer than distance between apex of radial (marginal) cell and apex of wing. Radial vein (r) arising from basal 0.4 of pterostigma. Second radial abscissa (3RSa) 1.9-2.1 times longer than first abscissa (r), 0.4 times as long as the slightly, evenly curved third abscissa (3RSb), 1.3-1.5 times longer than the almost straight and oblique first radiomedial vein (2RS). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell slightly widened towards apex, 2.6-2.9 times longer than its maximum width, 0.85 times as long as the rather wide brachial (first subdiscal) cell. Brachial (first subdiscal) cell slightly convex anteriorly. First medial abscissa ((RS+M)a) slightly sinuate. Recurrent vein (1m-cu) 1.1-1.2 times longer than first radiomedial vein (2RS), 0.6 times as long as basal vein (1M); recurrent (1m-cu) and basal (1M) veins subparallel. Discoidal (first discal) cell long, 2.5-2.6 times longer than its maximum width. Distance from nervulus (1cu-a) to basal vein (1M) 0.25-0.30 times nervulus (1cu-a) length. Hind wing 3.6 times longer than its maximum width. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.9-1.0 times as long as second abscissa (1M); basal part of second abscissa (1M) (before recurrent vein (m-cu)) 3.5 times longer than apical part of second abscissa (1M) (behind recurrent vein (m-cu)). Recurrent vein sclerotised, blackish.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Legs. Hind coxa 1.2-1.4 times longer than maximum width, 0.80-0.85 times as long as propodeum. Hind femur 2.4-2.6 times longer than width. Hind tarsus 0.9-1.0 times as long as hind tibia. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.5 times as long as basitarsus, 0.75-0.80 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Metasoma 1.2 times longer than head and mesosoma combined. First tergite rather strongly and obliquely widened basally, then distinctly and weakly-roundly widened from almost base to subapex, slightly narrowed apically, without oblique apico-lateral furrows. Maximum width of first tergite 1.5-1.6 times its width at dorsope level, 2.1-2.3 times its minimum width; length 1.1 times its apical width. Median length of second tergite 0.5 times its basal width, 2.3-2.5 times length of third tergite. Ovipositor sheath almost equal to metasoma, 1.7 times longer than mesosoma, 0.7 times as long as fore wing.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="92">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="92" start="start">Sculpture</pageBreakToken>
and pubescence. Head (including frons and clypeus) smooth. Mesosoma mainly smooth; mesoscutum in medioposterior third with longitudinally median carina and striation on rather wide area, metapleuron posteriorly punctate. Propodeum with medial length and subtriangular or suboval areola situated in posterior 0.4-0.5 of segment, with coarse long mediobasal carina in anterior half of segment, basolateral areas almost fused posteriorly with apico-lateral areas, mainly smooth. Hind coxa and femur entirely smooth. First tergite almost smooth widely in basal two-thirds and mostly laterally, distinctly striate in medio-apical third, with distinct longitudinal medial carina narrowly branched in apical half, lateral carinae slightly convergent. Second tergite medially strongly striate on large leaf-shaped median area, densely and distinctly punctate laterally; third tergite sparsely punctate and partly smooth, with crenulated and rather narrow transverse submedian furrow. Third and fourth tergites sub-posteriorly with transverse narrow punctate furrows. Remaining tergites distinctly sparsely punctate, smooth posteriorly. Vertex almost entirely glabrous, usually with not long and semi-erect setae laterally. Mesoscutum mainly glabrous, with rather dense, short and semi-erect pale setae laterally and in medioposterior third. Mesopleuron widely glabrous medially. Hind tibia dorsally with rather dense, short, and semi-erect golden setae, ventrally with dense or very dense, short and semi-erect golden setae and additionally with sparse, long and semi-erect setae; length of setae on dorsal margin of tibia 0.3-0.5 times maximum width of hind tibia.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="92">Colour. Body almost entirely light reddish brown, head with large black spot on all or most part of frons and on median part of vertex. Antenna entirely black. Palpi reddish brown, darker basally. Legs light reddish brown or partly reddish brown, apical segments of fore and middle tarsi dark brown to black; hind tibia and tarsus entirely black, tarsus sometimes medially dark reddish brown. Ovipositor sheaths black. Fore and hind wings entirely distinctly infuscate, without yellowish tint. Pterostigma entirely black.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="92">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="92">
Figures 1-11. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ivondrovia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ivondrovia grangeri" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grangeri">Ivondrovia grangeri</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female, holotype. 1 habitus, dorsal view 2 palpi 3 head, dorsal view 4 upper median process of occiput 5 head, front view 6 head, lateral view 7 basal segments of antenna 8 mesosoma, dorsal view 9 mesosoma, lateral view 10 fore femur, dorsal view 11 fore femur and tibia, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="92">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="92">
Figures 12-20. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ivondrovia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ivondrovia grangeri" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grangeri">Ivondrovia grangeri</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female, holotype. 12 fore and hind wings 13 hind leg 14 basal part of hind wing 15 upper apical part of hind wing 16 apical part of fore wing 17 propodeum and three basal tergites of metasoma, dorsal view 18 metasoma, dorsal view 19 metasoma, lateral view 20 apex of ovipositor, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="92" type="male">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="92">Male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="92">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>