<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4531858" ID-GBIF-Dataset="45d7b489-d4c8-4b94-939c-3fadee6678d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="177318270" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4531858" ID-ZooBank="F898059E-0B23-48F1-BFAE-BBBB3D87DA5A" checkinTime="1612248766138" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Colmenares-Pinzón, Javier E." docDate="2021" docId="03C687837D671038FF297E3A8868FBF0" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4920.4.1.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4920 (4)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.5:Zootaxa.2013.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013.journal_article" docStyleVersion="5" docTitle="Neacomys Thomas 1900" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="476" masterDocId="FFFFFFFB7D6B1021FFBE79528C57FFE1" masterDocTitle="Calling for a reassessment of rodent diversity in Colombia: description of a new species of Neacomys (Cricetidae: Oryzomyini) from the Magdalena Valley, with a new phylogenetic hypothesis for the genus and comments on its diversification" masterLastPageNumber="494" masterPageNumber="451" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" updateTime="1643434865143" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Calling for a reassessment of rodent diversity in Colombia: description of a new species of Neacomys (Cricetidae: Oryzomyini) from the Magdalena Valley, with a new phylogenetic hypothesis for the genus and comments on its diversification</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Colmenares-Pinzón, Javier E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2021</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2021-02-02</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4920</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>4</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>451</mods:start>
<mods:end>494</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4920.4.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">45d7b489-d4c8-4b94-939c-3fadee6678d2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">4491116</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F898059E-0B23-48F1-BFAE-BBBB3D87DA5A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4531858" ID-GBIF-Taxon="177318270" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4531858" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03C687837D671038FF297E3A8868FBF0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C687837D671038FF297E3A8868FBF0" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="476" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">
<subSubSection box="[151,540,1896,1922]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,540,1896,1922]" box="[151,540,1896,1922]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,231,1896,1922]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">Genus</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Thomas, 1900" authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[238,540,1896,1922]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[238,359,1897,1922]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">Neacomys</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Thomas, O." box="[366,540,1896,1922]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" pagination="148 - 153" refId="ref29406" refString="Thomas, O. (1900) New South American mammals. Annals and Magazine of Natural History, Series 7, 5, 148 - 153. https: // doi. org / 10.1080 / 00222930008678252" type="journal article" year="1900">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[366,540,1896,1922]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">Thomas, 1900</emphasis>
</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,899,1968,1994]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,899,1968,2031]" box="[151,899,1968,1994]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,414,1969,1994]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[151,414,1969,1994]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">Neacomys serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[429,899,1968,1994]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[429,573,1968,1994]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
(
<figureCitation box="[588,749,1968,1994]" captionStart-0="FIGURE 1" captionStart-1="FIGURE 2" captionStart-10="FIGURE 11" captionStart-11="FIGURE 12" captionStart-2="FIGURE 3" captionStart-3="FIGURE 4" captionStart-4="FIGURE 5" captionStart-5="FIGURE 6" captionStart-6="FIGURE 7" captionStart-7="FIGURE 8" captionStart-8="FIGURE 9" captionStart-9="FIGURE 10" captionStartId-0="3.[151,250,1427,1451]" captionStartId-1="4.[151,250,1538,1562]" captionStartId-10="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionStartId-11="21.[151,250,1615,1639]" captionStartId-2="9.[151,250,1528,1552]" captionStartId-3="12.[151,250,1394,1418]" captionStartId-4="13.[151,250,1655,1679]" captionStartId-5="15.[151,250,1328,1352]" captionStartId-6="16.[151,250,1901,1925]" captionStartId-7="17.[151,250,1161,1185]" captionStartId-8="18.[151,250,1875,1899]" captionStartId-9="19.[151,250,1873,1897]" captionTargetBox-0="[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetBox-1="[151,1436,597,1514]" captionTargetBox-10="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetBox-11="[170,1417,345,1592]" captionTargetBox-2="[189,1394,181,1503]" captionTargetBox-3="[189,1398,181,1370]" captionTargetBox-4="[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetBox-5="[151,1436,345,1305]" captionTargetBox-6="[151,1436,489,1878]" captionTargetBox-7="[151,1436,181,1137]" captionTargetBox-8="[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetBox-9="[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetId-0="figure-182@3.[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetId-1="figure-219@4.[151,1436,597,1514]" captionTargetId-10="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId-11="figure-92@21.[170,1417,345,1592]" captionTargetId-2="figure-18@9.[189,1398,181,1503]" captionTargetId-3="figure-22@12.[189,1398,181,1370]" captionTargetId-4="figure-162@13.[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetId-5="figure-95@15.[151,1436,345,1305]" captionTargetId-6="figure-209@16.[151,1436,489,1878]" captionTargetId-7="figure-18@17.[151,1436,181,1137]" captionTargetId-8="figure-22@18.[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetId-9="figure-18@19.[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetPageId-0="3" captionTargetPageId-1="4" captionTargetPageId-10="20" captionTargetPageId-11="21" captionTargetPageId-2="9" captionTargetPageId-3="12" captionTargetPageId-4="13" captionTargetPageId-5="15" captionTargetPageId-6="16" captionTargetPageId-7="17" captionTargetPageId-8="18" captionTargetPageId-9="19" captionText-0="FIGURE 1. Map of collecting localities of the specimens of Neacomys sp. nov. (stars) 1. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí, vereda La Bodega, sector Manchurrias, western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes, Finca Buenos Aires, in the basin of the La San Guillerma stream (Type locality); 2. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of Hato, vereda Hoya Negra. Numbers also correspond to the localities listed in Appendix I. Dashed lines represent boundaries of the municipalities encompassing the two localities. Green polygon represents the area comprised by the Serranía de los Yariguíes National Natural Park." captionText-1="FIGURE 2. Map showing collection localities of the named and unamed small-bodied species of Neacomys (except N. pictus) along with salient topographic features of northern South America. Localities of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov are numbered according to Appendix I. Localities of the remaining species are detailed in Voss et al. (2001), Sánchez-Vendizú et al. (2018), and Semedo et al. (2020). Miniature in the right side of the map corresponds to the Bayesian Cytb phylogeny recovered here (FIGURE 3): species in the map and phylogeny are same colored; the numbers in some nodes correspond to the median divergence times estimated by Upham et al. (2019) within Neacomys." captionText-10="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." captionText-11="FIGURE 12. Illustration of Neacomys serranensis sp. nov. by wildlife artist and zoologist Velizar Simeonovski." captionText-2="FIGURE 3. Bayesian Inference topology based on Cytb sequence data used to assess the position of Neacomys sp. nov. in relation to other species in the genus (BI and ML analyses resulted in congruent topologies). Support values are indicated for each node (Bayesian posterior probabilities to the left, and percentages of 1,000 bootstrap replicates to the right). Each terminal is identified by country of origin, the next largest political unit, and GenBank accession number (in red). For specimens of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov. sequenced here, collection numbers are provided, as well as a number referring to localities mapped in FIGURE 2 and listed in Appendix I. Shaded colored boxes enclose the species groups proposed by Hurtado &amp; Pacheco (2017) and Semedo et al. (2020). Abbreviations: BO (Bolivia), BR (Brazil), CO (Colombia), EC (Ecuador), FG (French Guyana), GU (Guyana), PE (Peru), and SU (Suriname)." captionText-3="FIGURE 4. Scatterplots of the Principal Components Analyses: PC1 and PC2 are represented in the graphics. A. PCA of the external and craniodental variables of all the small-bodied species of Neacomys; B. PCA of the craniodental variables of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov. Miniatures in the right side correspond to the Bayesian Cytb phylogeny recovered here (FIG- URE 3): species in the scatterplots and the phylogenies are same colored." captionText-4="FIGURE 5. A) Montane forest habitat along the left Bank of the La San Guillerma stream, adjacent to the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. (municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón) B) View of the forest remnant where the second specimen of Neacomys sp nov. was collected (municipality of Hato) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón). C) Topography of the western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes from the campsite “Finca Buenos Aires”; near the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. D) Educational activity with members of the community in the municipality of El Carmen del Chucurí, Vereda la Bodega, Sector Manchurrias, illustrating the importance of government funded projects (like Santander BIO expeditions), not only to inventory the biodiversity of remote areas, but also to teach local people to preserve it." captionText-5="FIGURE 6. Dorsal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723); note that a portion of the tail is missing in this specimen." captionText-6="FIGURE 7. Frontal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068); note the distinctive broad ochraceous-orange patches in the sides of the muzzle of this species. B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723)." captionText-7="FIGURE 8. Ventral perspectives of adult specimens illustrating the striking difference in ventral fur of the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) Section of the holotype of Neacomys sp. nov. showing its characteristic gray-based ochraceous-buff ventral fur. C) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723); note the contrasting entirely white ventral fur of this species." captionText-8="FIGURE 9. Comparison of the dorsal and ventral views of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B), D) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note the nasals more expanded anteriorly, the shallower zygomatic notches, the less developed supraorbital ridges, the procingulum of M1 flattened laterally, and the incisive foramina extending almost to anterior alveolus of M1 in Neacomys sp. nov. if: incisive foramen; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; nas: nasal bone; sob: supraorbital beads; zn: zygomatic notch." captionText-9="FIGURE 10. Comparison of the lateral profiles of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note a more convex profile of the braincase, a thicker hamular process of the squamosal, a broader condylar process, a larger and laterally projected mental foramen, and the anterior margin of nasals without a hump in Neacomys sp. nov. con: condylar process; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; mf: mental foramen; nas: nasals." figureDoi-0="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491120" figureDoi-1="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491122" figureDoi-10="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" figureDoi-11="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491146" figureDoi-2="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491124" figureDoi-3="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491126" figureDoi-4="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491128" figureDoi-5="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491132" figureDoi-6="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491134" figureDoi-7="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491136" figureDoi-8="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491138" figureDoi-9="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491142" httpUri-0="https://zenodo.org/record/4491120/files/figure.png" httpUri-1="https://zenodo.org/record/4491122/files/figure.png" httpUri-10="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" httpUri-11="https://zenodo.org/record/4491146/files/figure.png" httpUri-2="https://zenodo.org/record/4491124/files/figure.png" httpUri-3="https://zenodo.org/record/4491126/files/figure.png" httpUri-4="https://zenodo.org/record/4491128/files/figure.png" httpUri-5="https://zenodo.org/record/4491132/files/figure.png" httpUri-6="https://zenodo.org/record/4491134/files/figure.png" httpUri-7="https://zenodo.org/record/4491136/files/figure.png" httpUri-8="https://zenodo.org/record/4491138/files/figure.png" httpUri-9="https://zenodo.org/record/4491142/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">Figures 1-12</figureCitation>
; 
<tableCitation box="[762,890,1968,1994]" captionStart-0="TABLE 1" captionStart-1="TABLE 2" captionStart-2="TABLE 3" captionStart-3="TABLE 4" captionStart-4="TABLE 5" captionStartId-0="6.[151,239,1304,1328]" captionStartId-1="11.[151,239,151,175]" captionStartId-2="23.[151,239,152,176]" captionStartId-3="25.[151,239,1088,1112]" captionStartId-4="27.[151,239,151,175]" captionText-0="TABLE 1. External and craniodental measurements of adult specimens of most of the small-bodied species of Neacomys, including the taxon described here. Weigh (Wt) is given in grams and the measurements are in millimeters. Mean and Standard Deviation (above), observed range (middle), and sample size (below, in parenthesis). High Body Length (HBL), Tail Length (TL), Hind Foot Length (HF), and Ear Length (Ear). Condylo-incisive Length (CIL); Length of Diastema (LD); Length of Molars (LM); Breadth of M1 (BM1); Length of Incisive Foramen (LIF); Breadth of Incisive Foramen (BIF); Breadth of Palatal Bridge (BPB); Breadth of Zygomatic Plate (BZP); Length of Rostrum (LR); Length of Nasals (LN); Least Interorbital Breadth (LIB); Breadth of Braincase (BB); Zygomatic Breadth (ZB)." captionText-1="TABLE 2. Factor loadings of the first two components of each of the Principal Components Analyses performed. Bold values indicate the eigenvectors of the five variables that explains most of the variance for each component." captionText-2="TABLE 3. Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of Neacomys, Part I" captionText-3="TABLE 4. Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of Neacomys, Part II" captionText-4="TABLE 5. Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of Neacomys, Part III" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">Tables 1-5</tableCitation>
)
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,744,2004,2031]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="12.[151,899,1968,2031]" box="[151,744,2004,2031]" pageId="12" pageNumber="463">Serrano Spiny Mouse or Ratoncito Espinoso Serrano</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="464" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,150,466]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3033805302" collectingDate="2018-02-28" collectionCode="II" collectorName="Alejandro Lopera &amp; Javier E. Colmenares-Pinzon" county="Coleccion de Mamiferos del Museo de Historia Natural" location="Coleccion de Tejidos del Museo de Historia Natural" municipality="Museo de Historia Natural de la Universidad Industrial" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" specimenCode="JEC 127" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Santander" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis box="[151,287,150,177]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,262,150,177]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<typeStatus box="[151,258,150,177]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Holotype</typeStatus>
.
</emphasis>
—
</emphasis>
A young adult male specimen (age class 
<collectionCode box="[739,759,151,177]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">II</collectionCode>
) housed in the 
<collectingCounty pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
Colección de Mamíferos del 
<collectingMunicipality pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Museo de Historia Natural</collectingMunicipality>
</collectingCounty>
de la Universidad Industrial de 
<collectingRegion box="[635,747,187,213]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Santander</collectingRegion>
(UIS-MHN-M 1608), 
<collectingMethod box="[1005,1437,187,213]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">caught in an entomological pitfall trap</collectingMethod>
by 
<collectorName box="[184,381,223,249]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Alejandro Lopera</collectorName>
and prepared by 
<collectorName box="[571,895,223,249]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Javier E. Colmenares-Pinzón</collectorName>
in 
<date box="[928,1132,223,249]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" value="2018-02-28">
<collectingDate box="[928,1132,223,249]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" value="2018-02-28">February 28, 2018</collectingDate>
</date>
(original field number 
<specimenCode collectionCode="JEC" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">JEC 127</specimenCode>
); skin with skull and mandibles, in good condition; liver, heart, and skeletal muscle fragments preserved in 96% ethanol and maintained in the 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03C687837D671038FF297E3A8868FBF0:8EB0604E7D66102CFE5778758879FEA0" box="[489,1070,295,321]" county="Coleccion de Mamiferos del Museo de Historia Natural" municipality="Museo de Historia Natural de la Universidad Industrial" name="Coleccion de Tejidos del Museo de Historia Natural" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" stateProvince="Santander">Colección de Tejidos del Museo de Historia Natural</location>
UIS; baculum preserved in 10% buffered formalin; ectoparasites preserved in 70% ethanol.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="464" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,150,466]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<emphasis box="[199,375,366,393]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,350,366,393]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Type locality.</emphasis>
—
</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3033805301" collectorName="La Bodega &amp; La San Guillerma" country="Colombia" elevation="1595" latitude="6.6847777" location="Municipality of El Carmen de Chucuri" longLatPrecision="1" longitude="-73.436226" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Santander">
<collectingCountry box="[375,488,367,393]" name="Colombia" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Colombia</collectingCountry>
, Department of 
<collectingRegion box="[665,779,367,393]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Santander</collectingRegion>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03C687837D671038FF297E3A8868FBF0:8EB0604E7D66102CFCAA783D8895FE68" box="[788,1218,367,393]" country="Colombia" latitude="6.6847777" longLatPrecision="1" longitude="-73.436226" name="Municipality of El Carmen de Chucuri" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" stateProvince="Santander">Municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí</location>
, vereda 
<collectorName box="[1308,1432,367,393]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">La Bodega</collectorName>
, sector Manchurrias, western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes, Finca Buenos Aires, in the basin of the 
<collectorName pageId="13" pageNumber="464">La San Guillerma</collectorName>
stream (
<geoCoordinate box="[362,499,438,465]" degrees="6" direction="north" minutes="41" orientation="latitude" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" precision="1" seconds="5.2" value="6.6847777">6°41’5.2’’N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate box="[511,679,439,465]" degrees="73" direction="west" minutes="26" orientation="longitude" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" precision="1" seconds="10.4" value="-73.436226">73°26’10.4’’W</geoCoordinate>
, 
<elevation box="[691,840,438,466]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.595" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" unit="m" value="1595.0">
<quantity box="[691,783,438,465]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.595" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" unit="m" value="1595.0">1,595 m</quantity>
a.s.l.
</elevation>
) (
<figureCitation box="[866,944,439,465]" captionStart="FIGURE 1" captionStartId="3.[151,250,1427,1451]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetId="figure-182@3.[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURE 1. Map of collecting localities of the specimens of Neacomys sp. nov. (stars) 1. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí, vereda La Bodega, sector Manchurrias, western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes, Finca Buenos Aires, in the basin of the La San Guillerma stream (Type locality); 2. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of Hato, vereda Hoya Negra. Numbers also correspond to the localities listed in Appendix I. Dashed lines represent boundaries of the municipalities encompassing the two localities. Green polygon represents the area comprised by the Serranía de los Yariguíes National Natural Park." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491120" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491120/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Figs. 1</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation box="[998,1036,438,465]" captionStart="FIGURE 5" captionStartId="13.[151,250,1655,1679]" captionTargetBox="[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetId="figure-162@13.[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 5. A) Montane forest habitat along the left Bank of the La San Guillerma stream, adjacent to the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. (municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón) B) View of the forest remnant where the second specimen of Neacomys sp nov. was collected (municipality of Hato) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón). C) Topography of the western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes from the campsite “Finca Buenos Aires”; near the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. D) Educational activity with members of the community in the municipality of El Carmen del Chucurí, Vereda la Bodega, Sector Manchurrias, illustrating the importance of government funded projects (like Santander BIO expeditions), not only to inventory the biodiversity of remote areas, but also to teach local people to preserve it." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491128" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491128/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">5A</figureCitation>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491128" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491128" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491128/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" startId="13.[151,250,1655,1679]" targetBox="[207,1380,489,1632]" targetPageId="13">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1437,1655,1895]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,277,1655,1679]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">FIGURE 5.</emphasis>
A) Montane forest habitat along the left Bank of the La San Guillerma stream, adjacent to the type locality of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,255,1692,1715]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[151,255,1692,1715]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[263,343,1692,1715]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón) B) View of the forest remnant where the second specimen of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[469,573,1728,1751]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[469,573,1728,1751]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
sp nov. was collected (municipality of Hato) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón). C) Topography of the western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes from the campsite “Finca Buenos Aires”; near the type locality of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[180,284,1800,1823]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[180,284,1800,1823]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[291,371,1800,1823]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
D) Educational activity with members of the community in the municipality of El Carmen del Chucurí, Vereda la Bodega, Sector Manchurrias, illustrating the importance of government funded projects (like Santander BIO expeditions), not only to inventory the biodiversity of remote areas, but also to teach local people to preserve it.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<subSubSection lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="465" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,1941,2040]" lastBlockId="14.[151,1437,150,2013]" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="465" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<emphasis box="[199,457,1941,1968]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,432,1941,1968]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">Referred specimens.</emphasis>
—
</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3033805303" collectingDate="2019-11-25" country="Colombia" county="This" elevation="2124" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="465" latitude="6.5938363" location="Serrania" longLatPrecision="1" longitude="-73.35545" municipality="Km" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Santander">
Only an additional very young specimen, 
<collectingMethod box="[923,1402,1941,1968]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">also caught in an entomological pitfall trap</collectingMethod>
by Juliette Gualdrón in 
<date box="[379,604,1977,2004]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" value="2019-11-25">
<collectingDate box="[379,604,1977,2004]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464" value="2019-11-25">November 25, 2019</collectingDate>
</date>
, and preserved in fluid (ethanol 96%) with not extracted skull (UIS-MHN-M 1928); tissues (fragments of heart and liver) preserved in ethanol 96%. 
<collectingCounty box="[1004,1054,2013,2039]" pageId="13" pageNumber="464">This</collectingCounty>
specimen was collected southern of the 
<typeStatus box="[228,276,151,177]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">type</typeStatus>
locality (̴13.45 
<collectingMunicipality box="[461,507,151,177]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Km</collectingMunicipality>
), in the eastern slope of the 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03C687837D671038FF297E3A8868FBF0:8EB0604E7D65102FFCF979C58FF3FF50" box="[839,932,151,177]" country="Colombia" county="This" latitude="6.5938363" longLatPrecision="1" longitude="-73.35545" municipality="Km" name="Serrania" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" stateProvince="Santander">Serranía</location>
de los 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03C687837D671038FF297E3A8868FBF0:8EB0604E7D65102FFC4579C58832FF50" box="[1019,1125,151,177]" country="Colombia" county="This" latitude="6.5938363" longLatPrecision="1" longitude="-73.35545" municipality="Km" name="Yariguies" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" stateProvince="Santander">Yariguíes</location>
[
<collectingCountry box="[1141,1257,151,177]" name="Colombia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Colombia</collectingCountry>
, Department of 
<collectingRegion box="[151,265,187,213]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Santander</collectingRegion>
, Municipality of Hato, vereda Hoya Negra (
<geoCoordinate box="[758,924,186,213]" degrees="6" direction="north" minutes="35" orientation="latitude" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" precision="1" seconds="37.81" value="6.5938363">6°35’37.81’’N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate box="[934,1117,186,213]" degrees="73" direction="west" minutes="21" orientation="longitude" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" precision="1" seconds="19.65" value="-73.35545">73°21’19.65’’W</geoCoordinate>
, 
<elevation box="[1128,1279,186,213]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.124" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="m" value="2124.0">
<quantity box="[1128,1220,187,213]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.124" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="m" value="2124.0">2,124 m</quantity>
a.s.l.
</elevation>
)] (
<figureCitation box="[1312,1389,187,213]" captionStart="FIGURE 1" captionStartId="3.[151,250,1427,1451]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetId="figure-182@3.[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURE 1. Map of collecting localities of the specimens of Neacomys sp. nov. (stars) 1. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí, vereda La Bodega, sector Manchurrias, western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes, Finca Buenos Aires, in the basin of the La San Guillerma stream (Type locality); 2. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of Hato, vereda Hoya Negra. Numbers also correspond to the localities listed in Appendix I. Dashed lines represent boundaries of the municipalities encompassing the two localities. Green polygon represents the area comprised by the Serranía de los Yariguíes National Natural Park." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491120" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491120/files/figure.png" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Figs. 1</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation box="[151,187,222,249]" captionStart="FIGURE 5" captionStartId="13.[151,250,1655,1679]" captionTargetBox="[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetId="figure-162@13.[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 5. A) Montane forest habitat along the left Bank of the La San Guillerma stream, adjacent to the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. (municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón) B) View of the forest remnant where the second specimen of Neacomys sp nov. was collected (municipality of Hato) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón). C) Topography of the western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes from the campsite “Finca Buenos Aires”; near the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. D) Educational activity with members of the community in the municipality of El Carmen del Chucurí, Vereda la Bodega, Sector Manchurrias, illustrating the importance of government funded projects (like Santander BIO expeditions), not only to inventory the biodiversity of remote areas, but also to teach local people to preserve it." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491128" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491128/files/figure.png" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">5B</figureCitation>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="465" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="14.[151,1437,150,2013]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
<emphasis box="[199,853,258,285]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,576,258,285]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Distribution and natural history.</emphasis>
— 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[605,853,259,284]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">Neacomys serranensis</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[860,948,259,285]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is only known from two localities in opposite slopes of the Serranía de los Yariguíes, but its distributional limits are not well characterized yet. The Serranía de los Yariguíes is a massif located within the limits of the Department of 
<collectingRegion box="[1008,1122,331,357]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Santander</collectingRegion>
, in Northeastern 
<collectingCountry box="[1319,1432,331,357]" name="Colombia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Colombia</collectingCountry>
, of about 80 Km South to North, emerging from the lowlands of the 
<collectingRegion box="[912,1036,367,393]" country="Colombia" name="Magdalena" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Magdalena</collectingRegion>
Valley with an approximate area of 5,000 Km 
<superScript attach="left" box="[264,272,402,416]" fontSize="6" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">2</superScript>
and altitudes between 500 and 
<quantity box="[631,724,402,429]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="3.5" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="m" value="3500.0">3,500 m</quantity>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Diaz, M." box="[740,868,403,429]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" refId="ref25529" refString="Diaz, M. (2008) Parque Nacional Natural Serrania de los Yariguies, Plan de manejo. Informe tecnico. Parques Nacionales Naturales de Colombia, Bogota. Available from: http: // www. parquesnacionales. gov. co / PNN / portel / libreria / pdf / YariguesPM 2009. pdf (accessed 30 December 2020)" type="book" year="2008">Díaz, 2008</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Jara-Munoz, O. A. &amp; Zabala-Rivera, J. C." box="[881,1286,403,429]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" pagination="355 - 363" refId="ref27140" refString="Jara-Munoz, O. A. &amp; Zabala-Rivera, J. C. (2018) Dos nuevas especies de Begonia (Begoniaceae) de la Serrania de los Yariguies (Santander, Colombia). Novon: A Journal for Botanical Nomenclature, 26 (4), 355 - 363. https: // doi. org / 10.3417 / 2018226" type="journal article" year="2018">Jara-Muñoz &amp; Zabala-Rivera, 2018</bibRefCitation>
) (
<figureCitation box="[1310,1388,403,429]" captionStart="FIGURE 1" captionStartId="3.[151,250,1427,1451]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetId="figure-182@3.[151,1436,522,1400]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURE 1. Map of collecting localities of the specimens of Neacomys sp. nov. (stars) 1. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí, vereda La Bodega, sector Manchurrias, western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes, Finca Buenos Aires, in the basin of the La San Guillerma stream (Type locality); 2. Colombia, Department of Santander, Municipality of Hato, vereda Hoya Negra. Numbers also correspond to the localities listed in Appendix I. Dashed lines represent boundaries of the municipalities encompassing the two localities. Green polygon represents the area comprised by the Serranía de los Yariguíes National Natural Park." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491120" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491120/files/figure.png" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Figs. 1</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation box="[151,188,438,465]" captionStart="FIGURE 5" captionStartId="13.[151,250,1655,1679]" captionTargetBox="[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetId="figure-162@13.[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 5. A) Montane forest habitat along the left Bank of the La San Guillerma stream, adjacent to the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. (municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón) B) View of the forest remnant where the second specimen of Neacomys sp nov. was collected (municipality of Hato) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón). C) Topography of the western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes from the campsite “Finca Buenos Aires”; near the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. D) Educational activity with members of the community in the municipality of El Carmen del Chucurí, Vereda la Bodega, Sector Manchurrias, illustrating the importance of government funded projects (like Santander BIO expeditions), not only to inventory the biodiversity of remote areas, but also to teach local people to preserve it." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491128" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491128/files/figure.png" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">5C</figureCitation>
). It is considered as part of the Cordillera Oriental, the eastern ramus of the Colombian Andes, but is isolated from the main mountain chain by the dry valleys of the Suárez River in the east, and the Sogamoso River in the north. The entire massif belongs to the 
<collectingRegion box="[592,716,511,537]" country="Colombia" name="Magdalena" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Magdalena</collectingRegion>
Valley Montane Forest ecoregion (
<bibRefCitation author="Olson, D. M. &amp; Dinerstein, E. &amp; Wikramanayake, E. D. &amp; Burgess, N. D. &amp; Powell, G. V. N. &amp; Underwood, E. C. &amp; D'Amico, J. A. &amp; Itoua, I. &amp; Strand, H. E. &amp; Morrison, J. C. &amp; Loucks, C. J. &amp; Allnutt, T. F. &amp; Ricketts, T. H. &amp; Kura, Y. &amp; Lamoreux, J. F. &amp; Wettengel, W. W. &amp; Hedao, P. &amp; Kassem, K. R." box="[1111,1318,511,537]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" pagination="933 - 938" refId="ref27698" refString="Olson, D. M., Dinerstein, E., Wikramanayake, E. D., Burgess, N. D., Powell, G. V. N., Underwood, E. C., D'Amico, J. A., Itoua, I., Strand, H. E., Morrison, J. C., Loucks, C. J., Allnutt, T. F., Ricketts, T. H., Kura, Y., Lamoreux, J. F., Wettengel, W. W., Hedao, P. &amp; Kassem, K. R. (2001) Terrestrial ecoregions of the world: A new map of life on earth. BioScience, 51 (11), 933 - 938. https: // doi. org / 10.1641 / 0006 - 3568 (2001) 051 [0933: TEOTWA] 2.0. CO; 2" type="journal article" year="2001">
Olson 
<emphasis box="[1187,1237,511,537]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">et al</emphasis>
., 2001
</bibRefCitation>
). The type locality of the species is at 
<quantity box="[462,556,546,573]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.595" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="m" value="1595.0">1,595 m</quantity>
on the western slope, the less intervened portion (Donegan 
<emphasis box="[1240,1304,547,573]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">et al.,</emphasis>
2009); it is dominated by 
<emphasis box="[317,441,583,609]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">terra firme</emphasis>
high dense forest, and corresponds with the lower montane moist forest life zone and the Andean orobiome (
<bibRefCitation author="Holdridge, L." box="[410,600,619,645]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" refId="ref26643" refString="Holdridge, L. (2000) Ecologia basada en zonas de vida. Instituto Interamericano de Cooperacion para la Agricultura, San Jose, 219 pp." type="book" year="2000">Holdridge, 2000</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Diaz, M." box="[612,738,619,645]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" refId="ref25529" refString="Diaz, M. (2008) Parque Nacional Natural Serrania de los Yariguies, Plan de manejo. Informe tecnico. Parques Nacionales Naturales de Colombia, Bogota. Available from: http: // www. parquesnacionales. gov. co / PNN / portel / libreria / pdf / YariguesPM 2009. pdf (accessed 30 December 2020)" type="book" year="2008">Diaz, 2008</bibRefCitation>
) (
<figureCitation box="[762,853,618,645]" captionStart="FIGURE 5" captionStartId="13.[151,250,1655,1679]" captionTargetBox="[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetId="figure-162@13.[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 5. A) Montane forest habitat along the left Bank of the La San Guillerma stream, adjacent to the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. (municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón) B) View of the forest remnant where the second specimen of Neacomys sp nov. was collected (municipality of Hato) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón). C) Topography of the western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes from the campsite “Finca Buenos Aires”; near the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. D) Educational activity with members of the community in the municipality of El Carmen del Chucurí, Vereda la Bodega, Sector Manchurrias, illustrating the importance of government funded projects (like Santander BIO expeditions), not only to inventory the biodiversity of remote areas, but also to teach local people to preserve it." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491128" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491128/files/figure.png" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Fig. 5A</figureCitation>
). The climate is characterized by a bimodal rainfall regime with a first peak of rains in April-May, and a second in September-October; December-February, as well as July, are the months with the lowest precipitation values. Mean annual precipitation is 
<quantity box="[1125,1239,690,717]" metricMagnitude="0" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.625" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="mm" value="1625.0">1,625 mm</quantity>
and mean annual temperature is 18.89 °C (
<bibRefCitation author="Fick, S. E. &amp; Himans, R. J." box="[431,680,727,753]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" pagination="4302 - 4315" refId="ref26042" refString="Fick, S. E. &amp;. Himans, R. J. (2017) WorldClim 2: new 1 km spatial resolution climate surfaces for global land areas. International Journal of Climatology, 37 (12), 4302 - 4315. https: // doi. org / 10.1002 / joc. 5086" type="journal article" year="2017">Fick &amp; Himans, 2017</bibRefCitation>
). Plant families with highest importance value in the zone are 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Burseraceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Sapindales" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="family">Burseraceae</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName box="[249,367,763,789]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Lauraceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Laurales" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="family">Lauraceae</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName box="[378,502,763,789]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Clusiaceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Malpighiales" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="family">Clusiaceae</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName box="[514,627,763,789]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Moraceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Rosales" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="family">Moraceae</taxonomicName>
, and 
<taxonomicName authority="(Ayala, 2011)" baseAuthorityName="Ayala" baseAuthorityYear="2011" box="[685,963,763,789]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Meliaceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Sapindales" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="family">Meliaceae (Ayala, 2011)</taxonomicName>
. The 
<typeStatus box="[1024,1122,763,789]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">holotype</typeStatus>
was caught on the left bank of the La San Guillerma stream, in an entomological pitfall trap baited with approximately 
<quantity box="[1164,1213,798,825]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="kg" metricValue="5.0" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="g" value="50.0">50 g</quantity>
of human feces and installed in a forest belt with abundant leaf litter and a canopy above 
<specimenCount box="[922,986,835,861]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" type="generic">
<quantity box="[922,982,835,861]" metricMagnitude="1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.0" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="m" value="20.0">20 m</quantity>
.
</specimenCount>
There, historical logging is evident, and the surrounding area has been transformed into crops (coffee) and pastures for livestock. The collected individual is a young adult male with no scrotal testis. Other small terrestrial mammals also were recorded in nearby forest, some of them comprising typical montane taxa: 
<taxonomicName authority=", Handleyomys" authorityName="Handleyomys" box="[694,1106,943,969]" class="Mammalia" family="Soricidae" genus="Cryptotis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Soricomorpha" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tamensis">
<emphasis box="[694,798,943,969]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Cryptotis</emphasis>
cf. 
<emphasis box="[842,1106,943,969]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">tamensis, Handleyomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
alfaroi, Heteromys australis, Marmosa (Micoureus) phaea, 
<taxonomicName authority=", Nephelomys" authorityName="Nephelomys" box="[497,870,979,1005]" class="Mammalia" family="Didelphidae" genus="Marmosops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Didelphimorphia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="caucae">Marmosops caucae, Nephelomys</taxonomicName>
childi, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Bangs" authorityYear="1900" box="[957,1113,979,1005]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Oligoryzomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Oligoryzomys</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
sp., 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1896" box="[1169,1430,979,1005]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Rhipidomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="fulviventer">
<emphasis box="[1169,1430,979,1005]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Rhipidomys fulviventer</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, and 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Thomas" baseAuthorityYear="1895" box="[199,433,1015,1041]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Thomasomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="laniger">
<emphasis box="[199,433,1015,1041]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Thomasomys laniger</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="14.[151,1437,150,2013]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
The second locality is at 
<quantity box="[475,567,1051,1077]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.124" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="m" value="2124.0">2,124 m</quantity>
on the eastern slope of the massif, the most intervened portion. The landscape is dominated by a mosaic of pastures with scarce fragments of secondary growth forest and corresponds with the lower montane moist forest life zone and the upper Andean orobiome (
<bibRefCitation author="Holdridge, L." box="[939,1128,1123,1149]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" refId="ref26643" refString="Holdridge, L. (2000) Ecologia basada en zonas de vida. Instituto Interamericano de Cooperacion para la Agricultura, San Jose, 219 pp." type="book" year="2000">Holdridge, 2000</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Diaz, M." box="[1139,1263,1123,1149]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" refId="ref25529" refString="Diaz, M. (2008) Parque Nacional Natural Serrania de los Yariguies, Plan de manejo. Informe tecnico. Parques Nacionales Naturales de Colombia, Bogota. Available from: http: // www. parquesnacionales. gov. co / PNN / portel / libreria / pdf / YariguesPM 2009. pdf (accessed 30 December 2020)" type="book" year="2008">Diaz, 2008</bibRefCitation>
) (
<figureCitation box="[1286,1373,1122,1149]" captionStart="FIGURE 5" captionStartId="13.[151,250,1655,1679]" captionTargetBox="[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetId="figure-162@13.[207,1380,489,1632]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 5. A) Montane forest habitat along the left Bank of the La San Guillerma stream, adjacent to the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. (municipality of El Carmen de Chucurí) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón) B) View of the forest remnant where the second specimen of Neacomys sp nov. was collected (municipality of Hato) (Photograph by Juliette Gualdrón). C) Topography of the western slope of the Serranía de los Yariguíes from the campsite “Finca Buenos Aires”; near the type locality of Neacomys sp. nov. D) Educational activity with members of the community in the municipality of El Carmen del Chucurí, Vereda la Bodega, Sector Manchurrias, illustrating the importance of government funded projects (like Santander BIO expeditions), not only to inventory the biodiversity of remote areas, but also to teach local people to preserve it." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491128" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491128/files/figure.png" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Fig. 5B</figureCitation>
). The climate also is characterized by a bimodal regime with the first peak of rains between April and July, and the second in September-October. November-March are the months with the lowest precipitation values, as well as August. The mean annual precipitation is 
<quantity box="[475,592,1230,1257]" metricMagnitude="0" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.503" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" unit="mm" value="1503.0">1,503 mm</quantity>
, whereas the mean annual temperature is 16.08 C° (
<bibRefCitation author="Fick, S. E. &amp; Himans, R. J." box="[1175,1425,1231,1257]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" pagination="4302 - 4315" refId="ref26042" refString="Fick, S. E. &amp;. Himans, R. J. (2017) WorldClim 2: new 1 km spatial resolution climate surfaces for global land areas. International Journal of Climatology, 37 (12), 4302 - 4315. https: // doi. org / 10.1002 / joc. 5086" type="journal article" year="2017">Fick &amp; Himans, 2017</bibRefCitation>
). The young specimen collected there was caught in a forest remnant along a small stream, in a pitfall trap baited with human feces. The surrounding area has been severely deforested and transformed into pastures for livestock that remain abandoned, which is evidenced by the presence of abundant ferns (genus 
<emphasis box="[1059,1176,1339,1365]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Pteridyum</emphasis>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="465" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="14.[151,1437,150,2013]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
<emphasis box="[199,353,1374,1401]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,328,1374,1401]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Etymology.</emphasis>
—
</emphasis>
the specific epithet harbors a double meaning. Firstly, it derives from the Spanish adjective 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">serrano</emphasis>
, from the sierra o serranía, as the species have only been recorded within the range of the Serranía de los Yariguíes, an important isolated massif that is part of the western slopes of the Cordillera Oriental of 
<collectingCountry box="[1319,1433,1447,1473]" name="Colombia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Colombia</collectingCountry>
. Secondly, it is a tribute to Victor Hugo Serrano Cardozo, Professor of the Universidad Industrial de 
<collectingRegion box="[1263,1377,1483,1509]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Santander</collectingRegion>
, who has supported for more than 20 years the study of the biodiversity in the Department of 
<collectingRegion box="[1124,1238,1519,1545]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Santander</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[1249,1363,1519,1545]" name="Colombia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Colombia</collectingCountry>
. Without his motivation, the discovering of this new species had not been possible.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="466" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="14.[151,1437,150,2013]" lastBlockId="15.[151,1436,151,321]" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="466" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
<emphasis box="[199,599,1591,1617]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,321,1591,1617]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
— 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[350,599,1591,1616]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">Neacomys serranensis</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[607,690,1591,1617]" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
is a small species within the genus 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1101,1216,1591,1616]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1101,1216,1591,1616]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
distinguished from other similar-sized congeners, especially from 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[682,809,1627,1652]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[682,809,1627,1652]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(the only other Trans-Andean species in 
<collectingCountry box="[1280,1392,1627,1654]" name="Colombia" pageId="14" pageNumber="465">Colombia</collectingCountry>
) by the following combination of characters: ventral fur superficially ochraceous-buff, with individual gray-based hairs from chin to anus (the same pattern in the inner surface of the arms and legs), sides of the muzzle (above the mouth) with distinctive broad patches of ochraceous-orange hairs, tail much longer than the combined length of head and body, with small caudal scales bearing long hairs (under magnification and at least at the terminal half), short rostrum, nasals short and expanded anteriorly, narrow zygomatic plate, very shallow zygomatic notches, long incisive foramina (in relation to diastema length), almost reaching the anterior alveolus of M1, maxillary with small perforations at the posterior border of the incisive foramina, dorsal margin of the tegmen tympani exposed above the ectotympanic dorsal margin (leaving to a smaller postglenoid foramen), dorsal margin of the ectotympanic not reaching the mastoid tubercle (leaving to an open ectotympanic ring), short and broad hamullar process of the squamosal, short subsquamosal foramen, wide oval orbicular apophysis with its longitudinal axis forming an almost right angle with the manubrium of malleus, paraoccipital process slightly bifurcated and situated well above the ventral margin of the occipital condyle, M1 with narrow and divided anterocone, principal labial cusps (paracone, metacone) smaller than lingual cusps (protocone, hypocone), mesoflexus divided into a short labial cleft and a broad triangular fossette that forms a prominent landmark in the center of the tooth, broad and distally bifurcated metaflexus, round and laterally positioned mental foramen, and broad coronoid process.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491132" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491132" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491132/files/figure.png" pageId="15" pageNumber="466" startId="15.[151,250,1328,1352]" targetBox="[151,1436,345,1305]" targetPageId="15">
<paragraph blockId="15.[151,1436,1328,1424]" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,274,1328,1352]" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">FIGURE 6.</emphasis>
Dorsal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1145,1249,1329,1352]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="15" pageNumber="466" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1145,1249,1329,1352]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
present in Colombia: A) Holotype of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[354,458,1365,1388]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="15" pageNumber="466" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[354,458,1365,1388]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[464,537,1364,1387]" pageId="15" pageNumber="466" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
(UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[799,993,1365,1388]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="15" pageNumber="466" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[799,993,1365,1388]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">Neacomys tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(UIS-MHN-M 1723); note that a portion of the tail is missing in this specimen.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<subSubSection lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="476" pageId="15" pageNumber="466" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="15.[151,1437,1470,2037]" lastBlockId="16.[151,1437,151,466]" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="467" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">
<emphasis box="[199,531,1470,1497]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,507,1470,1497]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">Morphological description</emphasis>
—
</emphasis>
A small sized species. The dorsal pelage has a general orange brownish appearance given by a mix of individual predominantly orange hairs (with a very narrow blackish tip), and black-tipped spines (
<figureCitation box="[236,331,1542,1568]" captionStart="FIGURE 6" captionStartId="15.[151,250,1328,1352]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,345,1305]" captionTargetId="figure-95@15.[151,1436,345,1305]" captionTargetPageId="15" captionText="FIGURE 6. Dorsal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723); note that a portion of the tail is missing in this specimen." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491132" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491132/files/figure.png" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">Figs. 6A</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation box="[384,415,1542,1568]" captionStart="FIGURE 12" captionStartId="21.[151,250,1615,1639]" captionTargetBox="[170,1417,345,1592]" captionTargetId="figure-92@21.[170,1417,345,1592]" captionTargetPageId="21" captionText="FIGURE 12. Illustration of Neacomys serranensis sp. nov. by wildlife artist and zoologist Velizar Simeonovski." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491146" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491146/files/figure.png" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">12</figureCitation>
). The brownish tint prevails in the middle of the back and the rump due to the concentration of black-tipped spines, while the paler orange tint prevails along the sides; most of the dorsal hairs and spines are grayish basally. The upper surface of the arms is covered by brown-grayish short hairs (some of them with a narrow buff-ochraceous tip) intermixed with buff-ochraceous hairs, which gives a general grayish appearance; the upper surface of the legs is similar to the adjacent parts of the dorsum. The ears are externally dark brown and scantily covered by dark-brownish and yellowish-orange short hairs; the region surrounding the external auditory meatus has a yellowish tint. The muzzle appears darker above (even more above the nose) due to the presence of entirely short black hairs. There are relatively broad orange-ochraceous patches in the sides of the muzzle (above the mouth) covering the area where the thickest mystacial vibrissae arise (
<figureCitation box="[878,971,1830,1856]" captionStart="FIGURE 7" captionStartId="16.[151,250,1901,1925]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,489,1878]" captionTargetId="figure-209@16.[151,1436,489,1878]" captionTargetPageId="16" captionText="FIGURE 7. Frontal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068); note the distinctive broad ochraceous-orange patches in the sides of the muzzle of this species. B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723)." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491134" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491134/files/figure.png" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">Fig. 7A</figureCitation>
). A clear narrow band, also ochraceousorange in color, delineates dorsal and ventral pelage. Ventral fur is superficially ochraceous-buff, with individual hairs grayish basally; the chin, the inguinal region, and the inner surface of the arms display a slightly paler tone (
<figureCitation box="[160,251,1938,1964]" captionStart="FIGURE 8" captionStartId="17.[151,250,1161,1185]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1137]" captionTargetId="figure-18@17.[151,1436,181,1137]" captionTargetPageId="17" captionText="FIGURE 8. Ventral perspectives of adult specimens illustrating the striking difference in ventral fur of the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) Section of the holotype of Neacomys sp. nov. showing its characteristic gray-based ochraceous-buff ventral fur. C) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723); note the contrasting entirely white ventral fur of this species." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491136" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491136/files/figure.png" pageId="15" pageNumber="466">Fig. 8A</figureCitation>
). The genal, superciliary, and mystacial vibrissae are long and extend beyond the posterior border of the pinnae. Dorsal surfaces of manus and pes are covered predominantly by short white hairs, but there are also white hairs with grayish-brown roots and entirely grayish brown hairs. Ungual manus tufts are whitish and do not pass the claws. Hind feet are small and narrow with six plantar pads; whitish ungual pedal tufts pass slightly the claws. Outer pedal digits are short, with the claw of the first digit reaching the second digit base, and the claw of the fifth digit extending approximately half length of the phalange 1 of adjacent fourth digit. Tail longer than the combined length of head and body (± 28% longer in the 
<typeStatus box="[676,778,259,286]" pageId="16" pageNumber="467">holotype</typeStatus>
), appearing dark brown dorsally but ventrally with a paler tone at the base. Relatively small caudal scales (20 per centimeter at the base of the holotype’s tail dorsal surface) are present, the dorsal ones bearing dark hairs and the ventral ones bearing paler (whitish) hairs. Tail upper hairs cover approximately the length of one scale at the first 1/3 of the total tail’s length, but in the remaining 2/3 they cover the length of one and a half scale; lower tail hairs are longer, covering more than the length of one scale (up to two scales) along the entire surface of the tail. There is an inconspicuous tuft of hairs at the tail’s tip.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491134" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491134" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491134/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="467" startId="16.[151,250,1901,1925]" targetBox="[151,1436,489,1878]" targetPageId="16">
<paragraph blockId="16.[151,1437,1901,1997]" pageId="16" pageNumber="467">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,274,1901,1925]" pageId="16" pageNumber="467">FIGURE 7.</emphasis>
Frontal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1146,1250,1902,1925]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="16" pageNumber="467" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1146,1250,1902,1925]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="467">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
present in Colombia: A) Holotype of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[357,461,1938,1961]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="16" pageNumber="467" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[357,461,1938,1961]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="467">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[468,541,1938,1961]" pageId="16" pageNumber="467" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
(UIS-MHN-M 1068); note the distinctive broad ochraceous-orange patches in the sides of the muzzle of this species. B) 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[483,678,1974,1997]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="16" pageNumber="467" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[483,678,1974,1997]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="467">Neacomys tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(UIS-MHN-M 1723).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491136" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491136" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491136/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" startId="17.[151,250,1161,1185]" targetBox="[151,1436,181,1137]" targetPageId="17">
<paragraph blockId="17.[151,1437,1161,1293]" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,275,1161,1185]" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">FIGURE 8.</emphasis>
Ventral perspectives of adult specimens illustrating the striking difference in ventral fur of the two Trans-Andean species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[259,363,1198,1221]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[259,363,1198,1221]" italics="true" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
present in Colombia: A) Holotype of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[750,854,1198,1221]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[750,854,1198,1221]" italics="true" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[861,934,1198,1221]" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
(UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) Section of the holotype of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[180,284,1234,1257]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[180,284,1234,1257]" italics="true" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[291,371,1234,1257]" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
showing its characteristic gray-based ochraceous-buff ventral fur. C) 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[1085,1281,1234,1257]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[1085,1281,1234,1257]" italics="true" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">Neacomys tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(UIS-MHN-M 1723); note the contrasting entirely white ventral fur of this species.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="17.[151,1437,1339,2014]" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">
Skull with relatively short rostrum flanked by shallow zygomatic notches (
<figureCitation box="[1033,1123,1339,1366]" captionStart="FIGURE 9" captionStartId="18.[151,250,1875,1899]" captionTargetBox="[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetId="figure-22@18.[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetPageId="18" captionText="FIGURE 9. Comparison of the dorsal and ventral views of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B), D) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note the nasals more expanded anteriorly, the shallower zygomatic notches, the less developed supraorbital ridges, the procingulum of M1 flattened laterally, and the incisive foramina extending almost to anterior alveolus of M1 in Neacomys sp. nov. if: incisive foramen; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; nas: nasal bone; sob: supraorbital beads; zn: zygomatic notch." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491138" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491138/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">Fig. 9A</figureCitation>
). Short nasal bones expanded anteriorly, with irregular almost squared posterior ends placed slightly beyond the premaxillary-maxilary-frontal, and maxillary-frontal-lacrimal sutures; there is a slight depression at the end of the nasal bones. Sutures between maxillary and frontal bones appear as large interdigitations. Lacrimals are conspicuous and irregular in form, having a wide portion in contact with maxillary, and a small portion with a spinous projection in its posterior borders in contact with frontals. Interorbital region hourglass in shape, with supraorbital beads weakly developed, dorsally oriented, and continuing onto braincase as low temporal crest (reaching the fronto-parietal joint). Braincase relatively wide and conspicuously inflated
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="17.[151,1437,1339,2014]" lastBlockId="20.[151,1437,1422,2025]" lastPageId="20" lastPageNumber="471" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">
In lateral profile the skull seems convex due to the globose braincase (
<figureCitation box="[1018,1124,1627,1654]" captionStart="FIGURE 10" captionStartId="19.[151,250,1873,1897]" captionTargetBox="[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetId="figure-18@19.[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetPageId="19" captionText="FIGURE 10. Comparison of the lateral profiles of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note a more convex profile of the braincase, a thicker hamular process of the squamosal, a broader condylar process, a larger and laterally projected mental foramen, and the anterior margin of nasals without a hump in Neacomys sp. nov. con: condylar process; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; mf: mental foramen; nas: nasals." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491142" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491142/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">Fig. 10A</figureCitation>
). The anterior edges of the nasals extend slightly beyond the rostral processes of premaxilla; gnathic process is short. Zygomatic plate is narrow and zygomatic notches indistinct; anterior border of plate relatively flat and placed slightly in front of anterior margin of superior maxillary root of zygoma; posterior margin of zygomatic plate situated anterior to the alveolus of M1. The infraorbital foramen is narrow (frontal view). The insertion of the superficial masseter is found at the inferior zygomatic root, slightly behind the anterior margin of the zygomatic plate. The sphenopalatine foramen is placed at the level of the metacone of M1. Alisphenoid strut is absent. The presence of a conspicuous sphenofrontal foramen and a squamosal-alisphenoid groove on each side, in conjunction with the presence of the stapedial foramen, indicate a primitive carotid circulation (pattern 1 of 
<bibRefCitation author="Voss, R. S." box="[796,921,1916,1942]" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" pagination="25 - 493" refId="ref29551" refString="Voss, R. S. (1988) Systematics and ecology of ichthyomyine rodents (Muroidea): patterns of morphological evolution in a small adaptative radiation. Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History, 188, 25 - 493." type="journal article" year="1988">Voss, 1988</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Carleton, M. D. &amp; Musser, G. G." box="[933,1221,1915,1942]" pageId="17" pageNumber="468" pagination="1 - 83" refId="ref24802" refString="Carleton, M. D. &amp; Musser, G. G. (1989) Systematics studies of Oryzomyine rodents (Muridae, Sigmodontinae): a synopsis of Microryzomys. Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History, 191, 1 - 83." type="journal article" year="1989">Carleton &amp; Musser, 1989</bibRefCitation>
). The hamular process of the squamosal is short but relatively thick and stout (
<figureCitation box="[815,922,1951,1978]" captionStart="FIGURE 10" captionStartId="19.[151,250,1873,1897]" captionTargetBox="[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetId="figure-18@19.[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetPageId="19" captionText="FIGURE 10. Comparison of the lateral profiles of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note a more convex profile of the braincase, a thicker hamular process of the squamosal, a broader condylar process, a larger and laterally projected mental foramen, and the anterior margin of nasals without a hump in Neacomys sp. nov. con: condylar process; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; mf: mental foramen; nas: nasals." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491142" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491142/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">Figs 10A</figureCitation>
, and 
<figureCitation box="[978,1007,1952,1978]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="468">11</figureCitation>
). Tegmen tympani is partially exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, acting as a membrane that partially covers the ventral portions of the subsquamosal and posglenoid foramina; tegmen tympani does not reach the posterior process of the squamosal (
<figureCitation box="[160,241,1458,1485]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">Fig. 11</figureCitation>
). Postglenoid foramen is relatively small and semicircular; the subsquamosal foramen is also small, shortened antero-posteriorly, and placed below the squamosal root of zygomatic arch. There is no contact between the anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic and the mastoid tubercle, which leads to an opened ectotympanic ring (
<figureCitation captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">Fig. 11</figureCitation>
). The orbicular apophysis of the malleus is wide and elongate (oval in shape), with its longitudinal axis forming an almost right angle with the manubrium (
<figureCitation box="[629,709,1602,1629]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">Fig. 11</figureCitation>
). Mastoid with a conspicuous but small dorsolateral fenestra. The paraoccipital process is small, robust, slightly bifurcated and placed close to the auditory bulla and well above the ventral margin of the occipital condyle.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491138" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491138" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491138/files/figure.png" pageId="18" pageNumber="469" startId="18.[151,250,1875,1899]" targetBox="[241,1347,181,1851]" targetPageId="18">
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,1875,2043]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,273,1875,1899]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">FIGURE 9.</emphasis>
Comparison of the dorsal and ventral views of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1118,1222,1876,1899]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="18" pageNumber="469" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1118,1222,1876,1899]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
present in Colombia: A), C) 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[220,324,1912,1935]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="18" pageNumber="469" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[220,324,1912,1935]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[329,407,1911,1934]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B), D) 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[804,997,1912,1935]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="18" pageNumber="469" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[804,997,1912,1935]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">Neacomys tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note the nasals more expanded anteriorly, the shallower zygomatic notches, the less developed supraorbital ridges, the procingulum of M1 flattened laterally, and the incisive foramina extending almost to anterior alveolus of M1 in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[990,1094,1984,2007]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="18" pageNumber="469" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[990,1094,1984,2007]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1101,1180,1983,2006]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1185,1210,1983,2007]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">if:</emphasis>
incisive foramen; 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">M1 prc:</emphasis>
procingulum of first upper molar; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[549,594,2019,2043]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">nas:</emphasis>
nasal bone; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[721,766,2019,2043]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">sob:</emphasis>
supraorbital beads; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[971,1005,2019,2043]" pageId="18" pageNumber="469">zn:</emphasis>
zygomatic notch.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491142" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491142" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491142/files/figure.png" pageId="19" pageNumber="470" startId="19.[151,250,1873,1897]" targetBox="[170,1417,181,1848]" targetPageId="19">
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1436,1873,2041]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,289,1873,1897]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">FIGURE 10.</emphasis>
Comparison of the lateral profiles of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1076,1180,1874,1897]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="19" pageNumber="470" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1076,1180,1874,1897]" italics="true" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
present in Colombia: A) 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,255,1910,1933]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="19" pageNumber="470" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[151,255,1910,1933]" italics="true" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[262,340,1909,1932]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B) 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[704,898,1910,1933]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="19" pageNumber="470" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[704,898,1910,1933]" italics="true" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">Neacomys tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note a more convex profile of the braincase, a thicker hamular process of the squamosal, a broader condylar process, a larger and laterally projected mental foramen, and the anterior margin of nasals without a hump in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[774,878,1982,2005]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="19" pageNumber="470" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[774,878,1982,2005]" italics="true" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[884,962,1981,2004]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[967,1014,1981,2005]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">con:</emphasis>
condylar process; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1203,1231,1981,2005]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">hp</emphasis>
: hamular process of the squamosal; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[309,347,2017,2041]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">mf:</emphasis>
mental foramen; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[526,571,2017,2041]" pageId="19" pageNumber="470">nas:</emphasis>
nasals.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="20" pageNumber="471" startId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" targetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" targetPageId="20">
<paragraph blockId="20.[151,1437,1136,1377]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,286,1136,1160]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">FIGURE 11.</emphasis>
Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1114,1218,1137,1160]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="20" pageNumber="471" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1114,1218,1137,1160]" italics="true" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
present in Colombia: A), C), E) 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[263,367,1173,1196]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="20" pageNumber="471" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[263,367,1173,1196]" italics="true" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[375,455,1173,1196]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
B), D), F) 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[572,687,1173,1196]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="20" pageNumber="471" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[572,589,1173,1196]" italics="true" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">N</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis box="[603,687,1173,1196]" italics="true" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1026,1061,1244,1268]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">ab:</emphasis>
auditory bullae; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1230,1299,1244,1268]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">adeect</emphasis>
: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[420,461,1280,1304]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">hyp</emphasis>
: hypoflexus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[601,637,1280,1304]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">hp:</emphasis>
hamular process of the squamosal; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1001,1089,1280,1304]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">M1 prc:</emphasis>
procingulum of first upper molar; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,202,1316,1340]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">mes:</emphasis>
mesoflexus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[337,387,1316,1340]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">met:</emphasis>
metaflexus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[518,556,1316,1340]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">mt:</emphasis>
mastoid tubercle; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[744,778,1316,1340]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">oa:</emphasis>
orbicular apophysis; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[998,1044,1316,1340]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">par:</emphasis>
paraflexus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1170,1214,1316,1340]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">pgf:</emphasis>
postglenoid foramen; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,188,1352,1376]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">pp:</emphasis>
paraoccipital process; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[421,467,1352,1376]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">pro:</emphasis>
protoflexus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[602,639,1352,1376]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">ssf:</emphasis>
subsquamosal fenestra; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[887,912,1352,1376]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">tt:</emphasis>
tegmen tympani.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="20.[151,1437,1422,2025]" lastBlockId="21.[151,1436,151,321]" lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="472" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">
The incisive foramina are moderately long (averaging about 65% of diastema length), with outer borders slightly curved and posteriorly convergent; their posterior margins extend almost to the anterior alveolus of M1 (
<figureCitation captionStart="FIGURE 9" captionStartId="18.[151,250,1875,1899]" captionTargetBox="[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetId="figure-22@18.[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetPageId="18" captionText="FIGURE 9. Comparison of the dorsal and ventral views of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B), D) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note the nasals more expanded anteriorly, the shallower zygomatic notches, the less developed supraorbital ridges, the procingulum of M1 flattened laterally, and the incisive foramina extending almost to anterior alveolus of M1 in Neacomys sp. nov. if: incisive foramen; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; nas: nasal bone; sob: supraorbital beads; zn: zygomatic notch." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491138" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491138/files/figure.png" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">Figs. 9B</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation box="[238,267,1783,1809]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">11</figureCitation>
). The premaxillary portion of the septum is slightly narrower than the maxillary portion. There are small perforations on the maxillary adjacent to the posterior margins of the incisive foramina. Relatively large and deep posterolateral palatal pits are placed posterior to M3, surrounding the anterior margin of the mesopterygoid fossa; at least in the 
<typeStatus box="[281,382,1890,1916]" pageId="20" pageNumber="471">holotype</typeStatus>
, there are two pits in one side and one in the other. Mesopterygoid fossa, which doesn´t reach the posterior end of M3, with wide M-shaped anterior margin (non-evident palatal spine). Irregular sphenopalatine vacuities are present around basisphenoid and presphenoid. The pterygoids are slightly convergent posteriorly; the parapterygoid fossae are shallow and triangular, with small irregularly distributed perforations but not evident fontanellae. Borders of the pterygoid plates are moderately curved. The posterior opening of the alisphenoid canal is oval, and its length is about M3 breadth. Auditory bullae small and flask-shaped, with the exposed flange of periotic extending to internal carotid canal; eustachian tube short and wide. Anterior bullae process is in contact with the posterior margin of the pterygoid plate. Anterior border of the foramen magnum is wide, with not conspicuous notch.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491146" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4491146" box="[151,1290,1615,1639]" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491146/files/figure.png" pageId="21" pageNumber="472" startId="21.[151,250,1615,1639]" targetBox="[170,1417,345,1592]" targetPageId="21">
<paragraph blockId="21.[151,1290,1615,1639]" box="[151,1290,1615,1639]" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,288,1615,1639]" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">FIGURE 12.</emphasis>
Illustration of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[439,666,1616,1639]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="21" pageNumber="472" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[439,666,1616,1639]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">Neacomys serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[673,751,1616,1639]" pageId="21" pageNumber="472" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
by wildlife artist and zoologist Velizar Simeonovski.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="21.[151,1437,1685,2036]" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">
Mandible with a wide and short condyle (
<figureCitation box="[680,787,1685,1711]" captionStart="FIGURE 10" captionStartId="19.[151,250,1873,1897]" captionTargetBox="[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetId="figure-18@19.[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetPageId="19" captionText="FIGURE 10. Comparison of the lateral profiles of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note a more convex profile of the braincase, a thicker hamular process of the squamosal, a broader condylar process, a larger and laterally projected mental foramen, and the anterior margin of nasals without a hump in Neacomys sp. nov. con: condylar process; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; mf: mental foramen; nas: nasals." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491142" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491142/files/figure.png" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">Fig. 10A</figureCitation>
). Thin, short, and claw-shaped coronoid process situated well anterior to the condyle, forming a u-shaped sigmoid notch. Masseteric crest placed below the protoconid of m1; capsular process forming a subtle rounded elevation that is placed slightly beyond the coronoid process. Mental foramen relatively large and laterally positioned.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="21.[151,1437,1685,2036]" lastBlockId="22.[151,1437,151,1978]" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="473" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">
Upper incisors are opisthodont, with rounded tips and pigmented anterior face (yellowish orange). Molar rows are parallel; principal labial cusps (paracone, metacone) smaller than lingual cusps (protocone, hypocone) (
<figureCitation captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">Fig. 11</figureCitation>
). First maxillary molar with narrow anterocone (which gives the tooth a general subtriangular appearance), divided by a weakly developed anteromedian flexus (only evident in the right M1 of the 
<typeStatus box="[1120,1220,1937,1964]" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">holotype</typeStatus>
) (
<figureCitation box="[1242,1338,1937,1963]" captionStart="FIGURE 9" captionStartId="18.[151,250,1875,1899]" captionTargetBox="[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetId="figure-22@18.[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetPageId="18" captionText="FIGURE 9. Comparison of the dorsal and ventral views of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B), D) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note the nasals more expanded anteriorly, the shallower zygomatic notches, the less developed supraorbital ridges, the procingulum of M1 flattened laterally, and the incisive foramina extending almost to anterior alveolus of M1 in Neacomys sp. nov. if: incisive foramen; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; nas: nasal bone; sob: supraorbital beads; zn: zygomatic notch." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491138" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491138/files/figure.png" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">Figs. 9B</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation box="[1392,1421,1937,1963]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="21" pageNumber="472">11</figureCitation>
); procingulum is anteriorly rounded. The anteroflexus does not reach the labial surface, and instead, is a relatively elongated internal fossette; the anteroloph is narrow, almost perpendicular to the longitudinal plane of the tooth and does not reach the labial surface. Paraflexus prominent, broad, long, and deep, divided distally by the intrusion of the protolophule. The mesoflexus is divided into a short labial cleft and a large internal fossette that forms a very prominent landmark in the center of the tooth. The mesoloph crosses the tooth diagonally and reaches the labial cingulum; it is relatively broad near the median mure, then gets compressed by the mesoflexus (labial cleft) but enlarges again when reaches the labial surface (at this zone, the mesoloph is almost perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the tooth). The metaflexus is also prominent, wide, long, deep, and “bifurcated” distally. The posteroflexus is a short internal fossette; posteroloph is moderately narrow and reaches the labial surface. The protoflexus and hypoflexus are very distinct and broad. M2 is approximately squared in occlusal outline; the anteroloph, mesoloph, and posteroloph are almost parallel (perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the tooth) and reach the labial surface. The paraflexus is narrow proximally (near the labial surface) but enlarges distally (in the middle of the tooth, near the anterior mure). The mesoflexus of M2 is divided and resembles that of M1, with a short labial cleft and a large internal fossette. The metaflexus is prominent and deep, while the posteroflexus is a short internal fossette. The protoflexus is indistinct, while the hypoflexus is clearly differentiated (deep and long). M3 is small, half the size of M2, and subtriangular; the anteroloph is short and straight. The paraflexus forms a continuous fold with a labial short element of the mesoflexus, surrounding the paracone; there is a distal (in the center of the tooth) element of the metaflexus forming a prominent internal fossete.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,1437,151,1978]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">In the lower dentition, the procingulum of m1 is narrow, which gives the tooth a general subtriangular appearance. The anteromedian flexid is almost indistinct, however, the anterolingual and anterolabial conulids are evident. There is no trace of the anteroflexid, and the anterolophid is fused with the anteroconid. The metaflexid is prominent and is fused with the mesoflexid, forming a deep and broad groove that surrounds the metaconid. The mesolophid is poorly developed and fused with the entoconid; the entoflexid does not reach the labial surface, and instead, it is reduced to a small internal fossette. The posteroflexid is prominent, deep, and very broad; the posterolophid is well developed and reaches the labial surface. The hypoflexid is divided by the ectostylid into an anterior broad and long element, and a posterior small cleft, both reaching the labial surface; the protoflexid also reaches the lingual surface and is remarkably broad. The anterolabial cingulum of m2 is well marked but slender, followed by a narrow, shallow, and not very long protoflexid. The mesoflexid is very broad, long, and slightly bifurcated on its anterior end; the mesolophid and the entoflexid are indistinguishable, fused with the entoconid. Contrary, the posteroflexid is prominent, deep and very broad; the posterolophid is evident and reaches the labial surface. The hypoflexid forms a prominent, deep and long basin on the tooth surface. On m3 the anterolabial cingulum is very narrow, and the protoflexid is indistinguishable. The protoconid, hypoconid, and metaconid are well defined, while the entoconid, as well as the mesolophid, are not evident. The mesoflexid is a semicircular, very prominent, and relatively deep fossette, contrary to the posteroflexid, which is a shallow, short and narrow element. The posterolophid is well defined. The hypoflexid is prominent, long, deep, and moderately broad.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,1437,151,1978]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">
<emphasis box="[199,501,1338,1365]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,476,1338,1365]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">
<typeStatus box="[199,303,1338,1365]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Holotype</typeStatus>
measurements
</emphasis>
—
</emphasis>
HBL: 80; LT: 102; HF: 20; Ear: 15.70; 
<collectionCode box="[937,986,1339,1365]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">CIL</collectionCode>
: 18.36; LD: 5.12; LM: 2.82; 
<collectionCode box="[1308,1360,1339,1365]" country="United Kingdom" name="Bristol Museum" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">BM</collectionCode>
1: 0.91; 
<collectionCode box="[151,197,1375,1401]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">LIF</collectionCode>
: 3.11; 
<collectionCode box="[271,319,1375,1401]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">BIF</collectionCode>
: 1.57; 
<collectionCode box="[393,450,1375,1401]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">BPB</collectionCode>
: 2.19; 
<collectionCode box="[524,580,1375,1401]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">BZP</collectionCode>
: 1.65; LR: 6.3; LN: 7.56; LIB: 4.32; 
<collectionCode box="[994,1035,1375,1401]" country="0" name="Buffalo Bill Museum" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">BB</collectionCode>
: 10.4; ZB: 10.95; Wt: 14 (
<tableCitation box="[1329,1413,1375,1401]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="6.[151,239,1304,1328]" captionText="TABLE 1. External and craniodental measurements of adult specimens of most of the small-bodied species of Neacomys, including the taxon described here. Weigh (Wt) is given in grams and the measurements are in millimeters. Mean and Standard Deviation (above), observed range (middle), and sample size (below, in parenthesis). High Body Length (HBL), Tail Length (TL), Hind Foot Length (HF), and Ear Length (Ear). Condylo-incisive Length (CIL); Length of Diastema (LD); Length of Molars (LM); Breadth of M1 (BM1); Length of Incisive Foramen (LIF); Breadth of Incisive Foramen (BIF); Breadth of Palatal Bridge (BPB); Breadth of Zygomatic Plate (BZP); Length of Rostrum (LR); Length of Nasals (LN); Least Interorbital Breadth (LIB); Breadth of Braincase (BB); Zygomatic Breadth (ZB)." pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Table 1</tableCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,1437,151,1978]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,380,1411,1437]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,351,1411,1437]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Comparisons</emphasis>
—
</emphasis>
There are only two species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[719,834,1411,1436]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[719,834,1411,1436]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
confirmed for 
<collectingCountry box="[1004,1119,1411,1437]" name="Colombia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Colombia</collectingCountry>
: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1129,1151,1411,1437]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">a.</emphasis>
The first of them, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1882" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="spinosus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. spinosus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, have been reported from the departments of 
<collectingRegion box="[721,779,1447,1473]" country="Colombia" name="Meta" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Meta</collectingRegion>
and 
<collectingRegion box="[831,915,1447,1473]" country="Colombia" name="Vaupes" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Vaupés</collectingRegion>
, in the Amazonian lowlands east of the Cordillera Oriental (Cis-Andean) (
<bibRefCitation author="Solari, S. &amp; Munoz-Saba, Y. &amp; Rodriguez-Mahecha, J. V. &amp; Defler, T. R. &amp; Ramirez-Chaves, H. E. &amp; Trujillo, F." box="[464,668,1483,1509]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" pagination="301 - 365" refId="ref29175" refString="Solari, S., Munoz-Saba, Y., Rodriguez-Mahecha, J. V., Defler, T. R., Ramirez-Chaves, H. E. &amp; Trujillo, F. (2013) Riqueza, endemismo y conservacion de los mamiferos de Colombia. Mastozoologia Neotropical, 20 (2), 301 - 365." type="journal article" year="2013">
Solari 
<emphasis box="[538,587,1483,1509]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">et al</emphasis>
., 2013
</bibRefCitation>
). However, the taxonomical identity of these populations is uncertain according to the work of 
<bibRefCitation author="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V." box="[433,739,1519,1545]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" pagination="401 - 440" refId="ref27021" refString="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V. (2017) Revision of Neacomys spinosus (Thomas, 1882) (Rodentia: Cricetidae) with emphasis on Peruvian populations and the description of a new species. Zootaxa, 4242 (3), 401 - 440. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 4242.3.1" type="journal article" year="2017">Hurtado &amp; Pacheco (2017)</bibRefCitation>
. These authors found remarkable genetical and morphological structure between different populations of 
<taxonomicName box="[630,749,1555,1580]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="spinous">
<emphasis box="[630,749,1555,1580]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. spinous</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, recognizing at least three well discretized taxa: 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1882" box="[1300,1432,1555,1580]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="spinosus">N. spinosus</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Hurtado &amp; Pacheco" authorityYear="2017" box="[151,322,1591,1617]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="vargasllosai">N. vargasllosai</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
, and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1903" box="[386,520,1591,1616]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="amoenus">
<emphasis box="[386,520,1591,1616]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. amoenus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. Relying on the distributional data provided in their work, but without the direct inspection of voucher specimens, it is possible to hypothesize that the Cis-Andean species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1204,1319,1627,1652]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1204,1319,1627,1652]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
present in 
<collectingCountry box="[151,261,1663,1689]" name="Colombia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Colombia</collectingCountry>
is 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1903" box="[292,424,1663,1688]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="amoenus">
<emphasis box="[292,424,1663,1688]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. amoenus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(subspecies 
<emphasis box="[565,726,1663,1689]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
), and not 
<emphasis box="[837,973,1663,1688]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1882" box="[837,969,1663,1688]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="spinosus">N. spinosus</taxonomicName>
.
</emphasis>
Despite of the notably allopatric distribution between 
<emphasis box="[302,466,1699,1725]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[520,682,1699,1724]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[520,682,1699,1724]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[689,771,1699,1725]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
, is important to mention that both taxa are morphologically and morphometrically well differentiated; 
<emphasis box="[633,800,1735,1761]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
belongs to the monophyletic large-bodied group within the genus (
<bibRefCitation author="Sanchez-Vendizu, P. &amp; Pacheco, V. &amp; Vivas-Ruiz, D." box="[274,608,1771,1797]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" pagination="1 - 38" refId="ref28867" refString="Sanchez-Vendizu, P., Pacheco, V. &amp; Vivas-Ruiz, D. (2018) An introduction to the systematics of small-bodied Neacomys (Rodentia: Cricetidae) from Peru with descriptions of two new species. American Museum Novitates, 3913, 1 - 38. https: // doi. org / 10.1206 / 3913.1" type="journal article" year="2018">
Sánchez-Vendizú 
<emphasis box="[478,528,1771,1797]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">et al</emphasis>
., 2018
</bibRefCitation>
) (
<figureCitation box="[631,699,1771,1797]" captionStart="FIGURE 3" captionStartId="9.[151,250,1528,1552]" captionTargetBox="[189,1394,181,1503]" captionTargetId="figure-18@9.[189,1398,181,1503]" captionTargetPageId="9" captionText="FIGURE 3. Bayesian Inference topology based on Cytb sequence data used to assess the position of Neacomys sp. nov. in relation to other species in the genus (BI and ML analyses resulted in congruent topologies). Support values are indicated for each node (Bayesian posterior probabilities to the left, and percentages of 1,000 bootstrap replicates to the right). Each terminal is identified by country of origin, the next largest political unit, and GenBank accession number (in red). For specimens of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov. sequenced here, collection numbers are provided, as well as a number referring to localities mapped in FIGURE 2 and listed in Appendix I. Shaded colored boxes enclose the species groups proposed by Hurtado &amp; Pacheco (2017) and Semedo et al. (2020). Abbreviations: BO (Bolivia), BR (Brazil), CO (Colombia), EC (Ecuador), FG (French Guyana), GU (Guyana), PE (Peru), and SU (Suriname)." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491124" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491124/files/figure.png" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Fig. 3</figureCitation>
) and its external and craniodental dimensions exceed those of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[290,374,1807,1833]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
, which belongs to the non-monophyletic small bodied group (e.g. HF = 23.25 vs. 20; 
<collectionCode box="[1367,1411,1807,1833]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">CIL</collectionCode>
= 21.78 vs. 18.36; LM = 3.20 vs. 2.82) (
<bibRefCitation author="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V." box="[575,872,1843,1869]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" pagination="401 - 440" refId="ref27021" refString="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V. (2017) Revision of Neacomys spinosus (Thomas, 1882) (Rodentia: Cricetidae) with emphasis on Peruvian populations and the description of a new species. Zootaxa, 4242 (3), 401 - 440. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 4242.3.1" type="journal article" year="2017">Hurtado &amp; Pacheco, 2017</bibRefCitation>
). Whereas 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[994,1156,1843,1868]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[994,1156,1843,1868]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1163,1243,1843,1869]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
has a gray-based ochraceous-buff ventral fur, in 
<emphasis box="[503,668,1879,1905]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
the ventral coloration is completely white (
<tableCitation box="[1163,1251,1879,1905]" captionStart="TABLE 3" captionStartId="23.[151,239,152,176]" captionText="TABLE 3. Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of Neacomys, Part I" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">Table 3</tableCitation>
). The muzzle of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,312,1915,1940]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[151,312,1915,1940]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[318,398,1915,1941]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
is also distinctive, with the presence of broad orange-ochraceous patches on each side (above the mouth) that have not been noted in specimens of 
<emphasis box="[744,907,1951,1977]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="473">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V." box="[922,1220,1951,1977]" pageId="22" pageNumber="473" pagination="401 - 440" refId="ref27021" refString="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V. (2017) Revision of Neacomys spinosus (Thomas, 1882) (Rodentia: Cricetidae) with emphasis on Peruvian populations and the description of a new species. Zootaxa, 4242 (3), 401 - 440. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 4242.3.1" type="journal article" year="2017">Hurtado &amp; Pacheco, 2017</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<caption box="[151,1099,152,177]" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1099,152,177]" box="[151,1099,152,177]" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,266,152,176]" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">TABLE 3.</emphasis>
Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of 
<taxonomicName authority=", Part I" box="[917,1099,153,176]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[917,1034,153,176]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Neacomys,</emphasis>
Part I
</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<table box="[163,1424,194,1969]" gridcols="7" gridrows="18" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<tr box="[163,1424,194,244]" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,194,244]" gridcol="0" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Characters</th>
<th box="[325,500,194,244]" gridcol="1" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[359,470,194,215]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp.nov.">
<emphasis box="[359,470,194,215]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[381,449,223,244]" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" rank="species">sp.nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</th>
<th box="[527,713,194,244]" gridcol="2" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[581,661,209,230]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[581,661,209,230]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th box="[737,893,194,244]" gridcol="3" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1903" box="[773,858,194,215]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="amoenus">amoenus</taxonomicName>
carceleni
</emphasis>
a
</th>
<th box="[918,1075,194,244]" gridcol="4" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<taxonomicName box="[944,1046,208,229]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="rosalindae">
<emphasis box="[944,1046,208,229]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">rosalindae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
b
</th>
<th box="[1101,1254,194,244]" gridcol="5" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<taxonomicName box="[1120,1239,208,229]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="macedoruizi">
<emphasis box="[1120,1239,208,229]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">macedoruizi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
b
</th>
<th box="[1287,1424,194,244]" gridcol="6" gridrow="0" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<taxonomicName box="[1311,1387,209,230]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="minutus">
<emphasis box="[1311,1387,209,230]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">minutus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
bc
</th>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,262,372]" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,262,372]" gridcol="0" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Tail</th>
<td box="[325,500,262,372]" gridcol="1" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">distinctly longer than HB; bicolored at the base</td>
<td box="[527,713,262,372]" gridcol="2" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">distinctly longer than HB; bicolored at the base</td>
<td box="[737,893,262,372]" gridcol="3" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">subequal to HB</td>
<td box="[918,1075,262,372]" gridcol="4" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">slightly longer than HB</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,262,372]" gridcol="5" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">slightly longer than HB</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,262,372]" gridcol="6" gridrow="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">slightly longer than HB</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,390,470]" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,390,470]" gridcol="0" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Ventral fur color</th>
<td box="[325,500,390,470]" gridcol="1" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">gray-based ochraceous-buff</td>
<td box="[527,713,390,470]" gridcol="2" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">completely white to pale orange</td>
<td box="[737,893,390,470]" gridcol="3" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">completely white</td>
<td box="[918,1075,390,470]" gridcol="4" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">completely white or slightly buffy</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,390,470]" gridcol="5" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">completely white</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,390,470]" gridcol="6" gridrow="2" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">completely white</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,488,598]" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,488,598]" gridcol="0" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Muzzle</th>
<td box="[325,500,488,598]" gridcol="1" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">With broad ochraceous- orange patches on each side</td>
<td box="[527,713,488,598]" gridcol="2" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">inconspicuous and very narrow patches</td>
<td box="[737,893,488,598]" gridcol="3" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">inconspicuous patches</td>
<td box="[918,1075,488,598]" gridcol="4" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">inconspicuous patches</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,488,598]" gridcol="5" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">inconspicuous patches</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,488,598]" gridcol="6" gridrow="3" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">inconspicuous patches</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,615,637]" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,615,637]" gridcol="0" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Rostrum</th>
<td box="[325,500,615,637]" gridcol="1" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">short</td>
<td box="[527,713,615,637]" gridcol="2" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">long</td>
<td box="[737,893,615,637]" gridcol="3" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
<td box="[918,1075,615,637]" gridcol="4" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">short</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,615,637]" gridcol="5" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">long</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,615,637]" gridcol="6" gridrow="4" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">long</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,654,764]" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,654,764]" gridcol="0" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Nasal bones</th>
<td box="[325,500,654,764]" gridcol="1" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">expanded anteriorly</td>
<td box="[527,713,654,764]" gridcol="2" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">narrow anteriorly; hooked-shaped anteriorly in lateral view</td>
<td box="[737,893,654,764]" gridcol="3" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
<td box="[918,1075,654,764]" gridcol="4" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">narrow anteriorly</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,654,764]" gridcol="5" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">expanded anteriorly</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,654,764]" gridcol="6" gridrow="5" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">narrow anteriorly</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,781,979]" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,781,979]" gridcol="0" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Interorbital region</th>
<td box="[325,500,781,979]" gridcol="1" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">hourglass- shaped; weakly convergent anteriorly; supraorbital beads weakly developed</td>
<td box="[527,713,781,979]" gridcol="2" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
hourglass-shaped; weakly convergent anteriorly; supraorbital beads weakly developed, but more than in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[527,638,958,979]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis">
<emphasis box="[527,638,958,979]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</td>
<td box="[737,893,781,979]" gridcol="3" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">weakly convergent anteriorly; supraorbital beads well developed</td>
<td box="[918,1075,781,979]" gridcol="4" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">hourglass- shaped; weakly convergent anteriorly; supraorbital beads well developed</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,781,979]" gridcol="5" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">strongly convergent anteriorly; strongly convergent anteriorly</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,781,979]" gridcol="6" gridrow="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">strongly convergent anteriorly; strongly convergent anteriorly</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,997,1048]" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,997,1048]" gridcol="0" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Dorsal profile of skull</th>
<td box="[325,500,997,1048]" gridcol="1" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">convex</td>
<td box="[527,713,997,1048]" gridcol="2" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">flat</td>
<td box="[737,893,997,1048]" gridcol="3" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">flat</td>
<td box="[918,1075,997,1048]" gridcol="4" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">convex</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,997,1048]" gridcol="5" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">convex</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,997,1048]" gridcol="6" gridrow="7" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">flat</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1065,1146]" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1065,1146]" gridcol="0" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Carotid circulatory pattern</th>
<td box="[325,500,1065,1146]" gridcol="1" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">primitive (pattern 1)</td>
<td box="[527,713,1065,1146]" gridcol="2" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">primitive (pattern 1)</td>
<td box="[737,893,1065,1146]" gridcol="3" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">primitive (pattern 1)</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1065,1146]" gridcol="4" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">primitive (pattern 1)</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1065,1146]" gridcol="5" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">primitive (pattern 1)</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1065,1146]" gridcol="6" gridrow="8" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">primitive (pattern 1)</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1163,1215]" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1163,1215]" gridcol="0" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Ectotympanic ring</th>
<td box="[325,500,1163,1215]" gridcol="1" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">opened</td>
<td box="[527,713,1163,1215]" gridcol="2" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">closed</td>
<td box="[737,893,1163,1215]" gridcol="3" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">closed</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1163,1215]" gridcol="4" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1163,1215]" gridcol="5" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1163,1215]" gridcol="6" gridrow="9" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1232,1313]" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1232,1313]" gridcol="0" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Postglenoid foramen</th>
<td box="[325,500,1232,1313]" gridcol="1" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">small and semicircular</td>
<td box="[527,713,1232,1313]" gridcol="2" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Large, with anterior margin bilobate</td>
<td box="[737,893,1232,1313]" gridcol="3" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">rounded</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1232,1313]" gridcol="4" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">large and semicircular</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1232,1313]" gridcol="5" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">large</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1232,1313]" gridcol="6" gridrow="10" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">large and semicircular</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1330,1381]" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1330,1381]" gridcol="0" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Subsquamosal fenestra</th>
<td box="[325,500,1330,1381]" gridcol="1" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">small</td>
<td box="[527,713,1330,1381]" gridcol="2" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">large</td>
<td box="[737,893,1330,1381]" gridcol="3" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1330,1381]" gridcol="4" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">small</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1330,1381]" gridcol="5" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">conspicuously large</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1330,1381]" gridcol="6" gridrow="11" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">large</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1399,1450]" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1399,1450]" gridcol="0" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Hamular process</th>
<td box="[325,500,1399,1450]" gridcol="1" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">thick and stout</td>
<td box="[527,713,1399,1450]" gridcol="2" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">slender</td>
<td box="[737,893,1399,1450]" gridcol="3" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">thick</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1399,1450]" gridcol="4" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">stout</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1399,1450]" gridcol="5" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">slender</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1399,1450]" gridcol="6" gridrow="12" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">slender</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1467,1577]" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1467,1577]" gridcol="0" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Posterior margins of incisive foramina</th>
<td box="[325,500,1467,1577]" gridcol="1" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">almost reaching alveolus of M1</td>
<td box="[527,713,1467,1577]" gridcol="2" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Evident gap between them and the alveolus of M1</td>
<td box="[737,893,1467,1577]" gridcol="3" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Evident gap between them and the alveolus of M1</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1467,1577]" gridcol="4" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Evident gap between them and the alveolus of M1</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1467,1577]" gridcol="5" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">almost reaching alveolus of M1</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1467,1577]" gridcol="6" gridrow="13" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">almost reaching alveolus of M1</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1595,1646]" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1595,1646]" gridcol="0" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Molar rows</th>
<td box="[325,500,1595,1646]" gridcol="1" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">parallel</td>
<td box="[527,713,1595,1646]" gridcol="2" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">parallel</td>
<td box="[737,893,1595,1646]" gridcol="3" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">posteriorly convergent</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1595,1646]" gridcol="4" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">parallel</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1595,1646]" gridcol="5" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">parallel</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1595,1646]" gridcol="6" gridrow="14" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">parallel</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1663,1832]" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1663,1832]" gridcol="0" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">M1 anterocone</th>
<td box="[325,500,1663,1832]" gridcol="1" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">narrow and rounded, weakly divided by an anteromedian flexus</td>
<td box="[527,713,1663,1832]" gridcol="2" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">broad, rounded or relatively flat, strongly divided by an anteromedian flexus</td>
<td box="[737,893,1663,1832]" gridcol="3" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Broad, rounded</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1663,1832]" gridcol="4" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">broad, rounded, weakly divided by an anteromedian flexus</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1663,1832]" gridcol="5" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">narrow and relatively flat, strongly divided by an anteromedian flexus</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1663,1832]" gridcol="6" gridrow="15" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">broad, relatively flat, weakly divided by an anteromedian flexus</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1849,1900]" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1849,1900]" gridcol="0" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Condylar process</th>
<td box="[325,500,1849,1900]" gridcol="1" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">broad</td>
<td box="[527,713,1849,1900]" gridcol="2" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">thin</td>
<td box="[737,893,1849,1900]" gridcol="3" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">broad</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1849,1900]" gridcol="4" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">relatively broad</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1849,1900]" gridcol="5" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">relatively broad</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1849,1900]" gridcol="6" gridrow="16" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
</tr>
<tr box="[163,1424,1918,1969]" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<th box="[163,302,1918,1969]" gridcol="0" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Mental foramen</th>
<td box="[325,500,1918,1969]" gridcol="1" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">large, laterally oriented</td>
<td box="[527,713,1918,1969]" gridcol="2" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">small, dorsally oriented</td>
<td box="[737,893,1918,1969]" gridcol="3" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Large, dorsally oriented</td>
<td box="[918,1075,1918,1969]" gridcol="4" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">small, dorsally oriented</td>
<td box="[1101,1254,1918,1969]" gridcol="5" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">small, dorsally oriented</td>
<td box="[1287,1424,1918,1969]" gridcol="6" gridrow="17" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">-</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<tableNote pageId="23" pageNumber="474" targetBox="[163,1424,194,1969]" targetPageId="23">
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1436,1982,2043]" box="[151,1436,1982,2007]" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">
<superScript attach="left" box="[151,158,1982,1996]" fontSize="6" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">a</superScript>
<taxonomicName authorityName="Hershkovitz" authorityYear="1940" box="[165,396,1983,2007]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="subSpecies" species="amoenus" subSpecies="carceleni">
<emphasis box="[165,396,1983,2007]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">N. amoenus carceleni</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
belongs to the monophyletic large-bodied group of 
<taxonomicName box="[952,1062,1984,2007]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="23" pageNumber="474" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[952,1062,1984,2007]" italics="true" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. It was included here only because
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1436,1982,2043]" box="[151,1436,2019,2043]" pageId="23" pageNumber="474">is one of the two species of the genus present in Colombia (Cis-Andean), so, was considered as important for comparative</paragraph>
</tableNote>
<tableNote pageId="24" pageNumber="475">
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1436,151,284]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">
purposes with the new species. Morphological and morphometric information of this species was retrieved from 
<bibRefCitation author="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V." pageId="24" pageNumber="475" pagination="401 - 440" refId="ref27021" refString="Hurtado, N. &amp; Pacheco, V. (2017) Revision of Neacomys spinosus (Thomas, 1882) (Rodentia: Cricetidae) with emphasis on Peruvian populations and the description of a new species. Zootaxa, 4242 (3), 401 - 440. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 4242.3.1" type="journal article" year="2017">Hurtado &amp; Pacheco (2017)</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1436,151,284]" box="[151,1173,222,248]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">
<superScript attach="left" box="[151,159,222,236]" fontSize="6" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">b</superScript>
Morphological information of these species was retrieved from 
<bibRefCitation author="Sanchez-Vendizu, P. &amp; Pacheco, V. &amp; Vivas-Ruiz, D." box="[843,1169,223,248]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" pagination="1 - 38" refId="ref28867" refString="Sanchez-Vendizu, P., Pacheco, V. &amp; Vivas-Ruiz, D. (2018) An introduction to the systematics of small-bodied Neacomys (Rodentia: Cricetidae) from Peru with descriptions of two new species. American Museum Novitates, 3913, 1 - 38. https: // doi. org / 10.1206 / 3913.1" type="journal article" year="2018">
Sánchez-Vendizú 
<emphasis box="[1034,1088,223,247]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">et al.</emphasis>
(2018)
</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1436,151,284]" box="[151,1206,258,284]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">
<superScript attach="left" box="[151,158,258,272]" fontSize="6" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">c</superScript>
Part of the morphological information of this species also was retrieved from 
<bibRefCitation author="Patton, J. L. &amp; da Silva, M. N. F. &amp; Malcolm, J. R." box="[993,1202,259,284]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" pagination="1 - 306" refId="ref28166" refString="Patton, J. L., da Silva, M. N. F. &amp; Malcolm, J. R. (2000) Mammals of the Rio Jurua and the evolutionary and ecological diversification of Amazonia. Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History, 244, 1 - 306. https: // doi. org / 10.1206 / 0003 - 0090 (2000) 244 % 3 C 0001: MOTRJA % 3 E 2.0. CO; 2" type="journal article" year="2000">
Patton 
<emphasis box="[1067,1114,259,283]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">et al</emphasis>
. (2000)
</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</tableNote>
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1437,330,2012]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">
The lateral profile of the skull allows to discriminate between both species, being flat in 
<emphasis box="[1219,1387,330,356]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
and convex in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[269,432,367,392]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[269,432,367,392]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[440,527,366,392]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
due to its globose braincase; also, unlike 
<emphasis box="[1001,1166,366,392]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
, the tegmen tympani of the new species is not in contact with the posterior process of the squamosal. In ventral view, the most important differences between both species are probably at the level of the molar rows: these are parallelly oriented in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[255,345,474,500]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, with anteriorly narrowed first molars, whereas in 
<emphasis box="[923,1090,474,500]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
they converge posteriorly and bear anteriorly rounded first molars. The mesoflexus of M1 and M2 are very distinctive in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1173,1335,511,536]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[1173,1335,511,536]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1343,1432,510,536]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, divided in a short labial cleft and a large internal fossette which are not present in upper molars of 
<emphasis box="[1271,1436,546,572]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. a. carceleni</emphasis>
nor in any other species within the genus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1437,330,2012]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,222,618,644]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">b.</emphasis>
The other species of 
<taxonomicName box="[457,572,619,644]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[457,572,619,644]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Neacomys</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
distributed in 
<collectingCountry box="[731,841,618,644]" name="Colombia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Colombia</collectingCountry>
is 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[872,997,619,644]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[872,997,619,644]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
; according to 
<bibRefCitation author="Solari, S. &amp; Munoz-Saba, Y. &amp; Rodriguez-Mahecha, J. V. &amp; Defler, T. R. &amp; Ramirez-Chaves, H. E. &amp; Trujillo, F." box="[1155,1366,618,644]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" pagination="301 - 365" refId="ref29175" refString="Solari, S., Munoz-Saba, Y., Rodriguez-Mahecha, J. V., Defler, T. R., Ramirez-Chaves, H. E. &amp; Trujillo, F. (2013) Riqueza, endemismo y conservacion de los mamiferos de Colombia. Mastozoologia Neotropical, 20 (2), 301 - 365." type="journal article" year="2013">
Solari 
<emphasis box="[1228,1276,618,644]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">et al</emphasis>
. (2013)
</bibRefCitation>
, Weksler &amp; Bovicino (2015), and 
<bibRefCitation author="Sanchez-Vendizu, P. &amp; Pacheco, V. &amp; Vivas-Ruiz, D." box="[478,821,654,680]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" pagination="1 - 38" refId="ref28867" refString="Sanchez-Vendizu, P., Pacheco, V. &amp; Vivas-Ruiz, D. (2018) An introduction to the systematics of small-bodied Neacomys (Rodentia: Cricetidae) from Peru with descriptions of two new species. American Museum Novitates, 3913, 1 - 38. https: // doi. org / 10.1206 / 3913.1" type="journal article" year="2018">
Sánchez-Vendizú 
<emphasis box="[681,731,654,680]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">et al</emphasis>
. (2018)
</bibRefCitation>
it has been reported west of the Cordillera Oriental in the departments of 
<collectingRegion box="[362,477,690,716]" country="Colombia" name="Antioquia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Antioquia</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[487,574,690,716]" country="Colombia" name="Boyaca" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Boyacá</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[584,663,690,716]" country="Colombia" name="Caldas" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Caldas</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[674,747,690,716]" country="Colombia" name="Cauca" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Cauca</collectingRegion>
, Chocó, 
<collectingRegion box="[843,1009,690,716]" country="Colombia" name="Cundinamarca" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Cundinamarca</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[1019,1100,690,716]" country="Colombia" name="Narino" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Nariño</collectingRegion>
, and 
<collectingRegion box="[1156,1333,690,716]" country="Colombia" name="Valle del Cauca" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Valle del Cauca</collectingRegion>
, between 5 and 
<quantity box="[220,315,726,753]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.75" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" unit="m" value="1750.0">1,750 m</quantity>
. In the context of the present work, the species is also recorded from the departments of Bolívar (
<quantity metricMagnitude="1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="9.3" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" unit="m" value="93.0">93 m</quantity>
; 
<quantity box="[187,258,762,789]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.05" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" unit="m" value="105.0">105 m</quantity>
) and 
<collectingRegion box="[318,430,762,788]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Santander</collectingRegion>
(
<quantity box="[444,537,762,788]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.091" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" unit="m" value="1091.0">1,091 m</quantity>
) (
<figureCitation box="[559,628,762,788]" captionStart="FIGURE 2" captionStartId="4.[151,250,1538,1562]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,597,1514]" captionTargetId="figure-219@4.[151,1436,597,1514]" captionTargetPageId="4" captionText="FIGURE 2. Map showing collection localities of the named and unamed small-bodied species of Neacomys (except N. pictus) along with salient topographic features of northern South America. Localities of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov are numbered according to Appendix I. Localities of the remaining species are detailed in Voss et al. (2001), Sánchez-Vendizú et al. (2018), and Semedo et al. (2020). Miniature in the right side of the map corresponds to the Bayesian Cytb phylogeny recovered here (FIGURE 3): species in the map and phylogeny are same colored; the numbers in some nodes correspond to the median divergence times estimated by Upham et al. (2019) within Neacomys." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491122" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491122/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Fig. 2</figureCitation>
; Appendix I). Although 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[895,1020,763,788]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[895,1020,763,788]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1072,1233,763,788]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[1072,1233,763,788]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1239,1319,762,788]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
are Trans-Andean species, and have even been reported in localities distanced by no more than 60 Km (linear) (
<figureCitation box="[1296,1365,798,824]" captionStart="FIGURE 2" captionStartId="4.[151,250,1538,1562]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,597,1514]" captionTargetId="figure-219@4.[151,1436,597,1514]" captionTargetPageId="4" captionText="FIGURE 2. Map showing collection localities of the named and unamed small-bodied species of Neacomys (except N. pictus) along with salient topographic features of northern South America. Localities of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov are numbered according to Appendix I. Localities of the remaining species are detailed in Voss et al. (2001), Sánchez-Vendizú et al. (2018), and Semedo et al. (2020). Miniature in the right side of the map corresponds to the Bayesian Cytb phylogeny recovered here (FIGURE 3): species in the map and phylogeny are same colored; the numbers in some nodes correspond to the median divergence times estimated by Upham et al. (2019) within Neacomys." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491122" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491122/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Fig. 2</figureCitation>
), both are clearly differentiable by means of discrete characters, and to a lesser extent by some measurements (
<tableCitation box="[1307,1402,834,860]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="6.[151,239,1304,1328]" captionText="TABLE 1. External and craniodental measurements of adult specimens of most of the small-bodied species of Neacomys, including the taxon described here. Weigh (Wt) is given in grams and the measurements are in millimeters. Mean and Standard Deviation (above), observed range (middle), and sample size (below, in parenthesis). High Body Length (HBL), Tail Length (TL), Hind Foot Length (HF), and Ear Length (Ear). Condylo-incisive Length (CIL); Length of Diastema (LD); Length of Molars (LM); Breadth of M1 (BM1); Length of Incisive Foramen (LIF); Breadth of Incisive Foramen (BIF); Breadth of Palatal Bridge (BPB); Breadth of Zygomatic Plate (BZP); Length of Rostrum (LR); Length of Nasals (LN); Least Interorbital Breadth (LIB); Breadth of Braincase (BB); Zygomatic Breadth (ZB)." pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Tables 1</tableCitation>
, 
<tableCitation box="[1415,1431,834,860]" captionStart="TABLE 2" captionStartId="11.[151,239,151,175]" captionText="TABLE 2. Factor loadings of the first two components of each of the Principal Components Analyses performed. Bold values indicate the eigenvectors of the five variables that explains most of the variance for each component." pageId="24" pageNumber="475">2</tableCitation>
, and 3). With individuals of both species in hand, 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[704,866,871,896]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[704,866,871,896]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[874,961,870,896]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
can be easily recognized by its distinctive gray-based ochraceous-buff ventral fur, which is markedly different from the completely white ventral coloration of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[151,277,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[151,277,943,968]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
; some specimens of this last species exhibit a pale orange ventral fur, however, basal hairs are not gray as in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[211,373,979,1004]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[211,373,979,1004]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[380,467,978,1004]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(
<tableCitation box="[481,568,978,1004]" captionStart="TABLE 3" captionStartId="23.[151,239,152,176]" captionText="TABLE 3. Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of Neacomys, Part I" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Table 3</tableCitation>
; 
<figureCitation box="[581,815,978,1004]" captionStart="FIGURE 8" captionStartId="17.[151,250,1161,1185]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1137]" captionTargetId="figure-18@17.[151,1436,181,1137]" captionTargetPageId="17" captionText="FIGURE 8. Ventral perspectives of adult specimens illustrating the striking difference in ventral fur of the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) Section of the holotype of Neacomys sp. nov. showing its characteristic gray-based ochraceous-buff ventral fur. C) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723); note the contrasting entirely white ventral fur of this species." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491136" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491136/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Figs. 8A, 8B and 8C</figureCitation>
). Also, 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[901,1063,979,1004]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[901,1063,979,1004]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1070,1157,978,1004]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
has broad orange-ochraceous patches on each side of the muzzle (above the mouth) that are absent or slightly pronounced (but narrower) in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[180,306,1051,1076]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[180,306,1051,1076]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation box="[322,510,1050,1076]" captionStart="FIGURE 7" captionStartId="16.[151,250,1901,1925]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,489,1878]" captionTargetId="figure-209@16.[151,1436,489,1878]" captionTargetPageId="16" captionText="FIGURE 7. Frontal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068); note the distinctive broad ochraceous-orange patches in the sides of the muzzle of this species. B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723)." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491134" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491134/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Figs. 7A and 7B</figureCitation>
). Individual hairs covering the dorsal surface of the hindfeet are also useful to differentiate both species; under magnification, most of these hairs appear completely white in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[1178,1303,1087,1112]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[1178,1303,1087,1112]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, whereas in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,314,1123,1148]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[151,314,1123,1148]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[322,404,1122,1148]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
they are predominately grayish (
<figureCitation box="[779,848,1122,1149]" captionStart="FIGURE 6" captionStartId="15.[151,250,1328,1352]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,345,1305]" captionTargetId="figure-95@15.[151,1436,345,1305]" captionTargetPageId="15" captionText="FIGURE 6. Dorsal perspectives of adult specimens belonging to the two Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Holotype of Neacomys sp. nov (UIS-MHN-M 1068). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723); note that a portion of the tail is missing in this specimen." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491132" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491132/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Fig. 6</figureCitation>
). In close inspection of the tail, the caudal scales of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[151,278,1159,1184]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[151,278,1159,1184]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
appear to be larger than in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[592,754,1159,1184]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[592,754,1159,1184]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[762,852,1158,1184]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, but this difference is hard to quantify because tails are stretched to varying degrees when skins are stuffed (
<bibRefCitation author="Voss, R. S. &amp; Lunde, D. P. &amp; Simmons, N. B." box="[792,987,1194,1220]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" pagination="1 - 236" refId="ref29629" refString="Voss, R. S., Lunde, D. P. &amp; Simmons, N. B. (2001) The mammals of Paracou, French Guiana: a Neotropical lowland rainforest fauna. Part 2. Nonvolant species. Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History, 263, 1 - 236. https: // doi. org / 10.1206 / 0003 - 0090 (2001) 263 &lt;0003: TMOPFG&gt; 2.0. CO; 2" type="journal article" year="2001">
Voss 
<emphasis box="[854,905,1194,1220]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">et al</emphasis>
., 2001
</bibRefCitation>
). Morphometrically, there is substantial overlapping between the two species in most external measurements (
<tableCitation box="[943,1040,1230,1256]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="6.[151,239,1304,1328]" captionText="TABLE 1. External and craniodental measurements of adult specimens of most of the small-bodied species of Neacomys, including the taxon described here. Weigh (Wt) is given in grams and the measurements are in millimeters. Mean and Standard Deviation (above), observed range (middle), and sample size (below, in parenthesis). High Body Length (HBL), Tail Length (TL), Hind Foot Length (HF), and Ear Length (Ear). Condylo-incisive Length (CIL); Length of Diastema (LD); Length of Molars (LM); Breadth of M1 (BM1); Length of Incisive Foramen (LIF); Breadth of Incisive Foramen (BIF); Breadth of Palatal Bridge (BPB); Breadth of Zygomatic Plate (BZP); Length of Rostrum (LR); Length of Nasals (LN); Least Interorbital Breadth (LIB); Breadth of Braincase (BB); Zygomatic Breadth (ZB)." pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Tables 1</tableCitation>
, and 2; 
<figureCitation box="[1133,1202,1230,1256]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="12.[151,250,1394,1418]" captionTargetBox="[189,1398,181,1370]" captionTargetId="figure-22@12.[189,1398,181,1370]" captionTargetPageId="12" captionText="FIGURE 4. Scatterplots of the Principal Components Analyses: PC1 and PC2 are represented in the graphics. A. PCA of the external and craniodental variables of all the small-bodied species of Neacomys; B. PCA of the craniodental variables of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov. Miniatures in the right side correspond to the Bayesian Cytb phylogeny recovered here (FIG- URE 3): species in the scatterplots and the phylogenies are same colored." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491126" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491126/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Fig. 4</figureCitation>
), however, the 
<typeStatus pageId="24" pageNumber="475">holotype</typeStatus>
of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[237,398,1267,1292]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[237,398,1267,1292]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[405,492,1266,1292]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
apparently has a longer tail than most of the specimens of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[1150,1275,1267,1292]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[1150,1275,1267,1292]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(at least those distributed west of the 
<collectingRegion box="[408,532,1302,1328]" country="Colombia" name="Magdalena" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Magdalena</collectingRegion>
river).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1437,330,2012]" lastBlockId="25.[151,1437,151,1041]" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="476" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">
In side-by-side comparisons of the skulls, several differences can be noted between the two species. In dorsal view, the rostrum of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[384,545,1375,1400]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[384,545,1375,1400]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[552,639,1374,1400]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is clearly shorter, which morphometrically is reflected by lower values of Rostral Length (
<collectionCode box="[366,406,1410,1436]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">RL</collectionCode>
), Length of Nasals (
<collectionCode box="[635,677,1410,1436]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">LN</collectionCode>
), Length of Incisive Foramen (
<collectionCode box="[1026,1073,1410,1436]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">LIF</collectionCode>
), and Length of Diastema in the 
<typeStatus box="[151,249,1446,1472]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">holotype</typeStatus>
than in most of the specimens of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[624,750,1447,1472]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[624,750,1447,1472]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<tableCitation box="[764,859,1446,1472]" captionStart="TABLE 1" captionStartId="6.[151,239,1304,1328]" captionText="TABLE 1. External and craniodental measurements of adult specimens of most of the small-bodied species of Neacomys, including the taxon described here. Weigh (Wt) is given in grams and the measurements are in millimeters. Mean and Standard Deviation (above), observed range (middle), and sample size (below, in parenthesis). High Body Length (HBL), Tail Length (TL), Hind Foot Length (HF), and Ear Length (Ear). Condylo-incisive Length (CIL); Length of Diastema (LD); Length of Molars (LM); Breadth of M1 (BM1); Length of Incisive Foramen (LIF); Breadth of Incisive Foramen (BIF); Breadth of Palatal Bridge (BPB); Breadth of Zygomatic Plate (BZP); Length of Rostrum (LR); Length of Nasals (LN); Least Interorbital Breadth (LIB); Breadth of Braincase (BB); Zygomatic Breadth (ZB)." pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Tables 1</tableCitation>
, 
<tableCitation box="[873,890,1446,1472]" captionStart="TABLE 2" captionStartId="11.[151,239,151,175]" captionText="TABLE 2. Factor loadings of the first two components of each of the Principal Components Analyses performed. Bold values indicate the eigenvectors of the five variables that explains most of the variance for each component." pageId="24" pageNumber="475">2</tableCitation>
; and 3; 
<figureCitation box="[977,1055,1446,1472]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="12.[151,250,1394,1418]" captionTargetBox="[189,1398,181,1370]" captionTargetId="figure-22@12.[189,1398,181,1370]" captionTargetPageId="12" captionText="FIGURE 4. Scatterplots of the Principal Components Analyses: PC1 and PC2 are represented in the graphics. A. PCA of the external and craniodental variables of all the small-bodied species of Neacomys; B. PCA of the craniodental variables of N. tenuipes and Neacomys sp. nov. Miniatures in the right side correspond to the Bayesian Cytb phylogeny recovered here (FIG- URE 3): species in the scatterplots and the phylogenies are same colored." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491126" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491126/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Figs. 4</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[1067,1189,1446,1472]" captionStart="FIGURE 9" captionStartId="18.[151,250,1875,1899]" captionTargetBox="[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetId="figure-22@18.[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetPageId="18" captionText="FIGURE 9. Comparison of the dorsal and ventral views of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B), D) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note the nasals more expanded anteriorly, the shallower zygomatic notches, the less developed supraorbital ridges, the procingulum of M1 flattened laterally, and the incisive foramina extending almost to anterior alveolus of M1 in Neacomys sp. nov. if: incisive foramen; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; nas: nasal bone; sob: supraorbital beads; zn: zygomatic notch." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491138" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491138/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">9A and 9B</figureCitation>
). The anterior borders of the nasals are more expanded in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[544,706,1483,1508]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp.nov.">
<emphasis box="[544,706,1483,1508]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[713,792,1482,1508]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp.nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
than in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[882,1007,1483,1508]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[882,1007,1483,1508]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. At the level of the interorbital region, the difference is given principally by the supraorbital beads, which are more developed and dorsally projected in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[151,277,1555,1580]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[151,277,1555,1580]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
than in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[369,530,1555,1580]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[369,530,1555,1580]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[538,625,1554,1580]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Nevertheless, this difference should be interpreted with caution because interorbital beads are less developed in young individuals, as is the case of the 
<typeStatus box="[1043,1141,1590,1616]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">holotype</typeStatus>
of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1179,1342,1591,1616]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[1179,1342,1591,1616]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1349,1437,1590,1616]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(young adult class 
<collectionCode box="[362,384,1626,1652]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">II</collectionCode>
). In lateral view, 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[578,740,1627,1652]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[578,740,1627,1652]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[747,834,1626,1652]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
can be quickly recognized by the convex profile conferred by its globose braincase, while in most specimens of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[834,961,1663,1688]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[834,961,1663,1688]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
the profile is flatter (
<figureCitation box="[1205,1423,1662,1688]" captionStart="FIGURE 10" captionStartId="19.[151,250,1873,1897]" captionTargetBox="[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetId="figure-18@19.[170,1417,181,1848]" captionTargetPageId="19" captionText="FIGURE 10. Comparison of the lateral profiles of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note a more convex profile of the braincase, a thicker hamular process of the squamosal, a broader condylar process, a larger and laterally projected mental foramen, and the anterior margin of nasals without a hump in Neacomys sp. nov. con: condylar process; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; mf: mental foramen; nas: nasals." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491142" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491142/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Figs. 10A and 10B</figureCitation>
). From this view is also possible to note a difference in the dorsal surface of the anterior borders of the nasals; in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
a subtle hump gives them a hooked appearance, whereas a flatter profile is typical in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1232,1395,1735,1760]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[1232,1395,1735,1760]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Posteriorly, at the level of the auditory bullae, there are even more marked differences; the opened ectotympanic ring is distinctive in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[450,611,1807,1832]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[450,611,1807,1832]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[619,708,1806,1832]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, resulting of the anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic not being in contact with the mastoid tubercle. Contrary, in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[711,837,1843,1868]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[711,837,1843,1868]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
both structures are in contact, which lead to a closed ectotympanic ring (
<figureCitation box="[371,454,1878,1904]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">Fig. 11</figureCitation>
). In 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[507,670,1879,1904]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[507,670,1879,1904]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[678,765,1878,1904]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
the tegmen tympani is exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, acting as a membrane that partially covers the ventral portions of the subsquamosal and posglenoid foramina; in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[354,480,1951,1976]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[354,480,1951,1976]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, a non-exposed tegmen tympani leads to a larger posglenoid foramen. In this region, 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,314,1987,2012]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[151,314,1987,2012]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[321,409,1986,2012]" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
also exhibits a distinctive thicker hamular process of the squamosal than in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[1271,1398,1987,2012]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="24" pageNumber="475" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[1271,1398,1987,2012]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="475">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, as well as a larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus. With respect to the paraoccipital process, this element is slightly bifurcated in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[300,462,187,212]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[300,462,187,212]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[469,551,187,213]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
, but not in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[677,802,187,212]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[677,802,187,212]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,151,1041]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">
In the ventral view of the skull, the first apparent difference between both species involves the incisive foramina, which extend posteriorly almost, but not quite, to the anterior alveolus of M 
<quantity box="[1037,1075,259,285]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.54" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" unit="in" value="1.0">1 in</quantity>
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1080,1241,259,284]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[1080,1241,259,284]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1247,1335,259,285]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, whereas in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[180,306,295,320]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[180,306,295,320]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
its posterior margins end before (
<figureCitation box="[686,875,295,321]" captionStart="FIGURE 9" captionStartId="18.[151,250,1875,1899]" captionTargetBox="[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetId="figure-22@18.[241,1347,181,1851]" captionTargetPageId="18" captionText="FIGURE 9. Comparison of the dorsal and ventral views of the skulls of Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C) Neacomys sp. nov. (UIS-MHN-M 1068, holotype). B), D) Neacomys tenuipes (UIS-MHN-M 1723). Note the nasals more expanded anteriorly, the shallower zygomatic notches, the less developed supraorbital ridges, the procingulum of M1 flattened laterally, and the incisive foramina extending almost to anterior alveolus of M1 in Neacomys sp. nov. if: incisive foramen; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; nas: nasal bone; sob: supraorbital beads; zn: zygomatic notch." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491138" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491138/files/figure.png" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">Figs. 9C and 9D</figureCitation>
). Also, on the maxillary of the 
<typeStatus box="[1224,1322,295,321]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">holotype</typeStatus>
of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[252,341,331,357]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, adjacent to the posterior margins of the incisive foramina, there are small perforations that are not evident in specimens of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[421,546,367,392]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[421,546,367,392]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. Dental morphology is another quick way to differentiate between both species; in the maxillary molars of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[465,629,403,428]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[465,629,403,428]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[640,725,403,429]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
, for example, the principal labial cusps (paracone, metacone) are smaller than their lingual counterparts (protocone, hypocone), but in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[986,1113,439,464]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[986,1113,439,464]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
the labial and lingual cusps are subequal (resulting in a more or less symmetrical occlusal design) (
<figureCitation box="[956,1038,475,501]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="20.[151,250,1136,1160]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetId="figure-22@20.[151,1436,181,1112]" captionTargetPageId="20" captionText="FIGURE 11. Selected qualitative morphological traits differentiating Trans-Andean species of Neacomys present in Colombia: A), C), E) Neacomys sp. nov. B), D), F) N. tenuipes. Note the tegmen tympani exposed above the dorsal surface of the ectotympanic, the opened ectotympanic ring, the larger orbicular apophysis of the malleus, the bifurcated paraoccipital process, the deeper folds of the upper molars, and the divided mesoflexus of M1 in the new species. ab: auditory bullae; adeect: anterodorsal edge of the ectotympanic; hyp: hypoflexus; hp: hamular process of the squamosal; M1 prc: procingulum of first upper molar; mes: mesoflexus; met: metaflexus; mt: mastoid tubercle; oa: orbicular apophysis; par: paraflexus; pgf: postglenoid foramen; pp: paraoccipital process; pro: protoflexus; ssf: subsquamosal fenestra; tt: tegmen tympani." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4491144" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4491144/files/figure.png" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">Fig. 11</figureCitation>
). 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1061,1223,475,500]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[1061,1223,475,500]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1231,1318,475,501]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
also has a characteristic M1 with laterally flattened procinculum, contrary to 
<emphasis box="[895,1028,511,536]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[895,1024,511,536]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">N. tenuipes</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
in which this tooth is approximately rectangular in outline due to a broad anterocone (not flattened procingulum). The folds of the first upper molars are particularly deep, broad, and bifurcated at their ends in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[786,950,583,608]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[786,950,583,608]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[958,1042,583,609]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
, but not in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[1173,1301,583,608]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[1173,1301,583,608]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. In the first species the mesoflexus is divided into a short labial cleft and a large internal fossette that forms a very prominent landmark in the center of the tooth, whereas in the second this element is also divided but the internal fossette is considerably smaller. Finally, in the mandible, there are two useful characters that allow to discriminate between both species: the first is the condylar process, which is notably wide and short in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1053,1214,727,752]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov">
<emphasis box="[1053,1214,727,752]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1221,1303,727,753]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
, while in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is slightly longer and slender. The second character is the mental foramen, typically larger in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[1276,1436,763,788]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[1276,1436,763,788]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[151,240,799,825]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, and projected laterally, whereas in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1900" box="[641,767,799,824]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="tenuipes">
<emphasis box="[641,767,799,824]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. tenuipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is much smaller and is almost dorsally projected.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="25" pageNumber="476" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,151,1041]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">
The enormous gap between the collecting localities of 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[836,1001,835,860]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[836,1001,835,860]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1011,1101,835,861]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
and the known geographical ranges of the other small-bodied species within the genus (implying many physical and environmental barriers), makes impossible to collect them in the same place. Anyway, 
<taxonomicName authority="Colmenares-Pinzón, 2021" authorityName="Colmenares-Pinzón" authorityYear="2021" box="[845,1007,907,932]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="serranensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[845,1007,907,932]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. serranensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1014,1101,907,933]" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is easily distinguishable from 
<emphasis box="[151,1011,943,969]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">
<taxonomicName box="[151,268,943,969]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="dubosti">N. dubosti</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Thomas" authorityYear="1905" box="[278,403,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="guianae">N. guianae</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName box="[413,585,943,969]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="macedoruizi">N. macedoruizi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Semedo, Da Silva, Gutierrez, Ferreira, Nunes, Mendes-Oliveira, Farias &amp; Rossi" authorityYear="2020" box="[595,750,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="marajoara">N. marajoara</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName box="[760,882,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="minutus">N. minutus</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName box="[893,1011,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="musseri">N. musseri</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[1024,1256,943,968]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">
<taxonomicName box="[1024,1152,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="paracou">N. paracou</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Semedo, Da Silva, Gutierrez, Ferreira, Nunes, Mendes-Oliveira, Farias &amp; Rossi" authorityYear="2020" box="[1162,1252,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="vossi">N. vossi</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Semedo, Da Silva, Gutierrez, Ferreira, Nunes, Mendes-Oliveira, Farias &amp; Rossi" authorityYear="2020" box="[1309,1402,943,968]" class="Mammalia" family="Muridae" genus="Neacomys" kingdom="Animalia" order="Rodentia" pageId="25" pageNumber="476" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="xingu">
<emphasis box="[1309,1402,943,968]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">N. xingu</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by its unique gray-based ochraceous-buff ventral fur, its broad ochraceous-orange patches in the muzzle, and for being larger in practically all external and craniodental dimensions (
<tableCitation box="[844,941,1015,1041]" captionStart="TABLE 2" captionStartId="11.[151,239,151,175]" captionText="TABLE 2. Factor loadings of the first two components of each of the Principal Components Analyses performed. Bold values indicate the eigenvectors of the five variables that explains most of the variance for each component." pageId="25" pageNumber="476">Tables 2</tableCitation>
, 
<tableCitation box="[953,968,1015,1041]" captionStart="TABLE 3" captionStartId="23.[151,239,152,176]" captionText="TABLE 3. Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of Neacomys, Part I" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">3</tableCitation>
, 
<tableCitation box="[981,997,1015,1041]" captionStart="TABLE 4" captionStartId="25.[151,239,1088,1112]" captionText="TABLE 4. Morphological comparisons among small-bodied species of Neacomys, Part II" pageId="25" pageNumber="476">4</tableCitation>
, and 5).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>