<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.72.743" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6434712d-f99c-497c-8745-1372f7db4960" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156201202" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-72-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:80CFF96F-2331-45EB-B4B5-DF5814A57660" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-72-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 72" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the endemic Taiwanese millipede genus Aponedyopus Verhoeff, 1939, with descriptions of two new species (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Paradoxosomatidae). Advances in the systematica of Diplopoda III" checkinTime="1555330309271" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Chen, Chao-Chun, Golovatch, Sergei I. &amp; Chang, Hsueh-Wen" docDate="2010" docId="B601D772549D32A0252B0C865AF820DD" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 72: 1-21" docOrigin="ZooKeys 72" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.72.743" docTitle="Aponedyopus similis Chen, Golovatch &amp; Chang, 2010, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="11" masterDocId="C647FF94985AFFAEB938D856FF8AFFF9" masterDocTitle="Revision of the endemic Taiwanese millipede genus Aponedyopus Verhoeff, 1939, with descriptions of two new species (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Paradoxosomatidae). Advances in the systematica of Diplopoda III" masterLastPageNumber="21" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" updateTime="1643724542928" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the endemic Taiwanese millipede genus Aponedyopus Verhoeff, 1939, with descriptions of two new species (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Paradoxosomatidae). Advances in the systematica of Diplopoda III</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chen, Chao-Chun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Golovatch, Sergei I.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chang, Hsueh-Wen</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>72</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>21</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.72.743</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.72.743</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-72-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="156201202" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:80CFF96F-2331-45EB-B4B5-DF5814A57660" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B601D772549D32A0252B0C865AF820DD" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:80CFF96F-2331-45EB-B4B5-DF5814A57660" class="Diplopoda" family="Paradoxosomatidae" genus="Aponedyopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aponedyopus similis" order="Polydesmida" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="similis">Aponedyopus similis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="8" pageNumber="9">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 24-3144, 4554 &amp; 55
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Material examined:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Holotype ♂ (TFRI), Taiwan (R. O. C.), Taichung County (台中縣), HePing (和平鄉), Shengguang (勝光), ca 2,200 m a.s.l., 26 March - 25 April, 2003, leg. W. C. Yeh.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Paratype ♂ (NSYSUB-DI 75), Taiwan (R. O. C.), Hsinchu County (新竹縣), Wufeng Township (五峰鄉), GuanU (觀霧), 24.5 km from entrance to national park, ca 2,000 m a.s.l., 13 August 2002, leg. C. C. Chen, Y. H. Lin &amp; J. N. Huang.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
Figures 24-31. 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Paradoxosomatidae" genus="Aponedyopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aponedyopus similis" order="Polydesmida" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="similis">Aponedyopus similis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., ♂ holotype (24) ♂ paratype (25-31). 24 Entire body, dorsal view 25 Anterior body portion, lateral view 26-27 Midbody segments, dorsal and lateral views, respectively 28-29 Epiproct, dorsal and lateral views, respectively 30 Hypoproct, ventral view 31 Sternal cones near gonopod aperture. Scale bars: 1.0 mm for 24-29, 0.5 mm for 30, 31. cal: calluses; pap: pre-apical papillae.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="name">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Name:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">To emphasize the close resemblance to the next new species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Diagnosis:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
Being apparently the most similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Paradoxosomatidae" genus="Aponedyopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aponedyopus latilobatus" order="Polydesmida" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="latilobatus">Aponedyopus latilobatus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., based both on several peripheral characters (shorter legs, mostly a smaller body size etc.) and gonopod conformation, it is distinguished by the gonopod lobe b being membranous and lobiform, the terminal branches of the solenophore differing in length and crossing each other, with branch x carrying an inconspicuous lobe (see also Key below).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Description:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Length ca 22 mm (♂, n=2); width of pro- and metazona 10 ca 1.8 and 2.0 mm, respectively.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
General coloration in alcohol brown to dark brown (Figs 24-27), with a clear pattern of a lighter brown to yellow brown axial stripe consisting of narrower subtriang 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="10" start="start">ular</pageBreakToken>
spots on proterga and twice as wide central spots on metaterga, these spots growing slightly infuscate, to blackish both towards stricture and posterior half of metaterga; prozona slightly darker than metazona, thus providing a vague cingulate pattern as well; paraterga, legs and venter slightly lighter than background, light grey-brown; head marbled brown, especially well so in vertigial region, genae contrastingly yellowish, a square median spot above antennal sockets contrastingly dark brown; antennae increasingly infuscate, up to blackish distad, distinctly darker at margins, marbled and lighter centrally, only tip contrastingly pallid; both collum and segment 2 with a very 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="11" start="start">faint</pageBreakToken>
, yellow-brown, axial line; epiproct uniformly light brown, only very slightly infuscate near base.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Postcollum constriction evident; in width, segment 2 = 3 &lt;4 &lt;collum &lt;head = segments 5-15; thereafter body gradually and gently tapering towards telson both in width and height. Antennae (Fig. 25) medium-sized, slender, reaching behind stricture of tergite 3. Paraterga (Figs 26 &amp; 27) very poorly developed, very evident and low only on segment 2, calluses (cal) (nearly) completely delimited by a sulcus dorsally, in caudal 1/3 also ventrally only on pore-bearing segments. Transverse sulcus (Figs 26, 27) developed on segments 5-17, traceable on segment 18, wanting on 19th, narrow, shallow, neither beaded at bottom nor reaching bases of paraterga. Surface smooth throughout, slightly granulated only below paraterga 2-4. Limbus thin, caudal margin entire. Stricture dividing pro- and metazona shallow, narrow, not beaded at bottom (Figs 26 &amp; 27). Pleurosternal carinae present only on segments 2 and 3 (Fig. 25). Tergal setae almost fully abraded, 2+1 retained only at anterior edge of collum; pattern untraceable. Ozopores lateral, lying on calluses ca 1/2 metatergal length in front of caudal edge (Figs 26 &amp; 27). Epiproct long (Figs 28 &amp; 29), flattened dorsoventrally, straight, not curved caudoventrad in lateral view, ratio of epiproct length to pre-epiproct length of telson 1: 1.3, tip of epiproct slightly concave; pre-apical papillae (pap) evident, close to apex. Hypoproct (Fig. 30) rounded, subtrapeziform, 1+1 setae at caudal corners situated on well-separated knobs, sides slightly concave.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Sterna sparsely setose; lamina between coxae 4 setose and emarginate (Fig. 31); segment 7 with a pair of prominent sternal cones (= spiracles) flanking gonopod aperture; each cross-impression with a transverse sulcus, but without axial groove. Legs (Fig. 27) moderately long and slender, legs 1 to anterior legs of segment 17 with tarsal brushes, thereafter legs broken off in both available ♂♂, each midbody leg ca 1.2 times as long as body height, coxa 2 with a small apical process supporting a gonopore.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Gonopods (Figs 44, 45, 54 &amp; 55) with process b at base of postfemoral part lobe-shaped, membranous, not like a distinct process; l at base of solenophore rather vague; distal part of gonopod deeply bifid, divided into a longer solenomere (sl), more complex at end and bearing a low terminal lobe, and a slightly shorter, simple, nearly pointed solenophore branch (sph); ends of both branches crossing.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Distribution:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">This species seems to be local, occurring only rather high (2,000-2,200 m a.s.l.) in the mountains of northern Taiwan (Map).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>