<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.609.9459" ID-GBIF-Dataset="0f0e086a-e700-4c23-b510-d083ce4fc260" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127856963" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-609-69" ID-ZBK="2B225925C5CF4870A817C33EF76E31F9" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:174E0AE5-52C3-417A-9AAF-3120652AAC8B" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-609-69" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 609" ModsDocTitle="Herniosina Roháček: revised concept, two new species, new key and atlas of male and female terminalia (Diptera, Sphaeroceridae)" checkinTime="1470750515516" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Rohacek, Jindrich" docDate="2016" docId="32A0921321E994FB5F257312BC0EF62F" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 609: 69-106" docOrigin="ZooKeys 609" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.609.9459" docTitle="Herniosina erymantha Rohacek, 2016, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="174E0AE5-52C3-417A-9AAF-3120652AAC8B" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="82" masterDocId="FFA1FFA76A1CFF9BFFD0EF75F633FFF4" masterDocTitle="Herniosina Rohacek: revised concept, two new species, new key and atlas of male and female terminalia (Diptera, Sphaeroceridae)" masterLastPageNumber="106" masterPageNumber="69" pageId="8" pageNumber="77" updateTime="1643597238333" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Herniosina Rohacek: revised concept, two new species, new key and atlas of male and female terminalia (Diptera, Sphaeroceridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Rohacek, Jindrich</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>609</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>69</mods:start>
<mods:end>106</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.609.9459</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.609.9459</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-609-69</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">2B225925C5CF4870A817C33EF76E31F9</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2B225925C5CF4870A817C33EF76E31F9</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127856963" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:174E0AE5-52C3-417A-9AAF-3120652AAC8B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/32A0921321E994FB5F257312BC0EF62F" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="82" pageId="8" pageNumber="77">
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="77" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="77">Taxon classification Animalia Diptera Sphaeroceridae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="77" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="77">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/174E0AE5-52C3-417A-9AAF-3120652AAC8B" class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina erymantha" order="Diptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erymantha">Herniosina erymantha</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="8" pageNumber="77">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 14, 15-19, 20-26
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="78" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="78">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="78" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
material.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="78">
Holotype ♂ labelled: &quot;GREECE: NW Peloponnese: Alepochori 0.5 km SE 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="37.982502">37°58'57&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="21.802776">21°48'10&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
&quot;, &quot;590 m, 27.5.2015, sifting leaves under 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Platanaceae" genus="Platanus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Platanus" order="Proteales" pageId="9" pageNumber="78" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Platanus</taxonomicName>
, J. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Roháček">Rohacek</normalizedToken>
leg.&quot;, &quot;Holotypus ♂ 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina erymantha" order="Diptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erymantha">Herniosina erymantha</taxonomicName>
sp. n., J. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Roháček">Rohacek</normalizedToken>
det. 2016&quot; (red label). The specimen is dry-mounted on pinned triangular card, with left wing and abdomen detached, genitalia dissected and all removed parts preserved in glycerine in coalesced plastic tube pinned below the specimen (SMOC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="78" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="78">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="78">The name of the new species is an adjective derived from the Erimanthos (= Lat. Erymanthos) Mts inasmuch as its type locality is situated in the western part of this montane range.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="82" pageId="9" pageNumber="78" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="78">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="9" pageNumber="78">
Male. Total body length 1.79 mm; general colour blackish brown with relatively sparse dark greyish brown microtomentum. Head blackish brown to brown. Frons largely blackish brown, brownish only at anterior margin, rather sparsely microtomentose. Occiput blackish brown and dark greyish brown microtomentose. Orbits, interfrontalia (poorly delimited) and ocellar triangle also greyish brown (not densely) microtomentose and duller than rest of frons; frontal triangle comparatively wide and shining. Cephalic chaetotaxy: pvt absent, only minute adpressed postocellar setulae behind ocellar triangle; occe and occi subequal and less than half length of vte; vti longest among frontal setae, vte and oc slightly shorter than vti; 2 strongly exclinate ors, both distinctly shorter than oc; only 3 relatively short ifr, the middle pair longest; 3-4 very minute ads inside and below ors; g weak, not longer than anterior peristomal setula; vi about as long as vti. Frontal lunule short, wide, similarly brown as anterior 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="79" start="start">margin</pageBreakToken>
of frons. Face with cavities below antennae dark brown, rather shining; medial carina slightly elevated but distinct. Gena high, reddish only anteriorly, otherwise blackish brown, sparsely greyish microtomentose. Eye relatively small; its longest diameter about 2.2 times as long as smallest genal height. Antenna blackish brown, relatively long; its 3rd segment distinctly tapered apically both in dorsal and lateral view. Arista long, about 3.8 times as long as antenna, relatively long ciliate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="79">Thorax dark brown to blackish, mesonotum subshining due sparser microtomentum, pleuron lighter and dull. Suturae between pleural sclerites paler brown. Scutellum relatively large and long, rounded triangular. Thoracic chaetotaxy: 2 hu but internal reduced to microseta; 2 postsutural dc, anterior short and weak (only twice longer than ac microsetae), posterior strong but slightly shorter than basal sc; 8-10 rows of ac microsetae on suture; medial prescutellar ac pair somewhat prolonged; 2 strong sc, basal slightly longer than scutellum, apical about 1.6 times as long as basal; 2 stpl but anterior reduced to minute hair-like setula.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="79">Legs dark brown, coxae, trochanters, knees and tarsi pale brown to ochreous. f1 with relatively sparse setae in posterodorsal and posteroventral rows. f2 with a row of curved but relatively short ventral setae in basal half (Fig. 18); t2 ventrally with a long row of small dense spines and reduced va seta (shorter than anteroapical seta), see Fig. 18; dorsal chaetotaxy of t2 as in congeners but posterodorsal seta in apical fourth somewhat shorter (Fig. 16). t2: mt2 = 1.84.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="79">Wing (Fig. 14) with pale brownish membrane and ochreous to dark brown veins. C hardly produced beyond apex of R4+5. R2+3 slightly sinuate but apically distinctly upcurved to C; R4+5 sinuate and its apical half almost straight. Discal cell (dm) relatively short and distally less tapered than in most relatives, with small process of M beyond dm-cu; posterior outer corner of dm not rounded but obtuse-angled. A1 sinuate; anal lobe well developed; alula narrow but not acute. Wing measurements: length 1.87 mm, width 0.77 mm, C-index = 0.95, rm\dm-cu: dm-cu = 2.62. Haltere with ochreous stem and dark brown knob.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="79">
Abdomen blackish brown, with some sclerites brown. Preabdominal terga large, shining blackish brown, with only scarce greyish microtomentum, sparsely and shortly setulose. T4 longer than T3; T5 enlarged but less than that of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina bequaerti" order="Diptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bequaerti">Herniosina bequaerti</taxonomicName>
, postabdomen strongly down-curved (Fig. 15). Preabdominal sterna as in Figs 15, 17: S1+2 strongly bulging (Fig. 15) and anteromedially narrowly desclerotized (Fig. 17); S3 and S4 deeply anteriorly emarginate due to large lateral lobes (Fig. 17), with distinctive pigmentation; S1+2, S3 and S4 with sparse setae at posterior margins, with only medial (in S4 submedial) pair longer. S5 (Fig. 19) reduced and transversely strip-shaped, with setose lateral parts as in relatives but with distinctive dark medial part provided with a flattened (in lateral view knob-like, Fig. 15) and distally forked process having 2 setulae on each lobe of its digitiform terminal part (Fig. 19). S6 and S7 fused to form a complex sclerite on left side of postabdomen, narrow ventrally and dorsally but dilated laterally (Fig. 15) as in congeners. S8 shorter and more tapered, with a slit left laterally and a few setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="82" pageId="11" pageNumber="80">
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="80" start="start">Genitalia</pageBreakToken>
. Epandrium (Figs 20, 21) of medium length but comparatively wide and more angular dorsolaterally (see Fig. 21) than those of relatives, and with a group of longer and stronger setae laterally and lateroventrally (posterior seta longest and most robust) but dorsolaterally without longer seta. Anal fissure slightly wider than high (Fig. 21), subcircular. Cerci fused with epandrium, posteroventrally projecting in 2 processes, one (more anterior) robust, long (about as long as gonostylus) and distally 
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="81" start="start">somewhat</pageBreakToken>
thickened and bearing 1 long seta in addition to a number of setulae, the other (more medial) small, elongately conical and simple (Figs 20, 21). Medandrium small (low), reduced but connected by long internal arms with gonostyli (Fig. 21), posteromedially fused with cerci. Hypandrium with very long and slender anteromedial rod-like apodeme (Fig. 20). Gonostylus (Figs 20-23) most resembling that of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina bequaerti" order="Diptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="81" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bequaerti">Herniosina bequaerti</taxonomicName>
but ventrally simple (not emarginate in lateral view), with longer anteroven 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="82" start="start">tral</pageBreakToken>
seta, and with long, very slender, curved and apically lancet-shape dorsal internal process (cf. Fig. 22). Aedeagal complex (Figs 24-26) with long phallapodeme (as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina bequaerti" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bequaerti">Herniosina bequaerti</taxonomicName>
) but having distinctly lower dorsal keel. Aedeagus also somewhat similar to that of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina bequaerti" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bequaerti">Herniosina bequaerti</taxonomicName>
but with funnel-shaped apex of distiphallus more robust, its lateral lobes and unpaired ventral process markedly longer and its postgonite more slender, with curved, slender and terminally blunt apex. Phallophore closely resembling that that of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina bequaerti" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bequaerti">Herniosina bequaerti</taxonomicName>
, anteriorly rod-like but dorsoventrally flattened, posteriorly projecting ventrally and hence epiphallus-like. Ejaculatory apodeme not observed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">Female unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="82" type="discussion">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">Discussion.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina erymantha" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erymantha">Herniosina erymantha</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is only known from the male holotype and, consequently, for the evaluation of its relationships the female characters cannot be used. However, based on the male terminalia the species is a distinctive member of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Herniosina</taxonomicName>
unmistakeably recognizable from any other known congener. It differs from all relatives by the flattened, distinctively forked medial process of S5 (Fig. 19), broad epandrium with strikingly rectangular dorsolateral corners without dorsolateral long seta and with broad (wider than high) anal fissure (Fig. 21), relatively simple sub-oblong gonostylus (Fig. 23) with very slender and long internal process (Fig. 22), distinctive cercus with long and robust, distally somewhat dilated but laterally flattened lateral process combined with short medial ones (Figs 20, 21) and characteristic postgonite (Fig. 24).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">
Judging from the construction of the male abdomen and male genitalia, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina erymantha" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erymantha">Herniosina erymantha</taxonomicName>
seems to be related to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina bequaerti" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bequaerti">Herniosina bequaerti</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina horrida" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="horrida">Herniosina horrida</taxonomicName>
sharing with them the following synapomorphies: strongly bulging S1+2; very slender and dorsally situated internal process of gonostylus. Its closest relative obviously is 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina bequaerti" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bequaerti">Herniosina bequaerti</taxonomicName>
having similarly (albeit much more) prolonged and basally fused medial processes of S5, a small medial apically pointed process of cercus and more robust funnel-shaped apex of distiphallus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="82" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">
The holotype of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina erymantha" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erymantha">Herniosina erymantha</taxonomicName>
sp. n. was sifted towards the end of May from dead leaves under 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Platanaceae" genus="Platanus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Platanus" order="Proteales" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Platanus</taxonomicName>
trees (see Fig. 13, arrow) in a valley of a montane brook in the western ridge of the Erimanthos Mts (Fig. 12). The microhabitat (layers of decaying leaves of broad-leaved trees) is similar to that known for 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina horrida" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="horrida">Herniosina horrida</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Sphaeroceridae" genus="Herniosina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Herniosina pollex" order="Diptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pollex">Herniosina pollex</taxonomicName>
in Central Europe (see under these species).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="82" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="82">Hitherto only known from Greece: NW Peloponnese.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>