<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" ID-GBIF-Dataset="907713bd-c7f2-4f8e-a75e-b7f9c958865f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648665" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-689-1" ID-ZBK="2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-689-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 689" ModsDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" checkinTime="1502744367222" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lackner, Tomas &amp; Leschen, Richard A. B." docDate="2017" docId="FD5D49E801C75F3C16B58E750555B000" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 689: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 689" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" docTitle="Saprinodes falcifer Lewis 1891" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="67" lastPageNumber="68" masterDocId="D302FFB6FFA66345FFBAFF89311EFFDE" masterDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" updateTime="1643479489822" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lackner, Tomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Leschen, Richard A. B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>689</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-689-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648665" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:FD5D49E801C75F3C16B58E750555B000" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FD5D49E801C75F3C16B58E750555B000" lastPageId="67" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<taxonomicName authority="Lewis, 1891" authorityName="Lewis" authorityYear="1891" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes falcifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="falcifer">Saprinodes falcifer Lewis, 1891</taxonomicName>
Figs 279, 280-288, 289-291, 292-300, 759
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="63" pageNumber="64" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes falcifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="falcifer">
<pageBreakToken pageId="63" pageNumber="64" start="start">Saprinodes</pageBreakToken>
falcifer
</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1981: 396.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="63" pageNumber="64" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Australia: Queensland: Rockhampton.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
Figure 279. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes falcifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="falcifer">Saprinodes falcifer</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1891 habitus, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="63" pageNumber="64" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes falcifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="falcifer">Saprinodes falcifer</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1891: lectotype, designated by 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Dégallier">Degallier</normalizedToken>
in 1993, ♂, with genitalia glued to the same mounting card as the specimen, labelled: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Rockhampton/Queensland”">&quot;Rockhampton/Queensland&quot;</normalizedToken>
(hand-written); followed by: &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinodes</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="falcifer" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" rank="species" species="falcifer">falcifer</taxonomicName>
/Type Lewis&quot; (hand-written); followed by: &quot;G. Lewis Coll./B.M. 1926-369.&quot; (printed); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Type”">&quot;Type&quot;</normalizedToken>
(round label with red margins, printed); and a consecutive red label: &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinodes</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="falcifer" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" rank="species" species="falcifer">falcifer</taxonomicName>
/LECTOTYPE&quot; (hand-written); followed by a yellow label: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“10-120”">&quot;10-120&quot;</normalizedToken>
(pencil-written, added by the senior author) (BMNH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="63" pageNumber="64" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
AUSTRALIA. Queensland: 11 specs., 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-25.45">25°27'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="150.13333">150°08'E</geoCoordinate>
, Taroom District, Nathan Gorge, Riverine Forest, 12.ix.-13.xi.1996, P. Lawless leg., pitfall (QM; 2 exs. in coll. TLAN). New South Wales: 2 ♂♂, Bogan River, F.H. Taylor leg. (ANIC); 7 ♂♂ &amp; 3 ♀♀, ditto, but J. Armstrong (all exs. ANIC; 1 ♂ in coll. TLAN); 2 ♂♂ and 7 specs., ditto, but J. Armstrong leg. (MAMU).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="63" pageNumber="64" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="64" pageNumber="65" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">
<pageBreakToken pageId="64" pageNumber="65" start="start">Distribution</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Endemic to Australia: New South Wales and Queensland (Fig. 759).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="64" pageNumber="65" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">
In this sexually dimorphic species the male has a large depression on the metaventrite and the first abdominal ventrite has coarser and larger punctures than that of the female. Females are also substantially larger than males. The minute setae associated with dorsal punctures observed by 
<bibRefCitation author="Degallier, N" journalOrPublisher=")" pageId="214" pageNumber="215" pagination="47 - 53" title="Description de Saprinodesdistinctus sp. n., designation d'un lectotype pour S. falcifer Lewis, 1891 et notes sur un autre Histeridae (Coleoptera) d'Australie. Nouvelle Revue d'Entomologie (N. S." volume="10" year="1993">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Dégallier">Degallier</normalizedToken>
(1993
</bibRefCitation>
: 48) were not observed in our specimens.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="67" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="64" pageNumber="65" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Re-description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Body length: PEL: 2.50-3.75 mm; APW: 0.85-1.05 mm; PPW: 1.80-2.55 mm; EL: 1.55-2.20 mm; EW: 2.10-3.00 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<pageBreakToken pageId="65" pageNumber="66" start="start">Body</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 279) ovoid, flattened dorso-ventrally, cuticle light brown to castaneous, with slight metallic tinge; ventral side darker than dorsal; legs and body appendages similarly colored.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Antennal scape (Fig. 280) slightly thickened, punctuate dorsally, with few short setae; antennal club (Fig. 281) rather large, oval, dorsally without any visible structures, ventrally with two visible oval sensory areas, entirely covered in dense short sensilla, intermingled with sparse longer erect sensilla; sensory structures of antennal club (Fig. 291) in form of two ventral sensory areas, apical sensory area larger than basal, with pear-shaped vesicle situated beneath it.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
Figures 280-288. 280 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes falcifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="falcifer">Saprinodes falcifer</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1891 head, dorsal view 281 antennal club, ventral view 282 mentum, ventral view 283 pygidium 284 prosternum 285 mesoventrite 286 lateral disc of metaventrite + metepisternum 287 protibia, dorsal view 288 ditto, ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
Mandibles (Fig. 289) with rounded outer margin, acutely pointed, sub-apical tooth on inner margin of left mandible moderately large, rounded; labrum (Fig. 290) faintly convex dorsally, sparsely punctuate, anterior margin slightly emarginate; labral fold not particularly developed; setae of lateral fringe moderately long; labrum without pits or setae; terminal labial palpomere elongated, its width about half its length; palpal organ present on both labial and maxillary palpi; mentum (Fig. 282) sub-trapezoid, anterior angles produced, anterior margin with deep median excavation, surface around it with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="66" pageNumber="67" start="start">several</pageBreakToken>
short setae, lateral margins with a single row of much shorter sparse ramose setae, disc on apical half with few scattered setae, basal half asetose; cardo of maxilla with few short setae on lateral margin; stipes triangular, with two short setae; lacinia without lacinial hook (=uncus); terminal maxillary palpomere elongated, its width about half its length, about twice as long as penultimate palpomere.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">Clypeus (Fig. 280) large, rectangular, flattened, rounded laterally, with sparse fine punctures, separated by several times their diameter; supra-orbital striae well developed, carinate; frontal stria (Fig. 280) prolonged onto clypeus; frontal disc (Fig. 280) anteriorly somewhat depressed, punctuate, punctures separated by about their diameter, becoming coarser and denser near frontal stria, disappearing medially; eyes convex, well visible from above.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">
Pronotal sides (Fig. 279) on posterior half feebly convergent anteriorly, on anterior half strongly convergent, apical angles produced, marginal pronotal stria complete, carinate, behind head medially with tiny angulate projection; disc antero-laterally with deep, rugulose-lacunose oval punctation, medially punctures becoming much sparser and finer, separated by several times their diameter, forming vague impunctate areas (in some specimens these can be better delimited forming 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘mirrors’">'mirrors'</normalizedToken>
), interspaces between punctures on entire pronotal disc with sparse microscopic punctation; pronotal hypomeron glabrous; scutellum very small.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">
Elytral epipleura punctuate; marginal epipleural stria thin; marginal elytral stria well impressed, thin, continuous along elytral apex as apical elytral stria, connected with sutural elytral stria; humeral elytral stria erased under elytral punctation; inner subhumeral stria present medially, almost unrecognizable beneath elytral punctation; dorsal elytral striae almost unrecognizable from dorsal view, from oblique view striae 1-4 faintly recognizable, first the longest, originating near elytral base running to 3/4 of elytral length apically, striae 2-4 abbreviated basally and apically; sutural elytral stria complete, deeply impressed, surface between it and elytral margin with scattered microscopic punctation. Entire elytral disc very coarsely and densely punctate, punctation rugulose-lacunose, punctures separated by less than half of their diameter, on apical third punctures disappear, forming deep elongate wrinkles; basally between fourth dorsal and sutural striae a small round 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘mirror’">'mirror'</normalizedToken>
(= polished area) present, its surface with scattered microscopic punctation.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">Propygidium transverse, about five times as broad as long, partially covered by elytra, its punctation much finer and sparser than those of the elytra, punctures on apical half separated by about their diameter, on basal half propygidium almost impunctate, interspaces between punctures with fine alutaceous microsculpture; punctation of pygidium (Fig. 283) much coarser and denser, resembling that of elytra; pygidium carinate laterally.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="67" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="66" pageNumber="67">
Anterior margin of median portion of prosternum (Fig. 284) straight; marginal prosternal stria almost complete, interrupted laterally; prosternal process deeply concave on anterior half, laterally with sparse large oval punctures, interspaces imbricate; dorsally prosternal process with sparse shallow punctures; carinal prosternal striae (Fig. 284) carinate, slightly divergent anteriorly and united in front under a rounded 
<pageBreakToken pageId="67" pageNumber="68" start="start">loop</pageBreakToken>
; lateral prosternal striae carinate, widely convergent and 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘open’">'open'</normalizedToken>
anteriorly, near their origin a curious tiny projection present, unseen in any other members of the subfamily (Fig. 284). Lateral costa of antennal groove not reaching prosternal process.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="67" pageNumber="68">Anterior margin of mesoventrite (Fig. 285) deeply emarginate medially; discal marginal mesoventral stria anteriorly well impressed, absent laterally; disc with antero-lateral depressions, with sparse large round punctures separated by several times their diameter, each puncture with a microscopic seta, interspaces between punctures with scattered microscopic punctation; meso-metaventral suture indistinct, meso-metaventral sutural stria absent; intercoxal disc of metaventrite in males medially with large depression; metaventrite of females with only slight median longitudinal depression. Disc of metaventrite in both sexes almost smooth, punctation appears only along lateral and posterior margins. Lateral metaventral stria (Fig. 286) well impressed, almost straight, not reaching metacoxa; lateral disc of metaventrite (Fig. 286) depressed, with round shallow large punctures; metepisternum evenly punctate with similar punctation, punctures on fused metepimeron much sparser than those of metepisternum; lateral metepisternal stria (Fig. 286) present, deeply impressed, complete.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="67" pageNumber="68">
<paragraph pageId="67" pageNumber="68">
Figures 289-291. 289 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes falcifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="67" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="falcifer">Saprinodes falcifer</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1891 mandibles, dorsal view 290 labrum: left half depicting dorsal view and right half depicting epipharynx 291 antennal club, ventral view showing sensory structures of the antenna.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="67" pageNumber="68">Intercoxal disc of first abdominal ventrite in males with large depression, in females not depressed, completely striate laterally; surface of disc in males with scattered oblong punctation, punctures becoming sparser and finer medially, in females punctation much sparser and finer.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="67" pageNumber="68">Protibia (Fig. 287) slender, only very slightly dilated apically, terminating in massive protibial spur; setae of outer row very short, sparsely spaced; setae of median row even shorter than those of outer row, even; protarsal groove deep, designed to accommodate entire protarsus in repose; anterior protibial stria complete, costate; outer part of posterior surface of protibia (Fig. 288) with a row of sparsely spaced minuscule denticles; median part of posterior surface with a single row of regular minuscule setae; posterior protibial stria complete, very thin, with scattered minuscule setae; inner margin with single row of sparse microscopic setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="67" pageNumber="68">Mesotibia slender, outer margin with a single row of around five denticles growing in size apically; setae of outer row sparse, minuscule; setae of median row similar to those of outer row, between the two rows an additional complete stria present; posterior mesotibial stria shortened apically; anterior surface of mesotibia convex, with dense row of well-sclerotized short setae; anterior mesotibial stria complete; mesotibial spur inconspicuous; claws of apical tarsomere about half its length; metatibia basically similar to mesotibia, but denticles of outer margin much sparser than those of mesotibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="67" pageNumber="68">Male genitalia. Eighth sternite (Figs 292-293) separated longitudinally; vela with sparse short setae; eighth tergite and eighth sternite not fused laterally (Fig. 294). Ninth tergite (Figs 295-296) longitudinally fused medially; spiculum gastrale (Figs 297-298) gradually dilated on apical half, basal end slender, not dilated. Aedeagus (Figs 299-300) slender, slightly widening apically, slightly constricted before apex; basal piece of aedeagus very short, ratio of its length: length of parameres 1: 10; parameres of aedeagus fused almost along their entire length, with small circular aperture for median duct; aedeagus only slightly curved from lateral view, apex of aedeagus flattened dorso-ventrally.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="67" pageNumber="68">
<paragraph pageId="67" pageNumber="68">
Figures 292-300. 292 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinodes falcifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="67" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="falcifer">Saprinodes falcifer</taxonomicName>
Lewis, 1891 male terminalia: 8th sternite + 8th tergite, ventral view 293 ditto, dorsal view 294 ditto, lateral view 295 male terminalia: 9th + 10th tergites, dorsal view 296 ditto, lateral view 297 male terminalia: spiculum gastrale, ventral view 298 ditto, lateral view 299 male terminalia: aedeagus, dorsal view 300 ditto, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>