<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/afrinvertebr.59.30684" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6470913c-0ff8-4826-884d-836f1e67aab7" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154366190" ID-Pensoft-Pub="2305-2562-2-195" ID-ZBK="0F2906F5DE064F15BA2B69BDD7D2AAF1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="2305-2562-2-195" ModsDocOrigin="African Invertebrates 59 (2)" ModsDocTitle="Taxonomic revision of the assassin-fly genus Microphontes Londt, 1994 (Insecta, Diptera, Asilidae)" checkinTime="1552155250355" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Markee, Amanda &amp; Dikow, Torsten" docDate="2018" docId="F48B8A4A8E8438E51A0A1AB178045ED6" docLanguage="en" docName="AfrInvert 59(2): 195-237" docOrigin="African Invertebrates 59 (2)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/afrinvertebr.59.30684" docTitle="Microphontes Londt 1994" docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="195" masterDocId="FFC72C20C957F21C7C0EFFE1FF9EFFD0" masterDocTitle="Taxonomic revision of the assassin-fly genus Microphontes Londt, 1994 (Insecta, Diptera, Asilidae)" masterLastPageNumber="237" masterPageNumber="195" pageId="0" pageNumber="195" updateTime="1643468949448" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Taxonomic revision of the assassin-fly genus Microphontes Londt, 1994 (Insecta, Diptera, Asilidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Markee, Amanda</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Dikow, Torsten</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>African Invertebrates</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>59</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>195</mods:start>
<mods:end>237</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/afrinvertebr.59.30684</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/afrinvertebr.59.30684</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">2305-2562-2-195</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">0F2906F5DE064F15BA2B69BDD7D2AAF1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">0F2906F5DE064F15BA2B69BDD7D2AAF1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="154366190" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F48B8A4A8E8438E51A0A1AB178045ED6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F48B8A4A8E8438E51A0A1AB178045ED6" lastPageNumber="195" pageId="0" pageNumber="195">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="195" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/4AE2ACF4-F13B-4BE5-A4CA-4EBCB4916620" authority="Londt, 1994" authorityName="Londt" authorityYear="1994" class="Insecta" family="Asilidae" genus="Microphontes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Microphontes" order="Diptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="195" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Microphontes Londt, 1994</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="195" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Asilidae" genus="Microphontes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Microphontes" order="Diptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="195" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Microphontes</taxonomicName>
Londt, 1994: 86. Type-species: 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Asilidae" genus="Microphontes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Microphontes whittingtoni" order="Diptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="195" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="whittingtoni">Microphontes whittingtoni</taxonomicName>
Londt, 1994, by original designation.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="195" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">
The genus can be delineated by its small size with a wing length of only 3.0-
<quantity metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.5" unit="mm" value="55.0">5.5 mm</quantity>
, mystacal setae restricted to the lower facial margin, at least weakly macrosetose ante- and postpronotum, short to long setose dorsal anepisternum, male terminalia rotated by 90-180°, short or long postero-median projection on the hypandrium of males and presence of postero-paramedian pores on abdominal tergite 
<quantity metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.032" unit="in" value="8.0">8 in</quantity>
females.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="195" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">
Wing (Figs 6, 11, 15, 26, 30, 36, 38, 42, 44, 54): 3.0-
<quantity metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.5" unit="mm" value="55.0">5.5 mm</quantity>
, hyaline, evenly microtrichose; C circumambient (developed around entire wing), anterior wing margin straight; R2+3 distally relatively straight, r1 open; R4 terminating anterior to wing apex, relatively straight, stump vein (
<collectionCode>R</collectionCode>
3) absent (except in left wing of one specimen); r4 open, R4 and R5 more or less parallel; R5 terminating posterior to wing apex; r5 open; M1 terminating posterior to wing apex; cell d closed by base of M2 and m-m, M2 and m-m not aligned, r-m situated either in proximal or distal half or in centre; m3 open; cua open; alula reduced in size to small lobe; microtrichia on posterior wing margin arranged in a single plane.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">
<specimenCount>♀</specimenCount>
abdomen and genitalia (Figs 21-25): T7 and S7 without modifications, ovipositor comprised of 8th and following segments, T6-8 either grey pubescent or T8 entirely or partly apubescent, setation directed anteriorly on T6-7 and dorsally on T8 or entirely dorsally; postero-paramedian T8 pores present, either distinct and opening slightly elevated above tergite surface or indistinct and not elevated; T8 with or without internal apodeme anteriorly, S8 plate-like, hypogynial valves separated (surrounded by membrane); T9 and T10 entirely fused, sclerites not distinguishable, T10 divided into 2 heavily sclerotised acanthophorite plates, with 6-9 acanthophorite spines per plate; cerci simple and flat, long yellowish setose; 3 spermathecae, either all equally large or median spermatheca larger than lateral ones, reaching anterior end of segment 5, 6, or 7; common spermathecal duct either short and not extending beyond tip of genital fork (
<collectionCode>S</collectionCode>
9, furca) or very long, extending well-beyond tip of genital fork, individual spermathecal ducts either short or long; ejection apparatus not observable; spermathecal reservoirs formed by either more or less expanded ducts to sac-shaped reservoirs or spherical reservoirs, heavily sclerotised; genital fork (
<collectionCode>S</collectionCode>
9, furca) formed by single sclerite either inverted Y-shaped or inverted V-shaped, median sclerite (at posterior tip) absent, anterior apodeme absent or present, short plate-like apodeme.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="195">
<specimenCount>♂</specimenCount>
abdomen and terminalia (Figs 17-20, 56-70): T1-T8 and S1-S8 either entire (without modifications) or T1-T7 and S1-S7 entire and T8 + S8 reduced to ring of sclerites; hypopygium light brown to black, rotated either by 90°or 180°, directed posteriorly; epandrium divided medially into 2 halves, joined proximally; hypandrium well-developed, triangular, posterior margin with either short or long postero-median projection, distinctly separated from epandrium by gonocoxite, but approximating epandrium proximally, not fused to gonocoxite; gonocoxite entirely free from epandrium; gonocoxal apodeme present, short, entirely confined to hypopygium; gonostylus present, positioned proximally on gonocoxite; subepandrial sclerite asetose, ventrally smooth (without protuberances), laterally straight (without protuberances), distal margin simple, straight margin; cerci separate (not fused medially); phallus very short, tip at level of origin of gonostyli, 1 phallic prong, tip pointed, without any protuberance, parameral sheath short (sperm sac entirely free), lateral ejaculatory process present, large triangular sclerite, lateral ejaculatory process and ventral parameral sheath free (not surrounded by ventral parameral sheath), ejaculatory apodeme formed by single vertical plate (2 lateral surfaces).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>