<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047559" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BB25A9D6-18C5-405A-B3B6-18DE7C18CE09" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="F59B9D5E26EFDB743DC02057243DB8DB" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio wa Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="BB25A9D6-18C5-405A-B3B6-18DE7C18CE09" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="243" lastPageNumber="244" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="241" pageNumber="242" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047559" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BB25A9D6-18C5-405A-B3B6-18DE7C18CE09" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F59B9D5E26EFDB743DC02057243DB8DB" lastPageId="243" lastPageNumber="244" pageId="241" pageNumber="242">
<subSubSection pageId="241" pageNumber="242" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="241" pageNumber="242">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/BB25A9D6-18C5-405A-B3B6-18DE7C18CE09" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio wa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="241" pageNumber="242" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="wa">Oxyscelio wa Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="241" pageNumber="242">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 407-412; Morphbank105
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="243" lastPageNumber="244" pageId="241" pageNumber="242" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="241" pageNumber="242">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="241" pageNumber="242">Female. Body length 3.2-3.55 mm (n=10).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="241" pageNumber="242">Radicle color and shade: same as scape, both dark brown. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="241" pageNumber="242">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by a set of irregular elevations. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, complete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: granulate. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: granulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="242" lastPageNumber="243" pageId="241" pageNumber="242">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: densely covered with setiferous puncta. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally and ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal 
<pageBreakToken pageId="242" pageNumber="243" start="start">vein</pageBreakToken>
: present. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="242" pageNumber="243">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate; umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">
<pageBreakToken pageId="243" pageNumber="244" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Body length 3.1-3.3 mm (n=7). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad; as long as broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: truncate.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="243" pageNumber="244">
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">
Figures 407-412. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio wa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="243" pageNumber="244" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="wa">Oxyscelio wa</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 449005) 407 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 408 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 409 Head, anterior view. Paratype female (OSUC 449009) 410 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 449019) 411 Antenna 412 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank105
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="243" pageNumber="244" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">
Both sexes: Frontal depression with broadly interrupted transverse carinae, including some above dorsal separator; submedian carina weakly indicated but complete. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by weak rugae. Occipital carina complete, weakly convex medially. Metascutellum deeply concave, emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein present, short. Coxa darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A4, A5 much broader than long. Mesoscutellum without granulate sculpture. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T6 or beyond metasomal apex. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. T6 without metasomal flanges, main body of tergum not separated from apical rim, strongly sloping apically but not concave. Male: A4 broader than long, A11 slightly longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach beyond metasomal apex. T7 tiny, truncate apically. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio wa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="243" pageNumber="244" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="wa">Oxyscelio wa</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="243" pageNumber="244" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Oxyscelio nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
and in some ways to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio hyalinipennis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="243" pageNumber="244" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hyalinipennis">Oxyscelio hyalinipennis</taxonomicName>
, but differs in having a shorter A4 and A5 in females, and in having a postmarginal vein in combination with a truncate T7 in males. Known specimens of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio wa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="243" pageNumber="244" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="wa">Oxyscelio wa</taxonomicName>
also have dark coxae, which does not occur in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio hyalinipennis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="243" pageNumber="244" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hyalinipennis">Oxyscelio hyalinipennis</taxonomicName>
. The fore wing venation is at most slightly separated from the anterior wing margin, which aids in distinguishing this species from 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nigricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="243" pageNumber="244" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigricoxa">Oxyscelio nigricoxa</taxonomicName>
, a species where the venation does not closely approach the anterior wing margin.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="243" pageNumber="244" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">Arbitrary combination of letters, does not change spelling to agree with gender.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="243" pageNumber="244" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307119]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="243" pageNumber="244" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="243" pageNumber="244">Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, Mount Cooke, 17.II-18.IV.1991, malaise trap, M. S. Harvey &amp; J. M. Waldock, OSUC 449005 (deposited in WAMP). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 9 females, 7 males, OSUC 449006-449021 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>