<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" ID-GBIF-Dataset="92d38eff-94a4-404e-a09c-d535155922c8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043383" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-292-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-292-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 292" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" checkinTime="1451247388242" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="4BA66606F45AAE2CBF92AF8F5EE6910F" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 292: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 292" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" docTitle="Oxyscelio marginalis" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="164" lastPageNumber="165" masterDocId="FFB8FF92FF98D87CFFAE2F6B1E57FFC8" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="162" pageNumber="163" updateTime="1643534109502" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>292</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-292-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043383" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:4BA66606F45AAE2CBF92AF8F5EE6910F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4BA66606F45AAE2CBF92AF8F5EE6910F" lastPageId="164" lastPageNumber="165" pageId="162" pageNumber="163">
<subSubSection pageId="162" pageNumber="163" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="162" pageNumber="163">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D133686B-181B-4F91-BDE2-11942282B77D" authority="Kieffer" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio marginalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="162" pageNumber="163" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="marginalis">Oxyscelio marginalis (Kieffer)</taxonomicName>
Figures 312-315Morphbank87
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="162" pageNumber="163" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="162" pageNumber="163">
<taxonomicName genus="Camptoteleia" lsidName="Camptoteleia marginalis" pageId="162" pageNumber="163" rank="species" species="marginalis">Camptoteleia marginalis</taxonomicName>
Kieffer, 1916: 64, 172 (original description, keyed); 
<bibRefCitation pageId="162" pageNumber="163">Kieffer 1926</bibRefCitation>
: 380, 385 (description, keyed).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="162" pageNumber="163">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio marginalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="162" pageNumber="163" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="marginalis">Oxyscelio marginalis</taxonomicName>
(Kieffer): 
<bibRefCitation pageId="162" pageNumber="163">Dodd 1931</bibRefCitation>
: 76 (generic transfer).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="163" lastPageNumber="164" pageId="162" pageNumber="163" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="162" pageNumber="163">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="162" pageNumber="163">Female. Body length 4.35 mm (n=1).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="162" pageNumber="163">Radicle color: same color as scape. Scape color: Brown. A4: longer than broad. A5: broader than long. Antennal club: formed, segments compact.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="162" pageNumber="163">Interantennal process: not elongate. Median longitudinal elevation in frontal depression: absent. Frontal depression: flat. Frontal depression sculpture: with 3 or more broadly interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: weak, shallow and rounded or formed by ledge. Submedian carina medially: without peak. Concavity across dorsal part of frontal depression: absent. Depression extending ventrally from median ocellus: absent. Upper frons: not hood-like. Malar area near antennal foramen: without carina or expansion. Malar area at mouth corner: with radiating striae. Smooth strip along posterior side of malar sulcus: absent or not consistently broad. Middle genal carina: absent. Direction of middle genal carina dorsally: parallel to eye margin. Major sculpture of gena anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: punctate. Median carina extending posteriorly from hyperoccipital carina: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by rugae. Lateral connection between hyperoccipital and occipital carinae: absent. Area between vertex and occipital carina: umbilicate-foveate; irregularly rugose. Occipital carina medially: absent. Lateral corners of occipital carina: not protruding.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="163" lastPageNumber="164" pageId="162" pageNumber="163">
Lateral pronotal area: without bulge projecting towards anterior pit. Epomial corner: strong. Netrion surface anteriorly: not inflexed. Mesoscutum anteriorly: steep. Mesoscutal median carina: present and complete. Longitudinal carina between median carina and notauli: absent. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of 
<pageBreakToken pageId="163" pageNumber="164" start="start">medial</pageBreakToken>
mesoscutum posteriorly: granulate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum: umbilicate-foveate; umbilicate-punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum medially: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum laterally: granulate. Mesoscutellar apex: convex or straight. Setae along anterior limit of femoral depression: arising from rows of foveae. Number of carinae crossing speculum above femoral depression: 2. Number of carinae crossing femoral depression: 3-5. Mesepimeral sulcus pits: more than 5. Metascutellum dorsally: concave. Metascutellar sculpture dorsally: smooth or with transverse carinae. Median carina of metascutellum: absent or branched. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellar apex: weakly emarginate. Metapleuron above ventral metapleural area: crossed by carinae. Metasomal depression setae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae anteromedially: weakly diverging. Anterior areoles of metasomal depression: one or more areoles present. Anterior longitudinal carinae in metasomal depression: absent. Lateral propodeal areas: separated medially. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex: reaching beyond T6.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">T1 midlobe: with 5 longitudinal carinae. T1: without anterior bulge. T2: with straight longitudinal striae or rugae. T6: broader than long. Apical flange of T6: exposed apically. Metasomal apex: rounded. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate-punctate. Microsculpture of T6: granulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">Male. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="163" pageNumber="164" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">Female: Frontal depression flat, not margined laterally and with only its dorsal portion well-indicated. Frons without elevation between antennal foramen and eye. Hyperoccipital carina present, continuous with anterior genal carina. Netrion smooth between its anterior and posterior rows of pits. Metascutellum weakly emarginate, subrectangular. Metasomal depression elongate, without median carina; lateral propodeal carinae narrowly separated anteriorly. T1 midlobe with 5 longitudinal carinae. T6 rounded apically.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="163" pageNumber="164" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=5027]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="163" pageNumber="164" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">Neotype, female: PHILIPPINES: Benguet Prov., Luzon Isl., Baguio, no date, Baker, OSUC 268217 (deposited in USNM).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="164" lastPageNumber="165" pageId="163" pageNumber="164" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="163" pageNumber="164">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="164" lastPageNumber="165" pageId="163" pageNumber="164">
The type material of 
<taxonomicName genus="Camptoteleia" lsidName="Camptoteleia marginalis" pageId="163" pageNumber="164" rank="species" species="marginalis">Camptoteleia marginalis</taxonomicName>
Kieffer, collected from Palawan Island (Puerto Princesa) in the Philippines, could not be found after an extensive search of collections known to house Kieffer type material. The neotype of 
<taxonomicName genus="Camptoteleia" lsidName="Camptoteleia marginalis" pageId="163" pageNumber="164" rank="species" species="marginalis">Camptoteleia marginalis</taxonomicName>
is presently designated to clarify the taxonomic status of the species. It was selected because of its collection locality, and because it agrees with 
<bibRefCitation pageId="163" pageNumber="164">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kieffer’s">Kieffer's</normalizedToken>
(1916)
</bibRefCitation>
description in having largely granulate sculpture, a narrow frontal depression that is not laterally carinate, well-separated mandibular teeth, and a thick marginal vein that is nearly as long as the stigmal vein. The neotype female is the only examined specimen from the Philippines that reasonably matches the above characters, and we therefore conclude that Kieffer was mistaken in his account of the postmarginal and stigmal veins in the lost holotype. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio marginalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="163" pageNumber="164" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="marginalis">Oxyscelio marginalis</taxonomicName>
is an unusual species within its genus, but agrees with the cuculli-group in having a complete hyperoccipital carina that is continuous with an anterior genal carina. The relatively flat frontal depression is apparently a convergent character shared with some other species from the Philippines, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="164" pageNumber="165" start="start">and</pageBreakToken>
is correlated with reduced surface sculpture. The shape of the lateral propodeal carinae suggests that this species belongs in the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio convergens" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="164" pageNumber="165" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="convergens">Oxyscelio convergens</taxonomicName>
species complex within the cuculli-group.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="164" pageNumber="165">
<paragraph pageId="164" pageNumber="165">
Figures 312-315. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio marginalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="164" pageNumber="165" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="marginalis">Oxyscelio marginalis</taxonomicName>
(Kieffer), neotype female (OSUC 268217) 312 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 313 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 314 Head, anterior view 315 Fore wing venation, dorsal view. Morphbank87
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>