<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.671.12052" ID-GBIF-Dataset="44c4432b-b368-4773-b77b-2b8fa075a420" ID-GBIF-Taxon="128810336" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-671-1" ID-ZBK="BE1A34648F5E46A58597FAF2B5D259BD" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DD961DAC-CECF-49A2-86D7-30A9E13270A1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-671-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 671" ModsDocTitle="A new anchialine Stephos Scott from the Yucatan Peninsula with notes on the biogeography and diversity of the genus (Copepoda, Calanoida, Stephidae)" checkinTime="1493291504971" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Suarez-Morales, Eduardo, Gutierrez-Aguirre, Martha A., Cervantes-Martinez, Adrian &amp; Iliffe, Thomas M." docDate="2017" docId="AAC6AB3AA1D0F1A6AF3D53852D6CFE09" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 671: 1-17" docOrigin="ZooKeys 671" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.671.12052" docTitle="Stephos fernandoi Suarez-Morales, Gutierrez-Aguirre, Cervantes-Martinez &amp; Iliffe, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="DD961DAC-CECF-49A2-86D7-30A9E13270A1" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" masterDocId="FF9C3020FFD4FFCE4C1F5A1EFF80FFF6" masterDocTitle="A new anchialine Stephos Scott from the Yucatan Peninsula with notes on the biogeography and diversity of the genus (Copepoda, Calanoida, Stephidae)" masterLastPageNumber="17" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" updateTime="1643556891011" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new anchialine Stephos Scott from the Yucatan Peninsula with notes on the biogeography and diversity of the genus (Copepoda, Calanoida, Stephidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Suarez-Morales, Eduardo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gutierrez-Aguirre, Martha A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cervantes-Martinez, Adrian</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Iliffe, Thomas M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>671</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>17</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.671.12052</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.671.12052</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-671-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">BE1A34648F5E46A58597FAF2B5D259BD</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">BE1A34648F5E46A58597FAF2B5D259BD</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="128810336" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DD961DAC-CECF-49A2-86D7-30A9E13270A1" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AAC6AB3AA1D0F1A6AF3D53852D6CFE09" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/DD961DAC-CECF-49A2-86D7-30A9E13270A1" class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos fernandoi" order="Calanoida" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fernandoi">Stephos fernandoi</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="1">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1, 2, 3, 4
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Holotype. One adult ♀, collected on 6 July 2014 from the anchialine cave of Cenote Tres Potrillos, Cozumel Island (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="20.45089">20°27'3.2&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-86.98733">86°59'14.4&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
), Quintana Roo, Mexico. Specimen dissected on slide deposited in the collection of Zooplankton of El Colegio de la Frontera Sur (ECOSUR) in Chetumal, Mexico, under number ECO-CHZ-09411. Allotype: one adult ♂, collected on same date and site, specimen dissected (ECO-CHZ-09412). Paratypes: four dissected adult ♀♀, one dissected adult ♂, slides (ECO-CHZ-09413), two undissected ♀♀, eight undissected ♂♂ (ECO-CHZ-09414), and three undissected ♀♀, three ♂♂ (USNM-1422288), all from same date and site, ethanol-preserved, vials.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="3" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Descriptions.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Female. Mean length of prosome: 0.343 mm (n = 13); total length including caudal rami = 0.475 mm (n = 13). Body with typical calanoid shape, relatively robust in lateral and dorsal views, prosome 5-segmented, widest at first pedigerous somite (Figs 1A, 4A, B). Cephalosome and first pedigerous somite completely separate, fourth and fifth pedigerous somites fused, with posterolateral corners rounded, moderately produced, symmetrical (Fig. 4A). Rostrum weakly developed, represented by small medial expansion, rostral points absent (Fig. 4C). Urosome 4-segmented, representing 31% of total body length. Genital double-somite relatively long, almost 40% of urosome, barrel-shaped, symmetrical, weakly expanded mid-ventrally, expansion associated with genital field (Fig. 2J). Single gonopore opening ventrally at proximal 1/3 of somite; adjacent ventral surface of somite ornamented with 4 slender spiniform elements (arrowed in Fig. 4E) inserted at each side of simple, transverse genital operculum. Anal somite shortest of urosome, subrectangular, about 10% of urosome length, cuticular ornamentations absent on dorsal and ventral surfaces (Figs 2J, 4F).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos fernandoi" order="Calanoida" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fernandoi">Stephos fernandoi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., adult female from Cozumel, Mexico. A habitus, lateral view B antennule, segments 1-16 C antennule segments 17-24 D antennule segment 24 showing apical process E antenna F mandibular palp G gnathal base H maxillule I maxilla. Scale bars: A 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; D 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; B, C, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–I">E-I</normalizedToken>
20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Caudal rami subrectangular, symmetrical, length/width ratio = 1.6-1.7, armed with 6 caudal setae (II-VII) (Fig. 4F). Inner margin naked except for displaced dorsal seta (VII) inserted on proximal 1/4 of inner margin, seta reaching beyond distal margin of ramus (Fig. 4F). Caudal seta I absent, seta II (Fig. 4F) reduced, inserted near base of seta III. Terminal setae III-VI well developed. All ramal setae biserially plumose.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Antennule (Fig. 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
) 24-segmented, reaching posterior margin of preanal somite. Armature per segments as follows: segmental number (ancestral segment, setae (s) + aesthetasc (ae)): 1(I-II, 3s); 2(III-IV,4s + ae), 3(V, 2s), 4(VI, 2s), 5(VII, 2s), 6(VIII, 1s + ae), 7(IX, 2s), 8(X-XI, 3s), 9 (XII, 1s+ae), 10 (XIII, 1s), 11(XIV, 2s + ae), 12(XV, 2s), 13(XVI, 2s + ae), 14(XVII, 1s), 15(XVIII, 1s), 16(XIX, 1s), 17(XX, 1s), 18(XXI,1s + ae), 19 (XXII,1s), 20(XXIII,1s), 21(XXIV,2s +1s), 22(XXV,1s +1s), 23(XXVI, 1s +1s), 24(XXVII-XXVIII, 3s + ae) (Figs 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
). One of the setal elements on segment 12 spiniform (arrow in Fig. 4D). Distal segment with apical acute process present in some specimens (Fig. 1D).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="2" pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Antenna (Fig. 1E) biramous, with exopod longer than endopod. Coxa armed with one seta. Basis with two distal subequal setae on medial margin. Endopod 2-segmented, first segment long, cylindrical, with short seta inserted at 2/3 of medial margin; distal portion of terminal segment with two lobes, proximal lobe with 8 setae; distal lobe with single short, lateral seta plus five long terminal setae. Exopod indistinctly 7-segmented, first segment with one long seta, second segment longest, armed with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="2" start="start">three</pageBreakToken>
setae, one proximal, one medial and one on distal position. Segments 3-6 with 1, 2, 1, 1 setae, respectively. Distal segment with crown of three long, terminal setae, subequal in length and diameter.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="3" start="start">Mandible</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 1G) with gnathobase armed with four large monocuspid ventral teeth plus three smaller bicuspid teeth, dorsal monocuspid tooth, and short dorsal seta. Serial teeth distinctly separated from large ventralmost tooth by diastema. Palp biramous (Fig. 1F), basis robust, armed with four subequal setae inserted on medial margin. Endopod short, 2-segmented; proximal segment with two short and one long setae, outer margin protuberant; distal segment subrectangular, with 10 setae, one reduced. Exopod indistinctly 5-segmented, armed with 1, 1, 1, 1, 2 setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Maxillule (Fig. 1H) with praecoxal arthrite bearing nine spiniform marginal setae. Coxal epipodite with nine setae, coxal endite with two setae. Basis with proximal endite bearing four setae, distal basal endite armed with five setae. Endopod reduced, not articulated to basis, indistinctly 3-segmented, proximal segment with four setae, second segment with two setae, distal segment with six. Exopod oblong, with ten subequal setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Maxilla (Fig. 1I) indistinctly 6-segmented including precoxa, coxa, allobasis and 3-segmented endopod. Praecoxal and coxal endites with 5, 3, 3, 3 setae, distal coxal endite with two stout spinulated setae. Basal endite of allobasis with 3 setae, incorporated endopodal segment with single seta. Free endopodal segments armed with 1, 1, 3 setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Maxilliped (Fig. 2A) indistinctly nine-segmented, precoxa and coxa partially fused, precoxa unarmed, with cluster of spinules. Coxa with three groups of setae, proximal endite with 1 seta, middle endite with two, distal with two. Basis ornamented with row of short spinules; armed with 3 setae, one shorter than the rest. Endopod six-segmented, armed as follows: 2, 4, 4, 2, 2, 4. Basal and endopodal setae slender, distally attenuated.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Legs 1-4 (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–E">B-E</normalizedToken>
) biramous, increasing in size posteriorly. First swimming leg (Fig. 2B) with three-segmented exopod and one-segmented endopod; coxa subrectangular, with short outer coxal seta not reaching distal margin of basal segment; row of spinules at insertion of coxal seta. Basipod with long, recurved inner plumose seta reaching beyond distal margin of third exopodal segment; outer basipodal seta slender. Endopod with outer knob ornamented with 1-3 minute apical setules (Fig. 2B, G). First exopodal segment with row of spinules. Outer spine on third exopodal segment elongate, spine shorter in some specimens (arrowed in Fig. 2F). Second leg with two-segmented endopod (Fig. 2C), legs 3 and 4 with three-segmented exopods and endopods, with articulate setae (Fig. 2D, E). Armature formula of legs 1-4 as in Table 1.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos fernandoi" order="Calanoida" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fernandoi">Stephos fernandoi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., adult female from Cozumel, Mexico. A maxilliped B leg 1 C leg 2 D leg 3 E leg 4 F leg 1 exopod, another specimen showing reduced outermost apical spine (arrow) G leg 1 endopod, another specimen H male leg 1 I female leg 5, anterior view J fifth pedigerous somite and urosome, lateral view. Scale bars: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–I">A-I</normalizedToken>
20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; J 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Fifth legs (Fig. 2I) reduced, symmetrical, uniramous, two-segmented with proximal segment cylindrical, distal segment proximally globose, forming long spiniform bipinnate apical process (Figs 2I, 4G, H).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Male. Body slightly longer than female, average total length: 0.493 mm (n =10); length of prosome: 0.31 mm (Fig. 3A). Rostrum as in female. Urosome 5-segmented, representing 32% of total body length. First urosomite symmetrical; anal somite shortest. Caudal rami relatively short, symmetrical, caudal setae as in female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Left and right antennules 24-segmented, lacking geniculation, slightly longer than in female when extended posteriorly; antennulary armature as in female. Mouthparts and swimming legs 1-4 as in female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Fifth legs (Figs 3B, 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–L">I-L</normalizedToken>
) uniramous, asymmetrical. Left leg five-segmented, about as long as right counterpart; proximal segment widest of ramus, with inner margin expanded. Second, third, and fourth segments elongate, fourth with triangular plate on distomedial angle; distal segment with three terminal lamellae tapering distally plus subdistal subtriangular process, and with short seta inserted proximally on medial margin (Fig. 4J). Right fifth leg (Fig. 3B) four-segmented, first and second segments cylindrical, robust, unarmed. Third segment elongate and tapering. Fourth segment very slender and bifurcating distally into 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“C”">&quot;C&quot;</normalizedToken>
-shaped structure furnished with 6-8 peg-like elements along bifurcation (Fig. 4L). End of subdistal process acute, opposite end with apical leaf-like expansion (Fig. 4K).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos fernandoi" order="Calanoida" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fernandoi">Stephos fernandoi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., adult male from Cozumel, Mexico. A habitus, lateral view B leg 5. L=left ramus, R= right ramus. Scale bars: A 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; B 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
The new species is named after the Mexican carcinologist Dr. Fernando Alvarez (Instituto de 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Biología">Biologia</normalizedToken>
, UNAM, Mexico), who has significantly contributed to the knowledge of the Mexican crustacean fauna, particularly from caves and anchialine habitats.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
The new species was included in the diverse stephid genus 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos" order="Calanoida" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Stephos</taxonomicName>
based on its possession of the following characters: 1) cephalosome and first pedigerous somite separate, pedigers 4-5 partially fused, 2) female urosome 4-segmented, male five-segmented; 3) caudal rami with 4 terminal setae (
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–VI">III-VI</normalizedToken>
), dorsal caudal seta VII inserted on inner margin; 4) antennules 24-segmented in male and female, lacking geniculation in male; 5) female leg 5 uniramous, one or two-segmented, distal segment tapering, ornamented; 6) male fifth legs uniramous, strongly asymmetrical, modified into grasping organ, left leg five-segmented, with complex distal segment, right leg slender (
<bibRefCitation author="Bradford-Grieve, J" journalOrPublisher="New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="13 - 27" title="New species of benthopelagic copepods of the genus Stephos (Calanoida: Stephidae) from Wellington Harbour, New Zealand." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00288330.1999.9516853" volume="33" year="1999">Bradford-Grieve 1999</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Based on the morphology of the male fifth legs, 
<bibRefCitation author="Bradford-Grieve, J" journalOrPublisher="New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="13 - 27" title="New species of benthopelagic copepods of the genus Stephos (Calanoida: Stephidae) from Wellington Harbour, New Zealand." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00288330.1999.9516853" volume="33" year="1999">Bradford-Grieve (1999)</bibRefCitation>
divided the species of 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos" order="Calanoida" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Stephos</taxonomicName>
into four distinct groups. The new species 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. fernandoi" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="fernandoi">S. fernandoi</taxonomicName>
can be assigned to &quot;group IV&quot; by its possession of a male right leg 5 with a narrow fourth segment. Currently, this group includes nine species: 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. pentacanthos" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="pentacanthos">S. pentacanthos</taxonomicName>
Chen &amp; Zhang, 1965 from off China, 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. tsuyazakiensis" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="tsuyazakiensis">S. tsuyazakiensis</taxonomicName>
Tanaka, 1966 from Japan, 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. rustadi" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="rustadi">S. rustadi</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Strömgren">Stroemgren</normalizedToken>
, 1969 from Norway, 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. morii" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="morii">S. morii</taxonomicName>
Greenwood, 1977 from Australia, 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. pacificus" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="pacificus">S. pacificus</taxonomicName>
Ohtsuka &amp; Hiromi, 1987 from Japan, 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. angulatus" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="angulatus">S. angulatus</taxonomicName>
Bradford-Grieve, 1999 from New Zealand, 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. marsalensis" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="marsalensis">S. marsalensis</taxonomicName>
Costanzo, Campolmi &amp; Zagami, 2000 from Italy, 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. vivesi" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="vivesi">S. vivesi</taxonomicName>
Jaume, Boxshall &amp; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Gràcia">Gracia</normalizedToken>
, 2008 from the Balearic Islands, and 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. goejinensis" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="goejinensis">S. goejinensis</taxonomicName>
Moon, Yeon &amp; Venmathi Maran, 2015 from Korea (see table 1 in 
<bibRefCitation author="Bradford-Grieve, J" journalOrPublisher="New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="13 - 27" title="New species of benthopelagic copepods of the genus Stephos (Calanoida: Stephidae) from Wellington Harbour, New Zealand." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00288330.1999.9516853" volume="33" year="1999">Bradford-Grieve 1999</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Jaume, D" journalOrPublisher="Systematics and Biodiversity" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="503 - 520" title="Stephos (Copepoda: Calanoida: Stephidae) from Balearic caves (W Mediterranean)." url="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1477200008002764" volume="6" year="2008">Jaume et al. 2008</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Moon, SY" journalOrPublisher="ZooKeys" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="21 - 40" title="Two new species of benthopelagic Stephos (Copepoda, Calanoida, Stephidae) from Korea." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.495.7862" volume="495" year="2015">Moon et al. 2015</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<caption ID-Table-UUID="5679BEA593F746C69C45BB37A00820B2" httpUri="http://table.plazi.org/id/5679BEA593F746C69C45BB37A00820B2" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Table 1. Armature formula of swimming legs 1-4. Roman numerals indicate spines and Arabic numerals are setae.</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<table pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<tr pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<th colspan="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rowspan="1">coxa</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rowspan="1">basis</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rowspan="1">exopod</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rowspan="1">endopod</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
The new species is the only one in this group with a right leg 5 ramus combining a distal segment (segment 4) with diverging processes set at right angles with acute tips plus a series of peg-like elements along the longest process (Fig. 4L). It differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. angulatus" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="angulatus">S. angulatus</taxonomicName>
because in this species, the processes are both apically rounded and the segment lacks the peg-like elements observed in the new species. The left ramus has a similar structure in both species, with segment 4 bearing a distal lobular process (
<bibRefCitation author="Bradford-Grieve, J" journalOrPublisher="New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="13 - 27" title="New species of benthopelagic copepods of the genus Stephos (Calanoida: Stephidae) from Wellington Harbour, New Zealand." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00288330.1999.9516853" volume="33" year="1999">Bradford-Grieve 1999</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 8; Fig. 4L) and three distal lamellae, but the new species has an additional subdistal process (Figs 3B, 4J). In 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. marsalensis" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="marsalensis">S. marsalensis</taxonomicName>
, the distal segment of right male P5 is unbranched (
<bibRefCitation author="Costanzo, G" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Plankton Research" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="2007 - 2014" title="Stephosmarsalensis new species (Copepoda, Calanoida, Stephidae) from coastal waters of Sicily, Italy." url="https://doi.org/10.1093/plankt/22.10.2007" volume="22" year="2000">Costanzo et al. 2000</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 4d), thus diverging from the bifid condition found in 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. fernandoi" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="fernandoi">S. fernandoi</taxonomicName>
; also, the left leg has five lamellate hyaline processes on the distal segment vs. only three such processes in the new species. The anchialine 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. vivesi" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="vivesi">S. vivesi</taxonomicName>
has a left leg with eight narrow lamellae and a relatively simple, spatulate distal segment of the right leg with two proximal processes (
<bibRefCitation author="Jaume, D" journalOrPublisher="Systematics and Biodiversity" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="503 - 520" title="Stephos (Copepoda: Calanoida: Stephidae) from Balearic caves (W Mediterranean)." url="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1477200008002764" volume="6" year="2008">Jaume et al. 2008</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="b–d">b-d</normalizedToken>
), thus diverging from the pattern observed in the new species. The fifth leg of the new species differs from that of 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. geojinensis" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species" species="geojinensis">S. geojinensis</taxonomicName>
in the number of lamellae on the distal segment of the left leg, three (Fig. 4J) vs. seven 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">long</pageBreakToken>
plus 13 short lamellae, and right leg with distal segment bifurcate, with both branches subequally long (Fig. 3B) vs. outer branch extremely long, inner branch reduced (
<bibRefCitation author="Moon, SY" journalOrPublisher="ZooKeys" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="21 - 40" title="Two new species of benthopelagic Stephos (Copepoda, Calanoida, Stephidae) from Korea." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.495.7862" volume="495" year="2015">Moon et al. 2015</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 4d). The same kind of distally asymmetrical right fifth leg is present in 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. tsuyazakiensis" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="tsuyazakiensis">S. tsuyazakiensis</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Tanaka, O" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Marine Biological Association of India, Symposium on Crustacea" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" pagination="38 - 50" title="Neritic CopepodaCalanoida from the north-west coast of Kyushu." volume="1" year="1966">Tanaka 1966</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 1o), thus differing from the new species. In 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. morii" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="morii">S. morii</taxonomicName>
, the right leg distal segment has a strong inner bulb-like process (
<bibRefCitation author="Greenwood, JG" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="49 - 67" title="Calanoid copepods of Moreton Bay (Queensland). 2. Families Calocalanidae to Centropagidae." volume="88" year="1977">Greenwood 1977</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 4g) which is absent in the new species; also, the left leg terminal segment has a long, distinctive spiniform process on subdistal position which is not present in 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. fernandoi" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="fernandoi">S. fernandoi</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 3B). In 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. rustadi" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="rustadi">S. rustadi</taxonomicName>
, the right leg distal segment is chela-like, with an expanded inner margin and the left leg is clearly shorter that its right counterpart and has three distinctive hook-like processes (
<bibRefCitation author="Stroemgren, T" journalOrPublisher="Sarsia" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" pagination="1 - 8" title="A new species of Stephos (Copepoda, Calanoida) from the Norwegian west coast." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00364827.1969.10411141" volume="37" year="1969">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Strömgren">Stroemgren</normalizedToken>
1969
</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 3f), thus diverging from the fifth leg structure of the new species. In 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. penthacanthos" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="penthacanthos">S. penthacanthos</taxonomicName>
, the right fifth leg has a spiniform process on the outer margin and the terminal segment is modified into a long, slender claw-like process, curved inwardly (
<bibRefCitation author="Chen, QC" journalOrPublisher="Studia Marina Sinica" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="20 - 131" title="The planktonic copepods of the Yellow Sea and the East China Sea. 1. Calanoida." volume="7" year="1965">Chen and Zhang 1965</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 20.5), thus differing from the spatulate distal segment described in the new species. In 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. pacificus" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="pacificus">S. pacificus</taxonomicName>
, the right fifth leg distal segment is relatively simple, represented by an elongate, narrow unbranched structure (
<bibRefCitation author="Ohtsuka, S" journalOrPublisher="Publications of the Seto Marine Biological Laboratory" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="219 - 232" title="Calanoid copepods collected from the near-bottom in Tanabe Bay on the Pacific coast of the middle Honshu, Japan. III. Stephidae." volume="32" year="1987">Ohtsuka and Hiromi 1987</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 3f), different from the pattern observed in the new species, clearly branched (Fig. 3B).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos fernandoi" order="Calanoida" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fernandoi">Stephos fernandoi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., from Cozumel, Mexico. SEM-processed specimens. Female. A habitus, semi-lateral view B same, lateral view, another specimen C rostrum, ventral view D antennule segments 9-13, spiniform seta on segment 12 arrowed E genital double-somite, ventral surface showing ornamentation (arrows) F caudal rami showing caudal setae II-VII, ventral view G distal segment of leg 5 H leg 5, ventral view. Male. I left leg 5 showing segmentation J same, detail of distal segment K right leg 5, distal segment, detail of apical end L right leg 5, distal segment. Scale bars A, B 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; C, D, H, I 20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–G">E-G</normalizedToken>
, L 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; J, K 5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
The female fifth leg of 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. fernandoi" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="fernandoi">S. fernandoi</taxonomicName>
differs from that known in most species of 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos" order="Calanoida" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Stephos</taxonomicName>
, which has a medial seta and/or a row of spinules on the distal segment. It most closely resembles the fifth legs of the two species of 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Miostephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Miostephos" order="Calanoida" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Miostephos</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. cubrobex" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="cubrobex">M. cubrobex</taxonomicName>
from Cuba (
<bibRefCitation author="Bowman, TE" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="185 - 190" title="Miostephoscubrobex, a n. gen. and sp. of copepod from an anchialine pool in Cuba (Calanoida, Stephidae)." volume="89" year="1976">Bowman 1976</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 13) and 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. leamingtonensis" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="leamingtonensis">M. leamingtonensis</taxonomicName>
from Bermuda (
<bibRefCitation author="Yeatman, H" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Tennessee Academy of Science" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" pagination="20 - 21" title="Miostephosleamingtonensis, a new species of copepod from Bermuda." volume="55" year="1980">Yeatman 1980</bibRefCitation>
, fig. 5), both with an attenuated unarmed distal segment. The new species differs in the genus characters (i.e. three-segmented female urosome, six-segmented left male fifth leg, reduced male right fifth leg strongly resembling the female fifth leg) (
<bibRefCitation author="Bowman, TE" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="185 - 190" title="Miostephoscubrobex, a n. gen. and sp. of copepod from an anchialine pool in Cuba (Calanoida, Stephidae)." volume="89" year="1976">Bowman 1976</bibRefCitation>
). In species of 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos" order="Calanoida" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Stephos</taxonomicName>
, the female genital double-somite has widely different patterns of ornamentation on the ventral and/or lateral surfaces, including rows of spinules with both symmetrical and asymmetrical arrangements (
<bibRefCitation author="Ohtsuka, S" journalOrPublisher="Publications of the Seto Marine Biological Laboratory" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="219 - 232" title="Calanoid copepods collected from the near-bottom in Tanabe Bay on the Pacific coast of the middle Honshu, Japan. III. Stephidae." volume="32" year="1987">Ohtsuka and Hiromi 1987</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Bradford-Grieve, J" journalOrPublisher="New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="13 - 27" title="New species of benthopelagic copepods of the genus Stephos (Calanoida: Stephidae) from Wellington Harbour, New Zealand." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00288330.1999.9516853" volume="33" year="1999">Bradford-Grieve 1999</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Costanzo, G" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Plankton Research" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="2007 - 2014" title="Stephosmarsalensis new species (Copepoda, Calanoida, Stephidae) from coastal waters of Sicily, Italy." url="https://doi.org/10.1093/plankt/22.10.2007" volume="22" year="2000">Costanzo et al. 2000</bibRefCitation>
), lack of surface ornamentation, as in 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. canariensis" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="canariensis">S. canariensis</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Boxshall, GA" journalOrPublisher="Stygologia" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" pagination="33 - 41" title="A new species of Stephos Scott, 1892 (Copepoda: Calanoida) from and anchialine lava pool on Lanzarote, Canary Islands." volume="5" year="1990">Boxshall et al., 1990</bibRefCitation>
) or 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. grieveae" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="grieveae">S. grieveae</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kršinić">Krsinic</normalizedToken>
, 2015) or a highly modified, strongly asymmetrical somite as in 
<taxonomicName genus="S." lsidName="S. exumensis" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species" species="exumensis">S. exumensis</taxonomicName>
(Fosshagen, 1970). The new species has a unique pattern combining a symmetrical genital double-somite with an ornamentation pattern represented by a set of 4 spiniform elements at each side of the genital operculum; this pattern has not been observed in any other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos" order="Calanoida" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Stephos</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Figure 5. Geographic distribution of 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Stephidae" genus="Stephos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephos" order="Calanoida" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Stephos</taxonomicName>
female fifth leg groups 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
. Group A lateral seta present, segment apically elongate B lateral seta present, segment not apically elongate, short C lateral seta absent, segment apically elongate D lateral seta present, segment elongate, with additional segmental processes, branched or bifurcate E lateral seta absent, segment elongate, with outer segmental processes F lateral seta absent, segment short, apically truncate or blunt, leg rami symmetrical or asymmetrical.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>