<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282976" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6955b03d-9e5d-4fa0-a646-b1125380fdee" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135762" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282976" ModsDocID="6435" ModsID="6435" checkinTime="1243377042483" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="1979" docId="0AA518ACAC1C476192E88DEE4900FFAC" docLanguage="en" docName="6435" docOrigin="Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology 38" docSource="http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6435" docTitle="Tetramorium simillimum" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="171" masterDocId="5892A574E3D0640CD30DFC0CE265ADC5" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Tetramoriini (Hymenoptera: Formicidae). The genus Tetramorium Mayr in the Malagasy region and in the New World." masterLastPageNumber="181" masterPageNumber="129" pageNumber="170" updateTime="1645806053092" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Tetramoriini (Hymenoptera: Formicidae). The genus Tetramorium Mayr in the Malagasy region and in the New World.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1979</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>38</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>129</mods:start>
<mods:end>181</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6435</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6435</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282976" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135762" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282976" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:0AA518ACAC1C476192E88DEE4900FFAC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0AA518ACAC1C476192E88DEE4900FFAC" lastPageNumber="171" pageNumber="170">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph>
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:37226" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Tetramorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tetramorium simillimum (Smith)" lsidName-HNS="Tetramorium simillimum (Smith)" order="Hymenoptera" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="simillimum">Tetramorium simillimum (F. Smith)</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph>(Figs 38, 41)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="reference_group">
<paragraph>
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:145247" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Myrmica" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Myrmica simillima Smith" lsidName-HNS="Myrmica simillima Smith" order="Hymenoptera" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="simillima">Myrmica simillima F. Smith</taxonomicName>
, 1851: 118. Syntype workers, Great Britain: England, Dorset (types lost). 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:37226" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Tetramorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tetramorium simillimum (Smith)" lsidName-HNS="Tetramorium simillimum (Smith)" order="Hymenoptera" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="simillimum">Tetramorium simillimum (F. Smith)</taxonomicName>
; Mayr, 1861: 15, 61. [For a statement of current synonymy see Bolton, 1977: 131 with the exception of 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:36928" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Tetramorium" genus.completionEvidence="missing" genus.completionRound="1" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tetramorium caldarium (Roger)" lsidName-HNS="Tetramorium caldarium (Roger)" order="Hymenoptera" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="caldarium">caldarium (Roger)</taxonomicName>
, for which see above.]
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="170">Worker. TL 2.1 - 2.5, HL 0.54 - 0.60, HW 0.48 - 0.54, CI 88 - 93, SL 0.36 - 0.42, SI 74 - 80, PW 0.34 - 0.40, AL 0.58 - 0.68 (45 measured).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="170">Mandibles feebly striate or weakly shagreened, never strongly rugulose, rarely with sculpture almost effaced. Anterior clypeal margin convex and entire, without a median notch or impression. Frontal carinae strongly developed, weakly sinuate, extending back almost to the occiput and outcurved posteriorly, fading out around the posterior borders of the broad but shallow antennal scrobes. Eyes moderate in size, their maximum diameter 0.22 - 0.26 x HW. Occiptial margin of head in full-face view broadly but shallowly concave, the sides of the head broadened behind the eyes, weakly convex, merging into the evenly rounded occipital corners. Propodeum armed with a pair of short, triangular teeth which are usually shorter than the metapleural lobes, the latter broad and roughly triangular in shape. Petiole in profile as in Fig. 38, the node in dorsal view always slightly broader than long, somewhat variable in shape but always broadening posteriorly before narrowing to the postpetiolar junction. Dorsum of head finely longitudinally rugulose, the spaces between the rugulae packed with a fine, dense conspicuous reticulate-punctulation or granulation. Dorsal alitrunk finely, often faintly longitudinally rugulose, the spaces between rugulae densely punctulate. Dorsal petiole and postpetiole similarly but less strongly sculptured, the sculpture sometimes reduced but never completely absent. Gaster unsculptured or with faint granulation on base of first tergite. All dorsal surfaces of head and body with scattered short hairs, generally longer on the gaster then elsewhere. Hairs on alitrunk conspicuous, short, stout and blunt.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="171">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="171">Antennal</pageStartToken>
scapes and tibiae only with very short, fine pubescence which is appressed. Colour yellow to yellow brown, often with the gaster darker than the head and alitrunk but some populations uniformly coloured.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="171">Material examined (New World)</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="171">U. S. A.: Florida, Orlando (O. C. McBride); Florida, Bradenton (G. D. Reynolds); Florida, Ft Ogden (D. E. Read); Florida, Ft Myers (W. M. Barrows); California, San Francisco (no further data). Mexico: Cordoba {Mann &amp; Skewes); Cordoba (Silvestri); Chiapes, Ocosingo (R. L. Dressier). Guatemala: Los Amatea (Kellerman). Bahamas: Andros I. (W. M. Wheeler), Egg I. (Wickham). Virgin Is.: St Croix (H. Morrison). Cuba: Cristo (W. M. Mann); Soledad, Cienfuegos (N. A. Weber); Soledad, Atkins Gdns (E. O. Wilson). Jamaica: series without data; Balaclava (W. M. Wheeler). Haiti: Mts N. of Jacmel (W. M. Mann); Mannerville (W. M. Mann); Grande Riviere (W. M. Mann); Diquini (W. M. Mann). Trinidad: Curepe (J. Noyes); series ex Trinidad on palms, intercepted Philadelphia (W. Chapman). Venezuela: Caracas (N. Ferrine); Orinoco Delta (N. A. Weber); P. Anduz, Moitaco. Brazil: Bahia (H. L. Sumford); S. P., San Sebastiao (B. Fledderman) Manaus (Mann &amp; Baker). Peru: series ex Peru on orchids, intercepted Miami, Florida.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>