<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280196" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120186" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280196" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="EBF26CA934351014B517BEA12FC7FCB8" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys labaris Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="663" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="662" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280196" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120186" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280196" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:EBF26CA934351014B517BEA12FC7FCB8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EBF26CA934351014B517BEA12FC7FCB8" lastPageNumber="663" pageNumber="662">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="662">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155842" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys labaris Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys labaris Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="662" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="labaris">Strumigenys labaris Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="662">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 3.4, HL 0.85, HW 0.75, CI 88, ML 0.43, MI 51, SL 0.56, SI 74, PW 0.41, AL 0.83. Characters of sphera-complex. Each mandible with 1 preapical tooth, distance from preapical tooth to apicodorsal tooth approximately equal to length of preapical tooth. Upper scrobe margin bordered by a projecting laminar rim or flange throughout its length, eyes partially visible in full-face view. Eye very small, convex, its maximum diameter distinctly less than maximum width scape. Scape narrowed near base, slightly expanded and flattened in basal third; hairs on leading edge narrowly spatulate. Cephalic dorsum clothed with curved narrowly spatulate ground-pilosity; upper scrobe margin with hairs that are similar in size and shape to those on the dorsum. Cephalic dorsum with 4 pairs of long standing narrowly remiform hairs arranged as follows: transverse row of 3 pairs close to the occipital margin and 1 pair of erect hairs on vertex. Pronotal humeral hair absent; humeral angles rounded, posterolateral margin of pronotum bluntly marginate. Anterior margin of mesonotum with 1 pair of stout standing hairs. Propodeal spines with 1 pair of fine short, posteriorly curved hairs near anterior base. Alitrunk dorsum with very short curved ground-pilosity and concentrated on promesonotum. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly, posterior mesonotum sharply depressed, propodeum gradually sloping to declivity. Metanotal groove represented by a shallow impression. Propodeal spines short, triangular, posterior margin with a narrow spongiform strip; propodeal lamella absent. Alitrunk dorsum densely reticulatepunctate. Sides of pronotum with faint longitudinally striolate sculpture anteriorly. Pleurae mostly smooth and shiny with reticulate-punctate sculpture peripherally. Petiole node in dorsal view approximately as long as broad. Postpetiole disc with weak longitudinally striolate sculpture on a fine punctulate surface. In profile ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle a narrow curtain that is continuous along the base of the peduncle, depth of curtain is distinctly greater than maximum width of eye. Ventral spongiform lobe of postpetiole moderately developed. Basigastral costulae short and sharply defined. Dorsal surface of petiole, postpetiole, and gaster with stout standing remiform to narrowly spatulate hairs which are slightly thickened apically. Colour medium brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="662">PARATYPE WORKER TL 3.0 - 3.4, HL 0.78 - 0.86, HW 0.66 - 0.75, CI 84 - 89, ML 0.39 - 0.45, MI 49 - 54, SL 0.52 - 0.57, SI 74 - 80, PW 0.35 - 0.40, AL 0.73 - 0.84 (6 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="662">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 11.0 km. WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 14 Â° 45 ' S, 49 Â° 27 ' E, 1565 m., 16. xi. 1994, sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood), montane rainforest # 1232 (4) - 5. (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="662">Paratypes. 6 workers with same data as holotype but coded (31) - 4, (40) - 4 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="662">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: R. S. Manongarivo, 14.5 km. 220 Â° SW Antanambao, 1175 m. (B. L. Fisher); Amboangy hill, 30 km. N Antalaha, 115 m. (G. D. Alpert); 6.5 km. SSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 875 m. (B. L. Fisher); 17 km. W Andapa, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 875 m. (G. D. Alpert); 9.2 km. WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 1200 m. (B. L. Fisher); 6.9 km. NE Ambanizana, 825 m. (B. L. Fisher).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="662">Measurements of this material extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.70 - 0.80, HW 0.58 - 0.67, CI 83, ML 0.37 - 0.42, MI 52 - 55, SL 0.46 - 54, SI 78 - 84 (3 measured).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="663">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155842" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys labaris Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys labaris Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="663" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="labaris">S. labaris</taxonomicName>
is most similar to 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155837" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys admixta Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys admixta Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="663" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="admixta">admixta</taxonomicName>
in the sphera-complex. In both species the upper scrobe margin has a distinct, broad lamellate rim or flange throughout its length. They are most easily distinguished by the shape of the postbuccal margin with head in ventral view. In 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155842" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys labaris Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys labaris Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="663" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="labaris">labaris</taxonomicName>
, the posterior and lateral margins of the postbuccal groove are rounded to bluntly marginate, and the posterolateral face of groove is more or less vertical or gently sloping, never concave. In 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155837" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys admixta Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys admixta Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="663" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="admixta">admixta</taxonomicName>
, the posterolateral and lateral margins of postbuccal groove have a lamellate rim and the posterolateral face of the groove is concave.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>