<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.848.32263" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a300aab4-c705-4835-b3ec-d8b27313c258" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157232556" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-848-21" ID-ZBK="BC8282C2C971453FB5212A1BA06D77DA" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BE3AADFF-51A5-4F27-B039-346F0A280271" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="1313-2970-848-21" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 848" ModsDocTitle="Taxonomy of the thelyphonid genus Typopeltis Pocock, 1894, including homology proposals for the male gonopod structures (Arachnida, Thelyphonida, Typopeltinae)" checkinTime="1558375086222" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Seraphim, Gabriel, Giupponi, Alessandro Ponce de Leao &amp; Miranda, Gustavo Silva de" docDate="2019" docId="380AC0E9F35837B7866A5AACE77D318E" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 848: 21-39" docOrigin="ZooKeys 848" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.848.32263" docTitle="Typopeltis laurentianus Seraphim, Giupponi &amp; Miranda, 2019, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="BE3AADFF-51A5-4F27-B039-346F0A280271" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="25" masterDocId="FFE6FFC8FFCEFFFAFF91FF8CFFE2FF60" masterDocTitle="Taxonomy of the thelyphonid genus Typopeltis Pocock, 1894, including homology proposals for the male gonopod structures (Arachnida, Thelyphonida, Typopeltinae)" masterLastPageNumber="39" masterPageNumber="21" pageId="2" pageNumber="23" updateTime="1643495996087" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Taxonomy of the thelyphonid genus Typopeltis Pocock, 1894, including homology proposals for the male gonopod structures (Arachnida, Thelyphonida, Typopeltinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Seraphim, Gabriel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Giupponi, Alessandro Ponce de Leao</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Miranda, Gustavo Silva de</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>848</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>21</mods:start>
<mods:end>39</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.848.32263</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.848.32263</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-848-21</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">BC8282C2C971453FB5212A1BA06D77DA</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">BC8282C2C971453FB5212A1BA06D77DA</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="157232556" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BE3AADFF-51A5-4F27-B039-346F0A280271" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/380AC0E9F35837B7866A5AACE77D318E" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="23" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/BE3AADFF-51A5-4F27-B039-346F0A280271" class="Arachnida" family="Thelyphonidae" genus="Typopeltis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Typopeltis laurentianus" order="Uropygi" pageId="2" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laurentianus">Typopeltis laurentianus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="23">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="23" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
Holotype male: VIETNAM: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hà">Ha</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tĩnh">Tĩnh</normalizedToken>
, 18.355240, 105.886949, 1998 (MNRJ 08243). Paratypes: VIETNAM: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hà">Ha</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tĩnh">Tĩnh</normalizedToken>
, 18.355240, 105.886949, 1998 (2 males, MNRJ 08243); 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hà">Ha</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tĩnh">Tĩnh</normalizedToken>
, 18.355240, 105.886949, 1997 (1 male, 1 female, MNRJ 08242); Quang Binh: Phong Nha-Kẻ 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Bàng">Bang</normalizedToken>
National Park, 17.590802, 106.283344, 2001 (1 male, MNHN AR-UR-2 [ex MNRJ 08244]; 1 female, CAS, CASENT 9081667 [ex MNRJ 08245]); 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Vĩnh">Vĩnh</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Phúc">Phuc</normalizedToken>
, 17.590802, 106.283344, x.1980, leg. R. Boistel (2 females, MNRJ 08246).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="23" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
Species name 
<taxonomicName lsidName="laurentianus" pageId="2" pageNumber="23" rank="species" species="laurentianus">laurentianus</taxonomicName>
(laurentiana, laurentianum) is a Latin adjective after our friend, the distinguished Franco-Brazilian arachnologist Wilson 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lourenço">Lourenco</normalizedToken>
. The Latin form of Portuguese 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lourenço">Lourenco</normalizedToken>
is Laurentius (genitive 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Laurentiī">Laurentiī</normalizedToken>
), a noun of the second declension, cognate of English Lawrence or French Laurent. The ICZN allows authors of new species to choose the Latin version of contemporary names derived from Latin, which may be more euphonic than the modern counterparts.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="24" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="24" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
Males (about 35 mm in total length without flagellum) larger than females (see measurements); males with patellar apophysis very long, with narrow base and apex, broader in the middle, with a small antero-posterior curve. Patellar apophysis without spines in the trunk or the terminal portion, with a smooth integument texture that differs from all the other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Thelyphonidae" genus="Typopeltis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Typopeltis" order="Uropygi" pageId="3" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Typopeltis</taxonomicName>
. The male gonopod is simple, delimited by a sclerotized curved cuticle (posterior apex of Fi), with inverted trapezoid shape with rounded edges. The female gonopod has a bulbous RS with a wide base and a well marked CCh.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="3" pageNumber="24" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">(Holotype male) Colouration (in alcohol). Reddish-brown. Carapace darker on anterior region than posterior region. Abdomen slightly yellowish. Pedipalps dark red, lighter in females lighter. Median eyes dark, almost black, lateral eyes yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">Carapace (Figs 1A, 2A). With thick granules of irregular shapes homogeneously covering whole surface, granules interspaced. Lateral keel with one seta on each anterior end, next to median eyes; posterior end of keels above lateral triad of eyes, keel extends from posterior to anterior region of carapace; keels divided by median ocular ridge. Carapace has depression extending from posterior region of median ocular tubercle to region above subtriangular fovea. Median eye tubercle elevated, with well-marked ridge between eyes. Chelicerae with several setae in ventral region and on cheliceral claw. Cheliceral claw curved inwards, with thick base and narrow apex, and with short keel, smaller than half length of tooth (Fig. 3A).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Thelyphonidae" genus="Typopeltis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Typopeltis laurentianus" order="Uropygi" pageId="3" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laurentianus">Typopeltis laurentianus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype (male). A Carapace B sternum C pedipalps (dorsal) D pedipalps (ventral) E opisthosoma (dorsal) F opisthosoma (ventral) G ommatoid H gonopod.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Thelyphonidae" genus="Typopeltis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Typopeltis laurentianus" order="Uropygi" pageId="3" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laurentianus">Typopeltis laurentianus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype (female). A Carapace B sternum C pedipalps (dorsal) D pedipalps (ventral) E opisthosoma (dorsal) F opisthosoma (ventral) G ommatoid H gonopod. CCh = circulus chitinosus; ACh = arcus chitinosus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
Figure 3. SEM images of 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Thelyphonidae" genus="Typopeltis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Typopeltis laurentianus" order="Uropygi" pageId="3" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laurentianus">Typopeltis laurentianus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype (male). A Chelicerae (right) B gonopod. Details in dashed rectangles are shown in images C (lower rectangle) and D (upper rectangle). C Fulcrum (Fu) detail D Mensa (Me) detail.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">Sternum (Figs 1B, 2B). Typical of order, tri-segmented; inconspicuous mesosternum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
Opisthosoma (Figs 1E, G; 2E, G). Pleura divided by crest of granules from tergites 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–VIII">I-VIII</normalizedToken>
; tergites without suture. Sides with fine granules (Figs 1E, 2E). Subcircular ommatoids present (Figs 1G, 2G). Flagellum with 38 articles (female paratype) and 36 in holotype (broken).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="3" pageNumber="24">
Pedipalps (Figs 1C, D; 2C, D). Coxa without accessory tooth, with few setae. Trochanter punctated with granules covering dorsal surface. Four spines in dorso-mesal region (I &lt;II &lt;III &lt;IV), spines I-III as broad as or broader than long, conical, with broad base and acute apex; spine IV geminate with spine III, with long setae, conical; apex rhomboid and bigger than double size of spine III. Two small spines close to articular condyle (trochanter-femur), spines smaller than mesal spine I (Fig. 1C). Ventral region with thick ridge all along joint with femur, ending mesally with two small conical spines, broader than long (Fig. 1D). Femur unarmed and covered with shallow pores concentrated on outer margin (Fig. 1D). Ventro-mesal region with reduced rhombus spine (almost a granule), conical, broader than long, surrounded by long setae (Fig. 1C). In females, ventro-mesal spine well developed, twice longer than wide, with very sharp, curved tip and broad base. Two small conical spines dorsally (I &lt;II); in males these spines reduced to two small granules, clearly homologous to spines present in females. Patella covered by pores, especially on ectal face, with few setae; several setae mesally. Patellar apophysis almost as long as patella, with large non-terminal (median) expansion on external margin of apophysis (like large hump); unprecedented smooth texture and slight curvature in ventral direction on terminal portion. Apophysis with spatulated shape with slight concavity ventrally. Ventral face without spines. Females with two coni 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="25" start="start">cal</pageBreakToken>
spines of subequal size in dorso-mesal view (Fig. 2C); spines as broad as long, with broad base and sharp tip, most anterior at base of apophysis. Ventral apophysis with reduced ventro-mesal spine in distal position (Fig. 2D). Patellar apophysis well developed, but slightly smaller than length of patella, conical, tapering towards apex; with single spine on mesal surface, positioned just before apex; row of spines with three or four small subequal basal spines on ectal face, followed by median series of four spines increasing in size; second series of spines larger than double first row of spines; distal series composed of three spines, with middle ones larger than two others. Two rows of setae at edges of ventral region, absent in males. Tibia covered by pores, large concentration of setae (in mesal view), more than in femur and patella. Tibial apophysis conically-shaped, broad base, acute apex, with series of dorsal spines. In ventro-mesal view with two small spines, most apical rhombic and double the size of previous one; penultimate spine with conical shape, with wide base. Tarsus covered by long setae, with greater predominance on mesal surface. With longitudinal series of ventral rhomboid spines and another dorsal series.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="25">
Leg I. Eight tarsomers (variation: seven to nine), first very short (like small ring), second, third and last larger than others (I &lt;II&gt; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
&lt;VIII); size and number of tarsomers can vary if leg is regenerated. Apical portion of tibia with two dorsolateral tricobothria, absent in femur and patella. Femur covered with thick granules, patella and tibia with smooth appearance. All articles covered with setae dorsally and ventrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="25">
Legs 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–IV">II-IV</normalizedToken>
. Trochanter and femur with granules. Coxa, tibia and tarsus smooth, last two with concentration of setae. With dorso-apical tricobothrium on tibia; ventro-apical region with thin, acuminate spur. Basitarsus with two spurs, one mesal and other ectal; ventral region with two longitudinal rows with four or five spiniform setae. Distitarsus divided into three tarsomers (I&gt; II &lt;III), length of tarsomere I equal or greater than II + III. Tarsomere I with two longitudinal rows with eight spiniform setae. Tarsomeres II and III similar to previous, but with three and four setae, respectively.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="25">Sternite (Figs 1F, 2F). Genital plate about 1.5 times wider than long, with irregularly distributed setae and accumulated pores on sides. Other ventrites mostly smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="25">Male Gonopod (Figs 1H; 3B, C, 3D). LoL1 broader than long, reniform, with thin longitudinal sclerotized wrinkles, slightly curved and sinuous in terminal portion (Fig. 1H); Fi with sclerotized borders and inverted trapezoid shape with rounded edges. LoD with strongly sclerotized acute projection positioned above all other gonopod structures. LoL2 globose, soft, partially covered by LoL1; LaM as two parallel plates originating in Me and supported by Fu (Fig. 3C). Me subtriangular and covered by denticles (Fig. 3D). Female Gonopod (Fig. 2H) with seminal receptacle (RS) of bulbous shape, with base slightly narrower than more dilated distal portion; longer than wide; concave chitinous arc with two sclerotized chitinous rings at base of RS. Two well-sclerotized structures on sides of chitinous arch, very long and thin, slightly curved inwards, with base wider than apex.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="25" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="25">Measurements.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="25">(holotype male before brackets, variation inside brackets).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="25">Prosoma: 13.6 mm (length) [12.0-13.6 mm], 8.0 mm (width) [7.1-8.0 mm]; Opisthosoma: 19.4 mm (length) [17.5-19.4mm], 10.7 mm (width) [8.3-10.7mm]; Pedipalp: Trochanter: 4.2 mm [3.7-4.2 mm]; Femur: 4.0 mm [4.0-4.4mm]; Patella: 5.4 mm [4.8-5.4 mm]; Patellar apophysis: 4.4 mm [4.0-4.4 mm]; Tibia: 4.1 mm [3.0-4.1 mm]; Tibial apophysis: 1.7 mm [1.6-1.8 mm]; Tarsus: 3.1 mm [2.6-3.1 mm].</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>