<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6228961" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3a5c236f-b6ba-42e7-b352-a5f0cec6f49a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119361601" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6228961" checkinTime="1459846556271" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Leal, Jos Ẽ H." docDate="2008" docId="081987A1A21EBB52FF5DDCC7FAE789C7" docLanguage="en" docName="zt01764p018.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1764" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@747d1932" docStyleName="zootaxa.2007.monograph" docTitle="Dilemma Leal, 2008, new genus" docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" masterDocId="F420FFD9A21CBB51FFCADA13FFFA8E55" masterDocTitle="A remarkable new genus of carnivorous, sessile bivalves (Mollusca: Anomalodesmata: Poromyidae) with descriptions of two new species" masterLastPageNumber="18" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" updateTime="1645560880582" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A remarkable new genus of carnivorous, sessile bivalves (Mollusca: Anomalodesmata: Poromyidae) with descriptions of two new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Leal, Jos Ẽ H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2008</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1764</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>18</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.181996</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">3a5c236f-b6ba-42e7-b352-a5f0cec6f49a</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">181996</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6228961" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119361601" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6228961" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:081987A1A21EBB52FF5DDCC7FAE789C7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/081987A1A21EBB52FF5DDCC7FAE789C7" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<subSubSection box="[151,401,1748,1774]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,401,1748,1774]" box="[151,401,1748,1774]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,401,1748,1774]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,401,1748,1774]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<taxonomicName box="[151,262,1748,1774]" class="Bivalvia" family="Poromyidae" genus="Dilemma" kingdom="Animalia" order="Anomalodesmata" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Mollusca" rank="genus" status="new genus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,262,1748,1774]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Dilemma</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[271,401,1748,1774]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="genus">new genus</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,1437,1825,2012]" lastBlockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,279,1825,1851]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
Shell apparently nacreous internally, strongly compressed in anteroposterior direction and laterally expanded; shell compression associated with ca. 
<number box="[736,765,1866,1892]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="30.0">30</number>
º rotation of the largest dimension (height) in relation to the anteroposterior axis; lateral outline cardioid; height larger than width; width larger than length. Byssus very well developed (indicating attachment for life); foot vestigial, never leaving infraseptal chamber; posterior byssal retractor muscles wider in cross-section than posterior adductor muscles; anterior labial palps very well developed, cup-shaped; posterior labial palps very reduced, consisting of short projections flush to surrounding surface.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[205,357,231,257]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Description.</emphasis>
Shell apparently nacreous internally, thin, equivalve (except for slight anteroposterior overlap at umbo), inequilateral, strongly compressed in anteroposterior direction, lateral outline cardioid, anteroventral surface flat or slightly concave, height larger than width, width larger than length. Umbones projecting dorsally, anterior. Byssal gap anteroventral when present.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Hinge with sub-triangular, cardinal-like tooth in each valve; tooth in left valve with cleft distal extremity and more developed than that in right.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Ligament external, sunken; inner ligamental layer apparently calcified, white. Outer ligamental layer brown, splitting and diverging anteriorly, with each half curved as a result of tangential component of shell growth; periostracum fused externally with outer ligamental layer. Lithodesma absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Posterior byssal retractor scar larger than posterior adductor scar, elongate. Lunule absent; escutcheon smooth, well-defined.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Animal compressed in anteroventral to posterodorsal direction. Mantle lobes thin, except in siphonal area, with three apertures (see below).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Incurrent siphonal length and siphonal opening diameter larger than equivalent dimensions in excurrent siphon. Incurrent siphon eversible, resting inside infraseptal chamber. Incurrent siphonal opening separated from byssal gape by well-developed ventral portion of perisiphonal suture.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Base of incurrent siphon surrounded by up to 
<number box="[775,804,872,898]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="15.0">15</number>
tentacles; tentacles simple, tapered, with one large unpaired tentacle along fused mantle margin dorsal to excurrent siphon; pair of tentacles present internally, in supraseptal chamber, between posterior margin of excurrent siphon and posterior adductor muscle.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Septum thin, perforated by byssal opening and by groups of ostia arranged to roughly define three pairs of line segments deployed in septum around byssal opening.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Adductor muscles almost parallel to attachment surfaces on valves. Anterior adductor short, flattened; posterior adductor longer, also flattened. Posterior byssal retractors very well developed, attaching to locations close to posterior margin of valves. Anterior byssal retractors thinner, attaching dorsally to internal surface of entrance to umbonal cavity. (I prefer to use 
<emphasis box="[813,1109,1192,1217]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">byssal retractor muscles</emphasis>
instead of 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">pedal retractor muscles</emphasis>
.)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Byssus well-developed, prominent, circular in cross section. Vestigial foot dorsal to byssus, narrow, or consisting only of an expansion around the middle region of byssus. Position and size of vestigial foot indicates that it can never exit infraseptal chamber.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Mouth indicated by beginning of pleats that continue inside esophagus. Posterior labial palps reduced to two small projections flush with surrounding surface and united along midline. Posterior palps not extending posteroventrally on either side of vestigial foot. Anterior labial palps strongly developed, large, folded in the shape of cups over mouth, free from anterior adductor muscle, potentially expandable in posteroventral direction (toward siphonal area).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Esophagus very short, with strong internal folds, penetrating stomach anterodorsally. Stomach of 
<typeStatus box="[1343,1401,1592,1618]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Type</typeStatus>
II, compact, strongly muscular, situated in dorsal orientation in relation to mouth, between two “horns” that house digestive diverticula and ovary. Midgut relatively short, connecting to stomach in anterodorsal position, ventral to esophagus. Testes situated in anteroventral position in relation to ovary, ovary overlying the testes. Kidneys situated posterodorsally between remaining of visceral mass and posterior byssal retractor muscle. Kidneys comprising two elongate structures, one on each side of midline of posterior region.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[197,1123,1831,1858]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" box="[197,1123,1831,1858]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,364,1831,1857]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<typeStatus box="[197,258,1831,1857]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Type</typeStatus>
Species.
</emphasis>
<taxonomicName box="[372,681,1832,1857]" class="Bivalvia" family="Poromyidae" genus="Dilemma" kingdom="Animalia" order="Anomalodesmata" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Mollusca" rank="species" species="frumarkernorum" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[372,681,1832,1857]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Dilemma frumarkernorum</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[689,833,1832,1858]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
, by original designation.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,152,1938]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,338,1871,1897]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Etymology.</emphasis>
The generic name is the Greek noun 
<emphasis box="[781,889,1872,1897]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<taxonomicName box="[781,885,1872,1897]" class="Bivalvia" family="Poromyidae" genus="Dilemma" kingdom="Animalia" order="Anomalodesmata" pageId="3" pageNumber="17" phylum="Mollusca" rank="genus">dilemma</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
a proposition consisting of questionable alternatives. It is used in this case to denote the impasses faced by the author in the course of this work.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>