<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287978" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a14c41b0-c9f9-45cc-940b-e11e398c97ca" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116663" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287978" ModsDocAuthor="Clark, J." ModsDocDate="1926" ModsDocID="6097" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6097/6097.pdf" ModsDocTitle="Australian Formicidae." checkinTime="1264779824114" checkinUser="claudia" docAuthor="Clark, J." docDate="1926" docId="4836661706F6C404F5200C7DC2F4B752" docLanguage="en" docName="6097_tx1.xml" docOrigin="Journal of the Royal Society of Western Australia 12" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6097/6097.pdf" docTitle="Phyracaces reticulatus" docType="treatment" docVersion="11" lastPageNumber="46" masterDocId="30FFEB89CCE745B12DAF204B958B5401" masterDocTitle="Australian Formicidae." masterLastPageNumber="52" masterPageNumber="43" pageNumber="45" updateTime="1645823295758" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Australian Formicidae.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Clark, J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of the Royal Society of Western Australia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1926</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>52</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6097/6097.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6097</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287978" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116663" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287978" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:4836661706F6C404F5200C7DC2F4B752" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4836661706F6C404F5200C7DC2F4B752" lastPageNumber="46" pageNumber="45">
<subSubSection pageNumber="45" type="nomenclature">
<taxonomicName authority="Emery, 1901" authorityName="Emery" authorityYear="1901" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Phyracaces" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" source="A0772665D9805AB31797A3D26723D4C4,7B4A39779396FD19392525742032C5D5" species="reticulatus">Phyracaces reticulatus</taxonomicName>
n.sp. (Pl. VI, 2).
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageNumber="45" type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="45">Worker: Length 3.5-4 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="45">Red; antennae and tarsi testaeeous. Hairs yellowish, short, erect, moderately abundant. A thin grayish pubescence on the antennae and legs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="45">Shining. Head, thorax and petiole densely and finely reticulate, the postpetiole and abdomen more coarsely reticulate-punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="45">Head as long as broad, much broader behind than in front, the occipital border straight, the angles rounded. Frontal carinae erect, short, truncate behind. Carinae of the cheeks forming a blunt angle in front, and extending back to the middle of the eyes. Clypeus short, broadly rounded, with л long tooth-like projection in the middle in front» Eyes large, moderately convex, placed slightly in front of the middle, of the sides. No tracea of ocelli. Mandibles large, strongly bent at their base, the external border convex, the terminal border strongly dentate: they are coarsely punctate-striate. Antennae robust, scapes extending to the posterior margin of the eyes, gradually thickened to the apex; first joint of the funiculus as long as broad, the second to ninth broader than long, the tenth longer than broad, the apical joint pointed, as long as the four preceding joints together. Thorax barely one and one-half times longer than broad, as broad in front as behind, mesonutal sutures not indicated; anterior border of the pronotum convex, the angles rounded, posterior border of the epinotum nearly straight, with a slight indention in the middle; in profile strongly rounded and convex above, the epinotal declivity sloping at a slight angle; all four sides of the dorsum and sides of the declivity strongly marginate. Node of the petiole twice as broad as long, as broad as the thorax, concave in front, the angles sharp, the sides and posterior border convex, the posterior angles produced as long sharp spines, directed inward and slightly upward, the anterior and lateral borders strongly marginate; in profile feebly rounded and convex above, the anterior face vertical; the ventral surface with a short blunt tooth in front, Postpetiole one and one-half times broader than long, as broad as the thorax, the anterior border concave, the angles sharp, the sides convex; the anterior and lateral borders strongly marginate, the lateral margins ending abruptly just in front of the posterior border. A strong constriction between the postpetiole and the first segment of the gaster; this latter is mueh broader than long, and broader behind than in front, it is broader than the thorax. Pygidium truncate, minutely spinulose on the sides and tip. Legs short and stout.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageNumber="46" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="46">Hаb.: Western Australia, National Park (J. Clark).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageNumber="46" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="46">This species is not near any other known to me. The peculiar tooth-like projection on the clypeus will readily distinguish it from all the described forms. The whole insect has a heavy thick-set appearance, and looks shorter than it really is.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>