<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.312.5294" ID-GBIF-Dataset="fcdd0596-98fd-4483-b95f-06ac57d702f0" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152045685" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-312-89" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2173C040-6C15-45ED-962F-46E47F511D50" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-312-89" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 312" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Amphibulus Kriechbaumer (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) from Beijing with a key to species known from the Oriental and Eastern Palaearctic regions" checkinTime="1451247178826" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Zong, Shi-Xiang, Sun, Shu-Ping &amp; Sheng, Mao-Ling" docDate="2013" docId="C006404B6B68E42B5EAD313720968F02" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 312: 89-95" docOrigin="ZooKeys 312" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.312.5294" docTitle="Amphibulus melanarius Zong, Sun &amp; Sheng, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="2173C040-6C15-45ED-962F-46E47F511D50" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="93" masterDocId="8D14FF89FFC2FF82FC31DC05FF9F0631" masterDocTitle="A new species of Amphibulus Kriechbaumer (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) from Beijing with a key to species known from the Oriental and Eastern Palaearctic regions" masterLastPageNumber="95" masterPageNumber="89" pageId="3" pageNumber="92" updateTime="1643694270996" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of Amphibulus Kriechbaumer (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) from Beijing with a key to species known from the Oriental and Eastern Palaearctic regions</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zong, Shi-Xiang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sun, Shu-Ping</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sheng, Mao-Ling</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>312</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>89</mods:start>
<mods:end>95</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.312.5294</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.312.5294</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-312-89</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">0B45C671-DB0A-4746-8A98-9C41C9492D6E</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152045685" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2173C040-6C15-45ED-962F-46E47F511D50" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C006404B6B68E42B5EAD313720968F02" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="3" pageNumber="92">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="92" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2173C040-6C15-45ED-962F-46E47F511D50" authority="Zong, Sun &amp; Sheng" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amphibulus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Amphibulus melanarius" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="melanarius">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="92" start="start">Amphibulus</pageBreakToken>
melanarius Zong, Sun &amp; Sheng
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="3" pageNumber="92">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1-11
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="92" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">The specific name is derived from the body being entirely black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="92" type="types">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">Types.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">Holotype, female, CHINA: Mentougou, 800 to 900 m, Beijing, 22 June 2011, leg. Shi-Xiang Zong. Paratypes: 4 females, same data as holotype except 15 to 22 June 2011. 1 female, CHINA: Songshan Natural Reserve, 672m, Yanqing, Beijing, 27 June 2011, leg. Shi-xiang Zong. 2 females, same data as holotype except 9 June 2012.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="92" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">
Clypeus 3.0 to 3.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long. Area spiracularis and area lateralis separated by carina. First sternite reaching about half distance to spiracle. Postpetiole approximately 0.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, with dense longitudinal wrinkles. Head except mandibles and clypeus, mesosoma and all tergites black. Flagellomeres 5 to 10 (11) white. Coxae red.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="3" pageNumber="92" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">Female (Figs 1-11). Body length 6.5 to 7.5 mm. Fore wing length 5.5 to 6.0 mm. Ovipositor sheath length approximately 1.0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">
Head. Face and clypeus with dense brown hairs. Face (Fig. 2) 2.6 to 2.7 times as wide as long, median portion slightly convex; with dense punctures. Clypeus 3.0 to 3.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, basal half with dense punctures, apical half smooth and shiny, with unclear, indistinct striations; subapical portion distinctly raised as a transverse ridge; apical margin deeply depressed, median section almost truncate. Mandible (Fig. 3) distinctly elongate, shiny, with sparse, fine punctures; base distinctly concave centrally; upper tooth evidently longer than lower tooth. Subocular sulcus indistinct. Malar space 0.55 to 0.6 times as long as basal width of mandible. Gena in dorsal view 1.1 to 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as width of eye, with uneven, fine punctures, distance between punctures 0.5 to 4.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
their diameter. Vertex (Fig. 4) slightly shining, with irregular elongate punctures. Postocellar line 0.83 to 0.88
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as ocular-ocellar line. Upper portion of frons almost flat, with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 1.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
their diameter; mediocentral portion with fine transverse wrinkles; lower portion concave, smooth, shiny, with median longitudinal carina. Antenna with 25 or 26 flagellomeres, median portion of flagellum, flagellomeres 5 to 21, slightly widened; apical half cylindric. Ratios of lengths from first to fifth flagellomeres: 1.1:1.0:1.1:0.9:0.8. Apical truncation of scape 15 to 18 degrees from transverse. Occipital carina complete, lower end joining hypostomal carina at base of mandible.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="3" pageNumber="92">
Mesosoma. Anterior margin of pronotum with fine longitudinal wrinkles; lateromedian portion with transverse wrinkles; upper posterior portion with punctures, distance between punctures 0.5 to 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
their diameter. Anterior and lateral portions of mesoscutum (Fig. 5) smooth, shiny, with fine, sparse, indistinct punctures; posterior median portion with punctures and longitudinal wrinkles. Scutoscutellar groove with fine, short longitudinal wrinkles, without median longitudinal carina. Scutellum (Fig. 7) almost flat, shiny, with sparse, uneven punctures. Postscutellum trans 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="93" start="start">versely</pageBreakToken>
convex, anterior portion transversely concave; with sparse punctures. Upper and anterior portions of mesopleuron (Fig. 6) with distinct punctures; mediocentral portion rough, with elongate punctures; lower posterior portion with transverse wrinkles. Epicnemial carina reaching to subtegular ridge. Speculum small, smooth, shiny. Metapleuron convex, with dense, elongate punctures. Submetapleural carina complete, anterior end strongly convex. Hind leg (Fig. 8) with dense brown setae. Apical truncation of hind tibia approximately transverse, internal side with dense, fine fringe of setae at the apex (Fig. 8a). Ratios of lengths of first to fifth hind tarsomeres are 3.8:2.0:1.7:1.0:1.5. Fore wing with vein 1cu-a distal to 1/M by about 0.5 to 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of vein. Areolet (Fig. 9) receiving vein 2m-cu approximately at posterior 0.3. 2m-cu almost vertical, with a wide bulla. Hind wing vein 1-cu 2.3 to 3.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as cu-a. Propodeum (Fig. 7) completely areolated. Area basalis and area superomedia combined, with irregular punctures and short wrinkles; area externa with fine, indistinct punctures; area dentipara with indistinct punctures; area petiolaris with dense elongate punctures; remainder roughly sculptured. Propodeal spiracle small, circular.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
Metasoma (Fig. 10). First tergite approximately 1.35 to 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as apical width. Postpetiole approximately 0.75 as long as wide, with dense, fine longitudinal wrinkles. Dorsolateral and ventrolateral carinae complete. Spiracle circular, small, located approximately at posterior 0.3 of first tergite. Second tergite 0.5 to 0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, with fine punctures, punctures on posterior portion much sparser and finer than that on anterior portion. Third tergite 0.6 to 0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, anterior portion with fine, indistinct punctures, posterior almost smooth. Tergites 4 and 5 with dense brown hairs. Ovipositor (Fig. 11) with weak subapical nodus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">Color (Fig. 1). Black, except the following: anterior profiles of scape and pedicel, basal portion and anterior profile of apical half of flagellum slightly reddish black. Flagellomeres 5 to 10 (11) white. Apical portion of clypeus, mandible except base and teeth, maxillary and labial palpi, tegula, front and middle legs, hind coxa, trochanter, and base and ventral profile of femur, basal portion of hind tibia red to reddish brown. Dorsal surface of hind femur and apical portion of hind tibia dark brown. Hind tarsus brown to brownish black. Pterostigma and wing veins brownish black.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
Figures 1-11. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amphibulus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Amphibulus melanarius" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="93" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="melanarius">Amphibulus melanarius</taxonomicName>
Zong, Sun &amp; Sheng, sp.n. Holotype. Female 1 Habitus, lateral view 2 Head, anterior view 3 Mandible 4 Head, dorsal view 5 Mesoscutum 6 Mesopleuron 7 Scutellum, postscutellum and propodeum 8 Hind leg 8a Inner apical portion of hind tibia 9 Areolet 10 Metasoma, dorsal view 11 Ovipositor, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>