<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887" ID-GBIF-Taxon="182235010" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-415-217" ID-Pensoft-UUID="6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468" ID-Zenodo-Dep="578301" ID-ZooBank="287A4DC80EFC42C6AA55DBB4D7A3441B" ModsDocID="1313-2970-415-217" checkinTime="1451245774308" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Smith, Aaron D., Dornburg, Rebecca &amp; Wheeler, Quentin D." docDate="2014" docId="A4150232D1185D39B08F815329A8D637" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 415: 217-268" docOrigin="ZooKeys 415" docPubDate="2014-06-12" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887" docTitle="Eleodes (Eleodes) hispilabris" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" id="6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="232" masterDocId="6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468" masterDocTitle="Larvae of the genus Eleodes (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae): matrix-based descriptions, cladistic analysis, and key to late instars" masterLastPageNumber="268" masterPageNumber="217" pageId="14" pageNumber="231" updateTime="1643518370047" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Larvae of the genus Eleodes (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae): matrix-based descriptions, cladistic analysis, and key to late instars</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Smith, Aaron D.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Northern Arizona University, PO Box 5640, Flagstaff, AZ, 86011 - 5640, USA</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Dornburg, Rebecca</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Arizona State University, PO Box 874501, Tempe, AZ, 85287 - 4501, USA</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wheeler, Quentin D.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>SUNY College of Environmental Science and Forestry, 1 Forestry Drive, Syracuse, NY 13210, USA</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2014-06-12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>415</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>217</mods:start>
<mods:end>268</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-415-217</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">287A4DC80EFC42C6AA55DBB4D7A3441B</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-UUID">6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">578301</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="182235010" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A4150232D1185D39B08F815329A8D637" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A4150232D1185D39B08F815329A8D637" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="232" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="231" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="231">
<taxonomicName LSID="A4150232-D118-5D39-B08F-815329A8D637" authority="(Say, 1824)" baseAuthorityName="Say" baseAuthorityYear="1824" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Eleodes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eleodes (Eleodes) hispilabris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="231" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hispilabris" subGenus="Eleodes">
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="231" start="start">Eleodes</pageBreakToken>
(Eleodes) hispilabris (Say, 1824)
</taxonomicName>
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 9" captionStartId="F9" captionText="Figure 9. Epipharynges of four Eleodes species: A Eleodes (Melaneleodes) carbonarius B Eleodes (Eleodes) armatus C Eleodes (Eleodes) hispilabris D Eleodes (Eleodes) tribulus. Scale bars = 1 mm." httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/29492" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">Figs 9C</figureCitation>
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 14" captionStartId="F14" captionText="Figure 14. Pygidia of two Eleodes species: A Eleodes (Eleodes) hispilabris B Eleodes (Tricheleodes) pilosus. Scale bar = 1 mm." httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/29497" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">, 14A</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="231" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="231">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="231">
Larval 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Say" baseAuthorityYear="1824" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Eleodes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="" order="Coleoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="231" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hispilabris">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">Eleodes hispilabris</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
specimens were reared from adults with the following collecting information: &quot;USA: TX: El Paso County / El Paso, sand dunes off / Hwy 180/Montana Ave. / N31.82327, W106.13234 / 21-22.VIII.2010, ADSmith&quot;. A total of 46 eggs and larvae were reared and examined for this study, with 36 surviving until the 2nd instar or beyond. The following description is based on a detailed examination of five 8-11th instar specimens.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="232" pageId="14" pageNumber="231" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="231">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="231">TL: 21.0-32.0 mm, PL: 2.6-3.2 mm, PW: 3.0-3.7 mm, HW: 2.4-3.1 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="231">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">Head.</emphasis>
Prognathous or weakly declined; weakly dorsoventrally flattened; width narrower than prothorax; sides rounded; strongly constricted before occipital foramen; color ferruginous, more heavily pigmented than body segments; punctation minute, dense, separated by 1-2 puncture diameters. Epicranial suture stem length approximately one-fourth head capsule length; frontal arms sinuate, not obscured by sculpturing. Frons rugose. Epicranial plates rugose dorsally; lateral portions moderately setose; ventral portion of each plate with row of four to five long setae along anterior margin near buccal cavity, not confluent with setae on lateral portions of plates, with a patch of short setae medially, forming a triangular pattern with its base near the anterior margin. Two stemmata present on each epicranial plate, pigmented spots often faded. Clypeus trapezoidal, swollen, darker medially in basal half, minutely punctate, punctation dense, separated by 1-2 puncture diameters. Labrum swollen, sides rounded, basal half more darkly pigmented, medial setal row with six to seven erect setae, subapical setal row with 10-14 erect setae, anterior margin straight to weakly emarginate. Epipharynx (
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 9" captionStartId="F9" captionText="Figure 9. Epipharynges of four Eleodes species: A Eleodes (Melaneleodes) carbonarius B Eleodes (Eleodes) armatus C Eleodes (Eleodes) hispilabris D Eleodes (Eleodes) tribulus. Scale bars = 1 mm." httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/29492" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">Fig. 9C</figureCitation>
) anterior setal row with eight or more stout spiniform setae, anterolateral margins with stout spinose setae; six anterior sensory papillae present, arranged in two irregular rows, each with two posterior papillae and one near the anterior margin; four subanterior sensory papillae present, arranged as a transverse row subtended by two spinose setae; seven to eight posterior sensory papillae present, arranged in an irregular cluster. Tormae strongly asymmetric, left torma larger. Ligula apex lacking microsetae, two long subapical setae present ventrally, eight or more subapical setae present dorsally. Hypopharyngeal sclerome pentagonal, tricuspidate. Gula distinct, trapezoidal, widest in basal half, length less than maximum width. Antenna three segmented, cylindrical, first segment longer than second.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="232" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="231">Thorax.</emphasis>
Thoracic tergites light tan, prothoracic sternite anterior to legs light tan to ferruginous, thoracic sternites posterior to prolegs light brown. Prothoracic tergum wider than long, 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
or more length of meso- or metaterga; anterior transverse striated band present, darker than protergal disc; lateral margins with distinct granulated band, darker than protergal disc. Posterior transverse striated band present on all thoracic tergites, unicolorous brown. Meso- and metathoracic tergites wider than long, each with a heavily sclerotized transverse line present on anterior fifth. Thoracic tergites sparsely 
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="232" start="start">setose</pageBreakToken>
on dorsal surfaces, lateral margins more densely setose. Mesothoracic spiracle simple, ovate, approximately 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
size of abdominal spiracles; reduced metathoracic spiracle visible, less than one-fourth size of mesothoracic spiracle. Legs. Prothoracic leg slightly longer, much thicker than meso- and metathoracic legs; prothoracic tarsungulus strongly sclerotized, sickle-shaped; prothoracic trochanter with one or two stout ventromedially spines; prothoracic femur with ventromedial row of six to ten spines, dorsal surface with faintly indicated basal sclerotized band; prothoracic tibia with ventromedial row of eight to eleven spines or spinose setae, dorsal surface slightly more sclerotized than ventral surface. Mesotibia with four to five ventromedial spines.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="232">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="232">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Abdominal tergites and sternites light tan, with slightly darker transverse striated bands present along posterior margins of segments I-VIII, forming near contiguous unicolorous band around segments. Abdominal sternite I sparsely clothed in long erect setae from anterior margin to near midline. Abdominal laterotergites with lateral margins distinctly pigmented. Abdominal segment IX (pygidium) triangular in dorsal view, gradually reflexed to apex, urogomphi absent, apex forming a distinct tooth, sparsely clothed in short and mid length erect setae, sclerotized uniformly throughout, lacking maculations; marginal row of 17-23 socketed spines present, arranged as single row around posterior two-thirds to one half of segment. Abdominal sternites I-VIII lacking longitudinal tomentose bands along lateral margins. Pygopods short, subconical, each with 9-12 erect setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="232" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="232">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="232">
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Say" baseAuthorityYear="1824" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Eleodes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="232" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hispilabris">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="232">Eleodes hispilabris</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
larvae can be separated from the other currently known 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Eschscholtz" authorityYear="1829" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Eleodes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="232" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="232">Eleodes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species by the presence of an apical tooth on the pygidium, stout spiniform setae on the anterolateral margins of the epipharnyx, and a row of 6-10 ventromedial spines on the prothoracic femur.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>