<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/AfrInvertebr.59.14621" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e8ff2a16-c941-4663-97c5-5ea93c18baf0" ID-Pensoft-Pub="2305-2562-59(1)-1" ID-ZBK="3269C8DF93AB4B41B19E32CC863760E7" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="2305-2562-59(1)-1" ModsDocOrigin="African Invertebrates 59(1)" ModsDocTitle="A new genus of coprophagous water scavenger beetle from Africa (Coleoptera, Hydrophilidae, Sphaeridiinae, Megasternini) with a discussion on the CercyonsubgenusAcycreon" checkinTime="1515697193413" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Arriaga-Varela, Emmanuel, Seidel, Matthias &amp; Fikacek, Martin" docDate="2018" docId="C4DAC4A9290903087D68DDD6A70895D2" docLanguage="en" docName="AfrInvert 59(1): 1-23" docOrigin="African Invertebrates 59" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/AfrInvertebr.59.14621" docTitle="Evanesternum Arriaga-Varela, Seidel &amp; Fikacek, 2018, gen. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="20A0E313-3427-4049-89DF-0B80D8AEDCEE" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="2" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" masterDocId="AB22FFA4FC04FF913A4D9A0EFFC9FFEF" masterDocTitle="A new genus of coprophagous water scavenger beetle from Africa (Coleoptera, Hydrophilidae, Sphaeridiinae, Megasternini) with a discussion on the CercyonsubgenusAcycreon" masterLastPageNumber="23" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" updateTime="1569462915141" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new genus of coprophagous water scavenger beetle from Africa (Coleoptera, Hydrophilidae, Sphaeridiinae, Megasternini) with a discussion on the CercyonsubgenusAcycreon</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Arriaga-Varela, Emmanuel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Seidel, Matthias</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fikacek, Martin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>African Invertebrates</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>59</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>23</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/AfrInvertebr.59.14621</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/AfrInvertebr.59.14621</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">2305-2562-59(1)-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">3269C8DF93AB4B41B19E32CC863760E7</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">3269C8DF93AB4B41B19E32CC863760E7</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:C4DAC4A9290903087D68DDD6A70895D2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C4DAC4A9290903087D68DDD6A70895D2" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/20A0E313-3427-4049-89DF-0B80D8AEDCEE" class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Evanesternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Evanesternum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Evanesternum</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="3">gen. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Evanesternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Evanesternum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Evanesternum</taxonomicName>
gen. n. can be distinguished from other members of the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="tribe" tribe="Megasternini">Megasternini</taxonomicName>
by the following combination of characters: dorsal surface of head and protonum covered by granulose-reticulate microsculpture (Fig. 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="d–e">d-e</normalizedToken>
); anterior margin of mentum rounded (Figs 2b, 4b); gena with strong ridge parallel to posterior margin of eye (Fig. 4a); pronotum with broadly and deeply sulcate lateral margins (Fig. 4e); antennal grooves present, small, not reaching lateral margins of pronotum (Fig. 4c); middle portion of prosternum faintly demarcated from antennal grooves by a group of oblique wrinkled sulci (Fig. 4c); mesoventral plate broad, elliptical at base but abruptly vanished in anterior half (Fig. 4g); metaventrite without anterolateral arcuate lines and femoral lines, with very large median raised elevated area almost reaching lateral margins (Figs 3, 4h); male sternite 9 with lateral struts only reaching to half the length of the median projection (Fig. 1f).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Body small, elongate-oval, weakly convex.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Head. Clypeus with anterior margin with fine bead-like protuberance, anteromedian margin straight medially, anterolateral corners rounded, antennal bases exposed (Fig. 4a); frontoclypeal suture distinct laterally, reduced medially; transverse ridges absent. Median portion of frons and clypeus not elevated above remaining surface. Whole dorsal surface with coarse transverse, moderately dense punctation, punctures bearing fine decumbent setae. Area between punctures with granulose-reticulate microsculpture (Fig. 4d). Eyes small, situated on lateral angular portions of head, with dorsal portion smaller than ventral one, separated by 6.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="–7.5×">-7.5x</normalizedToken>
the width of one eye in dorsal view, posterior margin with an additional ridge present along the posterior margin of eye, arising from its dorsolateral portion and reaching ca. half-way between eye and maxillary articulation ventrally (Fig. 4a). Labrum ca. 0.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as head, membranous, largely retracted under clypeus, weakly bisinuate on anterior margin, sparsely pubescent dorsally, setae longer on lateral portions (Fig. 2a). Mandible with apex simple, strongly curved, with external margin slightly crenulate in anterior half; prostheca with anterior third lobed and covered by thicker setae (Fig. 2c). Maxilla of male with sucking disc on galea; maxillary palps with basal palpomere minute, palpomere 2 large, widened apically, 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as palpomere 3, palpomere 3 about as long as palpomere 4, slightly widening apicad, palpomere 4 fusiform, without digitiform sensilla (Fig. 2d). Mentum (Figs 2b, 4b) transverse, ca. 1.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long, lateral margins with few sparse setae, anterior margin rounded; labial palps trimerous, basal palpomere quadrate, palpomere 2 as long as and narrower than the basal one, with sparse long setae, terminal palpomere narrow, twice as long as the basal one. Submentum with few setiferous punctures, gular sutures vaguely developed, rather widely separated from each other, tentorial pits small, transverse. Antenna (Fig. 4a) with 9 antennomeres; scape long, cylindri 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">cal</pageBreakToken>
, slightly curved medially; pedicel short, bulbous basally; antennomeres 3-5 short, subequal in length, antennomere 5 widened distad; cupule slightly asymmetrical, slightly shorter than antennomere 5; antennomeres 7-9 forming a weakly elongate pubescent club 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, antennomere 7 shortest, antennomeres 8-9 subequal in length, antennomere 9 round at apex; special sensorial antennal fields absent. Genal ridge absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Prothorax. Pronotum transverse, moderately convex, about as wide as bases of both elytra combined; lateral margins broadly sulcate; punctation uniform, consisting of coarse transverse punctures, bearing very small setae; punctures deeper and more rounded laterally. Prosternum (Fig. 4c) narrowly longitudinally carinate medially, weakly tectiform; prosternal process elongate, almost reaching posterior margin of procoxae, not bifurcate; prosternal portion anterior of procoxae moderately wide, with two or three oblique faintly defined wrinkled sulci on each side at mid-width. Procoxal cavities large, open posteriorly. Notosternal suture very short. Antennal grooves present, small, vaguely defined posteriad. (Fig. 3).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Mesothorax. Mesoventrite completely fused with an episternum; anterior collar of mesothorax narrow. Median portion of mesoventrite elevated as a mesoventral plate slightly overlapping anterior margin of metaventrite; plate well defined posteriorly as a broad, semi-elliptical tablet abruptly vanished in anterior half leaving only a narrow median ridge. Grooves for reception of procoxae well defined by a conspicuous carina, short, transverse (Fig. 4g). Mesepimeron very narrow, widening laterad. Mesocoxal cavities moderately narrowly separated. Scutellar shield small, semi-elliptical, 1.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide. Elytra (Fig. 1a, b) weakly convex, narrowly explanate laterally, each elytron bearing 10 series, series 1-9 consisting of setiferous punctures as large as interval punctures but surrounded by a foveolate depression; punctures in series situated in longitudinal impressed sulci; series 1-4 and 9 reaching apex, series 5 and 8 enclosing series 6-7 subapically, series 10 reduced both anteriorly and posteriorly; epipleuron horizontal, weakly gradually narrowing posteriad, accentuating about half the length of metaventrite, vanishing shortly after the posterior margin of the metaventrite, bearing sparse short setae (Fig. 3).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Metathorax. Metaventrite (Fig. 4h) with anterior rim narrow, widening on anterolateral corners; mesal elevate area flat and very wide, almost reaching lateral margins; anterior and posterolateral corners distinctly rugose, with short setae. Femoral lines and anterolateral ridges absent. Metanepisternum ca. 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, with anterior oblique ridge, metepimeron with minute ventral portion. Metafurca well developed. Metathoracic wings well developed, with transverse vein r4 arising from basal portion of radial cell, RP rather long, reaching ca. halfway to wing base, basal cubito-anal cell small, closed, wedge cell absent, transverse vein mp-cua joining to MP3+4+CuA1+2; anal lobe not defined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Legs. Procoxae large, subglobular, slightly transverse, with few setae, junction with trochanter; meso- and metacoxae broad, transverse. Tronchatero-femoral junction straight. Femora flattened, with small setae; profemur without impressed parts; metafemur just slightly longer than mesofemur (Fig. 3). Tibiae short, triangular, flat 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="5" start="start">tened</pageBreakToken>
, with broad and relatively long lateral spines and mesal spines. Tarsi pentamerous, with moderately long tarsomeres (Fig. 3), each tarsomere with few stiff setae ventrally and a few fine setae dorsally; metatarsomere 1 slightly longer than tarsomere 2 and 3 together, tarsomeres 2-4 becoming continuously shorter, tarsomere 5 slightly shorter than tarsomere 1. Claws simple, arcuate; empodium bisetose.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Abdomen with five ventrites. Ventrite 1 with moderately high, broad median carina, briefly extending beyond posterior margin (Fig. 4i). Ventrites 2-5 without mesal carinae. Male sternite IX with tongue-like median projection with acute anterior margin and subtruncate posterior margin, lateral struts reaching half of the length of the median projection (Fig. 1f). Aedeagus (Fig. 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="c–e">c-e</normalizedToken>
) simple, median lobe subparallel-sided, phallobase long, symmetrical, with manubrium slightly asymmetrical; parameres simple. Female genitalia corresponding to that of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Kanala" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kanala" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Kanala</taxonomicName>
(see 
<bibRefCitation author="Fikacek, M" editor="Jaech, MA" journalOrPublisher="Monographs of Coleoptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" pagination="365 - 394" title="Hydrophilidae: The genus Kanala Balfour-Browne (Coleoptera)." volume="3" volumeTitle="Water Beetles of New Caledonia, Vol. 1." year="2010">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Fikáček">Fikacek</normalizedToken>
2010
</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
The generic name is derived from evanescere (Latin, &quot;to vanish&quot;) and sternum (Greek, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“chest”">&quot;chest&quot;</normalizedToken>
) which refers to the anteriorly vanishing mesoventral plate. The gender is neutrum.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="type and only species">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Type and only species.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Evanesternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Evanesternum pulsatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pulsatum">Evanesternum pulsatum</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Orchymont">d'Orchymont</normalizedToken>
, 1937), comb. n.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>