<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.21651" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4c42eda5-3754-400b-b0cf-6f975332694d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="139582953" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-0743-1-57" ID-ZBK="39801E33A9E44DE18885C3A78CF5A0C8" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E7EFEBE1-7CD7-46EF-B57D-DA6D9920C045" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1860-0743-1-57" ModsDocOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 94 (1)" ModsDocTitle="A review of the montane lacewing genus Rapisma McLachlan (Neuroptera, Ithonidae) from China, with description of two new species" checkinTime="1515178528470" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Liu, Xingyue" docDate="2018" docId="480274AB19CE3E9E76F5C413B30E2CEC" docLanguage="en" docName="ZoosystEvol 94(1): 57-71" docOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 94 (1)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.21651" docTitle="Rapisma changqingensis Liu, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="E7EFEBE1-7CD7-46EF-B57D-DA6D9920C045" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="64" masterDocId="FF8A256AFB44FFFE7439FFF8FFB6FF9C" masterDocTitle="A review of the montane lacewing genus Rapisma McLachlan (Neuroptera, Ithonidae) from China, with description of two new species" masterLastPageNumber="71" masterPageNumber="57" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" updateTime="1643529347626" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of the montane lacewing genus Rapisma McLachlan (Neuroptera, Ithonidae) from China, with description of two new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liu, Xingyue</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zoosystematics and Evolution</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>94</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>57</mods:start>
<mods:end>71</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.21651</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.21651</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-0743-1-57</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">39801E33A9E44DE18885C3A78CF5A0C8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">39801E33A9E44DE18885C3A78CF5A0C8</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="139582953" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E7EFEBE1-7CD7-46EF-B57D-DA6D9920C045" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/480274AB19CE3E9E76F5C413B30E2CEC" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="64" pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/E7EFEBE1-7CD7-46EF-B57D-DA6D9920C045" class="Insecta" family="Ithonidae" genus="Rapisma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rapisma changqingensis" order="Neuroptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="changqingensis">Rapisma changqingensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="6" pageNumber="63">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 2, 3, 7, 8, 10
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Body and forewings generally greenish in both males and females. Head medially without dark marking. Antenna extremely short, less than 1/5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
forewing length. Male gonocoxites 9 paired, glabrous; each with a broad subtrapezoidal lobe and a slender, arcuately curved lateral arm; fused gonocoxites 11 generally arched, anteriorly broadly concaved but with a semicircular median notch, posteriorly convex in dorsal view; gonostyli 11 having obtuse dorsal lobe with a few short setae, and flat ventral lobe distally with a pair of tufts of long setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Male. Body length 18.0 mm; forewing length 25.0 mm, hindwing length 21.7 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Head nearly semiglobular, largely retracted under prothorax, barely visible in dorsal view. Head slightly yellowish green; a narrow blackish stripe present around compound eye and slightly extending toward vertex. Compound eyes blackish brown; EI ratio 0.68. Antenna nearly moniliform, short, 4.0 mm long, with 24 flagellomeres; yellowish throughout. Mandibles with tips black.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Thorax entirely greenish, meso- and metathorax slightly paler than prothorax, without any distinct markings. Legs yellowish throughout; pretarsal claws reddish brown with base yellowish, proximally slightly produced.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Forewing greenish, immaculate. Trichosors absent. A proximal nygma present between RP+MA and MP, whitish. RP with 8 pectinate branches. Hindwing much paler than forewing. A proximal nygma present between RP+MA and MP, whitish. Costal space with a few interlink veinlets among costal crossveins on proximal half. RP with 7 pectinate branches.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Abdomen yellowish green, with terga and genitalia brown. Tergum 9 subtrapezoidal, with sparse short setae. Sternum 9 slightly shorter than tergum 9, about 2.0 times as wide as long, with slightly arcuate posterior margin. Ectoprocts slightly shorter and much narrower than tergum 9, ventrally divided into a pair of ovoid lobes; callus cerci present, slightly prominent. Gonocoxites 9 paired, glabrous; each with a broad subtrapezoidal lobe and a slender, arcuately curved lateral arm. Fused gonocoxites 11 generally arched, anteriorly broadly concaved but with a semicircular median notch, posteriorly convex in dorsal view. Gonostyli 11 with a pair of dorsal and a single ventral lobe; dorsal lobe obtuse, with a few short setae; ventral lobe flat, distally with a pair of tufts of long setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Female. Body length 24.8 mm; forewing length 32.0 mm, hindwing length 28.9 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Body and forewings in general greenish. Head without dark marking. Forewing with a few tiny dark spots.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Sternum 7 large, posteromedially with a narrow groove. Gonocoxites+gonapophyses 8 fused, broadly subtrapezoid, notched distally, with a pair of digitiform projections and a weak median projection. Gonocoxites 9 nearly semicircular in lateral view, distally with tiny gonostyli 9; a pair of small setose ovoid gonapophyses 9 present posteriad gonocoxites 8 and beneath gonocoxites 9. Ectoprocts nearly semicircular in lateral view.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Figure 7. Living habitus of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ithonidae" genus="Rapisma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rapisma changqingensis" order="Neuroptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="changqingensis">Rapisma changqingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., (A) male adult, lateral view; (B) female adult, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Figure 8. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ithonidae" genus="Rapisma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rapisma changqingensis" order="Neuroptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="changqingensis">Rapisma changqingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., (A) male genitalia, dorsal view; (B) male genitalia, ventral view; (C) male gonocoxites 11, dorsal view; (D) male gonostyli 11, dorsofrontal view; (E) complex of internal male genital sclerites, ventral view; (F) female genitalia, lateral view; (G) female genitalia, ventral view; (H) female gonocoxites+gonapophyses 8, ventral view. c - callus cercus; e - ectoproct; gx - gonocoxite; gp - gonapophysis; T - tergum; S - sternum. Gonocoxites 9, gonocoxites 11 and gonostyli 11 are respectively highlighted in pale blue, pale green and green in panels 
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–E">C-E</normalizedToken>
. Gonocoxites 9 and gonapophyses 9 are respectively highlighted in pale blue and dark blue in panel G (gonostyli 9 present but barely visible in lateral and ventral view), while gonocoxites 8 and gonapophyses 8 are respectively highlighted in pale yellow and yellow in panels G and H. Scale bar: 1.0 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Materials examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Holotype male, China, Shaanxi, Yangxian, Changqing National Nature Reserve, Yangjiagou, 1281 m, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="33.639">33.6390°N</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="107.4965">107.4965°E</geoCoordinate>
, 18.VII.2017, Bozun Huang &amp; Zhifei Liu (CAU). Paratype: 1 female, same collecting site as holotype, 24.VII.2017, Puyuan Liu (CAU).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">The new species is named based on the Changqing National Nature Reserve where type specimens of this species were collected.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">China (Shaanxi).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="64" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
The new species appears to be closely related to 
<taxonomicName genus="R." lsidName="R. yanhuangi" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" rank="species" species="yanhuangi">R. yanhuangi</taxonomicName>
from Sichuan by the similar body and wing coloration as well as the general characteristics of male genitalia, but it can be distinguished from the latter species by the male head medially without dark marking, the male gonostyli 11 with a pair of dorsal lobes not prominent posterolaterally, and the shape of male fused gonocoxites 11. In 
<taxonomicName genus="R." lsidName="R. yanhuangi" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" rank="species" species="yanhuangi">R. yanhuangi</taxonomicName>
the male head medially possesses several dark markings, the dorsal lobes of male gonostyli 11 are distinctly prominent posterolaterally, and the male fused gonocoxites 11 is differently shaped compared with 
<taxonomicName genus="R." lsidName="R. changqingensis" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" rank="species" species="changqingensis">R. changqingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="64" pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
The two specimens of this new species were collected by accident in a field survey performed by a summer camp for natural education called &quot;Wings of Nature&quot; in 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="64" start="start">Changqing</pageBreakToken>
National Nature Reserve, Shaanxi, China. All collectors of these two specimens are middle school students. The holotype male was found falling in a pond probably from a tree nearby, while the paratype female was found resting on a tree.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
The Changqing National Nature Reserve is located at the southern slope of Qinling Mountains, which is commonly considered as a boundary between Palaearctic and Oriental regions in China (
<bibRefCitation author="Zhang, YZ" journalOrPublisher="Science Press, Beijing" pageId="12" pageNumber="69" title="Zoogeography of China." year="1999">Zhang 1999</bibRefCitation>
), and it is one of the nature reserves that harbour some endangered wildlife, such as giant pandas, crested ibises, sub-nosed monkeys, etc. The climate of the collecting site of 
<taxonomicName genus="R." lsidName="R. changqingensis" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rank="species" species="changqingensis">R. changqingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is warm temperate, and the vegetation is kind of mixed evergreen broad-leaf and coniferous forest. However, most 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ithonidae" genus="Rapisma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rapisma" order="Neuroptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Rapisma</taxonomicName>
species are from subtropical or tropical regions with rainforests. So far, 
<taxonomicName genus="R." lsidName="R. changqingensis" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rank="species" species="changqingensis">R. changqingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. represents the northernmost record of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ithonidae" genus="Rapisma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rapisma" order="Neuroptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Rapisma</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>