<document ID="10.11646/zootaxa.4247.5.5SLASH10678" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6033244" ID-GBIF-Dataset="92957f37-f810-4bdf-a6e6-fcf99047b816" ID-GBIF-Taxon="128090212" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6033244" ID-ZooBank="427F743A-5286-4023-80A6-66659E5B7B49" checkinTime="1490859898841" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Bezark, Larry G. &amp; Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2017" docId="03CE9B411F7AFD15FF1D558AFB7D5E32" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4247.5.5SLASH10678.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4247 (5)" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@63fdffcd" docStyleName="zootaxa.2013.journal_article" docTitle="Odontocera magnifica Bezark &amp; Santos-Silva, 2017, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="590" masterDocId="FFF7E3391F79FD10FF8A5145FFF25D27" masterDocTitle="Three new species of Ecuadorian Rhinotragini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae)" masterLastPageNumber="592" masterPageNumber="585" pageId="3" pageNumber="588" updateTime="1644480930646" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Three new species of Ecuadorian Rhinotragini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bezark, Larry G.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4247</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>5</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>585</mods:start>
<mods:end>592</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4247.5.5</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">92957f37-f810-4bdf-a6e6-fcf99047b816</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">439185</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">427F743A-5286-4023-80A6-66659E5B7B49</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6033244" ID-GBIF-Taxon="128090212" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6033244" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03CE9B411F7AFD15FF1D558AFB7D5E32" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CE9B411F7AFD15FF1D558AFB7D5E32" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="590" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="588" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,523,1231,1291]" box="[151,523,1231,1258]" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,523,1231,1258]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="3" pageNumber="588" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,523,1231,1258]" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">
<taxonomicName box="[151,422,1231,1257]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="588" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="magnifica" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,422,1231,1257]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">Odontocera magnifica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[429,523,1232,1258]" pageId="3" pageNumber="588" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,523,1231,1291]" box="[151,273,1266,1291]" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,265,1266,1291]" captionStart="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4" captionStartId="2.[151,264,1953,1976]" captionTargetBox="[187,1392,196,1924]" captionTargetId="figure@2.[185,1402,193,1932]" captionTargetPageId="2" captionText="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4, Paraeclipta ecuadorensis sp. nov., holotype female: 1. Dorsal habitus; 2. Ventral habitus; 3. Lateral hatibus; 4. Head, frontal view. 5 – 8, Odontocera magnifica sp. nov., holotype female: 5. Dorsal habitus; 6. Ventral habitus; 7. Lateral habitus; 8. Head, frontal view." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/439186/files/figure.png" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">Figs. 5–8</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="590" pageId="3" pageNumber="588" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,1338,2011]" lastBlockId="4.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="589" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,401,1338,1363]" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">Description. Female.</emphasis>
Integument orange, more yellowish on some areas. Antennal tubercles black, except for small orange region on frontal base. Area between antennal tubercles and posterior margin of upper eye lobes black (this black area centrally projected toward frons between antennal tubercles). Frons slightly reddish-brown along longitudinal sulcus; central area between frons and clypeus reddish-brown. Labrum reddish-brown. Apex of mandibles dark brown. Genae with large, triangular, dark brown macula, not reaching lower eye lobe. Ventral side of head with dark brown macula on each side of base. Scape black dorsally, reddish-brown laterally and ventrally; pedicel black; antennomere III dark brown on base, gradually becoming reddish-brown toward apex; antennomeres IV–XI reddish-brown. Pronotum with complex, black macula (
<figureCitation box="[876,947,1590,1615]" captionStart="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4" captionStartId="2.[151,264,1953,1976]" captionTargetBox="[187,1392,196,1924]" captionTargetId="figure@2.[185,1402,193,1932]" captionTargetPageId="2" captionText="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4, Paraeclipta ecuadorensis sp. nov., holotype female: 1. Dorsal habitus; 2. Ventral habitus; 3. Lateral hatibus; 4. Head, frontal view. 5 – 8, Odontocera magnifica sp. nov., holotype female: 5. Dorsal habitus; 6. Ventral habitus; 7. Lateral habitus; 8. Head, frontal view." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/439186/files/figure.png" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">Fig. 5</figureCitation>
), partially projected toward sides (
<figureCitation box="[1351,1422,1590,1615]" captionStart="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4" captionStartId="2.[151,264,1953,1976]" captionTargetBox="[187,1392,196,1924]" captionTargetId="figure@2.[185,1402,193,1932]" captionTargetPageId="2" captionText="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4, Paraeclipta ecuadorensis sp. nov., holotype female: 1. Dorsal habitus; 2. Ventral habitus; 3. Lateral hatibus; 4. Head, frontal view. 5 – 8, Odontocera magnifica sp. nov., holotype female: 5. Dorsal habitus; 6. Ventral habitus; 7. Lateral habitus; 8. Head, frontal view." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/439186/files/figure.png" pageId="3" pageNumber="588">Fig. 7</figureCitation>
). Sides of prothorax with small, elongate, oblique, dark-brown macula on center of basal third. Mesosternum brownish anteriorly, with transverse, dark brown macula closer to mesosternal process, reddish-brown on remaining surface. Central area of metasternum reddish-brown, except for small, brown macula on distal half; margin of metasternum close to metepisterna with narrow, black band, not reaching base, which continues posteriorly along metacoxal cavity (not reaching center). Metepisterna with narrow, black band on anterior margin and along basal and distal area close to elytra (distinctly wider on distal area). Elytra reddish-brown on humeri, yellowish basally on each side of scutellum, with black, transverse macula near base, not reaching sides, continuing along suture, gradually becoming light reddish-brown toward apex; with narrow, dark-brown band close to lateral margin, from humeri to about apex of basal 1/5, enlarged about apex of basal quarter, continuing as narrow band toward apex close to translucent area; lateral margin reddish-brown from apex of basal 1/5 to apex near apex; remaining surface translucent. Femoral club reddish-brown dorsally and laterally. Mesotibiae with longitudinal, light brown macula on basal third of outer side. Abdominal ventrites I–II centrally with narrow, dark-brown band close to apex, distinctly enlarged laterally (continuing along lateral margin along distal half at ventrite I, from base to apex at ventrite II); ventrites III–V entirely black.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,2013]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,263,260,285]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">Head</emphasis>
. Basal area not elongate behind eyes (distance between posterior edge of eyes and prothoracic margin equal to width of upper eye lobes); rostrum (area between lower eye lobe and apex of gena) viewed from front, slightly shorter than length of lower eye lobe. Frons finely, abundantly punctate laterally close to lower lobe of eyes, smooth laterally and medially toward clypeus, finely striate-punctate medially below lower eye lobes, coarsely, confluently punctate in middle between lobes; with short, sparse, yellowish setae, denser close to margin of lower eye lobes. Area between antennal tubercles and prothoracic margin finely, densely punctate (punctures finer closer to prothoracic margin); with erect, moderately short, sparse, yellowish setae, slightly more abundant between antennal tubercles. Antennal tubercles finely, abundantly punctate anteriorly, punctures distinctly sparser posteriorly. Clypeus finely, sparsely punctate; with short, sparse setae interspersed with long, erect setae. Labrum finely, moderately abundantly punctate on narrow, transverse band close to clypeus, smooth on remaining surface except for moderately coarse punctures on each side, from which emerges long, erect seta. Outer edge of mandibles finely, abundantly punctate on basal half; with short, yellowish setae interspersed with some long, erect setae. Area behind lower eye lobes coarsely, abundantly punctate on central region, with punctures slightly marked close to eye, more finely punctate closer to prothoracic margin; with dense golden pubescence close eye interspersed with long, erect setae. Ventral surface of head smooth toward prothorax, obliquely striate laterally on sides of submentum, with shallow, coarse, sparse punctures, primarily laterally, more finely, transversely striate anteriorly in middle; with short, moderately sparse setae where sculptured. Genae finely, moderately abundantly punctate, except for narrow, smooth area close to apex; with minute, very sparse setae. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.55 times length of scape; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.55 times length of scape. Antennae 0.7 times elytral length, reaching extreme base of abdominal ventrite I; scape, pedicel and antennomeres III–VI with long, erect, dark, thick, moderately abundant setae ventrally (shorter on scape and antennomere III, and present only near apex on VI); antennal formula (ratio) based on antennomere III: scape = 0.95; pedicel = 0.28; IV = 0.61; V = 0.64; VI = 0.59; VII = 0.56; VIII = 0.46; IX = 0.41; X = 0.36; XI = 0.49.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,2013]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,288,1087,1112]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">Thorax</emphasis>
. Prothorax subcylindrical, slightly longer than wide (1.05 times). Pronotum coarsely punctatealveolate, except basal and distal smooth margins; with long, erect, sparse brown setae throughout. Sides of prothorax with same sculpture as on pronotum, except for sub-smooth basal and distal areas, which widens ventrally); punctate region with long, sparse, yellowish setae. Prosternum moderately finely, densely punctate on basal half in middle, finely, sparsely punctate on remaining surface; punctate area with short and long, erect, yellowish setae, nearly glabrous on remaining surface. Prosternal process moderately pubescent, interspersed with long, erect setae on widened distal area. Mesosternum finely, abundantly punctate close to procoxal cavities, microsculptured on remaining surface; with yellowish-white pubescence, indistinct depending on angle of light. Mesepimera and mesepisterna with yellowish-white pubescence interspersed with long, erect setae. Metepisterna with dense, yellowish-white pubescence on base, apex and on basal third adjacent to elytra; remaining surface with short, sparse, decumbent setae interspersed with long, erect, moderately abundant setae. Metasternum with short and long setae, both erect, moderately abundant throughout, pubescent near anterior margin. Scutellum with minute, decumbent, yellowish setae, indistinct depending on angle of light. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1066,1142,1519,1544]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">Elytra</emphasis>
. Apex of elytra slightly surpassing middle of abdominal segment IV; outer margin convergent on basal third, nearly parallel-sided toward apex; sutural margin fissate on distal half; apex narrowly, obliquely truncate; basal area before translucent region coarsely punctate-alveolate; narrow outer area along translucent region finely, confluently punctate; translucent area very finely, sparsely punctate; with long, erect, dark setae on base, distinctly shorter, sparser on translucent area. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[211,267,1700,1725]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">Legs</emphasis>
. Femoral club with erect, sparse, dark setae interspersed with yellowish setae. Metatarsomere I 1.2 times longer than II–III together.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,2013]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,316,1772,1797]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">Abdomen</emphasis>
. Sides of abdomen divergent from base to apex of segment III, then convergent toward apex of segment V. Ventrites I–II finely, sparsely punctate on light region, finely, densely punctate laterally on dark region; ventrites III–V finely, moderately abundantly punctate in middle, densely punctate laterally; ventrites with short, decumbent yellowish-white setae (indistinct depending on angle o light), slightly more abundant laterally, interspersed with erect setae; apex of ventrite V sub-truncate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastBlockId="5.[151,1437,151,789]" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="590" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,309,1952,1977]" pageId="4" pageNumber="589">Variation</emphasis>
. Black area between upper eye lobes not projected toward region between antennal tubercles; labrum dark-brown; macula on each side of base of head reddish-brown; pedicel dark reddish-brown; antennomere III entirely reddish-brown; small macula on basal third of sides of prothorax reddish-brown or almost absent; mesosternum entirely orange or brownish anteriorly, but without transverse dark-brown macula close to mesosternal process; central area of metasternum with wide, irregular, brown regions; center of basal half of ventrite III with irregular, yellowish area.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[151,1437,151,789]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,533,295,320]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Dimensions in mm (female)</emphasis>
. Total length, 13.00–11.90; prothorax: length, 2.20–2.00; anterior width, 1.70– 1.60; posterior width, 1.70–1.60; widest prothoracic width, 2.00–1.85; humeral width, 2.40–2.30; elytral length, 8.20–7.80. The largest dimensions are those of the 
<typeStatus box="[722,824,367,392]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="590" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="5.[151,1437,151,789]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1454954779" collectingDate="1998-09-16" collectionCode="CASC, MZSP, LGBC" collectorName="F. T. Hovore" country="Ecuador" location="Loreto Road" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" specimenCount="3" stateProvince="Napo" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,369,404,429]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">
<typeStatus box="[199,258,404,429]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Type</typeStatus>
material
</emphasis>
. 
<typeStatus box="[387,491,404,429]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Holotype</typeStatus>
female (
<collectionCode box="[596,675,404,428]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">CASC</collectionCode>
), two 
<typeStatus box="[750,846,405,429]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">paratype</typeStatus>
females (
<collectionCode box="[962,1040,404,428]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">MZSP</collectionCode>
; 
<collectionCode box="[1055,1129,404,428]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">LGBC</collectionCode>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1130,1139,404,429]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">)</emphasis>
from 
<collectingCountry box="[1214,1352,404,428]" name="Ecuador" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">ECUADOR</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[1367,1428,405,428]" country="Ecuador" name="Napo" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">
<emphasis box="[1367,1428,405,428]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Napo</emphasis>
</collectingRegion>
: 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03CE9B411F7AFD15FF1D558AFB7D5E32:8EB87C8C1F7CFD15FF1D50FDFED15CF7" box="[151,291,439,464]" country="Ecuador" name="Loreto Road" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" stateProvince="Napo">Loreto Road</location>
(
<locationDeviation box="[307,481,439,464]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">
<quantity box="[307,365,439,464]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="7.0" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" unit="km" value="7.0">7 km</quantity>
E Nampa
</locationDeviation>
), 
<collectingDate box="[500,630,439,464]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" value="1998-09-16">
<date box="[500,630,439,464]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" value="1998-09-16">16.IX.1998</date>
</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName box="[641,782,440,463]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">F. T. Hovore</collectorName>
col.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="590" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="5.[151,1437,151,789]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,326,476,501]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Etymology</emphasis>
. The species name 
<taxonomicName box="[551,663,476,500]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="magnifica">
<emphasis box="[551,663,476,500]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">magnifica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(splendid in Latin) refers to the distinct fascia on the pronotum and the base of the elytra.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="590" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="5.[151,1437,151,789]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,308,548,573]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Remarks</emphasis>
. 
<taxonomicName box="[323,577,548,572]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="magnifica" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[323,577,548,572]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Odontocera magnifica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[585,676,548,573]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" rank="species">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[585,676,548,573]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">sp. nov.</emphasis>
</taxonomicNameLabel>
differs from 
<taxonomicName authority="Zajciw, 1963" authorityName="Zajciw" authorityYear="1963" box="[828,1110,548,573]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armipes">
<emphasis box="[828,954,548,572]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">O. armipes</emphasis>
Zajciw, 1963
</taxonomicName>
as follows: elytra are longer when compared with prothorax (about 3.7 times); the markings on the pronotum formed by black maculae are different (
<figureCitation box="[265,336,620,645]" captionStart="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4" captionStartId="2.[151,264,1953,1976]" captionTargetBox="[187,1392,196,1924]" captionTargetId="figure@2.[185,1402,193,1932]" captionTargetPageId="2" captionText="FIGURES 1 – 8. 1 – 4, Paraeclipta ecuadorensis sp. nov., holotype female: 1. Dorsal habitus; 2. Ventral habitus; 3. Lateral hatibus; 4. Head, frontal view. 5 – 8, Odontocera magnifica sp. nov., holotype female: 5. Dorsal habitus; 6. Ventral habitus; 7. Lateral habitus; 8. Head, frontal view." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/439186/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">Fig. 5</figureCitation>
); and the transverse black band on the base of the elytra reaches the suture. In 
<taxonomicName box="[1258,1385,620,644]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armipes">
<emphasis box="[1258,1385,620,644]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">O. armipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, the elytra are shorter compared to prothorax (about 3.0 times), the black maculae on the pronotum are isolated (see photograph of the 
<typeStatus box="[357,455,692,717]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">holotype</typeStatus>
at 
<bibRefCitation author="Bezark" box="[490,636,692,717]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" refString="Bezark, L. G. (2016) A photographic Catalog of the Cerambycidae of the New World. Available from: https: // apps 2. cdfa. ca. gov / publicApps / plant / bycidDB / wsearch. asp? w = n (accessed 31 March 2016)" type="journal article" year="2016">Bezark 2016</bibRefCitation>
), and the black band on the base of the elytra does not reach the suture. The pronotal markings are very similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Zajciw, 1962" authorityName="Zajciw" authorityYear="1962" box="[626,972,727,752]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hirundipennis">
<emphasis box="[626,816,728,752]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">O. hirundipennis</emphasis>
Zajciw, 1962
</taxonomicName>
, but the new species has wider elytra and is not notably divergent as in this species (see photograph of the 
<typeStatus box="[875,973,764,789]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590">holotype</typeStatus>
at 
<bibRefCitation author="Bezark" box="[1007,1155,764,789]" pageId="5" pageNumber="590" refString="Bezark, L. G. (2016) A photographic Catalog of the Cerambycidae of the New World. Available from: https: // apps 2. cdfa. ca. gov / publicApps / plant / bycidDB / wsearch. asp? w = n (accessed 31 March 2016)" type="journal article" year="2016">Bezark 2016</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>