<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.686.12223" ID-GBIF-Dataset="1ec15483-640e-4600-9248-16f7ff65d128" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648818" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-686-1" ID-ZBK="C7DCD3FB3EB6413CB580972BC8B9075E" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7C4E336D-2489-45DF-8056-407428866AEE" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-686-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 686" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Hyalella from the High Andes of Ecuador (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Hyalellidae)" checkinTime="1502744451182" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Alonso, Miguel &amp; Jaume, Damia" docDate="2017" docId="8CE29E510955F639073F10C2403269F8" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 686: 1-13" docOrigin="ZooKeys 686" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.686.12223" docTitle="Hyalella cajasi Alonso &amp; Jaume, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="7C4E336D-2489-45DF-8056-407428866AEE" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="2" masterDocId="FFB6FFDCFF8DFFF89E34FF9611166D12" masterDocTitle="A new species of Hyalella from the High Andes of Ecuador (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Hyalellidae)" masterLastPageNumber="13" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" updateTime="1643583715083" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of Hyalella from the High Andes of Ecuador (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Hyalellidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Alonso, Miguel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jaume, Damia</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>686</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>13</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.686.12223</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.686.12223</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-686-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">C7DCD3FB3EB6413CB580972BC8B9075E</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">C7DCD3FB3EB6413CB580972BC8B9075E</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648818" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7C4E336D-2489-45DF-8056-407428866AEE" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8CE29E510955F639073F10C2403269F8" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="2" pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/7C4E336D-2489-45DF-8056-407428866AEE" class="Malacostraca" family="FAMILIA" genus="Hyalella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hyalella cajasi" order="ORDO" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cajasi">Hyalella cajasi</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="1">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
All collected by Henrietta Hampel at Cajas National Park (Azuay Province; southern Ecuador), 5th May 2015. Laguna Togliacocha (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-2.798861">S2°47'55.90&quot;</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-79.250595">W79°15'02.13&quot;</geoCoordinate>
); 3,859 m a.s.l. HOLOTYPE: male 9.0 mm, preserved in formaldehyde vial. PARATYPES: Five males and 5 females in formaldehyde vial. Holotype and paratypes registered under same registration number [MECN-SI-Cal-0003]. Laguna Cardenillo (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-2.7817554">S2°46'54.32&quot;</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-79.24735">W79°14'50.48&quot;</geoCoordinate>
); 4,103 m a.s.l. Four males and 6 females. Small laguna between Laguna Cardenillo and La Negra (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-2.7845027">S2°47'04.21&quot;</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-79.24747">W79°14'50.90&quot;</geoCoordinate>
); 4,076 m a.s.l. Nine males and 8 females. Laguna Azul (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-2.7882805">S2°47'17.81&quot;</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-79.24616">W79°14'46.19&quot;</geoCoordinate>
); 4,043 m a.s.l. Five males and 5 females. Small laguna close to La Larga (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-2.79325">S2°47'35.70&quot;</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-79.245575">W79°14'44.08&quot;</geoCoordinate>
); 3,954 m a.s.l. Ten males and 9 females. Pool close to Laguna Luspa (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-2.7983444">S2°47'54.04&quot;</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-79.26304">W79°15'46.94&quot;</geoCoordinate>
); 3,868 m a.s.l. Ten males and 10 females. Laguna Illincocha (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-2.7796082">S2°46'46.59&quot;</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-79.23093">W79°13'51.33&quot;</geoCoordinate>
); 3,986 m a.s.l. One male and 4 females.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Body smooth, non-processiferous. Eyes normal. Antenna 1 much shorter than antenna 2. Incisor of mandibles multi-denticulate. Palp of maxilla 1 short, reaching to less than half distance between its insertion and distal margin of outer lobe, crowned with short robust seta. Inner lobe of maxilla 2 with two pappose setae proximally on medial margin. Coxal plate IV deeply excavated posteriorly. Six pairs of sternal gills, on pereionites II to VII. Uropod 1 sexually dimorphic, with male exhibiting a modified robust seta (&quot;copulatory spine&quot; sensu 
<bibRefCitation author="Bousfield, EL" journalOrPublisher="Bollettino del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale de Verona" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" pagination="175 - 224" title="A contribution to the reclassification of Neotropical freshwater hyalellid amphipods (Crustacea: Gammaridea, Talitroidea)." volume="20" year="1996">Bousfield 1996</bibRefCitation>
) on endopod; modified robust seta hardly curved and only just surpassing tip of endopod. Ramus of uropod 3 shorter than protopod. Telson broader than long, with distal margin evenly rounded; distal armature arranged as a single row of robust setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Species name refers to Cajas National Park (Azuay Province; southern Ecuador), the type locality.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="2" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Description of male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Body (not figured) up to 9.0 mm long, strongly pigmented, virtually black, smooth. Head (Fig. 1A) shorter than pereionites I and II combined; rostrum wanting; lateral lobes truncate; postantennal sinus shallow and broad. Eyes small, round, located behind insertion of antenna 1. Epimeral plates (Fig. 1C) each with unarmed distal margin; plates 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–III">II-III</normalizedToken>
posterodistally acuminate with posterodistal angle strongly produced, subacute; posterior margin of plates with several tiny tooth-like projections each provided with short setule.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Hyalellidae" genus="Hyalella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hyalella cajasi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cajasi">Hyalella cajasi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male. A head with left antenna 1 and antenna 2 attached, lateral B inset of distomedial armature on posterior margin of articles 3-6 of antenna 1 C right epimeral plates D right pleopod 3, posterior. Scale bars: 0.2 mm (A, D); 0.1 mm (B); 0.5 mm (C, E, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–I">G-I</normalizedToken>
); 0.05 mm (F).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="2" pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Antenna 1 (Fig. 1A) much shorter than antenna 2 although longer than peduncle of latter; peduncle longer than head, segments 1-3 relative length as: 1: 1: 0.8; main 
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="2" start="start">flagellum</pageBreakToken>
longer than peduncle; accessory flagellum absent. Pair of aesthetascs present on distomedial angle of posterior margin of middle articles of flagellum (Fig. 1B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Antenna 2 (Fig. 1A) peduncle segments 4-5 relative length as: 0.7: 1.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Labrum (not figured) ordinary. 
<taxonomicName genus="Paragnaths" lsidName="Paragnaths" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" rank="genus">Paragnaths</taxonomicName>
(= lower lip; not figured) inner lobes absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName genus="Mandibles" lsidName="Mandibles" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" rank="genus">Mandibles</taxonomicName>
each with well-developed, triturative columnar molar; molar seta equally developed in both mandibles; palp lacking. Left mandible (Fig. 2A) incisor 7-denticulate; lacinia 5-denticulate. Right mandible (Fig. 2B) incisor 6-denticulate; lacinia complex, with 5 main cusps and multiple denticles, and with patch of short setules proximally on medial surface.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Hyalellidae" genus="Hyalella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hyalella cajasi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cajasi">Hyalella cajasi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male. A left mandible B distal portion of right mandible C maxilla 1 D maxilla 2 E inset of basal endite (= inner plate) of left maxilliped, anterior view. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Maxilla 1 (Fig. 2C) inner lobe finger-like, crowned with two pappose setae; outer lobe with nine serrated stout robust setae distally; palp reduced, unsegmented, reaching to less than half distance between its insertion and distal margin of inner lobe, tapering with tiny conical robust seta on tip.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Maxilla 2 (Fig. 2D) inner lobe with two unequal pappose setae proximally on inner margin, proximal-most seta largest, hyperthophied.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Maxilliped ordinary; basal endite (= inner plate) (Fig. 2E) subrectangular with three flattened triangular short cuspidate robust setae distally and row of pappose setae along medial margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Coxal gills (Figs 3E; 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
) on gnathopod 2 to pereiopod 6, smooth, unstalked, sac-like. Sternal gills on pereionites II to VII, finger-like (Fig. 4F), placed antero-laterally at each side on corresponding sternite.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Hyalellidae" genus="Hyalella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hyalella cajasi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cajasi">Hyalella cajasi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male. A left gnathopod 1, medial (armature on palm margin of propodus and on dactylus omitted) B inset of carpal lobe, medial C inset of palm margin and palm angle of propodus, medial D inset of dactylus, medial E right gnathopod 2, medial (armature on palm margin of propodus and on dactlylus omitted) F inset of carpal lobe, medial G detail of palm margin and palm angle of propodus, and of dactylus, medial (submarginal armature along lateral side of palm margin omitted). Scale bars: 0.2 mm (A, G); 0.1 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
, F); 0.5 mm (E).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
) subchelate. Carpus longer than propodus. Propodus 1.5 times as long as broad, with concave posterior margin; palm margin evenly convex; palm angle with two short flagellate robust setae subequal in length on medial side (Fig. 3C). Dactylus with single triangular denticle subdistally on medial margin (Fig. 3D).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–G">E-G</normalizedToken>
) subchelate. Propodus massive, broadly expanded, 1.3 times as long as broad with palm length longer than carpal lobe; palm margin longer than posterior margin of segment, convex but sinuous, with continuous row of densely set robust setae along both sides of margin (only row on medial side shown in Fig. 3G); palm angle with two short, reduced flagellate robust setae on medial side. Unguis completely incorporated into dactylus (Fig. 3G).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Pereiopods 3-4 (Fig. 4A, B) similar except for coxal plates. Pereiopod 4 slightly shorter than pereiopod 3, with coxa deeply excavated posteriorly.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Hyalellidae" genus="Hyalella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hyalella cajasi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cajasi">Hyalella cajasi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male. A right pereiopod 3, lateral B right pereiopod 4, lateral C right pereiopod 5, lateral, coxal gill omitted D right pereiopod 6, lateral, coxal gill omitted E left pereiopod 7, medial F left sternal gill on sternite of pereionite VII. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Pereiopods 5-7 (Fig. 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–E">C-E</normalizedToken>
) progressively longer towards posterior. Basis of pereiopod 7 broadest, 1.2 times as long as broad; basis of pereiopod 5 1.3 times as long as broad; basis of pereiopod 6 more slender, 1.5 times as long as broad. All limbs with propodus distinctly longer than their respective carpus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Pleopods (Fig. 1D) all similar, biramous, rami multi-annulated and provided with long plumose setae; integument of posterior face of protopod (= peduncle) and proximomedial margin of proximal article of endopod, setulose, as figured.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Uropod 1 (Fig. 1E) protopod longer than rami. Armature of protopod consisting of series of 3-4 flagellate robust setae proximally along posterolateral margin, and single flagellate robust seta at each posterodistal and posteromedial angle of segment; posteromedial margin of segment unarmed. Exopod with series of five flagellate robust setae along lateral margin and three robust setae on tip, none of which flagellate; medial margin of segment unarmed. Endopod with four flagellate robust setae along medial margin and three robust setae on tip, none of which flagellate; lateral margin of segment with series of four flagellate robust setae disposed subdistally on margin, of which proximal-most modified, longer than rest, slightly surpassing tip of endopod, slightly curved and complexly denticulate on tip (&quot;copulatory spine&quot; sensu Bousfield 1986; Fig. 1F).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Uropod 2 (Fig. 1G) protopod about as long as rami. Protopod with three flagellate robust setae along posterolateral margin; robust seta present on each posterodistal and posteromedial angle of segment, of which that on posteromedial angle non-flagellate and more slender than counterpart; posteromedial margin of segment unarmed. Exopod with five flagellate robust setae along lateral margin and three robust setae on tip; medial margin unarmed. Endopod with 3-4 flagellate robust setae along medial margin, three robust setae on tip, and three flagellate robust setae disposed subdistally on lateral margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Uropod 3 (Fig. 1H) ramus about as long as protopod. Protopod with transverse comb of 3-6 flagellate robust setae on distolateral angle, simple seta on distomedial angle, and isolated reduced simple seta on medial margin. Ramus 2.2 times longer than broad, with short robust seta and a bunch of long simple setae on tip.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Telson (Fig. 1I) broader than long, with distal margin evenly rounded. Armature consisting of continuous marginal series of 4-7 (exceptionally only three) flagellate robust setae distally plus three tiny plumose setae disposed distolaterally at each side.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Description of brooding female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Differing from male in smaller size (body up to 6.5 mm long); presence of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="oöstegites">ooestegites</normalizedToken>
on pereionites II-V (Fig. 5A, B); aspect of gnathopod 2 (Fig. 5A), which is similar to male gnathopod 1 but with a more slender propodus (1.7 times as long as broad and attaining 95% length of carpus; versus 1.5 times as long as broad and attaining 89% length of carpus in male gnathopod 1); unequal length of robust setae on palm angle of gnathopod 2 (Fig. 5C); and endopod of uropod 1 with two flagellate robust setae along distolateral margin (versus four in male), of which none modified (Fig. 5D).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Hyalellidae" genus="Hyalella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hyalella cajasi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cajasi">Hyalella cajasi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female. A left gnathopod 2, medial B inset of marginal setae on 
<normalizedToken originalValue="oöstegite">ooestegite</normalizedToken>
C inset of distal margin of propodus plus dactylus, medial D right uropod 1, posterior. Scale bars: 0.2 mm (A); 0.05 mm (B); 0.1 mm (C, D).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>