<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.131.1921" ID-GBIF-Dataset="72a81528-63ef-4531-9f9c-ade551a651d8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031139" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-131-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8D3CA11A-5DFF-4F3A-AA8E-20691FDB6893" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-131-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 131" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the Southeast Asian millipede genus Orthomorpha Bollman, 1893, with the proposal of a new genus (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Paradoxosomatidae)" checkinTime="1451249839150" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Likhitrakarn, Natdanai, Golovatch, Sergei I. &amp; Panha, Somsak" docDate="2011" docId="43AAA2F09E47ECD9574A545AF55DFEAF" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 131: 1-161" docOrigin="ZooKeys 131" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.131.1921" docTitle="Orthomorpha atypica Likhitrakarn, Golovatch &amp; Panha, 2011, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="8D3CA11A-5DFF-4F3A-AA8E-20691FDB6893" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" masterDocId="FFFF0F54FF88BD1C371C965D22453928" masterDocTitle="Revision of the Southeast Asian millipede genus Orthomorpha Bollman, 1893, with the proposal of a new genus (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Paradoxosomatidae)" masterLastPageNumber="161" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" updateTime="1643553799862" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the Southeast Asian millipede genus Orthomorpha Bollman, 1893, with the proposal of a new genus (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Paradoxosomatidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Likhitrakarn, Natdanai</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Golovatch, Sergei I.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Panha, Somsak</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>131</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>161</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.131.1921</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.131.1921</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-131-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B4F618FD-5F5D-4A8C-9140-98491F8A3B9B</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031139" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8D3CA11A-5DFF-4F3A-AA8E-20691FDB6893" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/43AAA2F09E47ECD9574A545AF55DFEAF" lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8D3CA11A-5DFF-4F3A-AA8E-20691FDB6893" class="Diplopoda" family="Aphelidesmidae" genus="Orthomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthomorpha atypica" order="Polydesmida" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atypica">Orthomorpha atypica</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="30" pageNumber="31">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 2830
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
♂ (CUMZ), Thailand, Chanthaburi Prov., Khlung Distr., Troknong Waterfall, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="12.908055">12°54'29&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="102.403336">102°24'12&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, 01.10.2009, leg. C. Sutcharit &amp; N. Likhitrakarn.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="paratypes">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Paratypes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">25 ♂, 30 ♀ (CUMZ), 3 ♂, 3 ♀ (ZMUC), 3 ♂, 3 ♀ (ZMUM), same data, together with holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="32" type="name">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
<pageBreakToken pageId="31" pageNumber="32" start="start">Name</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">To emphasize this species being not quite typical to readily fit into any of the former species groups.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="32" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
Superficially, this new species strongly resembles 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Aphelidesmidae" genus="Orthomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthomorpha communis" order="Polydesmida" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="communis">Orthomorpha communis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., especially as regards the color pattern, the degree of development of some paraterga, and size. Yet the two species differ markedly in the development in 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Aphelidesmidae" genus="Orthomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthomorpha atypica" order="Polydesmida" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atypica">Orthomorpha atypica</taxonomicName>
sp. n. of distinct sternal cones between ♂ coxae 4, coupled with a peculiar denticle placed on top of the outer lobule of the solenophore, not between the two terminal lobules characteristic of other species (see also Key below).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Length 32-39.5 (♂) or 34.5-44 mm (♀), width of midbody pro- and metazona 3.0-3.6 and 5.0-5.6 mm (♂), 3.6-4.0 and 5.5-6.4 mm (♀), respectively.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">
<pageBreakToken pageId="32" pageNumber="33" start="start">Coloration</pageBreakToken>
of live animals (Fig. 28A) blackish-brown with contrasting creamy light orange paraterga and epiproct, posterior halves of metaterga light yellow-brown to light brown, antennae blackish, legs dark brown; coloration of alcohol material after preservation (Fig. 25B-J) uniformly dark brown with contrasting pallid paraterga, epiproct and tip of antennae, legs brown to light grey-brown, posterior halves of metaterga light brown to brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="33" lastPageNumber="34" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">
Clypeolabral region densely setose, vertex barely setose, epicranial suture distinct. Antennae moderately long (Fig. 28A), clavate (antennomere 6 broadest), extending behind body segment 3 dorsally (♂, ♀). Head in width &lt;collum &lt;segments 3-4 &lt;2 &lt;5-16 (♂, ♀); thereafter body gently, and gradually tapering. Collum with three transverse rows of setae: 4+4 anterior, 2+2 intermediate and 3+3 posterior; posterior quarter evidently rugulose, mid-dorsal part with a superficial and shortened axial line; paraterga slightly declined ventrally, discontinuing 
<normalizedToken originalValue="dorsum’s">dorsum's</normalizedToken>
convexity, subrectangular, nearly reaching caudal edge; caudal corner of paraterga very narrowly rounded 
<pageBreakToken pageId="33" pageNumber="34" start="start">(</pageBreakToken>
Fig. 28B). Tegument of metaterga shining, leathery, rugulose-tuberculate, especially well so on several anterior metaterga; prozona very finely shagreened, metazona below paraterga faintly rugulose, finely microgranulate only near coxae. Metaterga 2-5 with two rows of 2+2 anterior and 3(4)+3(4) setiferous cones, usually slightly smaller cones in anterior (pre-sulcus) row and more evident ones laterally in posterior row (Fig. 28B &amp; C); thereafter same pattern, but traceable only as insertion points, tuberculation gradually growing obliterate to become nearly wanting on a few caudalmost metaterga. Metatergum 19 with 3+3 anterior and 4+4 posterior setae, the latter also borne on minute knobs or oblong wrinkles. Tergal setae very short, simple, about 1/5 metatergal length. Axial line barely traceable only on metaterga, slightly better visible in anterior halves than in posterior ones, always incomplete and sometimes missing. Paraterga very strongly developed (Fig. 28B-H), especially well so in ♂, all lying below dorsum (at about 1/3 body height), mostly subhorizontal (sometimes slightly upturned only on segments 2 and 3 in ♂ or only on segment 2 in ♀), in lateral view modestly enlarged on pore-bearing segments, thinner on poreless ones; shoulders always present, rather regularly rounded and narrowly bordered, fused to callus; caudal corner of all paraterga pointed, beak-like, extending increasingly beyond rear tergal margin, slightly curved mesad on segments 18 and 19 (Fig. 28F). Calluses delimited by a sulcus both dorsally and, albeit considerably more poorly so, ventrally, segment 2 with three very faint incisions at lateral edge, two similarly faint incisions on following poreless segments, one much stronger incision in front of pore sinuosity on pore-bearing segments. Posterior edge of paraterga evidently concave, especially strongly so on segments 16-19. Ozopores evident, lateral, lying in an ovoid groove at about 1/4 in front of caudal corner. Transverse sulcus evident (Fig. 28B-F &amp; H), thin, deep and only slightly incomplete on metaterga 2-4, complete, at most very faintly beaded at bottom, reaching bases of paraterga on metaterga 5-18, barely visible, highly superficial and again incomplete on metatergum 19 in ♂; somewhat less strongly developed in ♀. Stricture between pro- and metazona narrow and rather shallow, evidently beaded at bottom down to base of paraterga. Pleurosternal carinae complete high crests with a sharp caudal tooth on segments 2-4(5), thereafter increasingly well divided into a front bulge and a caudal tooth, both increasingly strongly reduced in size, bulge until segment 14, tooth until segment 17 (♂), or carinae considerably lower, their caudal tooth strongly rounded and only barely traceable until segment 17 (♀). Epiproct (Fig. 28F-H) conical, flattened dorsoventrally, very faintly narrowed caudad, with two evident apical papillae directed caudally, subtruncate at tip; pre-apical papillae very small, lying close to tip. Hypoproct (Fig. 28G) semi-circular, caudal margin rounded, setiferous knobs at caudal edge medium-sized and well-separated.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
Sterna sparsely setose, without modifications; cross-impressions shallow, especially so due to a superficial axial impression; a large, setose, transverse lobe bearing a paramedian pair of large, basally contiguous cones between ♂ coxae 4 (Fig. 28I &amp; J). A paramedian pair of small, but evident tubercles in front of gonopod aperture. Legs moderately long and slender, slightly incrassate in ♂, midbody ones ca 1.2-1.3 (♂) or 
<pageBreakToken pageId="34" pageNumber="35" start="start">0.8</pageBreakToken>
-1.0 times (♀) as long as body height, prefemora without modifications, ♂ tarsal brushes present only on legs 1-5(6).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Gonopods (Figs 29, 30) simple. Coxa long and slender, with several strong setae distodorsally. Prefemur densely setose, less than half the length of femorite + 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“postfemoral”">&quot;postfemoral&quot;</normalizedToken>
part. Femorite slender, slightly curved and nearly not enlarged distad, with a 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“postfemoral”">&quot;postfemoral&quot;</normalizedToken>
part demarcated by an oblique lateral sulcus. Solenophore with a bidentate tip, both prongs being subequal, but terminal lobule with an unusual minute denticle near base; solenomere long and flagelliform.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Figure 28. 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Aphelidesmidae" genus="Orthomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthomorpha atypica" order="Polydesmida" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atypica">Orthomorpha atypica</taxonomicName>
sp. n., ♂ holotype. A habitus, live coloration B, C anterior part of body, dorsal and lateral views, respectively D, E segments 10 and 11, dorsal and lateral views, respectively F, G, H posterior part of body, dorsal, ventral and lateral views, respectively I, J sternal cones between coxae 4, subcaudal and sublateral views, respectively.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Figure 29. 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Aphelidesmidae" genus="Orthomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthomorpha atypica" order="Polydesmida" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atypica">Orthomorpha atypica</taxonomicName>
sp. n., ♂ holotype. A, B right gonopod, mesal and lateral views, respectively C-F distal part of right gonopod, mesal, lateral, suboral and subcaudal views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.2 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Figure 30. 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Aphelidesmidae" genus="Orthomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Orthomorpha atypica" order="Polydesmida" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atypica">Orthomorpha atypica</taxonomicName>
sp. n., ♂ holotype. A, B right gonopod, lateral and mesal views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.2 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>