<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.646.11132" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d3eb24b1-218f-49cc-9a4b-b2ced66806ac" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127863705" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-646-139" ID-ZBK="8A14AA95714C46748B62C6734F5ED3A2" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:329C796C-EC46-4A85-A9EB-3FD21298A4BC" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-646-139" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 646" ModsDocTitle="Discovery of a new species of hermit crab of the genus Pylopaguropsis Alcock, 1905 from the Caribbean: “den commensal” or “cleaner”? (Crustacea, Anomura, Paguridae)" checkinTime="1484862043335" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lemaitre, Rafael" docDate="2017" docId="D5B6B5C2E12CEEBC26A922B9DA406976" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 646: 139-158" docOrigin="ZooKeys 646" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.646.11132" docTitle="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae Lemaitre, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="329C796C-EC46-4A85-A9EB-3FD21298A4BC" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="149" masterDocId="DE10002EFF91FFA2FFFAFFB3FFCC7D32" masterDocTitle="Discovery of a new species of hermit crab of the genus Pylopaguropsis Alcock, 1905 from the Caribbean: &quot; den commensal &quot; or &quot; cleaner &quot;? (Crustacea, Anomura, Paguridae)" masterLastPageNumber="158" masterPageNumber="139" pageId="2" pageNumber="141" updateTime="1643567328393" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Discovery of a new species of hermit crab of the genus Pylopaguropsis Alcock, 1905 from the Caribbean: &quot; den commensal &quot; or &quot; cleaner &quot;? (Crustacea, Anomura, Paguridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lemaitre, Rafael</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>646</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>139</mods:start>
<mods:end>158</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.646.11132</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.646.11132</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-646-139</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">8A14AA95714C46748B62C6734F5ED3A2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8A14AA95714C46748B62C6734F5ED3A2</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127863705" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:329C796C-EC46-4A85-A9EB-3FD21298A4BC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D5B6B5C2E12CEEBC26A922B9DA406976" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="149" pageId="2" pageNumber="141">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="141" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/329C796C-EC46-4A85-A9EB-3FD21298A4BC" authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="141" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="141">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, Table 1, Suppl. materials 1, 2, 3 (color photographs, video)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="141" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">
Holotype: male 2.4 mm, &quot;Something Special&quot;, central W coast of Bonaire, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="12.162777">12°09'46.0&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-68.28572">68°17'08.6&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 11.6 m, 17 December 2015, sand/rubble under coral ledge, night dive, coll. E Muller (USNM 1291987).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">Paratypes (all same locality, habitat, and collector, as holotype): 1 male 1.8 mm (USNM 1291989), 1 male 2.2 mm (USNM 1291988), 13.7 m; 1 male 0.9 mm, 1 female 1.5 mm, 27 January 2016 (USNM 1292072); 1 ovigerous female 1.9 mm, 28 January 2016 (USNM 1292073).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="141" type="non-type specimens (not collected) photographed in situ">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">Non-type specimens (not collected) photographed in situ.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">
5 sex undertermined (Fig. 6C, E, and Suppl. material 3), &quot;Something Special&quot;, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="12.162777">12°09'46.0&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-68.28572">68°17'08.6&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, ~10 m, night dive; 1 ovigerous female, 1 sex undetermined (color photos in Suppl. materials 1-2), &quot;Front Porch&quot;, E Muller night dives 4125 095a and 4125 156z2, central W coast of Bonaire, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="12.165333">12°09'55.2&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-68.28667">68°17'12.0&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, night dive, 12.2 m, 17 September 2016.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="146" pageId="2" pageNumber="141" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">Shield (Fig. 1A) about as long as broad, weakly convex, well calcified, smooth except for weak depression behind each lateral projection; naked except for few short rows or tufts of fine setae. Rostrum acutely triangular, ending in small, sharp spine, and extending well beyond distal level of lateral projections. Anterior margins between rostrum and lateral projections concave. Lateral projections broadly triangular, ending in small, sharp spine. Anterolateral margins sloping. Accessory portions narrow, well calcified, fused to shield. Branchiostegite membranous; anterior margin rounded, setose.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="141">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="141" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male 2.4 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291987). A shield, cephalic appendages, dorsal B left antennal flagellum, dorsal C propodus and dactyl of righ pereopod 4, lateral D sternum and coxae of chelipeds and pereopods 2-5, ventral E telson, dorsal. Scale bars 1 mm for A, B, D; 0.5 mm for C, E.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="141">Ocular peduncles moderately long, about 0.8 as long as shield, slightly inflated basally and tapering to base of corneas, with dorsodistal row of long setae; corneas weakly dilated. Ocular acicles subtriangular, with strong terminal spine; separated basally by less than basal width of one acicle.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="142">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="142" start="start">Antennules</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 1A) exceeding distal margins of corneas by 0.5-0.6 length of ultimate segment. Ultimate segment with few long dorsodistal setae. Penultimate and basal segments naked or with scattered short setae. Basal segment with laterodistal spine. Ventral flagellum with five or six articles.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="143" pageId="3" pageNumber="142">
Antennal peduncles (Fig. 1A) exceeding distal margins of corneas by 0.2 length of fifth segment. Fifth and fourth segments unarmed except for sparse setae. Third seg 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="143" start="start">ment</pageBreakToken>
with strong ventromesial spine. Second segment naked or with scattered short setae; dorsolateral distal angle strongly produced, ending in small spine at tip; dorsomesial distal angle with small spine. First segment with small spine on lateral face distally. Acicle broadly curved outward, slightly exceeding distal margin of cornea, terminating in strong spine; with dorsomesial row of long setae. Flagellum (Fig. 1B) slightly exceeding extended right cheliped, densely setose, with setae&gt;1 - 8 flagellar articles in length.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="145" pageId="4" pageNumber="143">
Mandible (Fig. 2A) with edge of incisor process armed with three blunt calcareous teeth. Maxillule (Fig. 2B) with endopod slender, internal lobe with one long bristle. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="144" start="start">Maxilla</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 2C) with endopodite slightly exceeding distal end of scaphognathite. First maxilliped (Fig. 2D) with endopodite not exceeding distal endite. Second maxilliped (Fig. 2E) without distinguishing characters. Third maxilliped (Fig. 2F) with merus armed with small blunt, dorsodistal spine; ischium with crista dentata consisting of about 13 small, subequal corneous teeth, two larger basal teeth, and one accessory 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="145" start="start">tooth</pageBreakToken>
; basis with two sharp teeth on mesial margin; coxa with small distomesial spine. Sternite IX (of third maxillipeds) with small, sharp spine on each side of midline.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype male 1.8 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291989). Left mouthparts, internal: A mandible B maxillule C maxilla D first maxilliped E second maxilliped F third maxilliped. Scale bar 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
Chelipeds markedly asymmetrical. Right cheliped (Fig. 3A, B, 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–E">A-E</normalizedToken>
) massive, nearly naked, with chela operculate, ovate; fingers curving ventrally, broad basally and terminating in small, inwardly curved, corneous claw; cutting edges (Fig. Fig. 3B) uneven, minutely and sharply denticulate, fixed finger with large subtriangular tooth medially. Dactyl 0.8 times as long as palm, set very obliquely relative to longitudinal axis of chela; dorsoventrally flattened; dorsal surface weakly convex, unarmed except for scattered short setae; dorsomesial margin sharp, plate-like; ventral surface moderately concave, with longitudinal ridge parallel to mesial margin. Palm and fixed finger weakly convex, nearly naked or with scattered short setae; dorsal surfaces with scattered small, low tubercles on lateral half, smooth except for shallow longitudinal groove on mesial half; lateral margin sharply defined by minute denticles; mesial face strongly produced ventrally, ventromesial margin rounded; ventral surface smooth, deeply excavated, mesial face and lateral margin forming distinct, semi-cylindrical scoop-like surface. Carpus subtrapezoidal, naked; dorsal surface with dorsolateral and dorsomesial ridges marked by minute, sharp spines; lateral face sloping; ventrolateral margin unarmed; mesial face strongly sloping, distomesial margin with row of minute spines; ventral surface convex, smooth. Merus subtriangular, smooth; ventromesial margin minutely spinulose proximally except for row of moderately strong spines distally; ventrolateral margin unarmed. Ischium unarmed except for ventromesial row of setae.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male 2.4 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291987). A right cheliped, dorsal B dactyl and fixed finger of same, ventral C left cheliped, dorsal D same, lateral E same mesial. Scale bar 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., right cheliped. A ventral, holotype male 2.4 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291987) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–E">B-E</normalizedToken>
dorsal (B), dorsomesial (C), ventral (D), ventromesial (E), paratype male 1.8 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291989). Scale bars 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
Left cheliped (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–E">C-E</normalizedToken>
) slender, reaching nearly to base of dactyl of right cheliped. Fingers each terminating in short, inwardly curved corneous claw; dactyl shorter than palm, cutting edge with row of closely set, minute corneous spinules, mesial face with few tufts of long setae; fixed finger with tufts of setae on lateral face, cutting edge with row of small, well-spaced calcareous teeth interspersed with fused corneous spinules. Palm smooth, naked except for tufts of long setae mostly on dorsomesial face. Carpus subtriangular; dorsal margin with row of tufts of setae, lacking spines. Merus nearly naked except for scattered tufts of setae; ventrolateral margin with row of few well-spaced spines usually on distal half; ventromesial margin unarmed. Ischium unarmed except for ventromesial row of setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
Ambulatory legs or pereopods 2 and 3 (Fig. 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
) not significantly different left from right; meri to dactyls with lateral faces evenly convex, with long setae or tufts of setae on dorsal margins. Dactyl nearly straight, about 1.8 times as long as propodi, terminating in sharp corneous claw; dorsomesial margin with row of minute corneous spinules on distal half; ventromesial margin with row of 6-8 corneous spinules. Propodus slightly arched. Carpi each with small dorsodistal spine. Merus unarmed. Ischium with row of setae on ventral margins.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male 2.4 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291987). A left pereopod 2, lateral B left pereopod 3 (dactyl tip missing), lateral C right pereopod 2, lateral D dactyl of same, mesial E right pereopod 3, lateral F dactyl of same, mesial. Scale bar 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">Sternite XII (of pereopod 3; Fig. 1D) with anterior lobe weakly rounded, setose.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 1C) semichelate. Dactyl subtriangular, terminating in sharp, corneous claw, lacking preungual process; with ventrolateral row of minute, fused corneous teeth. Propodal rasp consisting of one distal row of lanceolate scales.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="145">Pereopod 5 chelate. Propodal rasp occupying nearly half of lateral face of propodus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="146" start="start">Sternite</pageBreakToken>
XIV (pereopod 5) subdivided anteriorly into two subrectangular, setose lobes (Fig. 1D).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">Uropods strongly asymmetrical. Telson (Fig. 1E) with distinct lateral indentations separating anterior and posterior lobes; posterior lobes subtriangular, nearly symmetrical, separated by deep, narrow median cleft, distal margins armed with row of small, sharp spines and blunt laterodistal angle.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">Male with paired gonopores (Fig. 1D), and unpaired left pleopods 2-5. Female with paired pleopods 1 modified as gonopods, and unpaired left pleopods 2-5 (pleopod 5 not ovigerous).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="146" type="coloration">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">Coloration</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">(Fig. 6A, B, Suppl. materials 1-3). General background color white with bright red stripes. Shield white with two pairs of oblique red stripes on each side of anterior half. Ocular peduncles white with two red stripes uniting across corneas. Corneas transparent, with black colored core. Antennular peduncle white with red dorsal stripe. Antennal peduncles white with red dorsal and ventral red stripe; antennal acicle white with red dorsal stripe; flagellum light red. Right cheliped with dorsal surfaces of chela, carpus and merus light red, and mesial faces with continuous red stripe; lateral faces of carpus and merus white with continuous red stripe. Left cheliped white with dorsal, lateral, and mesial red stripes. Ambulatory legs or pereopods 2 and 3, with dactyl white with red lateral and mesial stripes; merus to propodus with dorsal, lateral and mesial red stripes; ischium white with red dorsal stripe.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="146">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">
Figure 6. In situ photographs of 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. and its habitat at Bonaire diving site &quot;Something Special&quot;. A holotype male 2.4 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291987) B paratype male 1.8 mm, Bonaire (USNM 1291989) C three individuals of 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (foreground, not collected) in den with &quot;broad banded moray&quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Muraenidae" genus="Channomuraena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Channomuraena vittata" order="Anguilliformes" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="vittata">Channomuraena vittata</taxonomicName>
D coral ledge habitat, with arrow indicating entrance to crevice where five specimens of 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. were collected E individual of 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (expanded and enhanced in oval inset, not collected) on body surface of &quot;broad banded moray&quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Muraenidae" genus="Channomuraena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Channomuraena vittata" order="Anguilliformes" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="vittata">Channomuraena vittata</taxonomicName>
, with frontal portion of brachyuran 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Portunidae" genus="Achelous" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Achelous sebae" order="Decapoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sebae">Achelous sebae</taxonomicName>
visible on lower right.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="146" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">So far known only from the island of Bonaire, Lesser Antilles, southern Caribbean Sea; depth: 11.6-13.7 m.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="147" pageId="7" pageNumber="146" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="146">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="147" pageId="7" pageNumber="146">
The name of this new species is given to acknowledge the efforts of the collector, photographer and environmentalist, Ms Ellen Muller, who when informed of the intended honor, preferred that the name of her granddaughter, Ms Molly Muller, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="147" start="start">be</pageBreakToken>
used, in hopes to inspire her to continue the tradition of protecting the amazing and fragile diversity of marine life in Bonaire.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="147" type="common name">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="147">Common name.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="147">&quot;Candy striped hermit crab&quot;, in reference to the bright white and red striped color pattern that is similar to that of traditional candy cane.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="149" pageId="8" pageNumber="147" type="affinities">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="147">Affinities.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="149" pageId="8" pageNumber="147">
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="147" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is remarkably similar in morphology to 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis teevana" order="Decapoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="147" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevana">Pylopaguropsis teevana</taxonomicName>
, a species distributed in the tropical eastern Pacific from Colombia 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="148" start="start">to</pageBreakToken>
Ecuador, including the Galapagos Islands. There is such minimal differentiation between the two species that they can be considered geminate. They are unique among congeners and even among other 
<taxonomicName family="Paguridae" lsidName="" pageId="9" pageNumber="148" rank="family">Paguridae</taxonomicName>
, in the unusual structure of the right chela, with a ventral surface deeply excavated, forming a semi-cylindrical scoop-like surface (Fig. 4A, D, E). Both species also have antennal flagella with long, dense setae. The condition of the antennal flagella was not mentioned by 
<bibRefCitation author="McLaughlin, PA" journalOrPublisher="Micronesica" pageId="14" pageNumber="153" pagination="123 - 171" title="On the status of Pylopaguropsiszebra Henderson, P. magnimanus (Henderson), and Galapagurusteevanus Boone, with descriptions of seven new species of Pylopaguropsis (Crustacea: Anomura: Paguridae)." volume="22" year="1989">McLaughlin and Haig (1989)</bibRefCitation>
in their redescription of 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis teevana" order="Decapoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="148" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevana">Pylopaguropsis teevana</taxonomicName>
, although in her description 
<bibRefCitation author="Boone, L" journalOrPublisher="New York" pageId="13" pageNumber="152" pagination="1 - 62" title="The littoral crustacean fauna of the Galapagos Islands. Part 2. Anomura." volumeTitle="Zoologica" year="1932">Boone (1932</bibRefCitation>
: fig. 4, as 
<taxonomicName authority="Boone, 1932" authorityName="Boone" authorityYear="1932" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Galapagurus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Galapagurus teevanus" order="Decapoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="148" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevanus">Galapagurus teevanus</taxonomicName>
) did illustrate this setal condition, noting that the flagella have &quot;long radiating setae&quot;. The only differences detected between these two species are minor, as follows: the antennal acicles slightly exceed the corneas, whereas the acicles do not reach the distal margin of the cornea in 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis teevana" order="Decapoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="148" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevana">Pylopaguropsis teevana</taxonomicName>
; the dorsal surfaces of the right chela is smooth (dactyl) or with only scattered minute tubercles on the lateral half (palm), whereas the same surfaces have numerous albeit well-spaced small tubercles in 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis teevana" order="Decapoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="148" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevana">Pylopaguropsis teevana</taxonomicName>
; and the lateral face of the dactyl of right pereopod 3 is evenly convex, whereas the lateral surface is slightly flattened in 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis teevana" order="Decapoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="148" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevana">Pylopaguropsis teevana</taxonomicName>
. Although coloration was 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="149" start="start">only</pageBreakToken>
briefly described by 
<bibRefCitation author="McLaughlin, PA" journalOrPublisher="Micronesica" pageId="14" pageNumber="153" pagination="123 - 171" title="On the status of Pylopaguropsiszebra Henderson, P. magnimanus (Henderson), and Galapagurusteevanus Boone, with descriptions of seven new species of Pylopaguropsis (Crustacea: Anomura: Paguridae)." volume="22" year="1989">McLaughlin and Haig (1989</bibRefCitation>
: 159, based on AJ Provenzano, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Jr’s">Jr's</normalizedToken>
color notes) for 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis teevana" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevana">Pylopaguropsis teevana</taxonomicName>
, it appears that at least the striped pattern of that eastern Pacific species is similar to that of the Caribbean 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. In this new species, however, the stripes are bright red over white, whereas in 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis teevana" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="teevana">Pylopaguropsis teevana</taxonomicName>
the stripes are brown over light cream.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="149">
Given that the dactyls of the left and right pereopods 3 in 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. are similar, this new species belongs in the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="teevana" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" rank="species" species="teevana">teevana</taxonomicName>
group of species of this genus as defined by 
<bibRefCitation author="McLaughlin, PA" journalOrPublisher="Micronesica" pageId="14" pageNumber="153" pagination="123 - 171" title="On the status of Pylopaguropsiszebra Henderson, P. magnimanus (Henderson), and Galapagurusteevanus Boone, with descriptions of seven new species of Pylopaguropsis (Crustacea: Anomura: Paguridae)." volume="22" year="1989">McLaughlin and Haig (1989)</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="149" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="149">Habitat and behavior.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="149">
As previously mentioned, 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. was first photographed fortuitously, but not collected, while observing the &quot;flaming reef lobster&quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Enoplometopidae" genus="Enoplometopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Enoplometopus antillensis" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antillensis">Enoplometopus antillensis</taxonomicName>
. Five of the six specimens collected of 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. were found living in gastropod shells, and obtained during dives in late afternoon or at night inside a crevice under a large coral ledge about 3.6 m wide by 1.5 m high at the site &quot;Something Special&quot; (Fig. 6D). The sixth specimen was collected a short distance north of that ledge, at a slightly shallower depth. Specimens were photographed, but not collected, in a crevice where a large &quot;broad banded moray&quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Muraenidae" genus="Channomuraena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Channomuraena vittata" order="Anguilliformes" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="vittata">Channomuraena vittata</taxonomicName>
, has been known to divers to live for many years (Fig. 6C, E). An &quot;ocellate swimming crab&quot;, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Portunidae" genus="Achelous" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Achelous sebae" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sebae">Achelous sebae</taxonomicName>
(H. Milne Edwards, 1834), was also observed at this crevice (Fig. 6E). It appears that this new species is reclusive, and prefers to hide in the deep, dark recesses of crevices under coral ledges where divers (E Muller, pers. comm.) occasionally have also observed two other species of moray eels, the &quot;spotted moray&quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Muraenidae" genus="Gymnothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gymnothorax moringa" order="Anguilliformes" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="moringa">Gymnothorax moringa</taxonomicName>
(Cuvier, 1829), and the &quot;green moray&quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Muraenidae" genus="Gymnothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gymnothorax funebris" order="Anguilliformes" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="funebris">Gymnothorax funebris</taxonomicName>
Ranzani, 1839. After the discovery of specimens of 
<taxonomicName authority="Alcock, 1905" authorityName="Alcock" authorityYear="1905" class="Malacostraca" family="Paguridae" genus="Pylopaguropsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae" order="Decapoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="149" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mollymullerae">Pylopaguropsis mollymullerae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., additional photographs were taken at the site &quot;Front Porch&quot;, and a video at the site &quot;Something Special&quot;, in order to document any particular behavior (see Suppl. materials 1-3). Frequently, one or more individuals of this this new hermit crab species were seen in close proximity of a moray eel, and in one instance clearly on its body (Fig. 6E).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>