<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.181.3043" ID-GBIF-Dataset="74f33415-0c20-4f30-a34d-3b0957324459" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152034500" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-181-53" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F79F7494-083C-4E1E-96C7-324B1F712E43" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-181-53" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 181" ModsDocTitle="Sinocorophium hangangense sp. n. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Corophiidae), a new species from Korea, with a key to the genus Sinocorophium" checkinTime="1451249161151" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Kim, Young-Hyo" docDate="2012" docId="F4E7E7542C5B4F0D1E05B1CAAF005712" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 181: 53-65" docOrigin="ZooKeys 181" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.181.3043" docTitle="Sinocorophium hangangense Kim, 2012, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="61" masterDocId="1943FF88FFFFEF07FFACDB14147CA621" masterDocTitle="Sinocorophium hangangense sp. n. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Corophiidae), a new species from Korea, with a key to the genus Sinocorophium" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="53" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" updateTime="1643709756795" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Sinocorophium hangangense sp. n. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Corophiidae), a new species from Korea, with a key to the genus Sinocorophium</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kim, Young-Hyo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>181</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>53</mods:start>
<mods:end>65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.181.3043</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.181.3043</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-181-53</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152034500" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F79F7494-083C-4E1E-96C7-324B1F712E43" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F4E7E7542C5B4F0D1E05B1CAAF005712" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F79F7494-083C-4E1E-96C7-324B1F712E43" class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="55">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 25
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="korean name">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Korean name:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Han-gang-baem-yeop-sae-u, new</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Holotype, adult male, 12.2 mm, NIBRIV0000245089, Gongreung stream, Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Gyeonggi-do, Korea, 37°45'10'N, 126°42'20'E, C.M. Lee and Y.H. Kim, 2 November 2002. Paratype, adult female, 11.0 mm, NIBRIV0000245090, same station data; one male, 11.5 mm and one female, 10.5 mm, CMNC 2012-0002, same station data; three females, 8.7-10.2 mm, DKU 201203, same station data.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="additional material examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">2 males, same locality as holotype, C.M. Lee, 30 September 2006; 2 males, 3 females, same locality as holotype, C.M. Lee, 4 November 2006; 5 males, 4 females, same locality as holotype, C.M. Lee, 3 May 2008.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="coloration in alcohol">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Coloration in alcohol.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Body yellowish grey; antennae to urosomites with light brownish reticulate pattern dorsally, especially pereonites with 2 longitudinal rows of light brown lines dorsally (Fig. 2).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male, 11.5 mm, Gongreung stream, Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Korea. A lateral view B dorsal view; female, 8.5 mm, Gongreung stream, Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Korea. C lateral view D dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Holotype, adult male, NIBRIV0000245089.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Body (Fig. 3A) 12.2 mm long, head longer than pereonite 1, rostrum (Fig. 3B) pointed distally, triangular in dorsal view. Eye invisible in alcohol. Cephalic lobe sharply produced. Pereonites 1-2 subequal in length, shorter than pereonite 3. Coxae flat dorsoventrally, except coxa 1, much shallower than pereonites. Urosomites 1-3 separate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Antenna 1 (Figs. 3B, 3C) weakly setose, subequal in length to head and pereonites 1-4 combined; peduncular article 1 rectangular, distinctly narrowed distally, medial margin irregularly serrated when viewed dorsally, ventrodistal corner with 1 small robust seta and 1 penicillate seta, distal half of ventral margin with 8 setae; length ratio of peduncular articles 1-3 = 1.00: 0.41: 0.31; flagellum 13-articulate, shorter than peduncle, several articles bearing club-shaped, small aesthetascs ventrodistally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
Antenna 2 (Figs. 3A, 3D) massive, nearly twice as long as antenna 1; peduncular article 2 with large curved and sharply pointed gland cone; peduncular article 3 longer than wide; peduncular article 4 1.23 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 5, with a row of tubercles ventromedially and a ventrodistal large tooth; peduncular article 5 rectangular, with a row of tubercles ventromedially; flagellum biarticulate, proximal one with a row of tubercles, 0.56 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
peduncular article 5, distal one short, about 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
proximal one, with 2 unequal setae apically.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="56" start="start">Lower</pageBreakToken>
lip (Fig. 3E) inner lobe subovate, coalescent proximally, rounded apically; mandibular process small and blunt; both lobes covered with patch of pubescence medially.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="57" start="start">Left</pageBreakToken>
mandible (Fig. 3F) well developed, incisor and lacinia mobilis produced inward, bluntly tridentate; accessory setal row with 2 curved, finely pectinate blades; molar well developed, massive, truncate; palp biarticulate, proximal segment shorter than distal, with 1 simple seta apically and 1 sparse plumose seta subapically, distal segment slender, with pubescence medially and long plumose seta apically.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">Maxilla 1 (Fig. 3G) inner plate unknown; outer plate armed with 7 setal-teeth (simple or serrulate) apically; palp biarticulate, proximal segment short, wider than long, distal one extending beyond end of outer lobe, with row of 7 simple setae and 2 unequal robust setae apically, with row of 7 setae subapically.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">Maxilla 2 (Fig. 3H) inner plate with longitudinal row of pinnate setae on inner margin, apical margin with 2 rows of simple or pectinate setae; outer plate extending beyond end of inner one, inner distal and apical margins with simple or plumose setae.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="57">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 12.2 mm, Gongreung stream, Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Korea. A habitus, lateral B head, dorsal C antenna 1 D antenna 2 E lower lip F mandible G maxilla 1 H maxilla 2 I maxilliped. Scale bars: 1.0 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
), 0.2 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–I">E-I</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">
Maxilliped (Fig. 3I) inner plate slender and elongate, inner surface covered by pubescence, basal portion with transverse row of about 22 plumose setae, apical margin with 3 unequal robust setae, 1 pinnate and 2 simple setae, respectively; outer plate not reaching distal end of article 2 of palp, inner margin straight, densely setose, with 1 long pinnate seta distally, outer margin pubescent, curved convexly; palp 4-articulate, proximal article with 2 long plumose setae on outer margin, article 2 elongate, more than twice length of proximal one, inner margin densely setose, outer margin with 4 simple setae distally, article 3 subrectangular, with rounded distal corner, surrounded by setae distally, 0.34 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 2, distal article short, 0.33 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 3, with apical setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">
Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 4A) subchelate; coxa elongate-ovate, much longer than wide, ventral margin rounded with 3 long plumose setae, anterior margin with 6 setules; basis as long as carpus, anterior margin straight, unarmed, posterodistal corner with unequal setae; ischium quadrate, with long pinnate setae ventrodistally; merus short, subtriangular, with long pinnate setae ventrodistally; carpus slightly narrowing distally, anterior margin with 5 simple setae, distomedial corner with transverse row of 6 simple setae, posterior margin with 2 rows of pinnate setae; propodus subrectangular, posterior margin concave, 0.74 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
carpus, anterior and medial portions with pectinate setae, posterior margin with pinnate and simple setae, palm transverse, slightly convex, lined with row of bifid spinules; dactylus falcate, almost fitting palm.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 4B) simple; coxa small, wider than long; basis subrectangular, posterodistal margin with cluster of simple setae; ischium flat, depressed; merus convexly curved posteriorly, with 2 rows of long pinnate setae along posterior margin and medial portion; carpus isosceles triangle in shape, strongly widening distally, with several pinnate setae posterodistally; propodus weakly narrowing distally, 1.57 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
carpus, both margins with unequal simple setae, proximal half of medial portion with oblique row of pinnate setae; dactylus long and falcate, curved concavely, inner margin with row of setules.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="57">
Pereopod 3 (Fig. 4C) coxa small, wider than long; basis weakly expanded medially, anterior margin with 5 setules, distal half of posterior margin with simple setae; merus slightly widening distally, 1.24 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
propodus; carpus rather elongated, 0.69 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
merus; dactylus simple, 0.52 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
propodus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="58">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="58" start="start">Pereopod</pageBreakToken>
4 (Fig. 4D) similar to pereopod 3.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="5" pageNumber="58">
Pereopod 5 (Fig. 4E) coxa depressed, much wider than long, slightly concave midventrally, narrowing distally; basis slightly widened medially, anteromarginally with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="59" start="start">row</pageBreakToken>
of setules, posteromarginally with sparse setae; merus widening distally, both margins with unequal simple setae; carpus with 2 oblique rows of 5 proximal and 8 distal robust setae respectively, subequal in length to propodus; dactylus short.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
Pereopod 6 (Fig. 4F) similar to pereopod 5, but about 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer; basis more greatly expanded posteriorly, with a row of setules and plumose setae; merus slightly widening distally, both margins with simple setae, posterodistally with 1 plumose seta; propodus slender, rectangular, 1.13 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
carpus; dactylus about 0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
propodus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">Pereopod 7 (Fig. 4G) elongate, much longer than either pereopod 5 or 6; coxa small, ventral margin convexly rounded, with 4 setules; basis elongate-ovate, moderately expanded anteroposteriorly, densely setose along both margins with long plumose setae; ischium to propodus linear and rectangular; length ratio of articles 2-7 = 1.00: 0.31: 0.67: 0.48: 0.75: 0.36.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">Urosomites 1-3 (Fig. 5A) separate; urosomite 1 longest, widest in middle when viewed dorsally, urosomite 2 longer than 3, nearly rectangular, posterodistal margins rounded in dorsal view; uropods 1-3 arising laterally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
Uropod 1 (Fig. 5A) slightly extending beyond end of uropod 2; peduncle rectangular, 1.84 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus, ventrodistal process present, triangular, blunt, lateral margin with row of simple setae, medial one with 3 robust setae; outer ramus slightly longer than inner, lateral margin with 6 robust setae, medial one with 5 robust setae, including 2 subdistal robust setae; inner ramus slightly curved medially.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">Uropod 2 (Fig. 5A) peduncle slightly longer than rami, with triangular ventrodistal process, apicodistal robust setae and cluster of setae; rami subequal in length, with robust setae marginally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
Uropod 3 (Fig. 5A) uniramous, peduncle short, broader than long, 0.78 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
ramus; ramus subelliptical, narrowing distally, margins with unequal simple setae, with apical setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">Telson (Fig. 5A) fleshy, thickened, grooved centrally, subtriangular, with truncate corners, broadest in middle, dorsolaterally with 2 penicillate setae and 1 setule.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">Paratype, female (sexually dimorphic characters), 11.0 mm, NIBRIV0000245090.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">Body (Fig. 5B) similar to male including antenna 2, but rostrum (Fig. 5C) weaker; antenna 1 (Fig. 5D) peduncular article 1 without medial serrations, article 3 rather short; antenna 2 (Fig. 5E) subsimilar to that of male, but less robust and shorter, peduncular article 4 with 1 ventromedial robust seta.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 12.2 mm, Gongreung stream, Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Korea. A gnathopod 1 B gnathopod 2 C pereopod 3 D pereopod 4 E pereopod 5 F pereopod 6 G pereopod 7. Scale bars: 0.4 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–G">A-G</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 12.2 mm, Gongreung stream, Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Korea. A urosomites, uropods and telson, dorsal; paratype, female, 11.0 mm, Gongreung stream, Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Korea. B habitus, lateral C head, dorsal D antenna 1 E antenna 2. Scale bars: 1.0 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–E">B-E</normalizedToken>
), 0.4 mm (A).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="6" pageNumber="59" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="59">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
<bibRefCitation author="Bousfield, EL" journalOrPublisher="Amphipacifica" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" pagination="67 - 139" title="The amphipod superfamily Corophioidea on the Pacific coast of North America. Part V. Family Corophiidae. Corophiinae, new subfamily. Systematics and distributional ecology." volume="2" year="1997">Bousfield and Hoover (1997)</bibRefCitation>
divided 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Sinocorophium</taxonomicName>
into two groups, a relatively ancestral and a more derived subgroup through a numerical taxonomic analysis. According to this classification, the new species belongs to the derived subgroup. Some characteristics which relate to this group include non sexual dimorphic antenna 2, convex palm of the gnathopod 1, short carpi of pereopods 3-4 and short ramus of the uropod 3 (Table 1). However, the new species shows more similarity with the ancestral subgroup in having an elongate-ovate ramus of uropod 3 which is longer than the peduncle. The new species is distinguished from its congeners by having a row of slender setae and not robust setae on the lateral margin of the peduncle of uropod 1. These are unique morphological systematic statuses among 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="60" start="start">the</pageBreakToken>
more derived subgroup which is sexually subsimilar in antenna 2. Ecologically the new species inhabits lower stream regions with lowered salinity, while related congeners except 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium intermedium" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="intermedium">Sinocorophium intermedium</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium minutum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minutum">Sinocorophium minutum</taxonomicName>
inNorth Vietnam are mainly abundant in shallow subtidal and intertidal mudflats. Among the derived subgroup species, the new species is more similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium alienense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alienense">Sinocorophium alienense</taxonomicName>
of the northeast Pacificthan to the geographically closer sinocorophiid amphipods in the Far East. These two species have several characteristics in common: 1) prominent ventromedial teeth row on peduncular articles 4-5 and first flagellum of male antenna 2; 2) inner ramus of uropod 1 curved medially and shorter than outer one; 3) antenna 2, posterodistal tooth of peduncular article 4 unidentate; 4) basis of pereopod 5 bearing posteromarginal setae. However, the new species is distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium alienense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alienense">Sinocorophium alienense</taxonomicName>
(different characters of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium alienense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alienense">Sinocorophium alienense</taxonomicName>
in brackets) by the combination of the following features: 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="61" start="start">1</pageBreakToken>
) peduncular article 1 of male antenna 1 with ventral simple setae (with pinnate setae); 2) peduncular article 1 of antenna 1 about 2.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 2 (peduncular article 1 subequal in length to article 2); 3) peduncular article 1 of antenna 1 with serrated medial margin (with smooth margin); 4) each lobe of telson with mid-lateral 1 simple and 2 penicillate setae, respectively (unornamented).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Table 1. Morphological characters of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
sp. n. and related species with sexually subsimilar antenna 2.&lt;br/&gt;
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<table pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="2">Character and distribution</th>
<th colspan="7" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">Species</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium alienense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alienense">Sinocorophium alienense</taxonomicName>
(♂)
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium homoceratum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="homoceratum">Sinocorophium homoceratum</taxonomicName>
(♂)
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium intermedium" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="intermedium">Sinocorophium intermedium</taxonomicName>
(♂)
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium japonicum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="japonicum">Sinocorophium japonicum</taxonomicName>
(♀)
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium monospinum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="monospinum">Sinocorophium monospinum</taxonomicName>
(♀)
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium triangulopedarum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="triangulopedarum">Sinocorophium triangulopedarum</taxonomicName>
(♂)
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (♂)
</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Chapman, JW" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Crustacean Biology" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" pagination="364 - 382" title="Invasions of the Northeast Pacific by Asian and Atlantic Gammaridean amphipod Crustaceans, including a new species of Corophium." url="10.2307/1548276" volume="8" year="1988">Chapman 1988</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Yu, SC" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of the Fan Memorial Institute of Biology, Zoological Series" pageId="10" pageNumber="63" pagination="83 - 103" title="Descriptions of two new amphipod Crustacea from Tangku." volume="8" year="1938">Yu 1938</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Dang, NT" journalOrPublisher="Tap San Sinh Vat-Dia Hoc" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" pagination="146 - 152" title="Mot so loai giap xac moi tim thay trong nuroc ngot va nuroc lo mien Bac Viet-nam." volume="4" year="1965">Dang 1965</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Hirayama 1984</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Shen, CJ" journalOrPublisher="Acta Zoologica Sinica" pageId="10" pageNumber="63" pagination="75 - 100" title="On some marine crustaceans from the coastal water of Fenghsien, Kiangsu Province." volume="7" year="1955">Shen 1955</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Hirayama 1990</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Named for the type locality, Gongreung stream, which is a small tributary on the lower reaches of the Han River in Gyeonggi-do, Korea. The Korean word 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Gang”">&quot;Gang&quot;</normalizedToken>
means river.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">The new species is found in brackish water regions, but it may inhabit intertidal regions, are downstream of the type locality.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Songchon-ri, Gyoha-eup, Paju-si, Gyeonggi-do, Korea.</paragraph>
<subSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="key to the species of sinocorophium">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Key to the species of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Sinocorophium</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<table lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium sinense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sinense">Sinocorophium sinense</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium heteroceratum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="heteroceratum">Sinocorophium heteroceratum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium lamellatum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lamellatum">Sinocorophium lamellatum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium minutum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minutum">Sinocorophium minutum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium japonicum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="japonicum">Sinocorophium japonicum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium homoceratum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="homoceratum">Sinocorophium homoceratum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium intermedium" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="intermedium">Sinocorophium intermedium</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium hangangense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hangangense">Sinocorophium hangangense</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
<td colspan="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium alienense" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alienense">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="62" start="start">Sinocorophium</pageBreakToken>
alienense
</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
<td colspan="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium triangulopedarum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="triangulopedarum">Sinocorophium triangulopedarum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
<td colspan="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Corophiidae" genus="Sinocorophium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinocorophium monospinum" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="monospinum">Sinocorophium monospinum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSection>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>