<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280192" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120176" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280192" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="44D7E636C55AF1647F726E6D8EDC6AE2" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys fronto Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="661" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="660" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280192" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120176" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280192" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:44D7E636C55AF1647F726E6D8EDC6AE2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/44D7E636C55AF1647F726E6D8EDC6AE2" lastPageNumber="661" pageNumber="660">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="660">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155840" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys fronto Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys fronto Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="660" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fronto">Strumigenys fronto Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Figs 397, 417)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="661" pageNumber="660">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 3.5, HL 0.85, HW 0.73, CI 86, ML 0.46, MI 54, SL 0.56, SI 76, PW 0.39, AL 0.84. Characters of carisa-complex. Each mandible with 1 preapical tooth which is situated in the apical third; preapical tooth on left mandible usually smaller than tooth on right. Upper scrobe margin bordered by a very narrow laminar rim throughout its length, eyes partially visible in full-face view. Eye small, convex, its maximum diameter slightly greater than maximum width of scape. Eye located slightly inwards from margin and apex formed by the junction of the posterior preocular notch and ventral scrobe margin. Scape more or less subcylindrical, basal portion slightly expanded and approximately straight; hairs on leading edge narrowly spatulate. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with curved narrowly spatulate ground-pilosity; upper scrobe margin fringed with hairs that are similar in size and shape to those on the dorsum. Cephalic dorsum with 7 pairs of long stout standing remiform hairs arranged as follows: transverse row of 3 pairs close to the occipital margin; dorsolateral margin posteriorly with 3 pairs of hairs that are longer than hairs on leading edge of scape; 1 pair on vertex. Pronotal humeral hair long and stout, filiform and projecting; humeral angles rounded. Mesonotum with 1 pair of stout standing narrowly spatulate hairs on anterior margin. Propodeum with two pairs of short, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Ground-pilosity on alitrunk dorsum as on head but sparser. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly, posterior alitrunk gradually sloping down to declivity, anterior propodeum slightly raised above posterior mesonotum. Metanotal groove represented by a shallow impression. Propodeal spines narrowly triangular, margins spongiform; propodeal lamella absent. Alitrunk dorsum and sides of pronotum densely reticulate-punctate. Pleurae mostly reticulate-punctate, katepisternum and central portion of metapleuron partially smooth. Petiole node in dorsal view approximately as long as broad. Postpetiole disc reticulate-punctate. In profile ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle a narrow, irregular strip that is continuous along the base of the peduncle, maximum depth of strip slightly less than the maximum width of eye. Ventral spongiform tissue of postpetiole moderately developed. Basigastral costulae short, distinct and widely spaced. Dorsal surface of petiole, postpetiole, and gaster with stout standing remiform to narrowly spatulate hairs. Colour medium brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="661">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 3.3 - 3.7, HL 0.80 - 0.88, HW 0.68 - 0.76, CI 85 - 90, ML 0.44 - 0.49, MI 52 - 57, SL 0.53 - 0.56, SI 73 - 78, PW 0.37 - 0.41, AL 0.76 - 0.86 (8 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="661">Holotype worker, Madagascar: Causse de Kelifely, 20 - 30. xi. 1974, forest humus and litter, dry forest (A. Peyrieras) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="661">Paratypes. 9 workers with same data as holotype (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="661">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155840" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys fronto Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys fronto Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="661" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fronto">S. fronto</taxonomicName>
can easily be isolated by the presence of only 1 preapical tooth on left and right mandibles, a long stiff projecting filiform hair on each pronotal humerus and the dorsolateral margin of the head posteriorly with 2 - 3 stiff erect hairs that are longer than hairs on leading edge of scape. See 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155838" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys carisa Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys carisa Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="661" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="carisa">carisa</taxonomicName>
for further discussion.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>