<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c990e4df-7ee4-4898-96ff-c96f45456873" ModsDocID="5831" checkinTime="1243376545748" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1946" docId="9BB25DF370AFC789AEE3AB90BD1300CC" docLanguage="en" docName="5831" docOrigin="Annals and Magazine of Natural History 12" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5831/5831.pdf" docTitle="Triglyphothrix mauricei Donisthorpe, 1946, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="779" masterDocId="8D8AC18485F43A7290ED28CAFA476F2F" masterDocTitle="New species of ants (Hym., Formicidae) from the island of Mauritius." masterLastPageNumber="782" masterPageNumber="776" pageNumber="778" updateTime="1569525771911" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species of ants (Hym., Formicidae) from the island of Mauritius.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1946</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>776</mods:start>
<mods:end>782</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5831/5831.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">5831</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:9BB25DF370AFC789AEE3AB90BD1300CC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9BB25DF370AFC789AEE3AB90BD1300CC">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="778">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:145070" authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Triglyphothrix" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Triglyphothrix mauricei Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Triglyphothrix mauricei Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="778" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mauricei">Triglyphothrix mauricei</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="778">[[ worker ]]. Reddish brown, mouth-parts, antennae and legs pale brownish yellow; body clothed with moderately short and abundant outstanding brown hairs of different lengths and structure.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="779" pageNumber="778">Head a little longer than broad, slightly narrower in front than behind, space between eyes and posterior angles straight, posterior angles rounded, posterior border very slightly and shallowly excised. Sculpture consisting of slightly raised longitudinally ridges, interrupted by cross striae, forming a network and enclosing irregular spaces. Mandibles massive, triangular, slightly striate and punctate, masticatory border armed with a sharp tooth at apex, preceded by a row of short and blunt teeth; clypeus' large, triangular, dorsal surface convex and striate longitudinally, the margin of the posterior border raised, forming a strong carina, which forms the anterior border of the antennal foveae, anterior border slightly excised in middle; scrobes shallow and smooth, extending back near to posterior border; frontal area and furrow wanting; eyes fairly large, round, and prominent, situated in about the middle of sides of head; antennae 12 - jointed, club 3 - jointed, scape curved, not reaching posterior border of head, funiculus with first joint subquadrate, next seven joints transverse, gradually increasing in width, first joint of club shorter and narrower than second, last joint slightly longer than the two preceding taken together. Thorax rather short, convex, robust, broader in front, narrowed behind, broadest a little behind humeral angles, which are slightly prominent, no sutures on dorsal surface; epinotum armed with two moderately long, sharp, divergent spines, declivity concave and smooth, with two short, sharp teeth, situated one on each side of base; the sculpture of thorax consists of a network of raised ridges, enclosing somewhat irregular spaces. Petiole with smooth peduncle, node rounded above and at sides, sculpture as in thorax; post-petiole slightly transverse, sides rounded, very slightly broader and sculpture finer than in petiole; gaster short oval, smooth, shining, excised at base at junction with post-petiole. Legs moderate, femora and tibiae spindle-shaped.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="779">Long. 2.5 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="779">No. 48. Described from three workers taken by Mr. R. Mamet at Rose Hill, Mauritius, in 1942.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="779">
This species comes near to the cosmopolital 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:160236" authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Triglyphothrix" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Triglyphothrix striatidens (Emery)" lsidName-HNS="Triglyphothrix striatidens (Emery)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="779" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="striatidens">T. striatidens Emery</taxonomicName>
, but is darker in colour, the sculpture of the petiole and post-petiole is considerably coarser, and the epinotal spines are shorter and straighter.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>