<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e8e04fdf-7ade-4df5-9a33-951aa243f7b3" ID-GBIF-Taxon="139438642" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-724-101" ID-ZBK="5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:761B4764-3A87-45D3-AB5A-D166CEC36F51" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-724-101" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 724" ModsDocTitle="Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)" checkinTime="1513881619487" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Rong, Hua &amp; Li, Houhun" docDate="2017" docId="EF67BC360F6189F8B50E9CBAC903B772" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 724: 101-118" docOrigin="ZooKeys 724" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262" docTitle="Locastra viridis Rong &amp; Li, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="761B4764-3A87-45D3-AB5A-D166CEC36F51" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="108" masterDocId="A540DC10FF9A2C5FFFF07461FF83FF84" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="118" masterPageNumber="101" pageId="7" pageNumber="108" updateTime="1643574149427" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Rong, Hua</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Houhun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>724</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>101</mods:start>
<mods:end>118</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-724-101</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="139438642" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:761B4764-3A87-45D3-AB5A-D166CEC36F51" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EF67BC360F6189F8B50E9CBAC903B772" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="7" pageNumber="108">
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="108" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/761B4764-3A87-45D3-AB5A-D166CEC36F51" class="Insecta" family="Pyralidae" genus="Locastra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Locastra viridis" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="108" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="viridis">Locastra viridis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="7" pageNumber="108">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 6, 11, 15
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="108" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">
Holotype: ♂ - CHINA, Xiajinchang (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="23.166666">23°10'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="104.8">104°48'E</geoCoordinate>
), Malipo County, Wenshan, Yunnan, 1470 m, 26.VII.2016, coll. Kaijian Teng, Gaeun Lee and Tao Wang.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">
Paratypes: (24♂, 2♀) - Guangxi: 8♂, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Yangmei’ao">Yangmei'ao</normalizedToken>
, Huajiang County, Hechi, 1180 m, 23-26.VII.2015, Meiqing Yang and Gaeun Lee, slide Nos. RH15427, RH15321; Henan: 3♂, Mt. Baiyun, Luoyang, 1560 m, 22.VII.2001, coll. Dandan Zhang, slide Nos. WYP05074, WYP06031; 1♂, 1♀, Mt. Wangwu, Jiyuan, 800 m, 30.VII.2006, coll. Hui Zhen and Denghui Kuang, slide No. WYP06036♀; Hubei: 1♂, Shayuan, Hefeng, 1260 m, 18.VII.1999, coll. Houhun Li et al., slide No. WYP06034; 1♂, Bapingying, Xianfeng, 1280 m, 22.VII.1999, coll. Houhun Li et al., slide No. WYP05077; Yunnan: 6♂, 1♀, 26-29.VII.2016, other data same as holotype, slide Nos. RH16459♂, RH16460♀; 4♂, Taiyanghe Nature Reserves, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pu’er">Pu'er</normalizedToken>
, 1450 m, 14.VII.2016, coll. Kaijian Teng, Gaeun Lee and Tao Wang.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="108" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">
This species is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. muscosalis" pageId="7" pageNumber="108" rank="species" species="muscosalis">L. muscosalis</taxonomicName>
in male genitalia. It can be distinguished by the sub-rectangular uncus, the valva without a process at the base of the ventral margin, and the juxta concave in V shape on the posterior margin; the sub-rectangular antrum and the corpus bursae approx 2/5 as long as the ductus bursae. In 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. muscosalis" pageId="7" pageNumber="108" rank="species" species="muscosalis">L. muscosalis</taxonomicName>
, the uncus is inverted sub-trapezoidal, the valva bears a triangular process at basal 1/3 of the ventral margin (Fig. 13), the juxta concave in U shape on the posterior margin; the antrum is narrower, and the shorter corpus bursae is approx 1/3 as long as the ductus bursae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="108" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Adult (Fig. 6) wingspan 29.0-38.0 mm. Head black mixed with grayish green. Male labial palpus pale grayish green, mixed with black on outer side; first segment half length of second; second segment reaching vertex, inner side with blackish green hair-like scales grayish white basally; third segment black, approx 1/4 length of second, tapering. Female labial palpus shorter than in male, slightly porrect; second segment with short grayish white hair-like scales on ventral surface; third segment approx 2/3 length of second. Maxillary palpus compressed, short, grayish green mixed with black. Antenna with ventral surface yellowish fuscous, with short pale gray cilia denser in male than in female; dorsal surface white mixed with black; scape extension extremely short, sub-globose, reaching before patagium, with grayish green scales. Thorax and tegula grayish green mixed with black and yellowish fuscous. Forewing with basal area black mixed with grayish green and fuscous; median area fuscous mixed with black, pale green mixed with black along costal margin; distal area pale green mixed with black; antemedian line black, wavy, running from 1/3 of costal margin slightly oblique outward to 2/5 of dorsum, edged with pale green fascia on both inner and outer margins; postmedian line black, serrate, running from 2/3 of costal margin oblique outward to CuA1, then inward to CuP, finally slightly outward to 4/5 of dorsum; glandular swelling small, yellowish fuscous, surrounded by black scales; black tuft placed below middle of lower margin of cell; discocellular spot small, represented by fuscous mixed with black tuft; terminal line grayish white, with uniform black rectangular spots evenly spaced along its inner side, interrupted with grayish white on veins. Hindwing gray, darkening from base toward apex; postmedian line ill-defined, blackish gray, serrate, extending from 2/3 of costal margin oblique outward to CuA2, edged with grayish white along its outer margin. Cilia of both wings pale grayish green, interrupted with black on extension of veins. Legs grayish white on inner side; on outer side black mixed with grayish green, fore tibia with grayish green hair-like scales, mid tibia with dense black mixed with grayish green hair-like scales, hind tibia with sparse grayish white mixed with grayish green hair-like scales, all tarsi white at apex of each tarsomere. Abdomen grayish white mixed with black on ventral surface; dorsal surface with 1st and 2nd segments yellowish fuscous, suffused with white and black scales, remaining segments black, suffused with white and yellowish fuscous scales.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Male genitalia (Fig. 11). Uncus sub-rectangular, app approximately rox 1.7 times as long as wide; distal 1/3 slightly widened, with dense short setae dorsally. Gnathos arms slender, joined from 3/5; distal process hooked, narrowed to pointed apex. Valva approximately 1.6 times as long as maximum width, with dense long hairs; costa reaching apex of valva; ventral margin arched obtusely, with narrow band from ventrobasal corner to base of juxta half length of ventral margin. Vinculum approximately as long as uncus. Juxta dilated proximally, its basal half separated, lateral arms relatively wide, sub-parallel; distal half merged sub-rectangularly, concav in U shape on posterior margin; posterolateral lobe membranous, elongate triangular, with short hairs; slender lateral arm extending from middle at 60° angle to vinculum. Phallus approximately 1.7 times as long as maximum length of valva; sclerotized sub-ovate dorsal plate smaller; cornutus long, slightly curved ventrad.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Female genitalia (Fig. 15). Papillae anales sub-triangular, obtuse posteriorly, with dense long hairs. Eighth tergite shallowly concave anterior margin medially; sternite sub-rectangular, membranous medially, with sparse setae on posterior margin. Apophyses anteriores slightly longer than apophyses posteriores, with basal 1/5 expanded triangularly; apophyses posteriores thinner, basal 1/5 slightly wavy. Antrum sub-rectangular, approx 1/2 as long as wide, weakly sclerotized. Ductus bursae membranous, basal 1/3 wide, distal 2/3 narrower, curved, with longitudinal ridges. Corpus bursae ovate, approx 2/5 length of ductus bursae; signa sub-ovate, with semicircular ridge medially, serrate on one edge.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="108" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">China (Guangxi, Henan, Hubei, Yunnan).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="108" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="108">The specific name is derived from the Latin viridis, referring to the forewing with more green scales.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>