<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.679.12805" ID-GBIF-Dataset="78b292ea-b47d-4078-a8e6-e05206605f29" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132649505" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-679-77" ID-ZBK="4EFD0B8CD9F24B048397C01AF6AFFAF5" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3C5872C4-1EE5-4262-B986-FD5D1F7A4785" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-679-77" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 679" ModsDocTitle="The genus Apodrosus Marshall, 1922 in Cuba (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae, Polydrusini)" checkinTime="1502744640237" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Anderson, Robert S. &amp; Zhang, Guanyang" docDate="2017" docId="E0A8058FA57E5B3F06AF8C6AEDE3FDE6" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 679: 77-105" docOrigin="ZooKeys 679" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.679.12805" docTitle="Apodrosus zayasi Anderson, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="3C5872C4-1EE5-4262-B986-FD5D1F7A4785" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="99" masterDocId="237BB520FF93DD13FF91FFD8FF9FFF8D" masterDocTitle="The genus Apodrosus Marshall, 1922 in Cuba (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae, Polydrusini)" masterLastPageNumber="105" masterPageNumber="77" pageId="20" pageNumber="97" updateTime="1643561099228" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The genus Apodrosus Marshall, 1922 in Cuba (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae, Polydrusini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Anderson, Robert S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhang, Guanyang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>679</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>77</mods:start>
<mods:end>105</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.679.12805</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.679.12805</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-679-77</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">4EFD0B8CD9F24B048397C01AF6AFFAF5</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">4EFD0B8CD9F24B048397C01AF6AFFAF5</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132649505" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3C5872C4-1EE5-4262-B986-FD5D1F7A4785" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E0A8058FA57E5B3F06AF8C6AEDE3FDE6" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="20" pageNumber="97">
<subSubSection pageId="20" pageNumber="97" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="97">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/3C5872C4-1EE5-4262-B986-FD5D1F7A4785" authority="Anderson" class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Apodrosus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Apodrosus zayasi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="20" pageNumber="97" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zayasi">Apodrosus zayasi Anderson</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="20" pageNumber="97">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 24-26
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="20" pageNumber="97" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="97">Specimens examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="97">1 male, 2 females. Holotype male (CMNC), labelled CUBA: Province Cienfuegos, Parque Nacional Pico San Juan, road, 21.98812, -80.14632, 1086 m, 19.V.2013, R. Anderson, 2013-022X, hand collections. Paratype. Data as holotype (1 female; CMNC). Pico San Juan, near peak, 21.9886833, -80.1465833, 1105 m, 19.V.2013, G. Zhang, CB-13, L.22 (1 female; ASUHIC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="20" pageNumber="97" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="97">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="97">This species is distinguished from other Cuban species by the eyes small, rounded, the distance from posterior margin of eye to posterior margin of head about the same as greatest diameter of an eye, and by distinctive male genitalia. It is the only Cuban species with such small, rounded eyes.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="20" pageNumber="97" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="97">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="20" pageNumber="97">
Male. Body length 3.6 mm; in dorsal view about 2.3 times longer than greatest width which is at about second third of elytra; dorsal outline in lateral view quite tumid. Vestiture composed of pale to dark brown scales, with very small recurved, fine brown setae. Eyes 1.1 times longer than wide, projected, separated from anterior margin of prothorax by about greatest diameter of eye; line of anterior margin of eyes very slightly impressed; shortest distance between eyes (dorsal view) 0.5 times greatest width of pronotum; median furrow linear, narrow and shallow, extending from anterior margin of eyes but not reaching anterior margin of pronotum, partially obscured by scales. Rostrum slightly longer than wide; epistoma apically with two setae 
<pageBreakToken pageId="21" pageNumber="98" start="start">situated</pageBreakToken>
on each side; nasal plate well defined, v-shaped, slightly tumid, not declivious. Antennal insertion apicad of midpoint of rostrum; scrobe curved downwards by 45°, directed posteriorly at end, barely reaching anterior margin of eye, separated from it by 2.0 times width of scrobe. Mandibles with 2 lateral setae. Antennae reddish brown; antennal scape extending to just slightly beyond posterior margin of eye; desmomere I about same length as II. Pronotum cylindrical, slightly wider than long, greatest width at midlength; dorsal surface shallowly punctate but largely obscured by scales, each puncture with a curved, fine brown seta; posterior margin slightly bisinuate, slightly wider than anterior margin; scutellum subcircular, glabrous. Mesocoxal cavities about 
<pageBreakToken pageId="22" pageNumber="99" start="start">5</pageBreakToken>
times width of intercoxal process. Metasternum with lateral portions slightly tumid, not posteriorly produced. Elytra in dorsal view 1.8 times their greatest width; anterior margin sinuate; humeral region of elytra 1.5 times width of posterior margin of pronotum; lateral margins slightly divergent until second third, thereafter convergent; apex acutely rounded; in lateral view with dorsal outline tumid; posterior declivity gradually descending; stria 9 complete, stria 10 interrupted above metacoxa (appearing to merge with stria 9), resuming at suture between ventrites 1 and 2; intervals completely covered with scales, with dark and light areas forming an irregular pattern; all intervals equally flat, humerus angled; interval 9 very slightly tumid above metacoxa; all intervals with recurved, fine brown setae. Venter with scales very sparse, linear and hair-like on all ventrites; ventrites 3 and 4 subequal in length, their combined length shorter than ventrite 5; posterior margin of ventrite 5 widely rounded, finely narrowly emarginate at middle, apex at middle narrowly impressed. Tegmen with tegminal apodeme 0.8 times length of aedeagus; tegminal plate simple. Aedeagus short and robust, in dorsal view about 3.0 times longer than its greatest width; apex rounded, deflexed ventrally. Endophallus extended to just beyond base of aedeagus, with no visible internal sclerotization. Aedeagus in lateral view slightly evenly convex. Aedeagal apodemes about same length as aedeagus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="99">Female. Body length 3.4-3.6 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="22" pageNumber="99" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="99">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="99">This species is named after Fernando de Zayas (1912-1983), entomologist, Cuban Academy of Sciences.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="22" pageNumber="99">
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="99">
Figures 24-26. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Apodrosus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Apodrosus zayasi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="22" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zayasi">Apodrosus zayasi</taxonomicName>
. 24 Lateral habitus, female 25 Dorsal habitus, female 26 Male aedeagus, dorsal.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="22" pageNumber="99" type="natural history">
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="99">Natural history.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="99">Adults were collected beating vegetation along the upper part of the road to Pico San Juan.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>