<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6160145" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5918b440-d835-4e34-9618-f1b58aab1bed" ID-GBIF-Taxon="114913867" ID-HNS-Pub="27552" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6160145" checkinTime="1409237179507" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Longino, John T" docDate="2013" docId="988FE8012237B665DFAE69A9DF5005A0" docLanguage="en" docName="27552.htm.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 3699" docTitle="Octostruma ascrobis Longino, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="19" masterDocId="EE74F677DCA4F13702125E9CE8D29A0F" masterDocTitle="A revision of the ant genus Octostruma Forel 1912 (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)" masterLastPageNumber="61" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="17" pageNumber="17" updateTime="1645264522075" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of the ant genus Octostruma Forel 1912 (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Longino, John T</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3699</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>61</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-Pub">27552</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.3699.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">65A19D30-8E7A-4073-B92B-9709F8384752</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6160145" ID-GBIF-Taxon="114913867" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6160145" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:988FE8012237B665DFAE69A9DF5005A0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/988FE8012237B665DFAE69A9DF5005A0" lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="19" pageId="17" pageNumber="17">
<subSubSection pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="mainText">
<taxonomicName authority="Longino" authorityName="Longino" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="17" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ascrobis">
<pageBreakToken pageId="17" pageNumber="17" start="start">Octostruma</pageBreakToken>
ascrobis 
<authority pageId="17" pageNumber="17">Longino</authority>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="17" pageNumber="17" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="mainText">(Figs 1H, 3G, 6C, 14I, 17, 44)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="mainText">
Type material. Holotype worker: GUATEMALA, Izabal: 5 km NW Morales, 15.51351, -88.86647, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="±" pageId="17" pageNumber="17">+/-</normalizedToken>
26 m, 245 m, 17 May 2009, 2° lowland rainforest, ex sifted leaf litter (LLAMA, Wm-B-04-1-01) [CAS, unique specimen identifier CASENT0611295]. Paratype workers: same data except 15.51078, -88.86105, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="±" pageId="17" pageNumber="17">+/-</normalizedToken>
50 m, 195 m (LLAMA, Wa-B-04-1-22) [MCZC, CASENT0611224; USNM, CASENT0611225]; 15.51465, -88.86440, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="±" pageId="17" pageNumber="17">+/-</normalizedToken>
28 m, 280 m, 18 May 2009 (LLAMA, Wm-B-04-1-09) [UVGC, CASENT0611425; MZSP, CASENT0611426].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="multiple">
<caption pageId="17" pageNumber="17">
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="caption">
FIGURE 17. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="17" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ascrobis">Octostruma ascrobis</taxonomicName>
, holotype worker (CASENT0611295), queen (CASENT0614238, Guatemala), face and lateral views. Scale bar = 0.2 mm face views, 0.5 mm lateral views.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="mainText">Geographic range. Mexico (Chiapas) to Costa Rica.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="mainText">
Diagnosis. Antennal scrobe very shallow, not distinctly margined; face with arcuate carina; frontal carinae extending back and joining termini of facial arc. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="17" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="convallis">Octostruma convallis</taxonomicName>
is similar, but the frontal carinae and facial arc do not join. They are separated by a transverse trough, and the termini of the facial arc extend laterally beyond the termini of the frontal carinae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="19" pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="description">
<paragraph lastPageId="18" lastPageNumber="18" pageId="17" pageNumber="17" type="mainText">
Description. Worker. HW 0.46-0.51, HL 0.43-0.49, WL 0.43-0.50, CI 102-107 (n=9). Labrum rectangular, formed of strap-like lateral portions joined by a thin translucent lamella (Fig. 1H); mandible strongly bowed, in profile view with mandible closed, basal portion of mandible in same plane as clypeus, apex of mandible strongly down-turned, the down-turned portion subequal in length to basal portion; with mandible fully open, dorsal face fully perpendicular to plane of clypeus and teeth projecting dorsally; mandible with 10 teeth (Fig. 3G), tooth 1 continuous with basal rim of dorsal surface, teeth 1-7 as in Fig. 3G, teeth 7-10 form an apical fork perpendicular to base of dorsal face, tooth 7 long and separate, tooth 8 about 1/3 length of tooth 7, teeth 9 and 10 slightly longer than 7, joined to near tip (or could be seen as single tooth bifid at the tip), tooth 9 slightly shorter than 10; dorsal surface of mandible roughened; ventral surface narrow, smooth and shiny; interior surface strongly concave, smooth and highly polished; scape flattened, with pronounced anterobasal lobe, dorsal surface shallowly foveolate anteriorly, grading to smooth and shining posteriorly; clypeus strongly emarginate anteriorly; frontal carinae sharp, narrow, divergent, joining and continuous with similar carina that arches across vertex; frontal carinae and arch delimit 
<pageBreakToken pageId="18" pageNumber="18" start="start">anterior</pageBreakToken>
concave surface that is shiny, with irregular median longitudinal carina and faint transverse rugulae laterally; side of head near compound eye shallowly foveolate; vertex posterior to facial arc largely smooth and highly polished, with distinct, sparse, uniformly distributed 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="18" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
; compound eye small, circular, composed of 4- 5 somewhat confluent ommatidia; short carina passes obliquely between antennal socket and eye, extending a short distance posterior to eye and toward frontal carina; antennal scrobe below eye, very shallow and not delimited with carina or flange; scrobe and undersurface of head shallowly foveolate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="18" type="mainText">
Promesonotum forming continuous convexity in profile; metanotal groove not impressed; propodeum a single, concave, sloping surface, not differentiated into dorsal and posterior faces; propodeal spines in the form of flattened perpendicular plates, right-angled to slightly acute, extending anteriorly as raised carinae that curve medially and join at the metanotal groove, extending ventrally as narrow lamella, thus posterodorsal face of propodeum entirely delimited by raised carinae confluent with propodeal spines; propodeal spiracle large, located immediately below propodeal spine and abutting posterior margin; pronotum sculpture smooth and shining with sparse 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="18" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
, like posterior vertex; mesonotum with feeble, mesh-like sculpture, contrasting sharply with pronotum and clearly demarcating juncture of pro- and mesonotum; posterodorsal face of propodeum shallowly foveolate; mesopleuron and side of propodeum not differentiated, matte, very faintly punctate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="18" type="mainText">Petiole in profile with peduncle not differentiated from node, anterior surface sloping evenly from petiolar foramen to node, dorsal face of node sloping posteriorly to projecting transverse cuticular rim, short concave posterior face beneath rim; anteroventral margin with small tooth or angle; dorsal face of node smooth and shining; postpetiole low, broad, crescent-shaped in dorsal view, dorsal face shallowly foveolate anteriorly, smooth and shining posteriorly, delimited anteriorly and posteriorly by thin transverse rim; first gastral tergite shallowly foveolate anteriorly, grading to smooth and shining at posterior rim; first gastral sternite foveolate anteriorly, grading to sparsely punctate with smooth and shining interspaces posteriorly.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="18" type="mainText">Labrum fringed on sides and apex with soft translucent thick setae, one of these on each anterior labral lobe much longer than the others, projecting ventrally; extreme base of ventral surface of mandible with very fine, long seta that curves forward and nearly touches ventrally projecting labral seta; each larger mandibular tooth with prominent fully appressed seta; anterior margin of scape with seven stiff clavate setae; clypeus with sparse fully appressed ground pilosity, anterior face with sparser and much less visible ground pilosity, posterior face essentially lacking ground pilosity; 1-3 stout clavate setae variably distributed between apex of oblique supraocular carina and outer margin of facial carina, near juncture of frontal carina and transverse carina; mesonotum, petiole and postpetiole lacking erect setae, ground pilosity extremely short, sparse, unnoticeable; mesotibia with short, thin, sparse, decumbent ground pilosity, a single large stout clavate seta and several thin shorter erect setae at apex; mesobasitarsus with 2 pairs long, thin, erect setae; first gastral tergite with row of 4 clavate setae at posterior margin, following exposed tergites each with row of clavate setae; ground pilosity of first gastral tergite short, sparse, fully appressed, somewhat more noticeable than on mesosoma; first gastral sternite with sparse, thin but stiff erect setae over much of surface except narrow area near postpetiolar insertion.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="18" type="mainText">Color red to red-orange.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="18" type="mainText">Queen. HW 0.54-0.57, HL 0.52-0.53, WL 0.70-0.73, CI 102-107 (n=2). Labrum, mandible, and scape similar to worker; anterior clypeal margin very different from worker and highly distinctive, with a broad shallow semicircular concavity medially, flanked on each side by a deep semicircular notch that nearly &quot;pinches off&quot; an anterolateral portion of the clypeus between the notch and the large antennal socket (Fig. 14I); clypeus confluent with the vertex posteriorly, with no evidence of a clypeal suture; transverse facial carina and posterior frontal carinae feeble to absent, but marked by a semicircular row of about 9 erect spatulate setae; face anterior to row of setae flat, with faint transverse rugulae, lacking longitudinal median carina, face posterior to seta row like worker; ocelli distinct, anteromedian ocellus immediately anterior to seta row; compound eye large, multifaceted, about 12 ommatidia in longest row; outermost seta of seta row at inner margin of compound eye; antennal scrobe shallow, like worker.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="18" type="mainText">
Mesosoma with queen-typical alar sclerites; pronotum smooth and shining laterally and anteriorly, with faint rugulae and sparse 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="18" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
on humeri; mesoscutum and axillae irregularly longitudinally rugulose; scutellum smooth and shining medially, with a few 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="18" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
and faint rugulae laterally; anepisternum and katepisternum separated by strong sulcus, both smooth and shining; posterodorsal propodeum concave, shallowly foveolate; side of propodeum matte with faint 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="18" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
; propodeal spines pronounced, in the form of flattened perpendicular plates, right-angle to slightly acute in profile; propodeal spiracle smaller and lower compared to worker, anterior to ventral propodeal lamella.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="19" type="mainText">
<pageBreakToken pageId="19" pageNumber="19" start="start">Petiole</pageBreakToken>
similar to worker, but posterior rim more pronounced and projecting; postpetiole also with a posterior projecting rim, ventral margin with a short acute tooth; first gastral tergite punctate over much of surface, grading to sparser and smaller 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
at posterior border, with 6-8 erect clavate setae along posterior border, about 6 scattered over disc; first gastral sternite densely punctate, with abundant short, stiff, erect setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="19" type="mainText">Color red.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="19" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="19" type="mainText">
Biology. This species inhabits lowland rainforest, from sea-level to 1000 m elevation, but is most abundant below 500 m. All specimens are from samples of sifted leaf litter and rotten wood from the forest floor. Frequencies in quantitative samples of 1 m 
<sup pageId="19" pageNumber="19">2</sup>
litter plots range from 0-16%. Dealate queens occasionally occur in samples, and one sample contained an alate queen. Worker number in samples is always &lt;10.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="19" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="19" type="mainText">
Etymology. The 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="name">name</taxonomicName>
refers to the lack of sharply delimited antennal scrobes. It is a dative plural noun and thus invariant.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>