<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.6891" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f6ef566b-85de-49d3-8b74-5eb3c8b070d6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152053508" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-415-311" ID-ZBK="412C5EF56C9F4D3FB0404D92DFA15C80" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-415-311" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 415" ModsDocTitle="Larvae and pupae of two North American darkling beetles (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae, Stenochiinae), Glyptotus cribratus LeConte and Cibdelis blaschkei Mannerheim, with notes on ecological and behavioural similarities" checkinTime="1451245765693" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Steiner, Warren E." docDate="2014" docId="62ECDB251A3343BA3688F70C88729E8A" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 415: 311-327" docOrigin="ZooKeys 415" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.6891" docTitle="Glyptotus cribratus LeConte" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="317" masterDocId="6C53FFB8182BDC56FFDFFFFFC710FFA2" masterDocTitle="Larvae and pupae of two North American darkling beetles (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae, Stenochiinae), Glyptotus cribratus LeConte and Cibdelis blaschkei Mannerheim, with notes on ecological and behavioural similarities" masterLastPageNumber="327" masterPageNumber="311" pageId="0" pageNumber="311" updateTime="1643521826793" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Larvae and pupae of two North American darkling beetles (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae, Stenochiinae), Glyptotus cribratus LeConte and Cibdelis blaschkei Mannerheim, with notes on ecological and behavioural similarities</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Steiner, Warren E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>415</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>311</mods:start>
<mods:end>327</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.6891</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.6891</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-415-311</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">412C5EF56C9F4D3FB0404D92DFA15C80</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">412C5EF56C9F4D3FB0404D92DFA15C80</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152053508" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:62ECDB251A3343BA3688F70C88729E8A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/62ECDB251A3343BA3688F70C88729E8A" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="317" pageId="0" pageNumber="311">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="311" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="311">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Glyptotus_cribratus" authority="LeConte" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="311" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus LeConte</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="312" pageId="0" pageNumber="311" type="background">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="311">Background.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="311">
A single larva from southern Florida, USA, presumed to be 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="311" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
, was reported by 
<bibRefCitation author="St. George, RA" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the United States National Museum" pageId="13" pageNumber="324" pagination="1 - 22" title="Studies on the larvae on North American beetles of the subfamily Tenebrioninae with a description of the larva and pupa of Merinus laevis (Olivier)." url="10.5479/si.00963801.65-2514.1" volume="65" year="1924">St. George (1924)</bibRefCitation>
, who provided some key characters though the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="specimen’s">specimen's</normalizedToken>
identity has remained uncertain. New associated adult and larval material, including one larva reared to an adult and another providing the first known pupal specimen (described herein), shows that the larva from St. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="George’s">George's</normalizedToken>
account was not that of 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="311" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Glyptotus</taxonomicName>
, as discussed below. The specimen, presumably in USNM, could not be located.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="312" pageId="0" pageNumber="311">
Three mature larvae, found in wood products from Mexico, 1982-84, were identified as &quot; 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="312" start="start">Glyptotus</pageBreakToken>
</taxonomicName>
sp.&quot; by T. J. Spilman, but it is uncertain what material he used to make this determination; these larvae are considered in the present study to be 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
, identical to specimens from USA; the species is known from southern Texas and thus its occurrence in north-eastern Mexico is feasible.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="314" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" type="description of mature larva">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="312">Description of mature larva.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="312">(Figs 1, 3-5, 9-12).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="312">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="312">
Figures 1-8. Mature larva of 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
, lateral view, length 22 mm (1), mature larva of 
<taxonomicName authority="Mannerheim, 1843" authorityName="Mannerheim" authorityYear="1843" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Cibdelis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cibdelis blaschkei" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="blaschkei">Cibdelis blaschkei</taxonomicName>
lateral view, length 25 mm (2), 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
larva, mandibles, ventral view, length 0.9-1.0 mm (3), epipharyngeal sclerome, length 0.4 mm (4), epipharynx, width 0.8 mm (5), 
<taxonomicName authority="Mannerheim, 1843" authorityName="Mannerheim" authorityYear="1843" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Cibdelis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cibdelis blaschkei" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="blaschkei">Cibdelis blaschkei</taxonomicName>
larva, mandibles, ventral view, length 0.7-0.8 mm (6), epipharyngeal sclerome, length 0.3 mm (7), epipharynx, width 0.7 mm (8).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="312">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="312">
Figures 9-16. Abdominal apices of mature larvae of 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
(9-12), dorsal (9) and lateral (10) view, urogomphi at rest, dorsal (11) and lateral (12) view, urogomphi raised, and abdominal apices of mature larvae of 
<taxonomicName authority="Mannerheim, 1843" authorityName="Mannerheim" authorityYear="1843" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Cibdelis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cibdelis blaschkei" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="312" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="blaschkei">Cibdelis blaschkei</taxonomicName>
(13-16), dorsal (13) and lateral (14) view, urogomphi at rest, dorsal (15) and lateral (16) view, urogomphi raised. Maximum widths of abdominal segments 3.3-3.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="312">Body. Length 23-30 mm; elongate-cylindrical, pale yellowish-white with light brown dorsal bands at posterior edges of terga and anterior edge of prothoracic tergum; mandible apices and bases, claws of tarsunguli, and apices of urogomphi and associated processes blackish to brown, heavily sclerotized; cuticle otherwise lightly sclerotized, surfaces shining, finely rugose, with scattered fine setae; abdominal tergum VIII slightly darker yellow-brown with scattered large circular punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="312">
Head. Prognathous, head slightly declined, globular but slightly flattened dorsoventrally. Head capsule width 3.4-3.5 mm. Epicranial stem about one fifth head capsule length; frontal arms widely V-shaped, fine and obscure. Each half of head capsule with 10-13 scattered, long erect setae positioned dorsally and laterally. Stemmata five on each side closely posterior to antenna base, variably pigmented; anterior row of three closely spaced and usually darker than offset pair behind them. Clypeus convex, transverse, weakly trapezoidal, about two times wider than long, with one long seta on each side of disc and three smaller setae at lateral edges. Labrum transverse, convex, with two long discal setae, two anterior setae near midline, and four smaller, fine setae along each side of anterior edge. Epipharynx with three relatively stout setae along each side of anterior margin and two very short, stout medial spines, the pair slightly offset to left; with a cluster of 8-9 small round sensory papillae anterior to spines; tormae slightly asymmetrical. Antenna three segmented with membranous base globular, wider than long; first segment longest, cylindrical, wider toward apex, 2.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide; second segment ovoid, two thirds as long as first, 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, with apical sensoria flat, kidney-shaped, partly encircling base of third segment; third segment very small, cylindrical, 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, with a single fine seta apically. Mandibles asymmetrical, apices tridentate, left mandible with a fourth feeble tooth dorsally along sharp incisor edge; left mola concave, with a prominent premolar tooth and three transverse, sclerotized ridges; right mola convex, with a transverse fossa surrounded by irregularly prominent ridges. Ligula with four fine apical setae; prementum, mentum, submentum each with a pair of long setae near base. Hypopharyngeal sclerome well developed, tridentate, with smooth concavity in middle; median tooth carinate, with Y-shaped arms to prominent, conical, lateral teeth; basal transverse ridge asymmetrical.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="312">Thorax. Prothorax as long as wide; meso- and metathorax wider than long; terga with 9-12 fine setae on each side, more closely spaced laterally. Mesothoracic spiracle simple, ovate, slightly larger and narrower than abdominal spiracles; metathoracic spiracle visible, very small, nearly circular. Prothoracic leg slightly larger than mid- and hindlegs; all legs with trochanter elongated, with anterior and posterior rows of setae on ridges; femur and tibia bearing scattered, shorter setae; tarsungulus with two pre-basal setae; claw simple, sharp, curved apically, two thirds the length of tarsungulus.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="314" pageId="1" pageNumber="312">
Abdomen. Abdominal segments I-VII similar, nearly as long as wide, gradually slightly wider posteriorly; terga with sparse setae as on thoracic terga; spiracles annular, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="313" start="start">broadly</pageBreakToken>
ovate; sterna on each side with an anterior group of 4-5 setae of varying sizes and a pair of setae posteriorly. Tergum VII with a field of circular, deep punctures across anterior two thirds of middle. Tergum VIII as long as wide, abruptly narrowing posteriorly, with an extensive field of large, deep, circular punctures across anterior half and expanding on sides and dorsally with 7-8 scattered fine setae on each side; sloped posterior bearing two somewhat sclerotized, umbonate bullae on each side, large lateral one with a long seta arising from anterior of base of umbo; small umbo posterior to larger one and closer to midline, connected to larger by a feeble ridge, the four bullae forming a trapezoidal arrangement in posterior view, immediately anterior to a broad membranous apical area which opposes a similar dorsal membrane at anterior of tergum IX. Tergum IX short, about two thirds the width of tergum VIII and hinged to it, allowing curved urogomphi to come forward to oppose and contact bullae of tergum VIII; lateral hinge joint with a sclerotized, tooth-like, anterior process; urogomphi long, gradually tapered, divergent and curved dorsally with sharp apices pointing anteriorly, nearly round in cross-section, darkly sclerotized in apical half, each with three other sclerotized, tooth-like projections near base, as follows: large 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="314" start="start">lateral</pageBreakToken>
claw-like process with apex pointed upward, forward and angled laterally, with a single dorsal seta below apex; small dorsal cone-like process bearing a single seta near apex; smaller, mesal, short, pointed to button-like process closely opposing other on opposite urogomphus. Other setae on tergum IX long, scattered; urogomphus with three setae on ventral (posterior) side; hinge process with a single seta near base; lateral and ventral surface with 7-8 scattered setae. Abdominal segment X small, ventral, transverse, semi-circular, convex, 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long, with a row of six fine setae across width; pygopods absent.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="316" pageId="3" pageNumber="314" type="description of pupa">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="314">Description of pupa.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="314">(Figs 17-20, 25, 27).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="314">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="314">
Figures 17-20. Pupa of 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="314" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
, dorsal view (17) and ventral view (18), pronotum, dorsolateral view (19), abdominal apex and urogomphi, dorsal view (20). Length of pupa 15.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="314">Body. Length (from anterior edge of pronotum to tips of urogomphi) 15.1 mm, width of pronotum 3.9 mm; body color white with brownish surface setae, apices of urogomphi and spines on lateral processes; body very sparsely setose except pronotum with numerous fine discal and marginal setae, more dense anteriorly. Lateral processes of middle abdominal segments well developed, wing-like, bearing anterior and posterior smooth teeth and two smaller setigerous lateral spines between them; urogomphi long, smooth, gradually tapered to divergent, upturned apices.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="314">Head. Hypognathous; surface smooth but with transverse wrinkles across frons; projection above antennal insertion rounded, not prominent; a few fine setae on frons, near eye, on clypeus and labrum; single seta on left mandible, near middle on outer curve; row of four setae on right mandible, from base to near middle on outer curve; single very small seta on outer edge of maxillary palpus, at base of last segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="314">
Thorax. Pronotum broadly shield-shaped, slightly wider than long, smooth with subtle transverse wrinkles; anterior angles and apex broadly rounded, posterior margin narrowly sinuate with posterior angles slightly pointed posteriorly. Pronotal surfaces with many short, fine setae except anterior margin and part of disc bare and setae more sparse in posterior part of disc; setae most closely spaced along margin of anterior angle, with some setae 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than adjacent ones, fine and often curved; hypomeron smooth, with a few widely spaced fine setae; meso- and metatergite transverse, smooth, with very few fine setae; mesonotum produced and elevated posteriorly at middle (scutellar umbo); metanotum about 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer mesonotum, nearly 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than abdominal tergite 1. Elytral sheath smooth with broad, shallow wrinkles; metathoracic wing sheath slightly shorter apically; meso- and metaventrite smooth. Legs and tarsi smooth, with a few scattered fine setae; femora with 5-7 setae from mid-length to near apex; tibiae with 3-5 setae along mid-length; protarsi with 3-4 setae on apical tarsomeres ventrally and laterally; apical tarsomeres of meso-and metatarsi with 1-2 setae laterally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="316" pageId="3" pageNumber="314">
Abdomen. All surfaces smooth, bearing scattered fine setae; spiracles annular, vertically ovate to reniform, barely pigmented, visible on segments 2-6. Tergite 1 short, with five discal setae on each side, lateral process with single small posterior tooth and two small lateral spines with a wide, U-shaped emargination between them; smallest spine near base of tooth and bearing an apical seta, largest (anterior) sharply pointed, with a sub-apical seta. Tergites 2-5 of similar form, quadrate, transverse, with 4-5 discal setae on each side; lateral processes each with anterior and slightly smaller posterior 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="315" start="start">teeth</pageBreakToken>
, stout but pointed at sclerotized, curved apices; lateral spines with sharp, sclerotized tips; larger of lateral spines near midpoint between teeth, bearing a sub-apical seta on posterior side, smaller spine arising from mid-length of posterior tooth, bearing a sub-apical seta on anterior side. Ventrites 2-6 smooth, convex, with 4-7 small fine setae on each side. Lateral process of tergite 6 with posterior tooth absent, both spines with sub-apical seta on posterior side. Tergite 7 narrower than preceding tergites, with four small fine setae on each side, with lateral process positioned and directed ventrally, not in same plane as preceding processes, anterior tooth reduced to a rounded lobe and posterior tooth absent, two posteriorly curved spines with sub-apical setae on posterior sides; sternite 7 roughly semicircular, transversely rugose apically, with three small discal setae on each side, the pair of larger setae along apical margin, with two smaller ones between them. Tergite 8 narrower than tergite 7, narrowing to broadly rounded apex, with lateral process reduced to a narrow ridge with two posteriorly curved spines only, posterior spine very reduced; spines with sub-apical setae on posterior sides; sternite 8 semicircular, with three small discal setae on each side, posterior most pair at sides of a transverse, raised area near apex. Tergite 9 short, bearing large divergent urogomphi, each gradually tapered and more sclerotized toward upturned, very sharp apices; cleft between urogomphi V-shaped with a narrowly rounded apex; base of uro 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="316" start="start">gomphus</pageBreakToken>
laterally with a single small, tooth-like protuberance, not heavily sclerotized, with a fine seta on mesal side near base; other long fine setae present on side of base of urogomphus and ventrolateral side of urogomphus to about mid-length, the latter arising from small protuberances. Genital segment (female pupa) roughly trapezoidal, smooth, with two divergent, protruding papillae bearing a single small seta laterally, papillae with a shallow V-shaped emargination between them.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="317" pageId="5" pageNumber="316" type="glyptotus cribratus larval, pupal and reared adult material examined">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="316">
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="316" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
larval, pupal and reared adult material examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="317" pageId="5" pageNumber="316">
Specimens collected in USA. &quot;FLORIDA: Highlands Co., Archbold Biol. Sta., S of Lake Placid, S. side of Lake Annie, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="27.209723">27°12'35&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-81.35">81°21'W</geoCoordinate>
, 19 April 2003 / In soft rotten dry wood of low dead branch on live Quercus virginiana; W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen et al. collectors&quot; (3 L); Same data except &quot;Reared from larva; emerged October 2003, larval exuvia not recovered&quot; (1 A); &quot;FLORIDA: Highlands Co., Archbold Biol. Sta., S. of Lake Placid, forest tract, NE part, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="27.2">27°12'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-81.333336">81°20'W</geoCoordinate>
, 19 April 2003 / W. E. Steiner &amp; J. M. Swearingen collectors / In pithy rotten wood of dead standing oak branch, mixed scrub forest burned ca 1 year ago&quot; (2 L); &quot;FLORIDA: Highlands Co., Archbold Biol. Sta., S. of Lake Placid, hill area E of Station, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="27.183332">27°11'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-81.34167">81°20'30&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
/ 31 December 2006, W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen, A. W. &amp; B. B. Norden, collectors / In dry rotten wood of recently fallen dead branch of live oak&quot; (1 L); &quot;FLORIDA: Highlands Co., 2 km N. Cornwell at Kissimmee River, 1 March 1984 / In rotting wood of log of live oak / W. E. Steiner, A. G. Gerberich, J. E. Lowry collectors&quot; (1 L); &quot;GEORGIA: Camden County, Little Cumberland Island, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="30.966667">30°58'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-81.416664">81°25'W</geoCoordinate>
, 30 November 1997 / In dry soft rotten wood of hanging branch 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="virginiana">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="317" start="start">Quercus</pageBreakToken>
virginiana
</taxonomicName>
in maritime forest / W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen, W. A. Dix, C. Wells collectors&quot; (1 L); same data except &quot;25 November 1998 / In dry soft rotten wood of dead branch in canopy of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="virginiana">Quercus virginiana</taxonomicName>
in maritime forest&quot; (2 L); same data except &quot;In pithy rotten wood of dead branch recently fallen from live oak, 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="virginiana">Quercus virginiana</taxonomicName>
&quot; (1 L); same data except &quot;28 November 1998 / Associated with adult 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus cribratus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cribratus">Glyptotus cribratus</taxonomicName>
in dry soft rotten wood of small low branch on live 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="virginiana">Quercus virginiana</taxonomicName>
in maritime forest&quot; (1 L); &quot;NORTH CAROLINA: Dare County, Kill Devil Hills, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="35.9925">35°59'33&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-75.65305">75°39'11&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 23 February 2007, coll. W. E. Steiner &amp; J. M. Swearingen / In dry rotten wood of recently fallen dead branch of s. red oak (
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus falcata" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="falcata">Quercus falcata</taxonomicName>
)&quot; (1 L); same data except &quot;Reared from larva in dry rotten wood of recently fallen dead branch of s. red oak (
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus falcata" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="falcata">Quercus falcata</taxonomicName>
); pupated 25 April, preserved 1 May 2007&quot; (1 P with larval exuvia); &quot;SOUTH CAROLINA: Dillon Co.; Fork; Little Pee Dee S.P., sand area, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="34.319443">34°19'10&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-79.284996">79°17'06&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 16 April 2012 / In dry soft rotten wood of dead branch of live 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus laevis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="laevis">Quercus laevis</taxonomicName>
in open pine-oak sand scrub; colls. J. C. Ciegler, W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen&quot; (1 L); &quot;SOUTH CAROLINA: Georgetown County; Huntington Beach, near Murrells Inlet, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="33.514168">33°30'51&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-79.052505">79°03'09&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 15 April 2012 / In dry soft rotten wood of dead lower branch 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="virginiana">Quercus virginiana</taxonomicName>
in maritime forest; colls. J. C. Ciegler, W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen&quot; (1 L); &quot;TEXAS: Comal County, Espinazo del Diablo, 9 km SW Wimberley, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="29.925">29°55'30&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-98.15139">98°09'05&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 17 November 2013 / In dry pithy wood of recently fallen branch of living 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana subsp. fusiformis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="virginiana" subSpecies="fusiformis">Quercus virginiana fusiformis</taxonomicName>
/ Colls. W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen, J. R. Ott, E. Silverfine&quot; (1 L); &quot;TEXAS: Hays County, Driftwood, at Dutchman Vineyards, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="30.1025">30°06'09&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-98.01417">98°0'51&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 15 November 2013 / In dry pithy wood of dead low branches on large living 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana subsp. fusiformis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="virginiana" subSpecies="fusiformis">Quercus virginiana fusiformis</taxonomicName>
/ Colls. W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen, J. R. Ott, E. Silverfine&quot; (4 L); &quot;TEXAS: Hays County, Freeman Ranch, NW of San Marcos, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="29.939722">29°56'23&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-98.01222">98°0'44&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 15 November 2013 / In dry pithy wood of dead low branch on large living 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana subsp. fusiformis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="virginiana" subSpecies="fusiformis">Quercus virginiana fusiformis</taxonomicName>
/ Colls. W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen, J. R. Ott, E. Silverfine&quot; (1 L); same data except second label &quot;In dry pithy wood of recently fallen branch of large living 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana subsp. fusiformis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="virginiana" subSpecies="fusiformis">Quercus virginiana fusiformis</taxonomicName>
&quot; (1 L); &quot;TEXAS: Hays County, Rutherford Ranch area NW of Kyle; oak grove near pond, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="30.046944">30°02'49&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-97.96555">97°57'56&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 16 November 2013 / In dry pithy wood of recently fallen branch of large living 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana subsp. fusiformis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="virginiana" subSpecies="fusiformis">Quercus virginiana fusiformis</taxonomicName>
/ Colls. W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen, J. R. Ott, E. Silverfine&quot; (1 L); same data except &quot;(Preserved 11 Dec. 2013) / In dry pithy wood of dead low branch on large living 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana subsp. fusiformis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="virginiana" subSpecies="fusiformis">Quercus virginiana fusiformis</taxonomicName>
&quot; (2L); &quot;TEXAS: Hays County, Rutherford Ranch area NW of Kyle; near old ranch house ruins, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="30.066668">30°04'0&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-97.94361">97°56'37&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 16 November 2013 / In dry pithy wood of recently fallen branch of large living 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana subsp. fusiformis" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="virginiana" subSpecies="fusiformis">Quercus virginiana fusiformis</taxonomicName>
/ Colls. W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen, J. R. Ott, E. Silverfine&quot; (1 L); &quot;TEXAS: San Patricio Co., 12 km NE Sinton, Welder Wildlife Refuge, 8 December 1984, W. Steiner, B. Gill &amp; D. Whitehead collrs. / In rotting wood of log of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Cannabaceae" genus="Celtis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Celtis" order="Rosales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Celtis</taxonomicName>
/ larva coll. 8 Dec. 84, pupated 25 Apr. 85, eclosed 14 May 85, preserved 1 June&quot; (1 adult pinned with larval and pupal exuvia); &quot;VIRGINIA: City of Va. Beach, First Landing S. P., beach campground, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="92" value="36.923332">36°55.4'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="92" value="-76.04667">76°2.8'W</geoCoordinate>
, 16 June 2007 / In pithy rotten wood of dead branch recently fallen from live oak, 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus virginiana" order="Fagales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="virginiana">Quercus virginiana</taxonomicName>
/ W. E. Steiner, J. M. Swearingen et al. collectors&quot; (1 L).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="317">
Specimens intercepted from MEXICO.&quot; 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Glyptotus</taxonomicName>
sp. det. T.J. Spilman 1982, ex Mexico, at Hidalgo 4194, in 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Prosopis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Prosopis" order="Fabales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Prosopis</taxonomicName>
sp. stem, at Brownsville, #11491, 22v82, 82-6571&quot; (1 L); &quot; 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Glyptotus</taxonomicName>
sp. det. T.J. Spilman 1983, ex Reynosa, Mexico, 8iii83, at Hidalgo 4194, on stem 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Prosopis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Prosopis juliflora" order="Fabales" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="juliflora">Prosopis juliflora</taxonomicName>
&quot; (1 L); &quot; 
<taxonomicName authority="LeConte, 1858" authorityName="LeConte" authorityYear="1858" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Glyptotus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="317" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Glyptotus</taxonomicName>
sp. det. T.J. Spilman 1984, ex Mexico, at Laredo, 17843, in rotting log, 4xii83, 84-549&quot; (1 L).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>