<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6ecd52bf-ea5e-4a9a-8ab6-baa91b99ea58" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648955" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-685-15" ID-ZBK="DF60153C7D8F448C9274CFF507523092" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6C36EF49-CECB-4506-BD82-0B49ACCBD83B" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-685-15" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 685" ModsDocTitle="Three new species of Heteromysis (Mysida, Mysidae, Heteromysini) from the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, with first documentation of a mysid-cephalopod association" checkinTime="1502744508259" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Wittmann, Karl J. &amp; Griffiths, Charles L." docDate="2017" docId="A47EE4B667812F28F1218173427B28B8" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 685: 15-47" docOrigin="ZooKeys 685" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890" docTitle="Heteromysis (Heteromysis) octopodis Wittmann &amp; Griffiths, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="6C36EF49-CECB-4506-BD82-0B49ACCBD83B" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="28" masterDocId="FFC0FFF4EE471008870FFFE18748FFC7" masterDocTitle="Three new species of Heteromysis (Mysida, Mysidae, Heteromysini) from the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, with first documentation of a mysid-cephalopod association" masterLastPageNumber="47" masterPageNumber="15" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" updateTime="1643572060749" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Three new species of Heteromysis (Mysida, Mysidae, Heteromysini) from the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, with first documentation of a mysid-cephalopod association</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wittmann, Karl J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Griffiths, Charles L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>685</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>15</mods:start>
<mods:end>47</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-685-15</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DF60153C7D8F448C9274CFF507523092</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DF60153C7D8F448C9274CFF507523092</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648955" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6C36EF49-CECB-4506-BD82-0B49ACCBD83B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A47EE4B667812F28F1218173427B28B8" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="28" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="25" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/6C36EF49-CECB-4506-BD82-0B49ACCBD83B" authority="Wittmann &amp; Griffiths" class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis (Heteromysis) octopodis" order="Mysida" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="octopodis" subGenus="Heteromysis">Heteromysis (Heteromysis) octopodis Wittmann &amp; Griffiths</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="10" pageNumber="25">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 6B, 9, 10, 11
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="25" type="type series">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="25">Type series.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
All materials from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Miller’s">Miller's</normalizedToken>
Point, on the False Bay coastline of the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, leg. Craig Foster. Holotype, adult male with 7.0 mm body length, in vial at NHMW-25907; paratypes immature female 6.2 mm and immature male 6.1 mm, in vial at SAM-MB-A067552; dissected paratypes adult male 6.8 mm, subadult female 10.8 mm, immature female 7.8 mm, on slides at NHMW-25908, associated with 
<taxonomicName class="Cephalopoda" family="Octopodidae" genus="Octopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Octopus vulgaris" order="Octopoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Mollusca" rank="species" species="vulgaris">Octopus vulgaris</taxonomicName>
inside den in 3 m depth, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-34.2295">34°13.77'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="18.474167">18°28.45'E</geoCoordinate>
, 15°C, 26 March 2017; paratype adult male 8.8 mm (dissected, slides at NHMW-25909) from euhaline intertidal pool, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-34.22983">34°13.79'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="18.473833">18°28.43'E</geoCoordinate>
, 10 Aug. 2014; paratypes 2 subadult females (9.4 mm entire, 9.0 mm in 2 parts, both in vial at SAM-MB-A067553) plus damaged subadult female (estimated original size 8.8 mm, head missing, dissected, slides at NHMW-25910), from same pool as before, at a few cm depth upon low tide, 8 Sept. 2015.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="25">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
Based only on adult males and subadult females. Carapace produced into well-projecting, (sub)triangular rostrum with rounded apex. Eyes well-developed; cornea occupies 60-70% of eye surface; eyestalks with inconspicuous, distally-directed, blunt extension of (obliquely anterior facing) inner margin. Antennular trunk with a number of smooth and barbed setae, but no particularly modified setae; inner distal corner of its terminal segment with apophysis carrying two medium-sized, smooth setae. Antennal scale stout, extending to 0-20% below tip of antennular trunk; outer margin convex. First thoracic sternite with anteriorly-projecting, terminally-rounded median lobe; sternites 2-8 without lobes. Carpopropodus of thoracic endopods 1-8 with 2, 2, 2-3, 4-6, 5-7, 5-8, 6-8, or 6-8 segments, respectively. Third thoracic endopod without any spines or spine-like setae; carpus not swollen with respect to merus. Carpus with series of three weakly-modified setae near outer margin; these setae subbasally furnished with bristles. Merus (sub)terminally with two subbasally toothed setae. Fourth thoracic endopod with series of 2-3 such toothed setae near outer margin of carpopropodus; no such modified setae in endopods 5-8. Penes long and slender, 1.6-1.7 times length of merus of eighth thoracic endopod; tip with three rounded lobes, each wider than long. Pleopods reduced to small setose, bilobate plates, without any spines. Exopods of uropods extend distinctly beyond endopods. Endopods with only one spine on inner margin, in subbasal position near statocyst. Telson subtriangular, terminally truncate; lateral margins weakly sigmoid, along their distal 46-53% furnished with almost continuous series of 13-17 spines each. Telson with apical cleft forming a proximally rounded 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘V’">'V'</normalizedToken>
. Cleft slightly deeper than wide, its depth 17-23% 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="26" start="start">telson</pageBreakToken>
length. Cleft densely furnished with a total of 26-37 acute laminae all along its margins. Two latero-apical lobes of telson show narrow transverse apical margins, each bearing a large latero-apical spine, plus much smaller medio-apical spine.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="27" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">
As described above for 
<taxonomicName genus="H." lsidName="H. cancelli" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" rank="species" species="cancelli">H. cancelli</taxonomicName>
sp. n. unless stated otherwise in the following. Cephalothorax comprises 37-44% of body length without telson, pleon 54-63%, and carapace 32-38%, when measured along dorsal median line. First thoracic sternite with median lobe showing smooth rounded apex. Each of first to fifth abdominal somites measure 0.8-1.1 times length of sixth somite. Terminal margin of sixth pleonite with lateral shields triangular, with tip more rounded in subadult females (Fig. 10L) than in males (Fig. 10K).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">
Carapace (Figs 6B, 9, 10A). Non-dimorphic, antero-lateral edges evenly rounded. Cervical sulcus well marked, cardial sulcus weak but distinct. Anterior pore group of carapace with 29-32 pores in strongly flattened 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘U’">'U'</normalizedToken>
-shaped arrangement; posterior group with 12-15 pores (n = 6).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Eyes (Figs 6B, 9, 10A). Anterior and posterior margins of eyestalks densely covered by scales, but not so the basal portions. Ocular symphysis with subtriangular to sinusoid, in any case terminally rounded, smooth, subrostral process (dashed line in Fig. 10A).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Antennulae (Fig. 10A, B). Basal segment 41-49% length of trunk, middle 14-18% and terminal segment 34-44%. Trunk on the average stouter in males, with basal segment 0.9-1.4 times longer than broad, compared to 1.2-1.5 times in subadult females. Terminal portion of basal segment with bifid dorsal apophysis bearing 4-5 barbed setae on its more median projection, plus two smooth setae on its outer projection. Outer ventral lobe of basal segment bears four plumose setae at its tip plus a small barbed seta in subbasal position. Anterior margin of median segment dorsally with apophysis bearing a smooth seta together with several barbed setae; inner margin anteriorly with medium-sized to large barbed seta together with smooth seta. Two small barbed setae antero-ventrally close to outer margin (not visible in Fig. 10A). Terminal segment ventrally with 1-2 large, obliquely forwards-directed, plumose setae and 0-2 additional plumose setae dorsally at inner distal corner in both sexes. Lobe with four medium-sized barbed setae plus a dense series of short bristles in about median position on anterior margin of terminal segment. Outer antennular flagellum 1.3-1.5 times as thick as inner flagellum, when measured near basis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Antennae (Fig. 10A). Length of antennal scale 2.8-3.2 times its maximum width. Apical segment contributing 5-7% to total scale length. Basal segment 21-28% length of peduncle, second 36-40% and third 34-40%.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Mouth parts (not figured). Pars incisivus of mandible with 3-4 large teeth, and digitus mobilis with 3-4 large plus 2-3 small teeth. Pars centralis with 3-4 spiny teeth. Distal segment of maxillula terminally with 9-12 weakly serrated spines, subterminally with a transverse row of 5-6 barbed setae. Endite of maxillula with three large, distally spinose setae, and 18-28 smaller, smooth or barbed setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">
Thoracopods in general (Figs 10
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–H">D-H</normalizedToken>
; 11
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
). Sizes increase from exopod 1 to (4-6) and decrease from 6 to 8. Flagellum of first to eighth exopods with 8, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9 segments. Exopods with basal plate 1.3-2.2 times longer than broad. Claws of endopods 1, 3, 4 more strongly serrated in male versus subadult female, not so in endopods 5-8.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="27" start="start">Maxillipeds</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 10C, D). Sympod of first endopod with hairs on outer half. First thoracic epipod large, leaf-like, with small field of minute scales near insertion with sympod, and (sub)basally with 1-2 large, sparsely barbed setae (Fig. 10C). Dactylus of first endopod with strong, subapically, bilaterally-microserrated claw (Fig. 10D). Dactylus of second endopod with dense brush of setae, among these 16-19 modified ones.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">
Gnathopods (Figs 10E, 11
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
). Endopod with comparatively slender carpopropodus, 4.9-5.5 times longer than broad; length 0.8-1.0 times that of merus, and 0.9-1.0 times that of ischium.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">
Pereiopods (Figs 10
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
, 11
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
). Fourth endopod with moderately-small dactylus bearing a long, weakly-bent claw, microserrated on two opposite sides of its subapical portions (Fig. 10F). Fifth to eighth endopods equipped with again smaller dactylus bearing much shorter claw that shows a stronger, distally increasing curvature; this claw unilaterally microserrated only in median portions of inner margin (Fig. 10G, H).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">Penes (Fig. 11F) long, facing obliquely in anterior direction up to basis of fourth thoracopod. Five to six small, barbed setae scattered all along the penis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">Oostegites. The subadult females already have eggs in the ovaries, visible in Fig. 9A by yellow complexion through the semi-transparent, essentially red carapace (best visible at the rostrum). The subadults show well-formed but still immature marsupial plates on the seventh and eighth thoracopods, plus rudimentary oostegites on the sixth thoracopods.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">Pleopods (Fig. 10J). The seta at inner, terminal edge of endopod weakly barbed, remaining setae well-barbed or plumose. Part of plumose setae of exopod with wave-like series of weak constrictions along shaft. Total length of pleopod 5 is 173-207% that of pleopod 1 (n = 7). Starting with pleopods 1 versus 2, the length increase between subsequent pleopods is 14-31%, 3-12%, 0-15%, and 21-58%, respectively.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">
Uropods. The exopods reach with 15-38% of their length beyond endopods and 33-43% beyond telson, endopods 6-17% of their length beyond telson. Exopod length 3.8-4.2 times maximum width. Statoliths composed of fluorite; diameter 120-196 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
(n = 12); statolith formula 2 + 3 + (0-1) + (8-16) + (12-19) = 27-39.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">Telson (Fig. 11G). Length 1.2-1.5 times that of ultimate abdominal somite, or 0.7-0.9 times exopod of uropods. Length of telson 1.5-1.6 times its maximum width. Laminae of cleft show about 0.5-0.7 times average length of lateral spines. Basal half of outer margins smooth. Length of lateral spines distally (somewhat discontinuously) increasing in size by a factor of 1.3-1.7.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="27">
Colour (Figs 6B, 9). General appearance of living specimens red-orange to blazing red. Cornea brown to yellow-golden; eyestalks red, except for a white ribbon along posterior, dorsal portions of the inner margin of the cornea (best visible in Fig. 6B). Chromatophores could only partly be discerned individually due to their strong expansion (stronger in Fig. 6B than in Fig. 9A) in three specimens micro-photographed alive. Red spots scattered over eyestalks, antennae, carapace, pleon, uropods, and telson. Transverse double series of spots near posterior margin of each pleomere, not well distinguishable in thoracomeres; a broader posterior red band on pleomere 6. Uropods and telson most intensively red. Compared with that of the male in Fig. 6B, the more orange tinge of the female thorax in Fig. 9A comes from yellow yolk in the ovarian tubes. Persistence of colours as in 
<taxonomicName genus="H." lsidName="H. cancelli" pageId="12" pageNumber="27" rank="species" species="cancelli">H. cancelli</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="28" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="28" start="start">Etymology</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
The species name 
<taxonomicName lsidName="octopodis" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" rank="species" species="octopodis">octopodis</taxonomicName>
is a noun in genitive singular, derived from the substantive octopus by using the third declension of New Latin.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="28" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
<taxonomicName class="Cephalopoda" family="Octopodidae" genus="Octopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Octopus" order="Octopoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" phylum="Mollusca" rank="genus">Octopus</taxonomicName>
den (Fig. 9B) in 3 m depth at 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Miller’s">Miller's</normalizedToken>
Point, on the False Bay coastline of the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-34.22983">34°13.79'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="18.473833">18°28.43'E</geoCoordinate>
. This is closely adjacent to the type locality of 
<taxonomicName genus="H." lsidName="H. fosteri" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" rank="species" species="fosteri">H. fosteri</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (above).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="28" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">Microdistribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
Schools of this mysid were encountered during daytime in shallow sublittoral waters inside dens occupied by 
<taxonomicName class="Cephalopoda" family="Octopodidae" genus="Octopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Octopus vulgaris" order="Octopoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" phylum="Mollusca" rank="species" species="vulgaris">Octopus vulgaris</taxonomicName>
(in case of Fig. 9B together with a crab and an additional, undetermined mysid species). Association with octopus appears a regular phenomenon as 
<taxonomicName genus="H." lsidName="H. octopodis" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" rank="species" species="octopodis">H. octopodis</taxonomicName>
was found there nine times between 14 May 2016 and 26 March 2017. Nonetheless, this mysid species was also found upon low tide in a few cm depth in rocky tide pools (Figs 6B, 9A). Also this kind of microdistribution appears to be a regular phenomenon since it occurred there upon various excursions, namely 10 Aug. 2014, 14 Aug. 2014, and 8 Sept. 2015.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
Figure 9. A subadult female of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis octopodis" order="Mysida" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="octopodis">Heteromysis octopodis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. with 11 mm body length from tide pool B multi-species association inside den in 3 m depth, occupied by 
<taxonomicName class="Cephalopoda" family="Octopodidae" genus="Octopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Octopus vulgaris" order="Octopoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" phylum="Mollusca" rank="species" species="vulgaris">Octopus vulgaris</taxonomicName>
, to the right with the crab 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Plagusiidae" genus="Guinusia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Guinusia chabrus" order="Decapoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="chabrus">Guinusia chabrus</taxonomicName>
; upper arrow points to a mysid school of what we assume to be 
<taxonomicName genus="H." lsidName="H. octopodis" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" rank="species" species="octopodis">H. octopodis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., lower arrow to a different but undetermined mysid species. A, B from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Miller’s">Miller's</normalizedToken>
Point, Cape Peninsula, South Africa; in situ images by Craig Foster B image is taken of the same octopus den from which the samples were collected, but on a different date.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis octopodis" order="Mysida" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="octopodis">Heteromysis octopodis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype adult male with 8.8 mm body length (A, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–K">D-K</normalizedToken>
), paratype subadult females with 9.0 mm (B, L) and 8.8 mm (C). A cephalic region plus anterior part of carapace in male, dorsal view B anterior margin of antennular trunk in subadult female, dorsal C epipod of first thoracopod, caudal 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–H">D-H</normalizedToken>
series of dactylus with claw in thoracic endopods 1, 3-5, 8, caudal J fourth male pleopod, rostral K, L terminal margin of sixth pleonite, lateral, in male (K) versus subadult female (L).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="28">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis octopodis" order="Mysida" pageId="13" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="octopodis">Heteromysis octopodis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype adult male with 8.8 mm body length. A tarsus with part of merus pertaining to third thoracic endopod, caudal aspect, details show subbasally toothed seta on merus (B) versus subbasally barbed seta on carpus (C) D tarsus with part of merus pertaining to fourth thoracic endopod, caudal, detail (E) shows subbasally toothed seta F eighth thoracopod with penis, caudal G telson, dorsal.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>