<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.34.4714" ID-GBIF-Taxon="182249365" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1314-2607-34-1" ID-Pensoft-UUID="FFFDD770AA0BFFD0FFC0A5332C49FFE8" ID-Zenodo-Dep="574826" ID-ZooBank="65D86C7A5BAC441E8493764EEE334BE0" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0A93BF85-DEEF-4293-8A35-2C225A080084" ModsDocID="1314-2607-34-1" checkinTime="1621553117152" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Talamas, Elijah J., Masner, Lubomir &amp; Johnson, Norman F." docDate="2013" docId="3ADABBECC8A08F7C597A4693CBFAFEE3" docLanguage="en" docOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 34" docPubDate="2013-08-05" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.34.4714" docTitle="Paridris phrikos Talamas &amp; Masner 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="0A93BF85-DEEF-4293-8A35-2C225A080084" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" id="FFFDD770AA0BFFD0FFC0A5332C49FFE8" lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="33" masterDocId="FFFDD770AA0BFFD0FFC0A5332C49FFE8" masterDocTitle="Systematics of Trichoteleia Kieffer and Paridris Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae)" masterLastPageNumber="79" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" updateTime="1643530313366" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of Trichoteleia Kieffer and Paridris Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Talamas, Elijah J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Systematic Entomology Lab, USDA / ARS c / o USNM, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D. C. 20560, U. S. A.</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, K. W. Neatby Building, Ottawa, Ontario K 1 A 0 C 6, Canada</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Department of Evolution, Ecology and Organismal Biology, The Ohio State University, 1315 Kinnear Road, Columbus, Ohio 43212, U. S. A.</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of Hymenoptera Research</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2013-08-05</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>34</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>79</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.34.4714</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.34.4714</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1314-2607-34-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">65D86C7A5BAC441E8493764EEE334BE0</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-UUID">FFFDD770AA0BFFD0FFC0A5332C49FFE8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">574826</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="182249365" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0A93BF85-DEEF-4293-8A35-2C225A080084" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3ADABBECC8A08F7C597A4693CBFAFEE3" lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="33" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/0A93BF85-DEEF-4293-8A35-2C225A080084" authority="Talamas &amp; Masner" authorityName="Talamas &amp; Masner" authorityYear="2013" class="Hexapoda" family="Platygastridae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paridris phrikos" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="phrikos" status="sp. n.">Paridris phrikos Talamas &amp; Masner</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="30" pageNumber="31">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
<figureCitation captionStart="Figures 70–75" captionStartId="F20" captionText="Figures 70 - 75. 95 Paridris phrikos sp. n., female holotype (FBA 134675) 70 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 71 Lateral habitus 72 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 73 Metasoma, dorsal view 74 Head, anterior view 75 Mesoscutellum, metascutellum, propodeum, T 1 - T 1, dorsolateral view." httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/11817" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Figures 70-75</figureCitation>
; Morphbank 34
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="33" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Female body length: 1.98-2.18 mm (n=4). Male body length: 2.24-2.33 mm (n=3).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Number of basiconic sensilla on A8: one. Shape of male flagellomeres: more than 3 times as long as wide.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="32" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
Color of head: dark brown; reddish brown. Distal margin of clypeus: serrate. Shape of distal margin of clypeus in anterior view: convex; concave with median bulge. Width of clypeus: greater than width across toruli. Lateral corner of clypeus: projecting into acute angle. Length of mediofacial striae: not extending above midpoint of compound eye. Anterodorsal node on interantennal process: absent. Central keel: absent. Length of OOL: greater than 2 ocellar diameters. Macrosculpture of frons between median ocellus and inner orbit of eye: absent. Patch of microsculpture posterior to lateral ocellus in male: absent. Patch of microsculpture posterior to lateral ocellus in female: present. Patch of microsculpture between median and lateral ocelli: present. Microsculpture on dorsal head: absent. Microsculpture of posterior gena: absent. Shape of gena: weakly to moderately receding posterior to eye. Macrosculpture of posterior vertex: absent. Patch of microsculpture on temples: absent. Occipital carina above occipital foramen: simple. Anterior margin of occipital carina above occipital foramen: 
<pageBreakToken pageId="31" pageNumber="32" start="start">comprised</pageBreakToken>
of cells. Ventral extent of occipital carina: absent below occipital foramen. Setation of postgena: sparse.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Color of mesosoma: pale brown; orange.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Shape of pronotal shoulder in dorsal view: narrow and striplike. Transverse pronotal carina: present in posterior half of pronotum. Dorsal half of pronotal cervical sulcus: present as smooth furrow. Ventral half of pronotal cervical sulcus: present as line of large cells. Sculpture of pronotal setal patch: irregular striae to rugulose.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Anterior notaulus: reaching mesoscutal suprahumeral sulcus as continuous furrow. Orientation of notauli: parallel. Shape of posterior notaulus: ovoid. Microsculpture on anterior half of medial mesoscutum: absent. Macrosculpture of anterior medial mesoscutum: absent. Pattern of punctation density on medial mesoscutum: increasing anteriorly. Scutoscutellar sulcus: comprised of short parallel striae. Median carina on posterior mesoscutellum: present. Posterior scutellar sulcus: comprised of shallow round cells.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Punctures on dorsal part of posterior mesepimeral area: absent. Mesopleural carina: absent; present. Postacetabular sulcus: crenulate. Striae ventrad of mesopleural carina: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Setae on metascutellum: absent. Posterior margin of metascutellum: straight.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Setation of metapleural triangle: sparse. Paracoxal and metapleural sulci: fused. Sculpture of posterodorsal part of ventral metapleural area: rugose; smooth. Dorsal metapleural area: smooth defined area. Posterior margin of metapleuron below propodeal spiracle: with triangular point above metapleural sulcus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Anterior projection of the propodeum: present. Setation of metasomal depression: absent. Posterior projection of the propodeum: lamellate extension formed from lateral propodeal carina. Plical carina: absent. Lateral propodeal area: undifferentiated from plical area.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Length of postmarginal vein: less than half as long as stigmal vein. Rs in fore wing: spectral. Cu vein in fore wing: spectral. M vein in forewing: spectral. Color of costal cell in female: hyaline. Color of sub-radial area in female: hyaline. Color of costal cell in male: hyaline. Color of cubito-medial area in female: hyaline. Color of anal margin in female: hyaline. Color of cubito-medial area in male: hyaline. Color of anal margin in male: hyaline. RS+M in forewing: nebulous. Color of sub-stigmal area in male: hyaline. Basal vein in hind wing: spectral. Setation of hind wing: uniform throughout.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="33" pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
Color of metasoma: yellow; pale brown. Longitudinal median carina on horn of T1: absent. Armature on posterior surface of T1 horn: present. Form of armature on posterior surface of T1 horn: transverse ridge. Interstitial sculpture of T1: finely rugulose. Patch of dense fine setae on anterolateral T1: absent. Form of T2 sulcus: simple constriction. Posterior margin of transverse sulcus on T2: weakly convex. Carina along posterior margin of transverse sulcus on T2 in female: absent. Sublateral tergal carina on T2: absent. Microsculpture on T2: absent. Macrosculpture of T2 in female: longitudinally striate. Macrosculpture of T2 in male: longitudinally striate throughout. Carina along posterior margin of transverse sulcus on T2 in male: absent. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of medial T3 in female: absent; weakly longitu 
<pageBreakToken pageId="32" pageNumber="33" start="start">dinally</pageBreakToken>
striate. Macrosculpture of lateral T3 in female: weakly longitudinally striate; longitudinally striate. Macrosculpture of medial T3 in male: absent. Macrosculpture of lateral T3 in male: weakly longitudinally striate; absent. Macrosculpture of female T5: absent. Microscupture on female T6: absent. Constriction of apical T6 in female: absent. Macrosculpture of S1: rugose. Setation of S1: sparse throughout. Distribution of longitudinal striae on S2: present throughout. Macrosculpture of S2: longitudinally striate. Form of S2 felt field: line of dense setae along longitudinal ridge. Marginal depression on S3: absent. Marginal depressions on S4: absent. Marginal depression on S5: absent.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="32" pageNumber="33" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Talamas &amp; Masner" authorityYear="2013" class="Hexapoda" family="Platygastridae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="32" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="phrikos">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Paridris phrikos</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is most similar to 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Talamas &amp; Masner" authorityYear="2013" class="Hexapoda" family="Platygastridae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="32" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="xestos">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Paridris xestos</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and females may be separated by the presence of a transverse ridge on the horn of T1 and longitudinal striation on lateral T3. Males lack this character and are separated from those of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Talamas &amp; Masner" authorityYear="2013" class="Hexapoda" family="Platygastridae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="32" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="xestos">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Paridris xestos</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
solely on the basis of having weak striation on lateral T3. For this reason, males are excluded from the paratype series.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="32" pageNumber="33" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">
The Greek word 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“phrikos”">&quot;phrikos&quot;</normalizedToken>
, meaning &quot;ruffling of a smooth surface&quot;, refers to the transverse ridge on the horn of T1. The name is treated as a noun in apposition.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="32" pageNumber="33" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">35</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="32" pageNumber="33" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="32" pageNumber="33">
Holotype, female: 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">FIJI</emphasis>
: Northern Div., Cakaudrove Prov., Taveuni Isl., 5.3km SE Tavuki, MT3, Devo Peak, 
<geoCoordinate degrees="16.841" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-16.841">16.841°S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate degrees="179.968" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-179.968">179.968°W</geoCoordinate>
, 1064m, 10.X-17.X.2002, malaise trap, Schlinger &amp; M. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tokota’a">Tokota'a</normalizedToken>
, FBA134675 (deposited in BPBM). 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Paratypes</emphasis>
: 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">FIJI</emphasis>
: 3 females, FBA136321 (BPBM); OSUC 265165 (CNCI); FBA184230 (FNIC). 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">Other material</emphasis>
: 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">FIJI</emphasis>
: 3 males, FBA105673 (BPBM); FBA127991 (CNCI); FBA164300 (FNIC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>