<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.824.31722" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f2ab6c9d-9489-4c90-98b5-5be43ad06434" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154125344" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-824-135" ID-ZBK="8B12D0BBE77741A3BCAB8A1197ADD888" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="1313-2970-824-135" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 824" ModsDocTitle="First description of the immature stages of Dasyheleaalula and a redescription of adults from China (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)" checkinTime="1551186944987" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Duan, Chen, Jiang, Xiao Hong, Chang, Qiong Qiong &amp; Hou, Xiao Hui" docDate="2019" docId="27941925302BB238EBB1CB96F921AC22" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 824: 135-145" docOrigin="ZooKeys 824" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.824.31722" docTitle="Dasyhelea alula Yu 2005" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="140" masterDocId="2518FFB3FF9FFF9D9525FFE2FF8A693A" masterDocTitle="First description of the immature stages of Dasyheleaalula and a redescription of adults from China (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="145" masterPageNumber="135" pageId="2" pageNumber="137" updateTime="1643463364801" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>First description of the immature stages of Dasyheleaalula and a redescription of adults from China (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Duan, Chen</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jiang, Xiao Hong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chang, Qiong Qiong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Hou, Xiao Hui</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>824</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>135</mods:start>
<mods:end>145</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.824.31722</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.824.31722</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-824-135</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">8B12D0BBE77741A3BCAB8A1197ADD888</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8B12D0BBE77741A3BCAB8A1197ADD888</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="154125344" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:27941925302BB238EBB1CB96F921AC22" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/27941925302BB238EBB1CB96F921AC22" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="140" pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="137" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
<taxonomicName authority="Yu, 2005" authorityName="Yu" authorityYear="2005" class="Insecta" family="Ceratopogonidae" genus="Dasyhelea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dasyhelea alula" order="Diptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alula">Dasyhelea alula Yu, 2005</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="137" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceratopogonidae" genus="Dasyhelea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dasyhelea (Pseudoculicoides) alula" order="Diptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alula" subGenus="Pseudoculicoides">Dasyhelea (Pseudoculicoides) alula</taxonomicName>
Yu, 2005: 259 (male and female, China)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="137" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
2 males, 3 females, 3 larvae, 3 larval exuviae, 2 male pupal exuviae, 3 female pupal exuviae. Xiaojiawan village, Xinpu new district, Zunyi city, Guizhou province, China, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="27.72301">27°43'22.83&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="107.07434">107°04'27.62&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, 7.VII.2018, alt. 866 m, Chen Duan leg.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="139" pageId="2" pageNumber="137" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">Descriptions.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
Fourth instar larva (Figs 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
; 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–f">a-f</normalizedToken>
). Head capsule yellowish, short, wide (Fig. 1a); HL 0.20-0.21 (0.20, n = 2) mm; HW 0.15-0.16 (0.15, n = 2) mm; HR 1.31-1.33 (1.32, n = 2); SGW 0.07-0.08 (0.08, n = 2) mm; SGR 0.47-0.50 (0.49, n = 2). Antenna short, cylindrical. Anterior portion of palatum (Figs 1a, 2a, b) with four pairs of campaniformia sensilla, posterior portion with three pairs of coeloconica sensilla, two simple, one serrate (Fig. 2a, c); messors well developed; scopae (Fig. 2a, c, d) well developed with more than 67 elongate, strong pointed teeth; maxilla (Fig. 2a) well sclerotized; mandible (Fig. 1a) stout, with three similar teeth, MDL 0.06 mm, MDW 0.02 mm; galeolacinia (Fig. 2a) with concentrated flap-like papillae, one seta; maxillary palpus (Fig. 2a, c) cylindrical, with 5-6 apical papillae; lacinial sclerite I with one short seta, dorsal view of lacinial sclerite I with three pairs of lobes; lacinial sclerite II without seta. Hypostoma (Fig. 2a) with mesal portion smooth, flanked with four strong, lanceolate lateral teeth on each side. Epipharynx (Fig. 1b) massive, strongly sclerotized, dorsal comb moderately wide, round, with 12 teeth, subequal elongate, lateral arms stout, elongate, with two auxiliary sclerites. LAW 0.08-0.13 (0.11, n = 3), DCW 0.03-0.04 (0.04, n = 3). Hypopharynx (Fig. 1c) stout, heavily sclerotized, posterior comb straight with fringe, with labium sclerotized. Thoracic pigmentation diffused, pale brown. Abdominal segments whitish, with diffused pale brown pigmentation. Caudal segment (Fig. 2e, f) with single comb, which has dense elongate and subequal teeth, with three long and stout crooked hooks.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceratopogonidae" genus="Dasyhelea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dasyhelea alula" order="Diptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alula">Dasyhelea alula</taxonomicName>
Yu. Larva (
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
), male pupa (
<normalizedToken originalValue="d–e">d-e</normalizedToken>
), female pupa (
<normalizedToken originalValue="f–g">f-g</normalizedToken>
). a head, dorsal view b epipharynx, dorsal view c hypopharynx, dorsal view d dorsal apotome (male) e segment IX (male) f dorsal apotome (female) g segment IX (female). Scale bars: 0.1 mm. Abbreviations: hypostoma (HY); hypopharynx (hpy); epipharynx (epy); genital lobe (GL); terminal process (TP).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceratopogonidae" genus="Dasyhelea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dasyhelea alula" order="Diptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alula">Dasyhelea alula</taxonomicName>
Yu, larva. a head capsule (palatum, frontal view) b detail of labrum c detail of scopae d detail of lacinial sclerite I e caudal segment f detail of caudal segment. Abbreviations: antenna (AN); galeolacinia (GL); hypostoma (HY); hooks (H); labrum (LB); lacinial sclerite I (LC1); lacinial sclerite II (LC2); maxilla (MX); maxillary palpus (MP); palatum (PL); sensilla coeloconica (Sco); sensilla campaniformia (Sca); scopae (Sc).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="138" pageId="2" pageNumber="137">
Pupa (Figs 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="d–g">d-g</normalizedToken>
; 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="f–k">f-k</normalizedToken>
). Male. Total length 1.97 mm. General coloration of exuviae pale brown. Dorsal apotome (Fig. 1d) 2.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
broader than long, triangular, with apex rounded, surface covered with brown rounded tubercles, anterior margin straight, lateral margin smooth, with three anterior wrinkles; apotome sensilla (Fig. 1d): DA-1-H elongate, thin seta, insert on well-developed tubercle, DA-2-H campaniform sensillum at base; disc surface covered by stout, rounded spinules; DAL 0.07 mm, DAW 0.19 mm, DAW/DAL 2.71. Respiratory organ, apex medium dark brown, 7.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than broad, with circular fold, 7-8 apical, three lateral pores; ROL 0.15 mm, ROW 0.02 mm; pedicel pale brown, short, length 0.01 mm, ROP/ROL 0.07. Mouthparts with mandible, lacinia absent; two clypeal/labrals (Fig. 3f), CL-1-H and CL-2-H both medium-sized and thin setae; two ocular sensilla, O-1-H long, thin seta, O-2-H campaniform sensillum (Fig. 3f); cephalothorax surface with small rounded tubercles, length 0.63 mm, width 0.45 mm; cephalothoracic sensilla as follows: three dorsolateral cephalic sclerite sensilla (Fig. 3g), DL-1-H and DL-2-H both medium- 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="138" start="start">sized</pageBreakToken>
, thin setae, DL-3-H campaniform sensillum; three anterolateral sensilla (Fig. 3h), AL-1-T, AL-2-T both medium-sized, thin setae, AL-3-T short, stout seta; two anteromedial sensilla (Fig. 3h), AM-1-T medium-sized, thin seta, AM-2-T short, thin seta. Cephalothorax length 0.63 mm, width 0.45 mm. Cephalothoracic sensilla as follows (Fig. 3j): three dorsal setae (D-1-T, D-2-T, and D-3-T), D-1-T and D-2-T short, thin setae, D-3-T campaniform sensillum, SA-2-T supraalar campaniform sensillum. Metathoracic sensilla (Fig. 3i): M-2-T and M-3-T both campaniform sensilla. Abdomen: covered with short, stout spinules on anterior, posterior margin. Tergite I (Fig. 3i) with two depressions in the middle, setae as follows: D-2-I medium-sized, thin seta; D-4-I, D-7-I both campaniform sensilla; L-1-I long, thin seta. Segment IV (Fig. 3k) with sensillar pattern, as follows: D-2-IV short, stout seta; D-4-IV, D-7-IV both campaniform sensilla, D-8-IV short, stout seta, all located on flattened tubercles; L-1-IV long and stout setae, L-2-IV short, thin seta, L-3-IV short, thin seta, L-4-IV short, stout seta, all located on triangular tubercles; V-6-IV long, thin seta, V-7-IV short, stout seta, also located on flattened tubercles. Segment IX (Fig. 1e) 0.95 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, length 0.19 mm, width 0.20 mm; ventral and dorsal surface with many spinules; terminal process triangular, elongated, acute, length 0.07 mm.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="138">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="138">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceratopogonidae" genus="Dasyhelea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dasyhelea alula" order="Diptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="138" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alula">Dasyhelea alula</taxonomicName>
Yu. Male adult (
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
), female adult (
<normalizedToken originalValue="d–e">d-e</normalizedToken>
), male pupa(
<normalizedToken originalValue="f–k">f-k</normalizedToken>
). a genitalia b parameres c aedeagus d subgenital plate e spermatheca f clypeal/labral sensilla and ocular sensilla g dorsolateral cephalic sclerite sensilla h anterolateral and anteromedial sensilla i metathoracics sensilla, lateral and dorsal sensilla of first abdominal segment j dorsal and supraalar sensilla k dorsal, lateral and ventral sensilla of segment IV. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="139" pageId="3" pageNumber="138">
Female. Similar to male with usual sexual differences. Total length 1.64-1.75 (1.70, n = 2) mm. General coloration of exuviae pale brown, except dorsolateral cephalic sclerite brown. Dorsal apotome (Fig. 1f), DAL 0.08 mm, DAW 0.18 mm, DAW/DAL 2.25. Cephalothorax length 0.71 mm, width 0.42 mm. ROL 0.16-0.18 (0.17, n = 3) mm, ROW 0.02 (n = 3) mm; pedicel length 0.01 (n = 3) mm, ROP/ROL 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="139" start="start">0.11</pageBreakToken>
-0.13 (0.12, n = 3). Segment IX (Fig. 1g) length 0.17-0.20 (0.19, n = 2) mm, width 0.20 (0.15, n = 2) mm; ventral surface with many spicules, single funnel-like structure medially. Terminal process (Fig. 1g) triangular, elongated, pointed, length 0.02-0.03 (0.02, n = 2) mm.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="139" type="redescription">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="139">
Redescription of adults (Figs 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–e">a-e</normalizedToken>
; 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–k">a-k</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="139">Male</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="140" pageId="4" pageNumber="139" type="(figs 3a–c; 4a–e)">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="139">
(Figs 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
; 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–e">a-e</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="139">Head. Eyes (Fig. 4a) contiguous, abutting medially for length of 1.0 ommatidia, with interfacetal hairs. Antennal flagellum (Fig. 4b) brown, with distinct sculpture, sparsely plumose, flagellomere 13 without apical projection; AR 1.28. Frontal sclerite nearly round, with long, slender ventral projection (Fig. 4a). Clypeus (Fig. 4c) with four pairs of setae. Palpus (Fig. 4d) brown; third segment slender, the length almost the sum of the fourth and fifth segment. Lengths of palpus segments in ratio of 5: 8: 27: 12: 14.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="139">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="139">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceratopogonidae" genus="Dasyhelea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dasyhelea alula" order="Diptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alula">Dasyhelea alula</taxonomicName>
Yu. Male adult (
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–e">a-e</normalizedToken>
), female adult (
<normalizedToken originalValue="f–k">f-k</normalizedToken>
). a frontal sclerites, anterior view b flagellomeres, anterior view c clypeus, anterior view d palpus, anterior view e genitalia, ventral view f flagellomeres, anterior view g frontal sclerites, anterior view h clypeus, anterior view i palpus, anterior view j wing k subgenital plate and spermatheca, ventral view. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="140" start="start">Thorax</pageBreakToken>
. Scutum dark brown, scutellum yellow, with six stout setae. Legs brown; hind tibial comb with eight spines; foreleg TR 2.18, midleg TR 2.21, hind leg TR 2.33. Wing length 1.12 mm, width 0.33 mm, CR 0.40; wing membrane hyaline, densely covered with microtrichia, cubital fork at same level of distal portion of second radial cell.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">Abdomen. Brown. Tergite IX nearly trapezoidal with prominent apicolateral processes. Posteromedial margin of sternite IX with elongate, slender projection, gonostylus slender (Figs 3a, 4e). Parameres fused, with median lobe short, thick, lateral lobe directly ventrolaterally (Figs 3b, 4e). Aedeagus complex, median process thick, long, its lateral processes each with curved apex (Figs 3c, 4e).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">
Female (Figs 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="d–e">d-e</normalizedToken>
; 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="f–k">f-k</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">Head. Eyes contiguous. Antennal flagellum (Fig. 4f) brown, without sculpture, flagellomere 13 without apical projection; AR 0.93. Frontal sclerite oval, with long, slender ventral projection (Fig. 4g). Clypeus (Fig. 4h) with seven pairs of setae. Palpus (Fig. 4i) brown; third segment slender, without capitate sensillae, lengths of palpus segments in ratio of 4: 7: 17: 7: 12.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">Thorax. Hind tibial comb with seven spines; foreleg TR 2.00, midleg TR 2.14, hind leg TR 2.16. Wing length 0.82 mm, width 0.34 mm, CR 0.50 (Fig. 4j).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">
Abdomen. Similar to male. Subgenital plate (Figs 3d, 4k) flat, ring-shaped, posterolateral arms sclerotized into darker bands. Spermatheca round (Figs 3e, 4k), strongly pigmented, diameter 53.60 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, neck short, stout, oblique, length 6.20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="140" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">China (Guizhou province Fig. 5).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="140">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="140">
Figure 5. Geographical location of collecting site (inset) of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceratopogonidae" genus="Dasyhelea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dasyhelea alula" order="Diptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="140" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alula">Dasyhelea alula</taxonomicName>
in Guizhou province, China.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>