<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.692.12062" ID-GBIF-Dataset="04e6c6ea-34c4-4729-abe0-df11fa38bdd4" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132786213" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-692-103" ID-ZBK="8E126CF580CE42618E2FA35C31750A1E" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:006909A8-2FEC-4B94-95AF-766C7B128E5F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-692-103" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 692" ModsDocTitle="Discovery of the genus Nipponodipogon Ishikawa in the Oriental region, with description of two new species from China (Hymenoptera, Pompilidae)" checkinTime="1503352893808" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Loktionov, Valery M., Lelej, Arkady S. &amp; Xu, Zai-fu" docDate="2017" docId="6C4EEFE173E333756D5E9A86881E8FAB" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 692: 103-127" docOrigin="ZooKeys 692" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.692.12062" docTitle="Nipponodipogon orientalis Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="006909A8-2FEC-4B94-95AF-766C7B128E5F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="113" masterDocId="211B0310FFDDC7348461FFE6FFA6376B" masterDocTitle="Discovery of the genus Nipponodipogon Ishikawa in the Oriental region, with description of two new species from China (Hymenoptera, Pompilidae)" masterLastPageNumber="127" masterPageNumber="103" pageId="3" pageNumber="106" updateTime="1643582418639" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Discovery of the genus Nipponodipogon Ishikawa in the Oriental region, with description of two new species from China (Hymenoptera, Pompilidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Loktionov, Valery M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lelej, Arkady S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Xu, Zai-fu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>692</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>103</mods:start>
<mods:end>127</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.692.12062</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.692.12062</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-692-103</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">8E126CF580CE42618E2FA35C31750A1E</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8E126CF580CE42618E2FA35C31750A1E</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132786213" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:006909A8-2FEC-4B94-95AF-766C7B128E5F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6C4EEFE173E333756D5E9A86881E8FAB" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="113" pageId="3" pageNumber="106">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="106" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/006909A8-2FEC-4B94-95AF-766C7B128E5F" authority="Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu" class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon orientalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="orientalis">Nipponodipogon orientalis Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="3" pageNumber="106">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1, 2-5, 6-10, 11, 12-17, 18-22
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="106" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">Holotype. CHINA: ♀, Guangdong, Nankunshan, 4-6.VI.2011, Zai-fu Xu, No. 2016001247 (SCAU). Paratypes. CHINA: 2 ♀, with the same data as holotype, No. 2016001227 and 2016001217 (SCAU); 1 ♀, with the same data as holotype, No. 2016001255 (SCAU); 1 ♀, Hainan, Diaoluoshan, 12-13.VII.2010, Hua-yan Chen, No. 2016000370 (SCAU); 1 ♂, Yunnan, Gaoligongshan, 20-21.VII.2006, Zai-fu Xu, No. 2016000480 (IBSS); 1 ♂, Yunnan, Gaoligongshan, 20-21.VII.2006, Zai-fu Xu, No. 2016000479 (SCAU).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="106" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">Female. Mesosoma completely yellow orange (Figs 1, 7). Posterolateral portion of propodeum with strong transverse rugae (Figs 5-7). T1 with long petiole basally (Fig. 6). Outer apicoventral corner of the metafemur produced triangularly (Fig. 8). Male. T1 distinctly petiolate basally (Fig. 15). F3-F11 not produced triangularly beneath, not forming serrated profile. Propodeum matt, with weak dense transverse striae posterolaterally (Fig. 15). Subbasal portion of hypopygium with round sublateral carina (Fig. 21, arrow).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="3" pageNumber="106" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">Female. Body length 6.1-8.0 mm; fore wing length 4.7-6.2 mm. Head and metasoma black; sometimes clypeus along anterior margin brownish; antenna black, except flagellomeres 3-10 muddy yellow ventrally and sometimes scape and pedicel yellowish-brown ventrally; mandible brownish subapically. Mesosoma completely yellow orange (Figs 1, 7). Legs brown with abundant yellowish-brown (Fig. 1) to completely muddy yellowish. Fore wing weakly infuscate or sometimes more or less yellowish, with distinct two fuscous bands (Fig. 9). Hind wing weakly infuscate (Fig. 10).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="106">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon orientalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="orientalis">Nipponodipogon orientalis</taxonomicName>
Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu, sp. n., female, holotype, habitus, lateral view. Scale bar 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="106">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="106">
Figures 2-5. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon orientalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="orientalis">Nipponodipogon orientalis</taxonomicName>
Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu, sp. n., female, paratype. 2 Head and pronotum, dorsal view 3 Head, frontal view 4 Head, lateral view 5 Propodeum, dorsolateral view. Scale bars 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="107" pageId="3" pageNumber="106">
Head and mesosoma matt. Frons, vertex, and mesosoma, except propodeum, finely and densely punctate. Pronotum anteriorly, laterally and collar finely striate and punctate. Mesopleuron with denser punctures. Upper mesopleuron and metapleuron finely 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="107" start="start">and</pageBreakToken>
densely striate. Lateral side of metanotum with several regular oblique striae. Propodeum strongly and densely punctate with fine transverse rugae posteriorly and much stronger rugae posterolaterally (Figs 5-7). Metasoma somewhat polished. T1-T5 with fine punctures; T6 and S6 less polished than other segments, with scattered setiferous pores located on all exposed portion; S1-S5 with somewhat larger punctures than on T1-T5. S1 with several longitudinal rugae baso-medially. Transverse groove on S2 gently arcuate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="107">Body with gray pubescence mostly short, but longer on clypeus, mesopleuron, propodeum posterolaterally and coxae. Body without setae except the following: upper frons sometimes with one long erect setae and a few shorter ones; clypeus with a few long suberect setae anteriorly; coxae and T1 basally with scattered short erect setae; S2-S5 with scattered longer erect setae posteriorly; T6 and S6 with denser long erect pale setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="4" pageNumber="107">
Width of head in frontal view 1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.2×">-1.2x</normalizedToken>
its height. Vertex weakly convex between eye tops (Fig. 3). Upper frons gently convex (Fig. 4). Frons without median line, but sometimes with indistinct elongate concavity medially. Supra-antennal area of frons 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="108" start="start">produced</pageBreakToken>
anteriorly into a frontal ledge overhanging the antennal radicle (Fig. 4). Inner orbits weakly convergent above and subparallel below (Fig. 3). Half of MID 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.4×">-1.4x</normalizedToken>
eye width. Ocelli large, slightly raised; ocellar triangle acute-angled (Fig. 2); POD/OOD=0.8-1.1. Posterior margin of vertex roundly concave (dorsal view) (Fig. 2). Clypeus convex medially with distinct concavity basolaterally; anterolateral corner broadly rounded; anterior margin almost straight or weakly emarginate medially; width 2.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2.9×">-2.9x</normalizedToken>
its length. Apical margin of labrum broadly rounded. Mandible with subapical tooth. Maxillary cardo with two tufts of thin, light brown bristles. Malar space short. Gena strongly narrowing posteriorly (Fig. 2, dorsal view; Fig. 4, lateral view). Antenna short, stout, and thickened toward middle of flagellum; F1-F3 distinctly widening toward apex; apex of apical flagellomere pointed; F1 length 0.95
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.0×">-1.0x</normalizedToken>
F2 length; F1 length 2.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2.4×">-2.4x</normalizedToken>
its width and 0.50
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.65×">-0.65x</normalizedToken>
UID.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="109" pageId="5" pageNumber="108">
Pronotum with anterior declivity flattened, not distinctly differentiated from dorsum; dorsum in dorsal view slightly narrowing anteriorly; shoulder gently rounded; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="109" start="start">juncture</pageBreakToken>
between dorsal and lateral faces narrowly and roundly raised; posterior margin weakly and arcuately emarginate medially. Mesoscutum slightly sloped anteriorly; posterolateral margin not reflexed; parapsidal sulcus finely impressed. Discs of mesoscutellum and metanotum barely raised above level of mesoscutum and propodeum (Fig. 7). Metapostnotum narrow and practically linear, deeply sunken between metanotum and propodeum (Fig. 6). Propodeum evenly convex with flattened posterior declivity not well differentiated from dorsum (Fig. 7).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="109">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="109">
Figures 6-10. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon orientalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="orientalis">Nipponodipogon orientalis</taxonomicName>
Loktionov, Lelej, Xu, sp. n., female, paratype. 6 Mesoscutellum, metanotum, metapostnotum, propodeum and T1, dorsal view 7 Mesosoma, lateral view 8 Metafemur, outer lateral view 9 Fore wing 10 Hind wing. Scale bars 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="109">
Fore wing (Fig. 9) with SMC2 receiving crossvein 1m-cu at almost middle; SMC3 1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.2×">-1.2x</normalizedToken>
longer than SMC2 on vein M, and 0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.7×">-0.7x</normalizedToken>
longer than SMC2 on vein Rs; receiving crossvein 2m-cu at almost middle; crossvein 2rs-m almost straight or sometimes barely curved; crossvein 3rs-m distinctly curved; crossvein cu-a barely postfurcal. Hind wing (Fig. 10). Outer apicoventral corner of metafemur produced triangularly (Fig. 8). Claws symmetrical with large subapical inner tooth. T1 distinctly petiolate (Fig. 6). S6 with a longitudinal median rounded carina posteriorly.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="109">Male. Body length 3.7-4.6 mm; fore wing length 3.5-4.1 mm. Body black; antenna black with scape brown or black ventrally and flagellum weakly brown ventrally; mandible brown subapically; pro- tibia and tarsi brown; spurs of pro- and mesotibia brown, spurs of metatibia dark brown (Fig. 11). Fore wing weakly infuscate, with weak subapical fuscous band (Fig. 16). Hind wing weakly infuscate (Fig. 17).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="109">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="109">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon orientalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="orientalis">Nipponodipogon orientalis</taxonomicName>
Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu, sp. n., male, paratype, habitus, lateral view. Scale bar 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="109">Body mostly punctate and somewhat polished. Frons, discs of pronotum, mesoscutum, mesoscutellum, and metanotum finely and densely punctate. Pronotum laterally polished and indistinctly punctate. Mesopleuron with coarser punctures than frons. Upper mesopleuron striate. Lateral side of metanotum with several regular oblique striae. Metapleuron finely punctate. Propodeum more or less matt, finely and densely punctate with weak dense transverse striae posterolaterally. Metasomal segments finely punctate. S1 with several longitudinal rugae basally. Transverse groove on S2 weak, gently arcuate, not connected medially. S6 with scattered setiferous pores (Fig. 18). Body with gray pubescence mostly short, but longer on lower face, clypeus, propleuron, propodeum posteriorly and mesepisternum. Body without setae except the following: upper frons with one long erect setae; T7 and S6 with long erect brown setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="109">
Width of head in frontal view 1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
its height. Vertex moderately convex between eye tops (Fig. 13). Upper frons gently convex (Fig. 14). Frons without median line, with indistinct elongate concavity medially. Supra-antennal area of frons produced anteriorly into weak frontal ledge overhanging the antennal radicle (Fig. 14). Inner orbits subparallel above and barely convergent below (Fig. 13). Half of MID 1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.6×">-1.6x</normalizedToken>
eye width. Ocelli large, noticeably raised; ocellar triangle right-angled (Fig. 12); POD/OOD=0.75-0.85. Posterior margin of vertex straight (dorsal view) (Fig. 12). Clypeus weakly convex medially; anterolateral corner broadly rounded; anterior margin barely broadly rounded, almost straight medially. Mandible with subapical tooth. Malar space short. Gena narrowing posteriorly (Fig. 12, dorsal view; Fig. 14, lateral view). Antenna shortened; flagellum filiform; flagellomeres indistinctly convex ventrally, not forming triangle projection; apex of apical flagellomere pointed; F1 length 0.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.0×">-1.0x</normalizedToken>
F2 length; F1 length 1.85
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.90×">-1.90x</normalizedToken>
its width and 0.30
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.36×">-0.36x</normalizedToken>
UID.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="110">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="110" start="start">Pronotum</pageBreakToken>
with anterior declivity weakly concave, more differentiated from dorsum than in female; dorsum in dorsal view narrowing anteriorly; shoulder gently rounded; juncture between dorsal and lateral faces roundly raised; posterior margin weakly and arcuately emarginate. Mesoscutum slightly sloped anteriorly; parapsidal sulcus finely impressed. Discs of mesoscutellum and metanotum somewhat more strongly raised above level of mesoscutum and propodeum than in female. Metapostnotum (Fig. 15) longer and not deeply sunken between metanotum and propodeum, as in female; somewhat narrowing in middle; metapostnotum length 0.15
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.25×">-0.25x</normalizedToken>
metanotum length medially. Propodeum evenly convex with posterior declivity not differentiated from dorsum; posterior surface evenly convex.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="110">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="110">
Figures 12-17. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon orientalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="orientalis">Nipponodipogon orientalis</taxonomicName>
Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu, sp. n., male, paratype. 12 Head, dorsal view 13 Head, frontal view 14 Head, lateral view 15 Mesoscutellum, metanotum, metapostnotum, propodeum and T1, dorsal view 16 Fore wing 17 Hind wing. Scale bars 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="7" pageNumber="110">
Fore wing (Fig. 16), hind wing (Fig. 17). Claws symmetrical with large subapical inner tooth. T1 distinctly petiolate; petiole long (Fig. 15). S6 deeply and arcuately emarginate posteriorly; lateral hook small, curved and pointed to apex (Fig. 18). Exposed portion of hypopygium stick form, compressed laterally, narrow (both in lateral and ventral views), 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="111" start="start">weakly</pageBreakToken>
widened apically; subbasal portion extended laterally, with short erected stout spines (Figs 21, 22). Paramere broadly widened basally and narrowing toward apex (lateral view), with long bristles, longer bristle as long as paramere; volsella broad apically (lateral view) (Figs 19, 20).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="113" pageId="9" pageNumber="112" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="112">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="112" start="start">Remarks</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="113" pageId="9" pageNumber="112">
The female of new species is similar to those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon kurilensis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="112" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kurilensis">Nipponodipogon kurilensis</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. sudai" pageId="9" pageNumber="112" rank="species" species="sudai">N. sudai</taxonomicName>
, and 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="9" pageNumber="112" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. by having outer apicoventral corner of metafemur produced triangularly (Fig. 8) and T1 petiolate basally (Fig. 6), but can be separated from all of them in having mesosoma completely yellow orange (Figs 1, 7) (vs completely or mostly black (Figs 23, 29)) and posterolateral portion of propodeum with strong transverse rugae (Figs 5-7) (vs with fine transverse striae or/and punctures (Figs 27-29, 44)). 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="113" start="start">Female</pageBreakToken>
of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. orientalis" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="orientalis">N. orientalis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. differs from that of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. kurilensis" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="kurilensis">N. kurilensis</taxonomicName>
in having T1 with long petiole (Fig. 6) (vs short one in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. kurilensis" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="kurilensis">N. kurilensis</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Shimizu, A" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="22" pageNumber="125" pagination="497 - 520" title="Revision of the Palaearctic brood parasitic genus Nipponodipogon Ishikawa, 1965 of spider wasps (Hymenoptera: Pompilidae: Pepsinae)." url="http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3948.3.6" volume="3948" year="2015">Shimizu et al. 2015</bibRefCitation>
: fig. 3D)); and from that of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. in having crossvein 3rs-m distinctly curved (Fig. 9) and T6 somewhat polished, not shagreened, with distinct scattered setiferous pores (vs crossvein 3rs-m almost straight and T6 matt, shagreened, without distinct setiferous pores in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (Figs 31, 39)).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">
Male of new species is closely related to that of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. by some morphological characters including shape of hypopygium and genitalia, but easily distinguishes in propodeum with fine transverse striae posterolaterally (Fig. 15) (vs propodeum without any striae in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (Fig. 38)); exposed portion of hypopygium narrow in lateral view (Fig. 22) (vs noticeably wider in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (Fig. 43)); subbasal portion of hypopygium in ventral view with round sublateral carina (Fig. 21, arrow) (vs with angulate sublateral carina in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (Fig. 42, arrow)); S6 with setiferous pores posteromedially (Fig. 18) (vs without setiferous pores posteromedially in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. shimizui" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="shimizui">N. shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (Fig. 39)). Male of new species is also similar to that of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. sudai" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="sudai">N. sudai</taxonomicName>
in having petiole on T1 basally (Fig. 15), but can be easily differentiated by having F3-F11 not producing triangularly beneath, not forming serrated profile (vsF3-F11 produced triangularly beneath, forming serrated profile in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. sudai" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="sudai">N. sudai</taxonomicName>
); lateral hook on S6 small, claw-like, curved and pointed to apex (Fig. 18) (vs lateral hook on S6 large, strongly compressed laterally and thin, subtriangular in profile in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. sudai" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="sudai">N. sudai</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 46)); and exposed portion of hypopygium without long erect setae (Figs 21, 22) (vs with long erect setae in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. sudai" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" rank="species" species="sudai">N. sudai</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 48)).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="113">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">
Figures 18-22. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon orientalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="orientalis">Nipponodipogon orientalis</taxonomicName>
Loktionov, Lelej &amp; Xu, sp. n., male, paratype. 18S6, ventral view 19 Genitalia, ventral view 20 Genitalia, lateral view 21 Hypopygium and S7, ventral view 22 Hypopygium and S7, lateral view. Scale bars 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="113" type="sex association">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">Sex association.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">
In spite of the fact that females and males were collected in different locations (two males from Yunnan and five females from Guangdong and Hainan) and have different coloration (mesosoma completely yellow orange in female vs completely black in male), we consider that they are opposite sexes of same species. Male of new species has propodeum with fine transverse striae posterolaterally that correlates with strong transverse rugae on propodeum posteriorly, especially in posterolateral portion in female (vs male without any striae, female with fine transverse striae in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Nipponodipogon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nipponodipogon shimizui" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="shimizui">Nipponodipogon shimizui</taxonomicName>
sp. n.). Such coloration differences in female and male of new species are not exception and occur in widely distributed Palaearctic species 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Pompilidae" genus="Arachnotheutes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Arachnotheutes rufithorax" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="113" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rufithorax">Arachnotheutes rufithorax</taxonomicName>
(Costa, 1881) (
<bibRefCitation author="Loktionov, VM" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="22" pageNumber="125" pagination="1 - 95" title="An annotated catalogue of the spider wasps (Hymenoptera: Pompilidae) of Russia." url="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4280.1.1" volume="4280" year="2017">Loktionov and Lelej 2017</bibRefCitation>
: figs 87, 88).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="113" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">The name of the new species refers to the first record of the genus in the Oriental Region.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="113" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="113">China (Guangdong, Hainan, Yunnan).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>