<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bcdbe5f4-2f0e-4240-8727-64b6c91db94a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886276" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-591-1" ID-ZBK="DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7AD41B89-6EE8-4536-99F3-2D6948D71390" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-591-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 591" ModsDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" checkinTime="1463833188709" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Monckton, Spencer K." docDate="2016" docId="23B92193385C978435FB8788BF8D56B3" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 591: 1-144" docOrigin="ZooKeys 591" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" docTitle="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) katherinae Monckton, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="7AD41B89-6EE8-4536-99F3-2D6948D71390" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="67" masterDocId="FFFED84DD544452EFFC446356171FFFD" masterDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" masterLastPageNumber="144" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="60" pageNumber="61" updateTime="1643603351127" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Monckton, Spencer K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>591</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>144</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-591-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886276" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7AD41B89-6EE8-4536-99F3-2D6948D71390" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/23B92193385C978435FB8788BF8D56B3" lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="60" pageNumber="61">
<subSubSection pageId="60" pageNumber="61" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Colletidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="60" pageNumber="61" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="60" pageNumber="61">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/7AD41B89-6EE8-4536-99F3-2D6948D71390" authority="Monckton" class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) katherinae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="60" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="katherinae" subGenus="Heteroediscelis">Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) katherinae Monckton</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="60" pageNumber="61">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 11A; 13
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
; 18D; 20A; 39
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–J">A-J</normalizedToken>
; 49
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="61" pageNumber="62" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="61" pageNumber="62">
<pageBreakToken pageId="61" pageNumber="62" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="61" pageNumber="62">
Males are diagnosable by the combination of malar space subequal to or longer than clypeal lateral (1
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.1×">-1.1x</normalizedToken>
), the S1 proces apical surface weakly longitudinally concave and in lateral view anterior and posterior margins divergent apically, and the metatibia&gt;2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth with summit of ventral convexity situated at approximately three-quarters tibial length. Females are diagnosable by the combination of protibia yellow on basal half of dorsal surface only and malar space subequal in length to the clypeal lateral (0.95
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.05×">-1.05x</normalizedToken>
). Females may be confused with 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola randolphi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="61" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="randolphi">Chilicola randolphi</taxonomicName>
or 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola vina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="61" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vina">Chilicola vina</taxonomicName>
, but can be distinguished from the former by the dark brown metasoma and from the latter by the shorter malar space (≥1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as clypeal lateral in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola vina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="61" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vina">Chilicola vina</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="66" pageId="61" pageNumber="62" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="61" pageNumber="62">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="61" pageNumber="62">Male (Holotype). Length 6.4mm, forewing length 3.9mm, head width 1.3mm, thorax width 1.4mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.15mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="61" pageNumber="62">Colouration: Black-brown, following parts yellow: labrum except apical margin yellow-brown; lower paraocular area to below transverse portion of epistomal suture medially, extending ~0.5OD further laterally; apicoventral spot on scape; apicoventral surface of pedicel; protrochanter apical rim posteriorly; narrow apical ring on profemur; dorsal surface of protibia; apical half of prodistitarsus; apicodorsal rim of mesofemur; basidorsal spot on mesotibia; apical lamina of metatibia; anterior spot on tegula. Following parts yellow-brown: median line and medial third of apical margin on clypeus, apex dark laterad; ventral surface of antennal flagellomeres F1-F10, narrowing basally on F1; mesobasitarsus ventrally; narrow apical ring on metafemur, expect brown dorsally. Following parts brown: ventral surface of antennal flagellomere F11; small apicodorsal spot on mesotibia; apical one-third of mesodistitarsus. Metasoma black, T1-T7 marginal zones translucent yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="63" lastPageNumber="64" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<pageBreakToken pageId="62" pageNumber="63" start="start">Pubescence</pageBreakToken>
: White hairs generally short (0.5OD) and sparse, not especially plumose; on lower paraocular area and around antennal base moderately long and moderately dense (1OD); genal beard long and moderately dense (0.5-2OD) longest at midlength; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="63" pageNumber="64" start="start">discs</pageBreakToken>
of mesoscutum, scutellum, and metanotum mostly bare, few short hairs (0.5OD), longer and denser toward lateral margin as follows: mesoscutum (0.5-1OD), scutellum (1-1.5OD) also on posterior margin, longest posteromedially, metanotum (≤2OD); propodeal hairs moderately long and dense dorsolaterally (0.5-1.5OD); T1-T2 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD), T3 apicolateral hair band sparse, not tomentose; S2 hairs long and dense (2OD basolaterad, 1.5OD distilaterad, shorter mesad).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Surface sculpture: Microsculpture imbricate, integument generally dull; punctures generally small and deep. Clypeus moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); supraclypeal area moderately densely and irregularly punctate (i=1-3d) densely punctate toward lateral margin (i≤d); lower paraocular area densely punctate (i=d); frontal area very densely punctate (i≤0.5d), densely punctate around ocelli (i≤d); ocellocular space moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); vertexal area rugose and densely punctate (i≤d); scape shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) densely punctate apicoventrally (i≤d); genal area weakly imbricate and moderately sparsely punctate (i=1-2d); hypostomal area weakly imbricate to glossy apically, shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i≥2d); pronotum densely punctate (i=0.5-1d), lateral surface coarsely imbricate; mesoscutum densely punctate (i≤d); scutellum moderately densely punctate (i=0.5-2d) punctures crowded around median (i≥2d); mesepisternum irregularly punctate, sparse below scrobe (i=1-3d), sparser anterior of episternal groove (i≥2d), impunctate just dorsad of scrobe, otherwise moderately dense on hypoepimeral area (i=1-2d); metanotum moderately densely punctate (i≤2d) punctures crowded around median and anteriorly (i≤d); metepisternum densely punctate (i≤d) distinctly longitudinally striate anterodorsally; metapostnotum rugose; propodeum coarsely imbricate, rugulose posteriorly, moderately densely punctate throughout (i=1-2d); T1 moderately densely punctate; T2-T6 coarsely imbricate; T2-T5 moderately densely punctate, basal depressed area more coarsely microsculptured; T6-T7 moderately sparsely punctate (i=1-3d); marginal zones of terga weakly imbricate and shiny, minutely punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="64" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
Structure: Labrum 2.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (25:10); malar space ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as clypeal lateral (9:8); LOT at level of anterior tentorial pits; clypeus ~1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width in frontal view (37:32) extending for approximately half its length beyond LOT; median longitudinal groove present on clypeus; subantennal sutures ~1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as the shortest distance between them (16:13); IAD ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
AOD (12.5:8.5); scape 2.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (25:10); pedicel as long as wide (9:9); F1 slightly shorter than wide (8.5:9); F2 ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F1 and shorter than F3 (F2:F3 - 12.5:15); UOD ~1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 53:58:39); frontal line carinate in lower two-fifths, flat just below median ocellus for a length of ~0.5OD, otherwise roughly defined; MOC subequal to width of head (93:94); OOC ~0.67
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (13:19); genal area ~0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as compound eye in lateral view (18:29); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 66:23:13:17; probasitarsus ~4.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (27:6.5); length of prodistitarsus subequal to that of preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V - 9:7:6:21); metafemur ~2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (71:36); summit of metatibial ventral convexity at approximately two-thirds tibial length; metatibia ~2.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as 
<pageBreakToken pageId="64" pageNumber="65" start="start">long</pageBreakToken>
as maximum depth (60:28); in apical view apical lamina of metatibia short and thick, length ~0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
OD (6.5:11); ventral metatibial carina angled ventrad, rounded inflection near midpoint, posterior carina absent basally and originating at midpoint of ventral carina; metabasitarsus ~5.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (46:9); S1 process apical surface longitudinally concave, in lateral view anterior and posterior margins divergent apically, apex appearing anteriorly bent. S7 apodemal arm sclerotized margin recurved mesad, dividing membranous portion of arm; ventral lobe ~0.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as broad as basal attached length; dorsal lobe strap-like, subparallel-sided and somewhat anteriorly curved, with basal tuft of long setae and a short apical row, midlength bare. S8 lateral process ~1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long, anteromedial sclerotized margin irregular with sclerotized spot disjunct from margin (but see variation below). Gonobase apicoventral truncate process biconvex and distinctly notched by ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of one convexity.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Female (Allotype). Length 5.5mm, forewing length 3.4mm, head width 1.2mm, thorax width 1.4mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.12mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Colouration: Black to black-brown except as follows: mandible with brown basal spot, apical half yellow-orange except apex black. Following parts brown: pedicel, F1 and F2, on apicoventral margins; apicodorsal rim of metafemur; protrochanter apical rim posteriorly; apical one-third of mesodistitarsus; narrow apical ring on metafemur; large basidorsal spot on metatibia. Following parts yellow: dorsal surface of protibia in basal half; apical half of prodistitarsus; basidorsal spot on mesotibia; faint anterior spot on tegula. Ventral surface of F3-F10 yellow-brown, narrowing basally on F3. Metasoma black, T1-T5 marginal zone translucent yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Pubescence: As in male except as follows: genal beard sparse (0.5-2OD); mesoscutal hairs short and sparse (≤0.5OD) denser toward lateral margin; discs of scutellum and metanotum mostly bare, few short hairs (0.5OD), longer and denser toward lateral and posterior margins of scutellum (0.5-1.5OD) longest posteromedially, and toward lateral margin of metanotum (≤2OD); propodeal hairs moderately long and dense dorsolaterally (0.5-1.5OD); scopae on metafemur and metatibia (1-1.5OD); T1-T2 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD), T3 apicolateral hair band sparse, not tomentose; S1 hairs long and moderately dense (≤2.5OD); S2 scopal hairs (1-2.5OD).</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="66" pageId="64" pageNumber="65">
Surface sculpture: As in male except as follows: clypeus moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) except sparsely punctate medially (i=2-3d); supraclypeal area moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) more densely punctate laterally (i≤d); frontal area moderately densely punctate (i≤2d), moderately densely punctate around ocelli (i=1-2d); ocellocular space moderately densely punctate adjacent to compound eye (i=1-2d) becoming impunctate adjacent to lateral ocellus; vertexal area densely punctate (i≤d); scape shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); genal area imbricate and moderately densely punctate; hypostomal area imbricate and moderately sparsely punctate (i≥2d); mesoscutum and scutellum densely punctate (i≤d), except mesoscutum moderately densely punctate laterally (i=1-2d) and scutellar punctures crowded on median (i=0.5d); mesepisternum irregularly punctate, sparse below scrobe (i=1-3d), sparser anterior of episternal groove (i≥3d), impunctate just dorsad of scrobe, otherwise moderately sparse on hypoepimeral area (i=0.5-3d); metanotum moderately densely punc 
<pageBreakToken pageId="65" pageNumber="66" start="start">tate</pageBreakToken>
(i=0.5-2d); metepisternum densely punctate (i≤d) weakly striate anterodorsally; metapostnotum rugose, fewer transverse lineations posteriorly; propodeum coarsely imbricate and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); T1-T5 punctures small; T1 &amp; T6 moderately sparsely punctate (i=1-3d); T2-T3 moderately densely punctate (i≤2d); T4-T5 sparsely punctate (i≥3d).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
Structure: Labrum ~2.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (28:11); malar space slightly longer than clypeal lateral (9.5:9); LOT at level of anterior tentorial pits; clypeus 1.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width in frontal view (40:32) extending for approximately half its length beyond LOT; clypeus without median longitudinal groove; subantennal sutures ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as the shortest distance between them (16:15); IAD ~1.33
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
AOD (13.5:10); scape ~3.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (27:8.5); pedicel longer than wide (9:8); F1 as long as wide (7.5:7.5); F2 shorter than F1 and shorter than F3 (F2:F3 - 5:6); UOD ~1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.05
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 54:56:41); frontal line carinate between antennal bases for a length of ~1.5OD, flat just below median ocellus for a length of ~1OD, otherwise roughly defined; MOC ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as width of head (98:88); OOC ~0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (13:21); genal area ~0.55
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as eye in lateral view (16:29); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 66:24:13:16; probasitarsus ~3.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (25:8); length of prodistitarsus subequal to that of preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V - 6:6:5:16); metafemur ~3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (53:18); metatibia ~4.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (67:16); metabasitarsus 4.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (41:10).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
Figure 39. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola katherinae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="katherinae">Chilicola katherinae</taxonomicName>
: A male habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm B male head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm C female habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm D female head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm E male metatibia, posterior view, scale bar 0.25 mm F male S1 process, lateral view, scale bar 0.25 mm G male S1 process, apical view, scale bar 0.25 mm H male S7, scale bar 0.25 mm I male S8, scale bar 0.25 mm J male genital capsule, scale bar 0.25 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="65" pageNumber="66" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Type material</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
(5 males &amp; 17 females): Holotype (male): Region VII, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Río">Rio</normalizedToken>
Teno nr. Estero Pichuante, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-35.0863">S 35.0863°</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.4971">W 70.4971°</geoCoordinate>
, 1457m, 19.ii.2015, S. Monckton, CCDB-22014 E01, parasitized (but see comments) (PCYU); Allotype (female): same data as holotype (PCYU); Paratypes: Region VII: one female, same locality as holotype, 28.ii-21.iii.2013, S. Monckton &amp; J. Postlethwaite, pan trap, parasitized (PCYU); one female, same locality as holotype, 2.iii.2015, S.Monckton (PCYU); one female, same locality as holotype, 2.iii.2015, S. Monckton (CTMI); one female, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Río">Rio</normalizedToken>
Teno, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-35.04417">S35.04417°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-70.59093">W70.59093°</geoCoordinate>
, 1241m, 22.ii.2016, L. Packer (PCYU); two females, E of Los 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Queñes">Quenes</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-35.028">S 35.028°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.713">W 70.713°</geoCoordinate>
, 817m, 1.i.2013, L. Packer &amp; R. Smith, CCDB-19991 C07, CCDB-19991 C08 (PCYU); four males, Los 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Queñes">Quenes</normalizedToken>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-35.001">S 35.001°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-70.816">W 70.816°</geoCoordinate>
, 707m, 31.x.1983, J. Magunacelaya (PUCV); one female, same locality and date, C. Tobar (PUCV); four females, same locality and date, F. Rodriguez (BBSL); Region VIII: two females, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ñuble">Nuble</normalizedToken>
: Shangrila (near Las Trancas), 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.876">S 36.876°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-71.468">W 71.468°</geoCoordinate>
, 1549m, 13-15.xii.1983, Luis E. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH); one female, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ñuble">Nuble</normalizedToken>
: Shangri-la, Las Trancas, SE of Recinto, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.876">S 36.876°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-71.468">W 71.468°</geoCoordinate>
, 1549m, 13-17.xii., Luis E. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH); one female, Las Trancas, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.911">S 36.911°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="555" value="-71.48">W 71.48°</geoCoordinate>
, 1250m, 10.xi.1976, H. Toro (AMNH); one female, Las Cabras, mts. in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Chillán">Chillan</normalizedToken>
area, S 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Chillán">Chillan</normalizedToken>
Volcano, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ñuble">Nuble</normalizedToken>
Prov., 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.918">S 36.918°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-71.429">W 71.429°</geoCoordinate>
, 1500m, 31.vi.1963, Luis E. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="66" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
Paratype males differ in colour from the holotype as follows: inverted T shape on clypeus yellow; lower paraocular maculation extending above transverse portion of epistomal suture; wide apical ring on profemur yellow; apical half of prodistitarsus yellow-brown; narrow basal ring and large apicodorsal spot on mesotibia yellow; wide 
<pageBreakToken pageId="66" pageNumber="67" start="start">basal</pageBreakToken>
and apical rings on metatibia yellow, expect dark apicodorsally; basal half of metabasitarsus yellow ventrally. Additionally, some females have a yellow or yellow-brown basal spot on the mandible, the apicoventral margin of F1 and F2 brown or yellow-brown, and/or a yellow-brown or brown spot on the lower paraocular area below the anterior tentorial pit. The male S8 anteromedial sclerotized margin varies in form among paratypes: C.kate.003 has a sclerotized spot disjunct from the margin as in the holotype (easily distinguished only on the righthand lateral process), C.kate.004 has a distinct convex incursion which appears swollen, and C.kate.005 has the margin only slightly widened and weakly convex; all three were collected from Los 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Queñes">Quenes</normalizedToken>
on the same date.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="66" pageNumber="67" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">
Southern Andean Cordillera, from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Río">Rio</normalizedToken>
Teno near Estero Pichuante west to Los 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Queñes">Quenes</normalizedToken>
(Region VII) and south to Valle Las Trancas (Region VIII); 707-1549m a.s.l.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="66" pageNumber="67" type="ecology">
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">Ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">Recorded October to March and June.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="66" pageNumber="67" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">
The specific epithet honours Katie 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D’Angelo">D'Angelo</normalizedToken>
, whose support, love, and encouragement were vital to the completion of this work. It is formed in the genitive singular case.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="66" pageNumber="67" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="66" pageNumber="67">The holotype is parasitized, with a visible female strepsipteran protruding from beneath T4. In order to verify that its morphology was not altered by parasitism, the holotype was thoroughly compared to the male paratypes for differences in colouration, pubescence, surface sculpture and structure; only colouration differed appreciably from the paratypes and these differences are noted in the variation section above. One female paratype (C.kate.007) from the same locality as the holotype is also parasitized, with two female strepsipterans protruding from beneath T4.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>