<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287422" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a79bfa9b-f103-4186-9d1f-add9ef6b2b3a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116822" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287422" ModsDocAuthor=" &amp; Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota" ModsDocDate="1936" ModsDocID="3011" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf" ModsDocTitle="The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1" checkinTime="1258815363179" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota" docDate="1936" docId="3ECE62D02E63BB0E3661C0F57371014C" docLanguage="en" docName="3011_tx.xml" docOrigin="Revista de Entomologia 7" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf" docTitle="Apterostigma ierense Weber, 1936, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="388" masterDocId="62511D09FB353213B214D7BBDF9210C0" masterDocTitle="The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1" masterLastPageNumber="409" masterPageNumber="378" pageNumber="387" updateTime="1645821295722" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revista de Entomologia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1936</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>7</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>378</mods:start>
<mods:end>409</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="">3011</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287422" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116822" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287422" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:3ECE62D02E63BB0E3661C0F57371014C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3ECE62D02E63BB0E3661C0F57371014C" lastPageNumber="388" pageNumber="387">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="387">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:25906" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Apterostigma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Apterostigma ierense Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="387" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ierense">Apterostigma ierense</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Fig. 4)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="387">Worker: Length 2.4-2.7 mm. - Head, excluding mandibles, 1.6 times as long as wide between the eyes. Neck short but distinct. Occipital margin impressed by broad groove, with parallel sides, which is a continuation of frontal area; occipital corners more angular than in many species of the genus. Sides of head sub-parallel, clypeal margin broadly convex. Frontal lobes semi-circular, slightly reflexed. Eyes convex, 1/5 in diameter the length of head without mandibles. Antennal scapes moderately stout, slightly bent distally, surpassing occipital margin by a distance equal to their distal diameter. Joints 2-9 of funiculus much broader than long; terminal joint longer than joints 5-9 taken together.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="387">Thorax in profile as illustrated (Fig. 4). Anterior margin of pronotum extended as two lobes. Mesonotum with a pair of median carinae of irregular height, produced posteriorly on declivity as a pair of lobes. Basal surface of epinotum with a pair of high, acute carinae. Dorsal surface of petiole nearly flat, with slightly raised and angular sides. Petiole 1/2 as wide as postpetiole. Postpetiole from above much broader behind, with rounded sides and dorso-medial impression. Gaster feebly marginate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="387">Opaque, coarsely punctate. - Pilosity abundant, of gray appressed hairs and finer, sparser pubescence. - Dark, red-brown, appendages paler.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="387">Female (dealate): Length 2.9 mm. - Resembling the worker with the usual sexual differences. The scutellum is bituberculate behind. Declivous surface of epinotum is carinate on each side. Petiole and postpetiole are impressed on dorsal surface and the gaster is distinctly marginate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="388" pageNumber="387">
Male: Length 2.6-3.1 mm. -' Head, with mandibles but excluding eyes, roughly triangular with angularly convex occipital margin; neck distinct, cylindrical. Occipital corners obtusely angulate. Anterior clypeal margin extended in an obtuse 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="388">angle</pageStartToken>
. Mandibles triangular, with edentate straight cutting- margin. Frontal lobes large, auriculate, almost vertical. Eyes hemispherical, occupying slightly more than 1/2 of sides. Antennal scapes stout, nearly straight, exceeding occipital angles by a distance less than their narrowest diameter. All but first joint of funiculus distinctly longer than broad, terminal joint as long as next two joints taken together.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="388">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="388">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="388">Pronotum</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
extended as a bi-lobed structure as in worker. Mesonotum with a pair of longitudinal carinae. Scutellum produced posteriorly as a pair of converging tubercles. Epinotum with low tubercles. Pedicel, in profile, evenly rounded; petiole appreciably longer than postpetiole but distinctly lower. Gaster very feebly marginate. Legs long and slender. Wings infuscated with margins of veins and an antero-distal blotch brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="388">Opaque, coarsely and sparsely punctate. - Pilosity abundant, of appressed gray hairs and finer and sparser pubescence. - Red-brown but paler than in worker.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="388">Described from a colony consisting of males and workers taken by myself May 28, 1936, near the Maracas Waterfall of the Maracas Valley, Northern Range (Type colony), a single worker taken July 12, 1935, in the foothills north of Tunapuna, and a dealate female with three workers taken July 24, 1935 in the latter locality, Trinidad, B. W. I. The fungus garden of the colony with males was 20 mm. in diameter, cellular, and without an enveloping mesh of mycelia. The nest was under leaf mold in a steep-sided heavily forested ravine. The colony with female had a fungus garden of ordinary appearance consisting of small pellets and slivers of woody plants under debris of the forest floor.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="388">
This species resembles 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:25910" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Apterostigma" genus.completionEvidence="missing" genus.completionRound="1" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Apterostigma mayri Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="388" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mayri">mayri</taxonomicName>
, which I have taken in neighboring valleys, in size but differs in strongly carinate thorax, coarse punctation, and somewhat paler color.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="etymology">
<paragraph pageNumber="388">The poetic name for Trinidad is lere, land of the humming bird.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>