<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9ff557b9-e220-41a4-84b7-eb1ac4ae2fcb" ModsDocID="21380" checkinTime="1243372374881" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Schatz, G. E., Lowry, P. P. &amp; Wolf, A. - E." docDate="2001" docId="CBB644D9E96963F2C681383D4C815456" docLanguage="en" docName="21380" docOrigin="Adansonia 23" docSource="http://www.mnhn.fr/publication/adanson/a01n2a1.pdf" docTitle="Leptolaena abrahamii Schatz, Lowry &amp; Wolf, 2001, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageNumber="177" masterDocId="2F51780DD7A081814C7B519960B5F62B" masterDocTitle="Endemic families of Madagascar. VII. A synoptic revision of Leptolaena Thouars sensu stricto (Sarcolaenaceaea)." masterLastPageNumber="189" masterPageNumber="171" pageNumber="175" updateTime="1569525776785" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Endemic families of Madagascar. VII. A synoptic revision of Leptolaena Thouars sensu stricto (Sarcolaenaceaea).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Schatz, G. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lowry, P. P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wolf, A. - E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Adansonia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2001</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>23</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>171</mods:start>
<mods:end>189</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.mnhn.fr/publication/adanson/a01n2a1.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">21380</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:CBB644D9E96963F2C681383D4C815456" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CBB644D9E96963F2C681383D4C815456">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="175">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="175">1</pageStartToken>
. 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="175" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="abrahamii">Leptolaena abrahamii G. E. Schatz &amp; Lowry</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="175">Haec species a congeneris ad Leptolaenam sensu stricto pertinentibus foliis glabris anguste ovatis falcatis inaequilateralibus in sicco atrorubentibus, sepalis dentes involucrales aequantibus veleos &lt;0.5 mm excedentibus distinguitur.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="175">TYPUS.Miller, Bradford, Rakotonasolo &amp; Randrianasolo 8746, Madagascar, Prov. Toamasina, forest N of Andasibe, along railroad tracks, 18° 56 ' S, 48° 25 ' E, 860 m, 20 Oct. 1996, fl. (holo-, MO!; iso-, P!, TAN!).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="175">Shrubs to trees (1 -) 4 - 15 m tall, trunk to 72 cm dbh, stems short tomentose. Leaves chartaceous, narrowly ovate, strongly falcate, 2.5 - 4.5 (- 5.5) X 1.3 - 2.5 cm, reduced in the inflorescence, glabrous, usually drying reddish black above, dark brown below, base broadly acute to ovate, margins minutely thickened and usually somewhat revolute, apex long acuminate to subcaudate, venation brochidodromous, distinct, especially below, secondary veins (12 -) 14 - 22 per side, midrib slightly raised above, distinctly below; petiole 3 - 4 mm long, 0.5 - 0.8 mm diam., narrowly canaliculate, sparsely puberulous, stipules caducous, scars evident. Inflorescence terminal, corymbose, c. 20 - 40 flowered, axes with minute stellate indumentum often interspersed with scattered appressed trichomes to 0.3 mm long; peduncle 1 - 1.5 mm long, involucre ellipsoid in bud, urceolate to narrowly cupulate at anthesis, 3.5 - 4 mm tall, 3 - 3.3 mm in diam., densely ferruginous stellate, apical margin with 6 - 7 subequal triangular teeth 0.5 - 1.2 mm tall, 0.5 - 1.5 mm broad at the base; sepals obovate, 4 X 2.5 mm, exserted to a height equal to the involucre teeth or exceeding them by no more than 0.5 mm, densely white hirsute outside, glabrous inside; petals narrowly elliptic, 8 - 9 X 1.8 - 2.2 mm, pale yellow, sparsely sericeous outside, exserted 5 - 6 mm beyond involucre teeth at anthesis; stamens 8 - 10, free to the base, filament c. 5 mm long, anther horseshoe shaped, 0.8 mm tall; ovary ovoid, densely light brown tomentose, style slender, exserted, 5 - 6 mm long, stigma hemispherical, crateriform, with 3 lobes, c. 2 mm across. Fruit ovoid to ellipsoid, 4 - 5 mm tall, 2.5 - 3.5 mm diam., irregularly longitudinally channeled, glabrous, entirely enclosed within the persistent sepals and involucre.Fig. 1.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="175">
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="175" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="abrahamii">Leptolaena abrahamii</taxonomicName>
is a shrub to mediumsized tree that occurs in mid-elevation humid forest from Analamazaotra-Perinet RS and around Moramanga NNE to Zahamena RNI, with populations also recorded farther S at Ampasinambo and Ranomafana PN (Fig. 2). It can be recognized by its glabrous, narrowly ovate, falcate leaves with a distinctly acuminate to cuspidate apex, which usually dry reddish black, and its sepals that are equal to the involucre teeth or exceed them by less than 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="etymology">
<paragraph pageNumber="175">
Etymology.The species epithet honors Jean Prosper Abraham, one of Madagascar's most distinguished forestry agents who was stationed for much of his career at Moramanga and Perinet, where he collected material of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="175" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="abrahamii">Leptolaena abrahamii</taxonomicName>
(Service Forestier 21955).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="175">Vernacular names.Amaninombilahy, Anjananjana, Fotona, Voandrozana.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageNumber="175">
Conservation status.With an extent of occurrence &lt;20,000 km 2 and five sub-populations, three of which occur within protected areas, 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="175" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="abrahamii">L. abrahamii</taxonomicName>
is assigned a preliminary status of Vulnerable (VU).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="177" pageNumber="175">PARATYPES.MADAGASCAR, Prov. Fianarantsoa: Service Forestier 13718, Sahamaizina, Ampasinambo, Nosy Varika, [20° 31 ' S, 48° 00 ' E], 18 Jan. 1955, y. fr., fr. (P); Service Forestier 14241, Ranovao, Ranomafana PN, [21° 18 ' S, 47° 38 ' 30 &quot; E], 13 June 1955, bud, fl., y. fr. (P, TEF). Prov. Toamasina: Cours 1206, Nonokambo, [17° 44 ' S, 48° 44 ' E], 950 m, Nov. 1938, bud, fl., y. fr. (P); Cours 4230, Bemainty a Androndramanitra [18° 00 ' S, 48° 47 ' E], 800 - 850 m, 9 Mar. 1951, fr. (MO, P); Dequaire 27840, Zahamena RNI, [17° 38 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 50 ' E], fl., y. fr. (P); Herb. Inst. Sci. Madag. 3773, Beravina, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 1 June 1951, bud (P, TAN); Herb. Inst. Sci. Madag. 4230 [= Cours 4230], Bemainty a Androndramanitra [18° 00 ' S, 48° 47 ' E], 800 - 850 m, 9 Mar. 1951, fr. (TAN); Herb. Jard. Bot. Tananarive 2844, Sihanaka, 21 Aug. 1937, bud (P); Mabberley 813, 3 km SE of Perinet, AnalamazaotraPerinet RS, 18° 55 ' S, 48° 25 ' E, 850 - 900 m, 29 - 30 Mar. 1971, ster. (K, TAN); Mission Schedl 37, Betsatsa, pres Perinet, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S,48° 26 ' E], 17 Nov. 1952, ster. (TAN); McPherson 17523, Ambatovy, 18° 50 ' 54 &quot; S, 48° 17 ' 56 &quot; E, 1000 m, 1 Mar. 1998, fr. (MO, P, TAN); Morat 3218, Ambatovy, [18° 49 ' S, 48° 18 ' E], May 1969, bud (MO, P, TAN); Perrier de la Bathie 5336, AnalamazaotraPerinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 800 m, fr. (K); Reserves Naturelles 15, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 30 Oct. 1936, fl. (MO, P); Reserves Naturelles 1587, Sahamalaza, Manakambanihy-Est, Zahamena RNI, [17° 38 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 50 ' E], 12 Nov. 1948, bud, fl., y. fr. (P); Reserves Naturelles 3169, Sahatavy, Zahamena RNI, [17° 38 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 50 ' E], 14 Sep. 1951, bud (MO, P, TAN); Reserves Naturelles 10953, same locality, 12 June 1960, bud, fl., (P, TEF); Reserves Naturelles 12684, Sahamalaza, Zahamena RNI, [17° 38 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 50 ' E], 28 Dec. 1963, fr. (TEF); Schatz &amp; Rabenantoandro 3991, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, 18° 55 ' 58 &quot; S, 48° 25 ' 16 &quot; E, 16 Mar. 2000, ster. (MO); Schatz &amp; Rabenantoandro 3993, 0.5 km E of Andasibe, 18° 55 ' 11 &quot; S, 48° 25 ' 17 &quot; E, 16 Mar. 2000, fr. (G, K, MO, P, TEF); Service Forestier 3497, Masse (= AmpasimpotsyGara), Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 58 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 21 ' E], 26 Apr. 1951, bud (P, TAN, TEF); Service Forestier 3773, Beravina, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, 1 June 1951, bud, fl. (P, TAN, TEF); Service Forestier 5070, Boqueton Abehovana (Piste MoramangaFarizana), [19° 05 ' S, 48° 15 ' E], 14 Apr. 1952, bud (P, TEF); Service Forestier 6242, Antsahatsaka, Beravina, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 58 ' S, 48° 16 ' 30 &quot; E], 5 Nov. 1952, fl. (MO, P, TEF); Service Forestier 7509, Sahamamy, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 21 Aug. 1953, bud (P, TEF); Service Forestier 7564, Sahamaloto, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 24 Jan. 1953, fl. (TEF); Service Forestier 10348, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 8 June 1954, bud (MO, P, TEF); Service Forestier 14959, km 2, Perinet, AnalamazaotraPerinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 27 Feb. 1955, bud (P, TEF); Service Forestier 17932, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 800 m, 4 Apr. 1958, bud (P, TEF); Service Forestier 21244, same locality, 26 July 1962, ster. (MO, P); Service Forestier 21278, 21279, 21280, 21281, 21282, same locality, 9 Nov. 1962, ster. (MO, P); Service Forestier 21898, Sandrangato FC, [19° 06 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 14 ' 30 &quot; E], 900 m, 29 Oct. 1964, bud (MO, P, TEF); Service Forestier 21955, Sandrangato FC, pres Toby, PK 27 route d'Anosibe An'ala, [19° 06 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 14 ' 30 &quot; E], c. 900 m, 29 Oct. 1964, bud, fl., y. fr. (MO, P, TEF); Service Forestier 25441, Sandrangato FC, [19° 06 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 14 ' 30 &quot; E], 900 m, 29 Oct. 1964, fl. (MO, P, TEF); Service Forestier 26096, Sahatsaora (= Sahatsara), Zahamena RNI, [17° 38 ' 30 &quot; S, 48° 50 ' E], 19 July 1966, bud (P, TEF); Service Forestier 26927, Nangaranana (= Nagarana), Canton Marovoay, [18° 44 ' S, 48° 22 ' E], Feb. 1970, bud (P, TEF); Service Forestier 26968, same locality and date, fr. (P, TEF); Service Forestier 105 - B-R- 172, Ambodivoasary, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 14 Mar. 1952, ster. (P, TEF); Service Forestier 124 - B-R- 172, Menalamba, near Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 52 ' S, 48° 22 ' 30 &quot; E], 9 Apr. 1952, ster. (TEF); Thouvenot 12, AnalamazaotraPerinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 1919, bud, fl., y. fr. (K, P); Viguier 851, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS, [18° 56 ' S, 48° 26 ' E], 1000 m, 21 Oct. 1912, bud, fl, y. fr. (MO, P).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="multiple">
<caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="176">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="176">Fig</pageStartToken>
. 1.
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="176" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="abrahamii">Leptolaena abrahamii</taxonomicName>
: A, flowering branch; B, leaf (adaxial surface); C, leaf (abaxial surface); D, flower; E, flower with petals removed. (A-C, Miller et al. 8746; D-E, Reserves Naturelles 15).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="177">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="177">Fig</pageStartToken>
. 2.Distributions of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="177" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Leptolaena</taxonomicName>
, mapped on the bioclimatic zones of Madagascar (after Cornet 1974; see Schatz 2000). 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="177" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="abrahamii">L. abrahamii</taxonomicName>
(&amp; # 9650;), 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="177" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="delphinensis">L. delphinensis</taxonomicName>
(&amp; # 9733;), 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="177" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="multiflora">L. multiflora</taxonomicName>
(#).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>