<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a503b11a-2446-4eb1-8c52-0be37806a642" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051543" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-387-33" ID-ZBK="462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:25C70887-9B54-4386-BE3E-83DC809D5458" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-387-33" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 387" ModsDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" checkinTime="1451246192135" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan F. &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2014" docId="B3070B96B391F6C8881346A8CFDE89A3" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 387: 33-49" docOrigin="ZooKeys 387" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827" docTitle="Cymatodera lineata Burke, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="25C70887-9B54-4386-BE3E-83DC809D5458" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="48" masterDocId="FFBDFF91FFAAFF8DFFBA9E66E77FFFFD" masterDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" masterLastPageNumber="49" masterPageNumber="33" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" updateTime="1643670665773" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burke, Alan F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>387</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>33</mods:start>
<mods:end>49</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-387-33</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051543" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:25C70887-9B54-4386-BE3E-83DC809D5458" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B3070B96B391F6C8881346A8CFDE89A3" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/25C70887-9B54-4386-BE3E-83DC809D5458" authority="Burke" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera lineata" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lineata">Cymatodera lineata Burke</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="12" pageNumber="45">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 4, 9, 14, 22, 23
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
Holotype: male, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="México">Mexico</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Michoacán">Michoacan</normalizedToken>
, km 23 carretera Morelia - 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pátzcuaro">Patzcuaro</normalizedToken>
, 2000 m, 26-V-1988, A. Cadena and L. Cervantes, printed red label, holotype 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="46" start="start">deposited</pageBreakToken>
in CNCI. Paratype: 1 female: Mexico, Durango, 26 miles W Durango, 13-VII-1974, beating oak, collector unknown (WFBM).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="46" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">
The distinctive dark, longitudinal fasciae on the elytral ground, unique among all 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Cymatodera</taxonomicName>
species, serve to separate 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera lineata" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lineata">Cymatodera lineata</taxonomicName>
from those species with a similar metathorax and anterior elytral margin.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="13" pageNumber="46" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Holotype. Moderately long, slender, posterior wings absent, TL = 9.9 mm. Color: Head, except gular region and pronotum, fuscous; antennae, mouthparts, gular region, prosternum, mesosternum and abdomen, except anterior portion of first visible ventrite, testaceous; legs, metasternum and anterior portion of first visible ventrite brown. Each elytron adorned with five longitudinal, moderately regular, fuscous fasciae; fasciae becoming paler and narrower toward epipleuron; fasciae 2-4 not reaching elytral apex; first and fifth fasciae interconnected at posterior portion of elytra, reaching apex (Fig. 4).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Head: HL = 1.3 mm, HW = 2.25 mm, length to width ratio of holotype 0.58. Measured across eyes conspicuously wider than pronotum; surface rugose; moderately, coarsely punctate; clothed with a set of intermixed moderately long, recumbent and semirecumbent setae; frons inconspicuously bi-impressed; eyes small, subsinuate, taller than wide, feebly bulging laterally, separated by approximately 3.2 eye widths. Antennae extending to base of elytra; third antennomere slightly longer than second antennomere; antennomeres 3-5 subequal in length; sixth antennomere slightly shorter than fifth antennomere; antennomeres 6-10 subequal in length; antennomeres 2-4 subcylindrical; antennomeres 5-10 very feebly serrate; last antennomere subacuminate, about the same length as tenth antennomere (Fig. 9).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Thorax: PL = 2.55 mm, PW = 1.8 mm; length to width ratio of holotype 1.42 mm. Pronotum somewhat elongate; widest at middle, middle slightly wider than anterior margin; sides constricted subapically, more strongly constricted behind middle; disc feebly convex; moderately impressed in front of middle; subbasal tumescences pronounced; surface moderately clothed with short, semirecumbent setae interspersed with erect setae of three lengths; surface feebly rugose, less rugose than head; moderately, shallowly punctate. Prosternum rugulose; surface feebly concave; weakly, shallowly punctate. Mesosternum concave; moderately, coarsely punctate, scarcely clothed with long, erect setae; metasternum conspicuously wider than long; strongly concave; rugulose; moderately, shallowly punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Legs: Femora and tibiae profusely clothed with short, semirecumbent setae interspersed with long, semierect and erect setae; femora and tibiae transversally, moderately rugose; fourth protarsomere with pulvillus medially incised, incision not extending beyond middle.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">
Elytra: EL = 6.05 mm, EW = 2.8 mm; length to width ratio of holotype 2.16. Base narrower than pronotum; humeri very feebly indicated; sides subparallel; widest at posterior 1/3; disc feebly convex; surface rugose; apices rounded; strongly dehiscent; clothed with erect setae of three sizes; sculpture consisting of coarse punctations arranged in irregular striae that gradually become smaller, shallower and less numerous before apex; interstices at elytral base about 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
the width of punctuation.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="14" pageNumber="47">
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="47" start="start">Abdomen</pageBreakToken>
: Ventrites 1-5 rugulose, subquadrate, moderately, shallowly punctate, vested with short, fine, pale, recumbent setae; posterior margin of third and fourth visible ventrite broadly, deeply emarginate. Fifth visible ventrite subquadrate; surface convex; moderately, coarsely punctate; lateral margins subparallel; posterior margin broadly, deeply emarginate; emargination reaching median region; posterolateral angles pointed (Fig. 22). Sixth visible ventrite subquadrate, longer than broad; surface rugose; moderately, coarsely punctate; with a pair of longitudinal carinae that extend from about the base to near posterolateral angles; lateral margins subparallel, posterior margin broadly, deeply triangularly emarginate, emargination extending from near posterolateral angles to basal fourth; posterolateral angles rounded, recurved ventrally. Fifth tergite rugulose, lateral margins subparallel; posterior margin truncate, with a narrow, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="48" start="start">shallow</pageBreakToken>
, triangular emargination on median region (Fig. 23). Sixth tergite subquadrate, broader than long; surface rugulose; lateral margins feebly arcuate, oblique; posterior margin, broadly, shallowly emarginate; posterolateral angles pointed, recurved dorsally. Sixth tergite extending slightly beyond apical margin of sixth visible ventrite, fully covering the latter from dorsal view. Aedeagus: 2.1 mm long; ratio of length of parameres to whole tegmen 0.65:1; tegmen fully covering phallus; parameres robust at base, then gradually becoming slender toward distal end, pointed at apex, lateral margins oblique; phallobase broad; phallus with copulatory piece rounded distally, posteriorly dilated; phallic plate armed with a row of moderately long denticles along dorsal margin; phallobasic apodeme short, robust, dilated distally; endophallic struts slender throughout their length (Fig. 14).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">The only female in the type series has the fifth visible ventrite rugulose; surface convex; lateral margins strongly oblique, rather arcuate; posterior margin widely, deeply emarginate. Sixth visible ventrite rugulose; coarsely punctate; moderately convex; lateral margins feebly arcuate, moderately oblique; posterior margin truncate. Fifth tergite rugulose; surface feebly convex; lateral margins oblique, moderately arcuate; posterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate. Sixth tergite subtriangular; rugulose; coarsely punctate; lateral margins strongly oblique, feeble arcuate; posterior margin narrowly truncate. Sixth tergite extends very slightly beyond sixth visible ventrite.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="48" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">The female has a length of 8.2 mm. Length to width ratio of head: 0.52. Length to width ratio of thorax: 1.51. Length to width ratio of elytra: 2.11. The female shows a moderately brownish coloration, somewhat lighter than the male, and the antennomeres 5-10 are filiform, rather than feebly serrate, as observed in the male.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="48" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">
The holotype was collected in the state of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Michoacán">Michoacan</normalizedToken>
, at the central-western portion of Mexico, on km 23 on the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Morelia-Pátzcuaro">Morelia-Patzcuaro</normalizedToken>
highway, a region that has suffered extensive logging and was originally covered by a high to mid altitude 
<taxonomicName class="Pinopsida" family="Pinaceae" genus="Pinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Pinus" order="Pinales" pageId="15" pageNumber="48" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Pinus</taxonomicName>
- 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus" order="Fagales" pageId="15" pageNumber="48" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Quercus</taxonomicName>
association; the female was collected in the state of Durango, 26 km west of the city of Durango, Mexico (Fig. 34).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="48" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">The specific epithet comes from the Latin linea (= line) and refers to the longitudinal fasciae on the elytral ground of this species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="48" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="48">
Although it is not usually desirable to describe a new species based on two specimens, this species is strikingly different from all other known 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="48" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Cymatodera</taxonomicName>
species. In addition, the urgent need for identifying and cataloging this diverse group of beetles justifies this description, particularly if such species inhabit poorly known or threatened environments (
<bibRefCitation author="Rifkind, J" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="16" pageNumber="49" pagination="1 - 2" title="New Central and Mexican Enoclerus Gahan (Coleoptera: Cleridae: Clerinae): part II." volume="3397" year="2012">Rifkind 2012</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>