<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047634" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="0E9E7C57F127E2A46EF9D8EB491C63E0" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio rugulosus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="179" lastPageNumber="180" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="175" pageNumber="176" updateTime="1643530488545" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047634" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:0E9E7C57F127E2A46EF9D8EB491C63E0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0E9E7C57F127E2A46EF9D8EB491C63E0" lastPageId="179" lastPageNumber="180" pageId="175" pageNumber="176">
<subSubSection pageId="175" pageNumber="176" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/7662C30F-0110-481C-8C4E-A7BFDA3D3EE7" authority="Dodd" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio rugulosus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="175" pageNumber="176" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugulosus">Oxyscelio rugulosus (Dodd)</taxonomicName>
Figures 283-288; Morphbank82
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="175" pageNumber="176" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Sceliomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sceliomorpha rugulosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="175" pageNumber="176" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugulosa">Sceliomorpha rugulosa</taxonomicName>
Dodd, 1913: 139 (original description); 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieffer, JJ" journalOrPublisher="Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co., Berlin" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" title="Scelionidae. Das Tierreich. Vol. 48." year="1926">Kieffer 1926</bibRefCitation>
: 302, 306 (description, keyed).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">
<taxonomicName authority="Kieffer, 1908" authorityName="Kieffer" authorityYear="1908" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Dicroteleia" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dicroteleia glabriscutellum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="175" pageNumber="176" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="glabriscutellum">Dicroteleia glabriscutellum</taxonomicName>
Dodd, 1914: 106 (original description); 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieffer, JJ" journalOrPublisher="Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co., Berlin" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" title="Scelionidae. Das Tierreich. Vol. 48." year="1926">Kieffer 1926</bibRefCitation>
: 387, 390 (description, keyed). syn. n.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">
<taxonomicName authority="Kieffer, 1908" authorityName="Kieffer" authorityYear="1908" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Dicroteleia" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dicroteleia rugulosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="175" pageNumber="176" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugulosa">Dicroteleia rugulosa</taxonomicName>
(Dodd): 
<bibRefCitation author="Dodd, AP" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="91 - 140" title="Further new genera and species of Australian Proctotrypoidea." volume="26" year="1914">Dodd 1914</bibRefCitation>
: 107 (generic transfer).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio rugulosus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="175" pageNumber="176" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugulosus">Oxyscelio rugulosus</taxonomicName>
(Dodd): 
<bibRefCitation author="Dodd, AP" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="71 - 81" title="The genus Oxyscelio Kieffer, its synonymy and species, with a description of one new genus (Hymenoptera: Proctotrypoidea)." volume="42" year="1931">Dodd 1931</bibRefCitation>
: 76 (generic transfer); 
<bibRefCitation author="Galloway, ID" journalOrPublisher="Queensland Journal of Agricultural and Animal Sciences" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="83 - 114" title="The types of Australian species of the subfamily Scelioninae (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae)." volume="33" year="1976">Galloway 1976</bibRefCitation>
: 100 (type information); 
<bibRefCitation author="Masner, L" journalOrPublisher="Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="1 - 87" title="Revisionary notes and keys to world genera of Scelionidae (Hymenoptera: Proctotrupoidea)." url="10.4039/entm10897fv" volume="97" year="1976">Masner 1976</bibRefCitation>
: 24 (description).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="178" lastPageNumber="179" pageId="175" pageNumber="176" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">Female. Body length 2.55-3 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="175" pageNumber="176">Radicle color and shade: same as scape, both yellowish or reddish. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: shorter than pedicel; as long as pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="177" lastPageNumber="178" pageId="175" pageNumber="176">
Ventral clypeal margin: concave. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: with transverse ledge, face sharply receding below it. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: present. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="176" pageNumber="177" start="start">Median</pageBreakToken>
longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: present as a single carina. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: present laterally, absent medially. Occiput 
<pageBreakToken pageId="177" pageNumber="178" start="start">sculpture</pageBreakToken>
: smooth. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, complete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="177" pageNumber="178">Lateral pronotal area sculpture: smooth anteriorly, densely setose posteriorly. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: narrowly separated, angled anteriorly to become parallel. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: with median areole or pair of pits. Median propodeal carina: present. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="177" pageNumber="178">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: straight. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: slightly emarginate, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: densely setose, setal pits between very weak longitudinal rugae. S5 sculpture: densely setose, setal pits between very weak longitudinal rugae. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="178" pageNumber="179">
<pageBreakToken pageId="178" pageNumber="179" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Body length 2.5-3 mm (n=20). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: longer than broad. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: truncate.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="178" pageNumber="179">
<paragraph pageId="178" pageNumber="179">
Figures 283-288. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio rugulosus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="178" pageNumber="179" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugulosus">Oxyscelio rugulosus</taxonomicName>
(Dodd), syntype female (SAMA DB 32-001590) 283 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 284 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 285 Metasoma, dorsal view. Female (OSUC 442410) 286 Head, anterior view. Male (OSUC 442459) 287 Antenna 288 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank82
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="178" pageNumber="179" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="178" pageNumber="179">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="178" pageNumber="179">Both sexes: Frontal depression shallow, weak transverse carinae present; submedian carina indicated by a set of weak rugae, flat or only weakly rounded dorsally. Hyperoccipital carina sharp and strong. Occipital carina incomplete, lateral portions nearly reaching hyperoccipital carina. Occiput almost entirely smooth, with a row of setiferous puncta. Mesoscutum with median carina. Metascutellum broad and concave, truncate or slightly concave apically, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein present. Coxa not darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina not expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 as long or longer than pedicel. A4, A5 broader than long. Mesoscutellum weakly sculptured, with only setiferous puncta. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach beyond T6. T6 broader than long. Male: All flagellomeres past A3 about as long as broad. Frontal depression without complete transverse carinae. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach beyond metasomal apex. T7 tiny, truncate.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="178" pageNumber="179" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="178" pageNumber="179">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="178" pageNumber="179">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=5033]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="179" lastPageNumber="180" pageId="178" pageNumber="179" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="178" pageNumber="179">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="179" lastPageNumber="180" pageId="178" pageNumber="179">
Syntype, male, S. rugulosa: AUSTRALIA: QLD, nr. Cairns, jungle edge, Gordonvale (Nelson), no date, sweeping, A. P. Dodd, SAMA DB 32-001589 (deposited in SAMA). Syntype, female, S. rugulosa: Female holotype of, D. glabriscutellum: AUSTRALIA: QLD, nr. Cairns, plant foliage / jungle country, Harvey Creek, 12.X.1914, A. P. Dodd, SAMA DB 32-001585 (deposited in SAMA). AUSTRALIA: QLD, jungle edge, nr. Gordonvale (Nelson), no date, sweeping, A. P. Dodd, SAMA DB 32-001590 (deposited in SAMA). Paratype: AUSTRALIA: 1 female, ANIC DB 32-020109 (ANIC). Other material: AUSTRALIA: 49 females, 68 males, 442441b, ANIC DB 32-020104, ANIC DB 32-020105, ANIC DB 32-020106, ANIC DB 32-020107, ANIC DB 32-020108, OSUC 442402, OSUC 442403, OSUC 442404, OSUC 442405, OSUC 442406, OSUC 442407, OSUC 442408, OSUC 442409, OSUC 442413, OSUC 442414, OSUC 442415, OSUC 442416, OSUC 442417, OSUC 442418, OSUC 442419, OSUC 442420, OSUC 442421, OSUC 442422, OSUC 442423, OSUC 442424, OSUC 442425, OSUC 442426, OSUC 442427, OSUC 442428, OSUC 442429, OSUC 442430, OSUC 442431, OSUC 442432, OSUC 442433, OSUC 442434, OSUC 442435, OSUC 442436, OSUC 442438, OSUC 442439, OSUC 442440, OSUC 442442, OSUC 442443, OSUC 442444, OSUC 442445, OSUC 442446, OSUC 442448, OSUC 442449, OSUC 442450, OSUC 442451, OSUC 442452, OSUC 442453, OSUC 442454, OSUC 442455, OSUC 442456, OSUC 442457, OSUC 442458, OSUC 442459, OSUC 442460, OSUC 442461, OSUC 442462, OSUC 442463, OSUC 442464, OSUC 442465, OSUC 442466, OSUC 442467, OSUC 442468, OSUC 442469, OSUC 442470, OSUC 442471, OSUC 442473, OSUC 442474, OSUC 442475, OSUC 
<pageBreakToken pageId="179" pageNumber="180" start="start">442477</pageBreakToken>
, OSUC 442478, OSUC 442479, OSUC 442480, OSUC 442481, OSUC 442482, OSUC 442484, OSUC 442488, OSUC 451299, OSUC 451300, OSUC 451302 (ANIC); OSUC 451301, 451303, 451305 (BMNH); OSUC 324331, 58660 (OSUC); OSUC 451304, QDPC 0-165688, QDPC 0-165691, QDPC 0-165694, QDPC 0-165701, QDPC 0-165703, QDPC 0-165713, QDPC 0-165724, QDPC 0-165731, QDPC 0-165735, QDPC 0-165737, QDPC 0-165745, QDPC 0-165749 (QDPC); OSUC 442437, 442485-442486 (QMBA); OSUC 448597, 448600 (QPIM); UCRC ENT 151376-151377 (UCRC); OSUC 442410-442412, 442447, 442472, 442476, 442483, 442487 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="179" pageNumber="180" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="179" pageNumber="180">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="179" pageNumber="180">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio rugulosus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="179" pageNumber="180" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugulosus">Oxyscelio rugulosus</taxonomicName>
differs from most members of the flavipes-group in having a median mesoscutal carina. This is accompanied by weak and sparse mesoscutal sculpture, which is also unusual in the flavipes-group. The type specimen of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio glabriscutellum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="179" pageNumber="180" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="glabriscutellum">Oxyscelio glabriscutellum</taxonomicName>
does not at all differ from our concept of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio rugulosus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="179" pageNumber="180" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugulosus">Oxyscelio rugulosus</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>