<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4ab1486d-256b-467d-a0dc-cf6658ed74fa" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127864958" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-647-37" ID-ZBK="B8255BDA82A442DC82F75BF13ACF632A" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:859877FC-DF4C-4BF8-BFE5-08CE11C94144" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-647-37" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 647" ModsDocTitle="Review of the genus Craspedolcus Enderlein sensu lato in China, with the description of a new genus and four new species (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Braconinae)" checkinTime="1485645102941" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Li, Yang, van Achterberg, Cornelis &amp; Chen, Xue-xin" docDate="2017" docId="595BDD1972471A7B1C10BE0DD2D6E776" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 647: 37-65" docOrigin="ZooKeys 647" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247" docTitle="Maculibracon hei Li, Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="859877FC-DF4C-4BF8-BFE5-08CE11C94144" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="51" masterDocId="F361FF8F0F34FFAAFFC4FFA6FF871747" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Craspedolcus Enderlein sensu lato in China, with the description of a new genus and four new species (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Braconinae)" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="37" pageId="12" pageNumber="49" updateTime="1643567205425" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the genus Craspedolcus Enderlein sensu lato in China, with the description of a new genus and four new species (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Braconinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Yang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>van Achterberg, Cornelis</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chen, Xue-xin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>647</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>37</mods:start>
<mods:end>65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-647-37</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">B8255BDA82A442DC82F75BF13ACF632A</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B8255BDA82A442DC82F75BF13ACF632A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127864958" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:859877FC-DF4C-4BF8-BFE5-08CE11C94144" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/595BDD1972471A7B1C10BE0DD2D6E776" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="51" pageId="12" pageNumber="49">
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="49" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="49">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/859877FC-DF4C-4BF8-BFE5-08CE11C94144" authority="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017" authorityName="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen" authorityYear="2017" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Maculibracon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Maculibracon hei" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hei">Maculibracon hei</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="12" pageNumber="49">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 55, 56-66
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="49" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="49">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="49">Holotype, ♀ (IZCAS), &quot;[China:] Yunnan, Lancang, 1000 m, 30.VII.1957, Lingchao Zang, No. IOZ(E)1964638&quot;.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="49" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="49">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="49">
Entire scapus dark brown or black, rather stout and more protruding ventrally; head rather directly narrowed posteriorly (Fig. 63); stigmal spot rather small, up to anterior third of first discal cell (Fig. 56); wing membrane yellow with slightly infuscate apical area of fore wing medium-sized, but remaining far from vein 1r-m (Figs 56, 57); pterostigma anteriorly dark brown and remainder yellow; medio-posterior protuberance of propodeum with two medium-sized round tubercles, ribbed in lateral view (Fig. 65); medial area of first tergite high anteriorly and gradually lowered basally (Figs 60, 65); body and hind leg brownish yellow; length of ovipositor sheath 0.6 times fore wing and 0.7 times body. Similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017" authorityName="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen" authorityYear="2017" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Maculibracon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Maculibracon leptopterus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leptopterus">Maculibracon leptopterus</taxonomicName>
(Cameron, 1903) because of dark scapus and medium-sized stigmal spot. The new species differs by the longer ovipositor sheath (0.7 times versus 0.4 times in 
<taxonomicName authority="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017" authorityName="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen" authorityYear="2017" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Maculibracon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Maculibracon leptopterus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leptopterus">Maculibracon leptopterus</taxonomicName>
according to the original description), the sculpture of the second metasomal tergite (absent versus crenulate or striate near smooth antero-lateral areas), colour of the setae of the face (yellow versus fuscous), the size of the stigmal spot (up to anterior third of first discal cell (versus up to middle of cell) and the colour of the pterostigma (anteriorly dark brown versus yellow except dark brown apex).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="51" pageId="12" pageNumber="49" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="49">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="49">Holotype, ♀, length of body 17.2 mm, of fore wing 17.8 mm, of ovipositor sheath 11.2 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="50" pageId="12" pageNumber="49">
Head. Antenna incomplete, left antenna with 83 segments remaining, right antenna with 67 segments remaining; scapus rather stout, 1.5 times longer than wide and distinctly emarginate apically, longer ventrally than dorsally in lateral view, with a narrow apical ledge at inner side and gradually narrowed basally (Fig. 66); third and fourth segments 1.7 and 1.1 times their maximum width, respectively; length of maxillary palp as long as height of head; inner side of eye not emarginated but slightly sinuate (Fig. 63); face moderately convex but flattened medially and medio-dorsally with weak median crest, coarsely and densely punctate, and with long erect setae; clypeus flat, rugose, dorsally with coarse curved carina and ventral margin thin and lamelliform, with few long setae ventrally; hypoclypeal depression 0.3 times as wide as minimum width of face (Fig. 62); frons shallowly concave behind antennal sockets, rugose, with a rather shallow median groove (Fig. 62); vertex smooth, with few long setae and shiny; stemmaticum distinctly protruding; OOL:diameter of posterior ocellus:POL = 25:10:8; in dorsal view length of eye 2.3 times temple; temples directly 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="50" start="start">narrowed</pageBreakToken>
behind eyes, with some long setae, punctate dorsally and sparsely punctate ventrally (Fig. 63, 64); malar suture shallow, curved; length of malar space 0.8 times basal width of mandible; mandible twisted, both teeth robust and subequal.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="50">Mesosoma. Length of mesosoma 1.8 times its height (Fig. 58); side of pronotum shiny and smooth; propleuron with spaced punctures; pronotum vertical anteriorly, with a shallow pronope and groove and narrow antescutal depression; mesopleuron smooth and glabrous, except for an oblique band with punctures and short setae; mesosternal sulcus smooth and narrow; metapleuron smooth and with long setae, convex; mesoscutum glabrous except some setae near notaulic courses, shiny and smooth; notauli smooth, only distinct anteriorly and medially shallowly impressed; scutellar sulcus present and with distinct fine crenulae; scutellum distinctly convex and smooth except for some very sparse punctulation; side of scutellum smooth; metanotum medio-anteriorly with short carina, posteriorly evenly convex and smooth; propodeum distinctly remotely punctate, with long setae, evenly convex but medio-posteriorly with protuberance consisting of small medium-sized round tubercles anteriorly followed by two short transverse crests (Fig. 59), ribbed in lateral view (Fig. 65).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="50">Wings. Fore wing (Fig. 56): m-cu 0.6 times as long as 1-M; 1-SR+M angularly bent subbasally 1.2 times as long as 1-M; 3-SR weakly curved, and SR1 straight; r:3-SR:SR1 = 5:29:24; 2-SR:3-SR:r-m = 11:29:11; r-m largely sclerotised; 1-CU1 slightly widened and 0.17 times 2-CU1; cu-a weakly inclivous; CU1b nearly as wide as 3-CU1. Hind wing (Fig. 57): with 4 or 5 coarse subbasal bristles on C+SC+R and with 3 hamuli on R1; SR weakly curved basally and marginal cell subparallel-sided apically; area near cu-a glabrous; 1r-m straight and 1.3 times as long as SC+R1; 2-SC+R as wide as long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="50">Legs. Tarsal claws simple and with long bristly setae ventrally; length of femur, tibia and basitarsus of hind leg 5.2, 12.5 and 7.9 times their maximum width, respectively; hind tibia with dense and rather appressed setae; hind tibial spurs 0.3 and 0.4 times as long as hind basitarsus; inner side of hind tibia and tarsus densely bristly setose (Fig. 61).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="50">
Metasoma. Length of first tergite 1.3 times its apical width, dorso-lateral carinae strongly developed, medial area smooth except for high median carina and medial area steep anteriorly (Fig. 60, 65); second tergite smooth (including deep oblique anterior grooves) except strong median carina connected to minute triangular medio-basal area, antero-lateral triangular areas large (Fig. 60); second metasomal suture strongly crenulated, laterally narrowed and weakly up curved; medially second tergite 1.5 times longer than third tergite; maximum width of third tergite 2.7 times its medial length; third and fourth tergites with rather weakly median carina; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="third–fifth">third-fifth</normalizedToken>
tergites smooth and without transverse subposterior groove and with long antero-lateral grooves; ovipositor sheath 0.63 times as long as fore wing and 0.65 times body; hypopygium ending just anterior of apex of metasoma (Fig. 55).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="51" pageId="13" pageNumber="50">
Colour. Yellowish brown; antenna (included scapus) and mandible apically dark brown; ovipositor sheath blackish with yellow setae; stigmal spot rather small, up to 0.4 anterior of first discal cell (Fig. 56); apical 0.2 of pterostigma dark brown and remainder 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="51" start="start">yellow</pageBreakToken>
; veins yellow except dark brown basal half of 1-SR+M and most of 1-SR; wing membrane yellow, except for stigmal spot and slightly infuscate apical area of fore wing medium-sized, but remaining far from vein 1r-m (Figs 56, 57).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="51" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="51">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="51">*China (Yunnan).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="51" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="51">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="51">
Named in honour of Prof. Dr Jun-hua He (Hangzhou) for his significant contribution to our knowledge of the Chinese 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="51" rank="order">Hymenoptera</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>