<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bcdbe5f4-2f0e-4240-8727-64b6c91db94a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886264" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-591-1" ID-ZBK="DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9CBF62E8-8C53-4139-A85F-F0A248D49E71" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-591-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 591" ModsDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" checkinTime="1463833188709" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Monckton, Spencer K." docDate="2016" docId="BD2146AC8B105921618A0361063588C4" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 591: 1-144" docOrigin="ZooKeys 591" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731" docTitle="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) randolphi Monckton, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="9CBF62E8-8C53-4139-A85F-F0A248D49E71" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="96" lastPageNumber="97" masterDocId="FFFED84DD544452EFFC446356171FFFD" masterDocTitle="A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species" masterLastPageNumber="144" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="90" pageNumber="91" updateTime="1643603351127" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of Chilicola (Heteroediscelis), a subgenus of xeromelissine bees (Hymenoptera, Colletidae) endemic to Chile: taxonomy, phylogeny, and biogeography, with descriptions of eight new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Monckton, Spencer K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>591</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>144</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.591.7731</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-591-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DD65A7BB1B834CB298BA7E8E2257FA4F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="150886264" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9CBF62E8-8C53-4139-A85F-F0A248D49E71" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BD2146AC8B105921618A0361063588C4" lastPageId="96" lastPageNumber="97" pageId="90" pageNumber="91">
<subSubSection pageId="90" pageNumber="91" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="90" pageNumber="91">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Colletidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="90" pageNumber="91" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="90" pageNumber="91">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/9CBF62E8-8C53-4139-A85F-F0A248D49E71" authority="Monckton" class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) randolphi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="90" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="randolphi" subGenus="Heteroediscelis">Chilicola (Heteroediscelis) randolphi Monckton</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="90" pageNumber="91">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 5B; 11D; 15
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
; 17A; 18
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
; 45
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–J">A-J</normalizedToken>
; 49
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="91" pageNumber="92" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="91" pageNumber="92">
<pageBreakToken pageId="91" pageNumber="92" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="91" pageNumber="92">
Males are readily diagnosed by the distinctly truncate S1 process with apex perpendicular to axis of process in lateral view, and metabasitarsus expanded basally (~0.33
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as deep as long). Among consubgeners, only 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola erithropoda" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="91" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erithropoda">Chilicola erithropoda</taxonomicName>
has the metabasitarsus expanded thus, but is readily distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola randolphi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="91" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="randolphi">Chilicola randolphi</taxonomicName>
by the entirely yellow-orange tibiae and S1 process in lateral view with anterior and posterior margins divergent apically. Females are diagnosable by the red-brown metasoma and protibia yellow only on basal half of dorsal surface. Females of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola packeri" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="91" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="packeri">Chilicola packeri</taxonomicName>
, many females of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola curvapeligrosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="91" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="curvapeligrosa">Chilicola curvapeligrosa</taxonomicName>
, and some females of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola neffi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="91" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="neffi">Chilicola neffi</taxonomicName>
also have the metasoma red-brown, but always have the protibia yellow on the entire dorsal surface.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="95" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="91" pageNumber="92" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="91" pageNumber="92">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="91" pageNumber="92">Male (Holotype). Length 5.6mm, forewing length 3.6mm, head width 1.3mm, thorax width 1.4mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.13mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="93" lastPageNumber="94" pageId="91" pageNumber="92">
Colouration: Black-brown, following parts yellow: labrum; clypeus except broadly dark along epistomal suture and apex brown laterad; lower paraocular area, extending 
<pageBreakToken pageId="92" pageNumber="93" start="start">dorsad</pageBreakToken>
to just below lower tangent of antennal socket laterally and about 1OD above transverse portion of epistomal suture medially; apicoventral spot on scape; protrochanter apical rim posteriorly; apex of profemur broadly on anterior surface, narrowly 
<pageBreakToken pageId="93" pageNumber="94" start="start">on</pageBreakToken>
posterior surface; protibia except dark medioventrally; basal half of dorsal surface of probasitarsus; wide apical ring on mesofemur; basal and apical quarters of mesotibia, dorsal surface suffused with yellow throughout; base of mesobasitarsus; apicodorsal rim of metafemur; ventral surface of metatibia, as well as dorsal surface in basal one-third and narrowly yellow apically except broad around apical lamina and posterior concavity; basal half of metabasitarsus ventrally; anterior spot on tegula; apex of T7. Following parts yellow-brown: ventral surface of antenna from apical half of pedicel to terminal flagellomere, narrowing basad on pedicel and F1; apical half of prodistitarsus; apicoventral rim of metacoxa and metatrochanter. Ventral and posterior metatibial carinae black. Metasoma dark brown, T1-T6 marginal zones amber to translucent yellow at margins.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Pubescence: White, hairs generally short (0.5OD) and sparse, not especially plumose; on lower paraocular area and around antennal base long and moderately dense (1.5OD); genal beard long and dense (0.5-3OD) longest at midlength; mesoscutal hairs moderately long and sparse, denser toward lateral margin (1-1.5OD); discs of scutellum and metanotum mostly bare, few short hairs (0.5OD), longer and denser toward lateral and posterior margin of scutellum (1-2OD) longest posteromedially, and toward lateral margin of metanotum (≤2.5OD); propodeal hairs moderately long and dense dorsolaterally (0.5-2.5OD); T1-T3 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD); S2 hairs long and dense (2OD basolaterad, 1.5OD distilaterad, shorter mesad).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Surface sculpture: Microsculpture imbricate, integument generally dull; punctures generally small and deep. Clypeus and lower paraocular area moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) except clypeus sparsely punctate medially (i=2-3d); supraclypeal area irregularly punctate (i=1-4d) densely punctate toward lateral margin (i≤d); frontal area very densely punctate (i≤0.5d), densely punctate around ocelli (i≤d); ocellocular space moderately densely punctate adjacent to compound eye (i=1-2d) becoming impunctate adjacent to lateral ocellus; vertexal area rugose and densely punctate (i≤d); scape shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) densely punctate apicoventrally (i≤d); genal area microstriate and moderately densely punctate (i≤2d); hypostomal area densely punctate (i=d); pronotum densely punctate (i=0.5-1d), lateral surface coarsely imbricate; mesoscutum densely punctate (i=0.5-1d) more sparsely punctate toward lateral margin (i=0.5-2d) punctures crowded around median (i≤d); scutellum moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) punctures crowded around median (i≤d); mesepisternum irregularly punctate, sparse below scrobe (i=1-3d), sparser anterior of episternal groove (i≥2d), denser on hypoepimeral area (i≤2d); metanotum moderately densely punctate (i≤2d) punctures crowded around median and anteriorly (i≤0.5d); metepisternum densely punctate (i≤d) and distinctly longitudinally striate anterodorsally; metapostnotum rugose; propodeum coarsely imbricate and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); T1 punctures small and moderately dense (i=1-3d); T2-T5 moderately densely punctate (i=1-3d); marginal zones of terga weakly imbricate and shiny, minutely punctate to impunctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="94" lastPageNumber="95" pageId="93" pageNumber="94">
Structure: Labrum ~2.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (25:11.5); malar space slightly shorter than clypeal lateral (7:8); LOT at level of anterior tentorial pits; length of clypeus 
<pageBreakToken pageId="94" pageNumber="95" start="start">subequal</pageBreakToken>
to maximum width in frontal view (30:31) extending for less than half its length beyond LOT and convex above anterior tentorial pit, in lateral view bulging ~1OD above compound eye; median longitudinal groove present on clypeus except on apex; subantennal sutures shorter than the shortest distance between them (15:16); IAD nearly double AOD (15: 8); scape ~2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (25:11); pedicel slightly shorter than wide (9:9.5); F1 as long as wide (9.5:9.5); F2 ~1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F1 and same length as F3 (F2:F3 - 14.5:14.5); UOD ~1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 55:60:42); frontal line carinate in lower half, flat above, interrupted at midlength; MOC shorter than width of head (82:93); OOC ~0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (16:19); genal area 0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as eye in lateral view (18:30); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 65:25:11:20; probasitarsus ~2.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (21:8); length of prodistitarsus subequal to that of preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V- 6:4:5:16); metafemur 1.85
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (74:40); summit of metatibial ventral convexity near tibial apex; metatibia less than twice as long as maximum depth (53:32); in apical view apical lamina of metatibia broadly expanded with distinct, secondary anterior lobe, length ~1.33
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
OD (12:9); ventral metatibial carina sharply toothed near apex, posterior carina sublinear and weakly defined basally; metabasitarsus very deep in basal half, only ~3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (46:15); S1 process apical surface longitudinally concave, in lateral view anterior and posterior margins subparallel apically. S7 apodemal arm sclerotized margin terminating laterally at arm midlength; ventral lobe ~0.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as broad as basal attached length; dorsal lobe strap-like, subparallel-sided and somewhat anteriorly curved, with basal tuft of long setae and a short apical row, midlength bare; apex of disc sinuate. S8 lateral process ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long, anteromedial sclerotized margin following marginal contour. Gonobase apicoventral truncate process biconvex and distinctly notched by a width less than one convexity.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="94" pageNumber="95">Female (Allotype). Length 5.6mm, forewing length 3.6mm, head width 1.1mm, thorax width 1.3mm, median ocellar diameter (OD) 0.10mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="94" pageNumber="95">Colouration: Black to black-brown except as follows: labrum yellow-brown; mandible with yellow basal spot, translucent yellow in apical half except apex translucent brown. Following parts brown: spot below anterior tentorial pit; median spot on clypeus just above upper margin of anterior tentorial pits; basoventral spot on scape. Following parts yellow: dorsal surface of protibia in basal half; apical two-thirds of prodistitarsus; narrow basal ring on mesotibia; faint anterior spot on tegula. Following parts yellow-brown: apicoventral surfaces of pedicel and F1; ventral surface of antenna from F2 to terminal flagellomere, flagellomeres suffused with brown basally; apical ring on protibia; apical half of mesodistitarsus; apical ring on metafemur; basal ring on metatibia. Metasoma orange-brown, graduli of T2-T4 &amp; S2-S4 dark and widened medially to basal half of disc on S2.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="95" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="94" pageNumber="95">
Pubescence: As in male except as follows: on lower paraocular area and around antennal base moderately long and moderately dense (1OD); genal beard moderately dense (0.5-2.5OD); discs of mesoscutum, scutellum, and metanotum with sparse short hairs (≤0.5OD), denser and as long or longer toward lateral margin as follows: 
<pageBreakToken pageId="95" pageNumber="96" start="start">mesoscutum</pageBreakToken>
(0.5OD), scutellum (1-2OD) also on posterior margin, longest posteromedially, metanotum (2OD); scopar on metafemur and metibia (1-1.5OD); T1-T3 apicolateral patches of tomentum (0.5-1OD); S1 hairs long and moderately dense (≤2OD); S2 scopal hairs (1-2OD).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Surface sculpture: As in male except as follows: lower paraocular area moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d) densely punctate adjacent to epistomal suture (i&lt;d); frontal area densely punctate (i≤d), moderately densely punctate around ocelli (i=1-2d); vertexal area densely punctate (i≤d); scape shallowly and moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d); genal area weakly imbricate, weakly microstriate posteriorly, and moderately densely punctate throughout (i=1-2d); hypostomal area moderately densely punctate (i≤2d); pronotum densely punctate (i=d); mesoscutum densely punctate (i=d) moderately densely punctate toward lateral margin (i=1-2d); scutellum and metanotum moderately densely punctate (i=0.5-2d) except metanotal punctures crowded around median and anteriorly (i≤0.5d); metapostnotum rugose; T1-T5 punctures small and sparse (i=1-3d); T6 moderately densely punctate (i=1-2d).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
Structure: Labrum ~2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long (26:11.5); malar space ~0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as clypeal lateral (7:9); LOT at level of anterior tentorial pits; length of clypeus subequal to maximum width in frontal view (34:33) extending for less than half its length beyond LOT and convex above anterior tentorial pit as in male; median longitudinal groove absent from clypeus; subantennal sutures shorter than the shortest distance between them (12.5:14.5); IAD 1.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
AOD (16:10); scape ~3.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum width (26:8); pedicel ~1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide (9:7); F1 slightly longer than wide (8:7.5); F2 ~0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F1 (4.5) and 0.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as F3 (6); UOD ~1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOD, IOD ~1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
UOD (UOD:IOD:LOD - 55:60:42); frontal line carinate in lower half, flat above; MOC shorter than width of head (85:90); OOC ~0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
IOC (13.5:20); genal area about two thirds as wide as eye in lateral view (18:28); ratio of lengths of mesoscutum: scutellum: metanotum: metapostnotum - 61:25:11.5:16; probasitarsus ~3.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (25:8.5); prodistitarsus ~0.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as preceding three tarsomeres combined (from II to V - 6:4:5:14); metafemur ~3.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (53:16); metatibia ~4.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (66:14); metabasitarsus almost 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as maximum depth (43:11).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
Figure 45. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Colletidae" genus="Chilicola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chilicola randolphi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="95" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="randolphi">Chilicola randolphi</taxonomicName>
: A male habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm B male head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm C female habitus, lateral view, scale bar 1 mm D female head, frontal view, scale bar 0.5 mm E male metatibia, posterior view, scale bar 0.25 mm F male S1 process, lateral view†, scale bar 0.25 mm G male S1 process, apical view, scale bar 0.25 mm H male S7 (C.rndi.003), scale bar 0.25 mm I male S8 (C.rndi.003), scale bar 0.25 mm J male genital capsule (C.rndi.003), scale bar 0.25 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="96" lastPageNumber="97" pageId="95" pageNumber="96" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Type material</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="96" lastPageNumber="97" pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
(6 males &amp; 15 females): Holotype (male): Region VII, Laguna del Maule, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-36.0027">S 36.0027°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.4555">W 70.4555°</geoCoordinate>
, 2227m, 4.i.2009, L. Packer, on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Hydrophyllaceae" genus="Phacelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Phacelia" order="Boraginales" pageId="95" pageNumber="96" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Phacelia</taxonomicName>
, CCDB-03755 D08, CHI09-6-5-004 (PCYU); Allotype (female): same data as holotype, CHI09-6-5-007 (PCYU); Paratypes: Region VII: one male and four females, same data as holotype, CHI09-6-5-008, CHI09-6-5-001, CHI09-6-5-002, CHI09-6-5-005, CHI09-6-6-001, (PCYU); two females, same data as holotype (PUCV); two females, same data as holotype (CTMI); one male and one female, E of Laguna del Maule, 160.120km, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-35.9928">S 35.9928°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.3991">W 70.3991°</geoCoordinate>
, 2505m, 1-6.i.2013, L. Packer &amp; R. Smith, white pan traps, CCDB-19991 D05, CCDB-19991 D02 (PCYU); one female, same locality, 1-20.iii.2013, S. Monckton &amp; J. Postlethwaite, pan trap (PCYU); one female, W of Laguna del Maule, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-35.9901">S 35.9901°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.3977">W 70.3977°</geoCoordinate>
, 2541m, 5.i.2009, L. Packer, on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Hydrophyllaceae" genus="Phacelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Phacelia" order="Boraginales" pageId="95" pageNumber="96" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Phacelia</taxonomicName>
, CCDB-03755 E07 // CHI09-6-5-056 (PCYU); one female, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Río">Rio</normalizedToken>
Maule, Hwy 115, km 122, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="-35.9016">S 35.9016°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-70.6426">W 70.6426°</geoCoordinate>
, 1359m, 1-20.iii.2013, S. Monckton &amp; J. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="96" pageNumber="97" start="start">Postlethwaite</pageBreakToken>
, pan trap (PCYU); Region VIII: two males, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ñuble">Nuble</normalizedToken>
, Los Lleuques, 4km. E of Recinto, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.854">S 36.854°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-71.645">W 71.645°</geoCoordinate>
, 783m, xii.1982, L. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH); one female, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ñuble">Nuble</normalizedToken>
, Las Trancas, Shangrila in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Chillán">Chillan</normalizedToken>
area, SE of Recinto, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.876">S 36.876°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-71.468">W 71.468°</geoCoordinate>
, 1549m, 14.xii.1983, L. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH); one female, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ñuble">Nuble</normalizedToken>
, Las Trancas, SE Recinto in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Chillán">Chillan</normalizedToken>
area, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.911">S 36.911°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="555" value="-71.48">W 71.48°</geoCoordinate>
, 1250m, i.1987, Luis E. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH); one male, Las Cabras, mts. in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Chillán">Chillan</normalizedToken>
area, S 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Chillán">Chillan</normalizedToken>
Volcano, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ñuble">Nuble</normalizedToken>
Prov., 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-36.918">S 36.918°</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="-71.429">W 71.429°</geoCoordinate>
, 1500m, 6-31.i.1963, L.E. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Peña">Pena</normalizedToken>
(AMNH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="96" pageNumber="97" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">Some males have the ventral margin of the metatibia dark. Females often have the gradulus of T1 dark, and usually lack the brown spots on the clypeus and below the anterior tentorial pit.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="96" pageNumber="97" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">Southern Andean Cordillera, from Laguna del Maule (Region VII) southwest to Valle Las Trancas (Region VIII); 783-2541m a.s.l.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="96" pageNumber="97" type="ecology">
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">Ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">
Collected on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Hydrophyllaceae" genus="Phacelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Phacelia" order="Boraginales" pageId="96" pageNumber="97" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Phacelia</taxonomicName>
(12 records). Recorded December to January and March.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="96" pageNumber="97" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="96" pageNumber="97">
The specific epithet honours the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="author’s">author's</normalizedToken>
father, W.F. Randolph Monckton, who nurtured an interest in science and geography, and encouraged a desire for knowledge. It is formed in the genitive singular case.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>