<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.459.8169" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b98eb4f7-4f19-4669-985a-305fbdb27739" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152056780" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-459-1" ID-ZBK="8275F1D6ADC94B8C894C8F13CA053A83" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:32726748-44E8-452C-A4FC-C461A084B73B" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-459-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 459" ModsDocTitle="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi sp. n., a new species from Eastern China (Chilopoda, Lithobiomorpha, Lithobiidae)" checkinTime="1451245018309" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Ma, Huiqin, Pei, Sujian, Hou, Xiaojie &amp; Zhu, Tiegang" docDate="2014" docId="45EE56D599B8BA361C0EDCBCE8CBC26E" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 459: 1-10" docOrigin="ZooKeys 459" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.459.8169" docTitle="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi Ma, Pei, Hou &amp; Zhu, 2014, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="32726748-44E8-452C-A4FC-C461A084B73B" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" masterDocId="FFE9BD531538FFA0FF9DFFC7FFC3FFC0" masterDocTitle="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi sp. n., a new species from Eastern China (Chilopoda, Lithobiomorpha, Lithobiidae)" masterLastPageNumber="10" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" updateTime="1643672857308" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi sp. n., a new species from Eastern China (Chilopoda, Lithobiomorpha, Lithobiidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ma, Huiqin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Pei, Sujian</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Hou, Xiaojie</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhu, Tiegang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>459</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>10</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.459.8169</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.459.8169</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-459-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">8275F1D6ADC94B8C894C8F13CA053A83</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8275F1D6ADC94B8C894C8F13CA053A83</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152056780" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:32726748-44E8-452C-A4FC-C461A084B73B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/45EE56D599B8BA361C0EDCBCE8CBC26E" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Taxon classification Animalia Lithobiomorpha Lithobiidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/32726748-44E8-452C-A4FC-C461A084B73B" class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhangi" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="1" pageNumber="2">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-6
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Holotype. ♀ (Figure 1), body length 8.0 mm, cephalic fig 0.5 mm long, 0.5 mm broad, Nanshan Park, Yantai City, Shandong Province, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="37.083332">37°05'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="121.066666">121°04'E</geoCoordinate>
, 27 m, 5 July 2005, leg. Huiqin Ma. Paratypes. 2 ♀♀, same data as holotype.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Other material. 15 ♀♀, 2 ♂♂, Wuyishan County, Nanping City, Fujian Province, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="27.716667">27°43'N</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="118.01667">118°01'E</geoCoordinate>
, 238 m, 10 August 2010, leg. Feng Zhang and Huiqin Ma.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="3" start="start">Etymology</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">The specific name is a patronym in honor of the myriapodologist Professor Chongzhou Zhang, Academician at the Chinese Academy of Sciences.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
A 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius)" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subGenus" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius)</taxonomicName>
species with body length 7.0-8.0 mm, antennae composed of 15-19 articles; 5-6 ocelli on each side, arranged in 2 irregular rows, the terminal ocellus comparatively large; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tömösváry’s">Toemoesvary's</normalizedToken>
organ moderately small, slightly smaller than adjoining ocelli; 2+2 coxosternal teeth; porodonts moderately slender, posterolateral to the most lateral teeth; posterior angles of all tergites without triangular projections; coxal pores 1222, oval to round; female gonopods with 2+2 small, coniform spurs; terminal claw of the third article tridentate; male gonopods short and small, with 1 long seta on the terminal segment.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Body length: 7.0-8.0 mm, cephalic fig 0.5-0.6 mm long, 0.5-0.6 mm wide.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Colour: basal antennal articles lavender, the 7-8 article gradually turning to yellow-brown, distalmost article yellow-brown; tergites pale brown to chestnut-brown; cephalic fig, TT1, 14 and 15 yellow-brown; pleural region pale grey to lavender; sternites pale grey to gray; distal part of forcipules brown, basal and proximal parts of forcipules, forcipular coxosternite and SS 14 and 15 pale yellow-brown with greyish hue; all legs lavender, the distal of every article of all legs slightly dark, the tarsus of all legs yellow-brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Antennae: 15-19 articles (Figure 1); basal article slightly longer than wide, second one markedly longer than wide, following articles gradually shortening, distal article up to 2.0-2.5 times as long as wide. Abundant setae on the antennal surface, less so on the basal articles, gradually increasing in density to about sixth article, then more or less constant.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Cephalic fig smooth, convex, width approximately equal to length; tiny setae emerging from pores scattered very sparsely over the whole surface; frontal marginal ridge with shallow anterior median furrow; short to long setae scattered along the marginal ridge of the cephalic fig; lateral marginal ridge discontinuous, posterior marginal ridge moderately broader, straight or slightly bulging.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Five–six">Five-six</normalizedToken>
oval to rounded ocelli on each side (Figure 3) in two irregular rows; the terminal ocellus comparatively large; other ocelli about equal in size apart the ocelli adjoining to the ventral; all ocelli domed, translucent, usually darkly pigmented.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tömösváry’s">Toemoesvary's</normalizedToken>
organ situated at the anterolateral margin of the cephalic fig, slightly smaller than the adjoining ocelli and lying well apart from them (Figure 3-To).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Coxosternite subtrapezoidal (Figure 2), anterior margin narrow; median diastema moderately deep, V-shaped; anterior margin with 2+2 teeth; porodonts slender, lying posterolateral to the most lateral teeth (Figure 4); some long setae scattered on the ventral side of coxosternite.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
All tergites smooth, without wrinkles, backside slightly hunched; T 1 posterolaterally narrower than anterolaterally, generally trapeziform, narrower than T 3 and the cephalic fig, the cephalic fig slightly wider than T 3 or equal to T 3; posterior margin of T 1 straight or slightly convex, its posterior marginal ridge continuous; posterior margin of TT 3, 5, 8, 10, 12 and 14 shallow concave, posterior marginal ridge of TT 3, 5, 8, 10 and 12 discontinuous; all posterior angles generally rounded, without 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">triangular</pageBreakToken>
projections; lateral marginal ridge of all tergites continuous (Figure 1); tiny setae scattered very sparsely over the surface.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Posterior side of sternites narrower than the anterior one, generally trapeziform, comparatively smooth, setae emerging from pores scattered very sparsely on the surface, slightly thicker setae on the surface of the anterior part of each sternite; A pair of longer setae approximately symmetrical on the surface of both the anterior and the posterior part of each sternite; 2-3 longer setae on both anterior lateral borders, 1-2 comparatively long setae scattered sparsely on posterior margin of sternites.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Legs strong, tarsal articulation not defined on legs 1-13, tarsal articulation well defined on legs 14-15; all legs with fairly long curved claws; anterior and posterior ac 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="5" start="start">cessory</pageBreakToken>
spines on legs 1-14; anterior accessory spine moderately long and slender, the posterior one slightly strong; the anterior accessory spines form relatively large angles with the pretarsus, the posterior accessory spines form relatively small angles with the pretarsus; no anterior accessory spines on legs 15. Short to comparatively long setae scattered very sparsely over the surface of all segments of all legs, more setae scattered on the surface of tarsus, slightly thick setae arranged in a row on the ventral side of tarsus; legs 14 and 15 absence of secondary sexual characters on femur or tibia, obvious thicker and stronger than other legs, tarsus 1 about 3.3-4.5 times as long as wide, tarsus 2 about 65%-82% the length of tarsus on legs 15. Leg plectrotaxy as in Table 1.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Coxal pores 1222, round or slightly ovate, coxal pore field in a relatively flat surface.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Female S 15 anterolaterally broader than posterolaterally, generally trapeziform, posteromedially straight, generally yellow-brown; short to long setae scattered sparsely on the surface and the lateral margin, 2 longer setae on posterior lateral borders; sternite of genital segment usually well chitinised, wider than long; relatively long setae scattered over the ventral surface of the genital segment, few setae near S 15, regularly fringed with longer setae along the posterior margin; posterior margin of genital sternite deeply concave between the condyles of gonopods, except for a small, median approximately triangular bulge. Gonopods: first article fairly broad, bearing 7-8 long setae arranged in three irregular rows; 2+2 moderately small, blunt, coniform spurs, inner spur slightly smaller than the outer (Figure 4); second article with 3-4 rather long setae, arranged in two irregular rows on the ventral side, third article with 2 comparatively long setae lying on the ventral side, terminal claw tridentate, the inner broader than the outer (Figure 5).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Male S 15 posterolaterally narrower than anterolaterally, generally trapeziform, posteromedially straight, sparsely covered with short to long setae; the sternite of the genital segment wider than long, usually well sclerotised. Posterior margin quite deeply concave between the gonopods, without a medial bulge; comparatively long setae evenly scattered on the ventral surface of the genital segment, few setae near S 15, gonopod short, consisting of a small bulge, with two long setae, apically slightly sclerotised (Figure 6).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="6" start="start">Habitat</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
The specimens were collected in a 
<taxonomicName class="Pinopsida" family="Pinaceae" genus="Larix" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Larix" order="Pinales" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Larix</taxonomicName>
forest. The species inhabits moderately moist habitats under roadside stones and forest floor.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
The new species is morphologically close to 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) songi" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="songi" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) songi</taxonomicName>
Pei, Ma, Shi, Wu, Zhou, 2011 from Province Hebei, China, with which it shares the following traits: 2+2 coxosternal teeth, 2+2 spurs of female gonopods and 1222 coxal pores, the terminal claw of the female gonopods tridentate. It can however be distinguished from the latter by antennae composed of 15+15-19+19 articles versus 19+19-21+21 articles, terminal claw of female gonopods inner tooth broader than the outer vs dorsal and ventral tooth about same in size, ventral plectrotaxy 01320, dorsal plectrotaxy 10210 in the 14th legs, 01210 respectively 10200 in 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) songi" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="songi" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) songi</taxonomicName>
. The new species is morphologically close to 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) dziadoszi" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dziadoszi" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) dziadoszi</taxonomicName>
Matic, 1970, from Korea, with which it shares the following traits: antennae composed of 15-20 articles, 2+2 coxosternal teeth, 2+2 spurs of female gonopods, the terminal claw of the female gonopods tridentate. It can however be distinguished from the latter by 5-6 ocelli versus 7 ocelli, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tömösváry’s">Toemoesvary's</normalizedToken>
organ smaller than adjoining ocellus versus larger than adjoining ocellus, 1222 coxal pores other than 3333 coxal pores, male legs 15 absence of secondary sexual characters on femur versus presence secondary sexual characters, ventral plectrotaxy 01320, dorsal plectrotaxy 10210 in the 14th legs, 01321 respectively 10310 in 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) dziadoszi" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dziadoszi" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) dziadoszi</taxonomicName>
. The new species is morphologically close to 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) riedeli" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="riedeli" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) riedeli</taxonomicName>
Matic, 1970, from Korea, with which it shares the following traits: antennae composed of 15-19 articles, 2+2 coxosternal teeth, 2+2 spurs of female gonopods, the terminal claw of the female gonopods tridentate. It can however be distinguished from the latter by 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tömösváry’s">Toemoesvary's</normalizedToken>
organ smaller than adjoining ocellus versus larger than adjoining ocellus, 1222 coxal pores other than 2222 or 3333 coxal pores, male legs 15 absence of secondary sexual characters on femur versus presence secondary sexual characters, ventral plectrotaxy 01320, dorsal plectrotaxy 10210 in the 14th legs, 01210 respectively 10200 in 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) riedeli" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="riedeli" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) riedeli</taxonomicName>
. The new species is morphologically close to 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) mroczkowskii" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mroczkowskii" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) mroczkowskii</taxonomicName>
Matic, 1970, from Korea, with which it shares the following traits: 5-6 ocelli, 2+2 coxosternal teeth, 2+2 spurs of female gonopods, male legs 15 absence of secondary sexual characters on femur. It can however be distinguished from the latter by antennae composed of 15-19 articles versus 20-21 articles, 1222 coxal pores other than 3343 or 4564 coxal pores, the terminal claw of the female gonopods tridentate other than simple, ventral plectrotaxy 01320, dorsal plectrotaxy 10210 in the 14th legs, 01332 respectively 10311 in 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) mroczkowskii" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mroczkowskii" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) mroczkowskii</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Figures 1-6. 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhangi" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 1-5 holotype, female: 1 habitus, dorsal view, scale bar 1 mm; 2 forcipular segment, ventral view, scale bar 500 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; 3 ocelli and 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tömösváry’s">Toemoesvary's</normalizedToken>
organ (To), lateral view, scale bar 250 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; 4 posterior segments and gonopods, ventral view, scale bar 500 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
; 5 terminal claw of right gonopod, dorsal view, scale bar 250 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
; 6 paratype, male: posterior segments and gonopods, ventral view, scale bar 500 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption ID-Table-UUID="90A141AED9AC64E5DCA1B680F19C33A5" httpUri="http://table.plazi.org/id/90A141AED9AC64E5DCA1B680F19C33A5" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Table 1. Leg plectrotaxy of 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Lithobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhangi" subGenus="Monotarsobius">Lithobius (Monotarsobius) zhangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<table pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="2">Legs</th>
<th colspan="5" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">Ventral</th>
<th colspan="5" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">Dorsal</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">C</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">Tr</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">P</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">F</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">Ti</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">C</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">Tr</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">P</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">F</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rowspan="1">Ti</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>