<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="587115f4-9410-4574-9f17-f0c9296f0447" ModsDocID="5959" checkinTime="1243376585186" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1949" docId="4DC650B936203FB6CDD4E3171C25BFBB" docLanguage="en" docName="5959" docOrigin="Annals and Magazine of Natural History 2" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5959/5959.pdf" docTitle="Technomyrmex primroseae Donisthorpe, 1949, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="274" masterDocId="A3F0C6F750B9C23088FB938E11D20C02" masterDocTitle="A new Camponotus from Madagascar and a small collection of ants from Mauritius." masterLastPageNumber="275" masterPageNumber="271" pageNumber="273" updateTime="1569525771751" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new Camponotus from Madagascar and a small collection of ants from Mauritius.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1949</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>271</mods:start>
<mods:end>275</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5959/5959.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">5959</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:4DC650B936203FB6CDD4E3171C25BFBB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4DC650B936203FB6CDD4E3171C25BFBB">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="273">
No. 126. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:36839" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Technomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Technomyrmex primroseae Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Technomyrmex primroseae Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="273" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="primroseae">Technomyrmex primroseae</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="273">[[ worker ]]. Black, rather shining, mandibles, antennae and legs dirty pale yellow, the petiole brighter yellow. Sculpture: head and gaster finely reticulate, thorax more distinctly so, clothed with fine golden pubescence, which is more pronounced on gaster and a few short outstanding hairs, more being present on gaster.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="274" pageNumber="273">Head oval, somewhat narrower in front than behind, broadest a little behind eyes, posterior angles rounded,. posterior border excised in middle; mandibles moderately long, triangular apical tooth sharp and curved, masticatory border armed with a number of small sharp teeth, the second and fourth being longer than the third; clypeus fairly large, anterior border excised in middle, posterior border extending in a point between the frontal carinae; frontal area small but distinct; frontal carinae short, low, fairly wide apart, parallel; eyes large, round, rather prominent, situated in front of sides of head; antennal 12 - jointed, scape long, extending beyond posterior border of head, funiculus with first joint longer than third, second joint the shortest, rest of joints gradually increasing in length and breadth, last joint as long as the two preceding taken together. Thorax with a neck, longer than broad, constricted in middle, broadest at humeral angles; pronotum large, transverse, convex, anterior border margined, posterior border semicircular encircling mesonotum; mesonotum shorter and narrower than pronotum, a little longer than broad, slightly convex; sutures between pro- and mesonotum and meso- and epinotum well marked, especially the latter; epinotum with angle between dorsal surface and declivity well marked, declivity abrupt, somewhat flat, considerably longer than dorsal surface. Petiole narrow, flat, slightly longer than broad, scale entirely rudimentary; gaster oval, overhanging the petiole, pointed at apex, fifth segment extending a little beyond the fourth, cloacial opening terminal. Long. 2.5 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="274">Described in honour of my cousin Primrose Griffiths (nee Donisthorpe), who has always taken an interest in my work, from sixteen workers. Mauritius on Le Pouce Mt., November 2 nd, 1948, nesting in a dead tree stump (R. Mamet).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>