<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047585" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="7D88C21FEAE6F0A2335628CC847D8954" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio atricoxa" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="28" lastPageNumber="29" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" updateTime="1643530488545" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047585" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:7D88C21FEAE6F0A2335628CC847D8954" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7D88C21FEAE6F0A2335628CC847D8954" lastPageId="28" lastPageNumber="29" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">
<subSubSection pageId="26" pageNumber="27" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="27">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/F96ABF90-FFB8-4580-9D55-43F1387D40C9" authority="Dodd" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio atricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atricoxa">Oxyscelio atricoxa (Dodd)</taxonomicName>
Figures 11-14; Morphbank28
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="26" pageNumber="27" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="27">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Sceliomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sceliomorpha atricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atricoxa">Sceliomorpha atricoxa</taxonomicName>
Dodd, 1914: 104 (original description); 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieffer, JJ" journalOrPublisher="Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co., Berlin" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" title="Scelionidae. Das Tierreich. Vol. 48." year="1926">Kieffer 1926</bibRefCitation>
: 303, 308 (description, keyed); 
<bibRefCitation author="Naumann, ID" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Linnean Society of New South Wales" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="69 - 72" title="Type specimens of Australian Hymenoptera (Insecta) transferred from the Macleay Museum, University of Sydney, to the Australian National Insect Collection, Canberra." volume="114" year="1994">Naumann et al. 1994</bibRefCitation>
: 71 (holotype transferred to ANIC).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="27">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio atricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atricoxa">Oxyscelio atricoxa</taxonomicName>
(Dodd): 
<bibRefCitation author="Dodd, AP" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="71 - 81" title="The genus Oxyscelio Kieffer, its synonymy and species, with a description of one new genus (Hymenoptera: Proctotrypoidea)." volume="42" year="1931">Dodd 1931</bibRefCitation>
: 74 (generic transfer); 
<bibRefCitation author="Galloway, ID" journalOrPublisher="Queensland Journal of Agricultural and Animal Sciences" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="83 - 114" title="The types of Australian species of the subfamily Scelioninae (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae)." volume="33" year="1976">Galloway 1976</bibRefCitation>
: 99 (type information).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="28" lastPageNumber="29" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Female. Body length 3.55-8.7 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: longer than broad. A5: longer than broad; as long as broad.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: granulate. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: granulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="27" lastPageNumber="28" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="27" pageNumber="28" start="start">Microsculpture</pageBreakToken>
of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching near apex of T5; reaching middle of T6. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="28" lastPageNumber="29" pageId="27" pageNumber="28">
T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 5. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: densely foveolate, longitudinal sculpture irregular. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally 
<pageBreakToken pageId="28" pageNumber="29" start="start">striate</pageBreakToken>
to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Male. unknown.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="28" pageNumber="29">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">
Figures 11-14. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio atricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atricoxa">Oxyscelio atricoxa</taxonomicName>
(Dodd), female (OSUC 429876) 11 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 12 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 13 Metasoma, dorsal view. Female (OSUC 429885) 14 Head, anterior view. Morphbank28
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="28" pageNumber="29" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">
Both sexes: Frontal depression shallow, not parallel-sided, many interrupted transverse carinae present, including some above dorsal separator; submedian carina weakly indicated but complete. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by weak rugae. Occipital carina complete, weakly convex medially. Metascutellum deeply concave, emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein absent. Coxa darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female only: A3 much longer than pedicel. A4 longer than broad, A5 nearly as long as broad. Mesoscutellum without granulate sculpture. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae or with raised sculpture obscuring them. T6 without metasomal flanges, main body of tergum not separated from apical rim. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T5 or middle of T6. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio atricoxa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atricoxa">Oxyscelio atricoxa</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio conjuncti" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="conjuncti">Oxyscelio conjuncti</taxonomicName>
mainly in having a shallower frontal depression, finer and denser mesoscutal and mesoscutellar foveae, and by the shape of T6. Males are unknown, but likely differ from those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio conjuncti" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="conjuncti">Oxyscelio conjuncti</taxonomicName>
mostly in depth of the frontal depression.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="28" pageNumber="29" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=5006]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="28" pageNumber="29" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="29">Holotype, female, S. atricoxa: AUSTRALIA: NSW, Sydney, Elizabeth Bay, no date, ANIC DB 32-012551 (deposited in ANIC). Other material: AUSTRALIA: 67 females, OSUC 429912-429917, 429919 (ANIC); OSUC 462560 (CNCI); OSUC 281687-281688, 309399 (OSUC); QDPC 0-165655, 0-165726, 0-165754 (QDPC); OSUC 429918 (QMBA); OSUC 437012 (UQIC); OSUC 429876-429911, 429920-429921, 448968-448980 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>