<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.577.7301" ID-GBIF-Dataset="82b5c257-743d-409a-9837-b7dceebaf21f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127876816" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-577-63" ID-ZBK="E323AAB6276D44A19BFBFD08204FA79E" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B19428FC-A83E-4E18-86BF-494F6EA075AC" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-577-63" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 577" ModsDocTitle="Tachysphexaustriacus Kohl, 1892 and T.pompiliformis (Panzer, 1804) (Hymenoptera, Crabronidae) are a complex of fourteen species in Europe and Turkey" checkinTime="1459885279662" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Straka, Jakub" docDate="2016" docId="6C1FB896DA7520916CA034A2F77C6EF9" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 577: 63-123" docOrigin="ZooKeys 577" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.577.7301" docTitle="Tachysphex nobilis Straka, 2016, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="B19428FC-A83E-4E18-86BF-494F6EA075AC" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="30" lastPageNumber="93" masterDocId="4C34FFFFFFB3FF83EE5C096776782D3C" masterDocTitle="Tachysphexaustriacus Kohl, 1892 and T. pompiliformis (Panzer, 1804) (Hymenoptera, Crabronidae) are a complex of fourteen species in Europe and Turkey" masterLastPageNumber="123" masterPageNumber="63" pageId="26" pageNumber="89" updateTime="1643604143908" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Tachysphexaustriacus Kohl, 1892 and T. pompiliformis (Panzer, 1804) (Hymenoptera, Crabronidae) are a complex of fourteen species in Europe and Turkey</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Straka, Jakub</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>577</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>63</mods:start>
<mods:end>123</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.577.7301</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.577.7301</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-577-63</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">E323AAB6276D44A19BFBFD08204FA79E</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">E323AAB6276D44A19BFBFD08204FA79E</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127876816" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B19428FC-A83E-4E18-86BF-494F6EA075AC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6C1FB896DA7520916CA034A2F77C6EF9" lastPageId="30" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="26" pageNumber="89">
<subSubSection pageId="26" pageNumber="89" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="89">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Crabronidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="26" pageNumber="89" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="26" pageNumber="89">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/B19428FC-A83E-4E18-86BF-494F6EA075AC" class="Insecta" family="Crabronidae" genus="Tachysphex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tachysphex nobilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="26" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nobilis">Tachysphex nobilis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="26" pageNumber="89">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 7, 19, 33, 40, 47, 73, 99, 108
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="28" lastPageNumber="91" pageId="27" pageNumber="90" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="90">
<pageBreakToken pageId="27" pageNumber="90" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
material.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="28" lastPageNumber="91" pageId="27" pageNumber="90">
<typeStatus pageId="27" pageNumber="90">Holotype</typeStatus>
: ♀, Hungary: &quot;HUNGARY centr. / 
<normalizedToken originalValue="ÖRKENY">OERKENY</normalizedToken>
env. / 15.VI.2007 / P. Bogusch lgt. // ♀ 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Crabronidae" genus="Tachysphex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tachysphex" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="27" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Tachysphex</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="nobilis" pageId="27" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="nobilis">nobilis</taxonomicName>
/ sp.n. / Jakub Straka det.2009 // ZSM / HYM 23689&quot;. 
<typeStatus pageId="27" pageNumber="90">Holotype</typeStatus>
in ZSM. 
<typeStatus pageId="27" pageNumber="90">Paratypes</typeStatus>
: Bulgaria: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Albena-Kraněvo">Albena-Kranevo</normalizedToken>
, 1 ♀, 4. vii. 1978, Z. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pádr">Padr</normalizedToken>
lgt., OLML; Asenovgrad env., 1 ♂, 15. vii. 1969, K. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Deneš">Denes</normalizedToken>
lgt., JSPC; Borika SW, Sredna Gora Mts., 1 ♂, 6. viii. 2010, T. Ljubomirov lgt., IBER; Konstantinovo N, 1 ♂, 26. vi. 2012, T. Ljubomirov lgt., IBER; Kurtovo Konare S, 1♂, 3. viii. 2012, T. Ljubomirov lgt., IBER; Pasarel NW, Isskar valey, 1 ♂, 2 ♀♀, 6. vi. 2009, T. Ljubomirov lgt., IBER; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Slančev">Slancev</normalizedToken>
Brjag env., 3 ♀♀, 14. vii. 1971, 1 ♂, 2. vii. 1978, Z. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pádr">Padr</normalizedToken>
lgt., OLML Z. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pádr">Padr</normalizedToken>
lgt., OLML, 2 ♀♀, 10. vii. 1983, P. Tyrner lgt., PTLC, 1 ♀, 30. v. 1989, J. Halada lgt., OLML; Vlahi, 1 ♂, 3 ♀♀, 14. viii. 1993, M. Halada lgt., 
<pageBreakToken pageId="28" pageNumber="91" start="start">JSPC</pageBreakToken>
; Vlahinska Reka, Strouma valey, 1 ♂, 29. vi. 2008, T. Ljubomirov lgt., IBER; Sandanski env., 1 ♂, 13. vii. 1966, M. Kocourek lgt., OLML; Czech Republic: Mor.mer., Bzenec env., 1 ♂, 14. vi. 1942, 1 ♀, 21. vi. 1942, A. Hoffer lgt., OLML, JSPC; Vracov env., 1 ♀, 21. viii. 1942, A. Hoffer lgt., OLML; Greece: Petritsio SE, Strymon valley, Hellas prov., 1 ♀, 21. v. 2009, G. Ramel lgt., IBER; Hungary: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Örkeny">Oerkeny</normalizedToken>
, puszta, 1 ♂, 18. v. 1985, J. Halada lgt., JSPC; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Iszák">Iszak</normalizedToken>
, 1 ♀, 18. v. 1989, Z. Karas lgt., ZKZC; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Sándorfalva">Sandorfalva</normalizedToken>
env., 1 ♀, 19. v. 1988, Z. Karas lgt., ZKZC; Poland: Karwia, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Władysławowo">Wladyslawowo</normalizedToken>
, Baltic see coast, 1 ♀, 24. vi. 1996, R. Dobosz lgt., USMB; Pasturka, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pińczów">Pinczow</normalizedToken>
env., Malopolska Upland, 1 ♀, 10. vi. 1998, R. Dobosz lgt., USMB; Pustynia 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Błędowska">Bledowska</normalizedToken>
, Gmina Klucze, 1 ♀, 30. vi. 1992, W. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Żyła">Żyla</normalizedToken>
lgt., USMB; Sarbinowo, Baltic see coast, 1 ♀, 18. viii. 1995, J. Batleja lgt., USMB; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Toruń-Glinki">Torun-Glinki</normalizedToken>
, 1 ♀, 14. vi. 2011, P. Olszewski lgt., JSPC; Wicie, Baltic see coast, 1 ♀, 18. vii. 2004, W. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Żyła">Żyla</normalizedToken>
lgt., USMB; Wicie, Baltic see coast, 1 ♀, 23. vii. 2004, W. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Żyła">Żyla</normalizedToken>
lgt., USMB; Wicie, Baltic see coast, 1 ♀, 28. vii. 2004, W. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Żyła">Żyla</normalizedToken>
lgt., USMB; Wicie, Baltic see coast, 1 ♂, 1 ♀, 25. vii. 2004, W. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Żyła">Żyla</normalizedToken>
lgt., USMB, JSPC; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Wisełka">Wiselka</normalizedToken>
env., Wolin, Baltic see coast, 1 ♂, 1 ♀, 25. vii. 1997, R. Dobosz lgt., USMB; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Władysławowo">Wladyslawowo</normalizedToken>
, 1 ♂, 30. vi. 1993, R. Dobosz lgt., USMB; Turkey: Ahlat, near Van lake, 1 ♂, 14. vii. 1996, P. Tyrner, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Voříšek">Vorisek</normalizedToken>
lgt., PTLC; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Çamardı">Camardi</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Niğde">Nigde</normalizedToken>
prov., 1 ♂, 13. vii. 1997, M. Halada lgt., OLML; Ilhara env., valley, Aksaray prov., 2 ♂♂, 13. vi. 2008, M. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Obořil">Oboril</normalizedToken>
lgt., JSPC.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="28" pageNumber="91" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="91">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="91">
Poland: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Wisełka">Wiselka</normalizedToken>
env., Wolin, Baltic see coast, 1 ♂, 25. vii. 1997, R. Dobosz lgt., USMB; Turkey: Ilhara env., valley, Aksaray prov., 1 ♂, 13. vi. 2008, M. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Obořil">Oboril</normalizedToken>
lgt., JSPC.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="28" pageNumber="91" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="91">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="91">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Crabronidae" genus="Tachysphex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tachysphex nobilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nobilis">Tachysphex nobilis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is most similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Crabronidae" genus="Tachysphex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tachysphex bohemicus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bohemicus">Tachysphex bohemicus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Crabronidae" genus="Tachysphex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tachysphex jokischianus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jokischianus">Tachysphex jokischianus</taxonomicName>
(Panzer) in having fine and dense body sculptures and sparsely punctate apical margin of tergum V in female. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Crabronidae" genus="Tachysphex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tachysphex nobilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="28" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nobilis">Tachysphex nobilis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is a characteristic and relatively easily recognizable species. It is generally slender in body, finely, densely punctate throughout, and possess an insignificantly convex clypeus, with the bevel small in the female and nearly absent in the male. Both sexes also have the gena dorsally inconspicuous, converging behind the compound eyes. The lateral emargination of the clypeal lip in the female is round, not angulated. The propodeal dorsum in the male has a finely sculptured longitudinal area posteromedially, which appears slightly shinier than the adjacent parts of the propodeum.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="29" lastPageNumber="92" pageId="28" pageNumber="91" type="description of female (holotype)">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="91">
Description of female (
<typeStatus pageId="28" pageNumber="91">holotype</typeStatus>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="91">Body length: 8.9 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="29" lastPageNumber="92" pageId="28" pageNumber="91">
Head. Clypeus slightly convex, top at clypeal midlength; basomedian area cover majority of space of clypeus, as densely punctate as lateral section; bevel very small, slightly convex to flat, only about 2-3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as clypeal lip, slightly longer medially than laterally, with few large punctures, ending far from base of clypeus, shiny; lip insignificanly arcuate to nearly straight, with faint lateral incision, separate from bevel by punctate groove, WML:LCL = 1.6, WCL:WML = 1.8. Supraclypeal area flat, finely and densely punctate, punctures ill defined, interspaces microsculptured, dull. Supraantennal tubercle small, slightly elevated on inner side. Frons uniformly, very densely punctate, punctures well defined, less than half diameter apart, interspaces uniform in size, dull; frontal median line distinct, shiny, not impressed. Vertex finely, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="29" pageNumber="92" start="start">densely</pageBreakToken>
punctate, punctures well defined, half to less than half diameter apart, interspaces finely microsculptured, slightly shiny. Vertex setae short, semierect, about 0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
MOD; postocellar impression well developed, widely Y-shaped; vertex slightly wider than long; WV:LV = 1.2. Gena dorsally well developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="92">
Mesosoma. Scutum without distinct anterior impression; scutum and scutellum densely punctate, punctures well defined, less than half diameter apart, interspaces well developed and relatively uniform in size, microsculptured, slightly shiny, setae about 1.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
MOD or less. Mesopleuron coarsely microsculptured, without distinct punctures; hypoepimeral area finely rugose with indistinct, longitudinal, irregular ridges, without punctures; ventral part of mesopleuron finely, densely punctate, with punctures ill defined, less than one diameter apart, interspaces small, slightly shiny. Propodeal dorsum relatively finely, regularly rugose, with short irregular longitudinal ridges basally, dull, posteromedially with transverse ridges on small longitudinal slightly shiny area; propodeal side regularly longitudinally ridged, ridges inconspicuous basally, microsculptured, dull; posteromedial margin of propodeal dorsum elevated, slightly produced between marginal ridges, marginal ridges positioned nearly horizontally above groove on posterior surface. Legs densely punctate, punctures small; forebasitarsal rake light reddish, with three apical spines, one preapical and one or two additional ones. Wings slightly infumate, yellowish, with brown veins.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="92">Metasoma. Terga I-III with distinct silvery, apical faciae; terga I-II very densely and finely micropunctate, punctures ill-defined but distinct, interspaces microsculptured, slightly shiny; apical depressions well developed, with distinct micropunctures; sculpture of terga III-V distinctly coarser than on previous terga, also more densely punctate; tergum V coarsely punctate, punctures ill-defined, but large, half to one diameter apart, interspaces microsculptured, apical depression of tergum V very sparsely, finely punctate. Pygidium of usual size, sparsely punctate, punctures large, ill defined, interspaces microsculptured basally, but unsculptured in apical half, slightly shiny to shiny. Central part of sternum II with several large punctures, interspaces microsculptured, shiny; lateral part slightly shiny, densely micropunctate; remaining sterna with uniform sculpture similar to that on sternum II, but more or less reduced laterally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="92">Coloration. Central part of mandibles, terga and sterna I-III red. Distal tarsomeres are dark red. Tegulae brown translucent. Apical parts of terga I-III slightly translucent. Remaining body parts all black.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="92">Variation of females: Body length: 7.2-9.0 mm. Antenna relatively short, LA3:WA3 = 1.9-2.1, LA5:WA5 = 2.9-3.0. In general, the species is not significantly variable in key characters. There is the usual variation in size dependent characters like the number of spins on foretarsal rake. The shape of the lateral emargination of the clypeal lip is one of a few variable characters; it can be well developed to nearly absent, but never angulated. The pygidium is slightly variable in width and sculpture; it is of usual shape in most specimens with distinct microsculpture, slightly shiny in basal half, but also wider and bright shiny in some specimens.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="30" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="29" pageNumber="92" type="description of male">
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="92">Description of male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="92">Body length: 5.4-6.8 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="30" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="29" pageNumber="92">
Head. Mandibular inner margin with one distinct rectangular tooth and distinct furrow next to tooth distally. Clypeus very slightly convex (appearing nearly flat), uni 
<pageBreakToken pageId="30" pageNumber="93" start="start">formly</pageBreakToken>
curved, top at about clypeal midlength; basomedian area dominant on clypeus, densely, uniformly punctate; bevel nearly or completely absent, reduced to shiny area ventromedially; lip arcuate or slightly sinuate, with small rectangular lateral corner, lip separated from bevel by distinct, punctate groove; WML:LCL = 0.9-1.2, WCL:WML = 2.2-2.4. Supraclypeal area groove-like, slightly concave, supraantennal tubercles slightly elevated ventromedially, circular; surface coarsely microsculptured with indistinct punctures, dull. Antenna relatively short, LA3:WA3 = 1.5-1.6, LA5:WA5 = 1.9-2.1. Frons finely punctate, punctures well defined, half to less than half diameter apart, interspaces relatively uniform in size; frontal median line distinct, narrow, finely or not impressed, shiny. Vertex finely punctate, punctures well defined, one to less than one diameter apart, interspaces microsculptured, slightly shiny to dull. Vertex setae short, semierect, less than 1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
MOD; postocellar impression distinctly impressed, but shallow, open widely V to Y-shaped; vertex moderately wider than long, WV:LV = 1.5. Gena dorsally inconspicuous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="93">
Mesosoma. Scutum without distinct anterior impression; scutum and scutellum densely punctate, punctures well defined, most punctures less than half diameter apart, interspaces distinct, microsculptured, slightly shiny to dull, setae about 1.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
MOD or less. Mesopleuron coarsely microsculptured, with distinct or indistinct punctures in lower areas, most punctures ill defined, interspaces dull; hypoepimeral area coarsely microsculptured to finely rugose, dull; ventral part of mesopleuron densely punctate, punctures small ill defined, interspaces slightly shiny. Propodeal dorsum finely irregularly areolate to rugose, without longitudinal ridges, posteromedially with finely sculptured longitudinal area, which appears slightly shinier than adjacent areas; lateral surface of propodeum coarsely microsculptured, with or without ill defined longitudinal ridges, dull; posteromedial margin of propodeal dorsum elevated, but not produced between marginal ridges, marginal ridges positioned nearly horizontally above groove on posterior side. Legs densely punctate, punctures small; forefemoral notch light red and large, semicircular, its diameter is usually longer than distance that separates it from forefemoral base, central part of notch slightly elevated, anterior and posterior margins lined by small ledge, nearly indistinct in some specimens, notch surface without distinct setae, microsculptured, dull. Wings slightly infumate, veins brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="93">Metasoma. Terga I-III with silvery apical faciae. Apical depressions of terga distinct, micropunctate similarly to that on tergal disk. Terga I-III densely, distinctly micropunctate, punctures ill defined, interspaces microsculptured, slightly shiny; sculpture of terga IV-VII slightly coarser than on previous terga, also punctures slightly denser. Sterna uniformly punctate, nearly like terga.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="93">Coloration. Apical part of mandible, terga and sterna I-III and forefemoral notch red. Distal tarsomeres reddish. Tegulae brown to reddish. Apical parts of all terga and tegulae translucent. Remaining body parts all black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="93" type="geographic distribution">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="93">Geographic distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="93">Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Greece, Hungary, Poland and Turkey.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="30" pageNumber="93" type="name derivation">
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="93">Name derivation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="30" pageNumber="93">
The species is named after its uniform sculptures. The species appears as a 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“noble”">&quot;noble&quot;</normalizedToken>
among other species of the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Crabronidae" genus="Tachysphex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tachysphex pompiliformis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="30" pageNumber="93" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pompiliformis">Tachysphex pompiliformis</taxonomicName>
species subgroup.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>