<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b92acfc0-9d67-42c4-9e37-ebd5a53d24b5" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200945" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-719-75" ID-ZBK="36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-719-75" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 719" ModsDocTitle="A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World" checkinTime="1555319501509" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2017" docId="BE9BFC1D909D7A85F7CF6985269E7719" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 719: 75-157" docOrigin="ZooKeys 719" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253" docTitle="Monophylla terminata Say 1835" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="134" masterDocId="5C2D8118751DD235197A6569FFE59A6E" masterDocTitle="A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World" masterLastPageNumber="157" masterPageNumber="75" pageId="56" pageNumber="131" updateTime="1643480888860" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burke, Alan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>719</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>75</mods:start>
<mods:end>157</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-719-75</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200945" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BE9BFC1D909D7A85F7CF6985269E7719" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE9BFC1D909D7A85F7CF6985269E7719" lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="134" pageId="56" pageNumber="131">
<subSubSection pageId="56" pageNumber="131" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="56" pageNumber="131">
<taxonomicName authority="Say, 1835" authorityName="Say" authorityYear="1835" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Monophylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monophylla terminata" order="Coleoptera" pageId="56" pageNumber="131" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="terminata">Monophylla terminata (Say, 1835)</taxonomicName>
Figs 4D, 7C, 10D, 17
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–H">E-H</normalizedToken>
, 20D
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="57" pageNumber="132" type="synonyms">
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">
<pageBreakToken pageId="57" pageNumber="132" start="start">Synonyms</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">
<taxonomicName authority="Olivier, 1790" authorityName="Olivier" authorityYear="1790" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Tillus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tillus (Macrotelus) terminatus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="57" pageNumber="132" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="terminatus" subGenus="Macrotelus">Tillus (Macrotelus) terminatus</taxonomicName>
Say, 1835, original designation, Bost. Journ. Nat. Hist. Mus., p. 160. Synonymized by 
<bibRefCitation author="Wolcott, AB" journalOrPublisher="Field Museum of Natural History, Zoological Series" pageId="78" pageNumber="153" pagination="339 - 401" title="Note on some Cleridae of Middle and North America with descriptions of new species." volume="7" year="1910">Wolcott (1910)</bibRefCitation>
. 
<taxonomicName authority="Le Conte, 1849" authorityName="Le Conte" authorityYear="1849" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Elasmocerus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmocerus terminatus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="57" pageNumber="132" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="terminatus">Elasmocerus terminatus</taxonomicName>
(Say, 1835) designated by 
<bibRefCitation author="LeConte, JL" journalOrPublisher="Annals of the Lyceum of Natural History of New York" pageId="76" pageNumber="151" pagination="9 - 35" title="Synopsis of the Coleopterous insects of the group Cleridae which inhabit the United States." volume="5" year="1849">LeConte 1849</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="57" pageNumber="132" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">Type material not examined.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="57" pageNumber="132" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">&quot;near Council Bluff, on the Missouri River&quot;. Type depository: The type material was destroyed, no lectotype has been designated.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="57" pageNumber="132" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">Canada: Ontario; USA: AL, AR, AZ, DC, FL, GA, IA, IL, IN, KS, KY, LA, MD, MI, MO, MS, NC, NE, NJ, NY, OK, OH, PA, RI, SC, TX, VA, WV. Mexico: Chihuahua, Sinaloa.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="58" lastPageNumber="133" pageId="57" pageNumber="132" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="57" pageNumber="132">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="58" lastPageNumber="133" pageId="57" pageNumber="132">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Monophylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monophylla terminata" order="Coleoptera" pageId="57" pageNumber="132" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="terminata">Monophylla terminata</taxonomicName>
is most similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. pallipes" pageId="57" pageNumber="132" rank="species" species="pallipes">M. pallipes</taxonomicName>
. The two species can be recognized based on antennal differences and integument color. In males of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. terminata" pageId="57" pageNumber="132" rank="species" species="terminata">M. terminata</taxonomicName>
, antennomeres 3-6 are robust and compacted, and antenno 
<pageBreakToken pageId="58" pageNumber="133" start="start">meres</pageBreakToken>
7-9 are serrate (Fig. 4D). In 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. pallipes" pageId="58" pageNumber="133" rank="species" species="pallipes">M. pallipes</taxonomicName>
, antennomeres 3-4 are robust and clavate, and antennomere 5-9 are serrate. In addition, males and females of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. terminata" pageId="58" pageNumber="133" rank="species" species="terminata">M. terminata</taxonomicName>
have the pronotum bicolored, the outer region of the pronotal disc is testaceous to ferrugineous and the median region is piceous to black (Fig. 4D). In 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Monophylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monophylla pallipes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="58" pageNumber="133" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pallipes">Monophylla pallipes</taxonomicName>
, the pronotum is predominantly dark-testaceous to piceous, with the anterior and posterior margins feebly dark-ferrugineous (Fig. 4C), this coloration may be absent in some specimens, with the pronotum completely dark-ferrugineous to almost black.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="59" lastPageNumber="134" pageId="58" pageNumber="133" type="redescription">
<paragraph pageId="58" pageNumber="133">Redescription.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="58" pageNumber="133">Male. Form: Small to moderately large, slender individuals. Color: Head, antennae, legs and scutellum dark testaceous to almost piceous; thorax bicolored, outer region of pronotal disc testaceous to ferrugineous, median region of pronotal disc piceous to black; prosternum testaceous to ferrugineous to almost black; meso and metathorax bicolored, testaceous to ferrugineous and piceous to black; elytra fuscous to black, the anterior half of the epipleural fold testaceous to ferrugineous, some individuals with a pale to yellowish fascia on the median region of the elytral disc that initiates on the epipleural fold and does not reach the elytral suture; abdomen light testaceous to ferrugineous; mouthparts testaceous (Fig. 4D).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="58" pageNumber="133">Head: Including eyes narrower than pronotum; eyes medium-sized, taller than wide, feebly bulging laterally, antennal notch in front of eye emargination; integument conspicuously punctate, punctation wide and shallow; vested with fine, pale, semi-erect and erect setae; antennae composed of 10 antennomeres; second antennomere robust, short; antennomeres 3-6 small, robust, conspicuously compacted; antennomeres 7-9 compacted, serrate, serration gradually increasing toward distal end; last antennomere noticeably enlarged, conspicuously compressed laterally, much longer that remaining antennomeres combined; last antennomere sexually dimorphic (Fig. 4D).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="58" pageNumber="133">Thorax: Pronotum subparallel, expanded at middle, then constricted before posterior margin; pronotum with surface moderately to conspicuously punctate, feebly rugulose; pronotal disc flat; clothed with fine, short, pale and dark, semi-erect setae interspersed with some long and very long, erect, dark setae; anterior transverse depression feebly impressed; subbasal tumescence absent (Fig. 7C). Prosternum rugose, as long as wide; punctation fine to moderately coarse, shallow; integument clothed with fine, long, semi-erect setae. Mesoventrite surface coarsely punctate, punctation coarse and shallow, interstices smooth, shiny; vested with fine, pale, semi-erect setae Metaventrite strongly convex; surface feebly to moderately punctate, punctation small and shallow; clothed with fine, pale, semirecumbent setae; longitudinal depression present, metaventral process absent.. Metepisterna visible throughout their length, not covered by elytra. Scutellum wide, clothed with pale, fine, recumbent setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="59" lastPageNumber="134" pageId="58" pageNumber="133">
Elytra: Anterior margin slightly broader than pronotum; elongate; subparallel, humeri feebly indicated, rounded; sides gradually expanding toward distal end, wider on middle third, then narrowing toward apex; elytral apices subtriangular to moderately rounded; inconspicuously dehiscent to almost confluent; elytral declivity gradual; surface clothed with fine, short, pale and dark, erect setae, intermingled with some scattered long, erect setae; conspicuously punctate, punctations wide and shallow, ir 
<pageBreakToken pageId="59" pageNumber="134" start="start">regularly</pageBreakToken>
arranged, punctations reaching the elytral apex; interstices smooth to feebly rugulose, narrow; epipleural fold gradually narrowing toward apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="134">Legs: Surface of femora smooth, shiny, expanded medially, laterally compressed; feebly clothed with some pale, fine, semi-erect setae, surface shallowly punctate. Tibiae shiny, slender, puncticulate; punctations shallow and small; vestiture consisting of fine, pale, erect and semi-erect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="134">Abdomen: Six visible ventrites. Ventrites 1-4 convex, smooth, shiny, subquadrate, slightly punctate, vested with fine, short, pale, appressed setae; segments not compressed laterally; posterior margins truncate. Fifth visible ventrite convex; subquadrate; integument smooth, shiny, punctate; punctations wide and shallow; vested with fine, pale, recumbent setae; lateral margins oblique, arcuate; posterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate. Sixth visible ventrite small, subquadrate; conspicuously wider than long; surface slightly rugulose, almost flat; clothed with some long, erect setae; vestitures more abundant on anterolateral margins; lateral margins strongly oblique, moderately arcuate; posterior margin broadly, deeply, U-shaped emarginate; posterolateral angles rounded (Fig. 17F). Fifth tergite subquadrate; surface convex; posterior margin broadly, very feeble emarginate. Sixth tergite subquadrate; finely rugulose; surface convex; clothed with some long, fine, pale, dark recumbent setae; lateral margins moderately oblique; posterior margin broadly, deeply, U-shaped emarginate; posterolateral angles rounded (Fig. 17E). Sixth tergite slightly extending beyond apical margin of sixth visible ventrite, covering sixth ventrite in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="134">Aedeagus: Phallobasic apodeme present; phallus with copulatory piece feebly swollen at apex; phallic plate devoid of denticles; intraspicular plate present, elongate; phallobasic apodeme short, expanded distally; phallobase sinuate; parameres free; tegmen incomplete, partially covering the phallus; parameres rounded anteriorly; endophallic struts short, robust, truncate distally (Fig. 20D).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="134">
Sexual dimorphism: Females of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. terminata" pageId="59" pageNumber="134" rank="species" species="terminata">M. terminata</taxonomicName>
show a number of differences with respect to males. The most apparent is the length of the last antennomere; specifically, this antennomere is somewhat shorter in females compared with that of males; additionally, antennomeres 6-9 are moderately large and serrate in females (Fig. 10D), but conspicuously reduced and compressed in males (Fig. 4D). Finally, females have the last abdominal segment broadly rounded, while males have this segment subquadrate in shape and emarginate posteriorly (Fig. 17
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–H">G-H</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="135" pageId="59" pageNumber="134" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="59" pageNumber="134">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="60" lastPageNumber="135" pageId="59" pageNumber="134">
1 female: Taney Co., MO, on wood pile, V-6-1955, B. Miller; 2 females: Brewster Co., TX, Chisos Mountains Basin, Big Bend Nat. Park, VI-15-1948, M. Cazier; 1 female: Terrell Co., TX, Sanderson, VI-12-1948, M. Cazier, 1 male, 1 female: Dimmit Co. TX, Catarina, VI-10-1948, M. Cazier; 1 female: NY, F. Montgomery, VI-17-1910, F. M. Schott; 1 female: Berks Co., PA, Virginville, VI-6-1968, P. Vaurie; 2 males, 1 female: Dekalb Co., GA, reared on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Vitaceae" genus="Vitis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Vitis" order="Vitales" pageId="59" pageNumber="134" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Vitis</taxonomicName>
sp., 1971, J. E. W.; 1 male, 1 female: TN, Coll. Chass Palm, [no collecting date, no collector data]; 1 male: 1 female: Encinal, TX, IX-13-1955, L. Downs; 1 male: Westfield, NJ, VI-8-1956, G. R. Ferguson, 4 males, 4 females: Fort Lee, NJ, 1912, [no collector data]; 1 female: Nutley, NJ, VIII-12, E. L. Dickenson; Denville, NJ, VII-1-1924, F. M. Schott; Greenwood, New Jersey, V-1930, J. A. Grossbeck; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="60" pageNumber="135" start="start">1</pageBreakToken>
male, 3 females: TX, 4 mi E of Mission, on mesquite, IV-16-1974, G. H. Nelson; 1 female: Southern Pines, NC, V-1-1923, A. H. Manee; 1 male: NY, 7-VIII-1886, [no collector data]; 1 male: Comal Co., TX, VI-12-1910, [no collector data]; 1 female: Washington, NJ, VII-16-1958, [no collector data]; 7 males, 5 females: Hummelstown, PA, VI-20-1920, J. N. Knull; 2 males, 1 female: Harrisburg, PA, V-12-1910, J. N. Knull; 1 male, 2 females: Mont Alto, PA, 29-V-1931, J. N. Knull; 1 female: n. Cumberland, PA, [no collecting data], A. Champlain; 1 male: Columbus, OH, VIII-1-1924, J. N. Knull; 4 females: Hocking Co., OH, VI-4-16, J. N. Knull; 4 males, 2 females: Key Largo, FL, V-13, J. N. Knull; 1 female: Lake Corpus Christi, TX, III-3-1961, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Delaware Co., OH, 4-VI, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Starr Co., TX, IV-5-1963, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Brooks, TX, IV-10-1950, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Uvalde Co., TX, VIII-25-1947, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Gillespie Co., TX, V-7-1946, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Valley, NE, VI-30-1938, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males: Lemoyne, PA, III-12-1911, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Brownsville, TX, III-15, J. N. Knull; 2 males: New York, NY, [no collecting date]; G. Beyer; 1 female: Stillwater, OK, V-21-1995, M. Gates; 1 female: Starr Co., TX, 7 mi E El Sauz, V-8-1986, N. M. Downy; 1 male: USA, Marion Co., FL, SR40, at Lynne, IV-17-2007, F. W. Skillman Jr, beating slash; 2 females: San Antonio, TX, VII-4-1968, G. H. Nelson family; Gambier, OH, VI-19-1940, [no collector data]; 2 males, 1 female: Berrien Co., GA, 3 mi E Alapaha, IV-2-4-1973, R. Turnbow; 1 female: Starr Co., TX, Falcon Heights, abandoned park, farm road 2098, [no collecting date], T. C. MacRae; 1 female: Alachua Co., FL, Gainesville, IX-24-1990, M. C. Thomas; 2 males: Taney Co., MO, Henning Cons. Area, White River Balds National Area, T. C. [no collecting date], MacRae; 1 male: Greenbrier Co., WV, Rupert, VIII-31-1992, S. F. Hutchinson; 2 males: Lawrence, KS, summer-1952, attracted to light, S. L. Wood; 1 female: Osage Co., OK, West Bartlesville, V-5-1981, K. Burnham; 1 male: Brazos Co., TX, IV-16-1960, J. N. Knull; 3 males, 4 females: Philadelphia Co., PA, [no collecting date], H. W. Wenzel; 3 males, 2 females: Hummelstown, PA, [no collecting date], J. N. Knull; 1 male: Franklin Co., OH, Columbus, VII-14-1968, [no collector data]; 1 male, 1 female: Carlisle, PA, VI-27-1917, H. R. Kirk; 1 male, 1 female: Benchley, TX, IV-30-1941, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Columbus, OH, VI-24-1967, C. A. Triplehorn; 1 male: Kennedy, TX, IV-1944, R. Klieforth; 2 females: Cameron Co., TX, IV-3-1964, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Lake Corpus Christy, TX, III-24-1965; 2 females: Seneca Co., OH, VII-25-1955, H. W. Hintz; 1 male: Dubuque, IA, VI-16-1955, H. Hintz; 1 male: Essex Co., Ontario, Wheatly, VI-9-1967, K. Stephan; 1 female: Ela, NC, Swan Co., 20-VIII-1954, G. B. Merrill; 1 female: Zapata Co., TX, 4 mi N San Ygnacio, VI-13-1975, R. Turnbow; 1 male: Latimer Co., OK, V-1986, K. Stephan; 1 male: Oxford, MS, V-15-1949, H. V. Weems Jr.; 1 female: Highlands Hamm Station Park, FL, III-5-1957, H. V. Weems Jr.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>