<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.233.3455" ID-GBIF-Dataset="61913f44-91f4-4a47-9d89-b82618bd2684" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152037508" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-233-31" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A382D0D8-F6F7-4BDD-A532-D5A2C31FBCEE" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-233-31" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 233" ModsDocTitle="Paridris Kieffer of the New World (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae)" checkinTime="1451248634579" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Talamas, Elijah J., Masner, Lubomir &amp; Johnson, Norman F." docDate="2012" docId="E89D84C6493D4002271DC63128C2AF18" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 233: 30-91" docOrigin="ZooKeys 233" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.233.3455" docTitle="Paridris lemete Talamas &amp; Masner, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="A382D0D8-F6F7-4BDD-A532-D5A2C31FBCEE" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="62" masterDocId="FF926B4B205EFFB1FFCAFFB9D35A5B21" masterDocTitle="Paridris Kieffer of the New World (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae)" masterLastPageNumber="90" masterPageNumber="31" pageId="29" pageNumber="60" updateTime="1643705255507" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Paridris Kieffer of the New World (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Talamas, Elijah J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>233</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>31</mods:start>
<mods:end>90</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.233.3455</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.233.3455</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-233-31</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">41B7B8BA-FAB7-4FFE-9A71-4AFADCC1573D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152037508" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A382D0D8-F6F7-4BDD-A532-D5A2C31FBCEE" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E89D84C6493D4002271DC63128C2AF18" lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="29" pageNumber="60">
<subSubSection pageId="29" pageNumber="60" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="60">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: A382D0D8-F6F7-4BDD-A532-D5A2C31FBCEE" authority="Talamas &amp; Masner" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paridris lemete" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="29" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lemete">Paridris lemete Talamas &amp; Masner</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="29" pageNumber="60">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 50-5386, 88 Morphbank33
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="29" pageNumber="60" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="60">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="60">Female body length: 2.16-2.35 mm (n=7). Male body length: 1.70-2.35 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="60">Number of basiconic sensilla on A8: 2.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="29" pageNumber="60">Color of head: black; reddish brown. Distal margin of clypeus: serrate. Width of clypeus: equal to or less than width of interantennal process. Lateral corner of clypeus: projecting into acute angle. Development of interantennal process ventrally: connecting with clypeus. Number of mandibular teeth: three. Length of mediofacial striae: not extending above midpoint of eye. Shape of gena in dorsal view: moderately receding behind compound eye. Striae on gena: pronounced. Length of striae on gena: extending above ventral margin of eye. Distribution of microsculpture on head: absent. Length of OOL: less than 2 ocellar diameters. Occipital carina above foramen magnum: present. Anterior margin of occipital carina: comprised of small to miniscule cells. Setation of postgena: sparse. Ventral extent of occipital carina: extending to base of mandible.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="31" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="29" pageNumber="60">
Color of mesosoma: yellow; reddish brown; yellowish brown. Dorsal half of pronotal cervical sulcus: present as smooth furrow. Ventral half of pronotal cervical sulcus: present as line of small to minute cells. Transverse pronotal carina: present in posterior half of pronotum. Shape of pronotal shoulder in dorsal view: narrow and 
<pageBreakToken pageId="30" pageNumber="61" start="start">striplike</pageBreakToken>
. Form of pronotal suprahumeral sulcus: areolate. Macrosculpture of anterior medial mesoscutum: absent. Density of punctation on anterior medial mesoscutum: dense along mesoscutal suprahumeral sulcus, otherwise sparse. Reticulate microfissures on anterior half of medial mesoscutum: absent. Density of punctation on posterior medial mesoscutum: sparse. Notaulus: percurrent, reaching suprahumeral sulcus as a smooth furrow; percurrent, reaching suprahumeral sulcus as a line of punctures; abbreviate, not reaching mesoscutal suprahumeral sulcus. Orientation of notauli: parallel. Shape of notaulus at posterior apex: ovoid. Macrosculpture of mesoscutellum: punctate rugose along margins, smooth medially. Postacetabular sulcus: smoothly 
<pageBreakToken pageId="31" pageNumber="62" start="start">furrowed</pageBreakToken>
. Mesopleural carina: absent. Punctures on posterodorsal mesepimeral area: very fine; absent. Sculpture of mesopleuron anteroventral to femoral depression: smooth with punctures or rugulae along prespiracular sulcus. Sculpture of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Form of metascutellum in female: transverse punctate rugulose lamella, posterior margin approximately straight. Form of metascutellum in male: transverse punctate rugulose lamella, posterior margin approximately straight. Paracoxal and metapleural sulci: separate. Posterior margin of metapleuron below propodeal spiracle: with blunt angle near intersection with metapleural sulcus. Sculpture between metapleural triangle and metapleural sulcus: smooth. Sculpture of metapleural triangle: punctate rugose. Setation of metapleural triangle: sparse. Anterior propodeal projection: absent. Setation of metasomal depression: absent. Lateral propodeal area: raised above plical area and indicated by sparser setation. Plical carina: present. Shape of lateral propodeal area: continuous with prespiracular propodeal area. Sculpture of lateral propodeal area: rugose.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">Color of metasoma: yellow; reddish brown; yellowish brown. Macrosculpture of T1: longitudinally striate. Interstitial sculpture of T1: smooth; finely rugulose. Adornment of horn on T1 in female: longitudinal median carina on dorsal surface, forming small point posteriorly. Macrosculpture of T2 in female: longitudinally striate throughout. Macrosculpture of T2 in male: longitudinally striate throughout. Microsculpture on T2: present. Setal patch of lateral T2: present throughout lateral surface of tergite. Posterior margin of transverse sulcus on T2: straight. Carina along posterior margin of transverse sulcus on T2 in male: present. Carina along posterior margin of transverse sulcus on T2 in female: present. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially in female: weakly longitudinally striate. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally in female: longitudinally striate. Macrosculpture of T3 medially in male: weakly longitudinally striate. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally in male: longitudinally striate. Microsculpture on T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 medially in female: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally in female: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 in male: absent. Macrosculpture of T5 in female: absent. Constriction of apical T6 in female: present. Punctation of T6 in female: densely and finely punctate throughout. Setation of S1: sparsely distributed throughout. Form of S2 felt field: longitudinal row or patch of setigerous punctures. Macrosculpture of S2 medially: longitudinally striate. Macrosculpture of S3: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">Wing development: macropterous. Basal vein in hind wing: spectral. Setation of hind wing: uniform throughout. Length of postmarginalis: approximately equal to length of stigmalis. RS+M in fore wing: spectral.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="62" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paridris lemete" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lemete">Paridris lemete</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paridris aenea" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aenea">Paridris aenea</taxonomicName>
. The additional basiconic sensillum present on A8 provides a straightforward character to separate the females of these species. Males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paridris lemete" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lemete">Paridris lemete</taxonomicName>
are best separated from 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paridris aenea" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aenea">Paridris aenea</taxonomicName>
by the smooth sculpture of the ventral mesopleuron.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="62" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">The species epithet is derived from the Spanish phrase &quot;le mete,&quot; slang in Puerto Rico for &quot;it is awesome&quot;, which we which we consider to be appropriate for this species. The name is treated as a noun in apposition.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="62" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">34</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="62" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">Holotype, female: PUERTO RICO: Aguas Buenas Mpio., guano, Aguas Buenas Cave, 30.V.1974, Berlese funnel, S. Peck, OSUC 334096 (deposited in CNCI). Paratypes: PUERTO RICO: 6 females, 20 males, OSUC 181371, 334086-334089, 334091-334093, 334097, 396069, 396437-396442, 396444-396448 (CNCI); OSUC 334090, 334094-334095, 396443, 396449 (OSUC).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="31" pageNumber="62">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="62">
Figures 50-53. 90 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Paridris" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paridris lemete" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lemete">Paridris lemete</taxonomicName>
, sp. n. 50 Lateral habitus, female holotype (OSUC 334096) 51 Dorsal habitus, female holotype (OSUC 334096) 52 Head, anterior view, female holotype (OSUC 334096) 53 Mesoscutellum, metascutellum, propodeum, T1, T2, dorsolateral view, female (OSUC 334091)
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>