<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.141.1912" ID-GBIF-Dataset="266ee121-66d8-4dbe-8ec3-524a7efc2113" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031710" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-141-53" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34931ABC-632E-4AC7-B3CD-44D8BE899142" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-141-53" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 141" ModsDocTitle="Two new species of genus Ateleute Förster (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) with a key to the Oriental species" checkinTime="1451249740875" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Sheng, Mao-Ling, Broad, Gavin R. &amp; Sun, Shu-Ping" docDate="2011" docId="B9C5A661E1C09D39380420FAE0B9C106" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 141: 53-64" docOrigin="ZooKeys 141" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.141.1912" docTitle="Ateleute ferruginea Sheng, Broad &amp; Sun, sp.n." docType="treatment" docUuid="34931ABC-632E-4AC7-B3CD-44D8BE899142" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="56" masterDocId="FF9BFFAFEB5D1A416A62CB31FFE5FFE8" masterDocTitle="Two new species of genus Ateleute Foerster (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) with a key to the Oriental species" masterLastPageNumber="64" masterPageNumber="53" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" updateTime="1643719245963" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Two new species of genus Ateleute Foerster (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) with a key to the Oriental species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sheng, Mao-Ling</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Broad, Gavin R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sun, Shu-Ping</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>141</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>53</mods:start>
<mods:end>64</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.141.1912</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.141.1912</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-141-53</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">E541E908-3FB3-4E0B-B9BB-4E1C70347912</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031710" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34931ABC-632E-4AC7-B3CD-44D8BE899142" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B9C5A661E1C09D39380420FAE0B9C106" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="56" pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34931ABC-632E-4AC7-B3CD-44D8BE899142" authority="Sheng, Broad &amp; Sun" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ateleute" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ateleute ferruginea" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ferruginea">Ateleute ferruginea Sheng, Broad &amp; Sun</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="55">sp.n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1-5
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">The specific name is derived from the terga being entirely brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="types">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Types.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
Holotype, Female, CHINA: Shuangjiang Forest Farm, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ji’an">Ji'an</normalizedToken>
County, 174 m, Jiangxi Province, 10 May 2009, leg. Lin-Da Li. Paratypes: 2 females, same data as holotype except 24 May 2009.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ateleute" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ateleute ferruginea" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ferruginea">Ateleute ferruginea</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished from all other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ateleute" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ateleute" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Ateleute</taxonomicName>
by combination of the second tergum having circular, concentric striations (Fig. 5) and the following colour pattern: mesopleuron, mesosternum, propodeum, legs and metasoma brown to reddish brown; lateral portions of vertex and upper portion of inner orbits broadly white.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Female. Body length 5.5 to 6.0 mm. Fore wing length 4.0 to 4.5 mm. Antenna length 6.0 to 6.5 mm. Ovipositor sheath length 1.5 to 1.8 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="head">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Head.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Face (Figure 2) 1.4 to 1.5 times as wide as long, lateral margins almost parallel, with fine granulose texture, median portion weakly convex. Clypeal suture weak. Clypeus evenly convex, with texture as that of face; median section of apical margin almost truncate, slightly concave centrally. Mandible and cheek with fine leathery texture. Mandible short, upper tooth as long as lower tooth. Malar space approximately 0.6 times as long as basal width of mandible. Gena very short, with fine leathery texture, strongly convergent backwardly. Vertex and frons with texture as that of gena. Posterior portion of vertex from hind margin of interocellar area to occipital carina slanted almost vertically, distinctly concave medially. Postocellar line slightly shorter than ocular-ocellar line. Frons almost flat, lower portion nearby antennal socket concave. Antenna longer than body, with 28 to 30 flagellomeres, median portion slightly thickened, ventral profile slightly flat, suddenly shortened from fifth flagellomere (Figure 3). Ratio of length from first to seventh flagellomeres: 8.0:7.9:7.7:6.9:5.6:4.0:3.7. Occipital carina dorso-medially interrupted.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="56" pageId="2" pageNumber="55" type="mesosoma">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="55">Mesosoma.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="56" pageId="2" pageNumber="55">
Pronotum, mesoscutum and dorsal and ventro-posterior portions of mesopleuron with fine granulose texture. Anterior margin of pronotum with indistinct fine longitudinal wrinkles; lateral concavity with indistinct and short transverse wrinkles. Mesoscutum slightly convex, median portion with dense oblique longitudinal wrinkles. Notaulus evident, reaching about 0.7 the distance to posterior margin of mesoscutum. Scutellum weakly convex, with texture as that of mesoscutum, but relatively finer than that; subapical portion with indistinct transverse concavity; lateral carina reaching to the concavity. Postscutellum weakly convex, posterior margin with fine carina-shaped edge. Median portion of mesopleuron (Figure 4) shallow oblique transverse concave. Sternaulus reaching middle coxa, posterior portion weak. Mesopleural fovea indistinct. Posterior transverse carina of mesosternum complete. Metapleuron with dense and unclear granulose texture. Subbasal portion of submetapleural carina triangularly convex, posterior end vanishing. Wings hyaline. Fore wing vein 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="56" start="start">1</pageBreakToken>
cu-a slightly distal of 1/M. Areolet pentagonal, vein 3rs-m disappearing, receiving 2m-cu at its basal 0.3 to 0.4. 2m-cu inclivous, with one bulla. Hind wing vein 1-cu approximately as long as cu-a, cu-a strongly reclivous. Legs slender. Dorsal profiles of tibiae and ventral profiles of tarsomeres with irregular and short spines, the spines separated by more than a spine length. Dorsal apex of hind first trochanter distinctly projecting. Ratio of length of hind first to fifth tarsomeres 5.7:2.4:1.5:0.6:1.0. Claws small. Propodeum with weak and indistinct fine transverse wrinkles. Area petiolaris with weak longitudinal wrinkles. Posterior transverse carina, pleural carinae and lateral carinae of area petiolaris present. Propodeal spiracle small, circular, approximately located basal 0.35.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="56" type="metasoma">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">Metasoma.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">First tergum 2.1 to 2.2 times as long as apical width, evenly and strongly narrowed toward base, median portion strongly arched, with dense, even and fine longitudinal wrinkles, dorsolateral carinae indistinct, ventrolateral carinae complete. Spiracle located slightly anterior of middle. Second tergum trapeziform, median portion with fine arcuate to circular lines (Figure 5), lateral with fine longitudinal wrinkles. Remaining terga with slightly fine leathery texture. Basal portion of third tergum with fine and weak transverse lines. Ovipositor sheath 0.5 to 0.6 times as long as hind tibia, apex truncated. Apical portion of ovipositor gradually pointed.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="56" type="color">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">Color.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">(Figure 1) Main body and legs brown to reddish brown, except the following: head, dorsal portion of pronotum and mesoscutum black. Scape, pedicel and flagellomeres 1 to 3 (4) dark brown. Flagellomeres 5 to 7 and apical portion black; 8 to 17 (18) white. Mandible except black teeth, maxillary and labial palpus yellow. Lateral portions of vertex and upper portion of frontal orbits broadly white. Lower portion of pronotum and scutellum darkish brown. Tegula brown. Stigma yellowish brown. Veins brownish black.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="56">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">
Figures 1-5. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ateleute" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ateleute ferruginea" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ferruginea">Ateleute ferruginea</taxonomicName>
Sheng, Broad &amp; Sun, sp.n. Holotype. Female 1 Body, lateral view 2 Head, anterior view 3 Basal portion of flagella 4 Mesosoma, lateral view 5 Terga 1 to 3.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="56" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="56">
This new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ateleute" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ateleute mesorufa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mesorufa">Ateleute mesorufa</taxonomicName>
Momoi, 1970, but can be distinguished from it by the following combination of characters: areolet receiving 2m-cu at its basal 0.3 to 0.4; scape and pedicel dark brown; all terga entirely brown. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ateleute" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ateleute mesorufa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mesorufa">Ateleute mesorufa</taxonomicName>
: areolet receiving 2m-cu approximately at its middle; scape and pedicel white; apical portions of terga 1 to 3 and spot of tergum 6 white.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>