<document ID-ISSN="1175­5334" approvalRequired="44" approvalRequired_for_originalDoi="1" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="8" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="30" approvalRequired_for_treatments="5" checkinTime="1629706483752" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Martynov, Alexander" docDate="2010" docId="BC5D5914FF8E5273FF48FDE1805DFB24" docLanguage="en" docName="zt02697p154.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2697" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1.1:Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleId="D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Ophiocymbium tanyae Martynov 2010, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageId="57" lastPageNumber="58" masterDocId="4064216CFFB6524AFFDFFFEC840FFFBE" masterDocTitle="Reassessment of the classification of the Ophiuroidea (Echinodermata), based on morphological characters. I. General character evaluation and delineation of the families Ophiomyxidae and Ophiacanthidae 2697" masterLastPageNumber="154" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" updateTime="1630054009333" updateUser="GgImagineBatch" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Reassessment of the classification of the Ophiuroidea (Echinodermata), based on morphological characters. I. General character evaluation and delineation of the families Ophiomyxidae and Ophiacanthidae 2697</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Martynov, Alexander</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2010-12-03</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2697</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>154</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BC5D5914FF8E5273FF48FDE1805DFB24" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BC5D5914FF8E5273FF48FDE1805DFB24" lastPageId="57" lastPageNumber="58" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<subSubSection box="[151,524,525,551]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="56.[151,684,525,586]" box="[151,524,525,551]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,524,525,551]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,524,525,551]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<taxonomicName authority="Martynov, 2010" authorityName="Martynov" authorityYear="2010" box="[151,423,525,551]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="tanyae" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,423,525,551]" italics="true" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Ophiocymbium tanyae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[430,524,525,551]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,684,560,586]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="56.[151,684,525,586]" box="[151,684,560,586]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<figureCitation box="[151,285,560,586]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="13.[151,256,1339,1363]" captionTargetBox="[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetId="figure-434@13.[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 4. Genital plates and radial shields of various taxa of the families Asteronychidae, Gorgonocephalidae and Ophiomyxidae. A. Gorgonocephalus arcticus Leach, 1819, ZMMU D-613, 39 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, showing articulation surface, dorsal view; B. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; C. Asteronyx loveni Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-833, 17.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; D. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view. E. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; F. same, radial shield showing articulation surface, ventral view; G. same, articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; H. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, dissected disk showing most proximal vertebrae and absence of the both genital plates and radial shield, dorsal view; I. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, ventral view; J. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., paratype ca. 17 mm dd, ZMMU D-792, dissected disk showing articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield in situ, dorsal view; K. same, separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; L. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; M. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, 4 mm dd, ZMMU D-814, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; N. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate adradial genital plate, dorsal view; O. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, adradial and abradial genital plates, dorsal view; P. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; Q. articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; R. radial shield, ventral view, showing distally the distinctive excavated articulation surface; S. articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; T. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, radial shield, ventral view; U. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, same, articulation surface of the radial shield, proximal view; Scale bars: A– B,1 mm; C–D, 300 µ; E–F, 100 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 200 µ; J, 1000 µ; K, 300 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 300 µ; N, 300 µ; O, 200 µ; P, 100 µ; Q–T, 100 µ; U, 200 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Figures 4H</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation box="[297,417,560,586]" captionStart="FIGURE 12" captionStartId="21.[151,255,1049,1073]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetId="figure-465@21.[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetPageId="21" captionText="FIGURE 12. Dental plates and jaws of the genera Ophioscolex, Ophiocymbium and Ophiologimus. A–B, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, dental plates; C–D, Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; E. same, dental plate; F. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-803, dental plate; G. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, dental plate; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, dental plate; I–J, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, dental plates; K–L, Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; M. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, jaw, adradial view; N–O, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; Scale bars: A, 200 µ; B, 200 µ; C–D, 300 µ; E, 100 µ; F, 300 µ; G, 100 µ; H, 300 µ; I–J, 100 µ; K–L, 300 µ; M, 100 µ; N–O, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="56" pageNumber="57">12C–E, H</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation box="[422,502,560,586]" captionStart="FIGURE 17" captionStartId="27.[151,255,1036,1060]" captionTargetBox="[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetId="figure-399@27.[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURE 17. Vertebrae of various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal and ventral views; B. same, distal segments, dorsal and ventral views; C. same, proximal segments, proximal view; D. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal view; E. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, proximal segments, dorsal view; F. Ophioscolex glacialis, proximal segments, distal view; G. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, proximal segments, proximal view; H. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, ventral view; I. same, proximal view; J. same, distal view; K. Ophiomyxa pentagona, ZMMU D-553, 21 mm dd, distal view; L. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., holotype ca. 18 mm dd, ZMMU D-788, proximal segments, dorsal view; M. same, ventral view; N. same, proximal view; O. same, distal view; P. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype 9.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-799, proximal segments, dorsal view; Q. same, ventral view; R. same, distal view; S. same, proximal view. Scale bars: A, 1000 µ; B, C, 200 µ, D, 200 µ; E, 300 µ; F, 200 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 1000 µ; L–S, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="56" pageNumber="57">17P–S</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation box="[514,594,560,586]" captionStart="FIGURE 27" captionStartId="38.[151,256,1544,1568]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1521]" captionTargetId="figure-295@38.[158,1428,194,1523]" captionTargetPageId="38" captionText="FIGURE 27. Arm spine articulations and spines of the various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A–C, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-817, 27 mm dd; spine articulations of the proximal segments; D. spine, lateral view, E. spine, ventral view showing large nerve opening; F. Ophiomyxa brevirima H.L. Clark, 1915, ZMMU D- 725, 19 mm dd, distal segments; G. Ophiomyxa brevirima, proximal segments; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, proximal segments; I. Ophiocymbium cavernosum, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm, proximal segment; J. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype, ZMMU D-799, 9.5 mm dd, proximal segments; K. same, middle segments; L. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, proximal segments; M. same a proximal segment with spines; N. same, details of the articulations of the proximal segments; O. Ophiobyrsa rudis Lyman, 1878, ZMMU D-868, 12.5 mm dd; P. Ophiologimus cf. secundus, most proximal segments; Q. Ophiolycus purpureus (Düben &amp; Koren, 1846), ZMMU D-845, 5.5 mm dd, most proximal segments; R. same, proximal segments; S. Ophiolycus nutrix Mortensen, 1936, ZMMU D-818, 8 mm dd, proximal segments with spines; T. same, other proximal segments; U. same, spine base, ventral view; Scale bars: A-B, 300 µ; C, 200 µ; D, 400 µ; E, 150 µ; F, 100 µ; G, 150 µ; H, 100 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 200 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 100 µ; N, 100 µ; O, 250 µ; P, 100 µ; Q, 100 µ; R, 100 µ; S–T, 120 µ; U, 150 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="56" pageNumber="57">27J, K</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation box="[606,684,560,586]" captionStart="FIGURE 40" captionStartId="52.[151,256,1746,1770]" captionTargetBox="[188,1398,309,1725]" captionTargetId="figure-160@52.[188,1398,309,1725]" captionTargetPageId="52" captionText="FIGURE 40. External views of the genera Ophiocymbium and Ophiologimus. A. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, holotype, BMNH 82.12.23.391, 8.3 mm dd, dorsal view; B. same, ventral view; C. Ophiocymbium cavernosum, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm dd, dorsal view; D. Ophiocymbium cavernosum, ZMMU D-795, 8.5 mm dd, ventral view; E. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype 9.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-799; F. same, ventral view; G. Ophiocymbium rarispinum sp. nov., holotype 9.2 mm dd, ZMMU D-798, dorsal view; H. same, ventral view; I. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-814, 8 mm dd, dorsal view; J. same, ventral view. Photos: Tatiana Korshunova." pageId="56" pageNumber="57">40E, F</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="56.[151,1437,634,2004]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,267,634,660]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation collectionCode="ZMMU, R, V" elevation="6795" latitude="29.283333" longLatPrecision="1228" longitude="143.25" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" specimenCount="5" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[274,386,634,660]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Holotype</typeStatus>
, dried, 
<collectionCode box="[472,563,634,660]" country="Russia" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/k3qp-615s" name="Zoological Museum, Moscow Lomonosov State University" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="Museum">ZMMU</collectionCode>
D-799, 
<collectionCode box="[660,679,634,660]" country="Chile" name="Departamento de Geologia, Universidad de Chile" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">R</collectionCode>
/ 
<collectionCode box="[688,709,634,660]" country="Canada" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:13946" name="Royal British Columbia Museum - Herbarium" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="Museum">V</collectionCode>
“Vityaz”, sta. 7407, 
<geoCoordinate box="[952,1063,634,660]" degrees="29" direction="north" minutes="18" orientation="latitude" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" precision="925" value="29.3">29° 18' N</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate box="[1070,1192,634,660]" degrees="143" direction="east" minutes="15" orientation="longitude" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" precision="925" value="143.25">143° 15' E</geoCoordinate>
– 
<geoCoordinate box="[1221,1331,634,660]" degrees="29" direction="north" minutes="17" orientation="latitude" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" precision="925" value="29.283333">29° 17' N</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate degrees="143" direction="east" minutes="15" orientation="longitude" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" precision="925" value="143.25">143° 15' E</geoCoordinate>
, Izu-Bonin Trench, depth 
<quantity box="[476,639,672,698]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="6.795" metricValueMax="6.85" metricValueMin="6.74" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" unit="m" value="6795.0" valueMax="6850.0" valueMin="6740.0">
<elevation box="[476,639,672,698]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="6.795" metricValueMax="6.85" metricValueMin="6.74" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" unit="m" value="6795.0" valueMax="6850.0" valueMin="6740.0">6740–6850 m</elevation>
</quantity>
, Sigsbee trawl. Four 
<typeStatus box="[885,1000,672,698]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">paratypes</typeStatus>
, ethanol, 
<collectionCode box="[1111,1202,672,698]" country="Russia" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/k3qp-615s" name="Zoological Museum, Moscow Lomonosov State University" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="Museum">ZMMU</collectionCode>
D-800, same sta. as 
<typeStatus box="[151,257,709,735]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">holotype</typeStatus>
. One 
<typeStatus box="[324,428,709,735]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">paratype</typeStatus>
, disarticulated and mounted on a SEM stub, 
<collectionCode box="[952,1043,709,735]" country="Russia" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/k3qp-615s" name="Zoological Museum, Moscow Lomonosov State University" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="Museum">ZMMU</collectionCode>
D-801, same sta. as 
<typeStatus box="[1286,1392,709,735]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="56.[151,1437,634,2004]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,346,746,772]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Etymology.</emphasis>
This species is named in honour of neurophysiologist and my wife Tanya Korshunova (
<collectingRegion box="[159,268,784,810]" country="Russia" name="Moscow" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Moscow</collectingRegion>
, Institute of Higher Nervous Activity and Neurophysiology) for her generous assistance and patience.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="57" lastPageNumber="58" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="56.[151,1437,634,2004]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,552,858,884]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">
Description of the 
<typeStatus box="[436,547,858,884]" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</emphasis>
The disk measures 9.5 mm dd, rather flattened, pentagonal with rounded angles. Numerous disk plates, most of elongated shape, narrowed, irregular-rhomboidal or polygonal, entirely devoid of spines and granules. Disk scales continue dorsally and extend onto the first arm segment. Skin layer is thin and not conspicuous. Radial shields and both genital plates are absent. The interradii are slightly swollen, ventrally with numerous scales. Each jaw bears one larger spiniform apical papilla and 1 –2 smaller adjacent ones. Apical papillae are distinct from the teeth, the latter are narrower and longer and only one in number in most interradii except a single jaw with two teeth. The proximalmost oral papillae are small, spiniform, typically placed in pairs. Three papillae are placed distally on each side of the jaws and characteristically block-shaped, appearing rather as modified, originally spiniform, papillae attached to the jaws over almost their entire length. The distalmost oral papillae are shorter than the middle one, which is rather long and rectangular, but pointed distally, the most proximal block-shaped papilla is more pointed, and in some interradii almost spiniform. The second tentacle pore is covered by two similarly sized, flattened and rounded scales, which are placed on the adoral shield and thus can be equally considered as both adoral shield spines or tentacle scales. The oral shield is wide, triangular or somewhat rhomboidal, with straight or slightly convex distal edge, as long as wide, completely separated from the first lateral arm plate by the adoral shields. Distally the oral shield adjoins a supplementary narrow plate or just an elevation formed by adjacent interradial scales. The adoral shield is wing-shaped laterally, widely adjoining the arm, narrowing towards the midline of the jaws, retaining a moderately narrow bar between the jaws and oral shield. True genital slits are barely conspicuous small openings under the adoral shields, but long furrows between the most proximal arm segments and the ventral disk interradius form a false slit.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="56.[151,1437,634,2004]" lastBlockId="57.[151,1436,152,1178]" lastPageId="57" lastPageNumber="58" pageId="56" pageNumber="57">Arm length is almost equal to the disk diameter. The dorsal arm plates are well developed but rather small, triangular, narrowing and turning pentagonal towards the middle of the arm, well separated on all segments (for about the length of the dorsal arm plate proximally and twice the dorsal plate distally). All dorsal arm plates have pointed proximal and straight distal edges. Arms have weakly developed nodes but arm spine articulations are placed on lateral plates without forming an elevation. On the most proximal segments under the disk there are two conical spines, on the proximal and distal segments there are three (rarely four) spines. The second dorsal spine is slightly longer than others. The first ventral arm plate is triangular. Further ventral arm plates have a characteristic pole-axe shape throughout entire arm length. Medially ventral arm plates have a distinct elevation, making the plates somewhat roundly carinate. The proximal edge of the ventral arm plate is straight, whereas the distal edge is convex with a small pit in the middle. Ventral plates throughout the length of the arm are separated, slightly so on the proximal segments, and similar in length distally. The tentacle pores are large. On the first three arm segments under the disk there are distinct large tentacle scales, placed on the lateral plates. On the first segment there are two flattened rounded tentacle scales, whereas on the second and third segments the scales become more spiniform. The tentacle scales are similar in size to the arm spines and capable of covering a considerable part of the tentacle pore. On the remaining segments tentacle scales are entirely absent. There are no tentacle scales on the ventral arm plates.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="57.[151,1436,152,1178]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,452,338,364]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">
<typeStatus box="[199,313,338,364]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Paratype</typeStatus>
variations.
</emphasis>
A 
<typeStatus box="[487,588,338,364]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">paratype</typeStatus>
in ethanol, from the same station as the 
<typeStatus box="[1057,1162,338,364]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">holotype</typeStatus>
, 12.0 mm dd, is similar to the 
<typeStatus box="[228,337,376,402]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">holotype</typeStatus>
, but differs in minor ways. The first 1–2 proximal segments near the disk lack dorsal arm plates and small scales, exposing the vertebrae. There are no teeth on any dental plates except for the conspicuous middle apical papilla and 1–2 adjacent smaller apical papillae. Oral shields are smaller than in the 
<typeStatus box="[194,300,488,514]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">holotype</typeStatus>
, triangular or irregularly oval. The madreporite has lost its usual shape and is markedly swollen. On the most proximal lateral arm plates under the disk there are two spines, on proximal and middle lateral plates three (occasionally four) flattened apically pointed spines.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="57.[151,1436,152,1178]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,724,599,625]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Internal and microstructural characters.</emphasis>
Radial shield and both genital plates are absent (
<figureCitation box="[1324,1422,600,626]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="13.[151,256,1339,1363]" captionTargetBox="[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetId="figure-434@13.[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 4. Genital plates and radial shields of various taxa of the families Asteronychidae, Gorgonocephalidae and Ophiomyxidae. A. Gorgonocephalus arcticus Leach, 1819, ZMMU D-613, 39 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, showing articulation surface, dorsal view; B. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; C. Asteronyx loveni Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-833, 17.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; D. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view. E. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; F. same, radial shield showing articulation surface, ventral view; G. same, articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; H. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, dissected disk showing most proximal vertebrae and absence of the both genital plates and radial shield, dorsal view; I. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, ventral view; J. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., paratype ca. 17 mm dd, ZMMU D-792, dissected disk showing articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield in situ, dorsal view; K. same, separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; L. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; M. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, 4 mm dd, ZMMU D-814, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; N. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate adradial genital plate, dorsal view; O. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, adradial and abradial genital plates, dorsal view; P. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; Q. articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; R. radial shield, ventral view, showing distally the distinctive excavated articulation surface; S. articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; T. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, radial shield, ventral view; U. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, same, articulation surface of the radial shield, proximal view; Scale bars: A– B,1 mm; C–D, 300 µ; E–F, 100 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 200 µ; J, 1000 µ; K, 300 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 300 µ; N, 300 µ; O, 200 µ; P, 100 µ; Q–T, 100 µ; U, 200 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 4H</figureCitation>
). Jaws are elongated (
<figureCitation box="[396,549,636,662]" captionStart="FIGURE 12" captionStartId="21.[151,255,1049,1073]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetId="figure-465@21.[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetPageId="21" captionText="FIGURE 12. Dental plates and jaws of the genera Ophioscolex, Ophiocymbium and Ophiologimus. A–B, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, dental plates; C–D, Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; E. same, dental plate; F. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-803, dental plate; G. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, dental plate; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, dental plate; I–J, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, dental plates; K–L, Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; M. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, jaw, adradial view; N–O, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; Scale bars: A, 200 µ; B, 200 µ; C–D, 300 µ; E, 100 µ; F, 300 µ; G, 100 µ; H, 300 µ; I–J, 100 µ; K–L, 300 µ; M, 100 µ; N–O, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Figs 12C–D</figureCitation>
). Adradial sides of the jaws distally irregularly folded (
<figureCitation box="[1221,1334,636,662]" captionStart="FIGURE 12" captionStartId="21.[151,255,1049,1073]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetId="figure-465@21.[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetPageId="21" captionText="FIGURE 12. Dental plates and jaws of the genera Ophioscolex, Ophiocymbium and Ophiologimus. A–B, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, dental plates; C–D, Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; E. same, dental plate; F. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-803, dental plate; G. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, dental plate; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, dental plate; I–J, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, dental plates; K–L, Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; M. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, jaw, adradial view; N–O, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; Scale bars: A, 200 µ; B, 200 µ; C–D, 300 µ; E, 100 µ; F, 300 µ; G, 100 µ; H, 300 µ; I–J, 100 µ; K–L, 300 µ; M, 100 µ; N–O, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 12D</figureCitation>
). Dental plate without folds, with few small rounded sockets (
<figureCitation box="[776,883,673,699]" captionStart="FIGURE 12" captionStartId="21.[151,255,1049,1073]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetId="figure-465@21.[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetPageId="21" captionText="FIGURE 12. Dental plates and jaws of the genera Ophioscolex, Ophiocymbium and Ophiologimus. A–B, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, dental plates; C–D, Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; E. same, dental plate; F. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-803, dental plate; G. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, dental plate; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, dental plate; I–J, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, dental plates; K–L, Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; M. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, jaw, adradial view; N–O, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; Scale bars: A, 200 µ; B, 200 µ; C–D, 300 µ; E, 100 µ; F, 300 µ; G, 100 µ; H, 300 µ; I–J, 100 µ; K–L, 300 µ; M, 100 µ; N–O, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 12E</figureCitation>
). Arm spine articulations are poorly developed and clearly belong to the single-opening 
<typeStatus box="[652,704,710,736]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">type</typeStatus>
(
<figureCitation box="[722,864,710,736]" captionStart="FIGURE 27" captionStartId="38.[151,256,1544,1568]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1521]" captionTargetId="figure-295@38.[158,1428,194,1523]" captionTargetPageId="38" captionText="FIGURE 27. Arm spine articulations and spines of the various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A–C, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-817, 27 mm dd; spine articulations of the proximal segments; D. spine, lateral view, E. spine, ventral view showing large nerve opening; F. Ophiomyxa brevirima H.L. Clark, 1915, ZMMU D- 725, 19 mm dd, distal segments; G. Ophiomyxa brevirima, proximal segments; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, proximal segments; I. Ophiocymbium cavernosum, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm, proximal segment; J. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype, ZMMU D-799, 9.5 mm dd, proximal segments; K. same, middle segments; L. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, proximal segments; M. same a proximal segment with spines; N. same, details of the articulations of the proximal segments; O. Ophiobyrsa rudis Lyman, 1878, ZMMU D-868, 12.5 mm dd; P. Ophiologimus cf. secundus, most proximal segments; Q. Ophiolycus purpureus (Düben &amp; Koren, 1846), ZMMU D-845, 5.5 mm dd, most proximal segments; R. same, proximal segments; S. Ophiolycus nutrix Mortensen, 1936, ZMMU D-818, 8 mm dd, proximal segments with spines; T. same, other proximal segments; U. same, spine base, ventral view; Scale bars: A-B, 300 µ; C, 200 µ; D, 400 µ; E, 150 µ; F, 100 µ; G, 150 µ; H, 100 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 200 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 100 µ; N, 100 µ; O, 250 µ; P, 100 µ; Q, 100 µ; R, 100 µ; S–T, 120 µ; U, 150 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 27J, K</figureCitation>
). The unevenly rounded or slightly subparallel muscle opening lacks a ribbed distal area and a distinct lobe. The nerve opening is not evident. Vertebrae rather long, not keeled and with well developed zygospondylous articulation (
<figureCitation box="[1085,1225,784,810]" captionStart="FIGURE 17" captionStartId="27.[151,255,1036,1060]" captionTargetBox="[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetId="figure-399@27.[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURE 17. Vertebrae of various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal and ventral views; B. same, distal segments, dorsal and ventral views; C. same, proximal segments, proximal view; D. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal view; E. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, proximal segments, dorsal view; F. Ophioscolex glacialis, proximal segments, distal view; G. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, proximal segments, proximal view; H. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, ventral view; I. same, proximal view; J. same, distal view; K. Ophiomyxa pentagona, ZMMU D-553, 21 mm dd, distal view; L. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., holotype ca. 18 mm dd, ZMMU D-788, proximal segments, dorsal view; M. same, ventral view; N. same, proximal view; O. same, distal view; P. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype 9.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-799, proximal segments, dorsal view; Q. same, ventral view; R. same, distal view; S. same, proximal view. Scale bars: A, 1000 µ; B, C, 200 µ, D, 200 µ; E, 300 µ; F, 200 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 1000 µ; L–S, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 17P, R</figureCitation>
). Vertebral dorsal median groove absent (
<figureCitation box="[424,528,820,846]" captionStart="FIGURE 17" captionStartId="27.[151,255,1036,1060]" captionTargetBox="[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetId="figure-399@27.[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURE 17. Vertebrae of various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal and ventral views; B. same, distal segments, dorsal and ventral views; C. same, proximal segments, proximal view; D. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal view; E. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, proximal segments, dorsal view; F. Ophioscolex glacialis, proximal segments, distal view; G. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, proximal segments, proximal view; H. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, ventral view; I. same, proximal view; J. same, distal view; K. Ophiomyxa pentagona, ZMMU D-553, 21 mm dd, distal view; L. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., holotype ca. 18 mm dd, ZMMU D-788, proximal segments, dorsal view; M. same, ventral view; N. same, proximal view; O. same, distal view; P. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype 9.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-799, proximal segments, dorsal view; Q. same, ventral view; R. same, distal view; S. same, proximal view. Scale bars: A, 1000 µ; B, C, 200 µ, D, 200 µ; E, 300 µ; F, 200 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 1000 µ; L–S, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 17P</figureCitation>
). Podial basins are large (
<figureCitation box="[828,937,820,846]" captionStart="FIGURE 17" captionStartId="27.[151,255,1036,1060]" captionTargetBox="[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetId="figure-399@27.[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURE 17. Vertebrae of various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal and ventral views; B. same, distal segments, dorsal and ventral views; C. same, proximal segments, proximal view; D. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal view; E. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, proximal segments, dorsal view; F. Ophioscolex glacialis, proximal segments, distal view; G. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, proximal segments, proximal view; H. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, ventral view; I. same, proximal view; J. same, distal view; K. Ophiomyxa pentagona, ZMMU D-553, 21 mm dd, distal view; L. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., holotype ca. 18 mm dd, ZMMU D-788, proximal segments, dorsal view; M. same, ventral view; N. same, proximal view; O. same, distal view; P. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype 9.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-799, proximal segments, dorsal view; Q. same, ventral view; R. same, distal view; S. same, proximal view. Scale bars: A, 1000 µ; B, C, 200 µ, D, 200 µ; E, 300 µ; F, 200 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 1000 µ; L–S, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 17Q</figureCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="57" pageNumber="58" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="57.[151,1436,152,1178]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[198,319,857,883]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Martynov, 2010" authorityName="Martynov" authorityYear="2010" box="[332,605,857,883]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="57" pageNumber="141" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="tanyae" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[332,605,857,883]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">
Ophiocymbium 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[525,605,857,883]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">tanyae</emphasis>
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[617,717,857,883]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
resembles 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[860,1043,857,882]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="57" pageNumber="58" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="cavernosum">
<emphasis box="[860,1043,857,882]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">O. cavernosum</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
in general disk appearance but differs from it in several important characters. All arm segments of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[981,1164,894,919]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="57" pageNumber="58" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="cavernosum">
<emphasis box="[981,1164,894,919]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">O. cavernosum</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
are entirely devoid of conspicuous tentacle scales (except for the first segment bearing a very small spiniform scale), whereas 
<taxonomicName authority="Martynov, 2010" authorityName="Martynov" authorityYear="2010" box="[151,421,967,993]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="57" pageNumber="141" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="tanyae" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[151,421,967,993]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">
Ophiocymbium 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[340,421,967,993]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">tanyae</emphasis>
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[429,525,967,993]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
has a conspicuous, wide, flattened tentacle scale on the first three proximal segments. The absence of the tentacle scales in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[743,929,1005,1030]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="57" pageNumber="58" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="cavernosum">
<emphasis box="[743,929,1005,1030]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">O. cavernosum</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is confirmed in the present study for the 
<typeStatus box="[151,259,1041,1067]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">holotype</typeStatus>
and several specimens from the Atlantic and Pacific oceans. Another important difference of 
<taxonomicName authority="Martynov, 2010" authorityName="Martynov" authorityYear="2010" box="[151,419,1078,1104]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="57" pageNumber="141" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="tanyae" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[151,419,1078,1104]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">
Ophiocymbium 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[339,419,1078,1104]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">tanyae</emphasis>
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[427,521,1078,1104]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is the complete absence of adradial and abradial genital plates and the radial shields, confirmed for all studied specimens (
<figureCitation box="[699,796,1115,1141]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="13.[151,256,1339,1363]" captionTargetBox="[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetId="figure-434@13.[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 4. Genital plates and radial shields of various taxa of the families Asteronychidae, Gorgonocephalidae and Ophiomyxidae. A. Gorgonocephalus arcticus Leach, 1819, ZMMU D-613, 39 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, showing articulation surface, dorsal view; B. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; C. Asteronyx loveni Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-833, 17.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; D. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view. E. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; F. same, radial shield showing articulation surface, ventral view; G. same, articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; H. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, dissected disk showing most proximal vertebrae and absence of the both genital plates and radial shield, dorsal view; I. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, ventral view; J. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., paratype ca. 17 mm dd, ZMMU D-792, dissected disk showing articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield in situ, dorsal view; K. same, separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; L. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; M. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, 4 mm dd, ZMMU D-814, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; N. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate adradial genital plate, dorsal view; O. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, adradial and abradial genital plates, dorsal view; P. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; Q. articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; R. radial shield, ventral view, showing distally the distinctive excavated articulation surface; S. articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; T. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, radial shield, ventral view; U. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, same, articulation surface of the radial shield, proximal view; Scale bars: A– B,1 mm; C–D, 300 µ; E–F, 100 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 200 µ; J, 1000 µ; K, 300 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 300 µ; N, 300 µ; O, 200 µ; P, 100 µ; Q–T, 100 µ; U, 200 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 4H</figureCitation>
). In contrast, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[962,1143,1115,1140]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="57" pageNumber="58" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="cavernosum">
<emphasis box="[962,1143,1115,1140]" italics="true" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">O. cavernosum</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
has a small, but evident adradial genital plate and radial shield (
<figureCitation box="[613,708,1152,1178]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="13.[151,256,1339,1363]" captionTargetBox="[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetId="figure-434@13.[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 4. Genital plates and radial shields of various taxa of the families Asteronychidae, Gorgonocephalidae and Ophiomyxidae. A. Gorgonocephalus arcticus Leach, 1819, ZMMU D-613, 39 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, showing articulation surface, dorsal view; B. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; C. Asteronyx loveni Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-833, 17.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; D. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view. E. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; F. same, radial shield showing articulation surface, ventral view; G. same, articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; H. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, dissected disk showing most proximal vertebrae and absence of the both genital plates and radial shield, dorsal view; I. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, ventral view; J. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., paratype ca. 17 mm dd, ZMMU D-792, dissected disk showing articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield in situ, dorsal view; K. same, separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; L. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; M. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, 4 mm dd, ZMMU D-814, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; N. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate adradial genital plate, dorsal view; O. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, adradial and abradial genital plates, dorsal view; P. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; Q. articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; R. radial shield, ventral view, showing distally the distinctive excavated articulation surface; S. articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; T. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, radial shield, ventral view; U. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, same, articulation surface of the radial shield, proximal view; Scale bars: A– B,1 mm; C–D, 300 µ; E–F, 100 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 200 µ; J, 1000 µ; K, 300 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 300 µ; N, 300 µ; O, 200 µ; P, 100 µ; Q–T, 100 µ; U, 200 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="57" pageNumber="58">Fig. 4G</figureCitation>
); confirmed also for the 
<typeStatus box="[996,1102,1152,1178]" pageId="57" pageNumber="58">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>