<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.860.19961" ID-GBIF-Dataset="37b2a078-3f92-4ec2-b892-d3e0a567f7d8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="158525323" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-860-1" ID-ZBK="11140DC997444A479EC83AF9E2891BAB" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="1313-2970-860-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 860" ModsDocTitle="A review of gorgonian coral species (Cnidaria, Octocorallia, Alcyonacea) held in the Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History research collection: focus on species from Scleraxonia, Holaxonia, and Calcaxonia – Part I: Introduction, species of Scleraxonia and Holaxonia (Family Acanthogorgiidae)" checkinTime="1562310422136" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Horvath, Elizabeth Anne" docDate="2019" docId="8984BDE5243CB57563C560172A0E0971" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 860: 1-66" docOrigin="ZooKeys 860" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.860.19961" docTitle="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica Kuekenthal 1909" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageNumber="1" masterDocId="843C0C24FF815E5FFFDD405D045AFFC6" masterDocTitle="A review of gorgonian coral species (Cnidaria, Octocorallia, Alcyonacea) held in the Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History research collection: focus on species from Scleraxonia, Holaxonia, and Calcaxonia - Part I: Introduction, species of Scleraxonia and Holaxonia (Family Acanthogorgiidae)" masterLastPageNumber="66" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" updateTime="1643458478999" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of gorgonian coral species (Cnidaria, Octocorallia, Alcyonacea) held in the Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History research collection: focus on species from Scleraxonia, Holaxonia, and Calcaxonia - Part I: Introduction, species of Scleraxonia and Holaxonia (Family Acanthogorgiidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Horvath, Elizabeth Anne</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>860</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>66</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.860.19961</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.860.19961</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-860-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">11140DC997444A479EC83AF9E2891BAB</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">11140DC997444A479EC83AF9E2891BAB</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="158525323" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:8984BDE5243CB57563C560172A0E0971" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8984BDE5243CB57563C560172A0E0971" lastPageNumber="1" pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<taxonomicName authority="Kuekenthal, 1909" authorityName="Kuekenthal" authorityYear="1909" class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="typica">
Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
, 1909
</taxonomicName>
Figures 8, 9A, B, 10, 11, 12
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="typica">Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
, 1909: 73-76; pl 6, fig 33; (syn.) 1919: 763. 
<bibRefCitation pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Aurivillius 1931</bibRefCitation>
: 67-72.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
? 
<taxonomicName family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="A." higherTaxonomySource="treatment-meta" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="A. gracillima var. lata" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="lata">A. gracillima var. lata</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
, 1909: 71, 73, 75.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">(?) Okinawa, Japan; 400 fathoms.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="type specimens">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Type specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Zoological Museum of the University of Hamburg, Germany (formerly, Naturhistorisches Museum, Hamburg); Catalog Number 3298, with Catalog Number 3297. (Not labeled as type.)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">1 lot (see Appendix 1: List of material examined).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Colony (Figures 8, 9A) richly branched, not entirely in one plane, forming bushy fan or tree no more than 10 cm at widest point. Colony appeared fragile and delicate, but actually a tough, spiky bush/fan, branches reminiscent of those in a bottlebrush (Figure 9B); not greatly flexible. Colony height (dictated by main, central, generally straight stem), base to tip, 15-16 cm; 7.0 cm broad; holdfast remnant present. If any regularity to branching pattern, slightly dichotomous to pinnate, usually in one plane; all lateral branches, of differing lengths, project at nearly right angles, extending/curving quickly upward, even those with more lateral placement. Branch diameter averages 2.0-3.0 mm. Polyps distributed over entire surface (not so much on lower portion of main stem, just above base), nearly in rings around branches, closely placed but not crowded (Figure 10); sometimes two with bases contiguous, generally separated by 1.0 mm, perhaps more; terminal twigs rounded, almost clavate in appearance; numerous polyps at apex, completely covered with straight and curved spindle-shaped sclerites. Polyps not retractile; very conspicuous, decidedly slender, columnar in shape, height between ~4.0-7.0 mm (most average 5.0-6.0 mm tall); diameter generally 1.0 mm for most of polyp length, narrowing slightly, then increasing to ~1.5 mm wide at the crown. Easily recognized by crown of sharp spines encircling top of polyp. Coenenchyme very thin and translucent, with axis color showing through. Color of freshly collected specimen bright lemon yellow (M Love, pers. comm.; Figure 8); on being placed in alcohol quickly turned, generally, light olive-green towards base, becoming slightly darker grey-green at uppermost branch tips. (While species in family are described as having a predominantly black, purely horny axis, color of axis showing through extremely thin coenenchyme appeared to account for overall olive-green color. Having now sat in 70% ETOH for some time, the colony has turned more yellowish brown.) Sclerites (Figures 11, 12A, B) mainly spindle-shaped; straight or curved, showing arrangement of eight double rows, forming longitudinally-placed chevrons (obliquely angled double-rows) characteristic of genus. A very few oddly branched; some, more a tripod shape. Sclerites appear mostly tuberculate, with distinct boomerang bend (Figure 12A), easily removed from surface of colony. The longest sclerites, with distinct bend roughly a third of the way along their length, range from 1.0-2.0 mm in length (average 1.6 mm L 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
0.17 mm W); one third of surface of sclerite bears tubercles, while other two-thirds is generally smooth; this smooth section, thin, rounded, somewhat beveled, is the distal, prominent spike that projects from the thorny basal portion embedded in the mesoglea of the body wall, in nearly longitudinal direction; lower, embedded portion, ~0.5 mm long, appears to cross over into the neighboring angled rows, these basal portions not much different one from another. These sclerites form the crown of thorns seen around top of polyp. Two very long spines project upwards to form the points of the crown at distal end of each of the eight double-rows. Smooth portion of these sclerites sit with approximately 1.0 mm of their length free of polyp. Numerous, slightly smaller, flatter sclerites have bend more centrally located, their entire surface covered with tubercles (average 1.0 mm L 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
~0.08 mm W). These primarily cover outside surface of polyp (Figure 11), illustrating chevron pattern (eight longitudinal double rows) in placement. Sclerites of coenenchyme similar to those seen on 
<normalizedToken originalValue="polyps’">polyps'</normalizedToken>
surface (~0.8 mm long), perhaps slightly thicker in width and slightly more fully covered with tubercles; tentacular sclerites smaller still, bent, flattened (up to ~0.18 mm long), completely covered with tubercles; more prominent, dense, on dorsal side of tentacles. If present, a few smaller (0.1 mm long) radiate or cross-shaped sclerites may be seen. In the coenenchyme covering the base, exclusively, are 0.25 mm long, bent, strongly spined spindles. All sclerites completely colorless, reminiscent of thin, bent shards of glass.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 8. 
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="typica">Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica</taxonomicName>
. In situ, living colonies, illustrating vibrant yellow color, as seen in Santa Barbara Channel, photograph by D Schroeder; image courtesy of M Love, UCSB.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="typica">Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica</taxonomicName>
, SBMNH 423074. A Whole colony preserved in 70% ETOH. Maximum height of colony 15-16 cm, ≤ 10 cm at widest point B magnified view of several branches; pronounced, rather spikey appearance of polyps is evident.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="typica">Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica</taxonomicName>
, greater magnification of SBMNH 423074. Shows position of polyps on branches. Note prominent crown of sclerites at distal end of each polyp, polyp height averages 5.0-6.0 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
For designation 
<taxonomicName genus="Holaxonia" lsidName="Holaxonia gracillima" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" rank="species" species="gracillima">gracillima</taxonomicName>
, the Latin gracili- means slender; this may reference the conspicuous, very slender polyps and very slender points in the crown of this species. 
<bibRefCitation author="Kuekenthal, W" journalOrPublisher="Supplement-Band" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" pagination="1 - 78" title="Japanische Gorgoniden. II. Teil: Die Familien der Plexauriden, Chrysogorgiiiden und Melitodiden. In: Beitrage zur Naturgeschichte Ostasiens. Abhandlungen der mathematische-physics. Klasse der K. Bayer. Akademie der Wissenschaften." volume="1" year="1909">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
(1909)
</bibRefCitation>
gave no explanation for the derivation of the species name.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="common name">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Common name.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">None specifically designated; the Slender glass-shard gorgonian would be appropriate. Worth considering is whether or not this is the species that, predominantly, MBARI and NOAA researchers are seeing and calling the &quot;Gold gorgonian.&quot;</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
For genus in general, &quot;species... inhabit moderate to considerable depths; various species of 
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="genus">Acanthogorgia</taxonomicName>
occur in all seas, some thriving in very cold waters&quot; (Bayer, penciled personal annotations in 
<bibRefCitation author="Kuekenthal, W" journalOrPublisher="Walter de Gruyter &amp; Company, Berlin" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" title="Gorgonaria. Das Tierreich, Vol. 47." year="1924">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
1924
</bibRefCitation>
). Examinations of the literature revealed numerous species in the Indo-Pacific region. Recent MBARI on-line postings indicated this genus is found in northern California waters, often at great depth. Milton Love (description based on specimen he collected) indicated (pers. comm.) that the color of this gorgonian is very vibrant, thus easily seen; it is quite abundant in certain areas, such as the Footprint, a feature outside the Anacapa/Santa Cruz Island Passage. Thus, for this species, range seems to extend around the Pacific Ocean from Japan (
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal’s">Kuekenthal's</normalizedToken>
specimen) to eastern Pacific waters of California; further study will be required to determine whether, and how far, it extends north and south of California.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">On this particular specimen, there were at least two scale worms wrapped around the base of polyps in two separate areas within the colony.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
To handle the specimen during examination, although colony fairly hardy, gloves were necessary. Generally, all the long sclerites were very sharp, comparable to small shards of thin glass; those that got into the skin under the fingernail were rather painful. Given the delicate, and somewhat brittle/fragile nature of the longer boomerang-type sclerites, these sclerites are easily broken. It was often difficult to ascertain whether radiates and crosses really existed as such, or whether they were bits that had broken off from the longer spindle forms; this could account for some of the odder-shaped sclerites that previous description (
<bibRefCitation author="Kuekenthal, W" journalOrPublisher="Supplement-Band" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" pagination="1 - 78" title="Japanische Gorgoniden. II. Teil: Die Familien der Plexauriden, Chrysogorgiiiden und Melitodiden. In: Beitrage zur Naturgeschichte Ostasiens. Abhandlungen der mathematische-physics. Klasse der K. Bayer. Akademie der Wissenschaften." volume="1" year="1909">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
1909
</bibRefCitation>
) made mention of. Microscopic examinations were always done without a cover glass, when possible, so that sclerites were not crushed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
This description (and original description for the species) was based on the specimen used by 
<bibRefCitation author="Kuekenthal, W" journalOrPublisher="Supplement-Band" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" pagination="1 - 78" title="Japanische Gorgoniden. II. Teil: Die Familien der Plexauriden, Chrysogorgiiiden und Melitodiden. In: Beitrage zur Naturgeschichte Ostasiens. Abhandlungen der mathematische-physics. Klasse der K. Bayer. Akademie der Wissenschaften." volume="1" year="1909">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
(1909)
</bibRefCitation>
. In initial comparisons of known, and described species, using characteristics of the colony (lying more or less in one plane, with polyps generally more than 4.0 mm in length), the key that 
<bibRefCitation author="Kuekenthal, W" journalOrPublisher="Walter de Gruyter &amp; Company, Berlin" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" title="Gorgonaria. Das Tierreich, Vol. 47." year="1924">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Kükenthal">Kuekenthal</normalizedToken>
(1924)
</bibRefCitation>
provided in his overview of the genus was relied upon, but it took some time to rule possibilities out. 
<bibRefCitation author="Bayer, FM" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" pagination="205 - 228" title="Three new species of precious coral (Anthozoa: Gorgonacea, genus Corallium) from Pacific waters." url="https://repository.si.edu/handle/10088/998" volume="109" year="1996 b">Bayer (1996b)</bibRefCitation>
stated that all the sclerites are so similar in form within all members of the genus, that distinguishing species is difficult; this was confirmed. As well, there are very few recent descriptions of any 
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="genus">Acanthogorgia</taxonomicName>
species that are truly adequate to use for comparative purposes. Few specimens had been collected from California waters; thus, not a lot of material to compare against. In examinations of collections at other institutions, only two/three specimens were found at NMNH that approximated the appearance of this colony (USNM 1071429, dry and USNM 1072361, wet, in two lots). The dry specimen is from Cross Seamount, Hawaii, USA and the wet lots are from a seamount east of Necker Island, Hawaii, USA. Both are identified to genus, but not to species; in color, branch pattern, pattern of sclerite positioning on polyps and sclerite morphology, specimen USNM1071429 appeared most similar. If NMNH specimens can be accurately identified to species, they could confirm (or negate) the notion of trans-Pacific distribution. In any event, this discussion/description represents one of the first published reports for this particular species in southern to central California waters; overall the genus needs further work, not only on those specimens being frequently noted in underwater explorations (cruises and surveys being done by MBARI and NOAA), but also on those that have already been collected, perhaps described or need description, currently housed in other museum collections. With greater access to locations of depth, and the use of ROV, AUV, digital imaging and improved ability to collect specimens at depth, many currently described species can be confirmed and many new species are likely to come to light. As well, with careful attention to locations where specimens are found, it should be possible to develop a far more accurate picture of the distribution of these deep-water forms.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
While the original specimen does indeed still exist, no opportunity to travel to Hamburg, Germany occurred and no request that the specimen be sent was made. The species is an accepted species in the WoRMS Data Base (
<bibRefCitation author="Cordeiro, R" journalOrPublisher="American Fisheries Society, Bethesda, Maryland" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" url="http://www.marinespecies.org/aphia.php?p=taxdetails&amp;id=125293" year="2018 e">Cordeiro et al. 2018e</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
[
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="genus">Acanthogorgia</taxonomicName>
(=? 
<taxonomicName authority="" authorityName="" class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acalycigorgia" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Metazoa" lsidName="Acalycigorgia" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="genus">Acalycigorgia</taxonomicName>
) Grey, 1857)]; not accepted, WoRMS (
<bibRefCitation author="Cordeiro, R" journalOrPublisher="American Fisheries Society, Bethesda, Maryland" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" url="http://www.marinespecies.org/aphia.php?p=taxdetails&amp;id=125293" year="2018 e">Cordeiro et al. 2018e</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="typica">Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica</taxonomicName>
(light microscopy image), SBMNH 423074. 4X magnification, demonstrating position of long, boomerang-shaped sclerites, arranged longitudinally on surface of polyp, mid-section to distal end.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 12. 
<taxonomicName class="Anthozoa" family="Acanthogorgiidae" genus="Acanthogorgia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="var." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica" order="Alcyonacea" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Cnidaria" rank="variety" species="gracillima" variety="typica">Acanthogorgia gracillima var. typica</taxonomicName>
, SBMNH 423074, SEM image. These sclerites are colorless. A Sclerites from crown B sclerites from polyp surface C small sclerites from coenenchyme D odd coronal or polyp surface sclerite.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>