<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" ID-GBIF-Dataset="92d38eff-94a4-404e-a09c-d535155922c8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043397" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-292-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EDAA6F52-41B2-4C11-870F-568EB113307F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-292-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 292" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" checkinTime="1451247388242" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="6B5DEDD86B984520D65E3DA62A9DBD06" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 292: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 292" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" docTitle="Oxyscelio aureamediocritas Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="EDAA6F52-41B2-4C11-870F-568EB113307F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="45" lastPageNumber="46" masterDocId="FFB8FF92FF98D87CFFAE2F6B1E57FFC8" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" updateTime="1643694823285" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>292</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-292-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043397" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EDAA6F52-41B2-4C11-870F-568EB113307F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6B5DEDD86B984520D65E3DA62A9DBD06" lastPageId="45" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
<subSubSection lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EDAA6F52-41B2-4C11-870F-568EB113307F" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio aureamediocritas" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aureamediocritas">
Oxyscelio aureamediocritas 
<pageBreakToken pageId="43" pageNumber="44" start="start">Burks</pageBreakToken>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="43" pageNumber="44">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 48-51Morphbank33
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="45" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Female. Body length 3.45 mm (n=1).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Radicle color: darker than scape. Scape color: Yellowish. A4: longer than broad. A5: longer than broad. Antennal club: formed, segments compact.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Interantennal process: not elongate. Median longitudinal elevation in frontal depression: absent. Frontal depression: concave. Frontal depression sculpture: with 3 or more broadly interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: strong, formed by a sharp raised carina. Submedian carina medially: without peak. Concavity across dorsal part of frontal depression: absent. Depression extending ventrally from median ocellus: absent. Upper frons: hood-like, protruding over pedicel when antenna at rest. Malar area near antennal foramen: without carina or expansion. Malar area at mouth corner: with radiating striae. Smooth strip along posterior side of malar sulcus: absent or not consistently broad. Middle genal carina: present. Direction of middle genal carina dorsally: parallel to eye margin. Major sculpture of gena anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate; rugose. Major sculpture of gena posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent. Median carina extending posteriorly from hyperoccipital carina: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: complete, continuous with anterior genal carina. Lateral connection between hyperoccipital and occipital carinae: absent. Area between vertex and occipital carina: crenulate; umbilicate-punctate. Occipital carina medially: convex, with a sharp median peak. Lateral corners of occipital carina: not protruding.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="44" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
Lateral pronotal area: without bulge projecting towards anterior pit. Epomial corner: weak. Netrion surface anteriorly: not inflexed. Mesoscutum anteriorly: not steep. Mesoscutal median carina: present and complete. Longitudinal carina between median carina and notauli: absent. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: umbilicate-punctate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum: umbilicate-foveate; irregularly rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum medially: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum laterally: absent. Mesoscutellar apex: convex or straight. Setae along anterior limit of femoral depression: arising from tiny pits. Number of carinae crossing speculum above femoral depression: 3. Number of carinae crossing femoral depression: more than 5. Mesepimeral sulcus pits: more than 5. Metascutellum dorsally: concave. Metascutellar sculpture dorsally: smooth or with transverse carinae. Median carina of metascutellum: absent or branched. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellar apex: deeply emarginate. Metapleuron above ventral metapleural area: smooth. Metasomal depression setae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae anteromedially: weakly diverging. Anterior areoles of metasomal depression: 
<pageBreakToken pageId="44" pageNumber="45" start="start">one</pageBreakToken>
or more areoles present. Anterior longitudinal carinae in metasomal depression: median carina present. Lateral propodeal areas: separated medially. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex: reaching beyond T6.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="44" pageNumber="45">T1 midlobe: with 5 longitudinal carinae. T1: without anterior bulge. T2: with straight longitudinal striae or rugae. T6: broader than long. Apical flange of T6: exposed apically. Metasomal apex: rounded. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate-punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
<pageBreakToken pageId="45" pageNumber="46" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Unknown.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="45" pageNumber="46" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
Female: A4, A5 longer than broad. Frons without elevation between antennal foramen and eye. Hyperoccipital carina present, continuous with anterior genal carina. Metascutellum deeply emarginate. Metasomal depression elongate, with median carina; lateral propodeal carinae narrowly separated anteriorly. T1 midlobe with 5 longitudinal carinae. T6 rounded apically. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio aureamediocritas" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="45" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aureamediocritas">Oxyscelio aureamediocritas</taxonomicName>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio convergens" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="45" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="convergens">Oxyscelio convergens</taxonomicName>
and other species with a sculptured and conspicuous metasomal depression, and with the flagellum in females having an elongate A4 and A5 and weakly developed club. It differs in having a propodeal median carina. Although males of this species are unknown, patterns of variation in other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="45" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Oxyscelio</taxonomicName>
suggest that males may lack the median propodeal carina.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="45" pageNumber="46" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">Latin noun in apposition to the generic name, based on &quot;The Golden Mean&quot; coined by Horace. Refers to the median propodeal carina and general golden color of the holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="45" pageNumber="46" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=275486]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="45" pageNumber="46" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
Holotype, female: THAILAND: Phetchabun Prov., Hell, evergreen forest, T1329, Nam Nao National Park, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="16.740034">16°44.402'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="101.576">101°34.560'E</geoCoordinate>
, 883m, 27.XI-4.XII.2006, malaise trap, N. Hongyothi, OSUC 280518 (deposited in QSBG).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
<paragraph pageId="45" pageNumber="46">
Figures 48-51. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio aureamediocritas" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="45" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aureamediocritas">Oxyscelio aureamediocritas</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 280518) 48 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 49 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 50 Head, anterior view 51 Propodeum, posterior view. Morphbank33
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>