<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280132" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120209" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280132" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="F23E7C732CC553000386064E8BDE32FB" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys schuetzi Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="637" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="636" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280132" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120209" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280132" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F23E7C732CC553000386064E8BDE32FB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F23E7C732CC553000386064E8BDE32FB" lastPageNumber="637" pageNumber="636">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="636">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155818" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys schuetzi Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys schuetzi Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="636" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="schuetzi">Strumigenys schuetzi Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="636">(Fig. 385)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="636">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 1.7, HL 0.40, HW 0.42, CI 105, ML 0.13, MI 32, SL 0.21, SI 50, PW 0.23, AL 0.41. Characters of schuetzi-complex. Mandible blade narrow, linear, outcurved; no intercalary denticles present between the apical fork teeth. Preapical dentition consisting of a single long spiniform tooth at about the midlength of each blade. Anterior clypeal margin broad, projecting beyond the mandibular bases on each side and with numerous small spatulate to spoon-shaped hairs which are curved towards the midline. Lateral margin of clypeus short. Preocular lamina broad, projecting below the antennal insertion. Median portion of clypeus broad, finely punctulate and with scale-like to spoonshaped appressed hairs present. Dorsum of head behind clypeus reticulate-punctate and with broadly scale-like to orbicular shaped hairs anterior of occipital corners. Dorsum of head without a transverse row of hairs close to the occipital margin. Row of scale-like to broad spoon-shaped hairs on upper scrobe margin not terminating at the posterior end with a more or less straight clavate hair. Eye very small, with 3 ommatidia in total and situated just above the ventral scrobe margin. Antenna with 4 segments. Leading edge of scape a dorsoventrally flattened convex lamella with a row of projecting broadly spoon-shaped hairs. Scape strongly back-curved, with a anteriorly projecting subbasal lobe at the bend, and apex of lobe with a projecting broad clavate, almost fan-like hair. In profile, the promesonotum slightly convex; propodeal dorsum shallowly convex anteriorly, sloping posteriorly to the declivity. Propodeal teeth very short, mostly incorporated in the lamellae, with only a small point projecting; lamella a very narrow strip. Side of alitrunk mostly smooth and shiny with weak peripheral punctures. Pronotal disk reticulate-punctate with longitudinal striolate and costulae sculpture, remainder of alitrunk dorsum reticulate punctate. Pronotal humeral hair present, straight clavate; remainder of alitrunk dorsum without erect hairs. Ground-pilosity of dorsal alitrunk consisting of scattered small suberect fine hairs. Dorsal surface of petiole node reticulate-punctate; the postpetiole more or less smooth. Petiole with a pair of broad clavate hairs; postpetiole and gaster with clavate to filiform hairs. In profile the petiole with a well developed spongiform lamella. Postpetiole with well developed lateral and ventral spongiform lobes. Base of first gastral tergite with costulae radiating on each side of a broad central clear area, remainder of gaster smooth and shiny where clean. Color pale brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="636">PARATYPE WORKER TL 1.6 - 1.8, HL 0.39 - 0.41, HW 0.41 - 0.42, CI 103 - 108, ML 0.13 - 0.15, MI 33 - 38, SL 0.21 - 0.22, SI 50 - 53, PW 0.24 - 0.25, AL 0.38 - 0.43 (4 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="637">Holotype worker, Madagascar: Prov. Antsiranana, R. S. Manongarivo, 10.8 km. 229 Â° SW Antanambao, 400 m., 13 Â° 57.7 ' S, 48 Â° 26.6 ' E, 8. xi. l 998, sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood) # 1996 (03) - 2 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="637">Paratypes. 10 workers with same data as holotype but coded # 1996 (7) - 2, (10) - 2, (ll) - 2, (50) - 4, (9) - 2, (38) - 3, (46) - 4, (2) - 2, (23) - l (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="637">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: R. S. Manongarivo, 12.8 km. SW Antanambao, 780 m. (B. L. Fisher); R. S. Manongarivo, 14.5 km. SW Antanambao, 1175 m. (B. L. Fisher).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="637">Measurements of non-paratypic material extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.40 - 0.45, HW 0.42 - 0.45, CI 99 - 103, ML 0.14 - 0.16, MI 32 - 35, SL 0.24, SI 54 - 56 (3 measured).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="637">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155818" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys schuetzi Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys schuetzi Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="637" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="schuetzi">S. schuetzi</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from other species in the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="637" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="arnoldi-group">arnoldi-group</taxonomicName>
by the presence of a laterally projecting straight clavate pronotal humeral hair, antenna with 4 segments, and mandible with only one preapical tooth, set at the midlength of blade. The upper scrobe margin with broadly spoon-shaped hairs that do not terminate at the posterior end with a more or less straight clavate hair also helps to distinguish this species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>