<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6485578" ID-GBIF-Dataset="68658be2-96b9-49b8-82ca-7046054a16c6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="141351640" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6485578" ID-ZooBank="C3029CC4-6A15-49A4-AAAD-F435D04E81C0" checkinTime="1520438930429" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Sanborn, Allen F." docDate="2018" docId="03B787C2FFF6FFA3FF5BFCFFFBF3FB49" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4389.1.1.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4389 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@5a4bef8" docStyleName="zootaxa.2013.monograph" docTitle="Procollina nuevoleonensis Sanborn 2018, n. sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="40" lastPageNumber="41" masterDocId="FF8EFFBAFFD3FF8BFFCCFFBBFFFFFFE9" masterDocTitle="The cicada genus Procollina Metcalf, 1952 (Hemiptera: Cicadidae): redescription including fourteen new species, with a key to the species of the subtribe Dazina Kato, 1932 rev. stat., the description of the Aragualnini n. tribe, and one new combination" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" updateTime="1650929950135" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The cicada genus Procollina Metcalf, 1952 (Hemiptera: Cicadidae): redescription including fourteen new species, with a key to the species of the subtribe Dazina Kato, 1932 rev. stat., the description of the Aragualnini n. tribe, and one new combination</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sanborn, Allen F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2018-03-07</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4389</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4389.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">68658be2-96b9-49b8-82ca-7046054a16c6</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">1193702</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">C3029CC4-6A15-49A4-AAAD-F435D04E81C0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6485578" ID-GBIF-Taxon="141351640" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6485578" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03B787C2FFF6FFA3FF5BFCFFFBF3FB49" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B787C2FFF6FFA3FF5BFCFFFBF3FB49" lastPageId="40" lastPageNumber="41" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="37.[151,544,836,895]" box="[151,544,836,862]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,544,836,862]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,544,836,862]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[151,471,836,862]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nuevoleonensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,471,836,862]" italics="true" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Procollina nuevoleonensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[478,544,836,862]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="37.[151,544,836,895]" box="[151,248,870,895]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,241,870,895]" captionStart="FIGURE 10" captionStartId="39.[151,250,1818,1840]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,373,1797]" captionTargetId="figure@39.[151,1436,373,1797]" captionTargetPageId="39" captionText="FIGURE 10. Procollina nuevoleonensis n. sp.: A, holotype male; B, holotype male dorsum; C, holotype male timbal cover; D, holotype male operculum; E, holotype male lateral view of genitalia; F, holotype male posterior view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 5 mm; C–D, 2 mm; E–F, 1 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/1193722/files/figure.png" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Fig. 10</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,1432,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="37.[151,1437,942,2027]" box="[151,1432,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1830866973" box="[151,1428,942,967]" collectingDate="1975-06-14" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="D. Weems" country="Mexico" location="Chipinque Mesa" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" stateProvince="Nuevo Leon" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,325,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<typeStatus box="[151,210,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Type</typeStatus>
material.
</emphasis>
<typeStatus box="[332,440,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Holotype</typeStatus>
. “ 
<collectingCountry box="[460,577,943,967]" name="Mexico" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">MEXICO</collectingCountry>
: 
<collectingRegion box="[587,727,943,966]" country="Mexico" name="Nuevo Leon" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
Nuevo 
<collectingRegion box="[669,727,943,966]" country="Nicaragua" name="Leon" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Leon</collectingRegion>
</collectingRegion>
/ 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03B787C2FFF6FFA3FF5BFCFFFBF3FB49:8EC1600FFFF6FFAEFD20FC15FC5AFC2F" box="[748,933,942,967]" country="Mexico" name="Chipinque Mesa" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" stateProvince="Nuevo Leon">Chipinque Mesa</location>
/ 
<date box="[954,1096,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" value="1975-06-14">
<collectingDate box="[954,1096,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" value="1975-06-14">14-Jun-1975</collectingDate>
</date>
/ 
<collectorName box="[1118,1237,943,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">D. Weems</collectorName>
” 
<specimenCount box="[1253,1328,942,967]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="male">1 male</specimenCount>
(
<collectionCode box="[1344,1420,943,967]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">FSCA</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="37.[151,1437,942,2027]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,334,978,1003]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Etymology.</emphasis>
The name is a combination of 
<emphasis box="[703,832,978,1003]" italics="true" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">nuevoleon–</emphasis>
for the state of origin of the 
<typeStatus box="[1180,1228,979,1003]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">type</typeStatus>
specimen, 
<collectingRegion country="Mexico" name="Nuevo Leon" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
Nuevo 
<collectingRegion box="[151,211,1015,1038]" country="Nicaragua" name="Leon" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Leon</collectingRegion>
</collectingRegion>
, and 
<emphasis box="[270,340,1015,1038]" italics="true" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">–ensis</emphasis>
(L. suffix denoting place).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="40" lastPageNumber="41" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="37.[151,1437,942,2027]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,345,1050,1075]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Description.</emphasis>
Ground color greenish-tawny marked with piceous and castaneous, fresh or live specimens may be green.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="37.[151,1437,942,2027]" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<emphasis box="[199,269,1122,1147]" italics="true" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Head:</emphasis>
Head green, not as wide as mesonotum, piceous surrounding posterior lateral ocelli connecting to anterolaterad curving marks lateral to lateral ocelli continuing as castaneous mark to near anterior of eye, piceous in anterior and posterior cranial depressions and posterior to anterior cranial depression near posterior of head, piceous tear-shaped mark between medial angle of eye and posterior head, castaneous marks on medial and anterior lateral ocelli connecting anteriorly on posterior median ocellus and extending posteriorly as fascia on either side of epicranial suture before expanding at posterior terminus, light castaneous mark on anterior vertex and along margin of supra-antennal plate almost reaching lateral margin, castaneous fascia on midline between frontoclypeal suture and median ocellus becoming transverse mark along frontoclypeal suture, light castaneous in anterior arm of epicranial suture. Covered with short piceous pile dorsally, and longer silvery pile posterolateral to eye. Ocelli rosaceous, eyes tawny. Ventral head tawny with castaneous spot on medial suture of gena and lorum, posteromedial margin and transverse castaneous fascia on middle lorum curving along posterolateral margin. Short silvery pile on gena, white pubescence on lorum. Postclypeus greenish-tawny with ochraceous lateral margins, castaneous spot on posteroventral margin, longitudinal castaneous marks connecting medial terminus of transverse grooves on either side of ventral midline, transverse castaneous spot on dorsal apex, dorsum light castaneous, darker on midline and posterolateral angles, with eleven transverse grooves, white pubescense on lateral postclypeus. Anteclypeus with castaneous fascia on either side of carina not reaching anterior or posterior margins, light castaneous between these fascia, covered with short silvery pile and white pubescence. Mentum and labium greenish, labium with piceous tip reaching to middle of sternite II with long golden pile. Scape and proximal pedicel green, remaining antennal segments dark castaneous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="37.[151,1437,942,2027]" lastBlockId="38.[151,1437,151,2012]" lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<emphasis box="[199,289,1791,1816]" italics="true" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Thorax:</emphasis>
Dorsal thorax greenish-tawny. Pronotum with castaneous fascia on either side of midline, expanding laterally to form a triangular anterior margin posterior to anterior prothoracic margin, slightly widening laterally on posterior before terminating on piceous spots on ambient fissure, comma-shaped piceous mark on disc extending posteriorly from middle of paramedian fissure towards lateral fissure, piceous within paramedian and lateral fissures, piceous continues anterolaterally from anterior paramedian fissure to ambient fissure joining with extension of mark from posterior lateral fissure across disc to encircle lateral disc. Pronotal collar greenish-tawny, small transverse castaneous mark across posterior midline. Pronotum and pronotal collar covered with short silvery pile, short piceous pile dorsally along castaneous fascia and across anterior lateral portion of pronotal collar and along posterior ambient fissure. Mesonotum green with tawny submedian sigillae, large castaneous fascia along middle of submedian sigilla, incomplete fascia on disc between parapsidal suture and lateral sigilla curving around posteromedial lateral sigilla, incomplete castaneous fascia along medial portion of lateral sigilla, mark on disc between submedian sigillae expanding laterally posterior to submedian sigillae and converging to a point between scutal depressions, scutal depressions castaneous expanding posteriorly across anterior arm of cruciform elevation to posterior margin and medially to fuse with widest point of the midline mark. Cruciform elevation green, anterior arms lighter, wing groove tawny posteriorly, ochraceous anteriorly. Metanotum tawny, anterior and posteromeidal castaneous spots. Short silvery pile on mesonotum, longer and denser on lateral margin giving the appearance of a lateral silver fascia, laterally and anteriorly between arms of cruciform elevation, shorter silvery pile on dorsolateral disc. Piceous pile on posterior margin, laterally and between anterior arms of cruciform elevation and in anterior and posterior of wing groove, shorter, sparse piceous pile on dorsal surface and medial posterior margin of cruciform elevation. Ventral thoracic segments tawny, green in some 
<typeStatus box="[984,1094,575,599]" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">paratypes</typeStatus>
, except transverse castaneous fascia on basisternum 2 and basisternum 3, with castaneous spots on episternum 2, epimeron 2 and episternum 3, covered with white pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="38.[151,1437,151,2012]" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
<emphasis box="[199,276,681,704]" italics="true" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Wings:</emphasis>
Fore wings hyaline with eight apical cells, hind wings hyaline with six apical cells. Venation greenish at base becoming tawny distally, except castaneous posterior margin of anal vein 2 + 3 and arculus expanding onto radius and subcostal vein. Basal cell clouded, infuscated on posterior along cubitus anterior and distally across arculus, infuscation along proximal cubitus anterior and cubitus posterior + anal vein 1, and anal vein 2 + 3, and distal clavus. Pterostigma present. Infuscation on distal wing veins connecting to infuscation on ambient vein producing L-shaped marks, anterior marks extending to wing margin, longitudinal infuscation near proximal portions of the L-shaped marks within apical cells 2–6, a zig-zag pattern of infuscation beginning on proximal radius anterior 2 connecting across radial crossvein, connecting across radius posterior to radiomedial crossvein, across median vein 1 and median vein 1 + 2 to terminate on the median crossvein, another linear mark beginning on base of median vein 3 along proximal median vein 4 across mediocubital crossvein, and along distal cubitus anterior 1 terminating on the ambient vein, infuscation spot at node that extends into distal medial cell, proximal ulnar cell 1 and along median vein covering most of the base of ulnar cell 2, infuscation on nodal line beginning in radial cell across junction of median vein and median vein 3 + 4 expanding across base of ulnar cell 3 to middle of median cell, along proximal cubitus anterior 1, distal cubitus anterior and entirety of cubitus anterior 2 expanding onto base of apical cell 6 and distal cubital cell. Basal membrane of fore wing white mottled with reddish-orange. Venation of hind wing tawny becoming darker distally. Anal cell 3 and anal cell 2 along anal vein 3 white mottled with reddish-orange, anal cell 1 and 2 along anal vein 2 white mottled with reddish-orange. Infuscation at base of medial cell, cubital cells 1 and 2, distal anal cell 1, base and along anal veins 2 and 3 and distal margin of anal cell 2, infuscation spot on median vein 3 and 4 at junction with mediocubital crossvein. Light infuscation along outer wing margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="38.[151,1437,151,2012]" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
<emphasis box="[199,262,1385,1408]" italics="true" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Legs:</emphasis>
Legs greenish-tawny, with castaneous spots on lateral base of coxa, transverse castaneous fascia on distal anterior and lateral coxa, trochanters and femora striped with light castaneous, tibiae with castaneous spot near base, distal tibiae becoming light castaneous. Fore femora proximal spine greenish-tawny with castaneous base, thin, elongate and adpressed against femur, castaneous secondary spine triangular, angled distally, small apical spine angled distally, castaneous with ochraceous tip. Tarsi tawny with annular light castaneous mark near ochraceous distal end, tarsal claws ochraceous with tips becoming castaneous and piceous at terminus, tibial spurs and comb tawny with castaneous with darker tips. Legs covered with short golden pile, longer on tibiae and tarsi. White pubescence on trochanters.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="38.[151,1437,151,2012]" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
<emphasis box="[199,333,1665,1690]" italics="true" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Operculum:</emphasis>
Male operculum with curved lateral margin joining to smoothly rounded posterior margin, reaching to anterior of sternite II, ochraceous with castaneous base, base covered with white pubescence. Medial margin rounded, extending to middle of hind coxa. Meracanthus pointed, ochraceous with castaneous spot on base, not reaching to middle of operculum, with sparse white pubescence. Opercula with long silvery pile radiating from edge.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="38.[151,1437,151,2012]" lastBlockId="39.[151,1436,151,320]" lastPageId="39" lastPageNumber="40" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
<emphasis box="[199,314,1843,1868]" italics="true" pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Abdomen:</emphasis>
Abdominal tergites greenish-tawny, tergites covered with long silvery and long piceous pile, piceous pile medially on tergites, proportion expanding laterally in distal tergites, piceous pile dorsolaterally on tergites 2–8 shifting laterally in posterior tergites, and lateral tergites 3–4, piceous pile separated by silvery pile giving the appearance of a central piceous fascia that widens posteriorly, with two piceous fascia separated by silver on either side of central fascia. Timbal cover recurved exposing timbal, tawny with castaneous mark on dorsolateral surface, short silvery pile radiating from timbal cover. Timbal with two long and one intercalary ribs, dark spot on timbal plate. Sternites and epipleurites greenish-tawny, sternite II with transverse castaneous mark on anterolateral margin and castaneous auditory capsule, male sternites III–VII translucent, sternite VIII V-shaped radiating long golden pile. Long golden pile radiating from sternites, sternites and epipleurites with white pubescence. Spiracles white.
</paragraph>
<caption httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/1193722/files/figure.png" pageId="39" pageNumber="40" startId="39.[151,250,1818,1840]" targetBox="[151,1436,373,1797]" targetPageId="39">
<paragraph blockId="39.[151,1436,1818,1909]" pageId="39" pageNumber="40">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,287,1818,1840]" pageId="39" pageNumber="40">FIGURE 10.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[293,561,1818,1840]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="39" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nuevoleonensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[293,561,1818,1840]" italics="true" pageId="39" pageNumber="40">
<taxonomicName box="[293,401,1818,1840]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="39" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Procollina</taxonomicName>
nuevoleonensis
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[567,624,1819,1840]" pageId="39" pageNumber="40">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[567,624,1819,1840]" pageId="39" pageNumber="40" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
: A, holotype male; B, holotype male dorsum; C, holotype male timbal cover; D, holotype male operculum; E, holotype male lateral view of genitalia; F, holotype male posterior view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 5 mm; C–D, 2 mm; E–F, 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="39.[151,1437,1957,2018]" lastBlockId="40.[151,1437,151,1184]" lastPageId="40" lastPageNumber="41" pageId="39" pageNumber="40">
<emphasis box="[199,314,1957,1982]" italics="true" pageId="39" pageNumber="40">Genitalia:</emphasis>
Male pygofer greenish-tawny with castaneous posteroventral and posterior margins extending to and including dorsal beak, covered with short golden pile dorsally and piceous pile laterally, with rounded distal shoulder, dorsal beak roughly triangular with golden pile dorsally. Pygofer basal lobe indistinct, pygofer upper lobes ochraceous, elongated with medial margin tapering to rounded terminus, adpressed laterally to pygofer. Anal styles tawny, anal tube ochraceous. Median uncus lobe tawny, short, base with parallel lateral margins and semicircular terminus, surrounded by lateral uncus lobes. Lateral uncus lobes tawny, wrapping around sides of median uncus lobe bifurcating angled medially to meet along midline posterior to median uncus lobe where they recurve slightly and form a semicircular terminus and branching off at an approximate right angle when viewed laterally and parallel to terminus posterior to median uncus lobe, curling under terminus to form a support for the distal aedeagus, basal lateral uncus lobes angulate forming an enclosure around aedeagus base. Aedeagus tubular, dark castaneous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="40.[151,1437,151,1184]" box="[199,426,476,501]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Female is unknown.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="40.[151,1437,151,1184]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,454,511,536]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Measurements (mm).</emphasis>
N = 
<specimenCount box="[515,595,511,536]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" type="male">1 male</specimenCount>
. Length of body: male 25.7; length of fore wing: male 33.4; width of fore wing: male 10.5; length of head: male 3.7; width of head including eyes: male 7.0; width of pronotum including suprahumeral plates: male 9.8; width of mesonotum: male 7.2.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="40" pageNumber="41" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="40.[151,1437,151,1184]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,321,620,645]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[329,627,620,645]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nuevoleonensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[329,627,620,645]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Procollina nuevoleonensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[635,699,620,645]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[635,699,620,645]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Metcalf" authorityYear="1952" box="[1008,1121,620,645]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="biolleyi">
<emphasis box="[1008,1121,620,645]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. biolleyi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Distant" baseAuthorityYear="1906" box="[1136,1229,620,645]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="obesa">
<emphasis box="[1136,1229,620,645]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. obesa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[1245,1364,620,645]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ustulata" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[1245,1364,620,645]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. ustulata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1372,1436,620,645]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1372,1436,620,645]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[203,303,655,680]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="webbi" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[203,303,655,680]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. webbi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[315,382,655,680]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[315,382,655,680]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
by the bronzing of the fore wing in these species. Similarly, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[1124,1316,655,680]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guatemalensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[1124,1316,655,680]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. guatemalensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1328,1396,655,680]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1328,1396,655,680]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mayaensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. mayaensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[275,339,692,717]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[275,339,692,717]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[395,578,692,717]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ulnamaculata" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[395,578,692,717]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. ulnamaculata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[585,649,692,717]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[585,649,692,717]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
can be distinguished by the spots in the fore wing ulnar cells 2 and 3 not found in this new species. 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[492,682,727,752]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="parva" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[492,682,727,752]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Procollina parva</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[690,753,727,752]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[690,753,727,752]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">n. sp.</emphasis>
</taxonomicNameLabel>
can be distinguished by its head being as wide or wider than the mesonotum and 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[381,494,765,788]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minima" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[381,494,765,788]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. minima</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[501,565,764,789]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[501,565,764,789]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
can be distinguished by its small body size and radiomedial crossvein being highly angled with respect to the radial crossvein. The distal fore wing medial veins lack a spot of infuscation between the proximal vein divergence and the distal L-shaped infuscation in 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[1039,1205,836,861]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hondurensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[1039,1205,836,861]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. hondurensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1214,1279,836,861]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1214,1279,836,861]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Stal" baseAuthorityYear="1864" box="[1296,1396,836,861]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="medea">
<emphasis box="[1296,1396,836,861]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. medea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nicaraguaensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. nicaraguaensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[330,394,871,896]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[330,394,871,896]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[409,566,871,896]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigrapilosa" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[409,566,871,896]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. nigrapilosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[575,638,871,896]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[575,638,871,896]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2007" box="[702,895,873,896]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="queretaroensis">
<emphasis box="[702,895,873,896]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. queretaroensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. The hind wing margin is not infuscated or any infuscation is restricted to distal edge and the base of hind wing apical cell 4 is not infuscated in 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[1245,1365,909,932]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="convexa" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[1245,1365,909,932]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. convexa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1372,1436,908,933]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1372,1436,908,933]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[199,390,943,968]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mesomaculata" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[199,390,943,968]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. mesomaculata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[397,461,943,968]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[397,461,943,968]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
The infuscation on the fore wing cubitus anterior 2 connects across the medial cell to the infuscation on the divergence of the median vein and median vein 3 + 4 and the lateral uncus lobes form a semicircle to the apex when viewed from above in 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[740,941,1015,1040]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nuevoleonensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[740,941,1015,1040]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. nuevoleonensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[950,1015,1015,1040]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[950,1015,1015,1040]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
but the infuscation on the fore wing cubitus anterior 2 is separated from the infuscation on the divergence of the median vein and median vein 3 + 4 and the lateral uncus lobes form a triangle to apex when viewed from above in 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2018" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[988,1197,1087,1112]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tamaulipasensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[988,1197,1087,1112]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">P. tamaulipasensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1204,1267,1087,1112]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1204,1267,1087,1112]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="40" pageNumber="41" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="40.[151,1437,151,1184]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,352,1124,1149]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Distribution.</emphasis>
The species is known only from the 
<typeStatus box="[779,877,1124,1149]" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">holotype</typeStatus>
collected in the state of 
<collectingRegion box="[1161,1302,1125,1148]" country="Mexico" name="Nuevo Leon" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
Nuevo 
<collectingRegion box="[1245,1302,1125,1148]" country="Nicaragua" name="Leon" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Leon</collectingRegion>
</collectingRegion>
in northern 
<collectingCountry box="[151,240,1159,1184]" name="Mexico" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">
<collectingRegion box="[151,240,1159,1184]" country="Mexico" name="Mexico" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Mexico</collectingRegion>
</collectingCountry>
. This is the most northern distribution of all known 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2018" box="[822,941,1159,1184]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Procollina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="40" pageNumber="41" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[822,941,1159,1184]" italics="true" pageId="40" pageNumber="41">Procollina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>