<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.557.6131" ID-GBIF-Dataset="1737a4c4-5308-4026-8ce8-481843aa6256" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127872146" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-557-121" ID-ZBK="139FC0288FA94E42949F2D6B29AA649D" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FED9C27A-95D9-43B5-A789-351F1F208953" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-557-121" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 557" ModsDocTitle="Systematic revision of the Taiwanese genus Kurixalus members with a description of two new endemic species (Anura, Rhacophoridae)" checkinTime="1454061984804" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Wu, Shu-Ping, Huang, Chuan-Chin, Tsai, Chi-Li, Lin, Te-En, Jhang, Jhih-Jia &amp; Wu, Sheng-Hai" docDate="2016" docId="0CF03D6DB7239D58BD15C6BD69ACA737" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 557: 121-153" docOrigin="ZooKeys 557" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.557.6131" docTitle="Kurixalus wangi Wu, Huang, Tsai, Lin, Jhang &amp; Wu, 2016, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="FED9C27A-95D9-43B5-A789-351F1F208953" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="137" masterDocId="FFCDFF96C558BF192C0AFF97FFACFFFE" masterDocTitle="Systematic revision of the Taiwanese genus Kurixalus members with a description of two new endemic species (Anura, Rhacophoridae)" masterLastPageNumber="153" masterPageNumber="121" pageId="10" pageNumber="131" updateTime="1643628135370" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematic revision of the Taiwanese genus Kurixalus members with a description of two new endemic species (Anura, Rhacophoridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wu, Shu-Ping</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Huang, Chuan-Chin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tsai, Chi-Li</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lin, Te-En</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jhang, Jhih-Jia</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wu, Sheng-Hai</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>557</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>121</mods:start>
<mods:end>153</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.557.6131</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.557.6131</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-557-121</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">139FC0288FA94E42949F2D6B29AA649D</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">139FC0288FA94E42949F2D6B29AA649D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127872146" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FED9C27A-95D9-43B5-A789-351F1F208953" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0CF03D6DB7239D58BD15C6BD69ACA737" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="137" pageId="10" pageNumber="131">
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="131" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="131">
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="131" start="start">Taxon</pageBreakToken>
classification Animalia Anura Rhacophoridae
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="131" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="131">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/FED9C27A-95D9-43B5-A789-351F1F208953" class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="10" pageNumber="131" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="10" pageNumber="131">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 3B, 4B, 5B, 6B, 7C, D, 8; Table 1, Table S5, Table S6, Table S7
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="132" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="132" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">
Holotype. ASIZAM 0055 (Figs 3B, 9, Table 1), adult male collected on Shouka timber trail, 400 meters above sea level, Pingtong County, Taiwan (Fig. 1, Blue dots, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="22.244757">22°14'41.12&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="120.8306">120°49'50.14&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
), 9 February 2005 by Shu-Ping Wu.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">
Paratypes. NCHUZOOL 11161-62, collected on 13 September 2005 by Sheng-Hai Wu at Shuan-Liu, Pingtung County (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="22.220995">22°13'15.58&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="120.822754">120°49'21.92&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
); NCHUZOOL 11314, 11318, 11321-32, collected on 20 October 2005 by Shu-Ping Wu, on Shouka timber trail, Pingtung County, NCHUZOOL 11315, collected on 8 December 2005 by Shu-Ping Wu at Nanjenshan, Pingtung County (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="22.085646">22°05'08.32&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="120.856674">120°51'24.04&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
); NCHUZOOL 11316-17, 11319, collected on 20 December 2005 on Shouka timber trail, Pingtung County; NCHUZOOL 11334-35, collected on 7 December 2005 by Shu-Ping Wu, on Shouka timber trail, Pingtung County; NCHUZOOL 11441 (tadpoles and eggs), ASIZAM 0056 and NCHUZOOL 11445-47, collected on 9-12 February 2006 by Shu-Ping Wu, on Shouka timber trail, Pingtung County.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="132" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">
Shouka timber trail, 400 meters above sea level, Pingtung County, Taiwan, Republic of China (Fig. 1, Loc. 21, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="22.220995">22°13'15.58&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="120.822754">120°49'21.92&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="132" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">
A small to moderate-sized 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus" order="Anura" pageId="11" pageNumber="132" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Kurixalus</taxonomicName>
. Females snout-vent length averaging about 34 mm (range: 30.8-37.1 mm); males averaging 30 mm (range: 28.6-31.6 mm). Iris golden-yellow. Two anterior horns of the X-shaped marking on back extending to eyelid. Webbing extensive on toes, extending to the toe disc on the inner margin of toe V. Belly and throat whitish. Anterior margin of tadpole dorsal fin extending to posterior body. Tadpole with almost no pigment on region of tail muscle. Upper lip of tadpole with shallow transverse furrow.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="132" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">
The epithet is named and dedicated to Mr. Ching-Shong Wang for his pioneering work and contributions to the herpetology of Taiwan (
<bibRefCitation author="Wang, CS" journalOrPublisher="Quarterly Journal of the Taiwan Museum" pageId="25" pageNumber="146" pagination="141 - 191" title="The reptiles of Botel-Tobago." volume="15" year="1962">Wang 1962</bibRefCitation>
). Mr. Wang discovered two rhacophorid frogs (
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Chelodesmidae" genus="Rhacophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rhacophorus taipeianus" order="Polydesmida" pageId="11" pageNumber="132" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="taipeianus">Rhacophorus taipeianus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus idiootocus" order="Anura" pageId="11" pageNumber="132" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="idiootocus">Kurixalus idiootocus</taxonomicName>
) (
<bibRefCitation author="Liang, YS" journalOrPublisher="Quarterly journal of the Taiwan Museum" pageId="23" pageNumber="144" pagination="185 - 202" title="A new tree frog, Rhacophorustaipeianus (Anura, Rhacophoridae) from Taiwan (Formosa)." volume="16" year="1963">Liang and Wang 1963</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Kuramoto, M" journalOrPublisher="Copeia" pageId="23" pageNumber="144" pagination="31 - 42" title="A new rhacophorid tree frog from Taiwan, with comparisons to Chirixaluseiffingeri (Anura: Rhacophoridae)." url="10.2307/1445556" volume="1987" year="1987">Kuramoto and Wang 1987</bibRefCitation>
) in Taiwan and suggested, in the early 1980s, that some 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus" order="Anura" pageId="11" pageNumber="132" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Kurixalus</taxonomicName>
specimens collected near the type locality of this new species might be different from 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="11" pageNumber="132" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
(personal communication). The name is used in the genitive case.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="134" pageId="11" pageNumber="132" type="description of holotype">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="132">Description of holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="133" pageId="11" pageNumber="132">
Habitus slender, body flat, small (SVL 29.3 mm), head wider than long, snout shape in dorsal view subovoid with pointed tip; profile acuminate, slightly protruding; canthus rostralis distinct, rounded; loreal region oblique, slightly concave; nostril oval and oblique; nostril closer to tip of snout than to eye; internarial distance equals nostril to eye distance; nostril to eye distance smaller than eye diameter; interorbital distance subequal to internarial distance and eyelid width; pupil horizontally oval; tympanum distinct, round, upper margin covered by curved supratympanic fold, which runs from posterior angle of eye to arm; angle of jaw at level of middle of tympanic ring; tympanum less than half of eye diameter; tympanum to 
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="133" start="start">eye</pageBreakToken>
distance greater than half tympanum diameter; premaxillary and maxillary teeth present; choana exposed; vomerine odontoid in oval patch, equal in diameter to choana; vomerine teeth present; tongue large, forked and shallowly emarginate; no lingual papilla; vocal slits long, near commissure of jaw on floor of mouth.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="134" pageId="12" pageNumber="133">
Limbs moderately robust; forearm shorter than hand; tips of fingers expanded into discs with ventro-marginal and transverse grooves; disc of finger III about 2/3 of 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="134" start="start">tympanum</pageBreakToken>
diameter; finger length I&lt;II&lt;IV&lt;III; disc even, truncate, with indistinct transverse groove; size of disc I&lt;II&lt;III&lt;IV; disc of finger I small, same width as phalanx width; phalanges emarginate with trace of webbing; subarticular tubercles prominent, rounded, globular; prepollex expanded, rounded; glandular skin associated with nuptial pad from base of disc I on medial and dorsal side of pollex; palmar tubercle double, oval, subequal in size; supernumerary tubercles small; outer margin of fourth finger with longitudinal flat tubercles connected into a weak flap.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="134">
Heels overlapping when adpressed; hind limb moderate in length; shank shorter than thigh and longer than foot; tips of toes expanded into discs with ventro-marginal and transverse grooves; relative length of toes I&lt;II&lt;III&lt;V&lt;IV; relative size of discs I&lt;II&lt;III&lt;IV&lt;V; disc on toe I same width as phalanx width; discs truncate and with indistinct transverse grooves. Webbing moderate on all toes; webbing formula I(1)
<normalizedToken originalValue="–(trace)II(0.5)–(1.5)III(1)–(2)IV(1)–">-(trace)II(0.5)-(1.5)III(1)-(2)IV(1)-</normalizedToken>
(0.2)V; weak dermal fringe on outer side of toe V, from posterior tarsus to base of disc V, formed by continuous elongated papilla; subarticular tubercles rounded, slightly conical; subarticular tubercle on proximal joint on toe IV smaller than the others; inner metatarsal tubercle oval, small; outer metatarsal tubercle absent; supernumerary tubercle absent; small white-tipped tubercle on heel.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="134">Skin shagreen, tubercles not present on back; ventral surface slightly granular, white tipped dermal tubercles on posterior thigh. Series of tubercles near lateral margin of upper eyelids; skin smooth on flank; white tipped tubercles on lateral lower arm in ventral view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="134">Color. In preservative, dorsum grayish with black irregular spots; patches of dark brown markings on median eyelid, forming triangular X-shaped blotch; two posterior branches of the X marking terminated at middle of dorsum; two dark blotches on posterior back; flank with dark oblique irregular band demarcating grayish dorsum and whitish venter; dark irregular blotches on loreal region, antero-ventral corner of eye, and tympanum; black band from anterior eye angle, through nostril to tip of snout; gular region sprinkled with black spots; upper arm with three wide bands, thigh and shank with three bands; ventral surface orange, speckled with brown spots on gular region; vent with large dark brown blotch over cloacal opening, surrounded ventrally and dorsally by white tubercles (Figs 3B and 8).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="134">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="134">
Figure 8. Holotype of 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="13" pageNumber="134" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Dorsal (A), ventral (B), and ventral view of hand (C) and foot (D). Scale bars 10 mm in (A) and (B); 5 mm in (C) and (D).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="134">Color in life, iris golden-yellow; dorsum dark brownish-green scattered with deep brown and black spots, with dark X marking on anterior half of dorsal surface; tympanic membrane light brown to milk-white; white and rounded tubercle located on outer fringe of heel (Fig. 3B).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="134">Variation. Females were 14% larger than males (Table 1) (t-test, p &lt;0.01). Males had longer hands than females. Sexual dimorphism is evident in the possession of nuptial pads and the hypertrophied upper and lower arms in males. Females possess supracloacal dermal flaps (absent in males). The dorsum color of both genders ranges from light brown with distinctly dark markings to almost uniformly light green. Webbing patterns between the two outer metatarsals vary. Among the 69 specimens examined, one was not webbed, and two were 2/3 webbed, and the rest of the specimens were half-webbed or less. Measurements of holotype and other type specimens are shown in Table 1.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="136" pageId="14" pageNumber="135" type="description of eggs and tadpoles">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="135">
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="135" start="start">Description</pageBreakToken>
of eggs and tadpoles.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="135">
Average diameter of eggs from 4 clutches was 3.37 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
0.27) mm with capsule (n = 38) and 1.74 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
0.09) mm without capsules; eggs were creamy yellow with developing embryos. The range of total length of ten tadpoles between stages 27-32 was 13.19-22.64 mm (Fig. 4B; Table S4).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="136" pageId="14" pageNumber="135">
Dorsal surface of tadpoles dark brown; ventral surface white; pigment on tail confined mostly to upper half of tail muscle; tail fins transparent; body ovoid in lateral view, flat and sloping above, rounded below; eye dorsal, not visible from below, located on anterior 1/3 of body; nostril lateral; distance from nostril to upper lip much shorter than to eye; internarial distance subequal to interorbital distance; eye-nostril distance less than internarial distance. Face with slightly elevated ridge, from rostrum to upper lip (Fig. 5B). Oral disc terminal, opening anteriorly; lower lip slightly protruding; lateral half of upper lip with a single row of papilla; a single row of short papil 
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="136" start="start">lae</pageBreakToken>
on lower lip without median interruption. Tooth row formula 3(3)/2(1); the first and second rows on upper lip long, traverse entire width of upper labium; the third upper tooth row only visible when the entire upper lip is upturned, very short, confined to the lateral-most edge of the upper labium. The first tooth row on lower labium interrupted medially by a gap half the width of the lower jaw, the second tooth row short, less than half of oral disc width. Lower beak visible only in youngest tadpoles, black in color, upper beak straight, with very short lateral processes, upper beak ridged in middle; lower beak serrated on inner surface; older tadpoles all have broken upper beaks, lower beak white; spiracle sinistral, not tubular; opens at center of body, visible in ventral aspect. Vent dextral, opening at lower edge of ventral fin; tail deeper than body at center; dorsal and ventral fin equal in depth, tail muscle moderately strong. Dorsal fin origin on posterior body (Figs 5B and 6B).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="136" type="distribution and ecological notes">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="136">Distribution and ecological notes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="136">
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="15" pageNumber="136" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is distributed in the southern part of Pingtung County in southern Taiwan below 500 meters above sea level (Fig. 1, Blue dots). All specimens were collected in the shrubs of secondary forests or lowland broad-leaved forests at low altitudes.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="136" type="mating calls">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="136">Mating calls.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="136">
Mating calls were heard in bushes or on tree branches up to 3 m above the ground between September and March, peaking in December. A slow call and a rapid call were identified. Both types of call consisted of a single beeping sound. Slow calls recorded in the field had an average duration of 99 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
19) ms (n = 30, equivalent hereafter) and rapid calls had an average duration of 57 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
15) ms. Intervals between notes were 1122 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
230) ms (slow calls) and 115 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
22) ms (rapid calls). For the slow and rapid calls, the maximum frequencies of calls were 3185 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
194) Hz (slow calls) and 3072 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
47) Hz (rapid calls); the minimum frequencies of calls were 2399 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
122) Hz (slow calls) and 2565 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
62) Hz (rapid calls). (Fig. 7C, D; Table 2). The diagrams of all 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus" order="Anura" pageId="15" pageNumber="136" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Kurixalus</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="species’">species'</normalizedToken>
calls from Taiwan are illustrated in Fig. 7 and detailed in Table 2.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="136">Eggs were discovered in tree hollows, plastic pipes embedded in retaining walls on slopes (Fig. 4B), and discarded plastic cups on the forest floor. Eggs of some clutches adhered in a single layer to the walls above water; others were submerged in water. The average clutch size was 70 (n = 7, range: 56-104). Tadpole stomachs contained yellow yolky substances, suggesting that the tadpoles might have ingested eggs recently.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="137" pageId="15" pageNumber="136" type="morphological comparisons">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="136">Morphological comparisons.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="136">
Within-species comparisons showed that the body size was differentiated by sex in 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="15" pageNumber="136" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="15" pageNumber="136" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., but not in 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus berylliniris" order="Anura" pageId="15" pageNumber="136" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="berylliniris">Kurixalus berylliniris</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (Table 1, Table S5). Among-species comparisons indicated that males were significantly different in body size (p &lt;0.001, Table S5). ANCOVA tests showed that the three species were significantly different in all morphometric characteristics. For the ANCOVA of male morphometric data, all characters differed significantly, and 17 characteristics exhibited significant variation in size-adjusted means (Table S6). In females, all characteristics also differed in slopes, and eight characteristics exhibited significant variation in size-adjusted means. A repeated ANOVA comparing the two new species and 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="15" pageNumber="136" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
showed that all morphometric characteristics differed significantly among species between males and females (Table S6).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
<pageBreakToken pageId="16" pageNumber="137" start="start">In</pageBreakToken>
the PCA, after eliminating the effect of size by using a normalizing ratio (measurements divided by SVL) and omitting the five non-normal morphometric characteristics (HL, EN, TAD, D3L, TL), 23.98% of the variation was associated with body size (Table S7). The large-sized 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus berylliniris" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="berylliniris">Kurixalus berylliniris</taxonomicName>
sp. n. was separated from the other three species, while 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus idiootocus" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="idiootocus">Kurixalus idiootocus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. overlapped considerably (Fig. 9A). In the plot of two shape components (Fig. 9B, Table S7), 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus berylliniris" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="berylliniris">Kurixalus berylliniris</taxonomicName>
sp. n. and 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
are clearly differentiated from the other two species 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus idiootocus" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="idiootocus">Kurixalus idiootocus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
Figure 9. PCA morphometric comparisons of four 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Kurixalus</taxonomicName>
species from Taiwan. Scatterplots of (A) principal components 1 and 2, and (B) principal components 2 and 3 of size-adjusted morphometric data for male frogs of the four 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Kurixalus</taxonomicName>
species. The 95% confidence ellipses for each population (ELM) are shown.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="16" pageNumber="137" type="mating call comparisons">
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="137">Mating call comparisons.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
The calls of the two new species and of 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
were found to be different in maximum frequency, single note duration, and time interval between notes of mating calls. The minimum frequency among the three species was not different (Table 3).
</paragraph>
<caption ID-Table-UUID="27CAFF199C68E16F2F315DA46968D8D5" httpUri="http://table.plazi.org/id/27CAFF199C68E16F2F315DA46968D8D5" pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
Table 3. Comparisons of the characteristics of slow mating calls among 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus berylliniris" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="berylliniris">Kurixalus berylliniris</taxonomicName>
sp. n. and 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
<table pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
<tr pageId="16" pageNumber="137">
<th colspan="1" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
vs. 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus berylliniris" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="berylliniris">Kurixalus berylliniris</taxonomicName>
*
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus berylliniris" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="berylliniris">Kurixalus berylliniris</taxonomicName>
* vs. 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
*
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus eiffingeri" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="eiffingeri">Kurixalus eiffingeri</taxonomicName>
vs. 
<taxonomicName class="Amphibia" family="Rhacophoridae" genus="Kurixalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kurixalus wangi" order="Anura" pageId="16" pageNumber="137" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="wangi">Kurixalus wangi</taxonomicName>
*
</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>