<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6160175" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5918b440-d835-4e34-9618-f1b58aab1bed" ID-GBIF-Taxon="114913880" ID-HNS-Pub="27552" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6160175" checkinTime="1409237179507" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Longino, John T" docDate="2013" docId="3B15380E778A84ADC7FA507BE25BD415" docLanguage="en" docName="27552.htm.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 3699" docTitle="Octostruma leptoceps Longino, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" masterDocId="EE74F677DCA4F13702125E9CE8D29A0F" masterDocTitle="A revision of the ant genus Octostruma Forel 1912 (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)" masterLastPageNumber="61" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" updateTime="1645264522075" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of the ant genus Octostruma Forel 1912 (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Longino, John T</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3699</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>61</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-Pub">27552</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.3699.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">65A19D30-8E7A-4073-B92B-9709F8384752</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6160175" ID-GBIF-Taxon="114913880" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6160175" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:3B15380E778A84ADC7FA507BE25BD415" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B15380E778A84ADC7FA507BE25BD415" lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="mainText">
<taxonomicName authority="Longino" authorityName="Longino" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leptoceps">
Octostruma leptoceps 
<authority pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Longino</authority>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="37" pageNumber="38" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="mainText">(Figs 1A, 5H, 28, 43)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="mainText">
Type material. Holotype worker: HONDURAS, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Cortés" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Cortes</normalizedToken>
: PN Cusuco, 15.48940, -88.23621, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="±" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">+/-</normalizedToken>
20 m, 1290 m, mesophyll forest, ex sifted leaf litter, 30 May 2010 (LLAMA, Wa-C-06-2-12) [CAS, unique specimen identifier CASENT0617645].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="mainText">Geographic range. Honduras.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="mainText">Diagnosis. Basal five teeth of mandible acute; labrum triangular with straight, evenly converging sides, anterior lobes converging and confluent at apex, such that labrum apex is blunt but not distinctly bilobed; head very narrow, CI 94.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="description">
<paragraph lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="mainText">
Description. Worker. HW 0.68, HL 0.73, WL 0.87, CI 94 (n=1); labrum as in Fig. 1A, sides straight, strap-like lateral portions converging from base to apex, apex bluntly rounded, not bilobed; mandible triangular, in profile view with mandible closed, base in same plane as clypeus, evenly curved downward toward apex; mandibles closed on holotype, but basal teeth visible, acute, apparently as in Fig. 3B, tooth 1 continuous with basal rim of dorsal surface; dorsal surface of mandible roughened; ventral surface flat, smooth and shining; interior surface concave, smooth and shining; scape with pronounced anterobasal lobe, dorsal surface smooth, matte; clypeus with broad, shallow emargination anteriorly; clypeus smooth, sublucid, with sparse 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
; face uniformly irregularly rugose; frontal carinae faint, nearly obsolete; antennal socket deep, dorsal rim of socket continuous with pronounced dorsal margin of antennal scrobe; antennal scrobe deep, strongly delimited dorsally, posteriorly, and ventrally with sharply defined thin cuticular rim; compound eye small, circular, composed of about 7 ommatidia; distinct carina extends from ventral margin of antennal socket across floor of scrobe to compound eye; scrobe floor 
<pageBreakToken pageId="38" pageNumber="39" start="start">matte</pageBreakToken>
; vertex margin anterior to occipital carina smooth, matte (top of head, not visible in face view); occipital carina extends anteriorly on ventral surface of head about to level of compound eye; postgenal suture visible as impressed line on undersurface of head; undersurface rugulose.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="mainText">Promesonotum moderately convex in profile, promesonotal suture moderately impressed; metanotal groove not impressed; propodeum with distinct dorsal and posterior faces; dorsal face weakly convex; propodeal spines well-developed, acute, laterally flattened, extending ventrally as thin carinae; propodeal spiracle somewhat protruding, located below propodeal spine, not quite abutting posterior margin, diameter about equal to width of base of propodeal spine; all surfaces of mesosoma matte; entire promesonotum irregularly rugose, with similar sculpture to face; mesopleuron and side of propodeum confluent; entire mesopleuron and propodeum smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="mainText">
Petiole in profile with peduncle differentiated from node, node with distinct anterior face; posterodorsal face of node an even convexity; anteroventral margin with anteriorly-directed tooth subtended by short posterior flange; postpetiole low, broad, weakly crescent-shaped in dorsal view; dorsum of petiolar node and postpetiole punctatorugose; first gastral tergite and sternite densely punctate, interspaces smooth and shining, tergal 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puncta">puncta</taxonomicName>
smaller posteriorly; first gastral sternite strongly convex, with prominent blunt medial keel.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="mainText">Anterior labral lobe with radiating tuft of soft, thick, translucent, capitate setae of unequal length projecting from apex (like Fig. 2); each larger mandibular tooth with fully appressed seta running length of tooth; anterior margin of scape with about nine stiff clavate setae; clypeus, face, promesonotal dorsum, petiolar node, and dorsal postpetiole with conspicuous, yellow, appressed ground pilosity of long, thin setae; face of holotype appears largely devoid of erect setae but specimen may have lost setae; a single spatulate seta present on one lateral vertex margin, and what may be a seta near medial vertex margin (Fig. 5H drawn to show what may be setal arrangement on typical specimens); mesosomal dorsum lacking erect setae; mesotibia with conspicuous ground pilosity, about 5 spatulate setae of variable length at apex; petiole and postpetiole lacking erect setae; first gastral tergite lacking erect setae, ground pilosity fully appressed, sparse (length of setae less than distance between them); first gastral sternite with abundant spatulate setae clustered on posterior half, anterior half devoid of setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="mainText">Color dark brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="mainText">The queen is unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="mainText">Biology. This is known from a single worker collected in mesophyll cloud forest at 1290 m elevation. The specimen was in a sample of sifted leaf litter from the forest floor.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="mainText">
Etymology. The 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Octostruma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="name">name</taxonomicName>
refers to narrow head relative to other species. It is a noun in apposition and thus invariant.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>