<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.770.24908" ID-GBIF-Dataset="39143575-5dd7-49dd-a914-eeaf43060fb1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156199960" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970--137" ID-ZBK="63FDA225900E42A69FD18B02D8CD1F44" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0233F3AD-8F60-4CBB-B64B-B0A48857CBFF" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970--137" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys " ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the ant genus Proceratium Roger (Hymenoptera, Formicidae, Proceratiinae) in China – with descriptions of three new species based on micro-CT enhanced next-generation-morphology" checkinTime="1555317040329" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Staab, Michael, Garcia, Francisco Hita, Liu, Cong, Xu, Zheng-Hui &amp; Economo, Evan P." docDate="2018" docId="2099C9001B8CA7AF90902DF3D4CF0CFC" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 770: 137-192" docOrigin="ZooKeys 770" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.770.24908" docTitle="Proceratium kepingmai Staab, Xu &amp; Hita Garcia, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="0233F3AD-8F60-4CBB-B64B-B0A48857CBFF" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="137" masterDocId="0E3A8F7EF24EFFF1D203FF811E3EFFCD" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the ant genus Proceratium Roger (Hymenoptera, Formicidae, Proceratiinae) in China - with descriptions of three new species based on micro-CT enhanced next-generation-morphology" masterLastPageNumber="192" masterPageNumber="137" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" updateTime="1643549215339" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the ant genus Proceratium Roger (Hymenoptera, Formicidae, Proceratiinae) in China - with descriptions of three new species based on micro-CT enhanced next-generation-morphology</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Staab, Michael</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Garcia, Francisco Hita</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liu, Cong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Xu, Zheng-Hui</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Economo, Evan P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>770</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>137</mods:start>
<mods:end>192</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.770.24908</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.770.24908</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970--137</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">63FDA225900E42A69FD18B02D8CD1F44</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">63FDA225900E42A69FD18B02D8CD1F44</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="156199960" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0233F3AD-8F60-4CBB-B64B-B0A48857CBFF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2099C9001B8CA7AF90902DF3D4CF0CFC" lastPageNumber="137" pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/0233F3AD-8F60-4CBB-B64B-B0A48857CBFF" authority="Staab, Xu &amp; Hita Garcia" class="Insecta" family="FAMILIA" genus="Proceratium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Proceratium kepingmai" order="ORDO" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kepingmai">Proceratium kepingmai Staab, Xu &amp; Hita Garcia</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="137">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 5B, 7A, 7C, 12, 13, 24
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
Holotype. Pinned worker from CHINA, Jiangxi Province, near the village Xingangshan, ca. 15 km SE of Wuyuan, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="29.124445">29°7'28&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="117.91111">117°54'40&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, 270 m asl, secondary subtropical mixed forest, Winkler leaf litter extraction, 26-III-2015, leg. Michael Staab, label 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“MS1836”">&quot;MS1836&quot;</normalizedToken>
(CASENT0790031), deposited in SWFU.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
Paratype. Pinned worker from CHINA, Zhejiang Province, Gutianshan National Nature Reserve, ca. 30 km NW of Kaihua, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="29.247223">29°14'50&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="118.13611">118°8'10&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, 665 m asl, secondary subtropical mixed forest, Winkler leaf litter extraction, 27-IV-2015, leg. Merle Noack, label 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“MS1859”">&quot;MS1859&quot;</normalizedToken>
(CASENT0790032), deposited in ZMBH.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
Cybertype. Volumetric raw data (in DICOM format), 3D rotation video (in.mp4 format, see Suppl. material 5: Video 3), still images of surface volume rendering, and 3D surface (in PLY format) of the physical holotype (CASENT0790031) in addition to montage photos illustrating head in full-face view, profile and dorsal views of the body. The data is deposited at Dryad (
<bibRefCitation author="Staab, M" journalOrPublisher="American Naturalist" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" url="https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.h6j0g4p" year="2018">Staab et al. 2018</bibRefCitation>
, http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.h6j0g4p) and can be freely accessed as virtual representation of the type. In addition to the cybertype data at Dryad, we also provide a freely accessible 3D surface model of the holotype at Sketchfab (https://skfb.ly/6txMy).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Proceratium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Proceratium kepingmai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kepingmai">Proceratium kepingmai</taxonomicName>
differs from the other members of the 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. itoi" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="itoi">P. itoi</taxonomicName>
clade by the following character combination: large species (TL 4.39-4.54); sides of head weakly convex, broadest at level of eyes and gently narrowing anteriorly and stronger posteriorly; vertex almost straight; very reduced eyes (OI 2-3) consisting of a single minute ommatidium; frontal carinae well developed, with large lamellae that extend laterally above the antennal insertions; frontal furrow darker than the surrounding anterior cephalic dorsum; posterodorsal corners of the propodeum broadly angular; propodeal declivity densely punctured, mostly opaque; posterior face of petiolar node in profile steeper than anterior face and about half as long as anterior face; apex of petiolar node distinctly broader than long in dorsal view; in addition to dense pubescence, erect hairs present on scapes and dorsal surface of body, longest of those hairs at most as long as the maximum dorsoventral diameter of metafemur.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
Figure 12. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Proceratium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Proceratium kepingmai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kepingmai">Proceratium kepingmai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. holotype worker (CASENT0790031). A Body in profile B Body in dorsal view C Head in full-face view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
Figure 13. Still images from surface display volume renderings of 3D model of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Proceratium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Proceratium kepingmai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kepingmai">Proceratium kepingmai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. holotype worker (CASENT0790031). A Body in profile B Body in dorsal view C Head in dorsal view D Head in anterodorsal view E Head in anterior view F Head in ventral view G Head in profile H Mesosoma in profile I Mesosoma in dorsal view J Propodeum in posterodorsal view K Abdominal segment II and parts of III in profile L Abdominal segment II and parts of III in dorsal view M Abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–VII">II-VII</normalizedToken>
in profile N Abdominal segment III and parts of II and IV in dorsal view O Abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–VII">II-VII</normalizedToken>
in ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Worker measurements.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Holotype.TL 4.39; EL 0.02; SL 0.57; HL 0.92; HLM 1.08; HW 0.86; WL 1.14; MFeL 0.71; MTiL 0.60; MBaL 0.44; PeL 0.45; PeW 0.36; LT3 0.64; LS4 0.32; LT4 1.08; OI 2; CI 92; SI 60; MFeI 83; MTiI 70; MBaI 51; DPeI 80; IGR 0.30; ASI 169.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Paratype.TL 4.54; EL 0.03; SL 0.59; HL 0.98; HLM 1.14; HW 0.90; WL 1.24; MFeL 0.79; MTiL 0.65; MBaL 0.48; PeL 0.46; PeW 0.37; LT3 0.65; LS4 0.34; LT4 1.05; OI 3; CI 93; SI 62; MFeI 88; MTiI 72; MBaI 53; DPeI 80; IGR 0.33; ASI 161.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Worker description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">In full-face view, head slightly longer than broad (CI 92-93), sides weakly convex, broadest at the eye level and gently narrowing anteriorly and (stronger) posteriorly, vertex weakly convex, almost straight. Clypeus reduced and narrow, with a broadly triangular median anterior projection. Frontal carinae relatively short, moderately separated, slightly covering antennal insertions, constantly diverging posteriorly, lateral expansions of anterior part of frontal carinae developed as broad lamellae, raised, conspicuously and broadly extending laterally above antennal insertions; frontal area convex; frontal furrow well developed as a raised carina, starting at the clypeal projection and extending over the anterior 2/5 of the cephalic dorsum, with a short gap at the level where the lamellae of frontal carinae are broadest. Eyes reduced, minute (OI 2-3), consisting of a single ommatidium and located on midline of head. Antennae 12-segmented, scapes short (SI 60-62), not reaching posterior head margin and thickening apically. Mandibles elongate and triangular, masticatory margin with four teeth in total, apical tooth long and acute, the other teeth smaller and decreasing in size from second to fourth tooth, gap between second and third tooth larger than between other teeth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Mesosoma in profile slightly convex and slightly longer than maximum head length including mandibles (WL 1.14-1.24 vs. HLM 1.08-1.14). Lower mesopleurae (katepisterna) with well-demarcated sutures, upper mesopleurae (anepisterna) with inconspicuous sutures, no other sutures developed on lateral and dorsal mesosoma; lower mesopleurae weakly inflated posteriorly; posterodorsal corner of propodeum broadly angular, propodeal lobes weakly developed as bluntly rounded lamellae; propodeal declivity almost vertical, slightly inclined anteriorly; in posterodorsal view sides of propodeum separated from declivity by distinct lamellate margins; in profile propodeal spiracle rounded, at mid height, opening of spiracle slightly facing posteriorly. Legs moderately long; all tibiae with a pectinate spur; calcar of strigil without a basal spine; pretarsal claws simple; arolia present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Petiolar node in profile high, nodiform, with a straight and sloping anterior face, dorsum of node broadly rounded, posterior face half as long and steeper than anterior face; petiole in dorsal view longer than broad but apex of node clearly broader than long; ventral process moderately developed on anterior petiole, with a relatively indistinct rectangular projection.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
In dorsal view abdominal segment III anteriorly much broader than petiole; its sides convex; abdominal sternite III anteriomedially with a conspicuous depression marked by a thin rim. Constriction between abdominal segments III and IV deep. Abdominal segment IV very large, recurved (IGR 0.30-0.33) and posteriorly strongly rounded, with a lamella on its anterior border around the constriction to abdominal segment III, this lamella thicker ventrally than dorsally; abdominal tergum IV 1.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.7×">-1.7x</normalizedToken>
longer than abdominal tergum III (ASI 161-169); remaining abdominal tergites and sternites inconspicuous and projecting anteriorly. Sting large and extended.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
Whole body covered with dense mat of short, decumbent to suberect pubescent hairs; additionally, the dorsal surfaces of body interspersed with significantly longer suberect and erect hairs, such hairs also present on abdominal sterna III + IV, scapes (anterior faces of scapes with many hairs, posterior faces with single hairs), and legs (ventral faces of femora and tibiae with many hairs, dorsal faces with single hairs); the longest hairs on dorsal surface of body at most as long as the maximum dorsoventral diameter of metafemur. Mandibles striate; entire body including propodeal declivity densely punctate; on sides of pronotum punctures aligned in diffuse lines, appearing striate; punctures on antennae, legs, and abdominal segment IV finer than on rest of body, abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="V–VII">V-VII</normalizedToken>
very superficially punctured and shiny. Body color uniformly orange brown to reddish brown, vertex of head slightly darker, frontal furrow conspicuously darker than surrounding cephalic dorsum, legs, antennal funiculus, and abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="V–VII">V-VII</normalizedToken>
yellowish brown.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">The species epithet is a patronym in honor of the Chinese botanist Prof. Keping Ma and his efforts in establishing the BEF-China project and promoting biodiversity research and nature conservation in China. All specimens of this species were collected in old-growth subtropical forest, an ecosystem Prof. Ma has investigated in detail.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Distribution and ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
Both specimens were collected in secondary mixed evergreen broadleaved forest of relatively advanced age, as indicated by the presence of large trees. The paratype was collected within the Gutianshan National Nature Reserve (
<bibRefCitation author="Yu, MJ" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Zhejiang University (Agriculture and Life Science)" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" pagination="375 - 380" title="Forest vegetation types in Gutianshan Natural Reserve in Zhejiang." volume="27" year="2001">Yu et al. 2001</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Bruelheide, H" journalOrPublisher="Ecological Monographs" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" pagination="25 - 41" title="Community assembly during secondary forest succession in a Chinese subtropical forest." url="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210x.12126" volume="81" year="2011">Bruelheide et al. 2011</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Staab, M" journalOrPublisher="ZooKeys" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" pagination="65 - 73" title="A new species of the Aenictuswroughtonii group (Hymenoptera, Formicidae) from South-East China." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.391.7213" volume="391" year="2014">Staab 2014</bibRefCitation>
), one of the larger remaining fragments of subtropical broadleaved forest in southeast China. The forest at this locality (the type locality is a similar but much smaller forest fragment) is on sloped land and rich in plant species; more than 250 woody species have been recorded on about 8000 ha. Approximately 50% of the woody species are deciduous but the tree layer is dominated by evergreen species including 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Castanopsis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Castanopsis eyrei" order="Fagales" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="eyrei">Castanopsis eyrei</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName family="Fagaceae" lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="family">Fagaceae</taxonomicName>
) (Champ. ex Benth.) Tutch., 
<taxonomicName authority="C.K.Schneid. (Oerst.)" authorityName="C.K.Schneid. (Oerst.)" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Cyclobalanopsis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Cyclobalanopsis glauca" order="Fagales" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="glauca">Cyclobalanopsis glauca</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName family="Fagaceae" lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="family">Fagaceae</taxonomicName>
) (Thunb.) Oerst., 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Lauraceae" genus="Machilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Machilus thunbergii" order="Laurales" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="thunbergii">Machilus thunbergii</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName family="Lauraceae" lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="family">Lauraceae</taxonomicName>
) Sieb. et Zucc., and 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Theaceae" genus="Schima" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Schima superba" order="Ericales" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="superba">Schima superba</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName family="Theaceae" lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="family">Theaceae</taxonomicName>
) Gardn. et Champ. No direct observations of biology and natural history are available for 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. kepingmai" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="kepingmai">P. kepingmai</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="taxonomic notes">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Taxonomic notes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Proceratium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Proceratium kepingmai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kepingmai">Proceratium kepingmai</taxonomicName>
is the largest (WL 1.14-1.24) member of the 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. itoi" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="itoi">P. itoi</taxonomicName>
clade and has, even for eye-bearing 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Proceratium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Proceratium" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Proceratium</taxonomicName>
, very minute eyes (OI 2-3). From each of the species in the clade with very similar body proportions (particularly indices) that also have erect hairs on the dorsal surface of the body (
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. itoi" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="itoi">P. itoi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. longmenense" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="longmenense">P. longmenense</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. malesianum" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="malesianum">P. malesianum</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
; no erect hairs, only dense pubescence in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. williamsi" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="williamsi">P. williamsi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. zhaoi" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="zhaoi">P. zhaoi</taxonomicName>
) it can safely be separated by one or more characters. In 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. kepingmai" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="kepingmai">P. kepingmai</taxonomicName>
the posterodorsal corner of the propodeum is angular (rounded in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. itoi" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="itoi">P. itoi</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. malesianum" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="malesianum">P. malesianum</taxonomicName>
), which is also the case for 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. longmenense" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="longmenense">P. longmenense</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
. However, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. longmenense" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="longmenense">P. longmenense</taxonomicName>
lacks erect hairs on the scape (at least some erect hairs present in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. kepingmai" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="kepingmai">P. kepingmai</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
), has a relatively narrower head (CI 85) with longer scapes (SI 68) (CI 92-93 and SI 60-62 in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. kepingmai" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="kepingmai">P. kepingmai</taxonomicName>
), and frontal carinae that touch each other at their anteriormost level (clearly separated in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. kepingmai" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="kepingmai">P. kepingmai</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
). With 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
, the most similar species, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. kepingmai" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="kepingmai">P. kepingmai</taxonomicName>
also shares the broad frontal carinae that have large lamellae and are conspicuously extended laterally above the antennal insertions (not extended and narrower in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. longmenense" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="longmenense">P. longmenense</taxonomicName>
). In contrast, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. kepingmai" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="kepingmai">P. kepingmai</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
by the shape of the head in full-face view that has convex sides, which are broadest at the level of the eyes and narrow weakly anteriorly and more strongly posteriorly towards to almost straight vertex (sides straight, not narrowing anteriorly and vertex convex in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
), the densely punctured and mostly opaque propodeal declivity (sparsely and superficially punctured and very shiny in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
), the conspicuous frontal furrow that is darker than the rest of the surrounding anterior cephalic dorsum (inconspicuous and of same color in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
), the posterior face of petiolar node in profile steeper than the anterior face of the node and about half as long as the anterior face (posterior face as steep as anterior face and less than half as long in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
), the apex of the petiolar node that is clearly broader than long in dorsal view (less broad than long in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
), and relatively fewer and shorter erect hairs (see 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. bruelheidei" pageId="0" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="bruelheidei">P. bruelheidei</taxonomicName>
for details).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="137" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="137">Apart from the small difference in body size (WL 1.14 vs. 1.24) there is no observable variation between the two specimens.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>