<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6224448" ID-GBIF-Dataset="7b48e51c-5516-4e0c-bcd7-59f71af9dc2a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100122457" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6224448" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9FDE1093-24E4-423B-ABBB-606604E5A32B" ModsDocID="22781" checkinTime="1249509728275" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Borowiec, M. L." docDate="2009" docId="16369ED527A3204D558789712991DEF1" docLanguage="en" docName="22781.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2069" docSource="http://hol.osu.edu/reference-full.html?id=22781" docTitle="Cerapachys doryloides Borowiec, 2009, n. sp." docType="treatment" docUuid="9FDE1093-24E4-423B-ABBB-606604E5A32B" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="11" lastPageNumber="48" masterDocId="E8A068E8C78AEA36E434C844B9406C4E" masterDocTitle="New ant species related to Cerapachys sexspinus and discussion of the status of Yunodorylus (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="58" masterPageNumber="43" pageNumber="46" updateTime="1645536898741" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New ant species related to Cerapachys sexspinus and discussion of the status of Yunodorylus (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Borowiec, M. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2069</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>58</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hol.osu.edu/reference-full.html?id=22781</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">22781</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">07A6B4C4-BCB0-42B8-83FB-2046E47A9AC3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6224448" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100122457" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6224448" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9FDE1093-24E4-423B-ABBB-606604E5A32B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/16369ED527A3204D558789712991DEF1" lastPageNumber="48" pageNumber="46">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="46">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:251620" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys doryloides" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="doryloides">Cerapachys doryloides</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="46">Figs. 1-2, 13</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="47" pageNumber="46">
Holotype worker measurements: HW 0.62, HL 0.64, SL 0.32, MH 0.41, ML 0.95, PrW 0.42, PW 0.31, PL 0.30, IIIAW 0.45, IIIAL 0.35, IVAW 0.60, IVAL 0.41, FFeW 0.19, FFeL 0.45, HFeL 0.45, FTiL 0.37, HTiL 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="47">0.47</pageStartToken>
, FBaL 0.23, HBaL 0.29, CI 103, MI 232, PI 97
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="47">Head almost as wide as long, widest at about midlength; sides parallel, slightly convex and converging anteriorly and posteriorly at about one fifth of head length; vertexal margin shallowly concave. Parafrontal ridges completely absent. Mandibles narrow and long; when closed, basal margin separated from anterior clypeal margin by wide gap. Basal margin long, meeting masticatory at obtuse angle; masicatory margin with two blunt teeth basally; remainder of margin elongated into broadly rounded apical tooth. Lateroclypeal tooth a small tubercle. Lateral portion of clypeus poorly developed, consisting only of semi-circular ridge surrounding antennal insertion. Antennae 12-segmented. Palp formula unknown.</paragraph>
<caption>
<caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="47">
FIGURES 1-2. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:251620" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys doryloides" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="doryloides">Cerapachys doryloides</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
, holotype worker; 1: dorsal view; 2: side view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="47">Mesosoma moderately stout, rectangular in dorsal view; dorsal surface flattened, bordered at the lateral sides by a distinct angle but with no margin. Openings of propodeal spiracles broadly oval, directed outwardly and upwardly at angle of 45°. Declivous face of propodeum immarginate above propodeal lobes. Propodeal lobes very small. Front femur short, very broad, and laterally compressed. Metatibial gland a whitish, elongate patch of cuticle, little longer than maximum width of hind tibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="48">Petiole</pageStartToken>
about as long as wide, with well developed dorsal and posterior faces. Subpetiolar process short and moderately broad; in side view with ventral margin sloping towards posterior end; translucent narrowing present along ventral margin, lamella gradually widening distally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">Abdominal tergite III wide relative to following segment, in side view the whole segment is robust, with developed anterior, perpendicular face.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">Pygidial field small, weakly impressed with four teeth on each side.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">Hypopygidium unarmed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">Mandibles sculptured with widely spaced punctures, interspaces shining. Head with regular punctures, spaced from about half of their diameter on dorsal and anterior lateral surfaces, to wider than diameter in posterior lateral section. Similar sculpture on dorsal surface of mesosoma with longitudinal stripe devoid of sculpturation in middle. All interspaces shining. Lateral sides of mesosoma microreticulate, only area around propodeal spiracle devoid of any sculpture and shining. Sides of petiole microreticulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">Body pilosity composed of (1) dense, subdecumbent hairs present on head, mesosoma, and abdominal segments and (2) about one and half times longer, subdecumbent to suberect hairs present on the pronotal shoulders, propodeum, petiole, margins of gastral tergites. Outer surface of middle tibiae with two modified peg-like setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">Color: yellowish-orange with brownish mandibles and genal areas around mandibular insertions. Gyne and male unknown</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="48">
Diagnosis and discussion. This species is most easily recognized by its peculiar falcate mandibles, unique in described workers of 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2249" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachyinae Forel" pageNumber="48" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Cerapachyinae">Cerapachyinae</taxonomicName>
. These are elongate, somewhat resembling the condition observed in 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2488" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Dorylus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Dorylus Fabricius" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="48" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Dorylus</taxonomicName>
, with the narrow masticatory margin equipped with two (excluding apical) well visible teeth and meeting the long basal margin at an obtuse angle, resulting in a wide gap between mandibles and clypeal margin at closure (Fig. 13).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="48">Since only one specimen of this species was available for study, nothing can be said of individual variability and degree of worker polymorphism.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="48">
Material examined. Holotype worker. MALAYSIA: Sarawak, Bako National Park, near Kuching, rainforest, soil core, IV 1978 (N.M. Collins) [
<collectionCode collectionName="United Kingdom, London, The Natural History Museum [formerly British Museum (Natural History)]">BMNH</collectionCode>
]
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>