<document ID-DOI="10.1206/819.1" ID-ISSN="0003-0090" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5404446" approvalRequired="231" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="222" approvalRequired_for_treatments="7" checkinTime="1630343522869" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Grismado, Cristian J. &amp; Ramírez, Martín J." docDate="2013" docId="03D1ED14FF9DFF8386481A5AFCA3F9B0" docLanguage="en" docName="B383.pdf" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 2013 (383)" docSource="http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/819.1" docStyle="DocumentStyle:915933466F796C9C739DF4DB6B8DCFA6.7:BulAmeMusNatHis.2011-.journal_article.1cover.type1" docStyleId="915933466F796C9C739DF4DB6B8DCFA6" docStyleName="BulAmeMusNatHis.2011-.journal_article.1cover.type1" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Neotrops Grismado &amp; Ramírez 2013, new genus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="7" masterDocId="FFE8956CFF98FF8485031C7FFF9EFFEA" masterDocTitle="The New World Goblin Spiders Of The New Genus Neotrops (Araneae: Oonopidae), Part 1" masterLastPageNumber="150" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="5" updateTime="1630645131315" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The New World Goblin Spiders Of The New Genus Neotrops (Araneae: Oonopidae), Part 1</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Grismado, Cristian J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ramírez, Martín J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2013-12-02</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2013</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>383</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>150</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/819.1</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.1206/819.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0003-0090</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5404446</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03D1ED14FF9DFF8386481A5AFCA3F9B0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D1ED14FF9DFF8386481A5AFCA3F9B0" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">
<subSubSection box="[843,1085,1573,1594]" pageId="5" pageNumber="5" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="5.[843,1085,1573,1594]" box="[843,1085,1573,1594]" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">
<heading box="[843,1085,1573,1594]" centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="5" pageNumber="5" reason="2">
<taxonomicName authority="Grismado &amp; Ramírez, 2013" authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[843,947,1573,1594]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="5" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus" status="new genus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[843,947,1573,1594]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">Neotrops</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[963,1085,1573,1594]" pageId="5" pageNumber="5" rank="genus">new genus</taxonomicNameLabel>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="5" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="5.[701,1228,1617,1759]" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">
<typeStatus box="[730,793,1617,1641]" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">TYPE</typeStatus>
SPECIES: 
<taxonomicName authority="Grismado &amp; Ramírez, 2013" authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[939,1150,1618,1641]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="5" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="darwini" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[939,1150,1618,1641]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">Neotrops darwini</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="5" pageNumber="5" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="5" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="5.[701,1228,1617,1759]" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">
ETYMOLOGY: The generic name is a contraction of Neotropical and 
<taxonomicName box="[1081,1167,1708,1729]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Oonops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="5" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1081,1167,1708,1729]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="5">Oonops</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, and is masculine in gender.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="6" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="6.[93,620,211,1759]" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">
DIAGNOSIS: 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[272,376,213,234]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="6" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[272,376,213,234]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">Neotrops</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
comprises soft-bodied oonopids usually with well-developed macrosetae on the forelegs. The males resemble those of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dalmas" authorityYear="1916" box="[309,454,301,322]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Heteroonops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="6" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[309,454,301,322]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">Heteroonops</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the palpal conformation, but differ by having a vesicle inside the bulb that connects to the conductor through a slitlike opening, presumably with secretory function (figs. 15C–F, 44 D–E), and by lacking the posteriorly directed projections on the endites. Females also resemble those of 
<emphasis box="[308,460,506,527]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dalmas" authorityYear="1916" box="[308,455,506,527]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Heteroonops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="6" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Heteroonops</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
but differ by having normal pedipalps (not particularly elongated or spinose), by lacking the posterior receptacle in the internal genitalia, and possessing only a more or less rounded plate, with an anterior concavity that covers dorsally the anterior elements (see figs. 10, 33, 68, 96).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="6" pageNumber="6" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="6.[93,620,211,1759]" lastBlockId="7.[128,654,213,1759]" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">
DESCRIPTION MALE: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[382,558,741,763]" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">Cephalothorax:</emphasis>
Pars cephalica strongly elevated in lateral view, carapace without any pattern, usually broadly oval (ovoid in some species) in dorsal view, with rounded posterolateral corners, posterolateral edge without pits, posterior margin not bulging below posterior rim, anterolateral corners without extension or projections, posterolateral surface without spikes, surface of elevated portion of pars cephalica smooth, sides smooth, thorax without depressions, fovea absent (fig. 11A), without radiating rows of pits; lateral margin smooth, without denticles; plumose setae near posterior margin of pars thoracica absent; cuticle with elongated platelets, at least in some species (as in figs. 3A, 5B, 14A, 24G, 68E). Clypeus margin unmodified, curved downward in front view, vertical in lateral view, low, ALE separated from edge of carapace by less than their radius, median projection absent. Chilum absent. Eyes six, well developed; posterior eye row recurved from above (figs. 11C, 93C). Sternum uniform, not fused to carapace, median concavity absent, without radial furrows between coxae I–II, II–III, III–IV, radial furrow opposite coxae III absent, surface smooth, without pits, microsculpture absent, sickle-shaped structures absent, anterior corner unmodified, lateral margin without infracoxal grooves, distance between coxae approximately equal, precoxal triangles present, lateral margins unmodified, without posterior hump; setae dark, needlelike, originating from surface, without hair tufts. Mouthparts: chelicerae straight, anteri- or face unmodified; without teeth on both promargin and retromargin; fangs without toothlike projections, directed medially, shape normal, without prominent basal process, tip unmodified (as in fig. 2A–C); setae needlelike; paturon inner margin with pairs of enlarged setae, distal region unmodified, posterior surface unmodified, promargin unmodified, inner margin unmodified, laminate groove absent. Labium elongated hexagon, not fused to sternum (fig. 12A), same as sternum in sclerotization; subdistal portion with unmodified setae. Endites: serrula present in single row. Endites of most species modified, with lateral furrow bisecting maxilla in two sections: dorsal one flattened, bearing the serrula, and ventral one usually with anterolateral modifications, such as membranous or sclerotized expansions, or foldings (figs. 12B, 44C). Many species with more sclerotized longitudinal area adjacent to the lateral furrow (see figs. 46E, 61E, 73E). 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[667,782,887,908]" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">Abdomen:</emphasis>
Ovoid, without long posterior extension, rounded posteriorly (fig. 12C); Dorsum without color pattern. Book lung covers large, without setae, anterolateral edge unmodified. Posterior spiracles connected by groove (figs. 12D, 94E). Pedicel tube short, unmodified, scuto-pedicel region unmodified (fig. 3B–D), plumose hairs absent, matted setae on anterior ventral abdomen in pedicel area absent, cuticular outgrowths near pedicel absent. Dorsal scutum absent, a few species with a narrow, slightly sclerotized dorsal stripe reaching near the pedicel (see below). Epigastric scutum weakly sclerotized, not surrounding pedicel, not protruding, small lateral sclerites absent. Postepigastric scutum weakly sclerotized, short, only around epigastric furrow, not fused to epigastric scutum, anterior margin unmodified, without posteriorly directed lateral apodemes. Supraanal scutum absent. Epigastric area setae uniform, dark, needlelike. Postepigastric area setae dark, needlelike. Dense patch of setae anterior to spinnerets absent. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[760,822,1591,1612]" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">Legs:</emphasis>
Without color pattern; patella plus tibia I nearly as long as carapace, tibia I unmodified (fig. 12E), tibiae III and IV with specialized, curved hairs on ventral apex, at least in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[759,880,1707,1730]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="6" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="darwini">
<emphasis box="[759,880,1707,1730]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">N. darwini</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[942,1070,1708,1729]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="6" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="waorani">
<emphasis box="[942,1070,1708,1729]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="6">N. waorani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(figs. 6A– B, G, 12H, 95C–F), presumably in all species. Leg spines: present, legs I–II usually with two prolateral ventral on femora, five ventral pairs on tibiae, and four or three ventral pairs on metatarsi, all spines longer than segment width. Three trichobothria on all tibiae, one on all metatarsi (as in fig. 6C, D); their bases rounded, aperture longitudinally narrowed, internal texture not gratelike, hood covered by numerous low, closely spaced ridges (as in figs. 8, 9A, 14B–D). Tarsal organ I–II with 3 sensilla visible and III–IV and palp with two (figs. 9B–F, 14E–G, 94F). Tarsi I to IV without inferior claw (as in figs. 6E, 7). 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[128,240,593,615]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">Genitalia:</emphasis>
Epigastric region with sperm pore not visible; furrow without Ω- shaped insertions, without setae. Palp normal size, not strongly sclerotized, right and left palps symmetrical; embolus prolateral excavation absent; trochanter normal size, unmodified; femur without posteriorly rounded lateral dilation, attaching to patella basally; patella shorter than femur, not enlarged, without prolateral row of ridges, setae unmodified; cymbium not extending beyond distal tip of bulb, plumose setae absent, without stout setae, without distal patch of setae. Bulb variable, slender, elongated, or piriform; distal part with a more or less forwardly directed conductor with a narrow basal opening on its prolateral side (figs. 15C–F, 44D–E); this opening probably discharges the internal vesicle of the conductor. Longitudinal, internal tendon observed in most species (see details in fig. 15E, G), as previously reported for other haplogynes (
<bibRefCitation author="Huber, B. H." box="[136,380,1238,1260]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7" pagination="364 - 376" refId="ref51947" refString="Huber, B. H. 2004. Evolutionary transformation from muscular to hydraulic movements in spider (Arachnida, Araneae) genitalia: a study based on histological serial sections. Journal of Morphology 261: 364 - 376." type="journal article" year="2004">Huber, 2004: 366</bibRefCitation>
); internal tracheoles present (at least in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[364,487,1267,1290]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="7" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="darwini">
<emphasis box="[364,487,1267,1290]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">N. darwini</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, fig. 15E, G). Some species (the 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[339,433,1297,1318]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="7" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="poguazu">
<emphasis box="[339,433,1297,1318]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">poguazu</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
group) with small, translucent conductor, and additional ventroapical, sclerotized projection (figs. 69B, D, 76B, D).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="7.[128,654,213,1759]" lastBlockId="7.[701,1228,213,1626]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">
FEMALE: As in male except as noted. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[128,304,1444,1466]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">Cephalothorax:</emphasis>
Mouthparts: endites distally not excavated, anteromedian tip unmodified. Palpal claw absent (figs. 4E, 32A–B); spines absent; tarsus unmodified, patella without prolateral row of ridges. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[445,560,1561,1582]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">Abdomen:</emphasis>
Dorsal scutum always absent. Epigastric scutum without lateral joints. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[412,474,1620,1641]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">Legs:</emphasis>
Trichobothria and claws examined in detail only in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="7" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="darwini">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">N. darwini</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(figs. 7, 8): superior tarsal claws with inner faces striate; tarsus I proclaw with two teeth on median surface, retroclaw with four teeth on lateral surface; tarsus II proclaw with four teeth on lateral surface, retroclaw with four teeth on lateral surface; tarsus III proclaw with four teeth on lateral surface, retroclaw with four teeth on lateral surface; tarsus IV proclaw with four teeth on lateral surface, retroclaw with four teeth on lateral surface. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[793,906,419,441]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">Genitalia:</emphasis>
Genital opening connecting to uterus externus, from which two elements emerge: anterior receptacle and posterodorsal plate. Between them, genital opening delimited by two transverse sclerotized ridges (e.g., fig. 10). Posterior ridge arising from base of posterodorsal plate, its anterior margin forming locking mechanism with anterior transverse ridge (complementary V- or U-shape visible in cleared preparations; see figs. 10, 40A, C, E, 53A, C, E). Some species with transverse ridges less conspicuous (e.g., figs. 69E, 76C, 99C). Anterior receptacle with accessory glands (fig. 10f), and two sets of paired muscles attached: one pair anteroventrally (presumably connecting to ventral cuticle), and one pair to lateral projections of posterior transverse ridge (figs. 10e, g). Opening of the receptacle in anterior transverse ridge (fig. 10h); terminal part of uterus externus sometimes visible in digested preparations as longitudinal (figs. 69a, 76a, c, 99a, c, e), or transverse (figs. 86c) slit. Anterior receptacle usually visible ventrally by transparence. Posterodorsal plate nearly oval, usually covering entirely anterior receptacle in dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="7" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="7.[701,1228,213,1626]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">
DISTRIBUTION: Probably all tropical, subtropical, and temperate South America and 
<collectingCountry box="[701,799,1279,1300]" name="Panama" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">Panama</collectingCountry>
, excluding 
<collectingCountry box="[940,1005,1278,1300]" name="Chile" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">Chile</collectingCountry>
. Not reported yet from the Guianas.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="7.[701,1228,213,1626]" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">
SPECIES GROUPS: The species discussed below are preliminarily assigned to four species groups (
<taxonomicName box="[894,1171,1397,1420]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="7" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="darwini" variety="nigromaculatus">
<emphasis box="[894,978,1397,1420]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">darwini</emphasis>
, 
<emphasis box="[998,1171,1397,1420]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">nigromaculatus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="7" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="poguazu">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">poguazu</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Grismado &amp; Ramírez" authorityYear="2013" box="[860,958,1426,1449]" class="Arachnida" family="Oonopidae" genus="Neotrops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="7" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="platnicki">
<emphasis box="[860,958,1426,1449]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="7">platnicki</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
) for convenience in identification. Some of the characters defining those groups may be synapomorphies, although this topic will be discussed after the revision of the Brazilian fauna and similar undescribed genera from South America is completed.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>