<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.544.6074" ID-GBIF-Dataset="0e5e47a0-f8f3-4039-b0e1-c159fef0b9f6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127853619" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-544-1" ID-ZBK="C5978BD0145B40F8ACDEB27371B7B9A4" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C9A8CE93-6268-45EE-8084-97F101E823A7" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1313-2970-544-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 544" ModsDocTitle="The Mecyclothorax beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Moriomorphini) of Haleakala-, Maui: Keystone of a hyperdiverse Hawaiian radiation" checkinTime="1451243640953" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Liebherr, James K." docDate="2015" docId="38D92CD0438683BAFE7889960297E4A5" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 544: 1-407" docOrigin="ZooKeys 544" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.544.6074" docTitle="Mecyclothorax anthracinus Liebherr, 2015, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="C9A8CE93-6268-45EE-8084-97F101E823A7" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" masterDocId="FF92FFC2FF9FFFC7191EFFB8FF91AF5D" masterDocTitle="The Mecyclothorax beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Moriomorphini) of Haleakala-, Maui: Keystone of a hyperdiverse Hawaiian radiation" masterLastPageNumber="407" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="80" pageNumber="81" updateTime="1643655204478" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Mecyclothorax beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Moriomorphini) of Haleakala-, Maui: Keystone of a hyperdiverse Hawaiian radiation</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liebherr, James K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>544</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>407</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.544.6074</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.544.6074</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-544-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">C5978BD0145B40F8ACDEB27371B7B9A4</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">C5978BD0145B40F8ACDEB27371B7B9A4</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127853619" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C9A8CE93-6268-45EE-8084-97F101E823A7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/38D92CD0438683BAFE7889960297E4A5" lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="80" pageNumber="81">
<subSubSection pageId="80" pageNumber="81" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Taxon classification Animalia Coleoptera Carabidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="80" pageNumber="81" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">
(030) 
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/C9A8CE93-6268-45EE-8084-97F101E823A7" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Mecyclothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mecyclothorax anthracinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="80" pageNumber="81" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="anthracinus">Mecyclothorax anthracinus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="80" pageNumber="81">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 44E, 45
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–G">F-G</normalizedToken>
, 46B, 47B, 48
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="80" pageNumber="81" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">The small, dark-bodied beetles that comprise this species look ever so like small bits of anthracite coal, their dorsal body surface a reflective black (Fig. 44E). Also, this is the only species in the group that is characterized by absence of the parascutellar seta. The pronotum is narrow and basally constricted, MPW/PL = 1.18-1.24, MPW/BPW = 1.42-1.50, the disc covered with well-developed transverse wrinkles. The elytral intervals are convex and striation irregular, with striae 5 and 6 fused near the basal groove, and the dorsal setal impressions foveate and of diameter equal to the width of interval 3, these impressions associated with longitudinal irregularities of striae 2 and 3. The femora are flavous apically and covered with a piceous cast over their basal third; tibiae piceous. Setal formula 2 2 2 2. Standardized body length 3.6-4.0.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="80" pageNumber="81" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Description</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="80" pageNumber="81">
(n = 5). Head capsule with frontal grooves deep near clypeus, straight with external carina to anterior supraorbital seta; dorsal surface of neck convex, eyes moderately convex, ocular ratio = 1.42-1.50, ocular lobe ratio 0.77-0.85; labral anterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate, antennae filiform, antennomere 3 with sparse pelage of short setae; mentum tooth with orthogonal sides, apex pointed. Pronotum with lateral margin subparallel to convergent anterad right to acute hind angle; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="81" pageNumber="82" start="start">median</pageBreakToken>
base depressed relative to disc, covered with rugose wrinkles; basal margin nearly straight, slightly convex medially; median longitudinal impression shallow, finely incised, crossed by wrinkles; anterior transverse impression broad, evident, bordered anteriorly by slightly convex anterior callosity that is crossed by fine wrinkles; front angles slightly projected, rounded; anterior width subequal to broader than basal width, APW/BPW = 1.00-1.06; lateral marginal depression moderately narrow, edge upturned to beaded; laterobasal depression broad, depressed with wrinkled surface. Proepisternum with 6 minute punctures along hind marginal groove; prosternal process 
<pageBreakToken pageId="82" pageNumber="83" start="start">medially</pageBreakToken>
depressed, without marginal bead. Elytra subellipsoid, disc flat, sides moderately sloped; basal groove slightly recurved to tightly rounded humeral angle; humeri narrow, MEW/HuW = 2.06-2.10; parascutellar striole finely incised, continuous; sutural interval moderately convex, slightly more upraised than intervals 2-4; sutural and 2nd striae of subequal depth from base to apex; discal striae 1-8 complete and deep to apex, smooth with minute irregularities along striae suggesting punctulae; 7th and 8th intervals of similar convexity mesad subapical sinuation; 2 dorsal elytral setae at 0.32
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
and 0.65
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.73×">-0.73x</normalizedToken>
elytral length; apical and subapical setae present; lateral elytral setae arranged in anterior series of 7 setae and posterior series of 4(5) setae; elytral marginal depression narrow, edge upturned; subapical sinuation very shallow, nearly obsolete. Mesepisternum with 8 shallow punctures in 2 rows; metepisternal width to length ratio = 0.71; metepisternum/metepimeron suture distinct, metathoracic flight wing an ovoid flap, length 2.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
breadth, with reduced R and M veins, the flap extended 2/3 distance to hind margin of metanotum. Abdomen with indistinct lateral wrinkles on ventrites 1-3; suture between ventrites 2 and 3 complete; apical male ventrite with 2 marginal setae, apical female ventrite with 4 equally spaced marginal setae and a median trapezoid of 4, subequal short setae. Legs-metatarsomere 1/metatibial length ratio = 0.17; metatarsomere 4 length along outer lobe 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
medial tarsomere length, apical and subapical setae present; metatarsal dorsolateral sulci broad, shallow. Microsculpture of vertex of granulate isodiametric sculpticells; pronotal disc covered with distinct transverse mesh, median base with granulate isodiametric sculpticells; elytral disc covered with well-developed transverse mesh, apex with well-developed isodiametric mesh in transverse rows; metasternum with upraised transverse mesh; laterobasal abdominal ventrites with swirling isodiametric and transverse microsculpture. Coloration of vertex granulate rufopiceous; antennomere 1 flavous, antennomeres 2-3 with piceous cast, 4-11 piceous; pronotal disc granulate rufopiceous, margins narrowly paler, rufobrunneous; proepipleuron rufobrunneous with piceous upper margin, proepisternum rufobrunneous with piceous cast; elytral disc rufopiceous, sutural interval paler, dark rufous throughout, margins narrowly paler basally, concolorous with disc apically; elytral epipleuron rufobrunneous, metepisternum rufopiceous; abdomen rufopiceous across width of ventrites 1-5, apical ventrite 6 with apical 1/3 paler, rufobrunneous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">
Male genitalia (n = 1). Aedeagal median lobe curved, gracile, distance from parameral articulation to tip 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
depth at midlength (Fig. 45F); apex angularly narrowed to tightly rounded tip formed at juncture of flat apical face and ventral margin; median lobe sinuously recurved left then right in ventral view (Fig. 45G), tip tightly rounded; internal sac with apparent dorsal ostial microtrichial patch (based on uneverted specimen; Fig. 45F), sac surface covered with microspicules; flagellar plate evident just inside dorsal margin of median lobe.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="82" pageNumber="83">
Female reproductive tract (n = 1). Bursa copulatrix a narrow digitiform lobe attached to broader vagina, lobe length 0.26 mm, lobe apical breadth 0.10 mm, vagina breadth 0.25 mm (Fig. 46B); bursal walls thin, transparent; gonocoxite 1 with 3 apical fringe setae and 5-6 smaller setae on medial surface (Fig. 47B); gonocoxite 2 falcate, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="83" pageNumber="84" start="start">narrow</pageBreakToken>
apically with base broadly extended laterally, 2 lateral ensiform setae with apical seta broader and longer, apical nematiform setae on medial surface at 0.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
gonocoxite length.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
Female (BPBM) labeled: NW 6000'-6500', / Haleakala / VIII-18-37 Maui // Beating // ECZimmerman / Collector // 3 // HOLOTYPE / 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Mecyclothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mecyclothorax" order="Coleoptera" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Mecyclothorax</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="anthracinus" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" rank="species" species="anthracinus">anthracinus</taxonomicName>
/ Liebherr / det. J.K. Liebherr 2015 (black-margined red label).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="paratypes">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Paratypes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
HI: Maui: Haleakala N.P., NW upper slope, beating 1830-1980 m el., 18-viii-1937, Zimmerman (BPBM, 2); Koolau For. Res., Hanawi N.A.R., Frisbee Meadow Camp, woods below, sift litter 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Asteraceae" genus="Dubautia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Dubautia" order="Asterales" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Dubautia</taxonomicName>
/tree, 2072-2099 m el., 19-v-1993 lot 01, Liebherr/Medeiros (CUIC, 6).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
The shiny coal black color of the dorsal surface of these beetles begs for use of the Latin adjective 
<taxonomicName lsidName="anthracinus" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" rank="species" species="anthracinus">anthracinus</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="distribution and habitat">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Distribution and habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Mecyclothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mecyclothorax anthracinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="anthracinus">Mecyclothorax anthracinus</taxonomicName>
is known from two isolated, high-elevation localities near the upper limits of the windward forest. E.C. Zimmerman beat three specimens from vegetation at 1830-1980 m elevation along the NW upper slope, and six specimens were taken from leaf litter samples of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Asteraceae" genus="Dubautia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Dubautia reticulata" order="Asterales" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="reticulata">Dubautia reticulata</taxonomicName>
litter at &quot;Frisbee Meadow Camp&quot; in the headwaters of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hanawī">Hanawī</normalizedToken>
Stream to the east (Fig. 48). Whether the unusual coal-black color and ridged dorsal body surface of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Mecyclothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mecyclothorax anthracinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="anthracinus">Mecyclothorax anthracinus</taxonomicName>
beetles serve to enhance crypsis on the dark, fissured bark of the tree 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Asteraceae" genus="Dubautia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Dubautia" order="Asterales" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Dubautia</taxonomicName>
seems a question worthy of study.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>