<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b76f4d8a-5fe9-43a1-9d03-25e568a1c973" ModsDocID="5835" checkinTime="1243376574979" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1947" docId="E0AA61F946DE55ADE3268F966A727F19" docLanguage="en" docName="5835" docOrigin="Annals and Magazine of Natural History 13" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5835/5835.pdf" docTitle="Ponera grandis Donisthorpe, 1947, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="284" masterDocId="D2948B97318703A15BCE7D5A74EB860E" masterDocTitle="New species of ants from China and Mauritius." masterLastPageNumber="286" masterPageNumber="283" pageNumber="283" updateTime="1569525771796" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species of ants from China and Mauritius.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1947</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>13</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>283</mods:start>
<mods:end>286</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5835/5835.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">5835</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:E0AA61F946DE55ADE3268F966A727F19" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E0AA61F946DE55ADE3268F966A727F19">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="283">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:147702" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Ponera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ponera grandis Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Ponera grandis Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="283" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandis">Ponera grandis</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="283">[[ worker ]]. Reddish brown, head darker, mandibles, antennae, and legs lighter. Whole body clothed with sparse yel] ow pubescence, more abundant on gaster.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="284" pageNumber="283">Head subquadrate, sides slightly rounded, posterior angles rounded, posterior border almost straight, sculpture rather closely and finely rugous; mandibles long, triangular, with a row of punctures along masticatory border near teeth, masticatory border armed with eight teeth, the apical one being long and pointed; clypeus narrow, transverse, anterior border very slightly emarginate in centre, sinuate at sides; frontal carinae short, flat, with a double lobe in front covering the insertion of the antennae, convergent behind; frontal furrow narrow and rather faint, separating the frontal carinae; antennae 12 - jointed, scape not quite reaching posterior border of head, funiculus gradually increasing in breadth to apex and not forming a distinct club, last joint pointed, as long as the two preceding taken together; eyes small, consisting of only eight ommatidia, situated before middle of sides of head. Thorax longer than broad, broader in front than behind; pronotum large, transverse, convex, puncturation not so close as on head, encircling mesonotum; suture between pro- and mesonotum deep and rather wide; mesonotum convex, transverse, much shorter than pronotum; suture between meso- and epinotum obsolete, represented by a shallow furrow; epinotum long, slightly constricted at sides, dorsal surface less closely punctured than pro- and mesonotum, longer than declivity, angle between dorsal surface and declivity well marked, declivity triangular, flat, smooth; node of petiole high, bluntly pointed above, anterior surface slightly concave, posterior surface flat, sculpture as in epinotum. Gaster rather long, subparallel, basal surface slightly concave, suture between post-petiole and rest of gaster well marked.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="284">Long. 5.5 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="284">Type in British Museum (Natural History).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="284">Described from a single worker: Yen Bay, Tonkin. Collected in a nest of termites by Prof. F. Silvestri.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>