<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.741.21814" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3d8439b6-b46d-4c68-8a61-b8a668e500ff" ID-GBIF-Taxon="141400969" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-741-133" ID-ZBK="A3B9317A69D94803A2DFD07736193677" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9FF56672-4164-42F2-84E2-37721098D16E" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-741-133" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 741" ModsDocTitle="Two new Lophoturus species (Diplopoda, Polyxenida, Lophoproctidae) from Queensland, Australia" checkinTime="1520489662411" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Huynh, Cuong &amp; Veenstra, Anneke A." docDate="2018" docId="66CD9328F52CBA073A8D726D4EA989F1" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 741: 133-154" docOrigin="ZooKeys 741" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.741.21814" docTitle="Lophoturus boondallus Huynh &amp; Veenstra, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="9FF56672-4164-42F2-84E2-37721098D16E" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="140" masterDocId="FF9CFFA0EA6FAB63FE5FFFC1F3068004" masterDocTitle="Two new Lophoturus species (Diplopoda, Polyxenida, Lophoproctidae) from Queensland, Australia" masterLastPageNumber="154" masterPageNumber="133" pageId="3" pageNumber="136" updateTime="1643542266035" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Two new Lophoturus species (Diplopoda, Polyxenida, Lophoproctidae) from Queensland, Australia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Huynh, Cuong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Veenstra, Anneke A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>741</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>133</mods:start>
<mods:end>154</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.741.21814</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.741.21814</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-741-133</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">A3B9317A69D94803A2DFD07736193677</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">A3B9317A69D94803A2DFD07736193677</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="141400969" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9FF56672-4164-42F2-84E2-37721098D16E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/66CD9328F52CBA073A8D726D4EA989F1" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="140" pageId="3" pageNumber="136">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="136" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/9FF56672-4164-42F2-84E2-37721098D16E" class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus boondallus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="3" pageNumber="136" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boondallus">Lophoturus boondallus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="3" pageNumber="136">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="136" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">
Adult male, stadium VIII - 13 leg pairs stage, collected from Boondall Wetlands Park, Boondall, Brisbane, Queensland; 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="-27.340515">27°20'25.85&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="153.07692">153°4'36.94&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, elevation 9 m. The species was collected from leaf litter near the main entrance of the park on 10 November 2015 by author (CH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="136" type="paratypes">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">Paratypes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">One male and 9 females were collected in the same location and date as holotype. (1 male and 2 females were used for SEM imaging in this study).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="136" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">
The species is named 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus boondallus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="3" pageNumber="136" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boondallus">Lophoturus boondallus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. as they were first found in Boondall Wetlands Park, Boondall, Queensland, Australia.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="137" pageId="3" pageNumber="136" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="136">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="137" pageId="3" pageNumber="136">
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. boondallus" pageId="3" pageNumber="136" rank="species" species="boondallus">L. boondallus</taxonomicName>
has the following morphological characteristics: 3 sensilla on the 6th antennal article and labrum with two linguiform processes. These features are typical characteristics of 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="3" pageNumber="136" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Lophoturus</taxonomicName>
. Live specimens from this species are light or 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="137" start="start">ange</pageBreakToken>
in colour with a round arc-shaped body form in cross section. Adults body length range from 1.6-2.2 mm.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="140" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
Measurements: Holotype male body length 1.9 mm, females (paratypes) (n = 8) range from 1.9-2.2 mm. Caudal bundle of the male is slightly narrower in width with 0.6 mm in length than that of the female (0.5 mm) (Fig. 6
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">Colouration. Head light orange and dark reddish-brown laterally; body light orange, contrasting with their white pleural trichomes and lighter coloured caudal bundle (Figure 2B).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
Figure 2. Three 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Lophoturus</taxonomicName>
species were found in state of Queensland, Australia. A 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. queenslandicus" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="queenslandicus">L. queenslandicus</taxonomicName>
Verhoeff, 1924 B 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. boondallus" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="boondallus">L. boondallus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. and C 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. molloyensis" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" rank="species" species="molloyensis">L. molloyensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. These 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Lophoturus</taxonomicName>
species showed differences in body lengths and colour.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">Head. Ommatidia absent. Vertex with two posterior trichome groups, a large gap presents between them. Each group consists of 2 rows, the anterior, oblique row has similar sized trichome sockets. Posterior row has fewer trichome sockets with a narrow space between the anterior and posterior rows. Holotype male has 12 + 12 trichome sockets in anterior rows and 4 + 4 trichome sockets in posterior rows (Fig. 3A); paratypes indicate that variation is common in this species, ranging from 12-15 (anterior rows) and 3-7 (posterior rows) (Fig. 6C). Trichobothria: trichobothrium a, located in posterior position with a medium socket; trichobothrium b, lateral position with largest socket; and trichobothrium c, anterior position with smallest socket. Trichobothria a and b have typically thin sensory hairs with narrow cylindrical funicles compared to trichobothrium c, with a claviform funicle. Trichobothrium sockets (a, b and c) arranged unevenly between ab and bc, as trichobothria a and c located more inward (Figs 3E, 6D).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
Figure 3. The depiction of holotype of 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus boondallus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boondallus">Lophoturus boondallus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A A head capsule showed the posterior vertex trichome sockets (pv) and trichobothria B, C, D Collum (col) with the lateral protuberances (Lp), tergite 2 (t2) and tergite 10 (t10), with trichome socket patterns E Trichobothria: Trichobothrium a (located posteriorly with medium socket), trichobothrium b (located laterally with largest socket) are typical thin sensory hairs and trichobothrium c with a claviform funicle (located anteriorly with smallest socket) F Gnathochilaria of male and G Gnathochilaria from female (paratype) H Labrum displayed two linguiform processes (lp) and setose surface.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
Antennae. 8 articles (4 tiny, reduced sensory cones), 7th and 8th antennal articles are equal in length (Fig. 4A), which is characteristic of 
<taxonomicName family="Lophoproctidae" lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" rank="family">Lophoproctidae</taxonomicName>
. The 6th antennal article has 3 thick bacilliform sensilla (T) of differing lengths: medium sensillum posteriorly (Tp); the longest and thicker intermediate sensillum (Ti); a short sensillum anteriorly (Ta) with its socket located distally; and a conical sensillum posteriorly (c) (Figs 4C, 6F). The 7th antennal article has 2 thick bacilliform sensilla (T), the anterior Ta shorter than Tp located posteriorly, with one setiform sensillum (s) between them plus a conical sensillum (c) located in the posterior position (Figs 4B, 6E). This pattern of sensilla on the 7th article is common to all 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Lophoturus</taxonomicName>
species.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
Figure 4. Antennal articles of the holotype 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus boondallus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="4" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boondallus">Lophoturus boondallus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A Antenna with eight articles and the arrangement of sensilla on the 6th and 7th articles; articles 7th and 8th were equal in length; the arrangement of sensilla on the 6th and 7th antennal articles B Sensilla on the 7th antennal article; a conical sensillum (c), a long thick sensillum located posteriorly (Tp) and a short thick sensillum located anteriorly (Ta) with a setiform sensillum (s) located between these sensilla C Sensilla on the 6th antennal article; a conical sensillum (c), a medium length thick sensillum (Tp), a long thick sensillum (Ti) and the short thick sensillum (Ta).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">Clypeo-labrum: Holotype has 10 setae, all half the width of the labrum. Setae on paratypes ranged from 10-12. Labrum surface setose, with tiny, backward facing hairs. Anterior margin of labrum with two whole lamellae, and a linguiform process present on each side of median cleft of labrum (Figs 3H, 7A).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
Gnathochilaria. Medial palps only, 58 sensilla on the palp of holotype (male) and 18-22 sensilla on paratypes (females) (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–G">F-G</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="138" pageId="4" pageNumber="137">
Trunk. Comprised of 10 segments, 9 pleural projections, excluding the telson and caudal bundle; 13 pairs of legs. Collum - tergite 1 (smallest tergite) with trichome sockets arranged in 2 oval shapes laterally, connected by posterior curved rows of trichome sockets with a large gap in the middle. The collum is the only tergite with lateral protuberances bearing a small number of trichome sockets. In holotype, the collum has 52 (Left: L), 52 (Right: R) trichome sockets and the lateral protuberances with 7 trichome sockets on each side (Fig. 3B). Numbers varied in paratype females within a range of 46-58 trichome sockets in the collum and the number of lateral protuberances trichome sockets range 6-8. Tergites 2 to 10, have a pair of pleural projections located antero-laterally. The arrangement of tergal trichome sockets from tergites 2 to 10 typically have 2 latero-posterior oval groups with a few sockets extended on both ends with these groups separated by a 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="138" start="start">large</pageBreakToken>
medial gap. Trichome sockets of tergite 2 in the holotype has 54 (L) and 54 (R) (Figs 3C, 6C), tergite 10 has 38 on both sides (Fig. 3D). In contrast, the trichome sockets of tergite 2 in paratypes ranged 54-66 and tergite 10 ranged 34-46 trichome sockets.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="139">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="139" start="start">Legs</pageBreakToken>
. Leg segments are named following 
<bibRefCitation author="Manton, SM" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Linnean Society London" pageId="13" pageNumber="146" pagination="153 - 187" title="The Evolution of Arthropodan Locomotory Mechanisms Part 5: The Structure, Habits and Evolution of the Pselaphognatha (Diplopoda)." url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1957.tb02516.x" volume="43" year="1956">Manton (1956)</bibRefCitation>
. Legs 1 and 2 without trochanter, leg 1 also lacks tarsus 1. Chaetotaxy as follows: coxa 1: 2 pubescent oval setae, coxa 2: 3 pubescent oval setae, coxae 3-13: 0-4 pubescent oval setae; pre-femur, femur and post-femur with 1 pubescent oval seta (Fig. 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
), tarsus 2 with a spine (Fig. 5C). Posterior edge of last sternite has 0-4 pubescent oval setae similar to those present on the coxa and the number of these pubescent oval setae varies: 2 on the holotype and 0-4 on the paratypes. Sex organs in male: A pair of penes on the 2nd coxa and coxal glands absent.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="139">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="139">
Figure 5. Holotype of 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus boondallus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="6" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boondallus">Lophoturus boondallus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A The second left leg showing a penis (p), seven leg segments (co coxa, pf pre-femur, f femur, pof: post-femur, ti tibia, T1 tarsus 1, T2 tarsus 2 and a spine), a claw and its chaetotaxy (setae on the leg segments) B a pubescent oval seta C a spine on tarsus 2 D A simple claw structure with two latero-dorsal denticles (ldd), claw (c), a basal denticle (bd) and small denticle (smd) E The ornamental trichome sockets, located dorsally on the caudal bundle structure, with six trichomes a, one trichome b and two trichomes c (c1 and c3).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="139">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Telotarsus–Claw">Telotarsus-Claw</normalizedToken>
. slender with two latero-dorsal denticles (ldd) equal in length, a basal denticle (bd) and a small denticle (smd) present near the tip of the claw (Figs 5D, 7B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="139">Telson. Dorsal ornamental trichome sockets symmetrically arranged on each side, with 6 sockets of trichome a in the holotype; paratype females have 6-8 sockets of trichome a, a single trichome b and two large protruding base sockets of trichome c: c1 and c3 (The absence of c2 is characteristic of lophoproctid species) (Fig. 5E).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="140">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="140" start="start">Caudal</pageBreakToken>
bundles. In the holotype male, the caudal bundle is formed by a single group of trichome sockets of uniform sizes; this structure is split ventrally with trichome socket-free tissue present and extending with a small gap dorsally toward the centre. 3 rows of the largest size barbate trichome sockets present, forming slightly uneven lateral rows that extend toward the centre of the caudal structure (Fig. 7C). In paratype females, the caudal bundle structure differed from the male, with two distinguishing structures apparent: the main dorsal structure, was similar to the male, and 2 latero-sternal structures with finer nest trichome sockets. These finer sockets located on the interior and were surrounded by 2 rows of caudal trichome sockets on exterior surface. A trichome socket-free area is present ventrally, extending with a small gap and connecting with central bare tissue with few barbate trichome sockets present. Caudal and nest trichome sockets are clearly separated. These structures gradually form a single caudal bundle structure (Fig. 7D). The structure of 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. boondallus" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" rank="species" species="boondallus">L. boondallus</taxonomicName>
caudal bundles and their caudal trichomes is similar to those of 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Polyxenidae" genus="Monographis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monographis" order="Polyxenida" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Monographis</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName family="Polyxenidae" lsidName="" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" rank="family">Polyxenidae</taxonomicName>
) (
<bibRefCitation author="Huynh, C" journalOrPublisher="Nucleic Acid Symposium Series" pageId="13" pageNumber="146" url="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3721.6.4" year="2013">Huynh and Veenstra 2013</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Huynh, C" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="13" pageNumber="146" pagination="460 - 474" title="Description of a new species of Penicillate Millipede from the genus Monographis (Diplopoda: Polyxenidae) found in Vietnam." url="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3964.4.5" volume="3964" year="2015">2015</bibRefCitation>
) and classified as Type II by 
<bibRefCitation author="Conde, B" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin de la Societe Zoologique de France," pageId="13" pageNumber="146" pagination="291 - 302" title="Classification actuelle des Diplopodes Penicillates (Myriapodes) avec nouvelles definition des taxa." volume="133" year="2008">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Condé">Conde</normalizedToken>
and Nguyen Duy-Jacquemin (2008)
</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="140">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="140">
Figure 6. SEM (Scanning Electron Microscopy) images of 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus boondallus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boondallus">Lophoturus boondallus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A A dorsal view of whole body showing the body trichome arrangements and the caudal bundle B A ventral view of whole body showed 13 pairs of legs C A head capsule displaying two posterior vertex trichome groups (pv), a collum (col) and tergite 2 (t2) D Trichobothria a (a), b (b) and c (c) showing different sizes in trichobothrium sockets E and F Antennal articles 6 and 7 with sensilla (Ta: thick sensillum located anteriorly, Ti: intermediated thick sensillum, Tp: posterior thick sensillum, setiform sensillum (s) and a conical sensillum (c)).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="140">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="140">
Figure 7. SEM images of 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus boondallus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boondallus">Lophoturus boondallus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A Mouth part showed setose labrum (l) with typical two linguiform processes (lp) and sensilla from the gnathochilarium (g) B Simple claw with lateral dorsal denticles (ldd), claw (c), small denticle (smd) and basal denticle (bd) C Male caudal bundle showed an ornamental trichome sockets (a, b and c) and the uniform caudal bundle trichome sockets (cbts); D Female caudal bundle structure displaying ornamental trichome sockets and two main parts: caudal bundle trichome sockets dorsally (cbts) and two nest trichome sockets (nts) ventrally.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="140" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="140">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="140">
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. boondallus" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" rank="species" species="boondallus">L. boondallus</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. queenslandicus" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" rank="species" species="queenslandicus">L. queenslandicus</taxonomicName>
in being shorter in length, in having light orange colouration, a round arc-shaped body form when viewed in cross section. Furthermore, it also differs genetically from the other 
<taxonomicName class="Diplopoda" family="Lophoproctidae" genus="Lophoturus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lophoturus" order="Polyxenida" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Lophoturus</taxonomicName>
species. In contrast, 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. queenslandicus" pageId="7" pageNumber="140" rank="species" species="queenslandicus">L. queenslandicus</taxonomicName>
is rusty brown with a yellowish light green median band dorsally and two darker brown strips laterally; body 2.4-2.8 mm long, with a flattened arc shape (Fig. 2).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>