<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" ID-GBIF-Dataset="907713bd-c7f2-4f8e-a75e-b7f9c958865f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648676" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-689-1" ID-ZBK="2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-689-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 689" ModsDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" checkinTime="1502744367222" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lackner, Tomas &amp; Leschen, Richard A. B." docDate="2017" docId="9A8B4FBCD1AD50F5533CDA9E2738D905" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 689: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 689" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" docTitle="Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis Marseul 1862" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="83" masterDocId="D302FFB6FFA66345FFBAFF89311EFFDE" masterDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" updateTime="1643479489822" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lackner, Tomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Leschen, Richard A. B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>689</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-689-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648676" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:9A8B4FBCD1AD50F5533CDA9E2738D905" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9A8B4FBCD1AD50F5533CDA9E2738D905" lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<taxonomicName authority="Marseul, 1862" authorityName="Marseul" authorityYear="1862" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="artensis" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis Marseul, 1862</taxonomicName>
Figs 320, 321-329, 330-336, 760
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus artensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="artensis">Saprinus artensis</taxonomicName>
Marseul, 1862: 445.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">New Caledonia.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
Figure 320. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="artensis" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis</taxonomicName>
Marseul, 1862 habitus, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus artensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="artensis">Saprinus artensis</taxonomicName>
Marseul, 1862: Lectotype, present designation: ♂, side mounted on a triangular card, with terminalia glued on the same triangular card as specimen, right protarsus and left mesotarsus missing, both metatarsal claws broken off, with the following labels: &quot;13 / 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="artensis" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" rank="species" species="artensis">artensis</taxonomicName>
m. / illegible text&quot; (round pink label, written); followed by: &quot; 
<taxonomicName lsidName="artensis" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" rank="species" species="artensis">artensis</taxonomicName>
/ type&quot; (pencil-written label added probably by G. Dahlgren); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“TYPE”">&quot;TYPE&quot;</normalizedToken>
(red-typed label); followed by: &quot;MUSEUM PARIS / 
<taxonomicName lsidName="artensis" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" rank="species" species="artensis">artensis</taxonomicName>
/ COLL / DE MARSEUL 1890&quot; (pink label, typed-written); followed by: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“09-052”">&quot;09-052&quot;</normalizedToken>
(yellow, pencil-written label, added by the senior author); followed by: &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="artensis" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" rank="species" species="artensis">artensis</taxonomicName>
/ Marseul, 1862 / LECTOTYPE / Des. T. Lackner 
<normalizedToken originalValue="’11”">'11&quot;</normalizedToken>
(red label, written) (MNHN). This species was described from an unknown number of specimens and the lectotype designation fixes the identity of species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
1 ♂, New Caledonia (MNHN). Apparently this specimen is also from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Marseul’s">Marseul's</normalizedToken>
collection, but does not originate from the same sampling as the lectotype. There is no 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Type”">&quot;Type&quot;</normalizedToken>
label on it and therefore it is not designated as the paralectotype; 5 ♂♂, &quot;New Caledonia&quot;, all from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Schmidt’s">Schmidt's</normalizedToken>
collection, one male has a small label: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Type”">&quot;Type&quot;</normalizedToken>
- it is not clear whether it forms a part of the syntype series or not (ZMHUB); 1 ♀, New Caledonia, A. Deyr[olle] (NCB). 1 ♂ &amp; 1 ♀, N. Caledonia, Fauvel (BMNH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Unknown, presumably similar to congeners.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Endemic to New Caledonia, rarely collected (Fig. 760).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Re-description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Body length: PEL: 3.35 mm; EL: 2.00 mm; APW: 1.25 mm; PPW: 2.50 mm; EW: 2.80 mm (only the type specimen was measured).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Body (Fig. 320), convex, cuticle dark brown, almost black, shining, without metallic luster; legs, mouthparts and antennal scape dark brown; antennal club black.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">Antennal scape (Fig. 321) black, slightly thickened, finely punctuate, with two setae; antennal club (Fig. 322) covered with dense short sensilla intermingled with sparse longer erect setae; sensory structures of antennal club not examined.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
<paragraph pageId="78" pageNumber="79">
Figures 321-329. 321 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="artensis" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis</taxonomicName>
Marseul, 1862 head, dorsal view 322 antennal club, ventral view 323 mentum, ventral view 324 propygidium + pygidium 325 prosternum 326 mesoventrite 327 lateral disc of metaventrite + metepisternum 328 protibia, ventral view 329 mesotibia, ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="79" pageNumber="80">
<pageBreakToken pageId="79" pageNumber="80" start="start">Mandibles</pageBreakToken>
dorso-laterally densely punctuate, rounded; labrum finely and sparsely punctuate, convex, with shallow median depression; labral pits present, each with a single labral seta; mentum (Fig. 323) almost quadrate, furnished with sporadic seate, anterior margin with deep triangular notch furnished with several longer setae; other mouthparts not examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="79" pageNumber="80">Clypeus (Fig. 321) broad, flattened, sloping down laterally, its punctation denser and coarser than that of labrum; frontal and supra-orbital striae complete, slightly carinate; frontal disc (Fig. 321) finely punctuate, punctures separated by about several times their diameter; eyes convex, well visible from above.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="80" lastPageNumber="81" pageId="79" pageNumber="80">
Pronotal sides (Fig. 320) moderately narrowing anteriorly, apical angles obtuse, pronotal depressions shallow but present, anterior incision for head shallow; marginal pronotal stria complete, slightly carinate, visible along its entire length from dorsal view, weakened anteriorly; pronotal disc laterally with a band of deep dense elongate punctures originating approximately in pronotal depressions, but not reaching basal angles of pronotum, between it and pronotal margin a narrow smooth band present; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="80" pageNumber="81" start="start">rest</pageBreakToken>
of the pronotal disc almost smooth, with only scattered microscopic punctation; double row of fine ovoid punctures present along pronotal base not reaching ante-scutellar area; pronotal hypomeron glabrous; scutellum small, visible.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Elytral epipleura with a double row of fine punctures; marginal epipleural stria complete; marginal elytral stria well impressed and slightly carinate, continued as complete apical elytral stria. Humeral elytral stria well impressed on basal fourth, faintly connected to rather long inner subhumeral stria; four dorsal elytral striae 1-4 well impressed, all about the same length (third elytral stria slightly shorter than others), not reaching elytral half apically; first and second dorsal elytral striae in fine punctures, first elytral interval with elongate strioles; third and fourth striae in large sparsely set punctures, surface of second and third elytral intervals almost smooth, only with microscopic punctation; fourth dorsal elytral stria curved towards sutural elytral stria but not connected with it; sutural elytral stria well-impressed, in fine punctures, abbreviated on basal fourth, apically connected with apical elytral stria; elytral disc on apical 4/7 in dense large punctures; punctures separated by about their own diameter, laterally and especially apically punctures aciculate; elytral flanks almost impunctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Propygidium (Fig. 324) very densely punctuate, punctures separated by less than their diameter; pygidium (Fig. 324) with similar, if somewhat sparser punctation, interspaces in both cases imbricate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Anterior margin of median portion of prosternum (Fig. 325) almost straight, rounded laterally; marginal prosternal stria present laterally and also as apical fragment; prosternal process between carinal prosternal striae flat, punctuate; carinal prosternal striae carinate, parallel on basal three-fourths, on apical fourth slightly divergent, united in front (Fig. 325); lateral prosternal striae carinate, rather short, apically attaining carinal prosternal striae at about three-fourths of their length.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Anterior margin of mesoventrite (Fig. 326) distinctly inwardly arcuate; discal marginal mesoventral stria well impressed, carinate; disc with sparse fine punctation, punctures becoming larger near meso-metaventral suture; meso-metaventral sutural stria indicated by a row of large punctures; intercoxal disc of metaventrite flattened, with slight longitudinal median depression; disc of metaventrite for the most part almost smooth, along posterior margin several rows of punctation appears; lateral metaventral stria (Fig. 327) well impressed, carinate, almost straight, shortened; lateral disc of metaventrite (Fig. 327) slightly concave, with dense shallow large setigerous punctures; metepisternum (Fig. 327) similar, but with deeper and larger punctures without setae, on fused metepimeron punctures becoming much sparser; metepisternal stria present along fused metepimeron, along metepisternum present as short intermittent fragments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="80" pageNumber="81">Intercoxal disc of first abdominal ventrite almost completely striate laterally; disc along basal and lateral margins with shallow punctures of various sizes; rest of sternite with scattered microscopic punctation.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="80" pageNumber="81">
Protibia (Fig. 328) slightly dilated, outer margin with five low teeth topped by large denticle, denticles diminishing in size proximally, followed by three minute denticles; setae of outer, median rows, anterior protibial stria and protarsal groove not examined; protibial spur large, bent, growing out from apical margin of protibia; outer 
<pageBreakToken pageId="81" pageNumber="82" start="start">part</pageBreakToken>
of posterior surface (Fig. 328) slightly obscurely variolate, separated from finely punctuate and narrow median part of posterior surface by a definite stria bearing a row of setae; posterior protibial stria complete, bearing almost along its entire length dense row of setae becoming stiffer and longer apically; apical margin of protibia ventrally 
<pageBreakToken pageId="82" pageNumber="83" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
three short denticles; inner row of setae single, setae leaf-like, short, diminishing in size basally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Mesotibia (Fig. 329) slender, outer margin with a row of sparse long denticles growing in size apically, another row of much shorter sparser denticles situated on anterior surface of mesotibia; setae of outer row regular, thick, almost as long as denticles themselves; setae of median row shorter and finer; posterior mesotibial stria almost complete; anterior surface of mesotibia sparsely punctuate, interspaces imbricate; anterior mesotibial stria complete; mesotibial spur stout, short; apical margin of mesotibia anteriorly with two short denticles; inner margin of mesotibia with sparse row of short setae; claws of apical tarsomere bent, longer than half its length; metatibia slenderer and longer than mesotibia, in all aspects similar to it, but denticles on outer margin much shorter and sparser.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Male genitalia. Eighth sternite (Figs 330-331) with pseudo-pores, fused medially, apex with large velum mesally adorned with dense rows of microscopic setae; laterally apex of eighth sternite with rows of longer dense setae; eighth tergite and eighth sternite not fused laterally (Fig. 332). Ninth tergite (Figs 333-334) typical for the subfamily; tenth tergite inwardly arcuate, apical angles strongly sclerotized, bent; spiculum gastrale (Fig. 333) gradually dilated on most of its apical half; basal end heart-shaped, inwardly arcuate. Aedeagus (Figs 335-336) parallel-sided, with parameres fused along their basal half (roughly), basal piece of aedeagus short, ratio of its length: length of parameres 1: 4; aedeagus slightly curved from lateral view (Fig. 336).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="82" pageNumber="83">
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">
Figures 330-336. 330 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="82" pageNumber="83" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="artensis" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) artensis</taxonomicName>
Marseul, 1862 male terminalia: 8th sternite + 8th tergite, ventral view 331 ditto, dorsal view 332 ditto, lateral view 333 male terminalia: 9th + 10th tergites, dorsal view; spiculum gastrale, ventral view 334 9th + 10th tergites; spiculum gastrale, lateral view 335 male terminalia: aedeagus, dorsal view 336 ditto, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>