<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.483.9222" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8dfdc43a-d0aa-4c06-a4b2-976e4747951a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152058353" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-483-97" ID-ZBK="AA541FB55148492A8A57F62764812F44" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1313-2970-483-97" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 483" ModsDocTitle="A revision of the Nearctic species of Liancalus Loew (Diptera, Dolichopodidae)" checkinTime="1451244636583" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Runyon, Justin B. &amp; Hurley, Richard L." docDate="2015" docId="59F90D72BE646A92C7A40171ED549E05" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 483: 97-147" docOrigin="ZooKeys 483" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.483.9222" docTitle="Liancalus limbatus Van Duzee 1917" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="116" masterDocId="FFB4C703FFDD5D00CF378F09FFE7CB38" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Nearctic species of Liancalus Loew (Diptera, Dolichopodidae)" masterLastPageNumber="147" masterPageNumber="97" pageId="18" pageNumber="115" updateTime="1643508886366" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of the Nearctic species of Liancalus Loew (Diptera, Dolichopodidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Runyon, Justin B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Hurley, Richard L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>483</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>97</mods:start>
<mods:end>147</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.483.9222</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.483.9222</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-483-97</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">AA541FB55148492A8A57F62764812F44</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA541FB55148492A8A57F62764812F44</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152058353" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:59F90D72BE646A92C7A40171ED549E05" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/59F90D72BE646A92C7A40171ED549E05" lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="116" pageId="18" pageNumber="115">
<subSubSection pageId="18" pageNumber="115" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Taxon classification Animalia Diptera Dolichopodidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="18" pageNumber="115" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">
<taxonomicName authority="Van Duzee, 1917" authorityName="Van Duzee" authorityYear="1917" class="Insecta" family="Dolichopodidae" genus="Liancalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liancalus limbatus" order="Diptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="115" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limbatus">Liancalus limbatus Van Duzee, 1917</taxonomicName>
Figs 2C, 3D, 5C, 10C, 14B, 16D
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="18" pageNumber="115" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Males of this species have long cerci, wing without marginal setae but with a distinct marginal lobe between veins M1 and CuA1, and with crossvein dm-cu relatively straight (Fig. 5C). Female wing as in Fig. 16D.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="18" pageNumber="115" type="redescription">
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Redescription.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Male. Body length 8.0-9.0 mm, wing length 6.5-7.5 mm. Head: Face narrow, slightly widening toward palpus, metallic green to bronze with sparse to moderately dense silver pollen. Vertex covered with silver pollen mostly hiding metallic green to blue ground color. Vertical setae on very small elevation; ocellar tubercle prominent with 2 large setae (subequal in size to vertical setae); with 2 postocellar setae which are one-half to two-thirds size of ocellar setae; postocular setae approximately one-half size of vertical setae with about dorsal one-half of postocular setae black (approximately 15 black setae), ventral half (approximately 10 setae) white and more slender and slightly longer than black postocular setae. Ventral postcranial hairs (beard) rather sparse, usually wholly white but rarely with 1-3 brown to black setae. Palpus relatively small, black, covered with sparse silver pollen and scattered yellow to yellow-brown hairs. Antenna black, first flagellomere about as long as wide, rounded apically, arista inserted near midpoint of dorsal edge.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Thorax: Scutum green to green-blue with moderately dense silver-gray pollen, with bronze to bronze-green stripes between acrostichal and dorsocentral setae and along intra-alar setae; posterior slope of scutum and scutellum blue-green with some silver pollen; notopleuron and postpronotum (humerus) covered with dense silver pollen, usually with some blue-green or bronze reflections; 6 dorsocentral setae; 6-9 large acrostichal setae (largest two-thirds size of dorsocentral setae), in a single row; 2 notopleural setae; postpronotum with 1-3 strong, black setae and often a few smaller white hairs; 2 presutural intra-alar setae (one near suture); 1 presutural and 2 postsutural supra-alar setae; 1 postalar seta; scutellum with 6 large marginal setae (3 per side), no additional hairs; proepisternum with 1 dorsal and 1 ventral tuft of white hairs. Pleura metallic green-bronze, covered with dense silver-gray pollen, without setae or hairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">
Legs: Legs concolorous with pleura, but with slightly less silver-gray pollen, femoral 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘knees’">'knees'</normalizedToken>
very narrowly orange. Coxa I uniformly covered with white hairs on anterior surface (length of hairs subequal to width of coxa I), with a couple black, slender setae near apex. Coxa II with scattered white hairs anteriorly, a few white and black setae near apex, and a black ad seta just beyond 1/2. Coxa III with a few short, white hairs on anterior surface and a black dorsal seta near 1/2. Femur I with row of short, black, pd setae on apical half (length ≤ half width of femur) and scattered, short, white hairs near base. Femur II with row of posterior hairs/setae (length ≤ width of femur), those on basal half white (longest near to just beyond middle of femur) and becoming black and shorter apically. Femur III with white hairs (length subequal to width of femur) dorsally to posteriorly at base. Tarsus I(2) very short, about as long as wide, with ventral row of setae/setulae (Fig. 3D). Ratios of tibia:tarsomeres for leg I: 16-8-2-4-3-2; for leg II: 26-20-8-4-2-2; for leg III: 37-20-17-6-2-2.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Wing (Fig. 5C): Hyaline, infuscated on anterior third, especially between R2+3 and R4+5 (mostly along veins apically); with a longitudinal spurious vein between R4+5 and M1 that is arched anteriorly near 2/3 of wing and terminates near midpoint of a semicircular, translucent, area that is white in certain lights and enclosed within a small, brown cloud; with a diffuse brown spot just above spurious vein at arch and small brown spot on CuA1 near dm-cu. Apex of wing shallowly excavated at M1, with a broad, blunt, apically-pointed lobe between M1 and CuA1, this lobe without setae. Calypter yellow with a fan of long, pale yellow setae at apex. Halter pale yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Abdomen: Cylindrical, elongate, blunt at apex (Fig. 2C); T1 metallic green with dense silver pollen laterally becoming somewhat less dense dorsally. T2-T4 blue-green with dense silver pollen basally, bronze apically. T5 dark bronze with metallic green reflections and sparse silver pollen. T6 dark bronze with blue-green reflections and with dense silver pollen. T1-T3 with yellowish hair laterally, longest on T1 and T2, without black hairs or setae. Sternites bronze with dense silver-gray pollen. S1 bare except for lateral small tuft of yellow hairs at extreme base. S2 and S3 with sparse yellow hairs. S4 mostly bare. Hypopygium (Fig. 10C): cercus very long (as long as abdomen in unshriveled specimens), slender, cylindrical, with yellow hairs that are longest medially (Fig. 2C).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">
Female. Body length 7.0-8.0 mm, wing length 6.5-7.5 mm. Similar to male except for face twice as wide, dark green to violet obscured by moderate to dense brown pollen; palpus larger, black with silver pollen apically, with dense golden-brown pollen in middle at base, and black setae. Acrostichal setae large, stout, two-thirds to three-quarters size of dorsocentral setae. Femur I with pd row of black setae on apical half (longest subequal to half width of femur) and sparse, very short white hairs on posterior and ventral surface. Femur II posteriorly with row of white hairs/setae on basal half to two-thirds (longest at base and just beyond middle) and black setae on apical half to one-third (longest of these posterior hairs/setae subequal to width of femur). Wing (Fig. 16D) hyaline, with three to four diffuse brown clouds: one in cells r4+5 and bm+dm near midpoint of wing (this often appears like two 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘spots’">'spots'</normalizedToken>
but actually connected by sometimes light brown clouding), one light brown cloud on M1 beyond crossvein dm-cu, and usually with very small light brown clouding on R4+5 at apex of wing; sometimes a small brown cloud is evident on CuA1.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="116" pageId="18" pageNumber="115" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="115">
The type specimens were collected by 
<bibRefCitation author="Van Duzee, MC" journalOrPublisher="Entomological News" pageId="42" pageNumber="139" pagination="123 - 128" title="New North American species of Dolichopodidae (Dip.)." volume="28" year="1917">Van Duzee (1917</bibRefCitation>
: 128) &quot;at Berkeley, California, May 8th, on a wall of rock in a little canyon; the wall was covered with water-soaked moss&quot;. Specimens have commonly been collected on or near beaches and sea cliffs.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="116">
<pageBreakToken pageId="19" pageNumber="116" start="start">Copulation</pageBreakToken>
of this species was described by Peter Dyte (in litt. to Richard Hurley, 1988): &quot;A pair of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Dolichopodidae" genus="Liancalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liancalus limbatus" order="Diptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limbatus">Liancalus limbatus</taxonomicName>
V.D. were seen in copula on a seepage at Wreck Beach, Vancouver, B.C., Canada, on 5.vii.1988, at 16.18 hrs. They were captured by placing a 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
1 in[ch] tube over them and they remained in copula in the tube until 17.20 hrs...All her tarsi and his mid and hind tarsi were on the substrate, but his foretarsi were held against the sides of her third abdominal segment with their apices projecting slightly below her abdomen. Thus the modified second segment of his foretarsus would have been touching her abdomen, though the separate tarsal segments could not be distinguished with the hand lens available. His long genital lamellae pointed forwards below the female abdomen but not touching it&quot;.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="116" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="116">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="116">This species occurs primarily along or near the Pacific coast from central California to Alaska, but also inland in Idaho, Oregon, Washington and British Columbia (Fig. 14B).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="116" type="type material examined">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="116">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="116">
HOLOTYPE ♂, labeled: &quot;Berkeley, Cal./ May 8 1915/ MC Van Duzee&quot;; &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Dolichopodidae" genus="Liancalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liancalus" order="Diptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Liancalus</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="limbatus" pageId="19" pageNumber="116" rank="species" species="limbatus">limbatus</taxonomicName>
/ Holotype. Van Duzee&quot; (CAS). PARATYPE ♀, same data as holotype (CAS).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="118" pageId="19" pageNumber="116" type="additional material examined">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="116">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="118" pageId="19" pageNumber="116">
CANADA.British Columbia: Vancouver, 8.viii.1917, ALM (1 ♂, USNM), P Rupert, 11.ix.1921, W.B. Anderson (2 ♂, CNC), 27 mi. E Pr. Rupert, on tide flats, 24.vi.1960, R.J. Pilfrey (1 ♀, CNC), Vancouver, Point Grey, on seepage on earth cliff, 23.vii.1973, JRV (4 ♂, 4 ♀, CNC), same as previous, 26.vii.1973 (6 ♀, CNC), same as previous, 23.ii.1973 (1 ♀, CNC), same as previous, 15.v.1973 (1 ♀, CNC), Robson, 19.viii.1947, H.R. Foxlee (1 ♀, CNC), same as previous, 3.ix.1948 (1 ♀, CNC), same as previous, 21.x.1955 (1 ♂, UBCZ), Cultus Lake, 8.vii.1948, H.R. Foxlee (1 ♀, CNC), Vancouver, 28.iii.1902, C.W. Johnson (1 ♀, MCZ), Hwy 97, Bijoux Falls Park, mileage 115.3 miles (185.6 km) from Prince George, Stop-234, 6.viii.1989, PHA (1 ♀, CAS), Vancouver, University of British Columbia, Wreck Beach Trail, behind beach, 8.vii.1988, PHA (1 ♀, CAS). USA.Alaska: Juneau Co., Thane, 29.vii.1958 (1 ♂, WSU). California: Santa Cruz Mts., 24.vii.1895 (1 ♂, 1 ♀, LACM); Humboldt Co., Arcata, 19.v.1976, M. Terzich (1 ♀, MTEC), Arcata, 22.iii.1981, RLH (2 ♀, MTEC); Marin Co., Muir Woods, 7.viii.1915, ALM (1 ♂, 1 ♀, USNM), Ross, 22.vi.1955, H.L. Mathis (1 ♂, 1 ♀, UCDC), Stinson Beach SP, 2nd inlet S main beach, sweeping rocks and vegetation about waterfall at ocean beach, 21.vi.1970, I.A. Boussy (1 ♂, 1 ♀, CAS), Mt Tamalpais, 26.v.1974, D.G. Denning (1 ♂, UCDC), Point Reyes, 19.iv.1980, S.A. Marshall (2 ♂, 2 ♀, DEBU), Phoenix Lake Pk., 22.v.1949, C.H. Spitzer (1 ♀, EMEC), same as previous, 30.v.1949 (1 ♂, EMEC); Monterey Co., Pacific Grove, 5-8.v.1906, JMA (8 ♂, 8 ♀, USNM); Napa Co., Butts Cyn, 0.5 mi. S Napa Co. line, 7.v.1970, E.E. Grissell &amp; R.F. Denno (1 ♀, UCDC); San Mateo Co., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Martin’s">Martin's</normalizedToken>
Beach, 9.ix.1969, T.W. Davies (1 ♂, 2 ♀, CAS), Memorial Park, 15.vii.1951, PHA (1 ♀, CSCA); Santa Barbara Co., Sta. Barbara, 6.vii.1917, JMA (1 ♂, 4 ♀, USNM); Santa Cruz Co., Capitola, 7-12.vi.1940, M.T. &amp; H.B. James (14 ♂, 14 ♀, CSUC, WSU), Davenport, 1.ix.1948, W.W. Wirth (3 ♂, 1 ♀, EMEC, USNM), Santa Cruz, beach, 15-17.vi.1950, M.T. James (5 ♂, 11 ♀, WSU), 1 mi. N Davenport, on beach, 4.vii.1967, A. &amp; A. Gillogly (1 ♂, UCR), Santa 
<pageBreakToken pageId="20" pageNumber="117" start="start">Cruz</pageBreakToken>
, beach, 15-17.vi.1950, M.T. James (4 ♂, 12 ♀, WSU), Santa Cruz, 9.vii.1972, D.G. Denning (1 ♀, UCDC); Sonoma Co., Bodega Bay, 13.v.1963, C.G. Moore (1 ♂, UCDC), Stillwater Cove, 23.v.1954, E.I. Schlinger (2 ♂, 2 ♀, UCDC), same as previous, J.G. Downey (1 ♂, 1 ♀, UCDC). Idaho: Adams Co., Little Salmon R, 18 mi. N New Meadows, 8.viii.1979, RLH (1 ♀, MTEC); Boise Co., Canyon Crk, 30 mi. NE Lowman, 15.ix.1981, RLH (1 ♀, MTEC); Kootenai Co., Beauty Crk, near Lake 
<normalizedToken originalValue="CD’A">CD'A</normalizedToken>
, 31.viii.1976, D.F. Veirs (1 ♀, WFBM); Latah Co., Mts Moscow, 25.vii.1920, R.C. Shannon (1 ♂, 1 ♀, USNM), Moscow Mts, East Twin Peak, 19.vii.1983, R.S. Zack (2 ♂, 1 ♀, WSU), Lower Sand Crk, nr. Bonami Crk, 16 mi. E Potlatch, 2900 ft, 5.viii.1979, WJT (3 ♂, WSU), same as previous, 9.viii.1979 (2 ♂, 6 ♀, WSU), same as previous, 28.viii.1982 (1 ♂, 1 ♀, WSU), 7 mi. N Troy, near Big Meadow Recreation Area, 3000 ft, 31.vii.1979, WJT (1 ♂, 1 ♀, WSU), Big Meadow Recreation Area, 7 mi. NNE Troy, 3000 ft, 7.viii.1986, WJT (1 ♂, 1 ♀, WSU); Nez Perce Co., Juliaetta Falls, 5.2 mi. S. Juliaetta, 3.iii.1983, J. Jenkins (2 ♀, MTEC). Oregon: Mt Hood, 29.vii.1966, FCH (10 ♂, 4 ♀, EMUS, FSCA, MTEC); Benton Co., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Mary’s">Mary's</normalizedToken>
Peak, Parker Crk, roadside seepage, 26.ix.1967, KJG (1 ♂, ODAC), Marys Peak, Hwy 34, 4097', 16.vii.1968, B.V. Peterson (1 ♂, 1 ♀, CNC), Parker Crk, Marys Peak Rd, 1.vii.1971, G. Steyskal (1 ♂, 1 ♀, OSAC), 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Mary’s">Mary's</normalizedToken>
Peak nr Corvallis, F.R. Cole (1 ♂, EMEC); Coos Co., Charleston, marine biological station, 9.vii.1954, M.T. James (1 ♀, WSU); Hood River Co., Hood River, seepage over road cut, 15.viii.1966, KJG (2 ♂, 1 ♀, CAS, OSAC), 8 mi. NW Mt Hood, Lolo Pass Rd, roadside seepage, 9.x.1966, KJG (1 ♂, OSAC), 20 mi. S Hood River, vertical roadside seepage,16.viii.1966, KJG (1 ♂, 2 ♀, CAS, MTEC, OSAC), Hood River, 21.vi.1917, F.R. Cole (1 ♀, CAS); Jackson Co., 10 mi. S Ruch, stream margins, 22.v.1964, KJG (2 ♀, ODAC); Josephine Co., Grants Pass, black light trap, 15.ix.1965, KJG (1 ♂, ODAC); Lincoln Co., Agate Beach, base sea cliff, 16.v.1976, R.L. Westcott (1 ♀, ODAC), 15 mi. S Newport, seepage on sea cliffs, 13.vii.1966, KJG (1 ♂, 3 ♀, FSCA, OSAC), Newport, seeps along coastal cliffs, 22.vii.1983, WJT (1 ♂, 10 ♀, WSU), 20 mi. S Hood River, vertical roadcut seepage, 16.viii.1966, KJG (1 ♂, OSAC), Yachats, 20.vi.1939, G.E. Bohart (1 ♂,UCDC), 1 mi. N Depoe Bay, H2O spring above beach, 24.vi.1956, J.D. Lattin (1 ♂, OSAC); Linn Co., 1 mi. S Marion Forks, 15.v.1967, KJG (2 ♀, ODAC), same as previous, seepage along road cut, 31.vii.1966 (5 ♂, 2 ♀, CAS,CSCA, ODAC, OSAC), same as previous, shaded vertical seepage, 24.viii.1967 (7 ♂, 4 ♀, ODAC, OSAC, MTEC), same are previous, 21.vii.1969, E.M. Fisher (1 ♀, CSCA); Multnomah Co., Larch Mt, 15.viii.1966, KJG (2 ♂, FSCA), Portland, 16.vi.1926, A. Spuler (1 ♂, SEMC), Troutdale, 1.viii.1965, FCH (2 ♂, 2 ♀, FSCA, MTEC), same as previous, 23.vi.1963, L.S. Miller (1 ♀, FSCA); Tillamook Co., Oceanside, seepage along ocean cliff, 29.vii.1966, KJG (2 ♀, ODAC). Washington: &quot;Washington (state)&quot; (♀ paralectotype of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Dolichopodidae" genus="Liancalus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Liancalus similis" order="Diptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="118" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="similis">
<pageBreakToken pageId="21" pageNumber="118" start="start">Liancalus</pageBreakToken>
similis
</taxonomicName>
, SEMC), Mt Adams, 24.vii.1921, ALM (1 ♀, USNM); Asotin Co., 17 mi. S Anatone, nr. Grande Ronde River, 1950 ft, dripping spring, 10.viii.1976, WJT (1 ♂, WSU); Columbia Co., Tucanon RS, Blue Mts, 13.viii.1922, V.N. Argo (1 ♂, 2 ♀, USNM); King Co., Lake Washington, 12.viii.1917, ALM (7 ♂, 6 ♀, USNM); Okanogan Co., 9 mi. W Conconully, Salmon Mdws, 4500 ft, 3-6.vii.1975, N.E. Woodley (1 ♀, WSU), Seattle (1 ♂, 2 ♀, OSAC); Pacific Co., Ilwaco, vii.1917, ALM (3 ♀, USNM); San Juan Co., Friday Harbor, 23.vii.1905, JMA (2 ♂, 2 ♀, USNM), same as previous, 27.vii.1905 (2 ♂, USNM), Olga, 17.v.1910 (2 ♀, USNM); Skagit Co., 2 mi. S Sedro-Woolley, 28.viii.1971, H.P. Stene (2 ♂, WSU); Stevens Co., Deer Lake, near Chewelah, 6-7.v.1972, M.T. James (1 ♀, WSU); Whatcom Co., 9 mi. N Concrete, 15.vii.1969, R. Turnbow (1 ♀, UGCA).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>