<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458880" ID-ISSN="1942-1354" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5458880" ID-ZooBank="E8606F00-5FEF-41A7-98D2-3F0523D3290F" approvalRequired="7" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="6" approvalRequired_for_treatments="1" checkinTime="1630211029253" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio &amp; Botero, Juan Pablo" docDate="2020" docId="BB196D689E719C3883DFF3F5A5A2222B" docLanguage="en" docName="0772.pdf" docOrigin="Insecta Mundi 2020 (772)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:6D85C66E4B52897F25DA165649BC06DC.1:InsectaMundi.2009-2020.journal_article" docStyleId="6D85C66E4B52897F25DA165649BC06DC" docStyleName="InsectaMundi.2009-2020.journal_article" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Pteroplatus antonkozlovi Santos-Silva and Botero 2020, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="4" masterDocId="472015109E729C3D831FF74AA002271F" masterDocTitle="A new species of Pteroplatus Buquet, 1840 (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae) and taxonomical notes in Neotropical Cerambycidae" masterLastPageNumber="10" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="3" pageNumber="2" updateTime="1630870264987" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-NC-3.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of Pteroplatus Buquet, 1840 (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae) and taxonomical notes in Neotropical Cerambycidae</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo Caixa Postal 42.494, 04218 - 970, São Paulo, SP, Brazil</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Botero, Juan Pablo</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo Caixa Postal 42.494, 04218 - 970, São Paulo, SP, Brazil</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Insecta Mundi</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2020-06-26</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2020</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>772</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>10</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458880</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1942-1354</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5458880</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">E8606F00-5FEF-41A7-98D2-3F0523D3290F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BB196D689E719C3883DFF3F5A5A2222B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BB196D689E719C3883DFF3F5A5A2222B" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">
<subSubSection box="[192,995,1215,1240]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="3.[192,995,1215,1272]" box="[192,995,1215,1240]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">
<heading bold="true" box="[192,995,1215,1240]" fontSize="10" level="2" pageId="3" pageNumber="2" reason="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,995,1215,1240]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva and Botero" authorityName="Santos-Silva and Botero" authorityYear="2020" box="[192,877,1215,1240]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,537,1215,1239]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">Pteroplatus antonkozlovi</emphasis>
Santos-Silva and Botero
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[891,995,1216,1240]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="3" pageNumber="2" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="3.[192,995,1215,1272]" box="[192,308,1248,1272]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">
(
<figureCitation box="[201,300,1248,1272]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">Fig. 2–6</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[190,1443,1297,1844]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,478,1297,1321]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">Description. Female.</emphasis>
Frons and central area of vertex black (black area gradually narrowed toward prothorax on vertex); most of antennal tubercles, sides of vertex, and superior region of area behind upper eye lobes orange; remaining surface of area behind upper eye lobes, and area behind lower eye lobes dark brown, gradually brown toward gulamentum; genae orange except brown apex; gulamentum mostly orange, with anterocentral area brown; mouthparts mostly brown, with apex of last palpomeres light reddish-brown; postclypeus brown; anteclypeus yellowish-brown; labrum brownish posteriorly, more reddish-brown anteriorly and dark brown laterally; mandibles dark reddish-brown on basal half, dark brown on anterior half; antennae black. Pronotum orange, with wide, longitudinal black central band (continuing on vertex). Sides of prothorax with wide, longitudinal black central band close to pronotum (continuing behind eyes), orange toward prosternum. Prosternum orange laterally, except brownish lateral area close to procoxal cavities, pale yellow centrally; prosternal process pale yellow. Meso- and metaventrite mostly black, except dark reddish-brown central area of mesoventrite, and pale yellow meso- and metaventral processes, and small, slightly distinct circular orange area on each side of metaventrite near metacoxal cavities. Scutellum black. Elytra mostly yellowish-brown, slightly orangishbrown on center of dorsal surface, except brownish punctures, and sutural black band on anterior half (continuing on pronotum). Coxae and trochanters brown; femora, tibiae and tarsi black. Ventrites black laterally, gradually brown toward central area, except yellowish-brown anterocentral area of ventrite I.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[192,1440,1869,1926]" lastBlockId="4.[190,1441,215,1171]" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="3" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,272,1869,1893]" pageId="3" pageNumber="2">Head.</emphasis>
Frons with narrow, nearly smooth, glabrous, slightly elevated central plate, widened toward clypeus; remaining surface finely, abundantly punctate, with dark brown pubescence not obscuring integument, slightly denser, bristly laterally. Vertex with sculpturing as on frons; with dark brown pubescence not obscuring integument on black area, and golden-yellow pubescence (longer and denser than pubescence on black area), with a few long, erect whitish setae interspersed laterally. Area behind upper eye lobes nearly glabrous close to eye, with golden-yellow pubescence not obscuring integument on remaining surface; with one very long, whitish seta close to eye. Area behind lower eye lobes finely, moderately sparsely punctate; nearly glabrous, with a few long, erect whitish setae close to eye. Antennal tubercles minutely, densely striate anteriorly, very finely, sparsely punctate on remaining surface; striate area glabrous; remaining surface with golden-yellow pubescence not obscuring integument; with a few long, erect whitish setae interspersed. Postclypeus minutely, densely punctate on wide central area, smooth laterally; with golden-yellow bristly pubescence on wide central area, glabrous laterally; with long, erect, sparse whitish setae interspersed on wide central area. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus posteriorly, strongly inclined anteriorly; finely, abundantly punctate on coplanar area; with long, erect, yellowish setae directed forward (whiter depending on light intensity), and fringe of golden-yellow setae in anterior margin. Genae finely, moderately abundantly punctate except smooth apex; with goldenyellow pubescence not obscuring integument, except glabrous smooth area; with a few long, erect whitish setae interspersed on pubescent area. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous posteriorly, rugose punctate, with sparse yellowish-white pubescence and a few long, erect setae of same color on area between eyes. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.76 times length of scape (0.41 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 1.10 times length of scape (0.60 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae slightly longer than elytra, reaching posterior third of elytra. Scape, pedicel, and antennomeres III–VI finely, densely punctate; remaining antennomeres minutely, densely, slightly distinctly punctate; with dark brown, somewhat bristly pubescence not obscuring integument; scape with long, erect dark brown setae throughout; pedicel and antennomeres III–VI with fringe of dense erect setae on posterior 3/4 of ventral surface, gradually longer toward apex of each antennomere, distinctly longer on VI; pedicel, and antennomeres III–V with long, erect, sparse dark brown setae on apex of dorsal surface, slightly more abundant on posterior third of ventral surface; antennomere VI with long, erect dark brown setae ventrally; remaining antennomeres with minute brownish pubescence, with grayish-white pubescence interspersed. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 1.41; pedicel = 0.46; IV = 1.05; V = 1.46; VI = 1.67; VII = 1.29; VIII = 1.12; IX = 0.96; X = 0.79; XI = 0.96.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[190,1442,1195,1926]" lastBlockId="5.[191,1441,215,335]" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="4" pageNumber="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,300,1195,1219]" pageId="4" pageNumber="3">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax widened laterocentrally, forming a slightly conspicuous tubercle. Pronotum gibbous on each side of posterior half; with slightly distinct gibbosity on central area of posterior 3/4, nearly indistinct anteriorly; coarsely punctate on anterior half of central gibbosity, smooth on posterior half of central gibbosity, moderately coarsely, densely punctate on remaining surface (punctures denser, less well-defined laterally); with sparse dark brown pubescence on black area, except glabrous posterior half of central gibbosity; with golden-yellow pubescence partially obscuring integument on remaining surface, with long, erect golden and whitish setae interspersed. Sides of prothorax with dark brown pubescence not obscuring integument on black area, denser, yellowish-white on orange area; with long, erect, sparse yellowish setae interspersed. Prosternum with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument (whiter depending on light intensity), with long, erect, moderately abundant setae of same color interspersed. Narrowest area of prosternal process 0.25 times width of procoxal cavity. Apex of mesoventral process slightly narrower than mesocoxal cavity. Meso- and metaventrite with yellowishwhite pubescence not obscuring integument (whiter depending on light intensity), sparser on central area of mesoventrite and nearly absent on center of metaventrite, with long, erect setae of same color interspersed, denser on metaventrite. Scutellum with brownish pubescence not obscuring integument. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,286,1677,1701]" pageId="4" pageNumber="3">Elytra.</emphasis>
Coarsely, abundantly punctate on basal half, and gradually finer toward apex; with short, decumbent golden yellow setae not obscuring integument; with long, erect, golden setae interspersed (some brownish on basal half, especially on anterior third); with two longitudinal carinae, starting on base between humerus and scutellum, the outermost almost reaching apex; without humeral carina (
<figureCitation box="[203,273,1805,1829]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="4" pageNumber="3">Fig. 6</figureCitation>
); apex rounded toward sutural angle. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[731,802,1806,1830]" pageId="4" pageNumber="3">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora finely, abundantly punctate dorsally and on posterior quarter of lateral surface (general appearance somewhat scabrous), finely, sparsely punctate on remaining surface; with brownish pubescence not obscuring integument on somewhat scabrous area, with a few long, erect dark brown setae interspersed; with long, erect yellowish-white setae ventrally, distinctly denser on mesofemora. Protibiae with dark brown pubescence, distinctly denser, bristly ventrally, with long, erect setae of same color interspersed. Meso- and metatibiae with short, sparse, subdecumbent dark brown setae, distinctly denser on posterior area of ventral surface, with long, erect setae of same color interspersed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[191,1440,359,448]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,329,359,383]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument (whiter depending on light intensity), with long, erect setae of same color interspersed. Apex of ventrite V truncate, with a few long, erect dark setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[190,1440,472,528]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,330,472,496]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Variation.</emphasis>
Metaventrite pale yellow behind mesocoxal cavities; central area of ventrites reddish-brown except yellowish brown anterocentral area of ventrite I.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[192,1440,552,641]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,909,552,576]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
Dimensions (mm), 
<typeStatus box="[449,569,552,576]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">holotype</typeStatus>
female/ 
<typeStatus box="[680,801,552,576]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">paratype</typeStatus>
female.
</emphasis>
Total length, 8.85/9.40; prothoracic length, 1.35/1.45; anterior prothoracic width, 1.60/1.65; posterior prothoracic width, 1.45/1.50; maximum prothoracic width, 1.80/1.85; humeral width, 2.35/2.45; elytral length, 6.55/6.80.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="4" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="5.[190,1440,664,785]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,390,665,689]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation collectionCode="MZSP" collectorName="A. Kozlov &amp; Y. Kovaleva" country="Panama" elevation="2050" latitude="8.8854" location="Volcan town" longLatPrecision="5" longitude="-82.68336" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Chiriqui" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[395,504,665,689]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Holotype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry box="[658,783,665,689]" name="Panama" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">PANAMA</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[790,924,664,691]" country="Panama" name="Chiriqui" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">CHIRIQUÍ</collectingRegion>
: near 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BB196D689E719C3883DFF3F5A5A2222B:366F8AA59E779C3880F7F5D3A48225AF" box="[1000,1152,665,689]" country="Panama" latitude="8.8854" longLatPrecision="5" longitude="-82.68336" name="Volcan town" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" stateProvince="Chiriqui">Volcán town</location>
, 
<geoCoordinate box="[1161,1271,665,689]" degrees="8.8854" direction="north" orientation="latitude" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" precision="5" value="8.8854">8.8854ºN</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate box="[1289,1436,665,689]" degrees="82.68336" direction="west" orientation="longitude" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" precision="1" value="-82.68336">82.68336ºW</geoCoordinate>
, 
<quantity box="[190,354,697,721]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.05" metricValueMax="2.2" metricValueMin="1.9" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" unit="m" value="2050.0" valueMax="2200.0" valueMin="1900.0">
<elevation box="[190,354,697,721]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.05" metricValueMax="2.2" metricValueMin="1.9" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" unit="m" value="2050.0" valueMax="2200.0" valueMin="1900.0">1900-2200 m</elevation>
</quantity>
, V-VI.2019, 
<collectorName box="[512,632,697,721]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">A. Kozlov</collectorName>
and 
<collectorName box="[700,851,697,721]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Y. Kovaleva</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode box="[921,1002,697,721]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<typeStatus box="[1024,1136,697,721]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Paratype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry box="[1308,1433,697,721]" name="Panama" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">PANAMA</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[192,327,728,755]" country="Panama" name="Chiriqui" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">CHIRIQUÍ</collectingRegion>
: near Volcán town, Totumas Mountain Cloud Forest, 
<geoCoordinate box="[999,1139,729,753]" degrees="8" direction="north" minutes="53" orientation="latitude" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" precision="1" seconds="6.01" value="8.885003">8º53’6.01”N</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate box="[1165,1328,729,753]" degrees="82" direction="west" minutes="41" orientation="longitude" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" precision="1" seconds="1.32" value="-82.6837">82º41’1.32”W</geoCoordinate>
, 
<quantity box="[1341,1435,729,753]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.92" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" unit="m" value="1920.0">1920 m</quantity>
, V-VI.2018, A. Kozlov and Y. Kovaleva col. (
<collectionCode box="[718,800,761,785]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">AKPC</collectionCode>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="4" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="5.[191,1441,809,866]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,347,809,833]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Etymology.</emphasis>
The new species is named in honor of Anton Olegovich Kozlov (AKPC), who sent the types, and donated the 
<typeStatus box="[397,501,841,865]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">holotype</typeStatus>
for MZSP collection.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="4" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="5.[190,1440,890,1075]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,323,890,914]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Botero, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Botero" authorityYear="2020" box="[329,630,890,914]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[329,630,890,914]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Pteroplatus antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[636,728,890,913]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Salle, 1850" authorityName="Salle" authorityYear="1850" box="[881,1172,890,914]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="variabilis">
<emphasis box="[881,1030,890,914]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">P. variabilis</emphasis>
Sallé, 1850
</taxonomicName>
, but differs as follows: elytra (
<figureCitation box="[280,382,922,946]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 2, 6</figureCitation>
) lacking humeral carina; short elytral setae distinctly sparser (
<figureCitation box="[1169,1241,922,946]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 6</figureCitation>
); antennomeres (
<figureCitation box="[202,271,954,978]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 2</figureCitation>
) proportionally shorter; elytra more projected toward sutural angle (
<figureCitation box="[1111,1182,954,978]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 2</figureCitation>
). In 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Salle" authorityYear="1850" box="[1236,1386,954,978]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="variabilis">
<emphasis box="[1236,1386,954,978]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">P. variabilis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, the elytra have distinct humeral carina (
<figureCitation box="[627,726,986,1010]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 7–9</figureCitation>
), short elytral setae distinctly denser (
<figureCitation box="[1179,1247,986,1010]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 7</figureCitation>
), antennomeres proportionally longer (
<figureCitation box="[465,566,1018,1042]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 8–9</figureCitation>
), and elytra more uniformly rounded (
<figureCitation box="[1035,1137,1018,1042]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 8–9</figureCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[190,1440,890,1075]" box="[232,1435,1050,1075]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Botero" authorityYear="2020" box="[232,535,1050,1074]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi">
<emphasis box="[232,535,1050,1074]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Pteroplatus antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
can be included in the alternative of couplet “5” from 
<bibRefCitation author="Botero, J. P. &amp; A. Santos-Silva &amp; L. G. Bezark" box="[1194,1430,1050,1075]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" pagination="69 - 100" refId="ref5682" refString="Botero, J. P., A. Santos-Silva, and L. G. Bezark, 2019. Revision of the genus Pteroplatus Buquet, 1840. Zootaxa 4658 (1): 69 - 100." type="journal article" year="2019">Botero et al. (2019)</bibRefCitation>
:
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[192,1440,1098,1187]" box="[192,1414,1098,1123]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
5(4). Elytra distinctly pubescent (
<figureCitation box="[614,715,1099,1123]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 7–9</figureCitation>
). 
<collectingCountry box="[733,849,1099,1123]" name="Colombia" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Colombia</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion box="[862,1002,1099,1123]" country="Colombia" name="Magdalena" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Magdalena</collectingRegion>
), 
<collectingCountry box="[1021,1148,1099,1123]" name="Venezuela" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Venezuela</collectingCountry>
..................
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[192,1440,1098,1187]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
...................................................... 
<taxonomicName authority="Salle, 1850" authorityName="Salle" authorityYear="1850" box="[1120,1440,1130,1155]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="variabilis">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1120,1440,1130,1155]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1120,1289,1130,1154]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">P. variabilis</emphasis>
Sallé, 1850
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
— Elytra not pubescent, with sparse setae (
<figureCitation box="[772,872,1163,1187]" captionStart="Figures 1–9. 1" captionStartId="10.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[226,1406,217,1815]" captionTargetId="figure-72@10.[226,1406,217,1817]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="Figures 1–9. 1) Neocompsa thelgema, female, dorsal habitus. 2–6) Pteroplatus antonkozlovi, holotype female. 2) Dorsal habitus.3) Lateral habitus.4) Ventral habitus.5) Frontal view.6) Elytral base.7–9) Pteroplatus variabilis. 7) Elytral base, syntype 1. 8) Syntype 1, dorsal habitus. 9) Syntype 2, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458882" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458882/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Fig. 2, 6</figureCitation>
)................................... 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1419,1434,1163,1187]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">5</emphasis>
′
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[192,1440,1210,1332]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
5′(5). Pronotum without black central band, with sparse golden-yellow pubescence on orange area; elytral apex uniformly rounded. 
<collectingCountry box="[709,768,1244,1267]" name="Peru" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Peru</collectingCountry>
....... 
<taxonomicName authority="Martins and Galileo, 2013" authorityName="Martins and Galileo" authorityYear="2013" box="[885,1440,1243,1267]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pallidicolor">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[885,1440,1243,1267]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[885,1083,1243,1267]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">P. pallidicolor</emphasis>
Martins and Galileo, 2013
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[192,1440,1210,1332]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
— Pronotum with black central band, with dense golden-yellow pubescence on orange area; elytral apex projected toward sutural angle. 
<collectingCountry box="[767,869,1308,1331]" name="Panama" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">Panama</collectingCountry>
................ 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1117,1440,1307,1332]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Botero, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Botero" authorityYear="2020" box="[1117,1329,1307,1331]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pteroplatus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1117,1329,1307,1331]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="4">P. antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1336,1440,1308,1332]" pageId="5" pageNumber="4" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>