<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5063838" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9bb2fc2c-bb1a-4739-ab2f-a0461642308a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116562" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5063838" ModsDocAuthor=" &amp; Clark, J." ModsDocDate="1930" ModsDocID="6104" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf" ModsDocTitle="New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species." checkinTime="1264892749103" checkinUser="claudia" docAuthor="Clark, J." docDate="1930" docId="65CA110124D40D24235F852E932CBB69" docLanguage="en" docName="6104_tx1.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria 43" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf" docTitle="Phyracaces flavescens Emery 1901, n. sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="11" lastPageNumber="6" masterDocId="9882AE8990DDB183F966C81C08BF69C4" masterDocTitle="New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species." masterLastPageNumber="25" masterPageNumber="2" pageNumber="5" updateTime="1643596530053" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Clark, J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1930</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>2</mods:start>
<mods:end>25</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6104</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5063838" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116562" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5063838" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:65CA110124D40D24235F852E932CBB69" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/65CA110124D40D24235F852E932CBB69" lastPageNumber="6" pageNumber="5">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:136635" authority="Emery, 1901" authorityName="Emery" authorityYear="1901" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Phyracaces" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Phyracaces flavescens Clark" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavescens">Phyracaces flavescens</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="5">(Text-fig. 1, No. 4.)</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="5">Worker.-Length, 3-8- -4-3 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="6" pageNumber="5">
Reddish yellow. Eyes and margins of the thorax and node black. 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="6">Shining</pageStartToken>
. Head very finely and densely reticulate-punctate. Mandibles smooth, with some large scattered punctures. Thorax, node and postpetiole reticulate-punctate as on the head, remainder of the gaster superficially reticulate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Hair yellow, long and erect, abundant throughout, very short and adpressed on the antennae and legs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Head slightly longer than broad, as broad in front as behind, the occipital border straight, the sides convex. Frontal carinae erect, truncate and confluent behind. Clypeus short and rounded. Eyes large, moderately convex, placed at the middle of the sides. No ocelli. Carina of the cheeks extending to and touching the anterior third of the eyes, bent inward and branched at the middle, one portion extending to the frontal carina above the antennal fovea. Scapes extending to the posterior third of the head, gradually thickened to their apex; first segment of the funiculus one fourth longer than the second, the apical as long as the three preceding segments together. Mandibles triangular, abruptly bent near the base, the external border concave at the middle, the inner border sharp, edentate. Thorax fully one and three quarter times longer than broad, without traces of sutures. Strongly constricted at the mesonotal region, the pronotum and epinotum of equal width. All four sides of the dorsum strongly marginate. Anterior border of the pronotum feebly convex, the angles sharp; in profile a sharp carina extending downward from the anterior angle. Posterior border of the epinotum convex; in profile the declivity abrupt and concave, marginate on the sides. Petiole broader than long, slightly broader behind than in front, the anterior border concave, the sides feebly convex, the posterior angles produced backward and inward as sharp, translucent teeth. The anterior border and sides marginate. Postpetiole slightly broader than long, convex in front and on the sides. First segment of the gaster much broader than long. Pygidium truncate, feebly margined, with a row of short bristles on each side. Legs long and slender, the posterior coxae with a large translucent lamina on top behind.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Female.-Length, 4.5-5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Very similar to the worker, but larger and more robust. Ocelli well developed. Mesonotum without mayrian furrows, parapsidal furrows well developed. Wings hyaline, with a brownish tinge, all the veins in front of the cubitus obsolete.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Habitat.-Western Australia: Eradu (J. Clark).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="6">
Near 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:136637" authority="Emery, 1901" authorityName="Emery" authorityYear="1901" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Phyracaces" genus.outerRound="1" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Phyracaces newmani Clark" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="newmani">P. newmani Clark</taxonomicName>
, from which it is distinguished by the colour, sculpture and more slender form, as well as by the form of the node.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>