<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.63.10480" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ea6080be-9022-4cf2-8b85-0727410ae682" ID-GBIF-Taxon="177274233" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-633-1" ID-ZBK="DEFC153072414BA6B778CA63DB45B422" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-633-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 633" ModsDocTitle="A biodiversity hotspot for Microgastrinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) in North America: annotated species checklist for Ottawa, Canada" checkinTime="1479448340849" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Fernandez-Triana, Jose, Boudreault, Caroline, Buffam, Joel &amp; Mclean, Ronald" docDate="2016" docId="B1DFF12334246623B6ADA53760369034" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 633: 1-93" docOrigin="ZooKeys 633" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.63.10480" docTitle="Glyptapanteles militaris Walsh 1861" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="34" masterDocId="FFE2FFAEFFADEE31FFCBFE75FFBDFF87" masterDocTitle="A biodiversity hotspot for Microgastrinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) in North America: annotated species checklist for Ottawa, Canada" masterLastPageNumber="93" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" updateTime="1643494675356" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A biodiversity hotspot for Microgastrinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) in North America: annotated species checklist for Ottawa, Canada</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fernandez-Triana, Jose</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Boudreault, Caroline</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Buffam, Joel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Mclean, Ronald</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>633</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>93</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.63.10480</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.63.10480</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-633-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DEFC153072414BA6B778CA63DB45B422</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DEFC153072414BA6B778CA63DB45B422</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="177274233" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B1DFF12334246623B6ADA53760369034" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B1DFF12334246623B6ADA53760369034" lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="34" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<subSubSection pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Braconidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName authority="Walsh, 1861" authorityName="Walsh" authorityYear="1861" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Glyptapanteles" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glyptapanteles militaris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="militaris">Glyptapanteles militaris (Walsh, 1861)</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">NEA, NEO, PAL.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="36" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="36" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
Ontario, Ottawa, City Garden, 45.381015 -75.715397, Malaise trap, 10.viii-1.ix.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC482042, CNC482043, CNC482044, CNC482045, CNC482046, CNC482047, CNC482048, CNC482049, CNC482050, CNC482051, CNC482052, CNC482053, CNC482054, CNC482055, CNC482056, CNC482057, CNC482058, CNC482059, CNC482060, CNC482061, CNC482062, CNC482063, CNC482064, CNC482065, CNC482066, CNC482067, CNC482068; 23-30.vii.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC482079, CNC482080, CNC482081, CNC482082, CNC482083, CNC482084, CNC482085, CNC482086, CNC482087, CNC482088, CNC482089, CNC482090, CNC482091, CNC482092, CNC482093, CNC482094, CNC482095, CNC482096, CNC482097, CNC482098, CNC482099, CNC482100, CNC482101, CNC482102, CNC482103, CNC482104, CNC482105, CNC482106, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="34" pageNumber="35" start="start">CNC</pageBreakToken>
482107, CNC482108, CNC482109, CNC482110, CNC482111, CNC482112, CNC482113, CNC482114, CNC482115, CNC482116, CNC482117, CNC482118, CNC482119, CNC482120, CNC482121, CNC482122, CNC482123, CNC482124, CNC482125, CNC482126, CNC482127, CNC482128, CNC482129, CNC482130, CNC482131, CNC482132, CNC482133, CNC482134; 24-30.v.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC482073, CNC482074, CNC482075, CNC482076; 26.vi-13.vii.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC482078; 30.vii-10.viii.2007, H. Goulet, H.Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC481889, CNC481890, CNC481891, CNC481928, CNC481929, CNC481930, CNC481931, CNC481932, CNC481933, CNC481934, CNC481935, CNC481936, CNC481937, CNC481938, CNC481939, CNC481940, CNC481941, CNC481942, CNC481943, CNC481944, CNC481945, CNC481946, CNC481947, CNC481948, CNC481949, CNC481950, CNC481951, CNC481952, CNC481953, CNC481954, CNC481955, CNC481956, CNC481957, CNC481958, CNC481959, CNC481960, CNC481961, CNC481962, CNC481963, CNC481964, CNC481965, CNC481966, CNC481967, CNC481968, CNC481969, CNC481970, CNC481971, CNC481972, CNC481973, CNC481974, CNC481975, CNC481976, CNC481977, CNC481978, CNC481979, CNC481980, CNC481981, CNC481982, CNC481983, CNC481984, CNC481985, CNC481986, CNC481987, CNC481988, CNC481997, CNC481998, CNC481999, CNC482000, CNC482001, CNC482002, CNC482003, CNC482004, CNC482005, CNC482006, CNC482007, CNC482008, CNC482009, CNC482010, CNC482011, CNC482012, CNC482013, CNC482014, CNC482015, CNC482016, CNC482017, CNC482018, CNC482019, CNC482020, CNC482021, CNC482022, CNC482023, CNC482024, CNC482025, CNC482026, CNC482027, CNC482028, CNC482029, CNC482030, CNC482031, CNC482032, CNC482033, CNC482034, CNC482035, CNC482036, CNC482037, CNC482038, CNC482039, CNC482040, CNC482041, CNC481878, CNC481879, CNC481880, CNC481881, CNC481882, CNC481883, CNC481884, CNC481885, CNC481886, CNC481887, CNC481888; 8-16.vi.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC482077; Ottawa, city garden, 45.381015 -75.715397, Malaise trap, 1-19.ix.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC475269, CNC475270, CNC475271, CNC475272; 10.viii-1.ix.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC481892, CNC481893, CNC481894, CNC481895, CNC481896, CNC481897, CNC481898, CNC481899, CNC481900, CNC481901, CNC481902, CNC481903, CNC481904, CNC481905, CNC481906, CNC481907, CNC481908, CNC481909, CNC481910, CNC481911, CNC481912, CNC481913, CNC481914, CNC481915, CNC481916, CNC481917, CNC481918, CNC481919, CNC481920, CNC481921, CNC481922, CNC481923, CNC481924, CNC481925, CNC481926, CNC481927; 23-30.vii.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC475244, CNC475245, CNC475246, CNC475247, CNC475248, CNC475249, CNC475250, CNC475251, CNC475252, CNC475253, CNC475254, CNC475255, CNC475256, CNC475257, CNC475258, CNC475259, CNC475260, CNC475261, CNC475262, CNC475263, CNC475264, CNC475265; 24-30.v.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC481852, CNC481853, CNC481854; 26.vi-13.vii.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC481855; 30.vii-10.viii.2007, H. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="35" pageNumber="36" start="start">Goulet</pageBreakToken>
, Voucher Code: CNC475238, CNC475239, CNC475240, CNC475241, CNC475242, CNC475243, CNC475273; 8-16.vi.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC475266, CNC475267, CNC475268; Ottawa, 45.381015 -75.715397, Malaise trap, 10.viii-1.ix.2007, H. Goulet, Voucher Code: CNC481856, CNC481857, CNC481858, CNC481859, CNC481860, CNC481861, CNC481862, CNC481863, CNC481864, CNC481865, CNC481866, CNC481867, CNC481868, CNC481869, CNC481870, CNC481871, CNC481872, CNC481873, CNC481874, CNC481875, CNC481876, CNC481877; 21.vii.1957, Guppy, J.C., J. C. Guppy, J.C. Guppy, Voucher Code: CNC280985, CNCHYM01317, CNC475225, CNC475226, CNC475227, CNC475228, CNC475229, CNC475230, CNC475231, CNC475232, CNC475233, CNC475234, CNC475235, CNC475236, CNC475237.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>