<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.57.12892" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4b29812b-51d4-4251-9fdd-3d31635b8fb3" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132649906" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1314-2607-57-1" ID-ZBK="6201DACE99004A2F92C9D3014851100D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1314-2607-57-1" ModsDocOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 57" ModsDocTitle="Eustochomorpha Girault, Neotriadomerus gen. n., and Proarescon gen. n. (Hymenoptera, Mymaridae), early extant lineages in evolution of the family" checkinTime="1502745096210" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Huber, John T." docDate="2017" docId="DEECE34A69029904E173933D86E73BAA" docLanguage="en" docName="JourHymenoptRes 57: 1-87" docOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 57" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.57.12892" docTitle="Eustochomorpha Girault 1915" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageNumber="2" masterDocId="FFCD6D009A24DB48FFB14501FF9BAA28" masterDocTitle="Eustochomorpha Girault, Neotriadomerus gen. n., and Proarescon gen. n. (Hymenoptera, Mymaridae), early extant lineages in evolution of the family" masterLastPageNumber="87" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" updateTime="1643477465413" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Eustochomorpha Girault, Neotriadomerus gen. n., and Proarescon gen. n. (Hymenoptera, Mymaridae), early extant lineages in evolution of the family</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Huber, John T.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of Hymenoptera Research</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>87</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.57.12892</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.57.12892</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1314-2607-57-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">6201DACE99004A2F92C9D3014851100D</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">6201DACE99004A2F92C9D3014851100D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132649906" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:DEECE34A69029904E173933D86E73BAA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DEECE34A69029904E173933D86E73BAA" lastPageNumber="2" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName authority="Girault, 1915" authorityName="Girault" authorityYear="1915" class="Insecta" family="Mymaridae" genus="Eustochomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eustochomorpha" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eustochomorpha Girault, 1915</taxonomicName>
Figs 1-3, 4-7, 8-10, 11-18, 19-24, 25-31
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="type species">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Type species.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Mymaridae" genus="Eustochomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eustochomorpha haeckeli" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="haeckeli">Eustochomorpha haeckeli</taxonomicName>
Girault, by monotypy.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Female. Antenna with funicle 8-segmented and clava 2-segmented (Figs 3, 7, 14). Venation about 0.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
fore wing length. Postmarginal vein distinct, uniformly thick and about 0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
marginal vein length, with at least 2 short, socketed setae (Fig. 8, apical one indicated by arrow, Fig. 20c). Hypochaeta possibly present (Fig. 20a), originating on the parastigma instead of on the costal cell. Ovipositor strongly extending posteriorly beyond gastral apex but not extending anteriorly under mesosoma (Figs 2, 4, 28, 30).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Female. Body ≈1280-1290 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in length, excluding section of ovipositor exserted beyond apex of hypopygium. Colour. Generally brown (Fig. 4), with a few metallic reflections (an artefact of lighting?) on gaster. Gaster at base and most parts of legs lighter brown to white. Wings hyaline, with venation light brown. Head. Head about 1.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high and 1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as high as long; in lateral view with anterior surface convex, receding strongly from ventral margin of eye to mouth opening, and bulging medially compared to laterally (at preorbital groove); posterior surface slightly, evenly convex (Fig. 4). Face about as wide as high (Fig. 5), without subantennal grooves; preorbital groove ventral to torulus straight then, more ventrally, slightly curving medially to ventrolateral margin of mouth opening. Torulus in slight triangular depression about 2.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as high as torulus width and separated by 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
torulus width from transverse trabecula (Fig. 5). Vertex in lateral view (Fig. 11) sloping obliquely to transverse trabecula to form an obtuse angle with face, and vertex posteriorly merging smoothly into occiput medially but separated laterally from occiput by short transverse vertexal suture. Ocellar triangle raised slightly above level of rest of vertex, the mid ocellus almost vertical, the lateral ocelli oblique, facing posterolaterally; ocelli with POL about 2.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
LOL and about 1.26 OOL. Transverse trabecula separated at each apex from supraorbital trabecula (Fig. 5); preorbital trabecula (apparently absent because not sclerotized) short, extending to inner orbit at about dorsal margin of torulus (Fig. 5); supraorbital trabecula in 2 subequal sections, the posterior sections slightly converging and the sutures outside posterior sections continuing onto occiput as the occipital grooves (short lines each appearing as posterior extension of supraorbital suture and strongly converging towards occipital foramen) (Fig. 6) separating occiput medially from temple dorsolaterally. Occiput separated from vertex by vertexal suture, this only present laterally behind lateral ocelli (Fig. 12). Eye large with numerous (about 100) small facets, in lateral view slightly higher than wide (10:9) and clearly separated dorsally from back of head (temple about 0.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
eye width). Ocular apodeme fairly long, crooked, needle-like. Malar sulcus absent (Fig. 11). Gena at level of ventral margin of eye wider than malar space. Occiput entire, not separated by transverse groove into upper and lower portions (Fig. 6a). Mouthparts. Labrum with 2? setae; mandible with 3 teeth. Antenna. Scape about 2.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, with radicle distinct from rest of scape and about 0.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
total scape length (Fig. 13); pedicel about 2.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, almost as wide and about 0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as entire scape; funicle 8-segmented; clava 2-segmented (Figs 3, 7, 14), 1.08
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as apical funicle segment and 0.32
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.36×">-0.36x</normalizedToken>
as long as entire funicle. Mesosoma. Mesosoma about 2.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, 2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as high and 1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high. Pronotum entire (Figs 9, 12, 15), in dorsal view clearly visible, medially about 0.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as mesoscutum; collar almost horizontal, with a shallow median longitudinal impression and prominent angular shoulders; neck shorter than collar, posteriorly strongly sloping up to collar; in lateral view, pronotum rectangular, slightly overlapping anterior margin of mesoscutum, with lateral surface merging smoothly into dorsal surface, with a shallow, oblique impression for femur. Spiracle (Figs 17, 18) apparently slightly stalked, at posterolateral angle of pronotum in a slight depression and facing dorsolaterally. Propleura near anterior apex not quite abutting, then gap widening slightly more anteriorly. Prosternum rhomboidal, incompletely divided medially by faint longitudinal groove posteriorly. Mesoscutum about 1.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as scutellum, in dorsal view with shallow, thin, slightly diverging notauli apparently absent posteriorly (Figs 9, 15, 16), in lateral view mesoscutum (Fig. 4) almost flat except anteriorly. Scutellum slightly wider than long; anterior scutellum about 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as narrowly trapezoidal, transverse frenum and separated from it by a shallow, curved frenal depression (Figs 9, 16); campaniform sensilla small, slightly closer to lateral margins of anterior scutellum than to each other, with apex of large, cone-shaped fenestra projecting anteriorly between them (Fig. 9). Axilla slightly advanced, the transscutal articulation laterally forming an obtuse angle with median section (Fig. 16); axillula long and narrow, separated from anterior scutellum by posteriorly recurved axillular groove; mesophragma widely convex posteriorly, extending to posterior apex of propodeum. Prepectus probably spindle-shaped (Fig. 17, partly hidden by fore leg); mesopleuron somewhat rectangular, with shallow depression separating mesepisternum from mesepimeron (Fig. 17). Metanotum with distinct lens-shaped dorsellum (only visible Fig. 9, a cleared, slide mount) and lateral panel length (toward hind wing articulation) about half length of dorsellum (Fig. 16). Metapleuron triangular, with a narrow anterior extension almost to base of hind wing, the margin at junction with mesopleuron deeply concave and posterior margin straight and vertical. Propodeum with a complete longitudinal groove medially, in lateral view weakly sloping, almost in same plane as dorsellum, in dorsal view with faint median longitudinal groove. Propodeal spiracle facing dorsolaterally in a slight depression and separated from anterior margin of propodeum by about its own diameter. Wings. Fore wing (Figs 4, 8, 19) wide, with completely transparent membrane sparsely scattered with minute microtrichia. Venation complete; submarginal vein with 1 subbasal seta and about 16 bullae, the most apical one at level of proximal macrochaeta (Fig. 8); parastigma, 0.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
submarginal vein length; marginal vein present, its length (from distal macrochaeta) about 2.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of parastigma; stigmal vein short but distinct, curving away from wing margin (Fig. 20) then closely paralleling it, with 4 apical campaniform sensilla (Fig. 21b); postmarginal vein present, about 0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long and as thick as marginal vein, with 4 microchaetae along anterior margin; hypochaeta absent (Fig. 8) but one similar to it originating on parastigma (Fig. 20a); proximal campaniform sensillum near posterior margin of marginal vein just beyond apical macrochaeta (far removed from the 4 campaniform sensilla on stigmal vein). Hind wing (Fig. 8) with membrane not extending to base of wing, relatively wide medially, tapering gradually almost to a point apically. Fore wing membrane with one irregular row of microtrichiae basally and two or three distally. Legs. Profemur and metafemur narrow (Fig. 17), metafemur widest, about 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as mesofemur. Tarsi 5-segmented. Calcar (moveable protibial spur) apparently without setae along outer margin, and with the inner tine about 0.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer tine. Middle and hind legs with tarsomere 1 shorter than tarsomere 2. Metasoma. About 2.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, 2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as high and 0.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high; its length, excluding exserted part of ovipositor, about 2.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
that of mesosoma (Fig. 4). Petiole ring-like, about 0.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide. Gastral terga apparently with fine longitudinal wrinkles except gt7; gt1 shorter than remaining terga and apparently gt6 the longest tergum, gt7 apically acutely triangular. Cercus a distinctly raised, longer than wide, peg-like plate, with 4 setae (Figs 22, 25). Gt6 with spiracle minute (apparently absent). Hypopygium extending posteriorly well beyond level of cercus (Figs 4, 23, 25). Ovipositor sheath exserted beyond gastral apex by about one third of its total length and abruptly upturned apically, apparently without subapical seta (Figs 22, 24).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Male. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="host">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Hosts and habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Hosts are unknown. The holotype was collected in forest (
<bibRefCitation author="Girault, AA" journalOrPublisher="Memoirs of the Queensland Museum" pageId="42" pageNumber="43" pagination="154 - 169" title="Australian HymenopteraChalcidoidea - II. Second supplement." volume="3" year="1915">Girault 1915</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>