<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784" ID-GBIF-Dataset="30d1c76a-41e1-4f66-9fb5-460bf381f752" ID-GBIF-Taxon="150814492" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-700-1" ID-ZBK="EBA4322720AD4CFFA04E8D2542DDA3D6" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F944B84B-6574-443C-8C68-8BE3DCFDAAD3" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-700-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 700" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the ant genus Melophorus (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)" checkinTime="1506009303549" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Heterick, Brian E., Castalanelli, Mark &amp; Shattuck, Steve O." docDate="2017" docId="D0E09528F08BF7412F8A3550774E619E" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 700: 1-420" docOrigin="ZooKeys 700" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784" docTitle="Melophorus gracilipes Heterick, Castalanelli &amp; Shattuck, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="F944B84B-6574-443C-8C68-8BE3DCFDAAD3" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="129" lastPageNumber="130" masterDocId="FF93E60CA711CB7BFF95D521FFFDFF9A" masterDocTitle="Revision of the ant genus Melophorus (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)" masterLastPageNumber="420" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="125" pageNumber="126" updateTime="1643555798786" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the ant genus Melophorus (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Heterick, Brian E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Castalanelli, Mark</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Shattuck, Steve O.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>700</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>420</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-700-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">EBA4322720AD4CFFA04E8D2542DDA3D6</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">EBA4322720AD4CFFA04E8D2542DDA3D6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="150814492" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F944B84B-6574-443C-8C68-8BE3DCFDAAD3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D0E09528F08BF7412F8A3550774E619E" lastPageId="129" lastPageNumber="130" pageId="125" pageNumber="126">
<subSubSection pageId="125" pageNumber="126" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="125" pageNumber="126">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/F944B84B-6574-443C-8C68-8BE3DCFDAAD3" authority="Heterick, Castalanelli &amp; Shattuck" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus gracilipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="125" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gracilipes">Melophorus gracilipes Heterick, Castalanelli &amp; Shattuck</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="125" pageNumber="126">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="125" pageNumber="126" type="types">
<paragraph pageId="125" pageNumber="126">Types.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="125" pageNumber="126">
Holotype minor worker (bottom ant-slightly damaged) from Yamarna Homestead 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-28.166666">28°10'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="123.666664">123°40'E</geoCoordinate>
, Western Australia, 16 December 1996-30 January 1997, S. Richardson, Acacia woodland with spinifex, sandy loam [ANIC32- 032240] (ANIC). Paratypes: major worker and media worker on same pin and with same details as holotype (ANIC); 2 media workers from 55 miles E of Wiluna, Western Australia, 10 October 1969, McInnes &amp; Dowse (ANIC); major worker and 2 minor workers from Murchison River, Western Australia, ' 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus bagoti" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="125" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bagoti">Melophorus bagoti</taxonomicName>
Lubbock, Det. J.J. McAreavey, 7 January 1960 [sic] [these specimens can easily be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="125" pageNumber="126" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
by the the two rows of spines on the metatibia-BEH] (BMNH); 2 media workers from 10 km SE Karonie, Western Australia, 9 November 1969, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Key’s">Key's</normalizedToken>
field notes. Trip 163, Stop 19405.6, ground strays, evening, sclerophyll wood., R.W. Taylor (MCZ); Major worker and minor worker from 30 km S of 'The 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Overlander’">Overlander'</normalizedToken>
, Western Australia, 20 March 1987, B. Heterick, soil, native vegetation, rural environment, 183, 8MelBH1 (WAM); 2 minor workers from Rabbit Proof Fence Road 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-30.449165">30°26'57&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="118.52028">118°31'13&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, Western Australia, 21 November 2009, Heterick, B.E., Laterite sandplain, proteaceous heathland with small trees, by hand, early pm [JDM32-004618] (WAM).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="127" lastPageNumber="128" pageId="125" pageNumber="126" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="125" pageNumber="126">Other material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="127" lastPageNumber="128" pageId="125" pageNumber="126">
Western Australia: 100 km E Wiluna (Forrest, J.), 10 mi SE Karonie (Taylor, R.W.), 11 mi E Meekatharra (McInnes &amp; Dowse), 13 mi SE Giles (McInnes &amp; Dowse), 16 mi S Leonora (McInnes &amp; Dowse), 16 mi W Coonana (Key, K.), 18 mi SE Agnew (McInnes &amp; Dowse), 30 km S of 'The 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Overlander’">Overlander'</normalizedToken>
(Heterick, B.E. [JDM32-001951]), 30 mi E Paynes Find on Sandstone Road (Douglas, A. 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="125" pageNumber="126" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
&amp; 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="125" pageNumber="126" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
J.), 31 mi SW Mundiwindi (McInnes &amp; Dowse), 4 mi W Mt Charles (McInnes &amp; Dowse), 55 mi E Wiluna (McInnes &amp; Dowse), 60 km N Ajana (Upton, 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="125" pageNumber="126" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
S.), 7 mi 
<pageBreakToken pageId="126" pageNumber="127" start="start">WSW</pageBreakToken>
Manunda Road House (McInnes &amp; Dowse), Ethel Creek (Varris, P.A.), G. J. Rd, 108 km E Carnarvon (Heterick, B.E. [M310]), Geeraning Rock (Heterick, B.E. [JDM32-001950]), Kanka water hole, near Warburton (Heatwole, H. &amp; Greenslade, P.J. 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="126" pageNumber="127" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
), Lyndon River (Mercer, R.), Mardathuna Rd turnoff (Heterick, B.E. [M08]), 
<pageBreakToken pageId="127" pageNumber="128" start="start">Meekatharra</pageBreakToken>
(Mercovich, C.), Mulga, NE Goldfields (Pringle, H.J.R. [ANIC32-029629]), Mullewa, Murchison River (Greaves, T.), nr Pamellia Hill (Heterick, B.E. [M178]), Pannawonica Hill (Bokhari, F. [M150]), Rabbit Proof Fence Rd. (Heterick, B.E. [JDM32-004618]), Sandstone Rd turnoff (Heterick, B.E.[M168/M169/M170]), Tardun (Mercovich, C.), Wiluna, Yamarna Homestead (Richardson, S.).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="127" pageNumber="128" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus gracilipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gracilipes">Melophorus gracilipes</taxonomicName>
is a member of the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. aeneovirens" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" rank="species" species="aeneovirens">M. aeneovirens</taxonomicName>
species-group (in full-face view, the anterior clypeal margin convex, apron-like and covering whole or part of the retracted mandible, except in 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. nemophilus" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" rank="species" species="nemophilus">M. nemophilus</taxonomicName>
, the medial clypeal sector often produced so that it is protrusive when seen in profile; the psammophore frequently with coarse and well-separated ammochaetae, these always placed on or just above anterior margin; in profile, the propodeum elongate and oblique or broadly rounded). The ant is also placed as a member of the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
complex because of the acuminate appearance of the midpoint of the anterior clypeal margin. In full-face view, the psammophore occurs as a row of long, thick setae set slightly above the anterior clypeal margin. Unlike its sister species, 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. gracilipes" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" rank="species" species="gracilipes">M. gracilipes</taxonomicName>
has just two rows of preapical tibial spines on the metatibia.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="128" lastPageNumber="129" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">Minor worker description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="128" lastPageNumber="129" pageId="127" pageNumber="128">
Head. Head approximately oval, sides of head divergent towards mandibular articulations; posterior margin of head extended posteriad as a convex, sloping surface with a slight medioccipital protuberance; frons matt or with weak sheen, microreticulate or microreticulate-shagreenate; frons consisting exclusively or almost exclusively of well-spaced, appressed setae only (small, erect setae, if present, usually confined to ocular triangle or posterior margin of head). Eye moderate (eye length 0.20-0.49 length of side of head capsule); in full-face view, eyes set above midpoint of head capsule; in profile, eye set anteriad of midline of head capsule; eyes elliptical or slightly reniform. In full-face view, frontal carinae straight or weakly convex, or straight, convergent posteriad; frontal lobes curved toward antennal insertion. Anteromedial clypeal margin convex, weakly acuminate anteromedially; clypeal psammophore set below midpoint of clypeus, or set at or just above anterior clypeal margin; palp formula 6,4. Five to six mandibular teeth in minor worker; mandibles triangular, weakly incurved; third mandibular tooth distinctly shorter than apical tooth and teeth numbers two and four; masticatory margin of mandibles approximately vertical or weakly oblique. Mesosoma. Integument of pronotum, mesonotum and mesopleuron moderately shining and shagreenate throughout; anterior mesosoma in profile convex anteriad, mesonotum often slightly overlapping pronotum, mesosoma planar or slightly sinuate posteriad; erect pronotal setae absent; in profile, metanotal groove shallow, broadly V or U-shaped; propodeum shining and uniformly striolate; propodeum always smoothly rounded; propodeal dorsum and declivity confluent; erect propodeal setae always absent; appressed propodeal setulae short, separated by more than own length and inconspicuous; propodeal spiracle situated at least twice its width from the declivitous face of propodeum, and shorter (length &lt;0.50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
height of propodeum). Petiole. In profile, petiolar node a broadly right angled triangle with steeply declivitous posterior face; in full-face view, shape of petiolar node uniformly rounded, or square with rounded angles; node shining and faintly striolate and microreticulate. Gaster. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="128" pageNumber="129" start="start">Gaster</pageBreakToken>
shining, shagreenate ('LP 
<normalizedToken originalValue="record’">record'</normalizedToken>
appearance); pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced short, inconspicuous, appressed setae only, erect setae always absent. General characters. Colour variable, pale yellow to brown.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="128" pageNumber="129" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="128" pageNumber="129">Major worker description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="128" pageNumber="129">
Head. Head square; posterior margin of head planar or weakly convex; cuticle of frons matt or with weak sheen, microreticulate; frons consisting exclusively or almost exclusively of well-spaced, appressed setae only (small, erect setae, if present, usually confined to ocular triangle or posterior margin of head). Eye small (eye length less than 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of head capsule); in full-face view, eyes set above midpoint of head capsule; in profile, eye set anteriad of midline of head capsule; roughly ovoid, eye narrowed posteriad. In full-face view, frontal carinae straight or weakly convex, or straight, convergent posteriad; frontal lobes straight in front of antennal insertion, or curved inward in front of antennal insertion. Anterior clypeal margin convex, acuminate anteromedially, margin entire; clypeal psammophore set below midpoint of clypeus, or set at or just above anterior clypeal margin; palp formula 6,4. Five mandibular teeth in major worker; mandibles triangular, weakly incurved; third mandibular tooth distinctly shorter than apical tooth and teeth numbers two and four; masticatory margin of mandibles approximately aligned vertically or weakly oblique. Mesosoma. Integument of pronotum, mesonotum and mesopleuron with weak to moderate sheen, shagreenate on pronotum and dorsum of mesonotum, otherwise microreticulate; anterior mesosoma in profile broadly convex, or convex anteriad, mesonotum overlapping pronotum, planar or slightly sinuate posteriad; erect pronotal setae absent; in profile, metanotal groove shallow, broadly V- or U-shaped; propodeum shining and finely striolate and microreticulate; propodeum angulate, propodeal angle blunt; length ratio of propodeal dorsum to its declivity between 1:1 and 1:2; erect propodeal setae absent; appressed propodeal setae short, separated by more than own length and inconspicuous; propodeal spiracle situated at least twice its width from the declivitous face of propodeum, and shorter (length less than 0.50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
height of propodeum). Petiole. In profile, petiolar node narrowly conical, vertex sharply defined, or a broadly right angled triangle; in full-face view, shape of petiolar node generally rounded with median indentation; node shining and faintly striolate and microreticulate. Gaster. Gaster shining with superficial microreticulation; pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced short, inconspicuous, appressed setae only, erect setae always absent. General characters. Colour concolorous light orange or russet with brown gaster.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="128" pageNumber="129" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="128" pageNumber="129">Measurements.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="128" pageNumber="129">Worker (n = 8): CI 101-120; EI 15-21; EL 0.29-0.44; HL 1.36-2.54; HW 1.38-3.04; ML 2.44-4.11; MTL 2.47-2.84; PpH 0.21-0.47; PpL 1.04-1.70; SI 89-153; SL 2.11-2.69.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="129" lastPageNumber="130" pageId="128" pageNumber="129" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="128" pageNumber="129">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="129" lastPageNumber="130" pageId="128" pageNumber="129">
Superficially, this large species resembles large members of the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. aeneovirens" pageId="128" pageNumber="129" rank="species" species="aeneovirens">M. aeneovirens</taxonomicName>
complex, but the appearance of the clypeus is sufficient to place it in the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="128" pageNumber="129" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
complex, and genetic sequencing data confirms this placement. The ant can easily be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="128" pageNumber="129" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
by its more gracile appearance and the presence of two rows of preapical spines on the metatibia (five rows in 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="128" pageNumber="129" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
). As with 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="128" pageNumber="129" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
, the colour of the gaster in this taxon can vary from yellowish orange and con 
<pageBreakToken pageId="129" pageNumber="130" start="start">colorous</pageBreakToken>
with the rest of the ant to an iridescent black, with various shades in between. (In the case of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. bagoti" pageId="129" pageNumber="130" rank="species" species="bagoti">M. bagoti</taxonomicName>
, nest series of the most strikingly bicoloured ants seem to be of the one colouration, but workers of other nests can nonetheless show variation in colour between light orange gaster and blackish-orange gaster morphs). A specimen of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. gracilipes" pageId="129" pageNumber="130" rank="species" species="gracilipes">M. gracilipes</taxonomicName>
collected in the Pilbara had the iridescent black gaster, but unfortunately the genetic similarity of this form compared with other, lighter-coloured morphs could not be tested due to poor DNA quality.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="129" pageNumber="130">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus gracilipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="129" pageNumber="130" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gracilipes">Melophorus gracilipes</taxonomicName>
is definitely an ant of the arid and semi-arid areas, and is absent from the wetter parts of the southern coastline. On the mainland all records have come from WA, although it likely also occurs in western parts of the NT and SA. As with other common species in the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. aeneovirens" pageId="129" pageNumber="130" rank="species" species="aeneovirens">M. aeneovirens</taxonomicName>
species-group, 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. gracilipes" pageId="129" pageNumber="130" rank="species" species="gracilipes">M. gracilipes</taxonomicName>
has been found in a wide range of phytogeographic zones including hummock grasslands, mulga woodlands, acacia woodlands with spinifex, and sclerophyll woodlands. Red clay soil seems to be a favoured substrate for its nests. This species is a scavenger: a couple of workers hand collected near Pamellia Hill, WA, were carrying a dead grasshopper.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="129" pageNumber="130" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="129" pageNumber="130">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="129" pageNumber="130">
Latin 
<taxonomicName lsidName="gracilis" pageId="129" pageNumber="130" rank="species" species="gracilis">gracilis</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘slender’">'slender'</normalizedToken>
) plus pes (
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘foot’">'foot'</normalizedToken>
); adjective in the nominative singular.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="129" pageNumber="130">
<paragraph pageId="129" pageNumber="130">
Figure 24. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus gracilipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="129" pageNumber="130" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gracilipes">Melophorus gracilipes</taxonomicName>
sp. n.: major worker paratype (ANIC32-032240-top ant) frons (a), profile (b) and dorsum (c); minor worker (ANIC32-032240-bottom ant) holotype frons (d), profile (e) and dorsum (f); distribution map for the species (g).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>