<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5063840" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9bb2fc2c-bb1a-4739-ab2f-a0461642308a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116523" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5063840" ModsDocAuthor=" &amp; Clark, J." ModsDocDate="1930" ModsDocID="6104" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf" ModsDocTitle="New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species." checkinTime="1264892749103" checkinUser="claudia" docAuthor="Clark, J." docDate="1930" docId="7106D6A6B5B7C7380C229F7026F53121" docLanguage="en" docName="6104_tx1.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria 43" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf" docTitle="Ponerinae Clark, 1930, n. sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="12" lastPageNumber="7" masterDocId="9882AE8990DDB183F966C81C08BF69C4" masterDocTitle="New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species." masterLastPageNumber="25" masterPageNumber="2" pageNumber="6" updateTime="1643596530053" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Clark, J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1930</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>2</mods:start>
<mods:end>25</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6104</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5063840" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116523" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5063840" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:7106D6A6B5B7C7380C229F7026F53121" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7106D6A6B5B7C7380C229F7026F53121" lastPageNumber="7" pageNumber="6">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="6">
Subfamily 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2261" lsidName-HNS="Ponerinae Lepeletier" pageNumber="6" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Ponerinae">PONERINAE</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:138746" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Acanthoponera" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Acanthoponera nigra Clark" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigra">Acanthoponera nigra</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="6">Worker.-Length, 2.7-3 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="7" pageNumber="6">
Black. Mandibles brown. Scapes and tarsi blackish brown. 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="7">Head</pageStartToken>
, thorax and node opaque. Mandibles coarsely punctate. Head finely, longitudinally, striate-rugose on the middle, more reticulate-punctate on the sides. Pronotum finely reticulate-punctate. Mesonotum, epinotum and node and postpetiole more coarsely so. Declivity and gaster finely and densely punctate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="7">Hair reddish, long and erect, abundant throughout, shorter and suberect on the antennae and legs. Pubescence reddish, rather long and coarse, particularly on the gaster.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="7">Head longer than broad, as broad in front as behind, the occipital border straight, the sides parallel, feebly convex, the angles rounded. Frontal carinae short, not as long as their distance apart, overhanging the antennal insertions in front. Clypeus convex above, the anterior border broadly convex. There is a strong carina extending from the anterior border of the clypeus to the occipital border. Eyes convex, placed at the posterior two-thirds of the head. Scapes extending slightly beyond the hind margin of the eyes; first segment of the funiculus three times longer than the second, the others subequal to the apical, which is longer than the two preceding together. Mandibles triangular, armed with five or six sharp teeth. Thorax one and a half times longer than broad. Pronotum one and two-third times broader than long, convex in front and on the sides. Suture between the mesonotum and epinotum very feebly defined. Mesonotum almost twice as long as broad. Epinotum fully twice as broad as long, the posterior border strongly concave, the angles produced. Declivity concave, with a distinct median furrow below, margined above and on the sides. Node one and two-third times broader than long, the anterior border and sides strongly convex, posterior border straight, or very feebly convex; in profile twice as high as long, parallel, the anterior, posterior and dorsal faces straight, the angles feebly rounded. There is a long, strong tooth in the middle of the under surface. This is continued in front, by a translucent membrane, as a plate-like projection. - Postpetiole slightly broader than long, strongly convex in front and on the sides. There is a strong constriction between the postpetiole and first segment of the gaster, the latter slightly broader than long. Legs short and stout.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="7">Habitat.-Victoria: Mt. William, Grampians (J. Clark).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="7">The colour and pilosity separate this from the other known species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>