<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.315.5593" ID-GBIF-Dataset="be524423-5b19-4e85-8908-08588493a22d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152045971" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-315-77" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:53BA8B47-3BC3-4AD1-9B5F-1CBD5F9F34DB" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-315-77" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 315" ModsDocTitle="Neogosseidae (Gastrotricha, Chaetonotida) from the iSimangaliso Wetland Park, KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa" checkinTime="1451247150633" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Todaro, M. Antonio, Perissinotto, Renzo &amp; Bownes, Sarah J." docDate="2013" docId="1C2765F18C0B97B97BAFDF505753084A" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 315: 77-94" docOrigin="ZooKeys 315" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.315.5593" docTitle="Kijanebalola devestiva Todaro, Perissinotto &amp; Bownes, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="53BA8B47-3BC3-4AD1-9B5F-1CBD5F9F34DB" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="87" masterDocId="3455C67BFF965369FFC8FF915401EE4C" masterDocTitle="Neogosseidae (Gastrotricha, Chaetonotida) from the iSimangaliso Wetland Park, KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa" masterLastPageNumber="94" masterPageNumber="77" pageId="2" pageNumber="79" updateTime="1643694220585" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Neogosseidae (Gastrotricha, Chaetonotida) from the iSimangaliso Wetland Park, KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Todaro, M. Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Perissinotto, Renzo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bownes, Sarah J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>315</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>77</mods:start>
<mods:end>94</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.315.5593</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.315.5593</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-315-77</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">234E4514-3079-43C6-A333-45324E675C02</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152045971" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:53BA8B47-3BC3-4AD1-9B5F-1CBD5F9F34DB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1C2765F18C0B97B97BAFDF505753084A" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="2" pageNumber="79">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="79" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="79">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:53BA8B47-3BC3-4AD1-9B5F-1CBD5F9F34DB" family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="2" pageNumber="79" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="79">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-6
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="79" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="79">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="79">
Roadside freshwater pond near 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Charter’s">Charter's</normalizedToken>
Creek, Lake St Lucia, Western Shores, iSimangaliso Wetland Park, South Africa (Lat. 28°15'19&quot;S; Long. 32°23'37&quot;E; Table 1, Figure 1S).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="79" type="type specimens">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="79">Type specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="79">
Holotype: adult specimen 267 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
long shown in Figure 2, no longer extant (International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, Articles 73.1.1 and 73.1.4).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="80" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="80" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">Thirteenspecimens (including the holotype) collected by the first author (10 from pond A and 3 from pond B, see Table 1). Seven specimens were observed alive and are not longer extant, while six were prepared for SEM analysis and are kept in the meiofauna collection of the first author (Ref. n. 2013-SA-01-02).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="80" type="ecology">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">Ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">Above silty substratum, among vegetation.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="80" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">
A 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="3" pageNumber="80" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
with an adult length to 310 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; body roughly barrel-shaped with head weakly separated from trunk and the rounded-off posterior end exhibiting medially a group of five spines; head with a pair of 26 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
long, club-like tentacles and a shallow cephalion; cuticular covering mostly smooth, except for a tiny patch of small triangular, keeled scales on the ventral side at the rear trunk; locomotor cilia arranged in tufts and interrupted bands on the head and 4 paired transverse bands along the trunk; three pairs of 14-16 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
long sensory bristles on the dorsal side, at U12, U22 and U92; mouth 13 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in diameter, slightly protruding down forward and reinforced internally by 17-20 thick, longitudinal ridges; pharynx up to 67 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, consisting of anterior spherical and posterior nosecone-shaped bulbs; PhIJ at U27; intestine straight, with anterior portion embracing the posterior portion of the pharynx; one pair of conspicuous protonephridia located adjacent to the intestine, from the PhIJ to about mid-body; parthenogenetic.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="80" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">The specific name devestiva (from the Latin, devestivus, undressed), alludes to the general absence of cuticular ornamentations, such as scales and spines that cover the body of other congeneric species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="86" pageId="3" pageNumber="80" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="80">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="81" pageId="3" pageNumber="80">
This description is mainly based on an adult specimen, 267 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in total length (TL, posterior spines excluded). The body is roughly barrel-shaped with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="81" start="start">the</pageBreakToken>
head weakly separated from the trunk by a slight neck constriction and the posterior trunk region rounded-off, without paired lateral projections but exhibiting medially a group of five spines. Body widths at the head/neck/trunk/caudum are 57/55/90/32 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, at U09/14/52/97, respectively. The head is provided with a pair of club-like tentacles projecting antero-laterally; they are 26 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in length and insert ventro-laterally at U07; the hypostomion is absent; a shallow cephalion (10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
4.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
) is appreciable only under SEM (Figure 5C). Under dissecting microscope, the animals appear swimming slowly in a rectilinear direction, with some following loose helicoidal trajectories. When purposely stimulated with a needle, specimens react by escaping aside, but never retracting the head inside the body; by contrast, most of the fixed specimens appear to have the head retracted to some extent (Figure 6A).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="82">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="82" start="start">Cuticular</pageBreakToken>
armour. The body is covered by a smooth cuticle, except for a minute patch of keeled scales located on the ventral side of the posterior trunk region, at U93 (Figures 1B, 2E). The scales, arranged in 5-7 columns of 3-5 scales each, are very small (ca 1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
) and may go undetected under light microscopy (DIC); when observed with a scanning electron microscope, they appear roughly triangular in shape and their keel continues in a proportionally long spiny process (Figure 6C). Five robust terminal spines, 15-24 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in length, ornate the posterior end of the trunk; they are inserted dorsally to the anus (Figure 6B, D).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="82">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="82">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="5" pageNumber="82" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
sp. n. schematic drawings. A Dorsal habitus B Ventral habitus, showing some internal structures. a anus alt antero-lateral tuft of cephalic cilia asb anterior sensory bristle ce cephalion ct cephalic tentacle dlvb lateral band of cephalic cilia extending dorsally and ventrally e egg I-IV, first to fourth band of trunk ciliature mvb median ventral band of cephalic cilia pcl proximal canal cell lumen PhIJ pharyngeo-intestinal junction ps patch of keeled scales psb posterior sensory bristle tsp terminal spines vlt ventro-lateral band of cephalic cilia.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="82">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="82">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="5" pageNumber="82" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
sp. n. DIC photomicrographs. A habitus B, C close-up ventral view of theanterior region showing the ciliary bands D close-up ventral view of the mid-trunk region showing the second ciliary bands E close-up ventral view, of the posterior region, showing the fourth ciliary bands (arrowheads) and the residual patch of spined scales (arrow).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="83">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="83" start="start">Ciliation</pageBreakToken>
. Locomotory cilia are arranged in tufts and interrupted bands around the head and paired transverse bands along the trunk (Figures 1, 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–E">A-E</normalizedToken>
, 5A, B). Most of the cephalic cilia have a ventral or ventro-lateral distribution; however, a precise organization is difficult to see due to their high density and relatively long span (16-18 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in length). From anterior to posterior end, it is possible to discern the following groups: a pair of antero-lateral tufts, a median ventral band, a pair of lateral bands extending ventrally and dorsally, followed by a pair of ventro-lateral tufts (Figure 1). The trunk ciliature consists of four pairs of oblique short bands, with first (U32) and fourth (U94) inserted dorso-latero-ventrally, the second (U59) inserted latero-ventrally and the third (U66) latero-dorsally (Figures 1, 2D, E, 5A).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="6" pageNumber="83">
Three pairs of sensory bristles (14-16 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in length) are present on the dorsal side at U12, U22 and U92, respectively (Figures 1A, 4B, C). The bristles of the first two 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="84" start="start">pairs</pageBreakToken>
emerge from round pits, while posterior bristles originate directly from the cuticle and are flanked by two anteriorly-converging keels. Presence of additional sensory bristles hidden among the cephalic locomotor ciliation cannot be excluded.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="84">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="7" pageNumber="84" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
sp. n. DIC photomicrographs. A habitus of a gravid specimen B close-up view of the inside egg with the shell bearing spine-like ornamentation (arrowheads).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="84">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="7" pageNumber="84" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
sp. n. DIC photomicrographs. A habitus of a subadult specimen showing developing egg (arrow) B close-up dorsal view of the posterior trunk region showing the two sensory bristles (arrow-heads) C close-up dorsal view of the anterior trunk and neck regions, showing two pairs of sensory bristles.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="85">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="85" start="start">Digestive</pageBreakToken>
tract: The strong mouth ring is terminal and about 13 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in diameter; it appears slightly protruding down forward and is reinforced inside by 17-20 thick longitudinal cuticular ridges, which protrude externally and bend on the outer contour (Figure 5). The pharynx is 64 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in length and shows anterior and posterior bulbs separated by a noticeable constriction; the anterior bulb, deprived of cuticular reinforcement, is roughly spherical (28 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
24 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
), while the posterior one (30 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
40 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
) is more nosecone-shaped (Figures 1, 4A); PhIJ is at U27. The intestine is straight; in the adult it appears impressively filled with green material (Figures 2A, 3A) while in juveniles it is packed with translucent globules (Figure 4A). Peculiarly, the anterior portion of the intestine extends forward encircling a large part of the posterior portion of the pharynx (about half the length of the posterior bulb), resulting in this region much wider than the pharynx itself (36 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
); at the PhIJ and for a short tract the intestine is about as wide as the pharynx (28-30 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
), then it widens again reaching a maximum width of 45 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
at about mid-body (U52); after this point the gut progressively narrows until it joins the 5-6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
sub-terminal anus at U97 (Figures 1, 6B, C).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="85">
Nephridial system. There is a pair of conspicuous protonephridia adjacent to the intestine; each protonephridium occupies an area extending from the PhIJ to about mid-body (U27-U53) and includes a clearly visible tubular canal containing two vibrating flagella, corresponding to the proximal canal cell lumen of 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieneke, A" journalOrPublisher="Zoomorphology" pageId="14" pageNumber="91" pagination="1 - 20" title="Ultrastructure of protonephridia in Xenotrichula carolinensis syltensis and Chaetonotus maximus (Gastrotricha: Chaetonotida): comparative evaluation of the gastrotrich excretory organs." volume="127" year="2008 a">Kieneke et al. (2008a)</bibRefCitation>
. This canal is about 25 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in length and runs almost parallel to the intestine, slightly converging towards the gut with its posterior portion (see Appendix: Figure 2S).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="85">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="85">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="8" pageNumber="85" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
sp. n. SEM photomicrographs. A habitus in a ventro-lateral view; note the arrangement of the first, second and third ciliary bands on the trunk region (number and arrows) B anterior region of a different specimen in a frontal view C close-up view of the mouth ring and cephalion (arrows).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="85">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="85">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="8" pageNumber="85" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
sp. n. SEM photomicrographs. A anterior region of specimen with head partially retracted inside the body (ventral view) B posterior trunk region of different specimen, showing the fourth ciliary band and the anus (arrow) C close-up view of the posterior end showing the anus (arrow) and the residual patch of spined scales (arrows) D close-up view of the posterior end (dorsal view), showing theterminal spines and the sensorial bristles (arrows).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="85">Reproductive tract. All the adult specimens were in parthenogenetic phase, with respective eggs at different stages of development.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="86">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="86" start="start">Variability</pageBreakToken>
and remarks. The largest adult was about 310 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in total length (terminal spines excluded) and was carrying a very big egg inside (73 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
107 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, Figure 3A). Remarkably, the egg shell was ornated with spikes (Figure 3B); this is quite surprising because in freshwater 
<taxonomicName authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Gastrotricha" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gastrotricha" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="86" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Gastrotricha</taxonomicName>
the shell ornamentation is believed to appear only after the egg has been laid, probably due to osmotic differences between the external vs internal milieu (
<bibRefCitation author="Hummon, MR" journalOrPublisher="Zoomorphologie" pageId="14" pageNumber="91" pagination="33 - 41" title="Reproduction and sexual development in a freshwater gastrotrich. 1. Oogenesis of parthenogenic eggs (Gastrotricha)." url="10.1007/BF00312169" volume="104" year="1984">Hummon 1984</bibRefCitation>
). The smallest animal was about 183 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in total length and had no recognizable female gametes inside. Oocytes became appreciable as such in a 230 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
long specimen (Figure 4A).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="9" pageNumber="86" type="taxonomic affinities">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="86">Taxonomic affinities.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="9" pageNumber="86">
The general body appearance, the presence of club-shaped cephalic tentacles and the planktonic lifestyle that characterise 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="87" start="start">Kijanebalola</pageBreakToken>
devestiva
</taxonomicName>
sp. n. suggest that the closest affiliation of the South African specimens lies with the 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" lsidName="" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" rank="family">Neogosseidae</taxonomicName>
. Notwithstanding this, autoapomorphic traits of the new species make somewhat difficult its affiliation to any of the two currently recognized genera, 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
, based on their current diagnosis (see 
<bibRefCitation pageId="10" pageNumber="87">Kisielewski 1991</bibRefCitation>
). For instance, the size of the South African worms exceed by far that of any other possible keen (max length 310 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
vs 200 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
spp., vs 210 in 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
spp.) and the body covering, made for most part of smooth cuticle, is a characteristic so far unknown among species of 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
or 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
. The presence in the new species of a single cephalic plate (i.e., the cephalion), combined with the structure of its mouth and pharynx, complicate further its taxonomic affiliation at generic level. However, in our opinion, some of the differences between the anatomical traits of the iSimangaliso gastrotrichs and those highlighted in the diagnosis of 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
or 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
no longer hold. Regarding 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
, for instance, the diagnosis: 1) is ambiguous about the presence of cephalic plates (i.e., cephalion and hypostomion reported as undetected); and 2) includes the mouth as consisting of two-segmented units (mouth units = internal cuticular ridges). A re-evaluation of these characteristics, especially in light of the new information gained by 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieneke, A" journalOrPublisher="Microcosmos" pageId="14" pageNumber="91" pagination="139 - 146" title="Eine interessante Teilgruppe der Suesswassergastrotrichen (Bauchharlinge): Neogosseidae und Dasydytidae." volume="96" year="2007">Kieneke and Riemann (2007)</bibRefCitation>
on German specimens of 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
(reported as 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea voigti" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="voigti">Neogossea voigti</taxonomicName>
(Daday, 1905) allows for the amendment of the generic diagnosis of 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
in both these aspects. More specifically, the specimens studied by 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieneke, A" journalOrPublisher="Microcosmos" pageId="14" pageNumber="91" pagination="139 - 146" title="Eine interessante Teilgruppe der Suesswassergastrotrichen (Bauchharlinge): Neogosseidae und Dasydytidae." volume="96" year="2007">Kieneke and Riemann (2007)</bibRefCitation>
under differential interference contrast and scanning electron microscopy show: 1) the hypostomion and 2) the mouth units as unsegmented. Considering that in 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" lsidName="" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" rank="family">Neogosseidae</taxonomicName>
the presence of a cephalion may be elusive (as reported above for the new species) we conclude that the presence/absence of the cephalic plates and the structure of the mouth and pharynx cannot be considered diagnostic characters at genus level (i.e., useful to distinguishing 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
from 
<taxonomicName genus="Kijanebala" lsidName="Kijanebala" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" rank="genus">Kijanebala</taxonomicName>
and vice versa); rather, peculiarities in these traits and others such as the presence/absence of cuticular reinforcements in the anterior pharyngeal bulb, may help differentiate among species (i.e., they are species specific).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="87">
Another potential difference between the two genera i.e., the presumed ability of 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
species to partially retract the head inside the body, can also be dismissed. Our observations with the new species demonstrate that retraction of the head is actually an artefact due to fixation (see above). Consequently, none of the above reported traits may be used to allocate our specimens to either of the two genera.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="87">
In summary, only a single character is apparently left to differentiate 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
; it pertains to the structure of the posterior part of the trunk, which appears truncate with a pair of postero-lateral projections, each provided with a tuft of relatively long spines in 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Neogossea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neogossea" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Neogossea</taxonomicName>
, but rounded-off with a median group of spines in 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
. As the difference in this character between species of the two genera is consistent, it is reasonable to use it as diagnostic feature and as a solid synapomorphy for each genus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="87">
Consequently, based on the round shape of the posterior trunk region of the iSimangaliso specimens, we propose that their closest affiliation is to the genus 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="genus">Kijanebalola</taxonomicName>
. Therefore, the large size, the cuticular ornamentation reduced to an epaulet of scales on the ventral side of the trunk ending, and the number and size of the terminal spines are considered autoapomorphic characters that can easily distinguish 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola devestiva" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="devestiva">Kijanebalola devestiva</taxonomicName>
sp. n. from 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola dubia" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="dubia">Kijanebalola dubia</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName family="Neogosseidae" genus="Kijanebalola" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kijanebalola canina" order="Chaetonotida" pageId="10" pageNumber="87" phylum="Gastrotricha" rank="species" species="canina">Kijanebalola canina</taxonomicName>
. Emended diagnoses are reported below.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>