<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280263" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120202" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280263" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="54F028DAD80DD842F27AFA7ADA2A2780" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys odacon Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="691" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="691" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280263" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120202" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280263" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:54F028DAD80DD842F27AFA7ADA2A2780" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/54F028DAD80DD842F27AFA7ADA2A2780" lastPageNumber="691" pageNumber="691">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="691">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155870" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys odacon Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys odacon Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="691" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="odacon">Strumigenys odacon Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="691">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 2.1, HL 0.51, HW 0.39, CI 77, ML 0.22, MI 44, SL 0.31, SI 78, PW 0.25, AL 0.52. Characters of scotti-complex. Mandibles in full-face view short, outer margins shallowly and evenly convex. Upper scrobe margin evenly and shallowly convex in full-face view, not bordered by a rim or flange, the eyes visible. Maximum diameter of eye approximately equal to maximum width of scape, with 3 ommatidia in longest row. Scape subcylindrical, curved and narrowed near base; hairs on leading edge slender, slightly flattened or spoon-shaped apically. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with erect to suberect filiform ground-pilosity. Upper scrobe margin fringed with sharply curved hairs which are flattened or spoon-shaped apically and are similar in size to, or slightly larger than, those on leading edge of scape. Cephalic dorsum with 6 standing filiform hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate. Mesonotum with two pairs of filiform hairs: a pair on the anterior margin and a shorter more posteriorly situated pair. Propodeum with one pair of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines which are more or less as long as spines. Ground-pilosity on dorsal pronotum as on head, pilosity inconspicuous on remainder of alitrunk. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and more or less flat posteriorly. Metanotal grove shallowly impressed. Anterior mesonotum without a conspicuous carina above the mesothoracic spiracle; mesopleural gland set in a small circular notch. Propodeal tooth triangular, lamellate, pointed apically, and subtended by a very narrow lamella that is continuous down the declivity. Pronotal dorsum longitudinally striolate with superficial punctulate sculpture. Mesonotal and propodeal dorsum reticulate-punctate. Side of pronotum superficially longitudinally striolate. Pleurae and side of propodeum glassy smooth and peripherally punctulate. Postpetiole disc with superficial longitudinally striolate sculpture. In profile ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle a well developed curtain that is continuous along the base of the peduncle and equal or greater in depth than the maximum diameter of eye. Basigastral costulae well developed and sharply defined, radiating on each side of a broad central clear area. Dorsal surface of petiole, postpetiole, and gaster with standing filiform hairs which are slightly thickened apically. Colour light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="691">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 2.0 - 2.2, HL 0.48 - 0.51, HW 0.37 - 0.41, CI 76 - 81, ML 0.22 - 0.25, MI 44 - 0.51, SL 0.29 - 0.31, SI 72 - 78, PW 0.23 - 0.25, AL 0.51 - 0.54 (9 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="691">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 40 km. S Ambalavao, Res. Andringitra, 22 Â° 13 ' S, 46 Â° 58 ' E, 1275 m., 15. x. 1993, sifted litter (leaf mold rotten wood), montane rainforest # 793 (50) - 8 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ). Paratypes. 9 workers and 2 ergatogynes with same data as holotype but coded (14) - 9, (29) - 7, (30) - 8, (35) - 5, (37) - 8, (42) - 10, (46) - 4 5 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="691">
See notes under 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155862" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys glycon Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys glycon Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="691" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="glycon">glycon</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155865" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys langrandi Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys langrandi Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="691" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="langrandi">langrandi</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>