<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/evolsyst.3.33580" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8428659a-8c4a-4aef-9ee7-851c1b4923d1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157251818" ID-Pensoft-Pub="2535-0730-1-29" ID-ZBK="DDCF7E3DE7354974A0C8A0A804FF3CCD" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D0F1B3CA-D1E6-49C3-8E2F-77973244E9E6" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="2535-0730-1-29" ModsDocOrigin="Evolutionary Systematics 3 (1)" ModsDocTitle="New Echiniscidae (Heterotardigrada) from Amber Mountain (Northern Madagascar)" checkinTime="1558621744125" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gasiorek, Piotr &amp; Voncina, Katarzyna" docDate="2019" docId="2C451FE3B13DDD53560891CDF855E8DC" docLanguage="en" docName="EvolutSyst 3(1): 29-39" docOrigin="Evolutionary Systematics 3 (1)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/evolsyst.3.33580" docTitle="Echiniscus succineus Gasiorek &amp; Voncina, 2019, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docUuid="D0F1B3CA-D1E6-49C3-8E2F-77973244E9E6" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="34" masterDocId="FFDEA962FFE4FFD01249FFCB9A6BF673" masterDocTitle="New Echiniscidae (Heterotardigrada) from Amber Mountain (Northern Madagascar)" masterLastPageNumber="39" masterPageNumber="29" pageId="0" pageNumber="29" updateTime="1643496015553" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New Echiniscidae (Heterotardigrada) from Amber Mountain (Northern Madagascar)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gasiorek, Piotr</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Voncina, Katarzyna</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Evolutionary Systematics</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>29</mods:start>
<mods:end>39</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/evolsyst.3.33580</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/evolsyst.3.33580</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">2535-0730-1-29</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DDCF7E3DE7354974A0C8A0A804FF3CCD</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DDCF7E3DE7354974A0C8A0A804FF3CCD</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="157251818" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D0F1B3CA-D1E6-49C3-8E2F-77973244E9E6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2C451FE3B13DDD53560891CDF855E8DC" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="34" pageId="0" pageNumber="29">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="29" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="29">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/D0F1B3CA-D1E6-49C3-8E2F-77973244E9E6" class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus succineus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="0" pageNumber="29" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="succineus">Echiniscus succineus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="29">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 2, 3, 4, 5, Tables 2, 3
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="30" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="30">
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="30" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="30">Holotype (adult female on the slide MG.005.05) and sixteen paratypes (slides MG.005.04-7, including two voucher exoskeletons preserved after DNA extraction on the slides MG.005.28-29 and two specimens on the SEM stub no. 17.11). Except for two paratypes (slide MG.005.04) deposited in the Natural History Museum of Denmark, University of Copenhagen, the entire type series deposited in the Institute of Zoology and Biomedical Research, Jagiellonian University, Poland.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="30" type="locus typicus">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="30">Locus typicus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="30">
Lowland rainforest close to the road from Joffreville (Diana Region, Antsiranana Province, Northern Madgascar); coordinates and altitude: 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-12.513611">12°30'49&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="49.182224">49°10'56&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
; 993 m asl. Substratum: moss growing on a tree branch (ca. two metres above ground level); collection: December 2018 by W. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Witaliński">Witalinski</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="30" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="30">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="30">
Small representative of the 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus spinulosus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="1" pageNumber="30" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="spinulosus">Echiniscus spinulosus</taxonomicName>
group with peculiarly complex dorsal plate sculpturing developed as thick epicuticular ridges on scapular, paired segmental and caudal plates. Spines in almost all lateral and dorsal trunk positions. Parthenogenetic.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="31" pageId="1" pageNumber="30" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="30">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="31" pageId="1" pageNumber="30">
Adult females and juveniles. Body dark yellow and plump. Red eyes present, dissolved after mounting. External cirri not markedly longer than internal cirri, with swollen cirrophores (Fig. 3C). Primary and secondary clavae (cephalic papillae) of similar lengths. Cirrus A short (cirrus A/body length ratio below 20%), with short and poorly marked cirrophore. Trunk appendage configuration (B)-C-Cd-D-Dd-E in adults (Figs 2, 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
), reduced to (Cd)-Dd-E in juveniles. All appendages in form of spines of similar lengths, spines Dd and E more robust, and sometimes gently serrated or rough (Figs 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
). Asymmetry in the development of appendages frequent, one of the spines B almost always absent, more rarely one of the spines C and D absent. Dorsal plates with rather irregularly distributed, large to very large pores (
<taxonomicName lsidName="spinulosus" pageId="1" pageNumber="30" rank="species" species="spinulosus">spinulosus</taxonomicName>
type; Figs 2, 3). Dark endocuticular rings variously developed: from barely visible on the central portions of median plates (Fig. 3A) to well-developed rings present in pores from different plates (Figs 3B, 4A); they are the 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="31" start="start">elements</pageBreakToken>
of sponge-like endocuticular layer visible under SEM (Fig. 3D, 4B). The level of development of the rings is not associated with life stage, and some individuals do not exhibit intraporal rings. Cephalic plate large, halved, with scarce and minute pores (Figs 2, 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
). Cervical (neck) plate present, poreless and developed as grey rectangular belt adjacent to the anterior margin of the scapular plate (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
). Scapular plate with the system of thick epicuticular extensions, dividing its surface into clearly defined areas of thinner cuticle, being lighter under PCM and slightly concave under SEM (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
). Median plates 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
large and uniformly dark under PCM, the first and the third plate are unipartite, whereas the second one is bipartite, with its anterior portion being a poorly developed, narrow triangle (Figs 2, 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
). At the posterior margins of median plates 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–II">I-II</normalizedToken>
and paired plates, irregular epicuticular thickenings may be present, especially in larger animals (compare Figs 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
, D). Each of paired plates indistinctly divided by a thin smooth band into a narrow anterior portion with condensed epicuticular matrix, and a larger posterior portion with more complex ornamentation pattern. The proximal part of each posterior portion is thick similarly to the anterior portion, but more distal one is thinner, with reduced and less numerous pores (Figs 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
, D). Marginally, a single dark epicuticular belt is present, and the second belt appears more centrally (Fig. 3A), however, sometimes it is not discernible (Fig. 3B). Caudal (terminal) plate with typical incisions, rarely sclerotised as if being a prolonged extensions of spine E (Fig. 3B). Its epicuticular ornamentation is similar in form to that occurring on the scapular plate (Figs 2, 3A), but may be less developed (Fig. 3B, 3E).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
Figure 2. Habitus of adult females of 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus succineus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="2" pageNumber="31" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="succineus">Echiniscus succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov.: A - holotype, dorsal view (PCM); B - paratype, dorsal view (SEM); C - paratype, lateral view (PCM, insert with the claws of the second leg pair, black arrowhead indicates spur); D - paratype, lateral view (SEM). White arrowheads point out spine on the first leg. Scale bars: in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
Figure 3. Detailed sculpturing of the dorsal plates of 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus succineus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="2" pageNumber="31" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="succineus">Echiniscus succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov.: A - paratype, dorsal view (PCM, arrowheads indicate epicuticular thickenings); B - paratype, smaller specimen, dorsal view (PCM); C - scapular plate (SEM); D - portion of the second paired segmental plate (SEM); E - caudal plate (SEM). Roman numerals signify lateral ornamented belts. Scale bars: in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
Ventral plates absent, but simple granulation covers the entire venter from the subcephalic to genital zone. Endocuticular pillars minute and not-differentiated in size. Pedal plates and pulvini absent. Spine on the first leg pair minuscule (Figs 2A, 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–D">C-D</normalizedToken>
, 5A), either in the form of usual triangle or blunt (Fig. 2A). Dentate collar on the fourth leg pair present, with short teeth similar in shape (Figs 2, 3B). Papilla on the fourth leg pair present (Figs 2, 3B). External claws spurless, but internal ones bear acute spurs inserted at ca. 20-25% of the claw branch and directed downwards (Figs 2C, 5). Claws IV longer than claws 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
Figure 4. Endocuticular (intraporal) rings of 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus succineus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="2" pageNumber="31" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="succineus">Echiniscus succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov.: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–">A-</normalizedToken>
median plates I and II (PCM); B - central portion of the second paired segmental plate (SEM). Scale bars: in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">
Figure 5. Claws of 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus succineus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="2" pageNumber="31" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="succineus">Echiniscus succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. (SEM): A - first leg pair (small spine I visible in the upper right corner); B - fourth leg pair. Scale bars: in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">Larvae and eggs. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="32" pageId="2" pageNumber="31" type="dna barcodes">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">DNA barcodes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="31">Four genetic markers were represented by single haplotypes. The 18S rRNA sequence (898 bp long, GenBank accession no. MK675903):</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="32" start="start">GATAACTGTGGTAATTCTAGAGCTAATACATGCAGTAAGCCTTGACCTTTACCGGCAAGGCGCAGTTATTAGATCAAAA</pageBreakToken>
ACCAATCGGTTGTGTCTTCGGATGCAGCCGTTAGCTTGGTGACTCTGAGTAACCACAGCGAACCGTATGGCCTCGTGCTC GACGGTCTGTCAGTCAAGCAACTGCCTTATCAGCTTGTTGTTAGGTTATATGCCTAACAAGGCTTCAACGGGTAACGAAC GATCGGGGTCGGATATCGGAGAGGGAGCTTGAGAAACGGCTACCACTTCCAAGGAAGGCAGCAGGCGCGCAAATTACCCA CTCTCGGCATGAGGAGGTAGCGATAAAATGTATCGATGCGGGGCCATTAGTGCCTTCGTAATCGGAATGAGTACACTTTA AATCCTATAACAAGGACCTATTGGAGGGCAAGTCTGGTGCCAGCAGCCGCGGTAATTCCAGCTCCAATAGCGTATATTAA TGCTGCTGCGGTTAAAAAGCTCGTAGTCGGATCTGGGTTACCGGCGGGTACCGCATGTTGCTTCACGCAGCATGTTGTGT ACTATACGTGTCGCTTCGGCGGCACTGCCAGTGTAATTGTGCCTCACGTAGGTACGTTACGCTGGTCGCCGGAACCACGA GCCGGGTTGAGCAGCATGCTCTTAATTGAGTGTGTTGTTTACTCGGTGCGTTTACTTTGAAAAAATTGGAGTGCTCAAAG CAAGCGTACAGTCGCTATGCGGCTTGAACAGTGGTGCATGGAATAATGGAATAGGGCCTCGGTTCTATTTTGTTGGTTTT AAGATATCGAGGTAATGATTAAGAGGGACAGACGGGGACGTTTGTATTGCGACGTTAGAGGTGAAATTCTTGGATCGTCG CAAGACACACTAATGCGAA
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">The 28S rRNA sequence (767 bp long, GenBank accession no. MK675914):</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">GCTGGACTTAAGCATATTAATAAGCGGAGGAAAAGAAACCAACAGGGATATTCTCAGTAACGGCGAGTGAAGAGAATAcA GCCCAGCGCTGAATCATACTGCTTGCAAGAGTAGTACGACATGTAGCGTGAAACTGGCGGCTGTTGATGTTGTCGATGCGT GTAAGTCTTCTTGATTGAGGCTCAGTCCCAGAGATGGTGCTAGGCCCGTATCGCGCGTGACAAGTACAGCAACGCCCGCTT GTGGAGAGTCAGGTTGTTTGGGAACACAATCTAAAGCCGGTGGTACACTCCATCGAAGGCTAAATATGGCCACGAGTCCGA TAGCGAACAAGTACCGTGAGGGAAAATTGAAAAGCACTTTGAAGAGAGAGCGAAATAGTGCGTGAAACCGCTTAGAGGCAA GCAGATGGATTCTCGAAGGTGTGCATAGGATTTATTTCCTAGTTCTCACGCCACCGCTGTTGTTGACGTGCACCATACGCT GACATTTGGACGCTTGAGATTGGGACTCGTGCCTGCTTGAGCTGCTCGGTGTCGGACGTATTGAGTTGATTCGTGGCATGC GATAACAGAGCAGAGCATTTGTCGTCGCTGTAAAGCGCTGACTGTGGCCGCTTGCTGATGCATTGTTGTTGTGGCAAGGCG CAAGCTTTGACATGCGATATGTATTGCAACTCGGCTATTAGTACCGGCAAGACGACTTCAAGACTCGGTGGCGAGTAGACG AACTTCCATCTAACCCGTCTTGAAACACGGACCAAGGGA</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">The ITS-2 sequence (442 bp long, GenBank accession no. MK675925):</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">GGTTTTCTGAACGTTAATTCTTCTAACGCAAATTGCAGCTGTGATTTTAGTCGCAGCTACGCCCGGTTGAGGGTCAGTTG ATCATAAACTCGCTTGTAACTGTTGTAACTACAAGCGCATTGGCTGTTCACATTGACTGCTTCAATGCGGCTGATGTGTTA GCTCAAATTGCCAAGCTGCCAACAAAGCAGTTTCGGATTTCTTGTTATGTATGCTGCTCTAGCAGGTCGTTGTTTGTCAGT ACTATGCACTGCTTCAAGATTATTGTGCGTGCTGACAAAGCTGCGTATGTGTGCGGCAGACAGCATGCGGACCAGTCGTTC GCATGACTCGTCTCTAACGGCATTTGCTTCTCATACACATATAACAAACCAATCATTTTTGTGACCTCAACTCGGACGAGA CTACCCGCTGAATTTAAGCATATCAATAAGCGGAGGAA</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">The cox1 sequence (614 bp long, GenBank accession no. MK649675):</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">TACTTTATATTTTTATTTTTTGGTTTATGGGCTGCTTCTGTTGGTTCAAGTTTAAGGTTTTTAATTCGAACTGAATTATC TCAACCAGGAATTTGGTTAGGCGACGAGCATTTATATAATGTCTTAGTTACTTCCCATGCTTTAATTATAATTTTTTTTAT GGTAATACCAATCTTAATTGGTGGTTTTGGTAATTGATTAATTCCTATTATAATTGGTGCCCCGGATATGTCATTTCCTCG AATAAATAATTTAAGTTTTTGGCTTTTACTACCTTCTTTGCTTTTGCTATTGATTTCTTCTAATATTAGATCTGGTGTGGG CTCTGGTTGAACTTTATACCCACCTTTATCTGAATTTATTGGTCATTCTAATTATACTGTTGATATGGCTATTTTTTCTTT CCATGTTGCTGGTGCTTCTTCTATTTTAGGTGCTATTAATTTTATTACTACTATTTTGAATATACGTTTTTTTTCTTTAAA TATAGAACAGTTATCTTTATTTGTTTGATCTGTTTTGATTACTGCTATCTTACTAATTTTATCTTTACCTGTTTTAGCCGG CGGTATTACTATATTATTGTTAGATCGTAATTTTAATAGTTCTTTTTT</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="32">From Latin succineus = amber, referring to the locus typicus near Amber Mountain. An adjective in the nominative singular.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="33" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">
<taxonomicName genus="Comparative" lsidName="Comparative discussion" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="discussion">Comparative discussion</taxonomicName>
: This is the second known member of the 
<taxonomicName lsidName="spinulosus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="spinulosus">spinulosus</taxonomicName>
group with scapular, paired segmental and caudal (terminal) plates markedly ornamented. Similar system of epicuticular thickenings exists in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. ornamentatus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="ornamentatus">E. ornamentatus</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Gąsiorek">Gasiorek</normalizedToken>
&amp; Kristensen, 2018 described recently from Tanzania, but an adult specimen of 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. is easily distinguishable from the latter taxon based on: the appendage configuration (A-(B)-C-Cd-D-Dd-E in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs A-(B)-C-D-Dd-E in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. ornamentatus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="ornamentatus">E. ornamentatus</taxonomicName>
), the location of epicuticular ornamentation on the dorsal armour (except for the median plates, all trunk plates ornamented in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs only scapular and caudal plates ornamented in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. ornamentatus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="ornamentatus">E. ornamentatus</taxonomicName>
), and the pore morphology (very large pores, sometimes with endocuticular dark rings in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs minute pores, always without endocuticular dark rings in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. ornamentatus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="ornamentatus">E. ornamentatus</taxonomicName>
). The claws 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–IV">II-IV</normalizedToken>
and all claw spurs seem to be relatively longer in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. with respect to 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. ornamentatus" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" rank="species" species="ornamentatus">E. ornamentatus</taxonomicName>
(compare values from Table 2 with table 4 from 
<bibRefCitation author="Gasiorek, P" journalOrPublisher="Tropical Zoology" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" pagination="131 - 160" title="Echiniscidae (Heterotardigrada) of Tanzania and Uganda." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/03946975.2018.1477350" volume="31" year="2018">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Gąsiorek">Gasiorek</normalizedToken>
and Kristensen (2018)
</bibRefCitation>
), 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="33" start="start">but</pageBreakToken>
given the low number of collated individuals, these traits are not included in the differential comparison.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
Table 2. Measurements [in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
] of selected morphological structures of adult females (the 3rd and older instars) of 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus succineus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="succineus">Echiniscus succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. mounted in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hoyer’s">Hoyer's</normalizedToken>
medium. N - number of specimens/structures measured, Range refers to the smallest and the largest structure among all measured specimens; SD - standard deviation.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<table pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="2">Character</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="2">N</th>
<th colspan="6" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Range</th>
<th colspan="2" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Mean</th>
<th colspan="2" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">SD</th>
<th colspan="2" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Holotype</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<th colspan="3" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
</th>
<th colspan="3" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">sc</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">sc</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">sc</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">sc</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">internus</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">externus</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">A</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">A</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">B</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">C</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Cd</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">D</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Dd</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">E</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
Table 3. Measurements [in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
] of selected morphological structures of juveniles (the 2nd instar) of 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus succineus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="species" species="succineus">Echiniscus succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. mounted in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Hoyer’s">Hoyer's</normalizedToken>
medium. N - number of specimens/structures measured, Range refers to the smallest and the largest structure among all measured specimens; SD - standard deviation.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<table pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="2">Character</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="2">N</th>
<th colspan="6" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Range</th>
<th colspan="2" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Mean</th>
<th colspan="2" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">SD</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<th colspan="3" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
</th>
<th colspan="3" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">sc</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">sc</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">sc</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">internus</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">externus</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">A</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">A</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Cd</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">Dd</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<td colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rowspan="1">E</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
Three other species are similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. in overall morphology: 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. marginatus" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="marginatus">E. marginatus</taxonomicName>
Binda &amp; Pilato, 1994, 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. scabrospinosus" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="scabrospinosus">E. scabrospinosus</taxonomicName>
Fontoura, 1982 and 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. tropicalis" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tropicalis">E. tropicalis</taxonomicName>
Binda &amp; Pilato, 1995. 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. differs from:
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. marginatus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="marginatus">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="34" start="start">E</pageBreakToken>
. marginatus
</taxonomicName>
, reported from Hawaii Archipelago, by the appendage configuration (A-(B)-C-Cd-D-Dd-E in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs A-(C)-(D)-Dd-E in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. marginatus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="marginatus">E. marginatus</taxonomicName>
), and the morphology of posterior portions of median plates 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–II">I-II</normalizedToken>
(narrow and with irregular thickenings in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs broad, solid and poreless in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. marginatus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="marginatus">E. marginatus</taxonomicName>
, see 
<bibRefCitation author="Pilato, G" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" pagination="41 - 54" title="New description of Echiniscusscabrospinosus Fontoura, 1982, and description of a new species of Echiniscus (Heterotardigrada) from China." volume="1856" year="2008">Pilato et al. 2008</bibRefCitation>
);
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. scabrospinosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="scabrospinosus">E. scabrospinosus</taxonomicName>
, known from Western Palaearctic and Afrotropical realm, by the appendage configuration (A-(B)-C-Cd-D-Dd-E in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs A-(C)-(D)-Dd-E in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. scabrospinosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="scabrospinosus">E. scabrospinosus</taxonomicName>
), and the morphology of posterior portions of median plates 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–II">I-II</normalizedToken>
(with irregular thickenings in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs porous in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. scabrospinosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="scabrospinosus">E. scabrospinosus</taxonomicName>
, see 
<bibRefCitation author="Pilato, G" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" pagination="41 - 54" title="New description of Echiniscusscabrospinosus Fontoura, 1982, and description of a new species of Echiniscus (Heterotardigrada) from China." volume="1856" year="2008">Pilato et al. 2008</bibRefCitation>
);
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. tropicalis" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="tropicalis">E. tropicalis</taxonomicName>
, recorded from the Seychelles, by the appendage morphology (spines in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs very short, triangular spicules in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. tropicalis" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="tropicalis">E. tropicalis</taxonomicName>
), and spurs on the internal claws IV (identical to spurs on internal claws 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. vs larger and better developed spurs IV, more divergent from the claw branches than on internal claws 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
in 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. tropicalis" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="tropicalis">E. tropicalis</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="5" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName genus="Comparative" lsidName="Comparative genetic" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="subspecies" species="genetic" subspecies="analysis">Comparative genetic analysis</taxonomicName>
: The uncorrected pairwise distances between 
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. succineus" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="succineus">E. succineus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. and the remaining 
<taxonomicName class="Heterotardigrada" family="Echiniscidae" genus="Echiniscus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Echiniscus" order="Echiniscoidea" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" phylum="Tardigrada" rank="genus">Echiniscus</taxonomicName>
spp. were as follows: (1) 18S rRNA - from 0.5% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. manuelae" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="manuelae">E. manuelae</taxonomicName>
da Cunha &amp; do Nascimento Ribeiro, 1962) to 2.5% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. testudo" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="testudo">E. testudo</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken originalValue="Doyère">Doyere</normalizedToken>
, 1840)); (2) 28S rRNA - from 2.7% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. manuelae" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="manuelae">E. manuelae</taxonomicName>
) to 6.1% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. testudo" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="testudo">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="35" start="start">E</pageBreakToken>
. testudo
</taxonomicName>
); (3) ITS-2 - from 17.6% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. testudo" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="testudo">E. testudo</taxonomicName>
) to 22.9% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. blumi" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="blumi">E. blumi</taxonomicName>
Richters, 1903); (4) cox1 - from 15.7% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. merokensis" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="merokensis">E. merokensis</taxonomicName>
Richters, 1904) to 18.5% (
<taxonomicName genus="E." lsidName="E. granulatus" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="granulatus">E. granulatus</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken originalValue="Doyère">Doyere</normalizedToken>
, 1840)).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>