<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.454.8558" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f5af9f55-0247-431c-8785-3560798260c8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152056349" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-454-41" ID-ZBK="59DD67E9ABBE4EE2A5DF3AF8D02A34E8" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-454-41" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 454" ModsDocTitle="The first sexual associations in the genus Darditilla Casal, 1965 (Hymenoptera, Mutillidae)" checkinTime="1451245121117" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Luz, David R. &amp; Williams, Kevin A." docDate="2014" docId="2F3AE80093DDC6EF445EC7D95C4B11D0" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 454: 41-68" docOrigin="ZooKeys 454" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.454.8558" docTitle="Darditilla debilis Gerstaecker 1874" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="52" masterDocId="19471237FF917736FFEB680C4740E262" masterDocTitle="The first sexual associations in the genus Darditilla Casal, 1965 (Hymenoptera, Mutillidae)" masterLastPageNumber="68" masterPageNumber="41" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" updateTime="1643523356883" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The first sexual associations in the genus Darditilla Casal, 1965 (Hymenoptera, Mutillidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Luz, David R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Williams, Kevin A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>454</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>41</mods:start>
<mods:end>68</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.454.8558</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.454.8558</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-454-41</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">59DD67E9ABBE4EE2A5DF3AF8D02A34E8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">59DD67E9ABBE4EE2A5DF3AF8D02A34E8</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152056349" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2F3AE80093DDC6EF445EC7D95C4B11D0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2F3AE80093DDC6EF445EC7D95C4B11D0" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="49" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Mutillidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="49" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
<taxonomicName authority="Gerstaecker, 1874" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1874" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Darditilla debilis (Gerstaecker, 1874)</taxonomicName>
Figs 5-6, 17-20
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="49" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
<taxonomicName authority="Linnaeus, 1758" authorityName="Linnaeus" authorityYear="1758" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Mutilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mutilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Mutilla debilis</taxonomicName>
Gerstaecker, 1874. Arch. Naturgesch. 40: 60. Holotype female, Brasil. mer, Sello. (ZMB, examined).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="49" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
Male. Males are similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla bejaranoi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bejaranoi">Darditilla bejaranoi</taxonomicName>
, but have a simply convex tegula, have the ventral impuctate lamella of the clypeus less produced than the preceding species (Fig. 5D), and have the apical and preapical teeth of the penis valve coalescent (Fig. 19).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Darditilla debilis</taxonomicName>
(Gerstaecker), male: A habitus, dorsal view B habitus, lateral view C head, dorsal view D head, anterior view E metasoma, dorsal view F T5, T6 and pydigium, dorsal view. Scale bars: 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
Female. The female of 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Darditilla debilis</taxonomicName>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla bejaranoi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bejaranoi">Darditilla bejaranoi</taxonomicName>
, but can be recognized by its reddish mesosoma, at most having reduced dark stains laterally (Fig. 6A); by its pygidium, which is densely granulate throughout (Fig. 6E); and by its S1, which has a weak darkened median longitudinal carina.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Darditilla debilis</taxonomicName>
(Gerstaecker), female: A habitus, dorsal view B habitus, lateral view C head, anterior view D metasoma, dorsal view E T5 and pydigium, dorsal view. Scale bars: 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="50" pageId="8" pageNumber="49" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
Male. Body length 5.7-8.4 mm. Coloration. Body and appendages black, except mandibles and metasoma dark brown apically. Tibial spurs white. Forewing slightly and uniformly infuscated between veins, veins brown; hindwing slightly infuscated. Body clothed with whitish setae, except disc of T2 and T7 with scattered brownish setae, mesoscutum, tegula, and T6 with dark brown setae, bristles of tergal fringes silver to pale yellowish. Head. Rounded posteriorly. Head width 1.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
pronotal width. Eye transversely ovate. Ocelli small; ocellocular distance 7.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of lateral ocellus, interocellar distance 3.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
lateral ocellus length. Occipital carina distinct, extending ventrally almost to level of oral fossa. Punctation on front dense, interspaces micropunctate; gena densely punctate, interspaces with sparse micropunctures; and vertex moderately punctate, interspaces glabrous. Gena ecarinate. Antennal scrobe broadly concave to eye margin, with transverse tubercle dorsally. Clypeus densely punctate, ventral margin produced as a short slightly upcurved transverse impunctate lamella. Flagellomere 1 1.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
pedicel length; flagellomere 2 1.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
pedicel length. Mandible convergent to bidentate apex, dorsal carina gradually becoming obsolete on inner tooth; edentate ventrally. Mesosoma. Epaulets weakly produced. Pronotal dorsum densely punctate; anterior face almost smooth; lateral face densely punctate. Tegula evenly convex, glabrous except with long recumbent setae anterolaterally and posteromesally. Mesoscutum with dense coarse punctures; posterolateral corner forming a small angulate lobe. Scutellum slightly convex, with coarse punctures. Axilla flat and punctate, except lateral margin with narrow vertical lamella. Metanotum surface obscured by dense shaggy mesally facing recumbent setae. Propodeum convex, broadly and deeply reticulate except smooth and shining adjacent to metapleuron. Mesopleuron moderately punctate, interspaces micropunctate. Metapleuron smooth and shining ventrally, setose and micropunctate dorsally. Wings. Forewing with moderate elongate sclerotized pterostigma; marginal cell broadly rounded and truncate apically; three submarginal cells, third scarcely delimited by obscure venation. Legs. Mid- and hind tibiae lacking strong spines, distinct apical secretory pore on inner surface near base of inner spur; spurs finely serrate on margins. Metasoma. T1 gradually broadened from base, not constricted apically, sessile with T2, 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of T2, sparsely punctate; apex with fringe of simple setae or thickened bristles. T2 with coarse to moderate punctures, interspaces smooth and generally broader than punctures; apex with fringe interspersed recumbent thickened parallel bristles; felt line 0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
lateral length of T2. T3-5 densely and finely punctate, covered with interspersed erect and recumbent setae, except fringes with row of bristles as in T2. T6 densely punctate, covered with less dense recumbent and erect setae. T7 coarsely and densely punctate, punctures uneven medially, appearing rugose; posterior half forming oval pygidium margined laterally and posteriorly by a strong sharp carina, apical margin rounded, surface flat, microgranulate with numerous large irregular transverse rugae. S1 punctate and setose, with medial longitudinal carina extending from base to apex. S2 moderately punctate. S3-6 moderately and finely punctate, with fairly sparse erect and recumbent setae. Lateral margins of S2-5 sometimes with similar bristles to those of T2-6. S7 transversely rectangular. Hypopygium coarsely punctate, posteromedial margin with two approximate weak teeth medially. Genitalia (Figs 17-20). Paramere tapering apically, slightly curved ventrally on basal half, dense setal brush on basoventral lateral margin, scattered setae along inner and lateral margins. Cuspis acute angulate apically, extending ~0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
free length of paramere, with densely setose oblique ventral surface. Digitus laterally compressed and rounded apically, extending ~0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
free length of paramere, asetose. Penis valve asetose, bidentate apically with apical and preapical tooth, basoventral margin slightly expanded apically as blunt tooth, basodorsal margin with slight tubercle.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="50" pageId="8" pageNumber="49">
Extended female diagnosis. Body length 4.8-10 mm. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="50" start="start">Coloration</pageBreakToken>
. Head and metasoma black. Mesosoma reddish, rarely with dark stains laterally. Appendages blackish, often reddish basally. Tibial spurs whitish. Vertex with arcuate transverse band of recumbent silver to golden setae, front and remainder of vertex with recumbent black setae; genal setae silver. Mesosomal dorsum with sparse erect black setae, except anterior margin pronotum with pale yellow setae. Posterior fringes of T1 and T2 black; T2 with lateral circular silver setal spots; T3-6 clothed with black setae basally and silver setae apically. Head. Transverse, posterior margin flat, occipital carina obscure. Head width 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
pronotal width. Eye slightly ovate transversely, ommatidia distinct. Front and vertex densely punctate; gena moderately punctate. Genal carina well-defined, extending nearly to hypostomal carina. Clypeus with transverse glabrous concavity, margined by dorsal and ventral carinae, between widely separated lateral teeth. Mandible slender, tapering, bidentate apically (subapical tooth minute, distant from apex and usually obliterated through wear), unarmed ventrally. Antennal scrobe with complete dorsal carina. Antennal tubercle punctate basally, with weak scratches on anterior face, glabrous dorsally. Scape simple, moderately punctate. Flagellomere 1 1.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
pedicel length; flagellomere 2 1.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
pedicel length. Mesosoma. Mesosomal length 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width. Mesosomal dorsum coarsely reticulate, propodeal reticulae broader and shallower. Lateral pronotal carina extending to epaulet, humeral angle with sharp obtuse angle. Mesopleuron finely densely punctate and setose, posterior margin defined by vertical carina. Metapleuron and lateral face of propodeum smooth and shining dorsally with isolated fine setae, micropunctate and densely setose ventrally. In dorsal view, mesosoma broadened to anterior third, strongly narrowed at propodeal spiracle, propodeum abruptly broadened. Scutellar scale lacking. Propodeum convex, dorsal and lateral faces not obviously differentiated. Legs. Foreleg with a few long strong articulated spines on posterior/lateral margins of tarsomeres. Mid- and hind tibiae each with two rows of prominent spines, 2-4 spines in each row; apical spurs finely serrated laterally. Hind tibia with distinct secretory pore on inner/posterior surface near base of inner spur. Metasoma. T1gradually broadened from base, not constricted apically, sessile with T2, 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as T2; anterior face moderately punctate and setose. T2 densely punctate and setose, punctures slightly larger and sparser anterolaterally; felt line broad, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as T2 laterally. T3-5 densely punctate. Pygidium broad and slightly convex, lateral margins defined by distinct weakly bowed carina, posterior margin rounded and defined by indistinct carina, densely granulate throughout. S1 punctate, with weak darkened median longitudinal carina. S2 densely punctate. S3-5 densely punctate. S6 moderately punctate.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="9" pageNumber="50" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="50">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="9" pageNumber="50">
Type material. Holotype: 'Brasil. mer\Sello.' (green label partially handwritten) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘6648’">'6648'</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘Type’">'Type'</normalizedToken>
(red label) 'Lectotypus\C.E. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Mickel’">Mickel'</normalizedToken>
(red label partially handwritten) [1 female: ZMB]. Other material. 92 males and 101 females as follows: ARGENTINA: Entre 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ríos">Rios</normalizedToken>
: XII.1996 (Liebig, Zelich) [4 females, 4 males: AMNH]; Missiones: Dos de Mayo, XII.1989 (Foerster) [1 male: AMNH]; Puerto Esperanza, XII.1976 (M.A. Fritz) [3 males: AMNH]; XII.1973 (M.A. Fritz) [19 males: AMNH]; BRAZIL: Minas Gerais: Belo Horizonte, Museu de 
<normalizedToken originalValue="História">Historia</normalizedToken>
Natural, 22.III.1998 (G.A.R. Melo) [1 female: DZUP]; 9 km E de Catas Altas, Serra da 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Caraça">Caraca</normalizedToken>
, 12.I.2012 (G.A.R. Melo) [1 female: DZUP]; 8 km S de Ouro Preto, Lago do 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Custódio">Custodio</normalizedToken>
, 20.I.2012 (G.A.R. Melo) [3 females: DZUP]; Serra do Caraca, S. Barbara, I.1970 (F.M. Oliveira) [1 male: EMUS]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Viçosa">Vicosa</normalizedToken>
, M. do Paraiso, 5.I.1995 (G.A.R. Melo) [1 female: DZUP]; same city, XII.1944 (Wygodzinsky) [1 female: MNRJ]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Paraná">Parana</normalizedToken>
: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Capitão">Capitao</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Leônidas">Leonidas</normalizedToken>
Marques, Salto Caxias, 6-13.X.2004 (Soares, E.D.G.) [3 males: DZUP]; same locality, 13-20.X.2004 (Soares, E.D.G.) [5 males: DZUP]; same 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="51" start="start">locality</pageBreakToken>
, 3-10.XI.2004 (Soares, E.D.G.) [12 males: DZUP]; Fazenda do 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Jordão">Jordao</normalizedToken>
, Posto Florestal, Salto Segredo, 6-10.X.2004 (Soares, E.D.G.) [1 male: DZUP]; Jaguatirica, Rio Capivari, 1.III.2003 (G.A.R. Melo) [1 male: DZUP]; Piraquara, Mananciais da Serra, 13.XII.2002 (Garcia, E.Q.) [2 males: DZUP]; same locality, 13.XII.2002 (Garcia, E.Q.) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 23.I.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 2.II.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 5.II.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 8.II.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 19.II.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 26.II.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [3 females: DZUP]; same locality, 27.II.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [2 females: DZUP]; same locality, 14.III.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [3 females: DZUP]; same locality, 3.IV.2003 (Garcia, E.Q.) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 27.I.2001 (G.A.R. Melo) [5 males: DZUP]; Ponta Grossa, Parque Estadual da Vila Velha, 5.IV.2013 (K.A. Williams) [12 females: DZUP]; same locality, 6.IV.2013 (K.A. Williams) [10 females: DZUP]; same locality, 11.XII.2000 (Ganho &amp; Marinoni) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 25.XII.2000 (Ganho &amp; Marinoni) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 11.III.2002 (Ganho &amp; Marinoni) [1 female: DZUP]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Prudentópolis">Prudentopolis</normalizedToken>
, 8.II.1970 (J.S. Moure) [1 female: DZUP]; Tibagi, XII.1952 (Justus) [1 female: DZUP]; Rio de Janeiro: Itatiaia: Faz. Penedo, II.1943 (Wygodzinsky) [1 female: MNRJ]; same city, 700m, XII.1954 (W. Zikan) [1 female: MNRJ]; Petropolis, IV.1952 (C. Novais) [1 female: MNRJ]; Rio Grande do Sul: Arroio Grande, 101m, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-32.216667">32°13'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-53.2">53°12'W</geoCoordinate>
, 9.IV.2004 (R.F. Kruger) [1 male: UFES]; Santa Catarina: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Criciúma">Criciuma</normalizedToken>
, Campus da UNESC, 16.XI.2002 (G.A.R. Melo) [1 male: DZUP]; Nova Teutonia, XI.1968 (F. Plaumann) [1 female: EMUS]; same locality, various dates (F. Plaumann) [16 females: MNRJ]; same locality, various dates (F. Plaumann) [3 females: YPM); same locality, XI.1968 (F. Plaumann) [2 males: YPM]; same locality, XII.1968 (F. Plaumann) [1 male: YPM]; same locality, XI.1980 (F. Plaumann) [1 female: DZUP]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="São">Sao</normalizedToken>
Paulo: Barueri, various dates (K. Lenko) [3 females: CASC]; same locality, V.1958 (K. Lenko) [1 female: MNRJ]; Batatais, I.1946 (J.S. Moure) [1 female: DZUP]; Cajuru, Fazenda Rio Grande, 2-18.XI.1999 (G.A.R. Melo &amp; Nascimento) [2 males: DZUP]; same locality, 17.XI-2.XII.1999 (G.A.R. Melo &amp; Nascimento) [3 males: DZUP]; same locality, 18.XII.1999-10.I.2000 (G.A.R. Melo &amp; Nascimento) [3 males: DZUP]; same locality, 10.I-1.II.2000 (G.A.R. Melo &amp; Nascimento) [4 males: DZUP]; Caraguatatuba, 1.III.1967 (M.E. Irwin) [1 female: CASC]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Cosmópolis">Cosmopolis</normalizedToken>
, 22.I.1974 (J.G. Rozen et al.) [3 females: EMUS]; Est. Biol. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Boracéia">Boraceia</normalizedToken>
, 850m, 27.II.1967 (M.E. Irwin) [2 females: CASC]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Estação">Estacao</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ecológica">Ecologica</normalizedToken>
de Jatai, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Luís">Luis</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Antônio">Antonio</normalizedToken>
, 22.IV.1999 (G.A.R. Melo) [1 female: DZUP]; same locality, 16.X.1999 (G.A.R. Melo) [3 females: DZUP]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Riberão">Riberao</normalizedToken>
Grande, P.E. Intervales: ponto 2, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-24.274721">24°16'29&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-48.42139">48°25'17&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 22.I.2010 (Perioto, N.W.) [2 males: MZSP]; same locality, 22.II.2010 (Perioto, N.W.) [1 male: MZSP]; same locality, 22.XII.2010 (Perioto, N.W.) [3 males: MZSP]; same locality, ponto 5, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-24.273056">24°16'23&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-48.42278">48°25'22&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 22.I.2010 (Perioto, N.W.) [2 males: MZSP]; same locality, 22.IV.2010 (Perioto, N.W.) [2 males: MZSP]; same locality, 22.XII.2010 (Perioto, N.W.) [2 males: MZSP]; same locality, 22.XI.2010 (Perioto, N.W.) [1 male: MZSP]; Parque Ainhanguera, 28.II.1986 (C. Costa) [1 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="52" start="start">female</pageBreakToken>
: MZSP]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="São">Sao</normalizedToken>
Jose dos Campos, XII.1934 (H.S. Lopes) [1 female: MNRJ]; same locality, 5-20.V.1999 (E.R. DePaula) [1 male: EMUS]; Teodoro Sampaio, P.E. Morro do Diabo, Estrada do Angelim, 16.II.1999 (G.A.R. Melo) [1 female: DZUP]; PARAGUAY: Alto Parana: Estancia Dimas, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-25.55">25°33'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-55.216667">55°13'W</geoCoordinate>
, 28-30.XI.2005 (U. Dreschel) [1 female: EMUS]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Canindeyú">Canindeyu</normalizedToken>
: Tava Yopoi, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-24.366667">24°22'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-55.883335">55°53'W</geoCoordinate>
, 26.X-4.XI.2007 (U. Dreschel) [1 female: EMUS]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Paraguarí">Paraguari</normalizedToken>
: La Rosada, 28-30.IV.2006 (U. Dreschel) [1 female: EMUS]; San Pedro: Rio Ypane, Cororo, various dates (Fritz) [2 females, 2 males: AMNH, EMUS]; URUGUAY, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Río">Rio</normalizedToken>
Negro: Arroyo Negro, 15 km S Paysandu, 27-31.XII.1962 (R.G. Van Gelder) [3 males: AMNH].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="52" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="52">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="52">This species apparently occurs throughout the forest and grassland regions of southern South America: Argentina, Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="52" type="host">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="52">Host.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="52">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="52" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="52">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="52">
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Darditilla debilis</taxonomicName>
is a widely distributed and common species. Over 200 additional specimens were examined in MZSP and others were studied from various North American collections.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="52">
Males are associated with 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Darditilla debilis</taxonomicName>
based on morphological similarity to 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla bejaranoi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bejaranoi">Darditilla bejaranoi</taxonomicName>
males and overlapping distribution with the females of 
<taxonomicName authority="Casal, 1965" authorityName="Casal" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Darditilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Darditilla debilis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="debilis">Darditilla debilis</taxonomicName>
, including five localities where both sexes were collected.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>