<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.424.7853" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8cef6776-788c-4ce7-812d-42469172d7f4" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152054128" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-424-101" ID-ZBK="04459A9484A642D4A44FED5C3B69A0BC" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FCE0859D-3AF2-42DC-BCBC-1D915779FD9D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-424-101" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 424" ModsDocTitle="Serendipity at the Smithsonian: The 107-year journey of Rhipidocyrtus muiri Falin &amp; Engel, new genus and species (Ripidiinae, Ripidiini), from jungle beast to valid taxon" checkinTime="1451245631770" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Falin, Zachary H. &amp; Engel, Michael S." docDate="2014" docId="FC3D557766D91F2910FB55A5B98CFFB1" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 424: 101-116" docOrigin="ZooKeys 424" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.424.7853" docTitle="Rhipidocyrtus muiri Falin &amp; Engel, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="FCE0859D-3AF2-42DC-BCBC-1D915779FD9D" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="112" masterDocId="FFFE8F03FFC8FFA112118434FFC7611E" masterDocTitle="Serendipity at the Smithsonian: The 107 - year journey of Rhipidocyrtus muiri Falin &amp; Engel, new genus and species (Ripidiinae, Ripidiini), from jungle beast to valid taxon" masterLastPageNumber="116" masterPageNumber="101" pageId="4" pageNumber="105" updateTime="1643661559619" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Serendipity at the Smithsonian: The 107 - year journey of Rhipidocyrtus muiri Falin &amp; Engel, new genus and species (Ripidiinae, Ripidiini), from jungle beast to valid taxon</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Falin, Zachary H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Engel, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>424</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>101</mods:start>
<mods:end>116</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.424.7853</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.424.7853</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-424-101</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">04459A9484A642D4A44FED5C3B69A0BC</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">04459A9484A642D4A44FED5C3B69A0BC</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152054128" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FCE0859D-3AF2-42DC-BCBC-1D915779FD9D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FC3D557766D91F2910FB55A5B98CFFB1" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="112" pageId="4" pageNumber="105">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="105" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="105" start="start">Taxon</pageBreakToken>
classification Animalia Coleoptera Ripiphoridae
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="105" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/FCE0859D-3AF2-42DC-BCBC-1D915779FD9D" authority="Falin &amp; Engel" authorityName="Falin &amp; Engel" authorityYear="2014" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Rhipidocyrtus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rhipidocyrtus muiri" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="105" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="muiri">Rhipidocyrtus muiri Falin &amp; Engel</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="4" pageNumber="105">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-15
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="105" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">
♂, USNM Type No. 41869, Department of Entomology, US National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC, USA; partially disarticulated, specimen preparation and labels distributed on two pins and three microscope slides as follows: first pin has only the original specimen labels; second pin contains the complete head, thorax, and poorly preserved portions of abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
mounted on a modified minuten (Fig. 1), the right elytron is glued to the minuten; first slide has the right antenna and left middle and hind legs; second slide has the left elytron, hind wing, and foreleg; third slide has the splayed abdomen and genitalia. Specimen labels read as follows [each preparation starts as a distinct paragraph, different lines of those labels separated by a slash (/) and separate labels by double slashes (//)]:
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Pin 1: No specimen parts: &quot;Borneo / 383&quot; // &quot;Rhipideus [sic]&quot; // &quot;This was left with Pierce / and after his leaving / Muir visited USNM / and got Schwarz to find / it. Then in 1928 Muir again / contacted us &amp; called attention / of H.S.B. but declined to take it back.&quot; [underside of last label reads] &quot;Found by / F. Muir / on flowers / P.T.O.&quot; // &quot;HOLOTYPE / Rhipidocyrtus / muiri / Z.H. Falin &amp; M.S. Engel&quot;.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Pin 2: Head, thorax, + basal abdominal segments, right elytron glued to minuten: &quot;F. Muir #383 / on flowers / Aug 1907 / Mowong / Borneo&quot; // &quot;Ripidius / muiri Bar. / U.S.N.M. / Type no. / 41869&quot; // &quot;SEMC1158329 / KUNHM-ENT&quot; // &quot;HOLOTYPE / Rhipidocyrtus / muiri / Z.H. Falin &amp; M.S. Engel&quot;.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Slide 1: &quot;muiri / Barber / antenna, middle &amp; hind leg / F. Muir #383 on flowers / Aug 1907 / Mowong Borneo. / Holotype No. 41869 U.S.N.M.&quot;.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Slide 2: &quot;Rhipidocyrtus / muiri / Barber / left wing elytron / &amp; front leg / F. Muir #383 on flowers / Aug 1907 Mwong Borneo / Type No. 41869 U.S.N.M.&quot;.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Slide 3: &quot;Rhipidocyrtus / muiri / Barber / ♂ genitalia / &amp; abd. seg. / spiracles nos. 3 (front) / 4, 5, &amp; 6. - Mwong Borneo / F. Muir / Type No. 41869 U.S.N.M.&quot;.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="105" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">As per the generic diagnosis above.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="4" pageNumber="105" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">
Male. Large, though difficult to measure given the longitudinally arched facies and the partial disarticulation; approximately 2.8 mm long in dorsal view from anterior margin of pronotum to posterior margin of metascutellum, approximately 2.2 mm wide at base of pronotum (although a gross approximation given the disarticulation involved, total length in life might approximate 6 mm); elytron length 2.4 mm; hind wing length 6.5 mm. Body nearly unicolorous brown (Figs 1-6); antennomere I similar in color to body, antennomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–XI">II-XI</normalizedToken>
lighter brown (Figs 1, 2) as are various subregions of the notum (e.g., posterolateral mesonotal angles). Elytra coriaceous, more or less translucent brown, darker along margins and with short, suberect setae (Fig. 7). Hind wing typical, very lightly pigmented at most (Fig. 8), but covered with microsetae giving an infuscate appearance and a reflective sheen.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="105">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">
Figures 7-12. Photographs of slide mounted structures from holotype male of 
<taxonomicName authority="Falin &amp; Engel, 2014" authorityName="Falin &amp; Engel" authorityYear="2014" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Rhipidocyrtus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rhipidocyrtus muiri" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="105" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="muiri">Rhipidocyrtus muiri</taxonomicName>
Falin &amp; Engel, gen. et sp. n. 7 Elytron 8 Hind wing 9 Right antenna 10 Foreleg 11 Mid-leg 12 Hind leg.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="107" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="106" start="start">Head</pageBreakToken>
subspherical (Figs 2, 4), slightly compressed dorso-ventrally (Fig. 3). Vertex weakly convex (Fig. 4), sloping uniformly to occiput, integument shining with indistinct punctation and weak, irregular, sculpturing. Dorsal and ventral aspects of head with suberect to erect setae. Compound eyes large (Figs 3, 4), coarsely faceted, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="107" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
erect setae dorsally; weakly convergent dorsally, strongly convergent ventrally, occupying nearly the entire ventral surface of the head (Fig. 3); two large post-ocular ommatidia present at posterolateral margins of compound eyes (Fig. 4). Frons obsolete between antennal bases and maxillary palpi, these structures dorsoventrally contiguous (Fig. 3). Maxillary palpi two-segmented, basal segments free, obliquely toroidal, apical segments approximately 3.5 to 4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of basal segments (Figs 3, 4), fusiform, broadest near base, with subapical, obliquely-depressed sensory pits.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="107">
Antennae consisting of 11 antennomeres; antennomere I stout (Fig. 3), asymmetrically cup-like, apical opening produced laterally; antennomere II irregularly toroidal, longest at midline, subequal to III; antennomere III similar in shape to II except strongly produced mesally (Fig. 2); antennomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–X">IV-X</normalizedToken>
with mesally facing rami (Figs 2, 9), bases of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–VI">IV-VI</normalizedToken>
longitudinally compressed, subequal, base of antennomere VII approximately 2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of antennomere VI; antennomere XI expanded, similar in shape to rami of previous segments (Fig. 9); antennae constructed such that rami VIII and IX nearly equal in apparent length, rami decreasing subequally in apparent length to either side, rami V shortest in apparent length; antennomeres I and II with moderately dense suberect setae similar to those of head, similar setae present on bases of antennomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–X">III-X</normalizedToken>
but diminish in length apically; rami of antennomeres with specialized sensory trichia beginning with mesal projection of antennomere III.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="107">
Pronotum with suberect to erect setae, integument shining, weakly, irregularly punctate; pronotum broadly bell-shaped in dorsal view (Fig. 2); anterior margin broadly excavate; anterolateral angles rounded, nearly obsolete, strongly deflected ventrally; posterior margin gently arcuate with a small medial projection, deflected dorsally (Fig. 1); posterolateral angles broadly rounded, projecting, slightly concave on surface and deflected dorsally; lateral margins evenly arcuate, converging anteriorly, strongly dorso-ventrally compressed, proplurae reduced, hidden in dorsal view. Pronotal disc with a raised medial tubercle at anterior margin and a weakly rounded medial carina extending posteriorly approximately 
<normalizedToken originalValue="¼">1/4</normalizedToken>
length of pronotum, gradually becoming obsolete, otherwise disc gently but irregularly convex laterally with two large but weak convexities near lateral margins, apparently demarcating internal articulation points of procoxae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="107">Mesonotum with suberect, posteriorly-facing setae, integument shining, very weakly punctate, appearing nearly glabrous; posterior margin weakly bisinuate with medial projection (Fig. 5), forming a broad but narrow mesoscutellum; posterolateral angles obtusely rounded, deflected dorsally; lateral and anterior margins obscured. Mesonotal disc gently but irregularly convex laterally (Fig. 2), with a large convexity on either side of midline near anterior margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">
Metanotum with scattered recumbent to suberect setae (many appear abraded on holotype specimen), integument shining, punctation variably weak and scattered to nearly obsolete with exception of metapostscutellum described below. Metascutum apparently divided into three regions - anteromedial box, anterolateral lobes, and posterolateral lobes (Figs 5, 6). Anteromedial box partially obscured medially by mesocutellum but appears to form a contiguous, narrow band separated posteriorly from posterolateral lobes by an arcuate impressed sulcus and laterally from anterolateral lobes by indistinctly impressed 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="108" start="start">longitudinal</pageBreakToken>
constrictions. Anterolateral lobes obliquely convex and themselves separated from obliquely convex posterolateral lobes by wide, deep and relatively setose impressions (Fig. 5). Metascutellum clearly delineated by a pair of oblique, deeply impressed sulci curved basally (Figs 5, 6), nearly linear anteriorly, converging to a single impressed medial sulcus terminating at apparent anterior metanotal margin (Fig. 5). Posterior margin of metascutellum straight in dorsal view (Fig. 5), gently convex dorsoventrally; metascutellar disc gently convex (Fig. 6) with a weak, rounded carina originating at apex, continuing approximately 1/3 length of metascutellum (Fig. 5), gradually becoming obsolete. Metapostscutellum a relatively narrow band positioned more or less dorso-ventrally, ventral and slightly anterior to posterior margin of metascutellum (Fig. 6), posterior margin of metapostscutellum strongly deflected dorsally (Figs 1, 6). Surface of metapostscutellum glabrous, impunctate except posterior-facing aspect of posterior marginal flange appearing setose due to superimposed abdominal tergite I.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="110" pageId="8" pageNumber="109">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="109" start="start">Lateral</pageBreakToken>
and ventral aspects of pterothorax typical of tribe, if slightly exaggerated in form; vestiture and texture similar to notum, setae more or less uniform, suberect; punctation variable, generally scattered and weak to nearly obsolete except as noted. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="110" start="start">Mesepisternum</pageBreakToken>
fused with mesosternum; mesepimeron a prominent, rounded flange separated from mesepisternum by a strong invagination. Metepisternum typical, dorsoanterior lobe present, nearly glabrous and impunctate (Fig. 1). Metepimeron separated from metepisternum by a strongly invaginated sulcus (Fig. 1), strongly dorsally arcuate in lateral view, widest near middle, tapering evenly to a point anteriorly, tapering posteriorly as well but then slightly thickening and recurving posteriorly.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
Legs typical; coxae, trochanters, and femora smooth, shining with suberect setae and scattered punctation. Tibiae clothed in more stout, spine-like setae, punctation much closer, integument appearing nearly granular; tibiae more or less straight (Figs 10-12), cylindrical, broadening slightly apically; apical spurs absent. Tarsi 5-5-4 (Figs 10-12), setation and texture similar to tibiae; all tarsomeres more or less cylindrical, progressively subequal in diameter, and obliquely truncate apically; apical tarsomeres obliquely tapered basally; protarsomere I approximately 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of protarsomere II, protarsomeres II and III subequal, protarsomere IV approximately 0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of protarsomere III, protarsomere V approximately equal to protarsomeres II and III combined; length of mesotarsi greater than that of protarsi, but relative ratios similar. Metatarsomere I approximately as long as metatarsomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–IV">II-IV</normalizedToken>
combined, metatarsomere II 2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of metatarsomere III, metatarsomere IV approximately equal to metatarsomeres II and III combined. Pretarsal claws small, simple, sickle-shaped.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Elytra as described above; widely separated, short, both disarticulated in holotype but approximately extending just past posterior margin of metanotum when closed. Deformed in preservation, lateral margin somewhat thickened (Fig. 7), both margins widening slightly in basal 1/3, roughly parallel in medial 1/3, then medial margin tapering unevenly laterally in apical 1/3, forming a blunt, rounded apex nearest lateral margin. Hind wing also as above, with vein R parallel to and more or less fused with C+Sc, terminating prior to wing apex (Fig. 8); vein Cu well defined, 2ndA3+3rdA1 less so, each reaching wing margin (Fig. 8).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
Abdomen partially disarticulated in holotype specimen making in situ characterization difficult. Abdomen likely bluntly sub-conical, possibly dorso-ventrally compressed in life; with eight (
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–VIII">I-VIII</normalizedToken>
) visible tergites and seven (
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–VIII">II-VIII</normalizedToken>
) visible ventrites; well-sclerotized spiracles present in poorly-defined pleural region of segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–VI">I-VI</normalizedToken>
(Fig. 13); tergites and ventrites fairly uniformly setose (Fig. 13), pleural regions slightly more densely. Tergites 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–V">I-V</normalizedToken>
and ventrites 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–V">II-V</normalizedToken>
weakly sclerotized; remaining visible abdominal segments (
<normalizedToken originalValue="VI–VIII">VI-VIII</normalizedToken>
) comparatively more so (Fig. 13), color similar to that of body, integument virtually impunctate. Abdominal segment IX with dorso-posterior margin evenly emarginate though sclerotization gives it a bilobed appearance (Fig. 13); dorso-ventrally convex, lobes fusing ventrally, forming a spine projecting anteriorly and asymmetrically to left in dorsal view (Fig. 13).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
Figures 13-15. Photographs of slide mounted abdominal structures from holotype male of 
<taxonomicName authority="Falin &amp; Engel, 2014" authorityName="Falin &amp; Engel" authorityYear="2014" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Rhipidocyrtus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rhipidocyrtus muiri" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="muiri">Rhipidocyrtus muiri</taxonomicName>
Falin &amp; Engel, gen. et sp. n. 13 Splayed abdomen as preserved on slide, numbered ventrites to the left, unnumbered tergites to the right 14 Enlarged detail, ventral view of tegmen 15 Enlarged detail of median lobe.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
Tegmen appearing typical for tribe (Fig. 14); an approximately bilaterally symmetrical tube sclerotized dorsally, open ventrally, truncate but slightly flared basally, deeply emarginate apically. Gonoforceps similarly sclerotized, membranously articulated to apex of tegmen dorsally, lateral articulation difficult to discern, also more or 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="111" start="start">less</pageBreakToken>
bilaterally symmetrical and consisting of paired, medio-obliquely truncate lobes dorsally and medio-obliquely oriented digitiform projections ventrally. Median lobe extremely simple, essentially appearing as a strongly beveled ovoid ring, the basal end with a dorsally sclerotized shelf and the apical end with a ventrally sclerotized shelf (Fig. 15).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Female. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="111" type="immature stages">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Immature stages.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="111" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">The specific epithet is as proposed by H.S. Barber and meant to commemorate Dr. Frederick Muir, a remarkable and inspiring entomologist.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="112" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="112">
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="112" start="start">Comments</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="112">
Most ripidiine species, this one included, are described on the basis of very few, if not unique specimens, naturally making estimations of intra-specific variation in size and appearance difficult. In the few cases in which we have examined long series of a single species, such variability appears to be quite low. We expect, then, that additional specimens of 
<taxonomicName authority="Falin &amp; Engel, 2014" authorityName="Falin &amp; Engel" authorityYear="2014" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Rhipidocyrtus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rhipidocyrtus muiri" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="112" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="muiri">Rhipidocyrtus muiri</taxonomicName>
will hew quite closely to the above description.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>