<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5286216" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5286216" approvalRequired="13" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="12" approvalRequired_for_treatments="1" checkinTime="1630047546148" checkinUser="marcus" docAuthor="M, Alexander" docDate="2015" docId="FF316C04FFB2FF9DFF6EFED607A01BB8" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2015.47.2.1865-1884.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 47 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Londokia leleji M 2015, nov.sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="1881" masterDocId="0308147CFFBCFF8DFFDCFFCD041B1A10" masterDocTitle="Ichneumon flies of the tribe Joppocryptini of Palaearctic. Description of new genus Londokia nov. gen. and two new species L. kasparyani nov. sp. and L. leleji nov. sp. (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae)" masterLastPageNumber="1884" masterPageNumber="1865" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879" updateTime="1630059861267" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Ichneumon flies of the tribe Joppocryptini of Palaearctic. Description of new genus Londokia nov. gen. and two new species L. kasparyani nov. sp. and L. leleji nov. sp. (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>M, Alexander</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2015-12-30</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>47</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1865</mods:start>
<mods:end>1884</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5286216</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5286216</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:FF316C04FFB2FF9DFF6EFED607A01BB8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FF316C04FFB2FF9DFF6EFED607A01BB8" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="1881" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="1879" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="14.[178,418,283,305]" box="[178,418,283,305]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">
<heading box="[178,418,283,305]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,418,283,305]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">
<taxonomicName authority="M, 2015" authorityName="M" authorityYear="2015" box="[178,335,283,305]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Londokia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leleji" status="nov.sp.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[178,335,283,305]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">Londokia leleji</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[341,418,283,304]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879" rank="species">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="14.[178,1086,321,391]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">
H o l o t y p e, Russian Far East, Ussurijsk, Kondratenovka, 03.08.199 2, Tereshkin A. leg. P a r a t y p e, Russian Far East, Ussurijsk, 
<date box="[681,784,345,367]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879" value="1992-08-13">13.08.1992</date>
, Tereshkin A. leg. The 
<typeStatus box="[1006,1085,345,367]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">holotype</typeStatus>
and 
<typeStatus box="[269,347,369,390]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">paratype</typeStatus>
are deposited in the collection of Zoologycal Institute RAS, 
<collectingRegion box="[901,1031,369,391]" country="Russia" name="Saint Petersburg" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">St. Petersburg</collectingRegion>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="1881" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="14.[178,254,407,429]" box="[178,254,407,429]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="14.[178,1086,445,554]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, 29-32-segments, ribbed from segments 3-4, not widened behind middle, with white semiannulus on (11)12-14(15,16) segments; tyloides distinct, short-oval on segments 8-15 or 11-17. Flagellum 1,1 times shorter than front wing and 1,6 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="14.[178,1086,570,1441]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">H e a d: Head contour from front roundly and rather strongly narrowed downwards, transversal, 1,3 times wider than height; eyes large, temples from front visible in 1/5 of lower part of an eye; genae short, malar space 7,7 times shorter than height of an eye; head from above rather stout, 1,9 times wider than length in middle. Vertex behind hind ocelli in middle slightly impressed to occipital carina; temples from lateral rather long, 1,2 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye in the middle, from above convex and slightly narrowed behind eyes, from side slightly narrowed downward from middle; occipital carina from above rather strongly and roundly impressed but not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, sharp all round, meeting with hypostomal carina on mandible base; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral; malar space short, 2,6 times shorter by length then mandible base width; mandibles sickle-shaped, smoothly curved and not bordered by lover margin, upper tooth long and sharp, lower one only just marked, but distinct, strongly moved inside in comparison with upper tooth, not visible from front; clypeus 2,2 times broader than height, convex at base and impressed from middle to apex, only just visible separated from face by very weak broad impression, with distinctly emarginate front margin, lateral margins oblique with rounded angles; clypeal foveae sharp, rounded with broad impression around them; labrum narrow, rounded, equal by breadth to central emarginated part of front margin of clypeus; middle field of face distinctly elevated above lateral fields, approximately 1,5 times wider than lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities not great, deep, laterally reach borders of eyes but far not reach level of front ocellus, lateral tubercles not expressed, tubercle between antennal fossae weak, but distinct; antennal fossae small, front margins of antennal fossae quite high elevated above lateral fields; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,3 times less than distance from ocellus to an eye; ocellar triangle only just elevated. Clypeus punctured at the base by big connivent smoothed punctures more sparse to apex, front and lateral margins bordered; surface of face punctured by big smoothed convinient punctures; frons punctured by convenient punctures; vertex and temples with superficial irregular punctures; surface of head between sculptural formations characteristically granulated except polished antennal cavities, shining; granulated sculpture more distinctly expressed in upper part of face and in area of frons, on temples very slight, smoothed, but distinct.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="14.[178,1085,1456,1595]" lastBlockId="15.[178,1086,219,914]" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="1880" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">
T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long with straight front margin, transverse furrow of pronotum narrow, shallow, not interrupted by keel; pronotal base sinuous with sharp apical angle; epomiae sharp, pronotal ridge slightly thickened; surface of pronotum in upper half densely punctured by small rather sharp punctures, in lower one by only just visible rare smoothed punctures, practically not sculpturated. Mesonotum quite strongly convex, 1,1 times longer than width; notauli narrow, distinct in front third of mesonotum; surface of mesonotum very densely punctured by connivent punctures, dull, interspaces between punctures with granulated sculpture; prepectus with smoothed punctures, shining; prepectal carina apically far not reach margin of pronotum; subalarum slightly thickened, high; speculum smooth; mesopleural fovea not expressed, but area around it sharply impressed; lower part of mesopleurae (mesosternum) not separated angularly with gradual bend; sternauli slightly impressed up to middle of mesopleurae; mesopleurae densely punctured to wrinkly-punctured in upper third; surface of mesopleurae between sculptural formations polished in upper half and with granulated sculpture between punctures in lower one; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, bordered by carinatae laterally up to apex, horizontal part of scutellum convex, with sparse smoothed punctures with smoothed granulates sculpture between them, shining; vertical surface of scutellum and postscutellum sculpturated similarly. Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral of broken type with convex horizontal part, its horizontal part 1,5 times shorter than area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum sharp; basal area fairly long, convex with distinct knoll; area superomedia hexagonal, with equal length and breadth, rounded from costulae anteriad; costulae in middle of area superomedia; areae dentiparae at apices without denticles but carinae closing area dentipara and area spiraculifera at apex distinctly broadened; spiracles elongated, 2 times longer than breadth; area superoexterna and area dentipara with big punctures, area spiraculifera wrinkly-punctured; metapleurae with big irregular punctures. Surface of propodeum from polished to polished with indistinct granulated sculpture at area of area superomedia (
<typeStatus box="[320,413,892,914]" pageId="15" pageNumber="1880">paratype</typeStatus>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="15.[178,1085,929,981]" pageId="15" pageNumber="1880">L e g s: Slender; claws small, slightly thickened at base, curved in upper third almost at right angle.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="15.[178,1086,996,1135]" pageId="15" pageNumber="1880">
W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, external vein of apex shorter than internal one; stigma narrow, dark; radius very slightly sinuous, almost straight; nervulus intersticial, ramulus from very short (
<typeStatus box="[361,450,1055,1077]" pageId="15" pageNumber="1880">paratype</typeStatus>
) to almost entirely its absent; veins of both of wings dark, normally sclerotized, including apical ones; membrane of wings hyaline. Length of front wing 1,5 times shorter than body length.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="15.[178,1086,1149,1563]" pageId="15" pageNumber="1880">A b d o m e n: From above rather narrow, almost parallelsided at a most part; second tergite transverse, from above 1,2 times shorter than width at apex. First tergite from lateral with gradual bend of petiolus to postpetiolus, almost stright; petiolus with only more over developed ventrolateral carinae, lateral surface of petiolus smoothed, shining; petiolus narrow, from above gradually widened to quite broad postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus distinctly elevated, not bordered, wider than lateral fields, smooth; lateral fields with some smoothed punctures; surface of postpetiolus shining, polished. Gastrocoeli deeply impressed, not oblique, rather short; thyridia sharp, reach border of tergite, 2 times wider than interval between them; lunulae distinct, situated behind middle of second tergite; surface of tergites 2-3 densely punctured by sharp connivent punctures, slackening backwards and laterally, other tergites densely punctured by indistinct superficial punctures which are decreasing in diameter towards the apex; granulated sculpture on second tergite only just visible on separate areas, smoothed, surface of abdomen shining. Sternites 2-5 strongly unsclerotized, with fold. Hypopygium with oblong roundeg apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="15.[178,1085,1578,1600]" lastBlockId="16.[178,1085,219,387]" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="1881" pageId="15" pageNumber="1880">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black; white (yellow): spots on scapus, face entirely with small darkening on middle field, maxillry palpae, margin of pronotal base narrowly, collar and hind angles of pronotum, spots on tegulae, subalarum and base of front wing, vertical surface of scutellum and postscutellum, spots on apex of propodeum, narrow stripe on apex of tergite 6, tergite 7 entirely. Legs predominantly black, coxae and trochanteres of front and middle legs and trochanteres 1 of hind legs white, apices of femora, tibiae and tarsi of front and middle legs white.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="16.[178,955,402,424]" box="[178,955,402,424]" pageId="16" pageNumber="1881">
S i z e: Body length – 7,5-8,7; front wing – 4,9-6,0; flagellum – 
<quantity box="[832,951,402,424]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.0" metricValueMax="5.5" metricValueMin="4.5" pageId="16" pageNumber="1881" unit="mm" value="5.0" valueMax="5.5" valueMin="4.5">4,5-5,5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>