<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5556453" ID-GBIF-Dataset="687811ca-2f85-4a24-a3e4-ff5760ca7d6a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="188638634" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5556453" ID-ZooBank="6BB63C32-4F47-4A27-9826-AE37F1128A22" checkinTime="1633692412530" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2021" docId="03D087FA8D4DB93FFF3AEA06FE0FFB6E" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.5048.3.4.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 5048 (3)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Anelaphus izabalensis Santos-Silva 2021, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="380" masterDocId="FFE9FF828D4BB936FFADEC55FF87FF87" masterDocTitle="Description of four new species of Anelaphus Linsley (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae Cerambycinae, Elaphidiini), correction of the spelling of species-group names and description of the female of Anelaphus pilosus Chemsak and Noguera" masterLastPageNumber="390" masterPageNumber="371" pageId="6" pageNumber="377" updateTime="1634221713310" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Description of four new species of Anelaphus Linsley (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae Cerambycinae, Elaphidiini), correction of the spelling of species-group names and description of the female of Anelaphus pilosus Chemsak and Noguera</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2021</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2021-10-07</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>5048</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>3</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>371</mods:start>
<mods:end>390</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.5048.3.4</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">687811ca-2f85-4a24-a3e4-ff5760ca7d6a</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5556437</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">6BB63C32-4F47-4A27-9826-AE37F1128A22</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5556453" ID-GBIF-Taxon="188638634" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5556453" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03D087FA8D4DB93FFF3AEA06FE0FFB6E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D087FA8D4DB93FFF3AEA06FE0FFB6E" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="380" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">
<subSubSection box="[151,522,1619,1646]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,522,1619,1682]" box="[151,522,1619,1646]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,522,1619,1646]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="377" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,522,1619,1646]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva, 2021" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,421,1619,1646]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Anelaphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="377" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="izabalensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,421,1619,1646]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">Anelaphus izabalensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[428,522,1620,1646]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="380" pageId="6" pageNumber="377" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,522,1619,1682]" box="[151,295,1655,1682]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,287,1655,1682]" captionStart="FIGURES 14–22. 14–18" captionStartId="8.[151,264,1943,1967]" captionTargetBox="[182,1403,185,1913]" captionTargetId="figure-24@8.[181,1406,181,1919]" captionTargetPageId="8" captionText="FIGURES 14–22. 14–18) Anelaphus izabalensis, holotype female: 14) Dorsal habitus; 15) Ventral habitus; 16) Lateral habitus; 17) Head, frontal view; 18) Basal segments of the antennae. 19–22) Anelaphus subseriatus (Bates, 1885), female from Panama (Panama): 19) Head, frontal view; 20) Basal segments of the antennae; 21) Dorsal habitus; 22) Ventral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5556445" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5556445/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">Figs 14–18</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1437,1727,2042]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,513,1727,1754]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">
Description. 
<typeStatus box="[307,416,1728,1754]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">Holotype</typeStatus>
female.
</emphasis>
Head capsule almost black; ventral mouthparts dark brown, except palpomeres reddish brown with apex yellowish; anteclypeus brown; labrum brown laterally, black on wide central area; antennae dark reddish brown. Prothorax and ventral surface of meso- and metathorax black. Elytra blackish on circum-scutellar region, dark brown on remaining basal third, then gradually brown toward apex. Legs brown (more dark reddish brown depending on light intensity). Ventral surface of abdomen black, except darker reddish brown posterocentral area of ventrites 3 and 4 and posterior third of 5, narrow yellowish-brown apex of 1–4 (this region distinctly widened centrally on 3 and 4).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1437,1727,2042]" lastBlockId="7.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="378" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,270,1980,2006]" pageId="6" pageNumber="377">Head.</emphasis>
Frons coarsely, abundantly punctate, with abundant yellow pubescence not obscuring integument, sparser on each side of center, and both short and decumbent, and long and erect yellowish-white setae interspersed. Antennal tubercles with punctures slightly finer and sparser than on frons, except smooth apex; pubescence and erect setae as on frons, except glabrous smooth area. Vertex with sculpturing as on frons, except posterocentral area with finer and sparser punctures, and sides of area close to prothorax finely rugose-punctate; pubescence and decumbent and erect setae as on frons, except glabrous central area between anterior area of upper eye lobes and prothorax.Area behind upper eye lobes smooth, glabrous close to eye; remaining surface finely rugose-punctate, with abundant yellow pubescence and yellowish-white setae interspersed on center of superior area, sparse, decumbent yellowish-white on superior remaining surface (yellowish-white setae shorter and sparser toward lower eye lobe). Area behind lower eye lobes almost smooth superiorly close to eye, coarsely, shallowly punctate on remaining surface close to eye, finely sparsely punctate on remaining surface; area close to eye with short, sparse yellowishwhite setae superiorly, gradually more abundant and interspersed with long, erect setae of same color toward ventral surface; remaining surface glabrous. Genae finely punctate, except smooth apex; with yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument close to eye, with long, decumbent yellowish-white setae interspersed toward postclypeus, long, erect yellowish-white setae interspersed toward ventral surface, glabrous on smooth area. Wide central area of postclypeus somewhat finely, abundantly punctate; with both yellowish-white and yellow pubescence not obscuring integument close to frons, sparse, erect, both short and long yellowish-white setae close to anteclypeus (slightly more abundant laterally, and forming sparse fringe on anterior margin). Sides of postclypeus smooth and glabrous. Labrum subcoplanar with anteclypeus at posterior 2/3 (anterior margin of this region strongly emarginate), inclined at anterior third; subcoplanar area with short, bristly yellowish-white setae on anterocentral region, absent close to anteclypeus, and long yellowish setae directed forward on sides of anterior region; inclined area with abundant yellowish setae directed forward. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous on posterior half; anterior half coarsely rugosepunctate, with somewhat abundant, bristly, short yellowish-white setae not obscuring integument (whiter depending on light intensity), and long, erect setae of same color interspersed; intermaxillary process almost glabrous and smooth. Maxillary palpomere IV and labial palpomere III gradually widened toward apex. Posterior 2/3 of outer side of mandibles coarsely rugose-punctate, with somewhat sparse yellowish-white setae (denser basally); anterior third smooth and glabrous. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.36 times distance between outer margins of eyes; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.48 times distance between outer margins of eyes.Antennae 1.3 times elytral length, reaching posterior fifth of elytra. Scape coarsely, somewhat rugose-punctate, except smooth dorsal apex; dorsal surface with abundant yellow pubescence not obscuring integument, and both short and decumbent, and long and erect yellowish-white setae interspersed; sides and ventral surface with somewhat sparse yellowish-white pubescence, and long, erect yellowish-white setae interspersed ventrally (erect setae more abundant toward apex). Pedicel and antennomeres III–XI with abundant yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument (pubescence shorter and denser from VI); pedicel and antennomeres III–VI with long, erect yellowish-white setae ventrally (erect setae sparser toward VI); apex of antennomeres III–X with long, erect yellowish-white setae apically; antennomere III with long spine at inner apex; antennomere IV with short spine at inner apex; antennomeres V–VI with spicule at inner apex. Antennal formula based on length of antennomere III (excluding apical spines): scape = 1.11; pedicel = 0.22; IV = 0.89; V = 1.05; VI = 0.97; VII = 1.00; VIII = 0.83; IX = 0.80; X = 0.69; XI = 0.97.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="7.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastBlockId="9.[151,1437,151,1257]" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="380" pageId="7" pageNumber="378">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,295,1447,1473]" pageId="7" pageNumber="378">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax slightly wider than long; sides uniformly rounded from anterolateral angles to near posterolateral angles. Pronotum with smooth, glabrous longitudinal band centrally, from anterior seventh to near apex, slightly tumid on its posterior half; remaining surface coarsely, somewhat abundant punctate; area between coarse punctures minutely punctate; with yellow pubescence not obscuring integument on wide central area (yellow pubescence more abundant, forming irregular tufts on anterior half), from anterior margin to posterior seventh; sides and posterior region with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument (this area gradually widened from middle to apex), denser anteriorly; with long, erect yellowish setae interspersed throughout, except on smooth central area. Sides of prothorax coarsely, somewhat abundantly punctate, except nearly smooth anterior region (this area gradually widened toward prosternum), and finely, transversely striate posterior region (this area gradually widened toward procoxal cavity); with abundant yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument on coarsely punctate region (appearing to be whiter depending on light intensity), nearly glabrous anteriorly and posteriorly. Prosternum coarsely punctate on posterior 2/3 (punctures coarser than on pronotum), somewhat finely, transversely striate on anterior third; with abundant grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument on posterior third, and a few short setae of same color on anterior third (distinctly denser laterally). Narrowest area of prosternal process 0.27 times procoxal with; apex slightly widened. Procoxal cavities open behind. Mesoventrite with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, except glabrous apex; mesanepisternum and mesepimeron with abundant yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument. Metanepisternum with somewhat abundant yellowish-white pubescence basally, sparser, grayish-white on remaining surface.Sides of metaventrite and anterior area with abundant grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument; area close to metacoxal cavities with dense yellowish-white pubescence; remaining surface with sparse grayish-white setae from about anterior quarter to apex, except smooth central area. Scutellum with dense yellow pubescence, except glabrous central area. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1108,1191,295,321]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Elytra.</emphasis>
Coarsely, abundantly punctate on basal half, punctures gradually finer, sparer toward apex; with abundant yellow pubescence (apparently, partially lost in the 
<typeStatus box="[372,472,367,394]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">holotype</typeStatus>
) not obscuring integument, forming irregular denser tufts, and both short, decumbent and yellowish-white, and long, erect and yellowish setae interspersed (both appearing to be whiter depending on light intensity); apex almost truncate, with short projection at sutural angle. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1036,1099,439,465]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora without longitudinal carina on sides of club; with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument; pro- and mesofemoral club with long, erect yellowish-white setae interspersed; metafemoral club with long, erect light yellow setae interspersed. Tibiae with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, and long, erect setae of same color interspersed, except ventral distal half of protibiae and ventral distal third of meso- and metatibiae with dense, bristly yellowishbrown setae. Metatarsomere I slightly shorter than II–III together.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5556445" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5556445" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5556445/files/figure.png" pageId="8" pageNumber="379" startId="8.[151,264,1943,1967]" targetBox="[182,1403,185,1913]" targetPageId="8">
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,1436,1943,2039]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,417,1943,1967]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">FIGURES 14–22. 14–18)</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2021" box="[423,648,1943,1967]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Anelaphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="379" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="izabalensis">
<emphasis box="[423,648,1943,1967]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">Anelaphus izabalensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, holotype female: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[836,870,1943,1967]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">14)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1035,1069,1943,1967]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">15)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1239,1273,1943,1967]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">16)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,185,1979,2003]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">17)</emphasis>
Head, frontal view; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[393,428,1979,2003]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">18)</emphasis>
Basal segments of the antennae. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[764,835,1979,2003]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">19–22)</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="(Bates, 1885)" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1885" box="[842,1216,1979,2003]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Anelaphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="379" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subseriatus">
<emphasis box="[842,1070,1979,2003]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">Anelaphus subseriatus</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Bates, H. W." box="[1084,1208,1979,2003]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379" refId="ref11907" refString="Bates, H. W. (1885) Supplement to Longicornia. In: Godman, F. D. &amp; Salvin, O. (Eds.), Biologia Centrali-Americana, Insecta, Coleoptera. Vol. 5. Taylor and Francis, London, pp. 249 - 436." type="book" year="1885">Bates, 1885</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
, female from Panama (Panama): 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[262,296,2015,2039]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">19)</emphasis>
Head, frontal view; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[504,538,2015,2039]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">20)</emphasis>
Basal segments of the antennae; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[876,909,2015,2039]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">21)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1076,1110,2015,2039]" pageId="8" pageNumber="379">22)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,151,1257]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,323,654,680]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites 1–2 with abundant grayish-white pubescence laterally, not obscuring integument, almost absent centrally on 1, sparse on basal 2/3 of central area of 2, absent on remaining surface; ventrites 3–4 with abundant grayish-white pubescence laterally, not obscuring integument, sparser on basal 2/3 of central area, absent on remaining surface; ventrite 5 with abundant grayish-white pubescence throughout; all ventrites with long, erect, sparse yellowish setae. Apex of ventrite 5 almost truncate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,151,1257]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,420,834,860]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Dimensions (mm).</emphasis>
Total length, 16.85; prothoracic length, 3.25; anterior prothoracic width, 2.65; posterior prothoracic width, 3.10; maximum prothoracic width, 3.60; humeral width, 4.50; elytral length, 11.40.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="380" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,151,1257]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,377,906,933]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3383507310" collectingDate="2003-05-27" collectingDateMax="2003-05-28" collectingDateMin="2003-05-27" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="Woodruff &amp; Monzon" country="Guatemala" county="Morales" elevation="1250" location="Finca Firmeza" municipality="Sierra del Merendon" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Izabal" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[388,492,907,933]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Holotype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry box="[656,833,907,933]" name="Guatemala" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">GUATEMALA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis box="[849,919,907,933]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<collectingRegion box="[849,919,907,933]" country="Guatemala" name="Izabal" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Izabal</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: E. of 
<collectingCounty box="[1007,1102,907,933]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Morales</collectingCounty>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[1117,1359,907,933]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Sierra del Merendón</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03D087FA8D4DB93FFF3AEA06FE0FFB6E:8EA660378D42B93FFAF3EFDEFF71FC4E" country="Guatemala" county="Morales" municipality="Sierra del Merendon" name="Finca Firmeza" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" stateProvince="Izabal">Finca Firmeza</location>
, 
<locationDeviation box="[257,495,943,969]" location="Honduras" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<quantity box="[257,314,943,969]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.0" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" unit="km" value="1.0">1 km</quantity>
W of Honduras
</locationDeviation>
, 
<quantity box="[506,593,942,969]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.25" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" unit="m" value="1250.0">
<elevation box="[506,593,942,969]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.25" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" unit="m" value="1250.0">1250 m</elevation>
</quantity>
, cloud forest, 
<date box="[752,906,943,969]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" value="2003-05-27" valueMax="2003-05-28" valueMin="2003-05-27">
<collectingDate box="[752,906,943,969]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" value="2003-05-27" valueMax="2003-05-28" valueMin="2003-05-27">27-28.V.2003</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName box="[917,1025,943,969]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Woodruff</collectorName>
and 
<collectorName box="[1080,1173,943,969]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Monzón</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode box="[1236,1312,943,969]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[199,1046,979,1005]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,151,1257]" box="[199,1046,979,1005]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,334,979,1005]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Etymology.</emphasis>
Allusive to 
<collectingRegion box="[471,542,979,1005]" country="Guatemala" name="Izabal" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Izabal</collectingRegion>
, Guatemalan department of the 
<typeStatus box="[901,949,979,1005]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">type</typeStatus>
locality.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="380" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,151,1257]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,315,1015,1041]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Santos-Silva, 2021" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2021" box="[321,569,1015,1041]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Anelaphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="izabalensis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[321,569,1015,1041]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Anelaphus izabalensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[575,664,1015,1041]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[575,664,1015,1041]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="(Bates, 1885)" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1885" box="[805,1118,1014,1041]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Anelaphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subseriatus">
<emphasis box="[805,963,1015,1041]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">A. subseriatus</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Bates, H. W." box="[977,1110,1014,1041]" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" refId="ref11907" refString="Bates, H. W. (1885) Supplement to Longicornia. In: Godman, F. D. &amp; Salvin, O. (Eds.), Biologia Centrali-Americana, Insecta, Coleoptera. Vol. 5. Taylor and Francis, London, pp. 249 - 436." type="book" year="1885">Bates, 1885</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation box="[1132,1261,1015,1041]" captionStart="FIGURES 14–22. 14–18" captionStartId="8.[151,264,1943,1967]" captionTargetBox="[182,1403,185,1913]" captionTargetId="figure-24@8.[181,1406,181,1919]" captionTargetPageId="8" captionText="FIGURES 14–22. 14–18) Anelaphus izabalensis, holotype female: 14) Dorsal habitus; 15) Ventral habitus; 16) Lateral habitus; 17) Head, frontal view; 18) Basal segments of the antennae. 19–22) Anelaphus subseriatus (Bates, 1885), female from Panama (Panama): 19) Head, frontal view; 20) Basal segments of the antennae; 21) Dorsal habitus; 22) Ventral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5556445" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5556445/files/figure.png" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">Figs 19–22</figureCitation>
), by the general appearance and length of some female specimens of the latter, but differs as follows: frons with yellow pubescence throughout; scape with abundant yellow pubescence dorsally; antennomeres III and IV slender and less pubescent; distance between upper and lower eye lobes wider, ventral pubescence sparser. In 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1885" box="[1061,1220,1123,1149]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Anelaphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="380" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subseriatus">
<emphasis box="[1061,1220,1123,1149]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="380">A. subseriatus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, the pubescence on the frons is mostly yellowish white and sparser, the scape has yellowish-white pubescence, antennomeres III and IV are shorter and densely pubescent, the distance between the upper and lower eye lobes is shorter, and the ventral pubescence is denser.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>