<document ID-DOI="10.1206/361.1" ID-ISSN="0003-0090" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5410834" approvalRequired="280" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="280" checkinTime="1630352015041" checkinUser="tatiana" docAuthor="Menard, Katrina L. &amp; Schuh, Randall T." docDate="2011" docId="03D08782FFCCC61075C15F0A449FFCDF" docLanguage="en" docName="B361.pdf" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 2011 (361)" docSource="http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/361.1" docStyle="DocumentStyle:915933466F796C9C739DF4DB6B8DCFA6.7:BulAmeMusNatHis.2011-.journal_article.1cover.type1" docStyleId="915933466F796C9C739DF4DB6B8DCFA6" docStyleName="BulAmeMusNatHis.2011-.journal_article.1cover.type1" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Ctypomiris solomonensis Menard &amp; Schuh 2011, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="97" lastPageNumber="96" masterDocId="FFE9FFFAFFACC67177085D1B401AFA00" masterDocTitle="Revision Of Leucophoropterini: Diagnoses, Key To Genera, Redescription Of The Australian Fauna, And Descriptions Of New Indo-Pacific Genera And Species (Insecta: Hemiptera: Miridae)" masterLastPageNumber="159" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="96" pageNumber="96" updateTime="1630962917007" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision Of Leucophoropterini: Diagnoses, Key To Genera, Redescription Of The Australian Fauna, And Descriptions Of New Indo-Pacific Genera And Species (Insecta: Hemiptera: Miridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Menard, Katrina L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Schuh, Randall T.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2011-11-23</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2011</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>361</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>159</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/361.1</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.1206/361.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0003-0090</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5410834</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03D08782FFCCC61075C15F0A449FFCDF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D08782FFCCC61075C15F0A449FFCDF" lastPageId="97" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="96" pageNumber="96">
<subSubSection pageId="96" pageNumber="96" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="96.[713,1147,528,582]" pageId="96" pageNumber="96">
<heading centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="96" pageNumber="96" reason="2">
<taxonomicName authority="Menard &amp; Schuh, 2011" authorityName="Menard &amp; Schuh" authorityYear="2011" box="[713,995,528,551]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Ctypomiris" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="96" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="solomonensis" status="new species">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[713,995,528,551]" italics="true" pageId="96" pageNumber="96">Ctypomiris solomonensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1012,1147,529,551]" pageId="96" pageNumber="96" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
<figureCitation box="[800,967,560,582]" captionStart-0="Figure 19" captionStart-1="Figure 20" captionStartId-0="96.[116,185,583,602]" captionStartId-1="96.[329,398,1738,1757]" captionTargetBox-0="[134,578,211,552]" captionTargetBox-1="[101,1185,1021,1708]" captionTargetId-0="graphics-242@96.[134,577,211,552]" captionTargetId-1="figure-389@96.[101,1185,1021,1708]" captionTargetPageId-0="96" captionTargetPageId-1="96" captionText-0="Figure 19. Distribution map of Ctypomiris spp." captionText-1="Figure 20. Male genitalia of Ctypomiris solomonensis (A–C)." figureDoi-0="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5410899" figureDoi-1="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5410901" httpUri-0="https://zenodo.org/record/5410899/files/figure.png" httpUri-1="https://zenodo.org/record/5410901/files/figure.png" pageId="96" pageNumber="96">Figures 19–20</figureCitation>
; plate 5
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="96" pageNumber="96" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="96.[667,1194,604,985]" pageId="96" pageNumber="96">DIAGNOSIS: Recognized by small size, completely yellowish-white clavus and corium and apex of scutellum (pl. 5), yellowishbrown to castaneous head, dark brown pronotum, membrane golden basally and brown distally, completely golden appendages, meso- and metathoracic pleura and all abdominal segments excluding dark brown pygophore, and characters of male genitalia.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="97" lastPageNumber="97" pageId="96" pageNumber="96" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="96.[667,1194,604,985]" lastBlockId="97.[701,1228,213,1759]" lastPageId="97" lastPageNumber="97" pageId="96" pageNumber="96">
DESCRIPTION: 
<emphasis box="[869,929,874,897]" italics="true" pageId="96" pageNumber="96">Male</emphasis>
: Macropterous, small, weakly medially constricted. Total length 2.38–2.52, width pronotum 0.73–0.76, maximum width across hemelytra 0.77–0.79. COLORATION: Dark brown and golden yellow. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[222,291,242,263]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Head:</emphasis>
Yellow brown to castaneous, generally paler along anterior margin. Eyes deep red to dark purple. Labium golden. Antennal segment 1 golden, segment 2 golden with distal margin with antennal segment 3 dark brown, segment 3 golden basally, brown distally, segment 4 brown. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[466,558,418,439]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Thorax:</emphasis>
Pronotum, thoracic pleura, and anterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[584,611,446,469]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">O</emphasis>
of scutellum dark brown. Dorsolateral margin of metepisternum dark brown, ventral area of scent gland golden, anterior area dark brown like thoracic pleura. 
<emphasis box="[466,529,565,586]" italics="true" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Legs:</emphasis>
All coxae golden. All femora orange-golden. Tibiae basally orange, distally golden, metatibia with parallel rows of dark spicules. All tarsomeres golden. 
<emphasis box="[362,492,681,704]" italics="true" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Hemelytra:</emphasis>
Golden with transparent partial transverse fascia limited to anterior area of corium and possessing dark posterior margin, lateral posterior margins of corium also possessing transparent areas anterior to lobelike extension overlapping cuneal fracture (pl. 5). Transparent area present below dark brown tinted apex of claval commissure, occupying majority of surface anterior to anterior margin of hemelytral membrane and with dark brown posterior margin. Cuneus primarily white with dark brown narrow band lateral to margin with membrane occupying distal 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[626,653,1061,1084]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">O</emphasis>
of margin. Bases of setae on hemelytron dark brown. Membrane golden basally adjacent to white area of cuneus, brown for remainder of length and continuous with brown band of cuneus, veins in brown portion of membrane pigmented dark brown. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[416,531,1239,1260]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Abdomen:</emphasis>
Brown to castaneous. SURFACE AND VESTITURE: Dorsal surface of body and eyes covered with long erect golden setae. Head, pronotum, and scutellum distinctly shiny. Hemelytron punctate and also possessing dark brown, erect setae. STRUCTURE: 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[397,466,1415,1436]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Head:</emphasis>
Clypeus visible and surpassing anterior margin of frons in lateral view and visible in dorsal view. Vertex convex and flat along posterior margin, width nearly equal to two times width of one eye. Eye height nearly equal to height of head, vertex visible in lateral view, gula obsolete. Antennal segment 1 inverted-cokebottle shaped, length surpassing apex of head; segment 2 long and narrower in diameter than segment 1, increasing in diameter distally but still narrower than segment 1 at apex. Length antennal segment 2 equal to one nearly 1.33 times head width. Antennal segments 3 and 4 slender and less than one-fifth length segment 2. Labial segment 1 not quite attaining posterior margin of head, apex of segment 4 reaching apex of mesocoxa. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[927,1020,389,410]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Thorax:</emphasis>
Pronotum nearly 1.5 times as wide as long, swollen dorsally, convex in lateral view, lateral margins of pronotum weakly concave and forming bellshaped pronotum in dorsal view, humeral angles swollen to appear shoulderlike. Flat, narrow pronotal collar present. Mesoscutum hidden under posterior margin of pronotum, anterior of scutellum weakly swollen. Scent gland approximately third total area of metepimeron. 
<emphasis box="[868,932,682,703]" italics="true" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Legs:</emphasis>
Moderate length, slender with metafemur widest in diameter subapical to joint with metatibia, and appearing kneelike. Claws of moderate length, relatively broad, pulvilli less than half of claw length. Parempodia parallel and setiform. 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Hemelytra</emphasis>
: Lateral margins weakly medially constricted, dorsally flat. R+M vein terminating at midpoint of hemelytron. Cuneus short triangular, length approximately equal to 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1200,1227,944,967]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">M</emphasis>
total length of hemelytral membrane, cuneal fracture angled anteromesially and with lateral margins thickened in white-pigmented area. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[765,880,1063,1084]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Abdomen:</emphasis>
Narrow, elongate. GENITA- LIA (fig. 20A–C): 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[919,1041,1092,1113]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Pygophore</emphasis>
: Boxlike, small, less than one-fifth length of abdomen. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[701,827,1151,1172]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Endosoma:</emphasis>
Small, slender, twisted, S-shaped, composed of two sclerotized straps unified by membrane, apex composed of spinelike process with ridges at apex and anterior strap folded subapically. Secondary gonopore small, weakly sclerotized, and subapical to spinelike process (fig. 20C). 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1086,1228,1327,1348]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Phallotheca:</emphasis>
Small, L-shaped, apex gently tapering toward point, base elongate (fig. 20A). 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Right Paramere:</emphasis>
Not examined. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[955,1130,1414,1436]" pageId="97" pageNumber="97">Left Paramere:</emphasis>
Moderately sized; posterior process broad, with sensory pits, and curved ventrally medially, dorsal surface appearing convex, posterior process relatively elongate compared to anterior process; anterior process stout but without sensory pits on interior margin, apex directed anteriorly and nearly perpendicular to base of paramere, dorsal surface below median line of total height of paramere. Dorsomedial margin between anterior and posterior processes rounded (fig. 20B).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>