<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287408" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a79bfa9b-f103-4186-9d1f-add9ef6b2b3a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116830" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287408" ModsDocAuthor=" &amp; Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota" ModsDocDate="1936" ModsDocID="3011" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf" ModsDocTitle="The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1" checkinTime="1258815363179" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota" docDate="1936" docId="0EC4801BFCF04B8EAAE93923B205129E" docLanguage="en" docName="3011_tx.xml" docOrigin="Revista de Entomologia 7" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf" docTitle="Mycocepurus smithi subsp. trinidadensis Weber, 1936, var. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="379" masterDocId="62511D09FB353213B214D7BBDF9210C0" masterDocTitle="The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1" masterLastPageNumber="409" masterPageNumber="378" pageNumber="378" updateTime="1645821295722" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The biology of the fungus-growing ants. Part. I. New forms. 1</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Neal A. Weber, University of North Dakota</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revista de Entomologia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1936</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>7</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>378</mods:start>
<mods:end>409</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3011/3011.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="">3011</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287408" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116830" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287408" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:0EC4801BFCF04B8EAAE93923B205129E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0EC4801BFCF04B8EAAE93923B205129E" lastPageNumber="379" pageNumber="378">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="378">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:140634" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Mycocepurus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Mycocepurus smithi var. trinidadensis Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="378" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="smithi" subSpecies="trinidadensis">Mycocepurus smithi Forel trinidadensis</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="variety">var. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Fig. 1)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="378">Worker: Length 1.7-1.9 mm. - Compared with the original description and redescriptions and figures of Dr. W. M. Wheeler and Dr. Santschi and with a worker taken by myself on the island of St. Lucia, next island to the north</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="378">1) Many of these new forms were taken while I was the recipient of a National Research Council Fellowship in Biology with headquarters at the Imperial College of Tropical Agriculture, Trinidad, B. W. I. I am also indebted to the late Dr. W. M. Wheeler for aid in the determination of ants, particularly for determining many while I was living in Trinidad. My thanks are due Major J. F. Phipps, R. E., Chief Commissioner of the British Section of the British Guiana-BrazilSurinam Boundary Commission, for his kindness in affording me transportation by boat to the Commission Base Camp on the Oronoque River, British Guiana, in a region uninhabited and practically unexplored.</paragraph>
<footnote>
<paragraph pageNumber="379">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="379">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="379">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="379">of</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
the type locality, St. Vincent, the workers of this variety differ chiefly in sculpture. The anteriorly directed convex and blunt ridge between the anterior mesothoracic spines is more reduced or practically absent. Between the sharply carinate sides of the first gastric segment the surface is longitudinally and finely rugulose. Pale ferruginous. Spinosity as in the figure (Fig. 1).
</paragraph>
</footnote>
<paragraph pageNumber="379">Female: Length about 3.5 mm. - Similar to the worker, with the usual sexual differences. Dorsolaterally the pronotum bears on each side a pair of acute tubercles whose bases are confluent and the more posterior is the larger. Scutum in profile gently convex, from above slightly impressed medially, rugulose with finer reticulations between. Epinotal spines large and acute with stout bases, slightly diverging when viewed from above. Postpetiole from above roughly hexagonal with sides acutely angulate, 1.7 times as wide as long. Sculpturing heavier than in worker, color dark ferruginous with ferruginous appendages.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="379">Described from one colony taken by myself June 23, 1935, in the Northern Range north of Arima, Trinidad, B. W. I., at an elevation of about 1800 feet. The species Js widely distributed in Trinidad but local and I have taken it in such representative localities as St. Augustine, Mayaro Bay, and Basin Holl Forest Reserve. The workers show sufficient variation to make identification uncertain without a knowledge of all three castes of the described varieties. To the distribution of this species may be added Antigua, B. W. I., (H. E. Box) and the Indian village of Apura on the Courantyne River, Surinam, by myself.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>