<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ca884005-01b3-4e3d-818b-3e74c244eaaf" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152052582" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-402-67" ID-ZBK="B0ED94FB951A4063BEED7BF5F4E85C39" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:17E90087-D9C9-41EC-8EF7-593A14006B5A" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-402-67" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 402" ModsDocTitle="A taxonomic review of the Neoserica (sensu lato) septemlamellata group (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Sericini)" checkinTime="1451245971557" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Ahrens, Dirk, Liu, Wan-Gang, Fabrizi, Silvia, Bai, Ming &amp; Yang, Xing-Ke" docDate="2014" docId="ABDDB6871D48F3151915791CEC2398E3" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 402: 67-102" docOrigin="ZooKeys 402" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360" docTitle="Neoserica guangpingensis Ahrens, Fabrizi &amp; Liu, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="17E90087-D9C9-41EC-8EF7-593A14006B5A" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="79" masterDocId="FFA3FFF0EF455B38FF99D505E866FFC3" masterDocTitle="A taxonomic review of the Neoserica (sensu lato) septemlamellata group (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Sericini)" masterLastPageNumber="102" masterPageNumber="67" pageId="10" pageNumber="77" updateTime="1643681492625" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A taxonomic review of the Neoserica (sensu lato) septemlamellata group (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Sericini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ahrens, Dirk</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liu, Wan-Gang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fabrizi, Silvia</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bai, Ming</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Yang, Xing-Ke</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>402</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>67</mods:start>
<mods:end>102</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-402-67</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">B0ED94FB951A4063BEED7BF5F4E85C39</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B0ED94FB951A4063BEED7BF5F4E85C39</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152052582" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:17E90087-D9C9-41EC-8EF7-593A14006B5A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/ABDDB6871D48F3151915791CEC2398E3" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="10" pageNumber="77">
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="77" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="77">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/17E90087-D9C9-41EC-8EF7-593A14006B5A" authority="Ahrens, Fabrizi &amp; Liu" class="Insecta" family="Melolonthidae" genus="Neoserica" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neoserica guangpingensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guangpingensis">Neoserica (s.l.) guangpingensis Ahrens, Fabrizi &amp; Liu</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="10" pageNumber="77">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–H">E-H</normalizedToken>
, 7
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="77" type="type material examined">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="77">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="77">Holotype: ♂ &quot;839462 Neoserica spYU09_2 China S. Murzin 29.07.2009 Guang Ping, 34km N Jihong Yunnan Pr. Xichuanbanna 1200m&quot; (ZFMK).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="10" pageNumber="77" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="77">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="77">Length: 8.8 mm, length of elytra: 6.5 mm, width: 5.2 mm. Body oblong, dark brown, antennal club yellowish brown, dorsal surface dull, except a few long setae on head and sides of elytra nearly glabrous.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="78" pageId="10" pageNumber="77">
Labroclypeus subtrapezoidal, considerably wider than long, widest at base, lateral margins moderately convex and strongly convergent anteriorly, anterior angles strongly rounded, anterior margin weakly sinuate medially, margins moderately reflexed; surface convexly elevated medially and shiny, basis without dull tomentum, punctation dense, small punctures mixed with coarse ones each bearing a long erect seta; frontoclypeal suture distinctly incised, not elevated and distinctly angled medially; smooth area anterior to eye approximately 2.5 times as wide as long; ocular canthus short (length = 1/4 of ocular diameter) and wide, with fine, moderately dense punctures and a few long setae. Frons in posterior quarter dull, otherwise moderately shiny, with coarse and fine, dense punctures, densely covered with long erect setae being partly bent posteriorly. Eyes 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="78" start="start">moderately</pageBreakToken>
large, ratio diameter/interocular width: 0.61. Antenna with ten antennomeres, club with seven antennomeres, moderately reflexed, twice as long as remaining antennomeres combined; antennomere 4 subequal to half of length of club, antennomere 3 half as long as pedicellus. Mentum elevated and slightly flattened anteriorly.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="78">Pronotum transverse, widest shortly before base, lateral margins evenly convex and moderately convergent anteriorly, anterior angles moderately sharp and distinctly produced, posterior angles strongly rounded; anterior margin moderately convexly produced medially, with a medially widely incomplete marginal line; surface densely and coarsely punctate, only with minute setae, and a few long erect setae on anterior sides; setae of lateral border fine and moderately dense, those of anterior margin numerous and in part widely displaced from margin; hypomeron distinctly carinate basally, carina not produced. Scutellum narrow and long, dull, with fine, dense punctures, on midline impunctate, with minute setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="78">
Elytra oblong, widest in posterior third, striae weakly impressed, finely and densely punctate, intervals weakly convex, finely and densely punctate, punctures mainly concentrated along striae, with minute setae, odd intervals on sides and apical declivity with a few erect setae (lacking on disc); epipleural edge wide, ending at widely rounded apical angle of elytra, epipleura densely setose, apical border broadly membranous, with a fine fringe of microtrichomes (visible at 100
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="78">Ventral surface dull, coarsely and densely punctate, metasternum moderately setose; metacoxa glabrous, with a few long setae laterally, posterior margin straight; abdominal sternites finely and densely punctuate, minutely setose, with a transverse row of coarse punctures each bearing a robust, long seta. Mesosternum between mesocoxae half as wide as mesofemur. Ratio of length of metepisternum/metacoxa: 1/1.62. Pygidium strongly convex and dull, coarsely and densely punctate, with a narrow smooth midline, with dense and long erect setae and minute setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="11" pageNumber="78">
Legs moderately slender and not very long; femora with two longitudinal rows of setae, finely and moderately densely punctate between rows, nearly glabrous; metafemur dull, anterior margin acute, immediately behind anterior edge with a continuously serrated line, punctures and setae of anterior longitudinal row complete, posterior margin in apical half ventrally smooth and little widened and smooth, posterior margin smooth dorsally, not serrated, with dense, short setae. Metatibia moderately slender and short, widest at apex, ratio of width/length: 1/2.6; dorsal margin sharply carinate, with three groups of spines, basal group at the middle, median one at two thirds, and apical group at 4/5 of metatibial length, basally with a few robust but single setae; beside dorsal margin with a continuously serrated line being subparallel with dorsal margin 4/5 of metatibial length and ending shortly before metatibial apex; lateral face longitudinally convex, coarsely and moderately densely punctate, with a few robust setae, in apical half punctures less dense, without convex subdorsal longitudinal carina on lateral face; ventral margin finely serrated, with four robust, nearly equidistant setae; medial face smooth, apex indistinctly sinuate interiorly near tarsal articulation. Tarsomeres with dense, short setae ventrally, not carinate laterally, smooth dorsally; metatarsomeres with a strongly serrated ventral ridge and a sharp subventral 
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="79" start="start">carina</pageBreakToken>
immediately beside it, first metatarsomere as long as following two tarsomeres combined and slightly longer than dorsal tibial spur. Protibia short, distinctly tridentate; anterior claws symmetrical, basal tooth of inner claw sharply truncate at apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="79">
Aedeagus: Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–G">E-G</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="79" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="79">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="79">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Melolonthidae" genus="Neoserica" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neoserica guangpingensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guangpingensis">Neoserica guangpingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. differs from very similar 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Melolonthidae" genus="Neoserica" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neoserica takakuwai" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="79" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="takakuwai">Neoserica takakuwai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. by the wide right paramere being deeply and concavely sinuate internally.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="79" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="79">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="79">The new species is named according to its type locality Guang Ping (China).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>