<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.706.20007" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3845d6cd-8371-41ab-9f46-1065a413a987" ID-GBIF-Taxon="135111875" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-706-17" ID-ZBK="BC9204C486724831AD4F6D8683DF69AE" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0DE2B629-ED1F-46EB-883C-EFDF8196AC78" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-706-17" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 706" ModsDocTitle="Arouiminusetosus, a new species of Scopelocheiridae from Korea (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Lysianassoidea)" checkinTime="1507181770478" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Jung, Tae Won, Coleman, Charles Oliver &amp; Yoon, Seong Myeong" docDate="2017" docId="6CFD49344F4A5845A98D68CB61D83116" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 706: 17-29" docOrigin="ZooKeys 706" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.706.20007" docTitle="Aroui minusetosus Jung, Coleman &amp; Yoon, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="0DE2B629-ED1F-46EB-883C-EFDF8196AC78" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="22" masterDocId="0E168E23FFD2D758AE6CE403FF9BFFDD" masterDocTitle="Arouiminusetosus, a new species of Scopelocheiridae from Korea (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Lysianassoidea)" masterLastPageNumber="29" masterPageNumber="17" pageId="0" pageNumber="17" updateTime="1643586694101" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Arouiminusetosus, a new species of Scopelocheiridae from Korea (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Lysianassoidea)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jung, Tae Won</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Coleman, Charles Oliver</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Yoon, Seong Myeong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>706</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>17</mods:start>
<mods:end>29</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.706.20007</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.706.20007</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-706-17</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">BC9204C486724831AD4F6D8683DF69AE</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">BC9204C486724831AD4F6D8683DF69AE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="135111875" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0DE2B629-ED1F-46EB-883C-EFDF8196AC78" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6CFD49344F4A5845A98D68CB61D83116" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="22" pageId="0" pageNumber="17">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="17" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/0DE2B629-ED1F-46EB-883C-EFDF8196AC78" class="Malacostraca" family="Lysianassoidea" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui minusetosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="0" pageNumber="17" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minusetosus">Aroui minusetosus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="17">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1, 2, 3, 4 Korean Name: Teol-son-gin-pal-yeop-sae-u, new
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="17" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">
Somaemul Island (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="34.6276">34°37.656'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="128.54112">128°32.467'E</geoCoordinate>
, depth 52 m), Gyeongsangnam-do, South Korea.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="17" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">Holotype: adult male, 4.3 mm, NIBRIV0000806536. Paratype: one male, 3.0 mm, NIBRIV0000807161; all dissected appendages and remain bodies of type specimens were preserved in 95% ethanol; collected from the type locality at 12 May 2012, by grab sampling. These specimens were provided by Prof. H.-Y. Soh.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="17" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">
The composite epithet of the specific name of 
<taxonomicName genus="Lysianassoidea" lsidName="Lysianassoidea minusetosus" pageId="0" pageNumber="17" rank="species" species="minusetosus">minusetosus</taxonomicName>
is a combination of the Latin minus and 
<taxonomicName genus="Lysianassoidea" lsidName="Lysianassoidea setosus" pageId="0" pageNumber="17" rank="species" species="setosus">setosus</taxonomicName>
, referring to having less setose appendages.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="18" pageId="0" pageNumber="17" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="17">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="18" pageId="0" pageNumber="17">
Head eyes ovoid, ommatidia large. Antennae calceoli absent. Mandible with columnar molar process, elevated, triturative surface weakly developed. Maxilla 1 inner plate with plumose setae along medial margin and apex; outer plate with toothed setae apically in 7/4 arrangement; palp article 3 swollen distally, with dentate setae apically. Maxilla 2 inner plate longer than outer plate; outer plate with marginal and submarginal rows composed of barbed and simple setae apically (all setae extremely elongate). Coxae 1-3 not densely setose ventrally; coxa 4 setose posteroventrally. Gnathopod 1 scopelocheirin form; coxa 1 subtriangular; propodus slightly longer than carpus, with rows of long setae forming tuft distally, palm absent; dactylus extremely reduced, anchored at posterodistal corner. Gnathopod 2 propodus subrectangular, with four robust setae posterodistally (distal locking seta extremely elongate), palm nearly transverse, with small protrusion. Pereopods 3-4 moderately developed. Pereopod 5 coxa anterior lobe slightly expanded downward than posterior lobe; basis shorter than coxa, wider than long, anterior margin distal 2/3 length with many elongate robust setae marginally and minute setae submarginally, posterior lobe largely expanded; ischium and merus lined with many simple and robust setae anteriorly; merus posterior margin expanded, with slender setae on distal 2/3 length, posterodistal corner produced (reaching 1/3 length of merus) with robust seta. Pereopod 6 longer and slender than pereopod 5; merus about half as long as basis, expanded posteriorly; carpus rectangular, 1.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus; propodus linear, 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, with simple long setae on distal half of posterior margin. Pereopod 7 slightly longer and stouter than pereopod 6; basis longer than that of pereopod 6; merus posterior lobe weaker, but setae stouter than those of pereopod 6; carpus and propodus stouter than those of pereopod 6. Epimeron 1 anteroventral corner angulate with one robust seta, posterior margin round and with small notches. Epimera 2-3 expanded and with facial setae 
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="18" start="start">anteroventrally</pageBreakToken>
, posterior margins lined with small notches. Urosomite 1 with deep dorsal depression and mid-dorsal carina. Uropods 1-2 peduncles longer than rami, with robust setae on lateral and medial margins; outer rami with lateral robust setae only. Uropod 3 shorter than uropod 2; outer ramus bi-articulate; inner ramus not reaching distal end of proximal article of outer ramus in position. Telson cleft about 70%, each lobe with deep apical notch bearing one pair of robust and sensory seta, with one robust seta and one pair of sensory setae dorsolaterally.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="20" pageId="1" pageNumber="18" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">Description of holotype male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">Head. Lateral cephalic lobes expanded anteriorly, round; eyes ovoid, ommatidia large (Fig. 1B).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
Antenna 1 (Fig. 1C, D) 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as antenna 2, as long as head to pereonite 1 combined; peduncular article 1 swollen anteriorly; accessory flagellum 3-articulate; flagellum article 1 distinctly elongate; calceoli absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
Antenna 2 (Fig. 1E) 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as body; peduncular articles moderately developed; flagellum 21-articulate; calceoli absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">Upper lip (Fig. 1F) epistome concave, separated from upper lip; upper lip slightly produced, rounded.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">Lower lip (Fig. 1G) with developed mandibular processes</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
Mandible (Fig. 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="H–J">H-J</normalizedToken>
) incisor smooth but bearing blunt denticles on both sides; lacinia mobilis present on left mandible only, stemmed, expanded distally, with irregularly cusped blade; three small raker setae present on both mandibles, patch setules between raker setae and molar processes absent; molar process columnar, elevated, with triturative, rather smooth surface; lateral setigerous crest absent; palp attached midway, 3-articulate; article 2 longest, swollen anteriorly, with an oblique row of ten setae distally; article 3 weakly falcate, 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as article 2, with twelve setae from middle of inner margin to apex.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui minusetosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="18" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minusetosus">Aroui minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, NIBRIV0000806536, 4.3 mm. A habitus B head C antenna 1, lateral D antenna 1, medial E antenna 2 F upper lip, lateral G lower lip H left mandible I, J right mandible. Scale bars: 0.1 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–J">F-J</normalizedToken>
), 0.2 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–E">B-E</normalizedToken>
), 0.5 mm (A).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">Maxilla 1 (Fig. 2A, B) inner plate narrowing distally, not short, setose, with nine plumose setae along medial margin and apex; outer plate with eleven toothed setae apically in 7/4 arrangement and with several setae submarginally; palp bi-articulate, distal article swollen distally, apical margin oblique, with six mono-dentate short setae, one multi-dentate elongate seta, and one plumose seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
Maxilla 2 (Fig. 2C) each plate broad; inner plate 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer plate, with two rows of simple and plumose setae along distal half of medial and apical margins; outer plate with one marginal and one submarginal rows composed of barbed and simple setae apically (all setae extremely elongate).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
Maxilliped (Fig. 2D) inner plate with one mediodistal row of plumose setae, apex with three nodular setae; outer plate well developed, subovoid, apex reaching the middle of palp article 3, lined with 13 nodular setae, eleven plumose setae, and two pairs of simple setae along mediodistal margin; palp 4-articulate, article 2 2.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as article 1, article 4 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as article 3, with one short apical seta.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="19" pageId="1" pageNumber="18">
Pereon.Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–G">E-G</normalizedToken>
) scopelocheirin form; coxa 1 large, subtriangular, expanded distally, round ventrally; basis 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as coxa, anterior margin straight, lined with short setae, posterior margin slightly expanded; ischium 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis; carpus elongate, 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis; propodus subrectangular, 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="19" start="start">as</pageBreakToken>
carpus, slightly curved, with one lateral and two medial rows of long setae forming tuft distally, palm absent; dactylus extremely reduced, anchored at posterodistal corner.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="19">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="H–J">H-J</normalizedToken>
) slender, subchelate; coxa 2 subrectangular, 2.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, slightly curved posteroventrally, with two small notches posteroventrally; basis 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as coxa, slightly widened distally; ischium elongate, slightly dilated posterodistally, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis; merus 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as ischium, round posteriorly, with many short setae and one cluster of long setae; carpus 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis, anterior margin swollen, with several clusters of short setae, longest seta at anterodistal corner reaching distal end of propodus, with two rows of plumose setae posterodistally; propodus subrectangular, 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, with four robust setae posterodistally (distal locking seta extremely elongate), palm nearly transverse, with small protrusion posterodistally; dactylus falcate, slightly beyond palm.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="19">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="19">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui minusetosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minusetosus">Aroui minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, NIBRIV0000806536, 4.3 mm. A maxilla 1 B inner plate of maxilla 1 C maxilla 2 D maxilliped E gnathopod 1 F coxa 1 G palm and dactylus of gnathopod 1 H gnathopod 2 I coxa 2 J palm and dactylus of gnathopod 2. Scale bars 0.05 mm (G, J), 0.1 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
), 0.2 mm (E, F, H, I).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="19">
Pereopod 3 (Fig. 3A) stout; coxa subrectangular, 3.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, slightly curved and with two small notches posteroventrally; basis 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as coxa, subtrapezoidal, somewhat expanded posterodistally; ischium elongate, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis, anterior lobe weak; merus expanded anteriorly, anterodistal corner weakly produced; carpus 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus, somewhat expanded distally, with simple and robust setae on posterior margin; propodus 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, lined with robust setae on posterior margin, with one pair of locking setae posterodistally; dactylus falcate, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="19">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 3B) coxa deeper than wide, expanded posteroventrally; other articles nearly similar to those of pereopod 3.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="19">
Pereopod 5 (Fig. 3C) coxa large, subquadrate, slightly wider than long, weakly bilobate and anterior lobe slightly expanded downward than posterior lobe, posteroventral margin oblique, lined with minute setae, with three minute notches each bearing seta; basis subovoid, smaller than coxa, wider than long, anterior margin round, with many elongate robust setae marginally and minute setae submarginally on distal 2/3 length, posterior lobe largely expanded, posterodistal end reaching 1/4 length of merus, margin weakly crenulate and lined with minute setae, with one row of four setae medially; ischium and merus lined with many simple and robust setae anteriorly; merus posterior margin expanded, with five slender setae distally on 2/3 length, posterodistal corner produced (reaching 1/3 length of merus) with one robust seta; carpus dilated posterodistally, 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus, anterior margin crenulate and lined with robust setae; propodus 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, with single and paired robust setae on anterior margin; dactylus falcate, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="20" pageId="2" pageNumber="19">
Pereopod 6 (Fig. 3D) longer and more slender than pereopod 5; coxa subrectangular, smaller than that of pereopod 5, bilobate, anterior lobe smaller than posterior lobe, expanded downward, with three plumose setae anteriorly, posterior lobe weakly crenulate, with three plumose setae posteroventrally and minute setae on posterior margin; basis ovoid, 1.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, anterior margin round proximally and remains nearly straight bearing short robust setae, with one cluster of elongate and short robust setae at anterodistal corner, posterior margin well expanded, smooth, weakly crenulate, posterodistal end reaching 1/4 length of merus; merus half as long as basis, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="20" start="start">expanded</pageBreakToken>
posteriorly; carpus rectangular, 1.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus; propodus linear, 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, with single and paired robust setae on anterior margin and simple long setae on distal half of posterior margin; dactylus falcate, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
Pereopod 7 (Fig. 3E) 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as and stouter than pereopod 6; coxa unilobate, with two plumose setae anteriorly, dilated and weakly crenulate posteroventrally; basis larger than that of pereopod 6, anterior margin slightly concave distally at 2/3 length, posterior lobe well developed, margin weakly crenulate, with two plumose setae proximally, somewhat flattened and angulate distally; merus posterior lobe weaker, but setae stouter than those of pereopod 6; carpus and propodus stouter than those of pereopod 6; dactylus falcate, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui minusetosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minusetosus">Aroui minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, NIBRIV0000806536, 4.3 mm. A pereopod 3 B pereopod 4 C pereopod 5 D pereopod 6 E pereopod 7. Scale bars 0.2 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–E">A-E</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">Pleon.Epimeron 1 not produced but angulate bearing one robust seta anteroventrally, posterior margin round and with three small notches. Epimera 2-3 expanded, with facial setae anteroventrally, posterior margins lined with small notches. Urosomite 1 with deep dorsal depression and mid-dorsal carina (Fig. 4A).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
Uropod 1 (Fig. 4B) longest; peduncle 1.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer ramus, with seven robust setae on dorsolateral margin and five elongate robust setae on dorsomedial margin; outer ramus with five lateral robust setae only; inner ramus 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer ramus, with two medial and four lateral robust setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
Uropod 2 (Fig. 4C) 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as uropod 1; peduncle with two robust setae medially (distal seta stoutest) and five robust setae laterally on each dorsal margin; outer ramus 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as peduncle, with five lateral robust setae only; inner ramus 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer ramus, with four lateral and three medial robust setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
Uropod 3 (Fig. 4D) 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as uropod 2; peduncle 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer ramus; each ramus with plumose setae on medial margin; outer ramus bi-articulate, distal article 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as proximal article; inner ramus 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer ramus, not reaching distal end of proximal article of outer ramus in position.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">Telson (Fig. 4E) longer than broad, cleft about 70%, each lobe with deep apical notch bearing one robust and one sensory seta apically, with one robust seta and one pair of sensory setae dorsolaterally.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui minusetosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minusetosus">Aroui minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, NIBRIV0000806536, 4.3 mm. A pleon, lateral B uropod 1 C uropod 2 D uropod 3 E telson. Scale bars 0.1 mm (E), 0.2 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
), 0.5 mm (A).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="22" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="20">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="22" pageId="3" pageNumber="20">
The subfamily 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="subfamily" subfamily="Scopelocheirinae">Scopelocheirinae</taxonomicName>
is a small group of 
<taxonomicName family="Scopelocheiridae" lsidName="" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="family">Scopelocheiridae</taxonomicName>
, composed of only eight species in three genera, united by the synapomorphy of the narrow columnar mandibular molar different from other lysianassoids (
<bibRefCitation author="Kilgallen, NM" journalOrPublisher="Zoosystematics and Evolution" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="1 - 43" title="A review of the scopelocheirid amphipods (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Lysianassoidea), with the description of new taxa from Australian waters." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zse.91.8440" volume="91" year="2015">Kilgallen and Lowry 2015</bibRefCitation>
). In their review, the diagnosis of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Aroui</taxonomicName>
was restricted concerning the sharing of the unusual long, distally barbed setae on the outer plate of maxilla 2 (
<bibRefCitation author="Kilgallen, NM" journalOrPublisher="Zoosystematics and Evolution" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="1 - 43" title="A review of the scopelocheirid amphipods (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Lysianassoidea), with the description of new taxa from Australian waters." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zse.91.8440" volume="91" year="2015">Kilgallen and Lowry 2015</bibRefCitation>
). The Korean scopelocheirid specimens in this study also show these synapomorphic characters and they are easily assigned to the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Aroui</taxonomicName>
. This genus has only four valid species: 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. americana" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="americana">A. americana</taxonomicName>
Lowry &amp; Stoddart, 1997; 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. hamatopodus" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="hamatopodus">A. hamatopodus</taxonomicName>
Lowry &amp; Stoddart, 1997; A 
<taxonomicName genus="Lysianassoidea" lsidName="Lysianassoidea onagawae" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="onagawae">onagawae</taxonomicName>
(Takekawa &amp; Ishimaru, 2000); and 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. setosus" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="setosus">A. setosus</taxonomicName>
Chevreux, 1911. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui minusetosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minusetosus">Aroui minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is readily distinguished from 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. americana" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="americana">A. americana</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. hamatopodus" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="hamatopodus">A. hamatopodus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. setosus" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="setosus">A. setosus</taxonomicName>
in that only coxa 4 has setose margin posteroventrally (vs. all coxae 1-4 of 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. americana" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="americana">A. americana</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. hamatopodus" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="hamatopodus">A. hamatopodus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. setosus" pageId="3" pageNumber="20" rank="species" species="setosus">A. setosus</taxonomicName>
are densely setose 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="21" start="start">ventrally</pageBreakToken>
). The new species is quite similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="4" pageNumber="21" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
from Japan having non-setose coxae 1-3, but show a difference in coxa 4: in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. minusetosus" pageId="4" pageNumber="21" rank="species" species="minusetosus">A. minusetosus</taxonomicName>
, it is densely setose with long setae posteroventrally, but only with a moderate setation posteriorly in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="4" pageNumber="21" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
. On the other hand, this new species has a less dense setation on the whole body compared to the original description of 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="4" pageNumber="21" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Takekawa, AT" journalOrPublisher="Zoological Science" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="681 - 687" title="A new species of the genus Scopelocheirus (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea) from Onagawa Bay, northeastern Japan." url="https://doi.org/10.2108/zsj.17.681" volume="17" year="2000">Takekawa and Ishimaru 2000</bibRefCitation>
). At first, we considered the much weaker setation related to the developmental stage, but the Korean specimens show an elongated antenna 2 that indicates maturity in male, and the body length of the new species is longer than the type specimen of 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="4" pageNumber="21" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Takekawa, AT" journalOrPublisher="Zoological Science" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="681 - 687" title="A new species of the genus Scopelocheirus (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea) from Onagawa Bay, northeastern Japan." url="https://doi.org/10.2108/zsj.17.681" volume="17" year="2000">Takekawa and Ishimaru 2000</bibRefCitation>
). Additionally, the new species shows some differences from 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="4" pageNumber="21" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
as follows: 1) the eyes are ovoid and their ommatidia are 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="22" start="start">larger</pageBreakToken>
in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. minusetosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="minusetosus">A. minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (vs. pyriform and smaller ommatidia in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
); 2) antenna 1 flagellum is composed of eight articles in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. minusetosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="minusetosus">A. minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (vs. 13 articles in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
); 3) gnathopod 2 is subchelate with a small protrusion on the palm in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. minusetosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="minusetosus">A. minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (vs. minutely chelate and without protrusion in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
); 4) gnathopod 2 propodus has a row of four robust setae posterodistally (distal locking seta is elongate and not paired) in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. minusetosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="minusetosus">A. minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (vs. having a pair of locking setae in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
); and 5) both telson each lobes have a robust seta dorsally in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. minusetosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="minusetosus">A. minusetosus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (vs. three dorsal robust setae in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
) (see the Table 1, 
<bibRefCitation author="Takekawa, AT" journalOrPublisher="Zoological Science" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="681 - 687" title="A new species of the genus Scopelocheirus (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea) from Onagawa Bay, northeastern Japan." url="https://doi.org/10.2108/zsj.17.681" volume="17" year="2000">Takekawa and Ishimaru 2000</bibRefCitation>
). This is the first record of a scopelocheirid lysianassoid from Korean waters.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
Table 1. Morphological differences between worldwide 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Scopelocheiridae" genus="Aroui" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aroui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Aroui</taxonomicName>
species.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<table pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Characters</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. americana" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="americana">A. americana</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. hamatopodus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="hamatopodus">A. hamatopodus</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. onagawae" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="onagawae">A. onagawae</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. setosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="setosus">A. setosus</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. minusetosus" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="minusetosus">A. minusetosus</taxonomicName>
</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Eyes</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Antenna 1</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Gnathopod 1</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Gnathopod 2</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Coxae 1-4</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Pereopods 3-7</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Uropod 1number of setae (medial + lateral)</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Uropod 2number of setae (medial + lateral)</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="6" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Telson</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="22">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">Reference</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Lowry, JK" journalOrPublisher="Memoirs of the Hourglass Cruises" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="1 - 148" title="AmphipodaCrustacea IV. Families Aristiidae, Cyphocarididae, Endevouridae, Lysianassidae, Scopelocheiridae, Uristidae." volume="10" year="1997">Lowry and Stoddart (1997)</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Lowry, JK" journalOrPublisher="Records of the Australian Museum" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="111 - 120" title="The scopelocheirid genus Aroui (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Lysianassoidea) with notes on the association between scopelocheirid amphipods, cassid gastropods and spatangoid echinoids." url="https://doi.org/10.3853/j.0067-1975.41.1989.139" volume="41" year="1989">Lowry and Stoddart (1989)</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Takekawa, AT" journalOrPublisher="Zoological Science" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="681 - 687" title="A new species of the genus Scopelocheirus (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea) from Onagawa Bay, northeastern Japan." url="https://doi.org/10.2108/zsj.17.681" volume="17" year="2000">Takekawa and Ishimaru (2000)</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="22" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Lowry, JK" journalOrPublisher="Records of the Australian Museum" pageId="6" pageNumber="23" pagination="111 - 120" title="The scopelocheirid genus Aroui (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Lysianassoidea) with notes on the association between scopelocheirid amphipods, cassid gastropods and spatangoid echinoids." url="https://doi.org/10.3853/j.0067-1975.41.1989.139" volume="41" year="1989">Lowry and Stoddart (1989)</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>