<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047609" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:78AF0228-0097-4F90-89AB-B80796180375" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="4CB5B5015263992FC454D758ED825766" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio radii Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="78AF0228-0097-4F90-89AB-B80796180375" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="172" lastPageNumber="173" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="169" pageNumber="170" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047609" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:78AF0228-0097-4F90-89AB-B80796180375" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4CB5B5015263992FC454D758ED825766" lastPageId="172" lastPageNumber="173" pageId="169" pageNumber="170">
<subSubSection pageId="169" pageNumber="170" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="169" pageNumber="170">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/78AF0228-0097-4F90-89AB-B80796180375" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio radii" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="169" pageNumber="170" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="radii">Oxyscelio radii Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="169" pageNumber="170">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 271-276; Morphbank80
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="171" lastPageNumber="172" pageId="169" pageNumber="170" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="169" pageNumber="170">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="169" pageNumber="170">Female. Body length 4-4.65 mm (n=19).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="169" pageNumber="170">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: at least partially darker than scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long; as long as broad. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="169" pageNumber="170">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by a set of irregular elevations. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: present. Occipital carina: present laterally, absent medially. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: rugose; umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="171" lastPageNumber="172" pageId="169" pageNumber="170">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: not steep, forming less than a right angle. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate 
<pageBreakToken pageId="170" pageNumber="171" start="start">foveate</pageBreakToken>
. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a ruga. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar 
<pageBreakToken pageId="171" pageNumber="172" start="start">rim</pageBreakToken>
: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally and ventrally. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, forming a flat, concave shelf. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with a longitudinal median ruga and some weak transverse carinae. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T5. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="171" pageNumber="172">T1 horn: present. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1 lateral carina: straight. T2 sculpture: densely foveolate, longitudinal sculpture irregular. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: longer than broad. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate; longitudinally striate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="171" pageNumber="172">Male. Body length 3.5-4.1 mm (n=14). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching apex of T5. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 3. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: truncate.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="171" pageNumber="172">
<paragraph pageId="171" pageNumber="172">
Figures 271-276. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio radii" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="171" pageNumber="172" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="radii">Oxyscelio radii</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 368185) 271 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 272 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view. Paratype female (OSUC 368178) 273 Head, anterior view 274 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 368190) 275 Antenna 276 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank80
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="172" lastPageNumber="173" pageId="171" pageNumber="172" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="171" pageNumber="172">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="172" lastPageNumber="173" pageId="171" pageNumber="172">
Both sexes: Frontal depression flat, with oblique interrupted carinae and sometimes with an incomplete longitudinal carina; submedian carina weak. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by sharp rugae. Occipital carina connected to hyperoccipital carina by a weak longitudinal carina or irregular ruga, laterally with strong corners and medially sinuate; area between occipital and hyperoccipital carinae densely sculptured. Mesoscutellum densely foveolate. Metascutellum flat, rugose. Postmarginal vein present. Coxa not darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina not expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 not longer than pedicel. A4 slightly longer than broad, A5 broader than long. T1 with raised horn obscuring longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T5 or base of T6. T6 slightly longer than broad. Male: A4 slightly longer than broad, A11 longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="172" pageNumber="173" start="start">3</pageBreakToken>
longitudinal carinae. Fore wing not long enough to exceed metasomal apex. T7 truncate or slightly emarginate apically. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio radii" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="172" pageNumber="173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="radii">Oxyscelio radii</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio aciculae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="172" pageNumber="173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aciculae">Oxyscelio aciculae</taxonomicName>
. These two species are best distinguished using metasomal length in both males and females.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="172" pageNumber="173" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“rod.”">&quot;rod.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="172" pageNumber="173" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307101]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="172" pageNumber="173" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, via Mount Carbine, Mount Windsor Tableland, 28.
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–">I-</normalizedToken>
5.III.1981, malaise trap, OSUC 368185 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 20 females, 14 males, Australian Museum K256238 (AMSA); OSUC 368176, 368178-368184, 368186-368189 (ANIC); OSUC 448966 (BMNH); OSUC 462582, 462585-462586 (CNCI); OSUC 368177, QDPC 0-165630, QDPC 0-165750, QDPC 0-165784, QDPC 0-165790 (QDPC); OSUC 148478, 368191 (QMBA); OSUC 448601 (QPIM); OSUC 448955, 448957 (UQIC); OSUC 368175, 368190, 368192-368194, 448949-448950 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="172" pageNumber="173" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="172" pageNumber="173">
Distinction between 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio radii" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="172" pageNumber="173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="radii">Oxyscelio radii</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio aciculae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="172" pageNumber="173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aciculae">Oxyscelio aciculae</taxonomicName>
is very difficult in some cases. These may represent a single species with strong variation due to differently-shaped hosts, which could be tested with further research. However, at present there is some justification in maintaining them as separate taxa.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>