<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5915568" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5c7a8963-3269-42d4-99ef-78cf39b08ee8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="192733713" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5915568" ID-ZooBank="92743F55-797F-4FA8-A758-E19CE3B940D4" checkinTime="1617872990080" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Sanborn, Allen F." docDate="2021" docId="C7170E171E03FFC583AF4154FE17F583" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4952.1.5.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4952 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Citroriginis elongata Sanborn 2021, n. gen., n. sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="93" masterDocId="3B2E766F1E00FFC383384400FF99F626" masterDocTitle="A new species, genus and tribe of cicada (Hemiptera: Cicadoidea: Cicadidae Tibicininae) from Chile with a list of Chilean cicada fauna" masterLastPageNumber="100" masterPageNumber="87" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" updateTime="1643435679897" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species, genus and tribe of cicada (Hemiptera: Cicadoidea: Cicadidae Tibicininae) from Chile with a list of Chilean cicada fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sanborn, Allen F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2021</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2021-04-08</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4952</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>87</mods:start>
<mods:end>100</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4952.1.5</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">5c7a8963-3269-42d4-99ef-78cf39b08ee8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">4671774</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">92743F55-797F-4FA8-A758-E19CE3B940D4</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5915568" ID-GBIF-Taxon="192733713" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5915568" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:C7170E171E03FFC583AF4154FE17F583" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C7170E171E03FFC583AF4154FE17F583" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
<subSubSection box="[151,574,1363,1390]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,574,1363,1426]" box="[151,574,1363,1390]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,574,1363,1390]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,574,1363,1390]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2021" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,403,1363,1390]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Citroriginis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongata" status="n. gen., n. sp.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,403,1363,1390]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Citroriginis elongata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[410,574,1364,1390]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" rank="species">n. gen., n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,235,1400,1426]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,574,1363,1426]" box="[151,235,1400,1426]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
(
<figureCitation box="[160,224,1400,1426]" captionStart="FIGURE 1" captionStartId="5.[151,250,1807,1831]" captionTargetBox="[151,1435,181,1784]" captionTargetId="figure-16@5.[151,1435,181,1784]" captionTargetPageId="5" captionText="FIGURE 1. Citroriginis elongata n. gen., n. sp.: A, holotype male; B, holotype male dorsum; C, holotype male wings, arrows identify origins of fore wing median vein 3 + 4 and base of cubitus anterior; D, holotype male operculum; E, holotype male lateral abdominal tergites 1 and 2 illustrating absence of timbal organ; F, holotype male lateral view of genitalia; G, paratype male posterior view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 1 cm; C, 2 mm; D–G, 1 mm." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4671776" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4671776/files/figure.png" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Fig. 1</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="90" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,1472,2039]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,325,1472,1498]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3459580303" box="[332,1094,1472,1499]" collectingDate="1952-11-25" collectionCode="V, MSUC" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" specimenCount="1" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[332,440,1472,1498]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Holotype</typeStatus>
. “Angol-Chile / 
<date box="[624,770,1472,1499]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" value="1952-11-25">
<collectingDate box="[624,770,1472,1499]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" value="1952-11-25">25 Nov 1952</collectingDate>
</date>
/ 
<collectionCode box="[791,811,1473,1499]" country="Canada" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:13946" name="Royal British Columbia Museum - Herbarium" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" type="Museum">V</collectionCode>
. Delpino” male (
<collectionCode box="[1000,1086,1472,1498]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">MSUC</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3459580305" collectingDate="1948-12-02" collectingDateMax="1953-10" collectingDateMin="1948-12-02" collectionCode="MSUC, AFSC" collectorName="J. D. Imos" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" specimenCount="1" typeStatus="paratype">
<typeStatus box="[1111,1224,1473,1499]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Paratypes</typeStatus>
. “ANGOL-CHILE / 
<date box="[165,288,1508,1534]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" value="1948-12-02">
<collectingDate box="[165,288,1508,1534]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" value="1948-12-02">2 Dic 1948</collectingDate>
</date>
/ Bello” male and female exuvia on same pin (
<collectionCode box="[806,892,1508,1534]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">MSUC</collectionCode>
); “Angol-Chile / 
<date box="[1083,1236,1508,1535]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" value="1953-10">
<collectingDate box="[1083,1236,1508,1535]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" value="1953-10">Octubre 1953</collectingDate>
</date>
/ 
<collectorName box="[1256,1366,1508,1535]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">J.D. Imos</collectorName>
” male (
<collectionCode box="[159,235,1544,1570]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">AFSC</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[199,1350,1580,1607]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,1472,2039]" box="[199,1350,1580,1607]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,334,1580,1606]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Etymology.</emphasis>
The name is in reference to the elongated fore wing medial cell (L. 
<emphasis box="[1096,1205,1580,1606]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">elongatus</emphasis>
, prolonged).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="93" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,1472,2039]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,345,1616,1642]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Description.</emphasis>
Ground color tawny, castaneous in one 
<typeStatus box="[793,892,1617,1643]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">paratype</typeStatus>
, head marked with piceous and ochraceous, thorax marked with piceous and castaneous, abdomen piceous marked with castaneous and ochraceous. Body covered with long and short golden pile.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,1472,2039]" lastBlockId="4.[151,1437,151,1977]" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="91" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
<emphasis box="[199,267,1724,1750]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Head.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3459580304" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="91" location="Antennal" municipality="Anteclypeus" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" specimenCount="2" stateProvince="Chin" typeStatus="paratype">
Head not as wide as mesonotum, dorsal head piceous except ground color supra-antennal plate and anteromedial corner of vertex and triangular ochraceous mark in posterior epicranial suture, short golden pile and radiating long golden pile on dorsal head, denser long pile posterior to eye. Ocelli rosaceous, ochraceous in one 
<typeStatus box="[151,250,1833,1859]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">paratype</typeStatus>
, eyes dark castaneous. Gena piceous with ground color margin, lorum piceous anteromedially surrounded by castaneous with ground color margin, short silvery pile and radiating long silvery pile on lorum and gena. Postclypeus with ground color transverse ridges and lateral margin, only short ridge on dorsum and medial portion of neighboring ridge castaneous, 11 transverse ridges, transverse grooves, central sulcus and most of dorsum piceous, piceous expanding onto lateral transverse ridges in one 
<typeStatus box="[766,865,1977,2003]" pageId="3" pageNumber="90">paratype</typeStatus>
, long silvery pile radiating from postclypeus. 
<collectingMunicipality pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Anteclypeus</collectingMunicipality>
piceous with ground color carina and castaneous post on anterior midline, covered with short and radiating long silvery pile. 
<collectingRegion box="[344,439,151,177]" country="Myanmar" name="Chin" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Mentum</collectingRegion>
castaneous, labium piceous with castaneous midline proximally, rostrum radiating golden pile, reaching to middle trochanters. 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:C7170E171E03FFC583AF4154FE17F583:4A61E9DA1E04FFC7810D44BBFD05F6F3" box="[565,668,187,213]" municipality="Anteclypeus" name="Antennal" pageId="4" pageNumber="91" stateProvince="Chin">Antennal</location>
segments castaneous except ground color distal scape, distal flagellum ground color in some antennae but not consistent even in an individual
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
<emphasis box="[199,288,259,285]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Thorax.</emphasis>
Pronotum ground color with ochraceous anterior margin, piceous fascia on either side of midline fusing anteriorly and expanding anterolaterally into triangular mark and posterior to posteromedial paramedian fissure, piceous within paramedian connecting to midline fascia and lateral fissure connecting to piceous ambient fissure, mark in paramedian fissure expanding posteriorly onto middle disk parallel to midline fascia, posterolateral expansion of mark in lateral fissure onto middle of lateral disk. Pronotal collar ground color, castaneous along lateral ambient fissure connecting across lateral collar to castaneous margin of pronotal collar lateral angle. Pronotum covered with short golden pile and radiating long golden pile. Mesonotum ground color, submedian sigillae piceous, lateral sigillae piceous with castaneous posteromedial region, castaneous mark on lateral margin near anterior, piceous posterior to submedian sigillae including scutal depressions and between anterior arms of cruciform elevation, ground color mark between submedian and lateral sigillae curving mediad around posterior submedian sigillae, extending posteriorly to posterior margin, extending mediad forming X on cruciform elevation, lateral cruciform elevation piceous, wing groove ground color with castaneous spot anterolaterally connecting to castaneous medial margin. Metanotum ground color dorsolaterally and posteriorly, castaneous spot on dorsal midline and within wing groove, short piceous fascia anterior to posterolateral margin. Dorsum with short golden pile and radiating long golden pile, long pile denser between anterior arms of cruciform elevation, between anterior and posterior arms of cruciform elevation, on posterior mesonotum, and in wing groove. Ventral thoracic segments ground color except castaneous basisternum 2, trochantin 2, meron 2, basisternum 3, medial episternum 3 and trochantin 3, covered with short silvery pile and radiating long silvery pile.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
<emphasis box="[199,275,907,932]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Wings.</emphasis>
Fore wings and hind wings hyaline with eight and five apical cells respectively. Venation ground color proximally, becoming castaneous distally, greenish tinge to basal veins in 
<typeStatus box="[986,1087,943,969]" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">holotype</typeStatus>
, costal margin with castaneous margin, castaneous mark proximal to basal cell, on wing base, basal subcostal &amp; radius vein, distal cubitus posterior, and anal vein 2 + 3 castaneous. Basal cell about three times longer than broad. Pterostigma absent. Basal membrane of fore wing grayish mottled with orange. Hind wing venation similarly colored with castaneous on wing base. Basal plaga, anal cell 3 along anal vein 3 to terminal curve, anal cell 2 along anal veins 2 and 3 to terminal curve, and anal cell 1 along proximal anal vein 2 margined with grayish mottled with orange, infuscation in anal cell 3 and anal cell 2 bordering grayish area.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
<emphasis box="[199,260,1195,1220]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Legs.</emphasis>
Legs castaneous, coxae, trochanters and femora striped with ground color and with ground color distal termini, fore tibiae with incomplete ground color fascia, amount of ground color increasing in middle and posterior legs, tibial spurs and tibial combs ground color with castaneous tips, fore and middle tarsi castaneous with ground color proximal pretarsus, hind tarsi ground color with castaneous dorsal mesotarsus and distal pretarsus, pretarsal claws castaneous. Fore femora with primary spine angled to femur, almost as long as secondary spine, secondary spine with expanded base, longest, upright, and small tertiary spine angled to greatest degree, all spines dark castaneous. Legs with short silvery and radiating long silvery pile. Male meracanthus ochraceous with castaneous base, parallel sided at base with triangular terminus, reaching beyond operculum posterior margin to middle of sternite II.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
<emphasis box="[199,311,1519,1545]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Opercula.</emphasis>
Male opercula ochraceous with dark castaneous spot on lateral base, lateral margin straight, obtusely angled posterolateral margin, posterior margin slightly curved, angled posteromedially, medial margin rounded, anteromedial margin concave to base, not reaching to anterior of sternite II posteriorly, well separated medially barely reaching lateral meracanthus, covered with short silvery pile, long silvery pile radiating from operculum margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[151,1437,151,1977]" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">
<emphasis box="[199,313,1663,1689]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="91">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Abdominal tergite 1 piceous with castaneous lateral region appearing to cover rudimentary timbal, tergites 2–8 piceous anteriorly bordered posteriorly with castaneous and ground color posterior and lateral margins, tergites 1 and 2 piceous on dorsal midline, tergites covered with short golden pile, very dense on lateral tergites 1 and 2. Timbal and timbal cover absent. Male sternites I and II castaneous medially, ground color laterally, sternite II with castaneous anterolateral margin in middle of tympanal cavity and piceous auditory capsule, sternites III–VI dark castaneous with ground color posterior margin, percentage of ground color sternite decreasing in posterior sternites, sternite VI castaneous. Epipleurites ground color with central dark castaneous spot. Sternite VIII dark castaneous, V-shaped when viewed from posterior. Sternites and epipleurites with short silvery pile and radiating long silvery pile, longer on sternites VII and VIII.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4671776" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4671776" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4671776/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="92" startId="5.[151,250,1807,1831]" targetBox="[151,1435,181,1784]" targetPageId="5">
<paragraph blockId="5.[151,1436,1807,1940]" pageId="5" pageNumber="92">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,275,1807,1831]" pageId="5" pageNumber="92">FIGURE 1.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2021" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2021" box="[282,496,1808,1832]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Citroriginis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="92" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongata" status="n. gen., n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[282,496,1808,1832]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="92">Citroriginis elongata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[502,643,1808,1832]" pageId="5" pageNumber="92">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[502,643,1808,1832]" pageId="5" pageNumber="92" rank="species">n. gen., n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
: A, holotype male; B, holotype male dorsum; C, holotype male wings, arrows identify origins of fore wing median vein 3 + 4 and base of cubitus anterior; D, holotype male operculum; E, holotype male lateral abdominal tergites 1 and 2 illustrating absence of timbal organ; F, holotype male lateral view of genitalia; G, paratype male posterior view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 1 cm; C, 2 mm; D–G, 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1437,151,933]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">
<emphasis box="[199,313,151,177]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">Genitalia.</emphasis>
Male pygofer castaneous anteriorly, piceous posteriorly, distal shoulder undeveloped, smoothly curved, not reaching to anal tube, dorsal beak small, pointed, separated from distal shoulders, pygofer with short golden pile dorsally and posteriorly. Upper pygofer lobe absent, pygofer basal lobes elongated, curving, extending more than half pygofer length, widening to triangular apex, apex against lateral pygofer margin, adpressed to lateral pygofer. Anal styles dark castaneous radiating short golden pile, anal tube dark castaneous with ochraceous posterior margin. Median uncus lobe dark castaneous, elongated, undivided, distal portion angled ventrally, parallel sided for proximal half, tapering to rounded posterior margin, small ridge on dorsal surface midline, ventral surface meeting along midline except for small hole near distal terminus where aedeagus extends. Terminal aedeagus hidden within uncus in 
<typeStatus box="[378,426,439,465]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">type</typeStatus>
series, basal aedeagus tubular, dark castaneous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1437,151,933]" box="[199,426,475,501]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">Female is unknown.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1437,151,933]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,454,510,537]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">Measurements (mm).</emphasis>
N = 
<specimenCount box="[513,602,511,537]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93" type="male">3 males</specimenCount>
, mean (range). Length of body: 15.77 (15.35–16.30); length of fore wing: 18.00 (17.60–18.75); width of fore wing: 7.25 (6.85–7.55); length of head: 2.62 (2.50–2.75); width of head including eyes: 5.05 (4.95–5.10); width of pronotum including suprahumeral plates: 5.90 (5.50–6.20); width of mesonotum: 5.18 (5.00–5.30).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="93" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1437,151,933]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,322,654,680]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
The new species can be distinguished from all other 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Distant" authorityYear="1905" box="[916,1043,655,681]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="93" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Tibicininae">Tibicininae</taxonomicName>
except the 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Kato" authorityYear="1932" box="[1171,1306,655,681]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="93" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="tribe" tribe="Platypediini">Platypediini</taxonomicName>
by the lack of timbal organs in the male. Additional diagnostic characters include the supra-antennal plate extending less than the half distance to the eye, the fore wing median vein 3 + 4 arises just distal to the arculus and the base of the cubitus anterior arises near the proximal base of the basal cell, the widened central region of ulnar cell 3, the long, curving medial cell of the fore wing, the fore wing median vein reaching almost to the distal end of apical cell 8, and the well developed and recurving basal pygofer lobes,
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="93" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1437,151,933]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,353,870,896]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">Distribution.</emphasis>
The species is known only from the 
<typeStatus box="[766,814,871,897]" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">type</typeStatus>
series collected in Angol, Malleco Province, 
<collectingRegion country="Chile" name="Araucania" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">Araucanía Region</collectingRegion>
, central 
<collectingCountry box="[329,393,907,933]" name="Chile" pageId="6" pageNumber="93">Chile</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>