<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566" ID-GBIF-Dataset="eefaafbb-9c99-458a-b139-c4f7943c6303" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127856744" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-1324-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1860-1324-1" ModsDocOrigin="Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift 61 (1)" ModsDocTitle="A review of the genus Oosternum Sharp of the West Indies (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae: Sphaeridiinae)" checkinTime="1418151709527" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Deler-Hernandez, Albert, Cala-Riquelme, Franklyn &amp; Fikacek, Martin" docDate="2014" docId="8829DD1F062CD54313124C3473BE861E" docLanguage="en" docName="DeutEntomolZeit 61(1): 43-63" docOrigin="Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift 61 (1)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566" docTitle="Oosternum megnai Deler-Hernandez, Cala-Riquelme &amp; Fikacek, 2014, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="43" masterDocId="FFECFFA4FFFEFFE7FFD46645CE45FFFA" masterDocTitle="A review of the genus Oosternum Sharp of the West Indies (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae: Sphaeridiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="63" masterPageNumber="43" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" updateTime="1643528765522" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of the genus Oosternum Sharp of the West Indies (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae: Sphaeridiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Deler-Hernandez, Albert</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cala-Riquelme, Franklyn</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fikacek, Martin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>61</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>63</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-1324-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127856744" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:8829DD1F062CD54313124C3473BE861E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8829DD1F062CD54313124C3473BE861E" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/E11CD275-C61D-42D2-BBDD-D8258ED20B73" class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Oosternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oosternum megnai" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="megnai">Oosternum megnai</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="43">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 13-14253245515861
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="type-locality">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Type-locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Cuba, Granma Province: PN Turquino, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="92" value="20.015">20°0.9'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="92" value="-76.888336">76°53.3'W</geoCoordinate>
, slope below Pico Naranjo ca. 0.4 km N of La Platica (by air), 950 m.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="type-specimens">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Type-specimens</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
(13 spec.). Holotype male, dry mounted, with genitalia mounted in Euparal on a microslide attach to the specimens. Original label: &quot;CUBA: Granma: PN Turquino, slope below Pico Naranjo ca. 04 km N of La Platica (by air), 24.vi.2012, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Deler-Hernández">Deler-Hernandez</normalizedToken>
&amp; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Fikáček">Fikacek</normalizedToken>
leg. 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="92" value="20.015">20°0.9'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="92" value="-76.888336">76°53.3'W</geoCoordinate>
, elevation 950 m, MF23 [printed] / Holotype, Oosternum megnai sp. n., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Deler-Hernández">Deler-Hernandez</normalizedToken>
&amp; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Fikáček">Fikacek</normalizedToken>
det. 2013 [red, printed]&quot; (NMPC). Paratypes CUBA: Granma province: same data as holotype (12 spec., NMPC, CMN, SEMC, BSC-E, BMNH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Body widest ca at midlength. Lateral margin of pronotum angulate. Punctation uniform in size, moderately dense, consisting of small, rasp-like punctures. Pronotal interstices without microsculpture. Mesal part of prosternum not divided from lateral portions. Lateral margin of antennal grooves rounded. Elytral interval 2 narrower than interval 3, as high as intervals 1 and 3, reaching elytral apex. Elytral intervals 5, 7 and 9 as convex as adjacent intervals. Elytral interstices shiny, without microsculpture. Preepisternal plate narrow, drop-like, 2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide. Interstices of median part of metaventrite without microsculpture. Anterolateral ridges of metaventrite not meeting together mesally. Parameres 0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than phallobase, bearing two long setae apically. Median lobe longer than parameres, oval in shape, with small apical projection. Membranous lateral projections of median lobe absent.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Habitus. Body elongate oval, gradually narrowing posteriad; total length/total width ratio = 1.9. Length: 1.47-1.49 mm, length of holotype: 1.32 mm; width: 0.75-0.82 mm, width of holotype: 0.8 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Coloration. Coloration of dorsal side brown to dark brown, head, pronotum and elytra dark brown. Ventral side light brown. Femora, tibiae, tarsi and antennomeres and light brown, antennal club dark brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Head. Clypeus with moderately dense punctation consisting of fine punctures, each puncture bearing fine decumbent seta; setae pale; interstices without microsculpture; anterior margin of clypeus truncate. Frons with dense punctation consisting of small, punctures of same shape medially and laterally; interstices without microsculpture. Eyes moderately large. Mentum 1.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long, anterior margin deeply emarginate; anteromedian part not distinctly impressed; with sparse punctation, punctation consisting of minute, nearly indistinct punctures bearing minute setae; interstices with fine microsculpture consisting of transverse ridges. Submentum without poriferous disc-like fields. Maxillary palpus with palpomeres 2 and 4 ca. 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than palpomere 3. Antenna with 9 antennomeres; scapus shorter than antennomeres 2-6 combined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Prothorax. Pronotum evenly convex forming continuous curve with elytra in lateral view. Lateral margin of pronotum angulate; with narrow marginal bead. Pronotal punctation uniform in size, moderately dense, as dense as that on frons; consisting of small rasp-like punctures, slightly sparser laterally than medially; all punctures bearing long setae; interstices without microsculpture. Median portion of prosternum not elevated and demarcated from lateral portions, median carina of prosternum narrow, projecting more anteriad mesally than anterior margin of median portion, with anterior portion elevated into small tooth in lateral view. Postero-mesal projection with shallow notch. Antennal grooves moderately large. Lateral margin of antennal grooves rounded.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Mesothorax. Scutellar shield bearing a few small, rasp-like punctures; interstices without microsculpture. Elytral series 1-5 and 8 arising basally, series 6-7 and 9 joint subbasally. Serial punctures small; transverse; sparsely arranged, with minute setae (indistinct under binocular microscope). Elytral interval 2 narrower than interval 3, as high as intervals 1 and 3, reaching elytral apex, intervals 5, 7 and 9 as convex as adjacent intervals. Elytral interstices shiny, without microsculpture. Preepisternal plate narrow, drop-like, 2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, widely attached to metaventrite; posterior part of preepisternal elevation slightly overlapping over anterior margin of metaventrite; median part flat; bearing densely arranged, large, shallow setiferous punctures; interstices without microsculpture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Metathorax. Metaventrite distinctly longer than preepisternal elevation of mesothorax, median portion markedly differing from lateral portion in punctation and microsculpture; punctation of median portion sparse consisting of small rounded punctures, interstices without microsculpture, shiny. Anterolateral ridges bent posteriad along lateral margin of metaventrite, concave laterally, not meeting together mesally. Anterior margin of metaventrite not crenulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Abdomen. Ventrite 1 with additional longitudinal ridges laterally. Ventrites 2-5 without longitudinal ridges; posterior margin of all ventrites lacking denticles.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Male genitalia. Aedeagus 0.52 mm long, parameres 0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than phallobase. Parameres continuously narrowing apicad, bearing two long setae apically. Phallobase narrow, 2.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide. Median lobe longer than parameres, oval in shape, with small apical projection. Membranous lateral projections of median lobe absent. Gonopore absent.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">The new species is dedicated to our excellent colleague and friend Yoandri S. Megna (Universidad de Oriente, Santiago de Cuba, Cuba).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Oosternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oosternum megnai" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="megnai">Oosternum megnai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is the Cuban endemic species currently known only from the type locality in the southeastern part of the island (Granma province) (Fig. 61). The locality is situated in the Sierra Maestra mountain range which is considered one of the main centers of diversity in Cuba (
<bibRefCitation author="CENAP," journalOrPublisher="Ministerio de Ciencia, Tecnologia y Medio Ambiente" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" title="Areas protegidas de Cuba" year="2004">CENAP 2004</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Specimens of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Oosternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oosternum megnai" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="megnai">Oosternum megnai</taxonomicName>
were collected in dry leaf litter in the secondary forest.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>