<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e8e04fdf-7ade-4df5-9a33-951aa243f7b3" ID-GBIF-Taxon="139438646" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-724-101" ID-ZBK="5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:609975D1-CEAB-4D9A-8966-DBAEF8FAE4A4" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-724-101" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 724" ModsDocTitle="Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)" checkinTime="1513881619487" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Rong, Hua &amp; Li, Houhun" docDate="2017" docId="450003D42A1F21626D4A3CF687366EB2" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 724: 101-118" docOrigin="ZooKeys 724" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262" docTitle="Locastra solivaga Rong &amp; Li, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="609975D1-CEAB-4D9A-8966-DBAEF8FAE4A4" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="111" masterDocId="A540DC10FF9A2C5FFFF07461FF83FF84" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="118" masterPageNumber="101" pageId="8" pageNumber="109" updateTime="1643574149427" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Rong, Hua</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Houhun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>724</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>101</mods:start>
<mods:end>118</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-724-101</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="139438646" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:609975D1-CEAB-4D9A-8966-DBAEF8FAE4A4" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/450003D42A1F21626D4A3CF687366EB2" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="8" pageNumber="109">
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="109" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="109">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/609975D1-CEAB-4D9A-8966-DBAEF8FAE4A4" class="Insecta" family="Pyralidae" genus="Locastra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Locastra solivaga" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="solivaga">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="109" start="start">Locastra</pageBreakToken>
solivaga
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="8" pageNumber="109">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 7, 12
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="110" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
material.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
Holotype: ♂ - CHINA, Laofoyan (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="28.35">28°21'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="118.683334">118°41'E</geoCoordinate>
), Shuangxikou, Jiangshan, Zhejiang, 424 m, 7.VIII.2016, coll. Qingyun Wang, Meiqing Yang and Ping Liu, slide No. RH16458.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Paratype: - Fujian: 1♂, Guadun, Wuyishan, 1100 m, 29.VII.2008, coll. Weichun Li, Yongling Sun and Haiyan Bai, slide No. RH16484.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
This species is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. muscosalis" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" rank="species" species="muscosalis">L. muscosalis</taxonomicName>
in the forewing pattern. It can be distinguished in male genitalia by the sub-rectangular uncus nearly 5.0 times as long as wide at maximum and the valva without a process at the base of the ventral margin. In 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. muscosalis" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" rank="species" species="muscosalis">L. muscosalis</taxonomicName>
, the inverted sub-trapezoidal uncus is approximately 1.5 times as long as wide at maximum, and the valva bears a triangular process at the base of the ventral margin (Fig. 13).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="110">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="9" pageNumber="110">
Adult (Fig. 7) wingspan 31.0-33.0 mm. Frons black, vertex yellowish fuscous mixed with yellowish white. Labial palpus grayish green mixed with black; first segment white basally, approx 1/4 length of second; second segment reaching vertex apically, inner side with dark grayish green hair-like scales shortening from base to tip; third segment short, approx 1/7 length of second, tapering, dirty white at apex. Maxillary palpus compressed, short, white mixed with fuscous on basal half, grayish green on distal half. Antenna with ventral surface brownish yellow, with short pale gray cilia; dorsal surface white; scape extension extremely short, sub-globose, reaching before patagium, with yellowish fuscous scales. Thorax and tegula dirty white mixed with black, or black mixed with dirty white and fuscous. Forewing with basal 1/3 black, mixed with reddish fuscous on posterior half; distal 2/3 pale grayish green, suffused with black and reddish fuscous scales, with more reddish fuscous scales near dorsum medially; antemedian line black, extending from 1/3 of costal margin slightly arched outward to near middle of wing, then arched outward to 2/5 of dorsum; postmedian line black, running from 2/3 of costal margin, slightly arched outward to anterior 1/4 from costa, then obliquely outward to CuA1, inward to CuP, finally straight to 3/4 of dorsum; glandular swelling large, yellowish fuscous; black mixed with reddish fuscous tuft placed below middle of lower margin of cell; discocellular spot small, represented by black mixed with reddish fuscous tuft; terminal line dirty white, with uniform black rectangular spots evenly spaced along its inner side, interrupted with dirty white on veins. Hindwing gray, darkening from base toward apex; postmedian line ill-defined, grayish white, running from 2/3 of costal margin obliquely outward to CuA2, then inward to 2A. Cilia of both wings grayish white with pale red, interrupted with black on extension of veins. Legs grayish white on inner side; on outer side, fore femur white mixed with black and reddish fuscous, tibia black mixed with grayish green and fuscous, tarsus grayish green mixed with black, mid femur black mixed with fuscous, tibia with basal 2/3 black, distal 1/3 white mixed with grayish green, with grayish white hair-like scales, tarsus grayish green mixed with black, hind 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="111" start="start">leg</pageBreakToken>
black mixed with white, tibia with grayish white hair-like scales, all tarsi white at apex of each tarsomere.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Male genitalia (Fig. 12). Uncus narrowly elongate, nearly 5.0 times longer than wide, slightly narrowed medially, obtuse apically, distal 1/3 with dense short setae dorsally. Gnathos arms slender, joined from 3/5; distal process tapering to hooked apex. Valva relatively narrow, approximately 3.0 times as long as maximum width, with dense long hairs; costa reaching apex of valva; ventral margin obtusely arched, with narrow band from ventrobasal corner to base of juxta approximately 0.7 times length of ventral margin. Vinculum as long as uncus. Juxta dilated proximally, basal 2/5 separated, lateral arms straight and parallel; distal 3/5 merged sub-rectangularly, concave in V shape on posterior margin; posterolateral lobe sub-rectangular, almost membranous, with short hairs; slender lateral arm extending from middle at right angle to vinculum. Phallus approximately as long as valva; sub-ovate plates subapical, dorsal plate smaller; cornutus long, slightly curved, distally enlarged.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Female unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="111" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">China (Fujian, Zhejiang).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="111" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="111">The specific name is derived from the Latin solivagus, referring to the narrow and elongate uncus.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>