<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.285.4286" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b159f98c-9341-46c6-928e-4731e2bf9afa" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152042307" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-285-23" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-285-23" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 285" ModsDocTitle="Genus Promalactis Meyrick (Lepidoptera, Oecophoridae) from China: Descriptions of twelve new species" checkinTime="1451247457359" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Du, Zhaohui &amp; Wang, Shuxia" docDate="2013" docId="ABA79510C812AB1B910697E2E1CBF202" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 285: 23-52" docOrigin="ZooKeys 285" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.285.4286" docTitle="Promalactis papillata Du &amp; Wang, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="29" masterDocId="FFBEDA114A45FFD6FFBF01285453FFED" masterDocTitle="Genus Promalactis Meyrick (Lepidoptera, Oecophoridae) from China: Descriptions of twelve new species" masterLastPageNumber="52" masterPageNumber="23" pageId="5" pageNumber="28" updateTime="1643534505424" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Genus Promalactis Meyrick (Lepidoptera, Oecophoridae) from China: Descriptions of twelve new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Du, Zhaohui</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wang, Shuxia</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>285</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>23</mods:start>
<mods:end>52</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.285.4286</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.285.4286</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-285-23</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152042307" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:ABA79510C812AB1B910697E2E1CBF202" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/ABA79510C812AB1B910697E2E1CBF202" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="29" pageId="5" pageNumber="28">
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="28" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="28">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EE5F3D8B-F17C-4C49-A750-C8FF6D610523" class="Insecta" family="Oecophoridae" genus="Promalactis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Promalactis papillata" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="papillata">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="28" start="start">Promalactis</pageBreakToken>
papillata
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="5" pageNumber="28">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 31931
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="28" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="28">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="28">
Holotype ♂ − China, Zhejiang Province: Zhonglieci, Mt. Tianmu (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="30.316668">30°19'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="118.45">118°27'E</geoCoordinate>
), 400 m, 27.VII.2011, coll. Linlin Yang &amp; Na Chen, genitalia slide No. DZH12147 (NKU); Paratypes − 1 ♂, 3 ♀, same data as holotype except dated 25−27.VII.2011 (NKU). Anhui Province: 1 ♀, Julongsi, Mt. Jiuhua, 23.VII.1979, coll. Sizheng Wang (IOZ), genitalia slide Nos. DZH11097 ♀, DZH12137 ♀, DZH12196 ♀, DZH12206 ♂.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="28" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="28">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="28">
This species is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Oecophoridae" genus="Promalactis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Promalactis scorpioidea" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="scorpioidea">Promalactis scorpioidea</taxonomicName>
sp. n.It can be separated by the uncus with two small lateral papillary processes at distal 1/3, and the left sacculus having a strong spine-like process at distal 2/5; the lamella postvaginalis produced to a trapezoidal or quadrangular process on the dorsal surface and to a short quadrangular process on the ventral surface. In 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Oecophoridae" genus="Promalactis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Promalactis scorpioidea" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="scorpioidea">Promalactis scorpioidea</taxonomicName>
sp. n., the uncus is trilobed distally, the left sacculus has a subrectangular process at distal 1/3; the lamella postvaginalis lacks the process posteriorly. This species is also similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Oecophoridae" genus="Promalactis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Promalactis brevivalvaris" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="brevivalvaris">Promalactis brevivalvaris</taxonomicName>
Wang, Li &amp; Zheng, 2000, but the latter can be distinguished by the uncus without papillary process at basal 2/3, with three pointed processes on the posterior margin which are absent in the new species, and the short cornutus about 1/3 the length of the aedeagus, which is 3/5 the length of the aedeagus in the new species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="29" pageId="5" pageNumber="28" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="28">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="28">Adult (Fig. 3). Wingspan 9.0−12.0 mm. Head with vertex shining white, frons and occiput yellowish brown. Labial palpus with basal and second segments ochreous brown on outer surface, light yellow on inner surface; third segment dark ochreous brown, almost same length as second. Antenna with scape white except dark brown on anterior and posterior margins; flagellum white and black on dorsal surface, dark brown on ventral surface. Thorax and tegula ochreous brown. Forewing dark orange yellow, markings white edged with black scales; narrow fascia from costal 2/3 obliquely inwards to end of fold, its anterior 1/2 broad subtriangular; orange yellow from outer margin of fascia to termen; two streaks arising from dorsal margin: basal streak from dorsal 1/5 to base of fold, straight, second streak from dorsal 1/2 to basal 1/3 of upper margin of cell, sinuate; cilia yellow. Hindwing and cilia dark grey.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="29" pageId="5" pageNumber="28">
Male genitalia (Fig. 19). Uncus with basal 2/3 broad and parallel sided, with a small, setose, papillary process at basal 2/3 laterally, distal 1/3 narrowed, posterior margin emarginate or narrowly rounded. Gnathos about 3/5 length of uncus, narrow tongue shaped, scobinate, apex narrowly rounded; lateral arm band shaped, slightly shorter than gnathos. Tegumen branched from posterior 1/3, triangularly narrowed anteriorly. Valva with costa slightly concave at base, apex blunt, asymmetrical; left valva almost parallel dorso-ventrally, slight longer than right valva; sacculus broad at base, gradually narrowed to pointed apex, exceeding end of valva, setose medially, strongly dentate and setose along distal 2/5 dorsally, with a heavily sclerotized, strong spine-like 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="29" start="start">process</pageBreakToken>
at distal 2/5, which is oblique toward basad; right valva broad basally, slightly narrowed distally; sacculus almost same width except narrowed distally, setose medially, dentate and setose along distal 1/4 dorsally, with a heavily sclerotized, upright, triangular process at distal 1/4, with a small apical spine. Saccus about twice length of uncus, broad at base, slightly narrowed to basal 1/3, distal 2/3 nearly finger-like, rounded at apex. Juxta sclerotized, a large quadrangular plate. Aedeagus curved, about 1.6 times length of left valva, sclerotized distally; cornutus long and curved, spine-like, about 3/5 length of aedeagus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="29">Female genitalia (Fig. 31). Apophysis anterioris about 1/2 length of apophysis posterioris. Lamella postvaginalis large and heavily sclerotized, columniform, sometimes narrowed anteriorly; posteriorly produced to a trapezoidal or quadrangular process on dorsal surface and a short quadrangular process on ventral surface: dorsal process rounded on posterior margin, or concave in V shape at middle and forming two small hill-like lateral processes; ventral process about 2/5 length of dorsal one, slightly concave on posterior margin. Antrum nearly funnelform. Ductus bursae long and coiled, about four times length of corpus bursae, sclerotized except small membranous posterior and anterior sections, dorsally with a sclerotized quadrate plate bearing four curved long spines on right side at posterior 1/6, ventrally with a cluster of short spines at posterior 1/6; ductus seminalis arising from near posterior end of ductus bursae. Corpus bursae rounded, membranous, with dense granules; signum absent.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="29" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="29">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="29">China (Anhui, Zhejiang).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="29" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="29">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="29">The specific name is derived from Latin papillatus (= having papillary process), referring to the uncus having a small papillary process at basal 2/3 laterally.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>