<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.804.28988" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f4a65643-a4cf-4e4a-b06a-5ec49f5d9ffc" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154126536" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-804-1" ID-ZBK="5D24427CBC394FCAB2D72499C444A09F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:358E21B7-E2BD-446F-BA28-2F1DFEFCA3A4" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-804-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 804" ModsDocTitle="The incredible diversity of Labiobaetis Novikova &amp; Kluge in New Guinea revealed by integrative taxonomy (Ephemeroptera, Baetidae)" checkinTime="1545315530609" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Kaltenbach, Thomas &amp; Gattolliat, Jean-Luc" docDate="2018" docId="36D0B794B8F4A50B6A983E4DAB6B7DE1" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 804: 1-136" docOrigin="ZooKeys 804" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.804.28988" docTitle="Labiobaetis janae Kaltenbach &amp; Gattolliat, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="358E21B7-E2BD-446F-BA28-2F1DFEFCA3A4" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" masterDocId="FF82FFD5D7468A24CC2DA908B80AFF9B" masterDocTitle="The incredible diversity of Labiobaetis Novikova &amp; Kluge in New Guinea revealed by integrative taxonomy (Ephemeroptera, Baetidae)" masterLastPageNumber="136" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" updateTime="1643519532851" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The incredible diversity of Labiobaetis Novikova &amp; Kluge in New Guinea revealed by integrative taxonomy (Ephemeroptera, Baetidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kaltenbach, Thomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gattolliat, Jean-Luc</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>804</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>136</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.804.28988</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.804.28988</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-804-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">5D24427CBC394FCAB2D72499C444A09F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5D24427CBC394FCAB2D72499C444A09F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="154126536" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:358E21B7-E2BD-446F-BA28-2F1DFEFCA3A4" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/36D0B794B8F4A50B6A983E4DAB6B7DE1" lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
<subSubSection pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
10. 
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/358E21B7-E2BD-446F-BA28-2F1DFEFCA3A4" class="Insecta" family="Baetidae" genus="Labiobaetis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Labiobaetis janae" order="Ephemeroptera" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="janae">Labiobaetis janae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="33" pageNumber="34">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 19, 20, 59d, 64b
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<pageBreakToken pageId="34" pageNumber="35" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Larva. Following combination of characters: A) labrum dorsal arc of setae with one plus 6-7 long, simple setae; B) both mandibles with outermost denticle blade-like; C) hypopharynx with slightly concave distal margin of superlingua; D) maxillary palp somewhat longer than length of galea-lacinia; E) fore femur rather broad, length 2.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximum width, dorsal margin with a row of ca. 34 curved, spine-like setae and with some stout, pointed setae near margin; F) gills long, gill IV as long as length of segments V to VII combined, gill VII somewhat longer than length of segments VIII to X combined.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="37" lastPageNumber="38" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Larva (Figs 19, 20, 59d). Body length 8-9 mm.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Figure 19. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Baetidae" genus="Labiobaetis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Labiobaetis janae" order="Ephemeroptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="janae">Labiobaetis janae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., larva morphology: a Labrum b Right mandible c Right prostheca d Left mandible e Left prostheca f 
<taxonomicName genus="Hypopharynx" lsidName="Hypopharynx" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" rank="genus">Hypopharynx</taxonomicName>
g Maxilla h Labium.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Figure 20. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Baetidae" genus="Labiobaetis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Labiobaetis janae" order="Ephemeroptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="janae">Labiobaetis janae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., larva morphology: a 
<taxonomicName genus="Foreleg" lsidName="Foreleg" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" rank="genus">Foreleg</taxonomicName>
b Fore claw c 
<taxonomicName genus="Tergum" lsidName="Tergum" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" rank="genus">Tergum</taxonomicName>
IV d Gill IV e 
<taxonomicName genus="Paraproct" lsidName="Paraproct" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" rank="genus">Paraproct</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Colouration. Head, thorax and abdomen dorsally grey-brown, abdominal segments VI, IX and X brighter, head and thorax with bright median, dorsal suture, forewing pads with bright striation. Head, thorax and abdomen ventrally light grey-brown, legs colourless with brown medial spot and dorsal margin on femur, caudal filaments light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Antenna with scape and pedicel sub-cylindrical, without distolateral process at scape; flagellum with lanceolate spines on apex of each segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="36" pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Labrum (Fig. 19a). Rectangular, length 0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximum width. Distal margin with medial emargination and small process. Dorsally with medium, fine, simple setae scattered over surface; submarginal arc of setae composed of one plus 6-7 long, simple setae. Ventrally with marginal row of setae composed of lateral and anterolateral long, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="35" pageNumber="36" start="start">feathered</pageBreakToken>
setae and medial long, pectinate setae, centrally bifid; ventral surface with eight short, spine-like setae near lateral and anterolateral margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="36" lastPageNumber="37" pageId="35" pageNumber="36">
Right mandible (Fig. 19b, c). Incisors fused. Outer and inner sets of denticles with 3 + 3 denticles plus one minute intermediate denticle, outermost denticle blade-like. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="36" pageNumber="37" start="start">Inner</pageBreakToken>
margin of innermost denticle with a row of thin setae. Prostheca robust, apically and distolaterally denticulate. Margin between prostheca and mola straight. Tuft of setae at apex of mola present.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">Left mandible (Fig. 19d, e). Incisors fused. Outer and inner sets of denticles with 3 + 4 denticles, outermost denticle blade-like. Prostheca robust, apically with small denticles and comb-shape structure. Margin between prostheca and mola straight, with few minute setae, and with minute denticles toward subtriangular process. Subtriangular process long and slender, above level of area between prostheca and mola. Denticles of mola apically constricted. Tuft of setae at apex of mola present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">Both mandibles with lateral margins almost straight. Basal half with fine, simple setae scattered over dorsal surface.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">
<taxonomicName genus="Hypopharynx" lsidName="Hypopharynx" pageId="36" pageNumber="37" rank="genus">Hypopharynx</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 19f). Lingua about as long as superlingua. Lingua about as broad as long; medial tuft of stout setae present; distal half not expanded. Superlingua slightly concave; lateral margin rounded; fine, long, simple setae along distal margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">
Maxilla (Fig. 19g). Galea-lacinia with two simple, robust apical setae under crown. Inner dorsal row of setae with three denti-setae, distal denti-seta tooth-like, middle and proximal denti-setae slender, bifid and pectinate. Medially with one bipectinate, spine-like seta and seven long, simple setae. Maxillary palp slightly longer than length of galea-lacinia; two segmented. Palp segment II 2.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of segment I. Setae on maxillary palp fine and simple, scattered over surface of segments I and II. Apex of last segment slightly pointed, without excavation at inner distolateral margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">
Labium (Fig. 19h). Glossa basally broad, narrowing toward apex; shorter than paraglossa; inner margin with 7-8 spine-like setae increasing in length distally; apex with three long, robust, pectinate setae; outer margin with five long, spine-like setae; ventral surface with few short, fine, simple setae. Paraglossa sub-rectangular, curved inward; apex rounded; with three rows of long, robust, apically pectinate setae; dorsally with three medium, simple setae; ventrally with three long, spine-like setae near inner margin. Labial palp with segment I 0.8
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of segments II and III combined. Segment I covered with micropores dorsally. Segment II with a short, thumb-like distomedial protuberance; distomedial protuberance 0.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of base of segment III; inner and outer margin both with short, fine, simple setae; dorsally with row of five long, spine-like, simple setae. Segment III oblong; apex slightly pointed; length 1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width; ventrally covered with long and medium spine-like, simple setae and short, fine, simple setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">Hind wing pads absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="37" lastPageNumber="38" pageId="36" pageNumber="37">
<taxonomicName genus="Foreleg" lsidName="Foreleg" pageId="36" pageNumber="37" rank="genus">Foreleg</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 20a, b). Ratio of foreleg segments 1.5:1.0:0.6:0.3. Femur. Length ca. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximum width. Dorsal margin with a row of ca. 34 curved, spine-like setae and some stout, pointed setae near margin; length of setae 0.15
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximum width of femur. Apex rounded; with two pairs of curved, spine-like setae and many short, stout, pointed setae. Many stout, lanceolate setae and a few fine, simple setae along ventral margin; femoral patch absent. Tibia. Dorsal margin with few short, curved, spine-like setae and a pair of longer, curved, spine-like setae on apex. Ventral margin with a row of curved, spine-like setae and some longer, stout, pointed setae on apex. Anterior surface scattered with many stout, lanceolate setae. Tibio-patellar suture present on 
<pageBreakToken pageId="37" pageNumber="38" start="start">basal</pageBreakToken>
2/3. Tarsus. Dorsal margin with some short, spine-like setae and fine simple setae. Ventral margin with a row of curved, spine-like setae. Tarsal claw with one row of 12 denticles; distally pointed; with three stripes; subapical setae absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<taxonomicName genus="Tergum" lsidName="Tergum" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" rank="genus">Tergum</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 20c). Surface with many micropores and scattered W-shaped scale bases, scales oblong. Posterior margin of tergum IV with rounded or triangular spines, wider than long.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<taxonomicName genus="Gills" lsidName="Gills" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" rank="genus">Gills</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 20d). Present on segments II - VII. Margin with small denticles and long, fine, simple setae. Tracheae extending from main trunk to inner margin and partly to outer margin. Gill IV as long as length of segments V, VI and VII combined. Gill VII somewhat longer than length of segments VIII and X combined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
<taxonomicName genus="Paraproct" lsidName="Paraproct" pageId="37" pageNumber="38" rank="genus">Paraproct</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 20e). Distally expanded, with many marginal, stout spines. Surface with W-shaped scale bases and many micropores. Postero-lateral extension (cercotractor) with small marginal spines.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
Dedicated to Janice (
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Jan”">&quot;Jan&quot;</normalizedToken>
) Peters (Florida A &amp; M University), who pioneered the collection of mayflies in New Guinea.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="37" pageNumber="38" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">New Guinea.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="biological aspects">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
<pageBreakToken pageId="38" pageNumber="39" start="start">Biological</pageBreakToken>
aspects.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">The specimens were collected at an altitude of 3200 m a.s.l.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Type-material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
Holotype. Nymph (on slide, GBIFCH 00465181), Indonesia, Papua, Lake Habemma, stream, 3200 m, 19 Oct 2011, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-4.1295">04°07.77'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="138.6795">138°40.77'E</geoCoordinate>
, Balke (PAP07). Temporary deposited in MZL before definitely housed in MZB. Paratypes. 30 nymphs (1 on slide, GBIFCH 00465182, 19 in alcohol, GBIFCH 00515252, GBIFCH 00508126, deposited in MZL; 11 in alcohol, GBIFCH 00515253, deposited in ZSM), same data as holotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>