<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.857.34938" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ac2d4aed-872a-48ad-91e8-f8a3f51f7c7f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="158387749" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-857-59" ID-ZBK="27E52E850B31445EBC90C7D5D17C429A" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B454A4B5-CCC7-4E42-AA5E-3DED1DD0FA53" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="1313-2970-857-59" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 857" ModsDocTitle="A new genus of Pelecotominae from Mexico, with notes on the genera Clinops and Scotoscopus and the description of new species (Coleoptera, Ripiphoridae)" checkinTime="1561532591110" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Engel, Michael S., Falin, Zachary H. &amp; Batelka, Jan" docDate="2019" docId="8184225DA7CB6F44FB4F0147CF939347" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 857: 59-84" docOrigin="ZooKeys 857" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.857.34938" docTitle="Clinops perpessus Engel, Falin &amp; Batelka, 2019, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docUuid="B454A4B5-CCC7-4E42-AA5E-3DED1DD0FA53" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="59" masterDocId="FFA5CF681E502B08FFCBFFCFFF8B2238" masterDocTitle="A new genus of Pelecotominae from Mexico, with notes on the genera Clinops and Scotoscopus and the description of new species (Coleoptera, Ripiphoridae)" masterLastPageNumber="84" masterPageNumber="59" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" updateTime="1643474484075" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new genus of Pelecotominae from Mexico, with notes on the genera Clinops and Scotoscopus and the description of new species (Coleoptera, Ripiphoridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Engel, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Falin, Zachary H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Batelka, Jan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>857</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>59</mods:start>
<mods:end>84</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.857.34938</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.857.34938</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-857-59</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">27E52E850B31445EBC90C7D5D17C429A</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">27E52E850B31445EBC90C7D5D17C429A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="158387749" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B454A4B5-CCC7-4E42-AA5E-3DED1DD0FA53" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8184225DA7CB6F44FB4F0147CF939347" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="59" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/B454A4B5-CCC7-4E42-AA5E-3DED1DD0FA53" authority="Gerstaecker, 1855" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1855" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Clinops" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Clinops perpessus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perpessus">Clinops perpessus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="59">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 4-5, 6, 7, 8-11, 12-14
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="59" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
<taxonomicName family="Ripiphoridae" higherTaxonomySource="treatment-meta" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="subfamily" subfamily="Pelecotominae">Pelecotominae</taxonomicName>
new genus 2 gen. nov.: 
<bibRefCitation pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Falin 2003</bibRefCitation>
: 186.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="59" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
Differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. inexpectatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="inexpectatus">C. inexpectatus</taxonomicName>
by the only slightly elevated vertex above the pronotum (greatly elevated in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. inexpectatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="inexpectatus">C. inexpectatus</taxonomicName>
: cf. Figs 6, 7 vs. Figs 19, 23), more robust head dorso-ventrally (1.63 mm vs. 1.08 mm in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. inexpectatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="inexpectatus">C. inexpectatus</taxonomicName>
in which the head appears more flattened), elytral coloration (notably lighter basal two thirds in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. perpessus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="perpessus">C. perpessus</taxonomicName>
: cf. Figs 6, 7 vs. Figs 19, 20), by the absence of a mediolongitudinal shallow impression (furrow) in basal third of pronotal disc (present in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. inexpectatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="inexpectatus">C. inexpectatus</taxonomicName>
: cf. Fig. 7 vs. Fig. 20), by the absence of a medioapical emargination to the median lobe of the pronotal posterior border (emargination present in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. inexpectatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="inexpectatus">C. inexpectatus</taxonomicName>
), by base of pronotal disc wider than the length of the pronotal disc (pronotal disc as wide as long in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. inexpectatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="inexpectatus">C. inexpectatus</taxonomicName>
), and by the stubbier terminal maxillary palpomere (cf. Fig. 5 vs. Fig. 22). Overall, the species is more similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. badius" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="badius">C. badius</taxonomicName>
, as both species have the scarcely elevated vertex relative to the pronotum (e.g., Figs 6-7, 15-16). 
<taxonomicName authority="Gerstaecker, 1855" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1855" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Clinops" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Clinops perpessus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perpessus">Clinops perpessus</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. badius" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="badius">C. badius</taxonomicName>
most notably in the shape of the terminal maxillary palpomere (cf. Fig. 5 vs. Fig. 18), the apically darkened elytra (uniformly colored in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. badius" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="badius">C. badius</taxonomicName>
: cf. Figs 6-7 vs. Figs 15, 16), the more elongate antennal rami (cf. Fig. 4 vs. Fig. 17), and absence of a medioapical emargination to the median lobe of the pronotal posterior border (emargination present in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. badius" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="badius">C. badius</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
Figures 6, 7. 
<taxonomicName authority="Gerstaecker, 1855" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1855" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Clinops" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Clinops perpessus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perpessus">Clinops perpessus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov., holotype male. 6 lateral habitus 7 dorsal habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
Figures 8-11. Male terminalia of holotype of 
<taxonomicName authority="Gerstaecker, 1855" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1855" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Clinops" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Clinops perpessus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perpessus">Clinops perpessus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. 8 tergum VII 9 tergum VIII 10 sternum VIII 11 sternum IX.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
Figures 12-14. Male genitalia of holotype of 
<taxonomicName authority="Gerstaecker, 1855" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1855" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Clinops" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Clinops perpessus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perpessus">Clinops perpessus</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. (tegmen = phallobase + parameres / parameres = lateral lobes, gonoforceps / median lobe = aedeagues). 12 dorsal oblique view 13 lateral oblique view 14 ventral oblique view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="59" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
♂: General size and appearance typical of 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="subfamily" subfamily="Pelecotominae">Pelecotominae</taxonomicName>
. Size 9.75 mm from tip of abdomen to base of antennae, 2.54 mm wide at base of pronotum. Body largely dark brown, slightly lighter reddish brown on lateral thirds of pronotum, basal two thirds of elytra, and apical abdominal sterna (Figs 6-7).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
Head ovoid, approximately 1.02
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide in facial view, medial length 1.67 mm, maximum width (across compound eyes) 1.63 mm. Vertex convex dorsally and posteriorly, as wide as lower face (below compound eyes), rising high above compound eyes in facial view, sloping uniformly to meet and slightly overlap pronotal anterior margin, with weak medially impressed line, disappearing posteriorly. Dorsal, lateral, and facial aspects of head with fine, decumbent, golden to fuscous setae, particularly numerous on face between compound eyes and vertex, abundant on genae; integument dull, with minute, nearly contiguous punctures separated by apparently smooth to imbricate integument. Compound eye of moderate size, encompassing much of medial third of lateral surface of head, finely faceted, emarginate in upper third (emargination deeper than in 
<taxonomicName genus="Z." lsidName="Z. sumichrasti" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="sumichrasti">Z. sumichrasti</taxonomicName>
, such that compound eye nearly appears bisected in facial view: cf. Figs 3 vs. 4). Postocular gena expanded into lobe. Frons broad, with antennal torulus laterally directed, antennal toruli separated by distance equal to length of scape, compound eyes separated by distance slightly less than maximum compound eye length. Malar space elongate, more than one-half length of scape, slightly less than basal mandibular width. Mandible short, slightly curved, with short, acute subapical tooth. Maxillary palpus long, tetramerous, terminal palpomere largest, trapezoidal, its apical width slightly less than maximum length, with blunt, truncate apex, not flattened or grossly enlarged (greatly enlarged and flattened in 
<taxonomicName authority="Gerstaecker, 1855" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1855" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Ancholaemus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancholaemus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Ancholaemus</taxonomicName>
Gerstaecker and 
<taxonomicName authority="Viana, 1971" authorityName="Viana" authorityYear="1971" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Micholaemus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Micholaemus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Micholaemus</taxonomicName>
Viana), distal sensory duct elongate, strongly oblique.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
Antenna consisting of eleven antennomeres; antennomere I longer than wide, slightly curved to approximate curvature of compound eye; antennomere II short, slightly wider than long; antennomere III longer than antennomere II, length approximately 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
apical width, apical margin truncate. Antennomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–XI">IV-XI</normalizedToken>
greatly dissimilar from preceding antennomeres; antennomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–X">IV-X</normalizedToken>
with internally facing, compressed rami; bases of antennomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–X">IV-X</normalizedToken>
short and of similar lengths; rami IX and X elongate, extending to apex of antennomere XI; remaining rami progressively shorter from X to IV. Antennomere XI expanded, similar in shape to rami of preceding antennomeres. Total length of antennomere XI approximately 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of bases of antennomeres 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–X">IV-X</normalizedToken>
combined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
Pronotum with semi-decumbent to decumbent, fine, golden setae except in medial third such setae fuscous, integument dull, and weakly and contiguously punctate, with punctures more indistinct anteriorly and posteriorly, integument becoming imbricate. Pronotum triangular in shape, narrowed anteriorly; anterior margin broadly rounded; posterior margin sinuate and generally trilobed, with medial lobe scarcely broader than mesoscutellum and rounded (not emarginate: distinctly emarginate in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. inexpectatus" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="species" species="inexpectatus">C. inexpectatus</taxonomicName>
, vide infra); lateral margins generally straight, converging anteriorly, convex ventrally to propleurae; propleuron well developed. Pronotal disc wider at base than length, without mediolongitudinal carina or impression; lateral aspect with a ventrally bowed sulcus. Mesonotum obscured by elytra. Mesoscutellum (mesoscutellar shield) short, flat, parallel-sided, with broadly rounded apex; integumental sculpturing and setation as on pronotal disc. Metanotum obscured by elytra.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Lateral and ventral aspects of pterothorax typical of subfamily. Mesepisternum weakly and faintly imbricate, with scattered minute punctures, fused with mesosternum, with scattered decumbent setae. Mesepimeron forming prominent, rectangular sclerite separated from mesepisternum by deep sulcus; sculptured and setation as on mesepisternum. Metepisternum an elongate, narrow rectangular sclerite, with sculpturing and setation as on mesepisternum; metasternum massive, weakly imbricate and with decumbent setae more numerous than on metepisternum. Metepimeron slightly expanded posteriorly, extending anteriorly to wing base as narrow (slightly more narrow than metepisternum), sclerotized band; weakly imbricate with scattered setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Legs typical for subfamily; coxae, trochanters, and femora weakly, irregularly, almost indistinctly punctate on otherwise smooth integument with decumbent, golden to lightly fuscous setae; metacoxa with strongly developed posterior flange; femora without densely setose patches ventrally; tibiae straight, cylindrical, broadened slightly apically, with apex terminated by dense row of regular, thin, spiniform setae; tibial spur formula 0-0-? (hind legs missing in holotype). Tarsi 5-5-[4, metatarsus presumed to have had four tarsomeres], all tarsomeres cylindrical, very slightly tapered basally, truncate apically; integument and setae similar to tibiae; protarsus longer than protibia. Protarsomere I subequal to combined length of protarsomeres II and III, protarsomere IV less than one-half length protarsomere V; relative ratios of basal mesotarsomeres similar (apical tarsomeres of meso- and metatarsi missing in holotype). Pretarsal claws bifid, apical and inner rami both sickle-shaped and acutely pointed, without any midlength or subsidiary teeth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Elytra elongate, completely covering abdomen, surface imbricate with minute, weak, nearly contiguous punctures; elytron basal width 1.27 mm, length 8.21 mm; each elytron with four indistinct costae; lateral margins parallel-sided, lateral margin comparatively straight until tapering inward in apical fifth, medial margin nearly straight until rounding at apex; apex weakly acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Abdomen with terga weakly and faintly imbricate; sterna imbricate with scattered minute punctures, with scattered decumbent, fine setae; male terminalia as depicted in figures 8-14.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
♀: 
<taxonomicName genus="Latet" lsidName="Latet" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="genus">Latet</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="59" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
♂, [South Africa: KwaZulu-Natal: eThekwini:] Port / Natal / 49 29 [on underside of label] [no collector or date] (NHMUK). The &quot;49 29&quot; on the underside of the label corresponds to the 29th accession of 1849 (M. Barclay, pers. comm.). This accession was a collection of 1627 insects, including 965 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="order">Coleoptera</taxonomicName>
, from Port Natal, South Africa collected by Wilhelm Gueinzius (1813-1874), and sold to the Natural History Museum through Samuel 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Stevens’">Stevens'</normalizedToken>
(1817-1899) auctions at 24 Bloomsbury Street in London during December 1849 (M. Barclay, pers. comm.). Gueinzius, a German naturalist who spent most of his life in present-day South Africa, lived in the area of Port Natal (settled along the Tugela River) from 1841 until late in 1843 when he returned to Cape Town after British troops looted his home during conflict with the Zulus and Boers. He returned to the Natal area in mid-1844 and remained there until shortly before his death. Since the present specimen was auctioned and accessioned in December 1849 it can safely be presumed it was collected sometime between 1844 and this date. A handwritten label from the 19th Century accompanying the specimen reads &quot;closely resembles the figure of 
<taxonomicName authority="Gerstaecker, 1855" authorityName="Gerstaecker" authorityYear="1855" class="Insecta" family="Ripiphoridae" genus="Ancholaemus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancholaemus lyciformis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lyciformis">Ancholaemus lyciformis</taxonomicName>
, but that is from Brazil.&quot; The handwriting generally matches that of George C. Champion (1851-1927). The 
<normalizedToken originalValue="specimen’s">specimen's</normalizedToken>
terminalia were apparently dissected by the late John K. Bouseman (1936-2006) (the sclerites are stored within a genitalia vial along with the specimen), who labeled the specimen &quot; 
<taxonomicName family="Rhipiphoridae" lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="59" rank="family">Rhipiphoridae</taxonomicName>
[sic] gen. et sp. nov. ♂ Det. Bouseman '71 [1971]&quot;.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="59" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="59">
The specific epithet is taken from the Latin, meaning &quot;suffer with patience&quot; or 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“endure”">&quot;endure&quot;</normalizedToken>
, and is a reference to the vast time over which this species has awaited description.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>