<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784" ID-GBIF-Dataset="30d1c76a-41e1-4f66-9fb5-460bf381f752" ID-GBIF-Taxon="150814511" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-700-1" ID-ZBK="EBA4322720AD4CFFA04E8D2542DDA3D6" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-700-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 700" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the ant genus Melophorus (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)" checkinTime="1506009303549" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Heterick, Brian E., Castalanelli, Mark &amp; Shattuck, Steve O." docDate="2017" docId="56064A349C65D0E9C0553719C405CAFA" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 700: 1-420" docOrigin="ZooKeys 700" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784" docTitle="Melophorus curtus Forel" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="89" lastPageNumber="90" masterDocId="FF93E60CA711CB7BFF95D521FFFDFF9A" masterDocTitle="Revision of the ant genus Melophorus (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)" masterLastPageNumber="420" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" updateTime="1643476612007" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the ant genus Melophorus (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Heterick, Brian E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Castalanelli, Mark</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Shattuck, Steve O.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>700</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>420</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.700.11784</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-700-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">EBA4322720AD4CFFA04E8D2542DDA3D6</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">EBA4322720AD4CFFA04E8D2542DDA3D6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="150814511" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:56064A349C65D0E9C0553719C405CAFA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/56064A349C65D0E9C0553719C405CAFA" lastPageId="89" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
<subSubSection pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
<taxonomicName authority="Forel" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus curtus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="curtus">Melophorus curtus Forel</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus curtus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="curtus">Melophorus curtus</taxonomicName>
<bibRefCitation author="Forel, A" journalOrPublisher="Revue Suisse de Zoologie" pageId="353" pageNumber="354" pagination="405 - 548" title="Fourmis nouvelles d'Australie." url="http://dx.doi.org/10.5962/bhl.part.13793" volume="10" year="1902">Forel 1902</bibRefCitation>
: 485.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="types">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">Types.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
Syntype small major worker, MacKey, Queensland [ANIC], here designated lectotype: (examined: ANIC specimen ANIC32-053434). Also examined: syntype minor worker with same details as lectotype [ANIC], here designated a paralectotype; AntWeb images of syntype major and minor worker, MacKey, Queensland [BMNH] (CASENT0903264, CASENT0903265), here designated paralectotypes; AntWeb images of syntype major and minor worker, MacKey, Queensland [MHNG] (CASENT0909810, CASENT0909811), here designated paralectotypes. Also designated a paralectotype is a syntype queen [MHNG] (
<bibRefCitation author="Taylor, RW" editor="Walton, DW" journalOrPublisher="Geological Society Special Publication" pageId="355" pageNumber="356" title="2. Hymenoptera: Formicoidea, Vespoidea and Sphecoidea. Canberra: Australian Government Publishing Service" url="http://www.antwiki.org/wiki/images/c/c2/Taylor_%26_Brown_1985.pdf" year="1985">Taylor and Brown 1985</bibRefCitation>
), not seen.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="87" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">Other material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="87" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
New South Wales: 40 km W Hillston (Greenslade, P.J. 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="86" pageNumber="87" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
[ANIC32-900023]), Armidale (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900016]), Armidale, west of golf course (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900015]), Bogan River (Armstrong, J. [ANIC32-900017]), Bourke (Barrett, C.L. [ANIC32-900018]), Emmett Vale (Valentine [ANIC32-900020]), Hay (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900021]), Hillston, The Common (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900022]), Lachlan River, Condobolin (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900019]), Mungindi (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900024]), Round Mountain (NE NSW) (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900025]), Whiporie, 55 km S Casino (York, A. [ANIC32-900026]). Northern Territory: CSIRO TERC, Darwin (Shattuck, S.O. [ANIC32-047317]), Hills, 27 km SW Katherine (Greenslade, P.J. 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="86" pageNumber="87" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
[ANIC32-900009]), Kapalga, Alligator Rivers area (Greenslade, P.J. 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="86" pageNumber="87" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
[ANIC32-900007]), Kapalga, Kakadu National Park (Andersen, A.N. [ANIC32-900008]), Manbullo I., SW Katherine (Greenslade, P.J. 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M." pageId="86" pageNumber="87" rank="genus">M.</taxonomicName>
[ANIC32-900010]). Queensland: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘Merigol’">'Merigol'</normalizedToken>
(Beutel, T.), 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘Paingo’">'Paingo'</normalizedToken>
turnoff (Monteath &amp; Cook), 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘Wallaroo’">'Wallaroo'</normalizedToken>
Hwy; 6 km WNW (Burwell/Monteath), 33 mi SSW Tara (Dowse, J.E. [ANIC32-900014]), Blackwood NP (Monteath &amp; Cook), Blair Athol Mine (Houston, W. [ANIC32-040330]), Corry HS, 2 km SW, Retro-Corry Rd (Burwell), Fanning R Hmstd, 3.3 km SE (Monteith &amp; Cook), Illaweena St. Drewvale (QM Party), Koondooloo, Hannaford Rd North via Tara (House, A./Brown, S.), Lizard Island (Reichel, H. [ANIC32-900011]), Lolworth NP (Wright, S.), Lords Table (Burwell), Moolayember Ck NP (Wright/Burwell), Moolayember Ck NP (Wright/Burwell), Moolayember Ck NP (Wright/Burwell), Mt Castor, 0.5 km W (Burwell/Monteath), Mt Pollux, SW base (Burwell, C.), Mt Pollux, SW base (Burwell, C.), N. Stradbroke Is. Enterprise (QM Party), Proserpine, Thompson Creek (Raven &amp; Burwell), Ransome Reserve (QM Party), Redlands Hilliards Ck, nr 
<pageBreakToken pageId="87" pageNumber="88" start="start">South</pageBreakToken>
St (RHC1) (Stanisic, J.), Redlands Hilliards Ck, nr South St (RHC1) (BAAM/ QM Party), St George (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900013]), St George (Lowery, B.B. [ANIC32-900012]), Springsure, 16 km N (Monteath, G.), Tindaree, Hannaford Rd South via Tara (House, A./Brown, S.), Tindaree, Hannaford Rd South via Tara (House, A./Brown, S.), Wolfgang Peak (Burwell, C.J./ Monteath, G.). Victoria: Patho (Potter, H.A. [ANIC32-900027]), Patho (Potter, H.A. [ANIC32-039539]). Western Australia: Argyle Diamond Mine via Kununurra (Postle, A. [JDM32-004540]), Mulga, NE Goldfields (Pringle, H.J.R. [ANIC32-029573]), Packsaddle (van Leeuwen, S. [JDM32-004542]), Pilbara locality unknown (Unknown [JDM32-004539]), Tropicana minesite (Summerhayes, J. [JDM32-004541]).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="87" pageNumber="88" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus curtus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="curtus">Melophorus curtus</taxonomicName>
is a member of the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. aeneovirens" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="aeneovirens">M. aeneovirens</taxonomicName>
species-group (in full-face view, the anterior clypeal margin convex, apron-like and covering whole or part of the retracted mandible, except in 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. nemophilus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="nemophilus">M. nemophilus</taxonomicName>
, the medial clypeal sector often produced so that it is protrusive when seen in profile; the psammophore frequently with coarse and well-separated ammochaetae, these always placed on or just above anterior margin; in profile, the propodeum elongate and oblique or broadly rounded), and the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. aeneovirens" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="aeneovirens">M. aeneovirens</taxonomicName>
species-complex (in full-face view, psammophore ranged along or just above anterior margin of clypeus and following the curve of the margin; anterior margin of clypeus broadly medially produced, and often with central notch that may be deeply impressed, but is never acuminate at its midpoint; metatibia with maximum of two rows of preapical spines). In 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. curtus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="curtus">M. curtus</taxonomicName>
the tibiae possess fine, appressed pubescence in addition to stout, socketed, appressed to subdecumbent setae This species differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. sulconotus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="sulconotus">M. sulconotus</taxonomicName>
in the appearance of the mesosoma, which, in profile, has a pronotum and mesonotum that are weakly to strongly convex in the minor worker, The antennal scapes and tibiae lack bristly erect and semi-erect setae, and short, erect setae are normally sparse on dorsum of mesosoma. The head of the minor worker is oval or squared and the frontal triangle is triangular in appearance. This combination of characters separates 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. curtus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="curtus">M. curtus</taxonomicName>
from 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. gibbosus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="gibbosus">M. gibbosus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. griseus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="griseus">M. griseus</taxonomicName>
, which share the pilosity pattern seen on the metatibae in 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. curtus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="curtus">M. curtus</taxonomicName>
. Both 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. griseus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="griseus">M. griseus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. gibbosus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="gibbosus">M. gibbosus</taxonomicName>
have erect setae on the antennal scape and the tibiae. The major worker of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. curtus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="curtus">M. curtus</taxonomicName>
can also be distinguished from that of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. gibbosus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="gibbosus">M. gibbosus</taxonomicName>
(the major worker of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. griseus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="griseus">M. griseus</taxonomicName>
is unknown) by its partially shagreenate frons, the frons being microreticulate in the 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. gibbosus" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="gibbosus">M. gibbosus</taxonomicName>
major worker.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="88" lastPageNumber="89" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">Minor worker description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="88" lastPageNumber="89" pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Head. Head approximately oval with straight sides; posterior margin of head strongly convex; frons matt or with weak sheen, shagreenate; frons consisting almost completely of appressed setae that may form pubescence (tiny, erect setae, if present, usually confined to ocular triangle). Eye moderate (eye length 0.20-0.49 length of side of head capsule); in full-face view, eyes set above midpoint of head capsule; in profile, eye set anteriad of midline of head capsule; eyes elliptical or slightly reniform. In full-face view, frontal carinae concave; frontal lobes straight in front of antennal insertion. Anteromedial clypeal margin narrowly convex and protruding, clypeal margin entire or very weakly indented; clypeal psammophore set at or just above anterior clypeal margin; palp formula 6,4. Five to six mandibular teeth in 
<pageBreakToken pageId="88" pageNumber="89" start="start">minor</pageBreakToken>
worker; mandibles triangular, weakly incurved; third mandibular tooth distinctly shorter than apical tooth and teeth numbers two and four; masticatory margin of mandibles approximately vertical or weakly oblique. Mesosoma. Integument of pronotum, mesonotum and mesopleuron moderately shining and shagreenate throughout; anterior mesosoma in profile broadly convex; appearance of erect pronotal setae short, (i.e., longest erect setae shorter than length of eye) and unmodified, or erect pronotal setae absent; in profile, metanotal groove shallow, broadly V or U-shaped; propodeum shining and shagreenate; propodeum smoothly rounded or with indistinct angle; propodeal dorsum and declivity confluent; erect propodeal setae variable in number, may be absent; appressed propodeal setulae long and closely aligned, creating pubescence; propodeal spiracle situated on or beside declivitous face of propodeum, and shorter (length &lt;0.50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
height of propodeum). Petiole. In profile, petiolar node squamiform; in full-face view, shape of petiolar node square with rounded angles; node shining and distinctly shagreenate-microreticulate. Gaster. Gaster weakly shining with indistinct shagreenation; pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of thick, appressed setae that form pubescence, interspersed with numerous short, bristly, erect setae, or consisting of long, closely aligned, whitish, appressed setae, with erect setae (present in at least some workers) confined to margin of the sclerite. General characters. Colour brown, gaster slightly darker in some workers.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="89" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="88" pageNumber="89" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Major worker description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="89" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="88" pageNumber="89">
Head. Head quadrate (i.e., heart-shaped); posterior margin of head weakly concave; cuticle of frons shining with superficial shagreenation or microreticulation only; pilosity of frons a mixture of a few well-spaced, erect setae interspersed with appressed setae only. Eye small (eye length less than 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of head capsule); in full-face view, eyes set above midpoint of head capsule; in profile, eye set anteriad of midline of head capsule; eyes elliptical. In full-face view, frontal carinae concave; frontal lobes curved inward in front of antennal insertion. Anterior clypeal margin narrowly convex and protruding anteromedially, clypeal midpoint notched; clypeal psammophore set at or above midpoint of clypeus; palp formula 6,4. Five mandibular teeth in major worker; mandibles triangular, weakly incurved; third mandibular tooth distinctly shorter than apical tooth and teeth numbers two and four; masticatory margin of mandibles approximately aligned vertically or weakly oblique. Mesosoma. Integument of pronotum, mesonotum and mesopleuron matt or with weak sheen and microreticulate throughout; anterior mesosoma in profile broadly convex; erect pronotal setae short, (i.e., shorter than length of eye) and unmodified; in profile, metanotal groove shallow, broadly V- or U-shaped; propodeum matt or with a weak sheen and indistinctly shagreenate; propodeum smoothly rounded or with indistinct angle; propodeal dorsum and declivity confluent; erect propodeal setae present and sparse to moderate (1-12); appressed propodeal setae long and closely aligned, creating pubescence; propodeal spiracle situated on or beside declivitous face of propodeum, and shorter (length less than 0.50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
height of propodeum). Petiole. In profile, petiolar node squamiform; in full-face view, shape of petiolar node uniformly rounded, or generally rounded with median indentation; node shining and faintly shagreenate-microreticulate. Gaster. Gaster shining, shagreenate ('LP 
<normalizedToken originalValue="record’">record'</normalizedToken>
appearance); pilos 
<pageBreakToken pageId="89" pageNumber="90" start="start">ity</pageBreakToken>
of first gastral tergite consisting of thick, appressed setae that form pubescence, interspersed with numerous short, bristly, erect setae. General characters. Colour of foreparts orange-red, gaster brown to black.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="89" pageNumber="90" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="89" pageNumber="90">Measurements.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="89" pageNumber="90">Worker (n = 8): CI 87-109; EI 15-31; EL 0.18-0.40; HL 0.68-2.40; HW 0.59-2.62; ML 0.94-2.81; MTL 0.57-1.81; PpH 0.11-0.35; PpL 0.49-1.23; SI 72-149; SL 0.88-1.90.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="89" pageNumber="90" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="89" pageNumber="90">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="89" pageNumber="90">
Most collections of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus curtus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="89" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="curtus">Melophorus curtus</taxonomicName>
have been made in Eastern Australia, where it is quite common, but no specimens were available for sequencing. There is some doubt that the taxon, as defined here, is monophyletic: although it is characterized by the presence of fine, appressed pubescence of the tibiae in addition to stout, socketed, appressed to subdecumbent setae, and also the absence of erect setae on the antenna and hind tibiae, other features are very variable, especially in the minor worker. Quite compressed, short-legged, relatively hairy workers are common in the Armidale area of NSW, while larger, more elongate and glabrous or near glabrous workers are common further north. In northern Australia a very elongate form with long, silvery, appressed setae on the head and body occurs. (However, this ant may represent the media worker of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. tenuis" pageId="89" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="tenuis">M. tenuis</taxonomicName>
, which is here described on the basis of the minor only.) The moderately gracile morphotype, which is the most common, can also easily be mistaken for 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. praesens" pageId="89" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="praesens">M. praesens</taxonomicName>
or 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. castaneus" pageId="89" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="castaneus">M. castaneus</taxonomicName>
, and the tibiae of specimens must be examined carefully to distinguish the former species from the latter two. The possibility that there could be at least two or three cryptic species cannot be discounted, and further investigation involving genetics work is desirable in order to unravel the phylogenetics of such variable populations. A small syntype major worker from MacKey is here designated lectotype. This specimen not only represents the most common morph of 
<taxonomicName genus="M." lsidName="M. curtus" pageId="89" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="curtus">M. curtus</taxonomicName>
but has clearly recognizable defining features that belong to this taxon. The other syntypes here become paralectotypes.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="89" pageNumber="90">Based on label data, this ant has a predilection for black soil, and has been taken in both dry sclerophyll woodland and savannah. Pitfall traps are a common means of capture. In all likelihood this species is a generalized scavenger.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="89" pageNumber="90">
<paragraph pageId="89" pageNumber="90">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Melophorus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melophorus curtus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="89" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="curtus">Melophorus curtus</taxonomicName>
Forel: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="non–type">non-type</normalizedToken>
major worker (ANCI32-900019-top ant) frons (a), profile (b) and dorsum (c); 
<normalizedToken originalValue="non–type">non-type</normalizedToken>
minor worker frons (ANCI32-900019-bottom ant) (d), profile (e) and dorsum (f); distribution map for the species (g). Low resolution scale bars: 1 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
); 0.5 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="d–f">d-f</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>