<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.56.519" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5cd1bde1-9049-456c-83cf-1b3faa7fa9cc" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359792" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-56-65" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-56-65" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 56" ModsDocTitle="New data on Neotropical Scolytus Geoffroy, 1762 with description of five new species from Peru (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Scolytinae)" checkinTime="1451251007590" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="V. Petrov, Alexander &amp; Y. Mandelshtam, Michail" docDate="2010" docId="9B1A253ED70C0D47A189F8E2C4CB4795" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 56: 65-104" docOrigin="ZooKeys 56" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.56.519" docTitle="Scolytus bicinctus Schedl 1972" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="74" masterDocId="FF8FFF9ED926FFB6DE0FA13AA40FCA11" masterDocTitle="New data on Neotropical Scolytus Geoffroy, 1762 with description of five new species from Peru (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Scolytinae)" masterLastPageNumber="104" masterPageNumber="65" pageId="8" pageNumber="73" updateTime="1643558822588" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New data on Neotropical Scolytus Geoffroy, 1762 with description of five new species from Peru (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Scolytinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>V. Petrov, Alexander</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Y. Mandelshtam, Michail</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>56</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>65</mods:start>
<mods:end>104</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.56.519</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.56.519</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-56-65</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">0F61753F-101A-427D-BED7-2D6A9D6E92E3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359792" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:9B1A253ED70C0D47A189F8E2C4CB4795" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9B1A253ED70C0D47A189F8E2C4CB4795" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="74" pageId="8" pageNumber="73">
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="73" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">
<taxonomicName authority="Schedl, 1972" authorityName="Schedl" authorityYear="1972" class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Scolytus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Scolytus bicinctus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicinctus">Scolytus bicinctus Schedl, 1972</taxonomicName>
Fig. 6
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="73" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">Brazil:Jacareacanda, Para, VI-1970, ER Barbosa. M.Alvarenga Collection.Holotype ♂; Peru: Loreto province, Morannon river, 20 km NNW from Nauta, Buen Fin vill., 130 m, 6.02.1995 A.Petrov (1♀); Junin province, Rio Perene, 8 km NNE from Puerto Ocopa, Cananeden vill., 1180 m, S11°49'; W74°16' 6.02.2008 A.Petrov (1♂).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="73">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">
Figure 6. Habitus, lateral view of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Scolytus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Scolytus bicinctus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicinctus">Scolytus bicinctus</taxonomicName>
, female
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="73" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">Species differs from its relatives by structure of abdomen, by frontal and elytral puncturation.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="74" pageId="8" pageNumber="73" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">Male: body length 1.5-1.9 mm, 2.3 times as long as wide; body colour from reddish-brown to grayish-brown; surface faintly shining, nearly dull. Head reddish-brown or grayish-brown. Front broadly, rather strongly convex, surface obscurely reticulate, moderately punctured over entire area; vestiture of sparse, fine, short hairs, with most hairs located on lateral frontal parts and above mandibles; scape and funicle are reddish brown, lighter compared to club, antennal club with acutely angulate groove for suture 1 clearly marked, apex of club is evenly rounded. Pronotum 1.04-1.1 times as long as wide, its lateral sides parallel from basis up to middle of its length, towards apex lateral sides are strongly narrowed; pronotal surface faintly shining, evenly punctured by shallow punctures; these punctures becoming larger in apical portion of pronotum; sparse pale hairs located in apical portion of pronotum. Pronotum is separated from the prosternite (propleura) by a poorly developed, obtuse and smooth margin. Puncturation of lateral sides of prosternite very shallow and unconspicuous. Prosternite covered by small recumbent scale-like, pale hairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="73">Scutelum triangular, set not deep in scutellular impression below elytral surface.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="74" pageId="8" pageNumber="73">
Elytra 1.3-1.4 times as long as wide, 1.25-1.3 times as long as pronotum; lateral sides of elytra nearly parallel up to short declivity, from beginning of declivity and up to suture elytra are narrowed, with their sides forming a 45° angle. Striae and interstriae weakly impressed, punctures in striae and interstriae about equal in size. Elytral surface from basis and to the apex is evenly covered by very short pale recumbent hairs. Central portion of posterior margin on first sternite and second sternite basis faintly projected backwards; the border between first and second sternites unevident. Basis of the second sternite with two unconspicuous callus-like tubercles, lateral sides of the first sternite are narrowed. Lateral denticles of the second sternite posterior margin with clearly attenuated apices, conspicuous; second sternite is nearly vertical towards posterior margin of the first sternite. Third, fourth and fifth sternites forming angle of 45° with first sternite. Lateral sides of third and fourth sternites unarmed. Fifth sternite 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="74" start="start">impressed</pageBreakToken>
near its posterior margin, the posterior margin forming an elevated rim. Surface of sternites is faintly shining, finely shagreen (reticulated) and evenly covered by recumbent pale hairs.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="74">Legs are reddish brown, covered by sparse short hairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="74">Female differs from male by more cylindrical form of body, by structure of front and of abdomen.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="74">Female: body length 1.8 mm, 2.5 times as long as wide; color reddish brown. Front convex, without tubercles or impressions, its surface finely shagreen and evenly punctured, in central portion front has light transverse wrinkles; all frontal surface in female covered by short pale hairs; longer singular hairs on epistoma overhanging the mandibles. Apical constriction of the pronotum poorly developed; therefore pronotum seems to be broader than in male. Elytra essentially as in male, their surface is covered with minute pale recumbent hairs. Central portion of the first abdominal sternite is weakly projected backwards, its posterior margin smooth. Lateral sides of first sternite narrowed, second sternite much broader compared to the first. Second sternite set nearly vertical towards posterior margin of first sternite. Lateral portions of posterior margin on second sternite with small horizontal sharpened denticles. Third, fourth and fifth sternites forming a 70° angle with first sternite. Lateral sides of third and fourth sternites unarmed. Fifth sternite with median impression nearb posterior margin, and margin with an elevated keel. Surface of abdominal sternites faintly shining, finely shagreen and evenly covered by short recumbent pale hairs.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="74" type="notes">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="74">Notes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="74">The species is found in Peru for the first time. Female is described for the first time here.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>