<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.170.2321" ID-GBIF-Dataset="7ea2a408-c5ff-4543-8a12-7c95fb0b1c76" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152033301" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-170-21" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-170-21" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 170" ModsDocTitle="A new species of genus Syntactus Förster (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ctenopelmatinae) with a key to Oriental and Eastern Palearctic species" checkinTime="1451249335184" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Sun, Shu-Ping &amp; Sheng, Mao-Ling" docDate="2012" docId="691C9748E4764BA56D4A72F8075691E7" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 170: 21-28" docOrigin="ZooKeys 170" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.170.2321" docTitle="Syntactus jiulianicus Sun &amp; Sheng, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="23" masterDocId="FFD45724FF9B051A4245B220FF9EDF5D" masterDocTitle="A new species of genus Syntactus Foerster (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ctenopelmatinae) with a key to Oriental and Eastern Palearctic species" masterLastPageNumber="28" masterPageNumber="21" pageId="0" pageNumber="21" updateTime="1643539868158" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of genus Syntactus Foerster (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ctenopelmatinae) with a key to Oriental and Eastern Palearctic species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sun, Shu-Ping</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sheng, Mao-Ling</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>170</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>21</mods:start>
<mods:end>28</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.170.2321</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.170.2321</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-170-21</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152033301" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:691C9748E4764BA56D4A72F8075691E7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/691C9748E4764BA56D4A72F8075691E7" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="23" pageId="0" pageNumber="21">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="21" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B09BEBC3-C706-48F6-B7B6-2EAF91361025" authority="Sun &amp; Sheng" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Syntactus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Syntactus jiulianicus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jiulianicus">Syntactus jiulianicus Sun &amp; Sheng</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="21">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1-6
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="21" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">The name of the new species is based on the type locality.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="21" type="types">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Types.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Holotype, Female, CHINA: Jiulianshan Natural Reserve, Longnan County, 629 m, Jiangxi Province, 27 April 2011, leg. Mao-Ling Sheng. Paratype: 1 male, same data as holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="21" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Syntactus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Syntactus jiulianicus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jiulianicus">Syntactus jiulianicus</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished from all other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Syntactus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Syntactus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Syntactus</taxonomicName>
by the combination of the face and clypeus smooth and shining, sparsely and finely punctuate; gena and frons impunctate; face, mesopleuron and mesosternum yellow; first to third terga of female reddish brown, male yellow.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="23" pageId="0" pageNumber="21" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Female. Body length approximately 8.5 mm. Fore wing length approximately 7.0 mm. Antenna length approximately 7.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Head. Face and clypeus almost smooth (Figure 2a). Face approximately 1.9 times as wide as long, with indistinct, uneven and fine punctures; median portion weakly and longitudinally convex. Clypeus gradually raised towards apical margin, with very sparse, fine and distinct punctures. Median portion of mandible with longitudinal wrinkles; upper tooth of mandible evidently shorter than lower tooth. Cheek nearly smooth, without punctures. Malar space approximately 0.6 times as long as basal width of mandible. Gena and vertex (Figure 2) and frons smooth and shining. Gena impunctate, hind portion slightly convergent posteriorly, in lateral view approximately 0.9 times as long as width of eye. Posterior-lateral portion of vertex with indistinct fine punctures, hind-median portion slightly concave. Interocellar area slightly convex. Postocellar line about 0.7 times as long as ocular-ocellar line. Frons impunctate; upper-median portion weakly convex; lower portion slightly concave. Antenna with 37 flagellomeres. Ratio of length from first to fifth flagellomeres: 2.0:1.8:1.4:1.3:1.3. Occipital carina complete, dorsomedian portion concave, lower end reaching base of mandible.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="21">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">
Figures 1-6. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Syntactus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Syntactus jiulianicus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jiulianicus">Syntactus jiulianicus</taxonomicName>
Sun &amp; Sheng, sp.n. Holotype. Female 1 Body, lateral view 2 Head, dorsal view 2a Head, anterior view 3 Mesosoma, lateral view 4 Propodeum 5 Terga 1 to 3, dorsal view 6 Apical portion of metasoma, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="21">Mesosoma. Anterior portion of pronotum smooth, lateral concavity with dense oblique fine wrinkles, dorsal-porsterior portion with fine punctures. Epomia present, weak. Mesoscutum with dense and fine punctures. Notauli present, anterior 0.3 sharp. Scutoscutellar groove with weak longitudinal wrinkles. Scutellum convex, with fine punctures, basal 0.3 with lateral carina. Postscutellum weakly convex, approximately quadrate. Subalar prominence strongly convex. Mesopleuron (Figure 3) and metapleuron smooth and shining. Lower portion of mesopleuron with sparse and indistinct fine punctures. Epicnemial carina strong, upper end reaching subalar prominence. Posterior portion of metapleuron with fine oblique wrinkles. Submetapleural carina strongly, anterior portion evidently convex. Wings slightly brownish, hyaline, apical portions smoky-gray. Fore wing with vein 1cu-a distal of 1/M by 0.2 times as long as 1cu-a. Vein 2-Cu approximately 1.8 times as long as 2cu-a. Hind wing vein 1-cu about 1.5 times as long as cu-a. Apical edge of fore tibia with a small tooth at outer side. Hind coxa smooth, with sparse and fine punctures. Ratio of length of hind tarsomeres 1:2:3:4:5 is 5.3:2.7:1.9:1.1:1.4. Propodeum (Figure 4) evenly convex. Area basalis slightly longer than wide, smooth, convergent anteriorly. Area superomedia longer than wide, costula connecting in front of its middle, combined with area petiolaris, combined area smooth, nearby apical margin with distinct transverse fine wrinkles, from costula to apex evidently convergent posteriorly. Area externa with fine punctures and gray hairs. Area lateralis with dense oblique wrinkles. Pleural carina distinctly curved at the level of propodeal spiracle, with carina between pleural carina and propodeal spiracle. Propodeal spiracle approximately 2.6 times as long as wide.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="22" pageId="0" pageNumber="21">
Metasoma. Terga almost smooth. First tergum approximately 2.3 times as long as apical width, strongly convergent toward base, median dorsal carinae indistinct
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="22" start="start">.</pageBreakToken>
Dorsolateral carinae weak, subbasal portion near spiracle indistinct. Ventrolateral carinae complete. Spiracle convex, located slightly before middle of first tergum. Second tergum trapeziform, approximately 0.7 times as long as apical width. Third tergum approximately 0.5 times as long as apical width. Ovipositor sheath approximately 0.7 times as long as apical depth of metasoma, subapical portion distinctly wider than basal portion (Figure 6). Ovipositor very thin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="23" start="start">Color</pageBreakToken>
. (Figure 1). Main body and legs yellow, except the following. Flagellum reddish brown. Apical teeth of mandibles, vertex, collar, mesoscutum, lateral portions of scutellum and postscutellum, axillary troughs of mesonotum and metanotum, a small spot beneath subalar prominence, fourth to seventh terga except narrow hind margins black. Median portions of scutellum and postscutellum red. Propodeum darkish brown, lateral portion fuscous. Terga 1 to 3 reddish brown. Posterior-lateral portions of third and fourth terga with longitudinal brownish black spots. Metapleuron and hind legs reddish brown. Stigma blackish brown. Veins dust-colored.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">Male. Body length approximately 7.0 mm. Fore wing length approximately 5.6 mm. Antenna length approximately 7.0 mm. Antenna with 35 flagellomeres. Ventral profiles of hind coxae, metapleuron, terga 1 to 3 and hind portion of tergum 4 yellow.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Syntactus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Syntactus delusor" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="delusor">Syntactus delusor</taxonomicName>
(Linnaeus, 1758). Female. Body, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
Figure 8. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Syntactus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Syntactus minor" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minor">Syntactus minor</taxonomicName>
(Holmgren, 1857). Female 8 Body, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="23">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Syntactus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Syntactus varius" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="varius">Syntactus varius</taxonomicName>
(Holmgren, 1858). Female. Body, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>