<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.764.25108" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8d95e407-f6d1-490d-8d54-04336312b327" ID-GBIF-Taxon="145906886" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-764-27" ID-ZBK="8BB7E0E6315446E9A010D8E52E7EEF4E" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-764-27" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 764" ModsDocTitle="A synopsis of the scorpion fauna of French Guiana, with description of four new species" checkinTime="1528216738787" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Ythier, Eric" docDate="2018" docId="C5A5770C2B2040B1D18FB6D3291AF5CE" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 764: 27-90" docOrigin="ZooKeys 764" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.764.25108" docTitle="Tityus (Atreus) obscurus Gervais 1843" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="39" masterDocId="5F2AFF97C459FFC4FFA4FFBDFB7D320E" masterDocTitle="A synopsis of the scorpion fauna of French Guiana, with description of four new species" masterLastPageNumber="90" masterPageNumber="27" pageId="10" pageNumber="37" updateTime="1643470496529" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A synopsis of the scorpion fauna of French Guiana, with description of four new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ythier, Eric</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>764</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>27</mods:start>
<mods:end>90</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.764.25108</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.764.25108</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-764-27</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">8BB7E0E6315446E9A010D8E52E7EEF4E</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8BB7E0E6315446E9A010D8E52E7EEF4E</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="145906886" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:C5A5770C2B2040B1D18FB6D3291AF5CE" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C5A5770C2B2040B1D18FB6D3291AF5CE" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="10" pageNumber="37">
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="37" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="37">
<taxonomicName authority="Gervais, 1843" authorityName="Gervais" authorityYear="1843" class="Arachnida" family="Buthidae" genus="Tityus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tityus (Atreus) obscurus" order="Scorpiones" pageId="10" pageNumber="37" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="obscurus" subGenus="Atreus">Tityus (Atreus) obscurus (Gervais, 1843)</taxonomicName>
Figs 12, 13
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="37" type="references">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="37">References.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="37">
<bibRefCitation pageId="10" pageNumber="37">Gervais 1843</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Pocock, RI" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Linnaean Society" pageId="30" pageNumber="57" url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00222939708680549" year="1897">Pocock 1897</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation pageId="10" pageNumber="37">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lourenço">Lourenco</normalizedToken>
1983
</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Lourenco, WR" journalOrPublisher="Revue Suisse de Zoologie" pageId="29" pageNumber="56" pagination="687 - 604" title="Additions a la faune de scorpions neotropicaux (Arachnida)." url="https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.part.80012" volume="104" year="1997 b">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lourenço">Lourenco</normalizedToken>
1997b
</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Fet, V" journalOrPublisher="New York, New York Ento-mological Society" pageId="28" pageNumber="55" title="Catalog of the Scorpions of the World (1758 - 1998)." year="2000">Fet et al. 2000</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Lourenco, WR" journalOrPublisher="Les Editions de l'IF, Paris" pageId="29" pageNumber="56" title="Scorpions of Brazil." year="2002 a">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lourenço">Lourenco</normalizedToken>
2002a
</bibRefCitation>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lourenço">Lourenco</normalizedToken>
and Leguin 2008, 
<bibRefCitation author="Stockmann, R" journalOrPublisher="NAP Editions, Paris" pageId="30" pageNumber="57" title="Scorpions of the World." year="2010">Stockmann and Ythier 2010</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="38" pageId="10" pageNumber="37" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="37">Material.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="38" pageId="10" pageNumber="37">
Cayenne, one adult female (lectotype) and one immature female (paralectotype), MNHN-RS3298, Mr. Leschenault &amp; Mr. Doumerc coll. Cayenne, one female, MNHNRS-0855, Noirot coll., 1890. Cayenne, one male and one female, MNHNRS0861, M. Melinon coll., 1877. Cayenne, three females, MNHNRS3297, M. Melinon coll., 1876. Cayenne, two females, MNHNRS3299, R. Pinchon leg., 1953. Cayenne, three males, MNHNRS3314, E. Abonnenc coll., two males, MNHNRS3317, E. Abonnenc coll., Inst. Pasteur leg. Cayenne, Montabo, in forest, one female, MNHNRS3319, III/1949. Cayenne, caught from a cat in a house, one female, MNHN-RS3321, D. Destombes coll., VI/1950. Cayenne, one female, MNHNRS3325, F. Geay coll., 1902. Cayenne, one female, MNHN-RS-0846, St. Laurent coll., 1899. Border with Para, one male and one female, MNHNRS-3286, 1900. Cayenne, Mt. St. Martin, forest, one female, MNHNRS7926, D. Quintero coll., 10/XII/1972. Cayenne, one male, MNHNRS8081, M. Condamin leg., 25/VI/1976. Cayenne, Mont Bourda, one immature, deposited in the RNA, J. Chevalier &amp; B. Tan coll., 09/VII/2017. Cayenne region, one male, deposited in the MHNG, Freitag leg., IX/1987. AmaroneBaraquin, one male and one female, MNHNRS0849, 1900. AntecumePata, in forest, one female, MNHN-RS-6268, J.P. Gasc coll., 18/VII/1972. AntecumePata, in forest, one female, MNHN-RS-6269, J.P. Gasc coll., 18/VII/1972. Antecume-Pata, one female, MNHNRS7918, J.P. Gasc leg., 1975. Antecume-Pata, one male, MNHN-RS7919, J.P. Gasc leg., 1975. Antecume-Pata, one female, MNHN-RS-7920, J.P. Gasc leg., 1975. Downstream from Saut 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pararé">Parare</normalizedToken>
on Arataye river, Approuague tributary, two males and one female, MNHNRS7389, J.P. Gasc coll., IV-V/1979. Downstream from Saut 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Pararé">Parare</normalizedToken>
on Arataye river, Approuague tributary, one male, MNHNRS7391, J.P. Gasc coll., IVV/1979. Camopi, Oyapock valley, one male and one female, MNHNRS3393, mission E. Aubert de la 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Rüe">Ruee</normalizedToken>
coll., 18/XII/1948. Upper Approuage, in forest, one male, MNHNRS3301, III/1946. Upper Oyapock, between Mount 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Orière">Oriere</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Dégrad">Degrad</normalizedToken>
Galoupa, two females, MNHNRS3310, mission E. Aubert de la 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Rüe">Ruee</normalizedToken>
coll., 1948-49. Kaw, one female, MNHNRS8296, J. Lescure coll., 2730/IV/1977. Mitaraka Massif, hand catch, one male, two females and one immature female, deposited in the MNHN, MNHN/PNI Guyane 2015, E. Poirier, P.H. Dalens &amp; J. Touroult coll., 11-18/III/2015. Mitaraka Massif, camp, layon D, tropical moist forest, in plateau, winkler, two females, deposited in the MNHN, MNHN/PNI Guyane 2015, J. Orivel &amp; F. PetitClerc coll., 23/II/2015-11/III/2015. Apatou, Crevette river, one male, one female and one immature male, deposited in the RNA, J. Chevalier &amp; P. Gallier coll., 30/VI/2017. Sinnamary, path of the Canceler river, under a palm 
<normalizedToken originalValue="tree’s">tree's</normalizedToken>
bark, one female and one male, deposited in the RNA, J. Chevalier &amp; P. Gallier coll., 05/VIII/2017. Iracoubo, Savanne Grand Macoua, one female, deposited in the RNA, J. Chevalier &amp; Q. Uriot coll., 28/VII/2017. Mounts of Montsinery, one female, MNHNRS5252, F. Geay coll., II/1902. Oyapock, two males, MNHN-RS0845, F. Geay coll., 1900. Oyapock, one female, MNHNRS0862, F. Geay coll., 1900. Oyapock, one male, MNHN-RS3305, mission E. Aubert de la 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Rüe">Ruee</normalizedToken>
coll., 1/XII/1948. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Saül">Sauel</normalizedToken>
, one male and three females, MNHNRS5286, Balachowsky leg., 27/X/1969. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Saül">Sauel</normalizedToken>
, Gros Arbres trail, one female, deposited in the RNA, J. Chevalier coll., 23/VIII/2017. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Saül">Sauel</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Belvédère">Belvedere</normalizedToken>
, one juvenile, deposited in the RNA, J. Chevalier coll., 21-22/VIII/2017. Saut Sabbat, one female, MNHNRS8208, D. Kopp coll., 8/VII/1976. Saut Sabbat, one immature female, deposited in the MNHN, E. Ythier coll., 03-11/XI/2010. St. Jean du Maroni, one female, MNHNRS0856, R. Benoist coll., 1914. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Yanioué">Yanioue</normalizedToken>
, upper Oyapock, upper Camopi, upstream waterfall, one male, MNHNRS3295, mission E. Aubert de la 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Rüe">Ruee</normalizedToken>
coll., II/1949. Cacao, four males and one immature, deposited in the MHNG, Chippaux leg., X/1983. Cacao, one male, deposited in the MHNG, W. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lourenço">Lourenco</normalizedToken>
leg., II/1989. Cacao, one male, deposited in the MHNG, P. Soler leg., I/1992. Kourou, one male, deposited in the MHNG, R. Garrouste leg., 16/II/1995. Kourou, one male, deposited in the MHNG, Freitag leg., 9/X/1987. Petit-Saut, in canopy with radeau des cimes, one immature female, deposited in the MHNG, H.P. Aberlenc coll., 4/XI/1989. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Trinité">Trinite</normalizedToken>
reserve, Aya river, pitfall trap, one immature female, deposited in the MNHN, C. Courtial coll., X/2009. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Trinité">Trinite</normalizedToken>
reserve, Aya river, one immature male, deposited in the MNHN, C. Courtial coll., X/2008. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Trinité">Trinite</normalizedToken>
reserve, Aya River, two males and one female, deposited in the MNHN, C. Courtial coll., XII/2010. Matoury, one male and one immature, deposited in the EYPC, EY0042, E. Ythier coll., 03-11/XI/2010. Salobroc, two immatures, MNHNRS0812. Guyane, three females, MNHN-RS0810, M. Lafon coll., 1872. Guyane, two males and one female, MNHNRS0844, G. Dewer coll., 1897. Guyane, one female, MNHN-RS0850, Viguier coll., 1877. Guyane, one female, MNHNRS8250, D. Kopp coll., 3/VII/1976. Between Oyapock and Amapa (disputed area), one female, MNHNRS0852, Villecourt coll., 1899. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="38" start="start">Between</pageBreakToken>
Oyapock and Mount SociatMarcel, on the ground, base camp, river bank, Eleuponsin, one female, MNHNRS8076, J. P. Gasc coll. III/1976. Paranama, one female, MNHNRS8251, D. Kopp coll., 3/VII/1976. Franco-brazilian region, two females, MNHNRS0839, F. Geay coll., 1899. Le Para (?), five males and five females, MNHN-RS0854.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="11" pageNumber="38" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="38">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="11" pageNumber="38">
Species of large size when compared with the average size of the other species within the genus, ranging from 75.7 to 100 mm in total length. General coloration uniformly dark brown to blackish. Carapace and mesosoma uniformly dark brown to blackish. Sternites with some pale zones; a triangular smooth testaceous area on the middle of the posterior border of the sternite III; pectines testaceous. Metasomal segments I to V and telson uniformly dark brown to blackish. In most cases the juvenile instars are yellowish or reddish yellow, with very numerous variegated spots, these spots being not visible in the adults as a result of the very marked sclerification of the cuticle. Chelicerae yellowish with variegated dark brown spots over the entire surface; fingers brownish; teeth dark reddish. Pedipalps dark reddish; chela fingers dark brown to blackish with tip yellowish. Legs yellowish almost entirely covered with brownish spots, except on telotarsus. Number of pectine teeth ranging from 18 to 22 teeth in both sexes; the basal middle lamellae strongly dilated in females. Metasomal segments I and II with ten carinae; segments III and IV with eight carinae; segment V with five carinae. Telson with a strong spinoid subaculear 
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="39" start="start">tooth</pageBreakToken>
present that can be moderate in size or almost totally absent in very large specimens. Dentate margins of pedipalp chela fixed and movable fingers with 15-17 oblique rows of granules. Very strong sexual dimorphism; male pedipalps are longer and more slender than those of the females; metasoma of the male is also longer than the one of the female.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="12" pageNumber="39">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="39">
Figure 12. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Buthidae" genus="Tityus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tityus obscurus" order="Scorpiones" pageId="12" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="obscurus">Tityus obscurus</taxonomicName>
, adult female from Cayenne.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="12" pageNumber="39">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="39">
Figure 13. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Buthidae" genus="Tityus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tityus obscurus" order="Scorpiones" pageId="12" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="obscurus">Tityus obscurus</taxonomicName>
, juvenile from Saut Sabbat.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>