<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.6.e24173" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1314-2828--24173" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1314-2828--e24173" ModsDocOrigin="Biodiversity Data Journal " ModsDocTitle="Ceraphronkrogmanni (Hymenoptera: Ceraphronidae), a new species from Lower Saxony with unusual male genitalia" checkinTime="1585356989567" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Ulmer, Jonah M, Miko, Istvan &amp; Deans, Andrew R" docDate="2018" docId="EE86170634C3D90E7C97B7320C94A6E2" docLanguage="en" docName="BiodivDatJour 6: e24173" docOrigin="Biodiversity Data Journal 6" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.6.e24173" docTitle="Ceraphron krogmanni Ulmer, Miko &amp; Deans, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="E762860F-DBB7-47AE-A94B-543290842491" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="24173" masterDocId="FFA6DA29FFB0795AFF98FF8DFF8BFFB0" masterDocTitle="Ceraphronkrogmanni (Hymenoptera: Ceraphronidae), a new species from Lower Saxony with unusual male genitalia" masterLastPageNumber="24173" masterPageNumber="24173" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" updateTime="1585373250100" updateUser="pensoft">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Ceraphronkrogmanni (Hymenoptera: Ceraphronidae), a new species from Lower Saxony with unusual male genitalia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ulmer, Jonah M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Miko, Istvan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Deans, Andrew R</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Biodiversity Data Journal</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>6</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>24173</mods:start>
<mods:end>24173</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.6.e24173</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.6.e24173</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1314-2828--24173</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">E762860F-DBB7-47AE-A94B-543290842491</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E762860F-DBB7-47AE-A94B-543290842491" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EE86170634C3D90E7C97B7320C94A6E2" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E762860F-DBB7-47AE-A94B-543290842491" class="Insecta" family="Ceraphronidae" genus="Ceraphron" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceraphron krogmanni" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="krogmanni">Ceraphron krogmanni</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Materials</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
<materialsCitation collectingDate="2013-06-08" collectingMethod="sweeping" collectionCode="State Museum of Natural History (SMNS), SMNS _ Hym _ T 00665" collectorName="L. Krogmann, R. Peters" country="Germany" latitude="53.06361" location="Niedersachen, Lkr. Luechow-Dannenberg, Pevestorf, Deichvorland &amp; Deich" longitude="119.4338" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" specimenCode="PSUC _ FEM 86417" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" typeStatus="Holotype">
Type status: 
<typeStatus pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Holotype</typeStatus>
. Occurrence: catalogNumber: 
<specimenCode pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">PSUC_FEM 86417</specimenCode>
; recordedBy: 
<collectorName pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">L. Krogmann, R. Peters</collectorName>
; individualCount: 
<specimenCount pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">1</specimenCount>
; sex: 
<specimenType pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">male</specimenType>
; lifeStage: 
<specimenType pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">adult</specimenType>
; preparations: glycerol; occurrenceID: urn:uuid:675a5573-994c-4136-be14-03ab9de2aace; Taxon: scientificName: Ceraphronkrogmanni; kingdom: Animalia; phylum: Arthropoda; class: Insecta; order: Hymenoptera; family: Ceraphronidae; genus: Ceraphron; specificEpithet: krogmanni; taxonRank: species; Location: locationID: 91c31a2d21f8ea1df5681e7f945ec536; continent: Europe; country: 
<collectingCountry pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Germany</collectingCountry>
; locality: 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:EE86170634C3D90E7C97B7320C94A6E2:434FD470E2E94A78CAE7CF9B2F141B13" country="Germany" latitude="53.06361" longitude="119.4338" name="Niedersachen, Lkr. Luechow-Dannenberg, Pevestorf, Deichvorland &amp; Deich" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
Niedersachen, Lkr. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lüchow-Dannenberg">Luechow-Dannenberg</normalizedToken>
, Pevestorf, Deichvorland &amp; Deich
</location>
; verbatimCoordinates: N53°03'49&quot;, E11°28'27&quot;; decimalLatitude: 
<geoCoordinate orientation="latitude" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" value="53.063611">53.063611</geoCoordinate>
; decimalLongitude: 
<geoCoordinate orientation="longitude" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" value="119.4338">119.4338</geoCoordinate>
; georeferenceProtocol: label; Identification: identifiedBy: 
<determinerName pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Jonah M. Ulmer</determinerName>
; dateIdentified: 2016; Event: samplingProtocol: 
<collectingMethod pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">sweeping</collectingMethod>
; eventDate: 
<collectingDate pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" value="2013-06-08">08/06/2013</collectingDate>
; Record Level: language: en; institutionID: SMNS; collectionID: urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34840; institutionCode: 
<collectionCode pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">State Museum of Natural History (SMNS)</collectionCode>
; collectionCode: 
<collectionCode pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">SMNS_Hym_T00665</collectionCode>
; basisOfRecord: PreservedSpecimen
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation collectingDate="2013-06-08" collectingMethod="sweeping" collectionCode="Frost Entomological Museum (PSUC), Insects" collectorName="L. Krogmann, R. Peters" country="Germany" latitude="53.06361" location="Niedersachen, Lkr. Luechow-Dannenberg, Pevestorf, Deichvorland &amp; Deich" longitude="119.4338" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" specimenCode="PSUC _ FEM 86221" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" typeStatus="Paratype">
Type status: 
<typeStatus pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Paratype</typeStatus>
. Occurrence: catalogNumber: 
<specimenCode pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">PSUC_FEM 86221</specimenCode>
; recordedBy: 
<collectorName pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">L. Krogmann, R. Peters</collectorName>
; individualCount: 
<specimenCount pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">1</specimenCount>
; sex: 
<specimenType pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">male</specimenType>
; lifeStage: 
<specimenType pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">adult</specimenType>
; preparations: glycerol; occurrenceID: urn:uuid:675a5573-994c-4136-be14-03ab9de2aace; Taxon: scientificName: Ceraphronkrogmanni; kingdom: Animalia; phylum: Arthropoda; class: Insecta; order: Hymenoptera; family: Ceraphronidae; genus: Ceraphron; specificEpithet: krogmanni; taxonRank: species; Location: locationID: 91c31a2d21f8ea1df5681e7f945ec536; continent: Europe; country: 
<collectingCountry pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Germany</collectingCountry>
; locality: 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:EE86170634C3D90E7C97B7320C94A6E2:869933D49DD4A7E2FC1DE90462FBAD90" country="Germany" latitude="53.06361" longitude="119.4338" name="Niedersachen, Lkr. Luechow-Dannenberg, Pevestorf, Deichvorland &amp; Deich" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
Niedersachen, Lkr. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lüchow-Dannenberg">Luechow-Dannenberg</normalizedToken>
, Pevestorf, Deichvorland &amp; Deich
</location>
; verbatimCoordinates: N53°03'49&quot;, E11°28'27&quot;; decimalLatitude: 
<geoCoordinate orientation="latitude" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" value="53.063611">53.063611</geoCoordinate>
; decimalLongitude: 
<geoCoordinate orientation="longitude" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" value="119.4338">119.4338</geoCoordinate>
; georeferenceProtocol: label; Identification: identifiedBy: 
<determinerName pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Jonah M. Ulmer</determinerName>
; dateIdentified: 2016; Event: samplingProtocol: 
<collectingMethod pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">sweeping</collectingMethod>
; eventDate: 
<collectingDate pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" value="2013-06-08">08/06/2013</collectingDate>
; Record Level: language: en; institutionID: PSUC; collectionID: http://grbio.org/cool/29fv-ztxs; institutionCode: 
<collectionCode pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Frost Entomological Museum (PSUC)</collectionCode>
; collectionCode: 
<collectionCode pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Insects</collectionCode>
; basisOfRecord: PreservedSpecimen
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Description</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Body length universal: 0.9-1.1 mm.</paragraph>
<subSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="coloration">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Coloration</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Colour hue pattern female: NOT CODED. Colour intensity pattern female: NOT CODED. Colour hue pattern male: brownish, legs yellowish, fore wing brown, with a transverse discoloured band at level of stigmal vein. Colour intensity pattern male: flagellum, tibiae and tarsi lighter than scape, pedicel, mandible, tegula, coxae and femora.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="head">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Head</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Foveolate sculpture on body count: present on mesosoma and frons. Head width vs. head height: HW:HH=0.9-1.0. Head width vs. interorbital space (HW/IOS) Female: NOT CODED. Head width vs. interorbital space (HW/IOS) Male: 1.4-1.5. Head width vs. head length lateral view (HW / HL): 1.6. Maximum eye diameter vs. minimum eye diameter: 1.1-1.2. Dorsal carina of occipital depression presence: absent. Dorsal carina of occipital depression medial continuity: NOT CODED. Occipital carina sculpture: smooth (Fig. 3a). Median flange of occipital carina count: present. Submedial flange of occipital carina count: present. Dorsal margin of occipital carina vs. dorsal margin of lateral ocellus in lateral view: occipital carina is ventral to lateral ocellus in lateral view. Preoccipital lunula count: present. Preoccipital ridge presence: present. Preoccipital furrow count: present. Preoccipital furrow anterior extension: adjacent anteriorly to the posterior margin of the median ocellus. Preoccipital furrow anterior region vs. posterior region sculpture: crenulate in its entire length. Preoccipital furrow anterior region width vs. posterior region width: as wide anteriorly as posteriorly. Preoccipital carina count: present. Preoccipital carina shape: complete. Preoccipital carina and occipital carina structure: occipital carina complete, preoccipital carina fused laterally with preorbital carina. Setal pit on vertex size: smaller than diameter of scutes. Female ocular ocellar line (OOL): posterior ocellar line (POL): lateral ocellar line (LOL): NOT CODED. Male ocular ocellar line (OOL): posterior ocellar line (POL): lateral ocellar line (LOL): 2:1-1.2:1-1.2 (Fig. 1a). postocellar carina count: absent. Preocellar pit count: present. Randomly sized areolae around setal pits on upper face count: absent. Antennal scrobe count: present. Carina delimiting antennal scrobe count: present. Transverse striation on upper face: present. Transverse scutes on upper face count: present. Region on upper face width transverse scutes lateral limit: extending entire width of frons. Transverse frontal carina count: present (Fig. 3b). Frontal ledge count: absent. Rugose region on upper face count: absent. Ocellar fovea margin sharpness: blunt. Anterior ocellar fovea shape: fovea extended ventrally into facial sulcus, reaching dorsal margin of antennal scrobe. Facial pit count: no external corresponding structure present. White, thick setae on upper face count: present. Ventromedian setiferous patch and ventrolateral setiferous patch count: absent. Supraclypeal depression count: present. Supraclypeal depression structure: present medially, inverted U-shaped. Intertorular carina count: present. Median process on intertorular carina presence: absent. Intertorular ridge vs. epistomal ridge: separated. Intertorular area count: present. Median region of intertorular area shape: flat. Torulus position relative to anterior ocellus and distal margin of clypeus: torulus not reaching epistomal sulcus, closer to distal margin of clypeus than anterior ocellus. Torulo-clypeal carina count: present. Subtorular carina count: present. Subantennal groove count: absent. Subantennal groove structure: NOT CODED. Posterolateral process of gena count: present. Ocular impression and post ocular orbital carina count: present. Ocular impression sculpture: scalloped (foveae composing ocellar impression adjacent, sometimes not separated from each other). Median conjunctiva of cardines count (median fusion of left and right cardines): absent (cardines are fused). Maxillary palpomeres count: 4. Mandibular tooth count: 2. Mandibular lancea count: NOT CODED.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="mesosoma and metasoma">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Mesosoma and Metasoma</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
Mesosoma shape: not compressed laterally, as wide as high or wider than high (Fig. 1b). Weber length: WL=370-390µm. Pronope count: present. Transverse pronotal sulcus (anterodirsal branch of pronotal y) count: absent. Epomial carina presence: present. Posterodorsal branch of pronotal Y count: absent. Occlusor muscle apodeme for the occlusor muscle of the anterior thoracic spiracle count: NOT CODED. Occlusor muscle apodeme for the anterior thoracic spiracle structure: NOT CODED. Pit corresponding to the apodeme for the occlusor muscle of the anterior thoracic spiracle pit count: NOT CODED. Atrium of anterior mesothoracic spiracle count: NOT CODED. Atrium of the anterior thoracic spiracle size: NOT CODED. Ventrolateral invagination of the pronotum count: present. Annullar pronotum count: present. Ventromedian region of pronotum and anteroventral region of mesopectus continuity: pronotum and mesopectus continuous ventromedially. Lateroventral invagination of the propleuron presence: absent. Mesonotal fossa of the pronotum and pronotal condyle of the mesonotum presence: present. Mesoscutal length vs. anterior mesoscutal width: MscL/AscW=1.5-1.7. Mesonotum anterolateral margin shape: square. Median mesoscutal sulcus count: present. Median mesoscutal sulcus posterior end: adjacent to transscutal articulation. Scutoscutellar sulcus vs. transscutal articulation: adjacent. Notaulus count: present. Anterior mesoscutal width vs. posterior mesoscutal width: AscW/PscW=0.3-0.5. Notaulus posterior end location: anterior to transverse midline of mesoscutum. Posterior end of notaulus vs. posterior end of antero-admedian line: NOT CODED. Transscutal articulation completion: complete. Scutes on posterior region of mesoscutum and dorsal region of mesoscutellum count: present. Scutes on posterior region of mesoscutum and dorsal region of mesoscutellum convexity: flat. Lateral carina on the mesoscutellum presence: present. Axillular carina count: present. Axillular carina shape: left and right carina are separated posteromedially. Axillular setae presence: present. Posterolateral margin of mesoscutellum shape: blunt. Posteromedian process of the mesoscutellum count: present. Posteromedian process of the mesoscutellum shape: blunt. Anteromedian projection of the metanoto-propodeo-metapecto-mesopectal complex count: present. Anteromedian projection of the metathorax-propodeum complex shape: bilobed. Anteromedian projection of the metathorax-propodeum complex curvature lateral in view: straight. Sternaulus count: present. sternaulus length: elongate, exceeding 3/4 of mesopleuron length at level of sternaulus. Longitudinal striae extending from crenulae of anterior mesopleural sulcus to Mesopleural pit count: NOT CODED. speculum ventral limit: NOT CODED. Mesometapleural sulcus count: present. Ventral invagination of mesometapleural sulcus presence: absent. Epicnemial carina count: complete. Epicnemial pit count: present. Epicnemium posterior margin shape: anterior discrimenal pit present; epicnemial carina curved. Mesodiscrimen count: present. Anterior metapleural carina count: absent. Anterior metapleural carina completion: incomplete. Metapleural carina count: present. Metapleural carina vs. propodeal spiracle: metapleural carina extending ventrally of propodeal spiracle. Ventral projection of the metapleural carina presence: absent. Ventral invagination of the metapleural carina: absent. Propodeal spiracle dilator muscle apodeme pit location: posterodorsally of the metapleural carina. lateral propodeal carina count: present. Lateral propodeal carina shape: inverted &quot;V'' (left and right lateral propodeal carinae are adjacent medially at their intersection with antecostal sulcus of the first abdominal tergum). Median propodeal carina count: present. Posterior propodeal projection count: present. Posterior propodeal projection shape: simple. Propodeal and metacoxal verricules presence: absent. Posterodorsal metapleural area shape: NOT CODED. Posterior line of the posterodorsal metapectal area count: absent. Mesofurca vs. metadiscrimenal lamella continuity: fused. Transverse line of the metanotum-propodeum vs. antecostal sulcus of the first abdominal tergum: NOT CODED. Carina limiting posteriorly antecosta count: NOT CODED. Line of separation between the lateral margin of the acrotergite of the first abdominal tergum and the posterodrosal metapleural area count: absent. Posterior margin of nucha in dorsal view shape: straight. Stigmal vein of fore wing count: present. Stigmal vein length vs. pterostigma marginal length: stigmal vein longer than the pterostigma marginal length. Pterostigma of fore wing count: absent (Fig. 5a). Hind wing reduction: well developed. Calcar shape: simple. Mesotibial spur count: 1. Mesobasicoxa width vs. metabasicoxa width: Metabasicoxa distinctly wider than mesobasicoxa. Posterior mesosomal comb count: absent. Anterior mesothoracic spiracle occlusor muscle site of origin: NOT CODED. Pronoto-mesobasalar muscle site origin: NOT CODED. Pronoto-procoxal muscle origin: NOT CODED. Prophragmo-postoccipital muscle site of origin: NOT CODED. Mesonoto-mesotrochanteral muscle presence: NOT CODED. Posterior mesonoto-metanotal muscle site of origin anterior limit: NOT CODED. Second and third mesopleuro-third axillary sclerite of fore wing muscle site of origin: NOT CODED. Mesopleuro-mesocoxal muscle site of origin: NOT CODED. Mesofurco-mesotrochanteral muscle presence: NOT CODED. Mesofurco-mesotrochanteral muscle relative position: NOT CODED. Mesofurco-mesotrochanteral muscle site of insertion: NOT CODED. S1 length vs. shortest width: NOT CODED. Transverse carina of petiole count: present (Fig. 2a). Transverse carina on petiole shape: concave. Basal, longitudinal carinae on syntergum count: more than 5 (Fig. 2b). Transverse sulcus of first metasomal sternum count (S1 count): absent. Waterston's evaporatorium count: present. Waterston's evaporatorium shape medially: not paired, single median evaporatorium present. Acrotergal calyx of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Waterston’s">Waterston's</normalizedToken>
evaporatorium count: acrotergal calyx absent.
</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="male genitalia">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Male Genitalia</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Median conjunctiva of male T9 count: absent. Row of short setae delimiting apical, cercus-bearing area of male T9: present. Male T10 shape: folded along median weakly sclerotised line. Median part of male S8 structure: not constricted medially, distal margin concave. Anterior margin shape of male S9: concave. Proximal margin part of male S9 shape: concave. Male S9 distal setal line / setal patch count: distal setae composing transverse setiferous line(s). Distomedian, hairless area (interrupting transverse row of setae or patch) on abdominal sternum 9 count: present (distal setiferous patch / line separated medially). Distal margin of male S9 shape: straight. Proximolateral corner of male S9 shape: acute. proximal lobe of vas deferens: NOT CODED. Distodorsal margin of cupula shape: straight (Fig. 4a). Cupula length vs. gonostyle-volsella complex length: cupula less than 1/2 the length of gonostyle-volsella complex in lateral view. Proximodorsal notch of cupula count: absent (Fig. 4a, b). Proximodorsal notch of cupula shape: NOT CODED. proximodorsal notch of cupula width vs. length: NOT CODED. Ventral part of cupula shape: cupula ventromedially is not extended more proximally than dorsomedially. Dorsal submedian impression of cupula count: present. Distoventral submedian corner of the cupula count: absent. Proximodorsal apodeme of cupula count: present. Proximolateral projection of the cupula shape: NOT CODED. Harpe presence: present. Harpe length: harpe shorter than gonostipes in lateral view. Lateral setae of harpe count: present. Lateral margin of harpe shape: widest point of harpe is at its articulation site with gonostyle-volsella complex (Fig. 4c, d). Sensillar ring area of harpe orientation: medially. Distodorsal setae of sensillar ring of harpe length vs. harpe width in lateral view: NOT CODED. Distoventral seta bearing projection of the harpe count: present. Distodorsal setae of sensillar ring of harpe orientation: NOT CODED. Proximomedial brush of the harpe count: present. Distal margin of harpe in lateral view: straight. Proximomedial apodeme of harpe count: absent. Lateral setae of harpe orientation: oriented distally. Proximodorsal projection of harpe accommodating the gonossiculus count: absent. Proximoventral margin of gonostyle/volsella complex shape: convex, pointed proximally. Distal end of dorsomedian conjunctiva of the gonostyle-volsella complex shape: NOT CODED. Dorsomedian conjunctiva of the gonostyle-volsella complex count: absent. Dorsomedian conjunctiva of the gonostyle-volsella complex length relative to length of gonostyle-volsella complex: NOT CODED. Gonostyle-volsella complex proximoventrally continuity: discontinuous, ventromedian conjunctiva of gonostyle-volsella complex complete, reaching proximal margin of gonostyle-volsella complex. Proximodorsal inflection of cupulal margin count: present. Gonostyle/volsella complex dorsally continuity: discontinuous, dorsomedian conjunctiva of gonostyle complete, extending between proximal and distal margins of gonostyle. Gonostyle/volsella complex proximodorsal margin shape: straight or slightly concave. Medioventral area of gonostyle/volsella complex orientation: horizontal. Distodorsal submedian notch of gonostyle/volsella complex count: absent. Submedian conjunctiva on distoventral margin of gonostyle/volsella complex: length (range of fusion of parossiculus/parossiculus complex from gonostipes): NOT CODED. Medioventral conjunctiva of the gonostyle-volsella complex presence (fusion of parossiculi): medioventral conjunctiva present (parossiculi independent or fused proximally). Parossiculus count (parossiculus and gonostipes fusion): absent (fused with the gonostipes). Apical parossiculal seta number: one. Distal projection of the parossiculus count: absent. Digital teeth orientation: dorsally. Penisvalva proximal region curvature: curved dorsally. Dorsal apodeme of penisvalva count: NOT CODED. Distal projection of the penisvalva count: absent. Ventromedian apodeme of aedeagus count: absent. Distal part of aedeagus and gonostyle continuity: continuous. Sensillar plate of the aedeagus shape: distinctly less than half as wide as the male genitalia. Mediolateral S9-cupulal muscle site of origin: laterally from anterolateral corner of S9. Lateral S9-cupulal muscle site of insertion: medially on the ventral part of cupula. Lateral S9-cupulal muscle subdivision: NOT CODED. Dorsomedial cupulo-gonostipal muscles orientation: converging proximally. Dorsolateral cupulo-gonostipal muscle count: present. Ventrolateral cupulo-gonostipal muscle count: present. Ventromedial cupulo-gonostyle muscle count: absent. Ventral gonostipo-penisvalval muscles site of origin-proximal extension: not extending distally on parossiculus. Lateral gonostyle-penisvalva muscle count: absent. Penisvalvo-gonossiculal muscle count: NOT CODED. Gonostipo-parossiculal muscle count: NOT CODED. Gonostyle/volsella complex-volsella muscle site of insertion: NOT CODED. Lateral intrinsic muscle of volsella: site of insertion: NOT CODED. Medial intrinsic muscle of the volsella count: NOT CODED. Parossiculo-penisvalval muscle count: NOT CODED. Proximal gonostipo-harpal muscle count: NOT CODED. Distal gonostipo-harpal muscle count: NOT CODED. Proximal gonostipo-harpal muscle site of origin: NOT CODED. Distal gonostipo-harpal muscle site of origin: NOT CODED. Distal gonostipo-harpal muscle gonostipal site of origin: NOT CODED.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="antennae">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Antennae</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Flagellar scrobe of the scape count: absent. Male flagellomeres shape: cylindric. 6th male flagellomere length vs. width, &quot;sensillar&quot; view: short, 1-1.4 times as long as wide. Length of setae on male flagellomere vs. male flagellomere width: setae shorter than width of flagellomeres. Male F1 length vs. pedicel length: 2.5-3.0. Male scape length vs. combined length of F1+F2: longer or equal. Whorled rows of erect, elongate setae on male flagellomeres count: absent. Male F6 length vs. combined length of F7+F8: Shorter than length of flagellomere 7+8. Male F1 length vs. male F2 length: 1.2-1.4. Male scape length vs. pedicel length: 4.1-4.3. Number of flagellomeres with male specific ventral sensilla: F5-9. Multiporous plates on male flagellomeres count: present. Male flagellomere branches count: None (Fig. 5b). Branch of male F5 length vs. length of male F5: NOT CODED. Branch of male flagellomere 5 length compared to flagellomere 6: NOT CODED. Basal resilin-rich area of male antennal branches count: NOT CODED. Female F1 length vs. pedicel length: NOT CODED. Female 9th flagellomere length: NOT CODED.</paragraph>
</subSection>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Diagnosis</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
Based on the presence of sickle-shaped sensilla on the male flagellomeres and the dorsoventrally compressed mesosoma (wider in dorsal view and high in lateral view), the new species belongs to the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceraphronidae" genus="Ceraphron" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceraphron" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Ceraphron</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceraphronidae" genus="Ceraphron" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceraphron krogmanni" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="krogmanni">Ceraphron krogmanni</taxonomicName>
differs from all other 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceraphronidae" genus="Ceraphron" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceraphron" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Ceraphron</taxonomicName>
species by the presence of a proximomedial harpal brush (mhb:Fig. 4c, d), the presence of ventromedial and dorsomedial ridges of the basal ring (vmr, dmr:Fig. 4a, b) and the unusually large male genitalia Fig. 2b (more than half the length of the syntergum in 
<taxonomicName authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Chironomidae" genus="C." higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="C. krogmanni" order="Diptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="krogmanni">C. krogmanni</taxonomicName>
whereas less than 1/3 of the syntergum in other 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ceraphronidae" genus="Ceraphron" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceraphron" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Ceraphron</taxonomicName>
species).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="24173" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">Etymology</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="24173">
The species epithet is a patronym, honouring Lars Krogmann, Staatliches Museum 
<normalizedToken originalValue="für">fuer</normalizedToken>
Naturkunde Stuttgart, who collected the specimens observed in this study.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>