<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6220557" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6a67b75c-4016-46fb-812c-b19c2b81b69e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119615143" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6220557" checkinTime="1461066789995" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Bittencourt, Jonathas De Souza &amp; Kellner, Alexander Wilhelm Armin" docDate="2009" docId="03BD5A05FF9CFFB3FF3525C5FD05FEDE" docLanguage="en" docName="zt02079p056.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2079" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@1cd3b138" docStyleName="zootaxa.2007.journal_article" docTitle="Staurikosaurus pricei Colbert 1970" docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" masterDocId="FF84227DFF9EFFB0FFA2207BFFB1FFAD" masterDocTitle="The anatomy and phylogenetic position of the Triassic dinosaur Staurikosaurus pricei Colbert, 1970" masterLastPageNumber="56" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" updateTime="1645519358687" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The anatomy and phylogenetic position of the Triassic dinosaur Staurikosaurus pricei Colbert, 1970</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bittencourt, Jonathas De Souza</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kellner, Alexander Wilhelm Armin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2079</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>56</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.187289</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">6a67b75c-4016-46fb-812c-b19c2b81b69e</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">187289</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6220557" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119615143" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6220557" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03BD5A05FF9CFFB3FF3525C5FD05FEDE" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BD5A05FF9CFFB3FF3525C5FD05FEDE" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,587,1470,1535]" box="[151,587,1470,1496]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,587,1470,1496]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" reason="1">
<taxonomicName authority="Colbert, 1970" authorityName="Colbert" authorityYear="1970" box="[151,587,1470,1496]" class="Reptilia" family="Staurikosauridae" genus="Staurikosaurus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Saurischia" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="pricei">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,587,1470,1496]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,410,1470,1496]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Staurikosaurus pricei</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Colbert" box="[418,587,1470,1496]" pageId="2" pageNumber="51" refString="Colbert, E. H. (1970) A saurischian dinosaur from the Triassic of Brazil. American Museum Novitates, 2405, 1 - 60." type="journal article" year="1970">
Colbert, 
<number box="[528,587,1470,1496]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="1970.0">1970</number>
</bibRefCitation>
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,587,1470,1535]" box="[151,305,1509,1535]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<figureCitation box="[151,305,1509,1535]" captionStart-0="FIGURE 1" captionStart-1="FIGURE 2" captionStart-10="FIGURE 11" captionStart-11="FIGURE 12" captionStart-12="FIGURE 13" captionStart-13="FIGURE 14" captionStart-14="FIGURE 15" captionStart-15="FIGURE 16" captionStart-16="FIGURE 17" captionStart-17="FIGURE 18" captionStart-18="FIGURE 19" captionStart-19="FIGURE 20" captionStart-2="FIGURE 3" captionStart-20="FIGURE 21" captionStart-21="FIGURE 23" captionStart-22="FIGURE 24" captionStart-23="FIGURE 25" captionStart-24="FIGURE 26" captionStart-25="FIGURE 27" captionStart-26="FIGURE 28" captionStart-27="FIGURE 29" captionStart-28="FIGURE 30" captionStart-29="FIGURE 31" captionStart-3="FIGURE 4" captionStart-30="FIGURE 32" captionStart-4="FIGURE 5" captionStart-5="FIGURE 6" captionStart-6="FIGURE 7" captionStart-7="FIGURE 8" captionStart-8="FIGURE 9" captionStart-9="FIGURE 10" captionStartId-0="3.[151,255,850,874]" captionStartId-1="4.[151,261,1654,1678]" captionStartId-10="17.[151,260,1337,1361]" captionStartId-11="18.[151,256,1384,1408]" captionStartId-12="19.[151,262,1152,1176]" captionStartId-13="20.[151,255,1022,1046]" captionStartId-14="21.[151,255,1368,1392]" captionStartId-15="22.[151,255,1110,1134]" captionStartId-16="23.[151,255,1599,1623]" captionStartId-17="24.[151,255,1211,1235]" captionStartId-18="25.[151,256,1574,1598]" captionStartId-19="26.[151,255,943,967]" captionStartId-2="5.[151,261,1920,1944]" captionStartId-20="27.[151,255,1702,1726]" captionStartId-21="30.[151,257,1849,1873]" captionStartId-22="31.[151,255,1396,1420]" captionStartId-23="34.[151,255,1743,1767]" captionStartId-24="35.[151,255,1713,1737]" captionStartId-25="36.[151,255,1379,1403]" captionStartId-26="37.[151,256,1731,1755]" captionStartId-27="38.[151,257,1595,1619]" captionStartId-28="39.[151,256,1305,1329]" captionStartId-29="40.[151,259,1184,1208]" captionStartId-3="6.[151,258,1487,1511]" captionStartId-30="41.[151,255,1491,1515]" captionStartId-4="11.[151,259,1269,1293]" captionStartId-5="12.[151,255,1291,1315]" captionStartId-6="13.[151,255,1250,1274]" captionStartId-7="14.[151,257,1546,1570]" captionStartId-8="15.[151,255,935,959]" captionStartId-9="16.[151,257,1583,1607]" captionTargetBox-0="[285,1295,475,803]" captionTargetBox-1="[264,1322,197,1615]" captionTargetBox-10="[264,1302,351,1311]" captionTargetBox-11="[264,1303,194,1360]" captionTargetBox-12="[264,1306,194,1127]" captionTargetBox-13="[264,1323,194,997]" captionTargetBox-14="[264,1322,197,1343]" captionTargetBox-15="[264,1322,493,1085]" captionTargetBox-16="[264,1322,194,1563]" captionTargetBox-17="[264,1323,194,1169]" captionTargetBox-18="[340,1221,197,1549]" captionTargetBox-19="[264,1322,194,919]" captionTargetBox-2="[264,1322,184,1919]" captionTargetBox-20="[151,1412,581,1677]" captionTargetBox-21="[378,1210,197,1789]" captionTargetBox-22="[264,1322,194,1342]" captionTargetBox-23="[151,1435,777,1717]" captionTargetBox-24="[264,1322,611,1688]" captionTargetBox-25="[264,1312,194,1355]" captionTargetBox-26="[151,1436,194,1706]" captionTargetBox-27="[264,1322,649,1571]" captionTargetBox-28="[264,1296,383,1280]" captionTargetBox-29="[264,1322,506,1158]" captionTargetBox-3="[264,1322,387,1463]" captionTargetBox-30="[265,1322,738,1464]" captionTargetBox-4="[264,1302,197,1243]" captionTargetBox-5="[264,1314,197,1266]" captionTargetBox-6="[264,1307,194,1226]" captionTargetBox-7="[264,1322,197,1501]" captionTargetBox-8="[264,1322,306,910]" captionTargetBox-9="[151,1419,197,1558]" captionTargetId-0="figure@3.[264,1323,429,825]" captionTargetId-1="figure@4.[264,1323,197,1629]" captionTargetId-10="figure@17.[264,1323,351,1311]" captionTargetId-11="figure@18.[264,1323,194,1360]" captionTargetId-12="figure@19.[264,1323,194,1128]" captionTargetId-13="figure@20.[264,1323,194,998]" captionTargetId-14="figure@21.[264,1323,197,1343]" captionTargetId-15="figure@22.[264,1323,493,1086]" captionTargetId-16="figure@23.[264,1323,194,1575]" captionTargetId-17="figure@24.[264,1323,194,1187]" captionTargetId-18="figure@25.[340,1248,197,1549]" captionTargetId-19="figure@26.[264,1323,194,919]" captionTargetId-2="figure@5.[264,1323,184,1928]" captionTargetId-20="figure@27.[151,1436,581,1679]" captionTargetId-21="figure@30.[378,1210,197,1824]" captionTargetId-22="figure@31.[264,1323,194,1372]" captionTargetId-23="figure@34.[151,1436,777,1718]" captionTargetId-24="figure@35.[264,1323,611,1688]" captionTargetId-25="figure@36.[264,1323,194,1355]" captionTargetId-26="figure@37.[151,1436,194,1708]" captionTargetId-27="figure@38.[264,1323,649,1572]" captionTargetId-28="figure@39.[264,1323,383,1280]" captionTargetId-29="figure@40.[264,1323,506,1158]" captionTargetId-3="figure@6.[264,1323,387,1463]" captionTargetId-30="figure@41.[265,1322,738,1466]" captionTargetId-4="figure@11.[264,1323,197,1244]" captionTargetId-5="figure@12.[264,1323,197,1266]" captionTargetId-6="figure@13.[264,1323,194,1226]" captionTargetId-7="figure@14.[264,1323,197,1521]" captionTargetId-8="figure@15.[264,1323,306,911]" captionTargetId-9="figure@16.[151,1436,197,1558]" captionTargetPageId-0="3" captionTargetPageId-1="4" captionTargetPageId-10="17" captionTargetPageId-11="18" captionTargetPageId-12="19" captionTargetPageId-13="20" captionTargetPageId-14="21" captionTargetPageId-15="22" captionTargetPageId-16="23" captionTargetPageId-17="24" captionTargetPageId-18="25" captionTargetPageId-19="26" captionTargetPageId-2="5" captionTargetPageId-20="27" captionTargetPageId-21="30" captionTargetPageId-22="31" captionTargetPageId-23="34" captionTargetPageId-24="35" captionTargetPageId-25="36" captionTargetPageId-26="37" captionTargetPageId-27="38" captionTargetPageId-28="39" captionTargetPageId-29="40" captionTargetPageId-3="6" captionTargetPageId-30="41" captionTargetPageId-4="11" captionTargetPageId-5="12" captionTargetPageId-6="13" captionTargetPageId-7="14" captionTargetPageId-8="15" captionTargetPageId-9="16" captionText-0="FIGURE 1. Staurikosaurus pricei, skeletal reconstruction, (based upon MCZ 1669, holotype), depicting the preserved bones. After Novas (1997). Scale bar = 20 cm." captionText-1="FIGURE 2. Photographs and drawings of the left mandibular ramus in lateral (a, b) and medial (c, d) views. Abbreviations: adf, adductor fossa; an, angular; ar, articular; d, dentary; df, dentary furrow; frm, foramen; pra, prearticular; sa, surangular; spl, splenial; t 1 – t 15, preserved teeth or fragments of teeth numbered sequentially beginning at the rostral end of the dentary. Scale bar = 4 cm." captionText-10="FIGURE 11. Photographs and drawings of the second sacral vertebra in cranial (a – b) and caudal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: crls, craniolateral sulcus; lcpl, lateral concavity on the lateral process; lpr, lateral process; mclp, medial concavity on the lateral process; ns, neural spine; prz, prezygapophysis; poz, postzygapophysis; sprzl, spinoprezygapophyseal lamina. Scale bars = 4 cm." captionText-11="FIGURE 12. Photographs and drawings of the third sacral vertebra in left lateral (a – b), dorsal (c – d) and ventral (e – f) views. Abbreviations: asi, articular surface for ilium; lpr, lateral process; prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process. Scale bar = 2 cm." captionText-12="FIGURE 13. Photographs and drawings of the third sacral vertebra in cranial (a – b) and caudal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: lpr, lateral process; tp, transverse process. Scale bar = 2 cm." captionText-13="FIGURE 14. Photographs of the third sacral (a) and the first caudal vertebrae (b) in right lateral view. Scale bar for (a) = 2 cm; (b) = 2.5 cm." captionText-14="FIGURE 15. Photographs of the second caudal vertebra in dorsal (a) and ventral (b) views, and the third caudal vertebra in right lateral (c) and caudal views (d). Scale bars = 2 cm." captionText-15="FIGURE 16. Photographs of the fourth caudal vertebra in right lateral (a), caudal vertebrae, sequence 1 (b) in left lateral view, and caudal vertebrae, sequence 2 (c) in right lateral view. Scale bar for (a) = 2 cm; (b – c) = 3 cm." captionText-16="FIGURE 17. Photographs and drawings of six distal caudal vertebrae, sequence 3, in right lateral view (a – b), and seven distal caudal vertebrae, sequence 4, in left lateral view (c – d). Abbreviations: prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process. Scale bar for (a – b) = 5 cm; (c – d) = 6 cm." captionText-17="FIGURE 18. Photographs and drawings of the distal caudal vertebrae, sequence 5 (a – b) and sequence 6 (c – d), in right lateral view. Abbreviation: zp, zygapophysis. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-18="FIGURE 19. Photographs and drawings of distal caudal vertebrae in ventral view, sequence 5 (a – b) and detail of the caudal vertebrae of sequence 3 (c). Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm; (c) = 2 cm." captionText-19="FIGURE 20. Photographs of the left scapula in lateral (a) and distal (b) views. Scale bar = 1 cm." captionText-2="FIGURE 3. Photographs and drawings of the left mandibular ramus in dorsal (a, b) and ventral (c, d) views. Abbreviations: an, angular; ar, articular; d, dentary; emf, external mandibular fenestra; mac, mandibular canal; pra, prearticular; sa, surangular; spl, splenial. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-20="FIGURE 21. Photograph and drawing of the left ilium associated with the vertebral column, in lateral view (a – b), and the right ilium in lateral view (c – d). Abbreviations: ant, antitrochanter; caic, caudal iliac concavity; cric, cranial iliac concavity; isp, ischial peduncle; prap, preacetabular process; prac, preacetabular crest; pup, pubic peduncle; poa, postacetabular process; poae, postacetabular elevation; s 1, first sacral vertebra; sac, supraacetabular crest. Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm; for (c – d) = 5 cm." captionText-21="FIGURE 23. Photographs and drawings of the left pubis in lateral (a – b) and medial (c – d) views. Abbreviations: b, distinct bevel on distal end of pubic; pdex, distal expansion of pubis. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-22="FIGURE 24. Photographs and drawings of the left ischium in lateral (a – b) and medial (c – d) views and the right ischium (e – f) in lateral view. Abbreviations: ciex, caudal ischial excavation; cipr, caudal ischial process; ia, ischial axis; iop, ischial obturator plate. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-23="FIGURE 25. Photographs of the right femur in cranial (a), medial (b), caudal (c), and lateral views (d). Abbreviations: calc, caudolateral crest; f 4 t, femoral fourth trochanter; ffic, femoral fibular condyle; fclc, femoral craniolateral crest; fh, femoral head; ftic, femoral tibial condyle. Scale bar = 7 cm." captionText-24="FIGURE 26. Photographs of the right femur in proximal (a) and distal (b) views, the proximal part of the left femur that is attached to vertebral column (see Fig. 8) in laterocaudal view (c), and the isolated distal part of the left femur in lateral view (d). Abbreviations: fccs, craniocaudal sulcus on the dorsal surface of the femoral head; ffic, femoral fibular condyle; fgt, femoral “ greater ” trochanter; fh, femoral head; fhct, craniomedial tuberosity of the femoral head; fhds, mediolateral dorsal sulcus of the femoral head; fhls, sulcus for ligamentum captis femoris; fhmt, caudomedial tuberosity of the femoral head; ftic, femoral tibial condyle. Scale bar for (a – b) = 2 cm; (c – d) = 8 cm." captionText-25="FIGURE 27. Photographs and drawings of the right (a – b) and left (c – d) proximal femora in cranial view. Abbreviations: artef, artefactual shelf; fclc (fgt), femoral craniolateral crest, part of the “ greater ” trochanter; fcmc, femoral craniomedial crest. Scale bars = 2 cm." captionText-26="FIGURE 28. Photographs of the right tibia in medial (a), cranial (b), caudal (c) and lateral (d) views; the left tibia in medial view (e), and the right tibia in proximal (f) and distal (g) views. Abbreviations: af, articular facet for the ascending process of the astragalus; cls, craniolateral sulcus; cms, craniomedial sulcus; cn, cnemial crest; crcs, craniocaudal dorsal sulcus; fck, fibular condyle keel; mls, mediolateral sulcus; ppv, caudoventral process; tfc, tibial condyle for fibula; tic, tibial inner condyle. Scale bar for (a – e) = 7 cm; (f – g) = 1 cm." captionText-27="FIGURE 29. Photographs of the left fibula in cranial (a), caudal (b), proximal (e) and distal (f) views, and the right fibula in lateral (c) and medial (f) views. Scale bar for (a – d) = 8 cm; (e – f) = 2 cm." captionText-28="FIGURE 30. Photographs and drawings of the left fibula in lateral (a – b) and medial (c – d) views. Abbreviations: fms, fibular medial sulcus; ifi, insertion of the ilifibularis muscle; mis, scar for muscular insertion. Scale bar = 8 cm." captionText-29="FIGURE 31. Photographs of an undetermined bone, initially described as the right humerus by Colbert (1970). Undetermined orientations. Scale bar = 2 cm." captionText-3="FIGURE 4. Photographs of the right mandibular ramus in medial (a) and lateral (b) views. Photographs of the left mandibular ramus in lateral view (c) demonstrating the morphology of the 8 th tooth and details of the serrated carina. Abbreviations: adf, adductor fossa; an, angular; d, dentary; emf, external mandibular fenestra; pra, prearticular; sa, surangular; spl, splenial. Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm. Scale bars for (c) = 4 cm for mandible, 5 mm for the tooth, and 1 mm for the details of tooth serrations." captionText-30="FIGURE 32. Undetermined bone fragments. Scale bar = 5 cm." captionText-4="FIGURE 5. Photographs and drawings of the fourth cervical vertebra in left (a – b) and right (c – d) lateral views. Abbreviations: caf, caudal fossa; crf, cranial fossa; ipoe, infrapostzygapophyseal excavation; ns, neural spine; pa, parapophysis; podl, postzygodiapophyseal lamina; poz, postzygapophysis; prdl, prezygodiapophyseal lamina; prz, prezygapophysis; przf, prezygapophysis articular facet; tp, transverse process; vk, median ventral keel. Scale bar = 3 cm." captionText-5="FIGURE 6. Photographs and drawings of the presumed fourth cervical vertebra in ventral (a – b) and dorsal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: ep, epipophysis; ns, neural spine; pa, parapophysis; poz, postzygapophysis; prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process; vk, median ventral keel. Scale bar = 3 cm." captionText-6="FIGURE 7. Photographs and drawings of the presumed fourth cervical vertebra in cranial (a – b) and caudal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: caaf, caudal articular facet of centrum; ccaf, cranial articular facet of centrum; itpos, interpostzygapophyseal sulcus; nc, neural canal; ns, neural spine; pa, parapophysis; poz, postzygapophysis; prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process. Scale bar = 3 cm." captionText-7="FIGURE 8. Photograph and drawing of cervical and dorsal vertebrae embedded within sediment along with the left femur, in right lateral view. Abbreviations: c 5 – c 9, presumed cervical vertebrae 5 to 9; d 1 – d 8, dorsal vertebrae 1 to 8; f, femur. Scale bar = 8 cm." captionText-8="FIGURE 9. Photographs of dorsal vertebrae 9 – 11 in right lateral view (a) and the centrum of the 12 th dorsal vertebra (b) in cranial view. Abbreviations: d 9 – d 11, dorsal vertebrae 9 to 11. Scale bar = 2.5 cm." captionText-9="FIGURE 10. Photographs and drawings of the caudal dorsal vertebrae in right lateral view, associated with the first sacral and the left ilium (a – b), and detail of the 8 th dorsal vertebra in left lateral view (c – d). The miniature photo (e) marks the region of the block detailed in (c – d) (see also Fig. 8). Abbreviations: ccdl, caudal centrodiapophyseal lamina; crcdl, cranial centrodiapophyseal lamina; d 8, 8 th dorsal vertebra; d 11 – d 15, dorsal vertebrae 11 to 15; hypo?, doubtful hyposphene; il, ilium; ipzf, infrapostzygapophyseal fossa; podl, postzygodiapophyseal lamina; poz, postzygapophysis; tp, transverse process; s 1, first sacral vertebra. Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm; (c – d) = 5 mm; miniature = 8 cm." httpUri-0="https://zenodo.org/record/187290/files/figure.png" httpUri-1="https://zenodo.org/record/187291/files/figure.png" httpUri-10="https://zenodo.org/record/187300/files/figure.png" httpUri-11="https://zenodo.org/record/187301/files/figure.png" httpUri-12="https://zenodo.org/record/187302/files/figure.png" httpUri-13="https://zenodo.org/record/187303/files/figure.png" httpUri-14="https://zenodo.org/record/187304/files/figure.png" httpUri-15="https://zenodo.org/record/187305/files/figure.png" httpUri-16="https://zenodo.org/record/187306/files/figure.png" httpUri-17="https://zenodo.org/record/187307/files/figure.png" httpUri-18="https://zenodo.org/record/187308/files/figure.png" httpUri-19="https://zenodo.org/record/187309/files/figure.png" httpUri-2="https://zenodo.org/record/187292/files/figure.png" httpUri-20="https://zenodo.org/record/187310/files/figure.png" httpUri-21="https://zenodo.org/record/187311/files/figure.png" httpUri-22="https://zenodo.org/record/187312/files/figure.png" httpUri-23="https://zenodo.org/record/187313/files/figure.png" httpUri-24="https://zenodo.org/record/187314/files/figure.png" httpUri-25="https://zenodo.org/record/187315/files/figure.png" httpUri-26="https://zenodo.org/record/187316/files/figure.png" httpUri-27="https://zenodo.org/record/187317/files/figure.png" httpUri-28="https://zenodo.org/record/187318/files/figure.png" httpUri-29="https://zenodo.org/record/187319/files/figure.png" httpUri-3="https://zenodo.org/record/187293/files/figure.png" httpUri-30="https://zenodo.org/record/187320/files/figure.png" httpUri-4="https://zenodo.org/record/187294/files/figure.png" httpUri-5="https://zenodo.org/record/187295/files/figure.png" httpUri-6="https://zenodo.org/record/187296/files/figure.png" httpUri-7="https://zenodo.org/record/187297/files/figure.png" httpUri-8="https://zenodo.org/record/187298/files/figure.png" httpUri-9="https://zenodo.org/record/187299/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figures 
<number box="[246,305,1509,1535]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="16.5" valueMax="32.0" valueMin="1.0">1–32</number>
</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,1437,1586,2038]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,276,1586,1612]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<typeStatus box="[151,271,1586,1612]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Holotype</typeStatus>
.
</emphasis>
Incomplete skeleton (
<collectionCode LSID="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33791" box="[546,613,1586,1612]" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33791" name="Museum of Comparative Zoology" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">MCZ</collectionCode>
<number box="[621,684,1586,1612]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="1669.0">1669</number>
, 
<figureCitation box="[698,822,1586,1612]" captionStart-0="FIGURE 1" captionStart-1="FIGURE 2" captionStart-10="FIGURE 11" captionStart-11="FIGURE 12" captionStart-12="FIGURE 13" captionStart-13="FIGURE 14" captionStart-14="FIGURE 15" captionStart-15="FIGURE 16" captionStart-16="FIGURE 17" captionStart-17="FIGURE 18" captionStart-18="FIGURE 19" captionStart-19="FIGURE 20" captionStart-2="FIGURE 3" captionStart-20="FIGURE 21" captionStart-21="FIGURE 23" captionStart-22="FIGURE 24" captionStart-23="FIGURE 25" captionStart-24="FIGURE 26" captionStart-25="FIGURE 27" captionStart-26="FIGURE 28" captionStart-27="FIGURE 29" captionStart-28="FIGURE 30" captionStart-29="FIGURE 31" captionStart-3="FIGURE 4" captionStart-30="FIGURE 32" captionStart-4="FIGURE 5" captionStart-5="FIGURE 6" captionStart-6="FIGURE 7" captionStart-7="FIGURE 8" captionStart-8="FIGURE 9" captionStart-9="FIGURE 10" captionStartId-0="3.[151,255,850,874]" captionStartId-1="4.[151,261,1654,1678]" captionStartId-10="17.[151,260,1337,1361]" captionStartId-11="18.[151,256,1384,1408]" captionStartId-12="19.[151,262,1152,1176]" captionStartId-13="20.[151,255,1022,1046]" captionStartId-14="21.[151,255,1368,1392]" captionStartId-15="22.[151,255,1110,1134]" captionStartId-16="23.[151,255,1599,1623]" captionStartId-17="24.[151,255,1211,1235]" captionStartId-18="25.[151,256,1574,1598]" captionStartId-19="26.[151,255,943,967]" captionStartId-2="5.[151,261,1920,1944]" captionStartId-20="27.[151,255,1702,1726]" captionStartId-21="30.[151,257,1849,1873]" captionStartId-22="31.[151,255,1396,1420]" captionStartId-23="34.[151,255,1743,1767]" captionStartId-24="35.[151,255,1713,1737]" captionStartId-25="36.[151,255,1379,1403]" captionStartId-26="37.[151,256,1731,1755]" captionStartId-27="38.[151,257,1595,1619]" captionStartId-28="39.[151,256,1305,1329]" captionStartId-29="40.[151,259,1184,1208]" captionStartId-3="6.[151,258,1487,1511]" captionStartId-30="41.[151,255,1491,1515]" captionStartId-4="11.[151,259,1269,1293]" captionStartId-5="12.[151,255,1291,1315]" captionStartId-6="13.[151,255,1250,1274]" captionStartId-7="14.[151,257,1546,1570]" captionStartId-8="15.[151,255,935,959]" captionStartId-9="16.[151,257,1583,1607]" captionTargetBox-0="[285,1295,475,803]" captionTargetBox-1="[264,1322,197,1615]" captionTargetBox-10="[264,1302,351,1311]" captionTargetBox-11="[264,1303,194,1360]" captionTargetBox-12="[264,1306,194,1127]" captionTargetBox-13="[264,1323,194,997]" captionTargetBox-14="[264,1322,197,1343]" captionTargetBox-15="[264,1322,493,1085]" captionTargetBox-16="[264,1322,194,1563]" captionTargetBox-17="[264,1323,194,1169]" captionTargetBox-18="[340,1221,197,1549]" captionTargetBox-19="[264,1322,194,919]" captionTargetBox-2="[264,1322,184,1919]" captionTargetBox-20="[151,1412,581,1677]" captionTargetBox-21="[378,1210,197,1789]" captionTargetBox-22="[264,1322,194,1342]" captionTargetBox-23="[151,1435,777,1717]" captionTargetBox-24="[264,1322,611,1688]" captionTargetBox-25="[264,1312,194,1355]" captionTargetBox-26="[151,1436,194,1706]" captionTargetBox-27="[264,1322,649,1571]" captionTargetBox-28="[264,1296,383,1280]" captionTargetBox-29="[264,1322,506,1158]" captionTargetBox-3="[264,1322,387,1463]" captionTargetBox-30="[265,1322,738,1464]" captionTargetBox-4="[264,1302,197,1243]" captionTargetBox-5="[264,1314,197,1266]" captionTargetBox-6="[264,1307,194,1226]" captionTargetBox-7="[264,1322,197,1501]" captionTargetBox-8="[264,1322,306,910]" captionTargetBox-9="[151,1419,197,1558]" captionTargetId-0="figure@3.[264,1323,429,825]" captionTargetId-1="figure@4.[264,1323,197,1629]" captionTargetId-10="figure@17.[264,1323,351,1311]" captionTargetId-11="figure@18.[264,1323,194,1360]" captionTargetId-12="figure@19.[264,1323,194,1128]" captionTargetId-13="figure@20.[264,1323,194,998]" captionTargetId-14="figure@21.[264,1323,197,1343]" captionTargetId-15="figure@22.[264,1323,493,1086]" captionTargetId-16="figure@23.[264,1323,194,1575]" captionTargetId-17="figure@24.[264,1323,194,1187]" captionTargetId-18="figure@25.[340,1248,197,1549]" captionTargetId-19="figure@26.[264,1323,194,919]" captionTargetId-2="figure@5.[264,1323,184,1928]" captionTargetId-20="figure@27.[151,1436,581,1679]" captionTargetId-21="figure@30.[378,1210,197,1824]" captionTargetId-22="figure@31.[264,1323,194,1372]" captionTargetId-23="figure@34.[151,1436,777,1718]" captionTargetId-24="figure@35.[264,1323,611,1688]" captionTargetId-25="figure@36.[264,1323,194,1355]" captionTargetId-26="figure@37.[151,1436,194,1708]" captionTargetId-27="figure@38.[264,1323,649,1572]" captionTargetId-28="figure@39.[264,1323,383,1280]" captionTargetId-29="figure@40.[264,1323,506,1158]" captionTargetId-3="figure@6.[264,1323,387,1463]" captionTargetId-30="figure@41.[265,1322,738,1466]" captionTargetId-4="figure@11.[264,1323,197,1244]" captionTargetId-5="figure@12.[264,1323,197,1266]" captionTargetId-6="figure@13.[264,1323,194,1226]" captionTargetId-7="figure@14.[264,1323,197,1521]" captionTargetId-8="figure@15.[264,1323,306,911]" captionTargetId-9="figure@16.[151,1436,197,1558]" captionTargetPageId-0="3" captionTargetPageId-1="4" captionTargetPageId-10="17" captionTargetPageId-11="18" captionTargetPageId-12="19" captionTargetPageId-13="20" captionTargetPageId-14="21" captionTargetPageId-15="22" captionTargetPageId-16="23" captionTargetPageId-17="24" captionTargetPageId-18="25" captionTargetPageId-19="26" captionTargetPageId-2="5" captionTargetPageId-20="27" captionTargetPageId-21="30" captionTargetPageId-22="31" captionTargetPageId-23="34" captionTargetPageId-24="35" captionTargetPageId-25="36" captionTargetPageId-26="37" captionTargetPageId-27="38" captionTargetPageId-28="39" captionTargetPageId-29="40" captionTargetPageId-3="6" captionTargetPageId-30="41" captionTargetPageId-4="11" captionTargetPageId-5="12" captionTargetPageId-6="13" captionTargetPageId-7="14" captionTargetPageId-8="15" captionTargetPageId-9="16" captionText-0="FIGURE 1. Staurikosaurus pricei, skeletal reconstruction, (based upon MCZ 1669, holotype), depicting the preserved bones. After Novas (1997). Scale bar = 20 cm." captionText-1="FIGURE 2. Photographs and drawings of the left mandibular ramus in lateral (a, b) and medial (c, d) views. Abbreviations: adf, adductor fossa; an, angular; ar, articular; d, dentary; df, dentary furrow; frm, foramen; pra, prearticular; sa, surangular; spl, splenial; t 1 – t 15, preserved teeth or fragments of teeth numbered sequentially beginning at the rostral end of the dentary. Scale bar = 4 cm." captionText-10="FIGURE 11. Photographs and drawings of the second sacral vertebra in cranial (a – b) and caudal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: crls, craniolateral sulcus; lcpl, lateral concavity on the lateral process; lpr, lateral process; mclp, medial concavity on the lateral process; ns, neural spine; prz, prezygapophysis; poz, postzygapophysis; sprzl, spinoprezygapophyseal lamina. Scale bars = 4 cm." captionText-11="FIGURE 12. Photographs and drawings of the third sacral vertebra in left lateral (a – b), dorsal (c – d) and ventral (e – f) views. Abbreviations: asi, articular surface for ilium; lpr, lateral process; prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process. Scale bar = 2 cm." captionText-12="FIGURE 13. Photographs and drawings of the third sacral vertebra in cranial (a – b) and caudal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: lpr, lateral process; tp, transverse process. Scale bar = 2 cm." captionText-13="FIGURE 14. Photographs of the third sacral (a) and the first caudal vertebrae (b) in right lateral view. Scale bar for (a) = 2 cm; (b) = 2.5 cm." captionText-14="FIGURE 15. Photographs of the second caudal vertebra in dorsal (a) and ventral (b) views, and the third caudal vertebra in right lateral (c) and caudal views (d). Scale bars = 2 cm." captionText-15="FIGURE 16. Photographs of the fourth caudal vertebra in right lateral (a), caudal vertebrae, sequence 1 (b) in left lateral view, and caudal vertebrae, sequence 2 (c) in right lateral view. Scale bar for (a) = 2 cm; (b – c) = 3 cm." captionText-16="FIGURE 17. Photographs and drawings of six distal caudal vertebrae, sequence 3, in right lateral view (a – b), and seven distal caudal vertebrae, sequence 4, in left lateral view (c – d). Abbreviations: prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process. Scale bar for (a – b) = 5 cm; (c – d) = 6 cm." captionText-17="FIGURE 18. Photographs and drawings of the distal caudal vertebrae, sequence 5 (a – b) and sequence 6 (c – d), in right lateral view. Abbreviation: zp, zygapophysis. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-18="FIGURE 19. Photographs and drawings of distal caudal vertebrae in ventral view, sequence 5 (a – b) and detail of the caudal vertebrae of sequence 3 (c). Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm; (c) = 2 cm." captionText-19="FIGURE 20. Photographs of the left scapula in lateral (a) and distal (b) views. Scale bar = 1 cm." captionText-2="FIGURE 3. Photographs and drawings of the left mandibular ramus in dorsal (a, b) and ventral (c, d) views. Abbreviations: an, angular; ar, articular; d, dentary; emf, external mandibular fenestra; mac, mandibular canal; pra, prearticular; sa, surangular; spl, splenial. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-20="FIGURE 21. Photograph and drawing of the left ilium associated with the vertebral column, in lateral view (a – b), and the right ilium in lateral view (c – d). Abbreviations: ant, antitrochanter; caic, caudal iliac concavity; cric, cranial iliac concavity; isp, ischial peduncle; prap, preacetabular process; prac, preacetabular crest; pup, pubic peduncle; poa, postacetabular process; poae, postacetabular elevation; s 1, first sacral vertebra; sac, supraacetabular crest. Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm; for (c – d) = 5 cm." captionText-21="FIGURE 23. Photographs and drawings of the left pubis in lateral (a – b) and medial (c – d) views. Abbreviations: b, distinct bevel on distal end of pubic; pdex, distal expansion of pubis. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-22="FIGURE 24. Photographs and drawings of the left ischium in lateral (a – b) and medial (c – d) views and the right ischium (e – f) in lateral view. Abbreviations: ciex, caudal ischial excavation; cipr, caudal ischial process; ia, ischial axis; iop, ischial obturator plate. Scale bar = 6 cm." captionText-23="FIGURE 25. Photographs of the right femur in cranial (a), medial (b), caudal (c), and lateral views (d). Abbreviations: calc, caudolateral crest; f 4 t, femoral fourth trochanter; ffic, femoral fibular condyle; fclc, femoral craniolateral crest; fh, femoral head; ftic, femoral tibial condyle. Scale bar = 7 cm." captionText-24="FIGURE 26. Photographs of the right femur in proximal (a) and distal (b) views, the proximal part of the left femur that is attached to vertebral column (see Fig. 8) in laterocaudal view (c), and the isolated distal part of the left femur in lateral view (d). Abbreviations: fccs, craniocaudal sulcus on the dorsal surface of the femoral head; ffic, femoral fibular condyle; fgt, femoral “ greater ” trochanter; fh, femoral head; fhct, craniomedial tuberosity of the femoral head; fhds, mediolateral dorsal sulcus of the femoral head; fhls, sulcus for ligamentum captis femoris; fhmt, caudomedial tuberosity of the femoral head; ftic, femoral tibial condyle. Scale bar for (a – b) = 2 cm; (c – d) = 8 cm." captionText-25="FIGURE 27. Photographs and drawings of the right (a – b) and left (c – d) proximal femora in cranial view. Abbreviations: artef, artefactual shelf; fclc (fgt), femoral craniolateral crest, part of the “ greater ” trochanter; fcmc, femoral craniomedial crest. Scale bars = 2 cm." captionText-26="FIGURE 28. Photographs of the right tibia in medial (a), cranial (b), caudal (c) and lateral (d) views; the left tibia in medial view (e), and the right tibia in proximal (f) and distal (g) views. Abbreviations: af, articular facet for the ascending process of the astragalus; cls, craniolateral sulcus; cms, craniomedial sulcus; cn, cnemial crest; crcs, craniocaudal dorsal sulcus; fck, fibular condyle keel; mls, mediolateral sulcus; ppv, caudoventral process; tfc, tibial condyle for fibula; tic, tibial inner condyle. Scale bar for (a – e) = 7 cm; (f – g) = 1 cm." captionText-27="FIGURE 29. Photographs of the left fibula in cranial (a), caudal (b), proximal (e) and distal (f) views, and the right fibula in lateral (c) and medial (f) views. Scale bar for (a – d) = 8 cm; (e – f) = 2 cm." captionText-28="FIGURE 30. Photographs and drawings of the left fibula in lateral (a – b) and medial (c – d) views. Abbreviations: fms, fibular medial sulcus; ifi, insertion of the ilifibularis muscle; mis, scar for muscular insertion. Scale bar = 8 cm." captionText-29="FIGURE 31. Photographs of an undetermined bone, initially described as the right humerus by Colbert (1970). Undetermined orientations. Scale bar = 2 cm." captionText-3="FIGURE 4. Photographs of the right mandibular ramus in medial (a) and lateral (b) views. Photographs of the left mandibular ramus in lateral view (c) demonstrating the morphology of the 8 th tooth and details of the serrated carina. Abbreviations: adf, adductor fossa; an, angular; d, dentary; emf, external mandibular fenestra; pra, prearticular; sa, surangular; spl, splenial. Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm. Scale bars for (c) = 4 cm for mandible, 5 mm for the tooth, and 1 mm for the details of tooth serrations." captionText-30="FIGURE 32. Undetermined bone fragments. Scale bar = 5 cm." captionText-4="FIGURE 5. Photographs and drawings of the fourth cervical vertebra in left (a – b) and right (c – d) lateral views. Abbreviations: caf, caudal fossa; crf, cranial fossa; ipoe, infrapostzygapophyseal excavation; ns, neural spine; pa, parapophysis; podl, postzygodiapophyseal lamina; poz, postzygapophysis; prdl, prezygodiapophyseal lamina; prz, prezygapophysis; przf, prezygapophysis articular facet; tp, transverse process; vk, median ventral keel. Scale bar = 3 cm." captionText-5="FIGURE 6. Photographs and drawings of the presumed fourth cervical vertebra in ventral (a – b) and dorsal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: ep, epipophysis; ns, neural spine; pa, parapophysis; poz, postzygapophysis; prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process; vk, median ventral keel. Scale bar = 3 cm." captionText-6="FIGURE 7. Photographs and drawings of the presumed fourth cervical vertebra in cranial (a – b) and caudal (c – d) views. Abbreviations: caaf, caudal articular facet of centrum; ccaf, cranial articular facet of centrum; itpos, interpostzygapophyseal sulcus; nc, neural canal; ns, neural spine; pa, parapophysis; poz, postzygapophysis; prz, prezygapophysis; tp, transverse process. Scale bar = 3 cm." captionText-7="FIGURE 8. Photograph and drawing of cervical and dorsal vertebrae embedded within sediment along with the left femur, in right lateral view. Abbreviations: c 5 – c 9, presumed cervical vertebrae 5 to 9; d 1 – d 8, dorsal vertebrae 1 to 8; f, femur. Scale bar = 8 cm." captionText-8="FIGURE 9. Photographs of dorsal vertebrae 9 – 11 in right lateral view (a) and the centrum of the 12 th dorsal vertebra (b) in cranial view. Abbreviations: d 9 – d 11, dorsal vertebrae 9 to 11. Scale bar = 2.5 cm." captionText-9="FIGURE 10. Photographs and drawings of the caudal dorsal vertebrae in right lateral view, associated with the first sacral and the left ilium (a – b), and detail of the 8 th dorsal vertebra in left lateral view (c – d). The miniature photo (e) marks the region of the block detailed in (c – d) (see also Fig. 8). Abbreviations: ccdl, caudal centrodiapophyseal lamina; crcdl, cranial centrodiapophyseal lamina; d 8, 8 th dorsal vertebra; d 11 – d 15, dorsal vertebrae 11 to 15; hypo?, doubtful hyposphene; il, ilium; ipzf, infrapostzygapophyseal fossa; podl, postzygodiapophyseal lamina; poz, postzygapophysis; tp, transverse process; s 1, first sacral vertebra. Scale bar for (a – b) = 6 cm; (c – d) = 5 mm; miniature = 8 cm." httpUri-0="https://zenodo.org/record/187290/files/figure.png" httpUri-1="https://zenodo.org/record/187291/files/figure.png" httpUri-10="https://zenodo.org/record/187300/files/figure.png" httpUri-11="https://zenodo.org/record/187301/files/figure.png" httpUri-12="https://zenodo.org/record/187302/files/figure.png" httpUri-13="https://zenodo.org/record/187303/files/figure.png" httpUri-14="https://zenodo.org/record/187304/files/figure.png" httpUri-15="https://zenodo.org/record/187305/files/figure.png" httpUri-16="https://zenodo.org/record/187306/files/figure.png" httpUri-17="https://zenodo.org/record/187307/files/figure.png" httpUri-18="https://zenodo.org/record/187308/files/figure.png" httpUri-19="https://zenodo.org/record/187309/files/figure.png" httpUri-2="https://zenodo.org/record/187292/files/figure.png" httpUri-20="https://zenodo.org/record/187310/files/figure.png" httpUri-21="https://zenodo.org/record/187311/files/figure.png" httpUri-22="https://zenodo.org/record/187312/files/figure.png" httpUri-23="https://zenodo.org/record/187313/files/figure.png" httpUri-24="https://zenodo.org/record/187314/files/figure.png" httpUri-25="https://zenodo.org/record/187315/files/figure.png" httpUri-26="https://zenodo.org/record/187316/files/figure.png" httpUri-27="https://zenodo.org/record/187317/files/figure.png" httpUri-28="https://zenodo.org/record/187318/files/figure.png" httpUri-29="https://zenodo.org/record/187319/files/figure.png" httpUri-3="https://zenodo.org/record/187293/files/figure.png" httpUri-30="https://zenodo.org/record/187320/files/figure.png" httpUri-4="https://zenodo.org/record/187294/files/figure.png" httpUri-5="https://zenodo.org/record/187295/files/figure.png" httpUri-6="https://zenodo.org/record/187296/files/figure.png" httpUri-7="https://zenodo.org/record/187297/files/figure.png" httpUri-8="https://zenodo.org/record/187298/files/figure.png" httpUri-9="https://zenodo.org/record/187299/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figs 
<number box="[758,822,1586,1612]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="16.5" valueMax="32.0" valueMin="1.0">1–32</number>
</figureCitation>
), housed in the Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard University, comprising: both mandibular rami with fragments of teeth 
<emphasis box="[1082,1154,1625,1650]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">in situ</emphasis>
; six cervical, 
<number box="[1320,1349,1625,1651]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="15.0">15</number>
dorsal, three sacral, and 
<number box="[351,380,1664,1690]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="34.0">34</number>
caudal vertebrae; rib fragments; distal left scapula; ilia, ischia, and pubes; femora, tibiae, and fibulae; several unidentified fragments. A cast (MN 
<number box="[825,887,1702,1728]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="6104.0">6104</number>
-V) is housed at the Museu Nacional/ 
<collectionCode box="[1330,1400,1702,1728]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">UFRJ</collectionCode>
, in Rio de Janeiro, 
<collectingCountry box="[335,410,1741,1767]" name="Brazil" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Brazil</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,1437,1586,2038]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,369,1779,1805]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<typeStatus box="[197,259,1779,1805]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Type</typeStatus>
locality.
</emphasis>
An outcrop of the Alemoa Member, Santa Maria Formation (Carnian), locality Sanga Grande, city of Santa Maria, Rio Grande do Sul, 
<collectingCountry box="[725,800,1818,1844]" name="Brazil" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Brazil</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[151,1437,1586,2038]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,425,1856,1882]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Revised diagnosis.</emphasis>
Saurischian dinosaur distinguished by the following autapomorphies: 
<number box="[1251,1264,1857,1883]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="1.0">1</number>
) craniomedial region of the distal pubis is distinctly beveled (Novas 
<number box="[831,896,1896,1922]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="1993.0">1993</number>
; Figs 
<number box="[972,1055,1896,1922]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="22.5" valueMax="23.0" valueMin="22.0">22–23</number>
); 
<number box="[1077,1093,1896,1922]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="2.0">2</number>
) femoral cranial trochanter reduced in size (
<figureCitation box="[344,433,1934,1960]" captionStart="FIGURE 27" captionStartId="36.[151,255,1379,1403]" captionTargetBox="[264,1312,194,1355]" captionTargetId="figure@36.[264,1323,194,1355]" captionTargetPageId="36" captionText="FIGURE 27. Photographs and drawings of the right (a – b) and left (c – d) proximal femora in cranial view. Abbreviations: artef, artefactual shelf; fclc (fgt), femoral craniolateral crest, part of the “ greater ” trochanter; fcmc, femoral craniomedial crest. Scale bars = 2 cm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/187315/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Fig. 
<number box="[400,433,1934,1960]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="27.0">27</number>
</figureCitation>
); 
<number box="[455,470,1934,1960]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="3.0">3</number>
) distal end of tibia is subcircular in distal view (modified from 
<bibRefCitation author="Rauhut" box="[1222,1377,1934,1960]" pageId="2" pageNumber="54" refString="Rauhut, O. (2003) The interrelationships and evolution of basal theropod dinosaurs. Special Papers in Palaeontology, 69, 1 - 213." type="journal article" year="2003">
Rauhut 
<number box="[1315,1377,1934,1960]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="2003.0">2003</number>
</bibRefCitation>
; 
<figureCitation captionStart="FIGURE 28" captionStartId="37.[151,256,1731,1755]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,194,1706]" captionTargetId="figure@37.[151,1436,194,1708]" captionTargetPageId="37" captionText="FIGURE 28. Photographs of the right tibia in medial (a), cranial (b), caudal (c) and lateral (d) views; the left tibia in medial view (e), and the right tibia in proximal (f) and distal (g) views. Abbreviations: af, articular facet for the ascending process of the astragalus; cls, craniolateral sulcus; cms, craniomedial sulcus; cn, cnemial crest; crcs, craniocaudal dorsal sulcus; fck, fibular condyle keel; mls, mediolateral sulcus; ppv, caudoventral process; tfc, tibial condyle for fibula; tic, tibial inner condyle. Scale bar for (a – e) = 7 cm; (f – g) = 1 cm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/187316/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Fig. 
<quantity box="[151,184,1973,1999]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="kg" metricValue="2.8" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" unit="g" value="28.0">28</quantity>
</figureCitation>
g); 
<number box="[223,239,1973,1999]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="4.0">4</number>
) dorsoventrally oriented sulcus present on the medial surface of the proximal third of fibula (
<figureCitation captionStart="FIGURE 30" captionStartId="39.[151,256,1305,1329]" captionTargetBox="[264,1296,383,1280]" captionTargetId="figure@39.[264,1323,383,1280]" captionTargetPageId="39" captionText="FIGURE 30. Photographs and drawings of the left fibula in lateral (a – b) and medial (c – d) views. Abbreviations: fms, fibular medial sulcus; ifi, insertion of the ilifibularis muscle; mis, scar for muscular insertion. Scale bar = 8 cm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/187318/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Fig. 
<number box="[151,182,2012,2038]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" value="30.0">30</number>
</figureCitation>
c–d).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1436,151,371]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,339,151,177]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Comments.</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Rauhut" box="[347,518,152,178]" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" refString="Rauhut, O. (2003) The interrelationships and evolution of basal theropod dinosaurs. Special Papers in Palaeontology, 69, 1 - 213." type="journal article" year="2003">
Rauhut (
<number box="[448,510,152,178]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2003.0">2003</number>
)
</bibRefCitation>
proposed two additional autapomorphies for 
<taxonomicName authority="Colbert, 1970" authorityName="Colbert" authorityYear="1970" box="[1056,1154,152,178]" class="Reptilia" family="Staurikosauridae" genus="Staurikosaurus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Saurischia" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="pricei">
<emphasis box="[1056,1071,152,177]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">S</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis box="[1086,1154,152,177]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">pricei</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
: postacetabular process of ilium abbreviated and caudally straight; pubic boot confluent with pubic shafts caudally. These proposed autapomorphies are problematic because the postacetabular iliac process is also short in several primitive dinosaurs, including 
<taxonomicName box="[403,644,268,294]" class="Reptilia" family="Herrerasauridae" genus="Herrerasaurus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Saurischia" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="ischigualastensis">
<emphasis box="[403,424,268,293]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">H</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis box="[440,644,268,293]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">ischigualastensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
; moreover, in 
<taxonomicName authority="Colbert, 1970" authorityName="Colbert" authorityYear="1970" box="[822,922,268,294]" class="Reptilia" family="Staurikosauridae" genus="Staurikosaurus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Saurischia" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="pricei">
<emphasis box="[822,837,268,293]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">S</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis box="[852,922,268,293]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">pricei</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
the process is rounded rather than straight caudally. The configuration of the pubic boot identified as autapomorphic by 
<bibRefCitation author="Rauhut" box="[1061,1231,306,332]" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" refString="Rauhut, O. (2003) The interrelationships and evolution of basal theropod dinosaurs. Special Papers in Palaeontology, 69, 1 - 213." type="journal article" year="2003">
Rauhut (
<number box="[1161,1223,306,332]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2003.0">2003</number>
)
</bibRefCitation>
is also present in 
<taxonomicName authority="Langer &amp; Benton 2006" authorityName="Langer &amp; Benton" authorityYear="2006" box="[151,688,345,371]" class="Reptilia" family="Herrerasauridae" genus="Herrerasaurus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Saurischia" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="ischigualastensis">
<emphasis box="[151,172,345,370]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">H</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis box="[187,387,345,370]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">ischigualastensis</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Langer" box="[402,680,345,371]" pageId="3" pageNumber="53" refString="Langer, M. C. &amp; Benton, M. J. (2006) Early dinosaurs: a phylogenetic study. Journal of Systematic Palaeontology, 4, 309 - 358." type="journal article" year="2006">
Langer &amp; Benton 
<number box="[616,680,345,371]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2006.0">2006</number>
</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>