<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.458.8531" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ad80fd70-e21f-4a5c-9c56-6d22762dd464" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152056730" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-458-1" ID-ZBK="D653F0941A114123815A1298D64457B8" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:00BD104B-26C2-488C-BF69-2F78C192B812" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-458-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 458" ModsDocTitle="Review of Gasteruption Latreille (Hymenoptera, Gasteruptiidae) from Iran and Turkey, with the description of 15 new species" checkinTime="1451245031406" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="van Achterberg, Cornelis &amp; Talebi, Ali Asghar" docDate="2014" docId="66379E950F4AE73D6FFECC92EBAA3289" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 458: 1-187" docOrigin="ZooKeys 458" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.458.8531" docTitle="Gasteruption nigrapiculatum van Achterberg, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="00BD104B-26C2-488C-BF69-2F78C192B812" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="95" lastPageNumber="96" masterDocId="FFC5BA67FFECFF9AFF97FFD2FFDCFF8B" masterDocTitle="Review of Gasteruption Latreille (Hymenoptera, Gasteruptiidae) from Iran and Turkey, with the description of 15 new species" masterLastPageNumber="187" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="93" pageNumber="94" updateTime="1643659176286" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of Gasteruption Latreille (Hymenoptera, Gasteruptiidae) from Iran and Turkey, with the description of 15 new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>van Achterberg, Cornelis</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Talebi, Ali Asghar</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>458</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>187</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.458.8531</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.458.8531</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-458-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">D653F0941A114123815A1298D64457B8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">D653F0941A114123815A1298D64457B8</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152056730" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:00BD104B-26C2-488C-BF69-2F78C192B812" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/66379E950F4AE73D6FFECC92EBAA3289" lastPageId="95" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="93" pageNumber="94">
<subSubSection pageId="93" pageNumber="94" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Gasteruptiidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="93" pageNumber="94" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/00BD104B-26C2-488C-BF69-2F78C192B812" authority="van Achterberg" authorityName="Latreille" authorityYear="1796" class="Insecta" family="Gasteruptiidae" genus="Gasteruption" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gasteruption nigrapiculatum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="93" pageNumber="94" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigrapiculatum">Gasteruption nigrapiculatum van Achterberg</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="93" pageNumber="94">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 331-345
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="93" pageNumber="94" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">
Holotype (RMNH), ♀, &quot;N. Iran: Qazvin, Zereshk Road, MT [= Malaise trap] 3, 7-22.vi.2011, A. Mohammadi, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="RMNH’12“">RMNH'12&quot;</normalizedToken>
. Paratypes (1 ♀ + 1 ♂): 1 ♂ (RMNH), &quot;N. Iran: Alborz, Shahrestanak, Chalous Road, MT 28, 15-22.vi.2010, S. Farahani, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="RMNH‘12“">RMNH'12&quot;</normalizedToken>
; 1 ♀ (BZL), &quot;Jordan NW, N of Janesh, 15.v.2010, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Snižek“">Snizek&quot;</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="93" pageNumber="94" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Head weakly convex dorsally, in front of occipital carina without medio-posterior depression; face moderately wide (Fig. 335); frons with satin sheen and densely finely punctulate; occipital carina narrowly lamelliform and dark brown; vertex rather shiny and transversely finely aciculate, anteriorly punctulate and without punctures; mandible yellowish brown basally, but somewhat darkened dorso-basally; propleuron 0.8 times as long as mesoscutum in front of tegulae; antesternal carina medium-sized lamelliform, directed posteriorly; middle lobe of mesoscutum shiny, densely transversely rugulose, without smooth interspaces, medio-posteriorly reticulate-rugose, lateral lobe shiny, densely obliquely rugulose and medially irregularly punctate (Fig. 333); scutellum shiny, partly smooth medially and with indistinct transverse rugulae and anteriorly punctate-rugulose; mesosoma laterally (except pronotal side ventrally) silvery pilose (Fig. 332); middle lobe rather protuberant (Fig. 333); hind basitarsus entirely dark brown, darker than yellowish brown hind tibial spurs (Fig. 334); hind tibia rather slender, outer side with punctures and short dark bristles and with large subbasal ivory patch (Fig. 334); ovipositor sheath 0.9 times as long as body, 1.3-1.4 times as long as metasoma, 2.5-2.7 times as long as hind tibia and tarsus combined and 4.1 times hind tibia; apex of ovipositor sheath dark brown or brown; length of body 9-11 mm; paramere ivory apically (Fig. 345).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="95" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="93" pageNumber="94" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Female, length of body 9.1 mm (of fore wing 4.4 mm).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="93" pageNumber="94">Head. Head weakly convex dorsally, posteriorly rather directly narrowed, without medio-posterior depression; face and anteriorly frons conspicuously silvery pilose; occipital carina narrowly lamelliform, dark brown (Figs 331, 337); third and fourth antennal segments 1.6 and 2.3 times as long as second segment, apical segment 1.5 times as long as penultimate segment; face moderately wide (Fig. 335); frons with satin sheen and densely finely punctulate; vertex rather shiny and transversely finely aciculate, anteriorly punctulate and without punctures; ventrally head not enlarged in anterior view, malar space 0.2 times length of pedicellus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="94" pageNumber="95">
<pageBreakToken pageId="94" pageNumber="95" start="start">Mesosoma</pageBreakToken>
. Length of mesosoma 1.9 times its height; propleuron 0.8 times as long as mesoscutum in front of tegulae, silvery pilose and moderately stout posteriorly; laterally pronotum largely smooth postero-ventrally and rugose antero-ventrally and shiny, ventrally without pilosity; side of pronotum with obsolescent tooth antero-ventrally; antesternal carina medium-sized lamelliform, directed posteriorly; middle lobe of mesoscutum shiny, densely transversely rugulose, without smooth interspaces, medio-posteriorly reticulate-rugose, lateral lobe shiny, densely obliquely rugulose and medially irregularly punctate (Fig. 333); notauli rather shallow; scutellum shiny, partly smooth medially and with indistinct transverse rugulae and anteriorly punctate-rugulose; mesopleuron and metapleuron silvery pilose (Fig. 333); eyes inconspicuously setose.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
<pageBreakToken pageId="95" pageNumber="96" start="start">Legs</pageBreakToken>
. Length of hind femur, tibia and basitarsus 5.1, 4.7 and 5.2 times their width, respectively; hind tibia rather slender (Fig. 334); fore coxa close to mesopleuron; hind coxa shiny and rugulose dorsally; hind basitarsus moderately slender, as long as remainder of tarsus and distinctly widened in dorsal view.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Metasoma. Ovipositor sheath 0.9 times as long as body, 1.4 times as long as metasoma, 2.7 times as long as hind tibia and tarsus combined and 4.1 times as long as hind tibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Colour. Black; metasoma dark brown, but second-sixth tergites yellowish brown apically and ventrally and sternites basally and apically brown, but apical half of hypopygium largely brown; mandible (but dorso-basally darkened) and tegulae yellowish brown; fore and middle femora apically and tibiae basally and basitarsi and hind tibia subbasally ivory; remainder of legs (except coxae) largely dark brown; palpi, pterostigma and hind basitarsus entirely dark brown; hind tibial spurs yellowish brown and paler than base of hind basitarsus; apex of ovipositor sheath dark brown; wing membrane subhyaline.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Male. Third antennal segment 1.2 times as long as second segment, fourth segment 2.3 times as long as third segment and 1.2 times as long as second and third segments combined, fifth segment as long as fourth segment (Fig. 342); mandible yellowish brown; scutellum partly smooth and shiny medially and mesoscutum irregularly rugose; antesternal carina medium-sized; hind tibia dark brown ventrally and with subbasal ivory band; hind tibial spurs paler than base of basitarsus; hind tarsus dark brown; hind coxa transversely rugulose dorsally; apex of paramere ivory (Fig. 345).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Variation. Length of body of ♀ 9.1-11.4 mm (of ♂ 9.5 mm); mesoscutum in paratype somewhat coarser sculptured than in holotype; apical half of hypopygium dark brown or largely yellowish brown; ovipositor sheath 0.9 times as long as body, 1.3-1.4 times as long as metasoma, 2.5-2.7 times as long as hind tibia and tarsus combined and 4.1 times hind tibia.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="95" pageNumber="96" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Iran, Jordan.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="95" pageNumber="96" type="biology">
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Unknown. Collected in May-June.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="95" pageNumber="96" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
Derived from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“nigra”">&quot;nigra&quot;</normalizedToken>
, (Latin for 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“black”">&quot;black&quot;</normalizedToken>
) and 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“apiculus”">&quot;apiculus&quot;</normalizedToken>
, (Latin for &quot;small top&quot;), because of the blackish apex of the ovipositor sheath.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
Figures 331-339. 
<taxonomicName authority="Latreille, 1796" authorityName="Latreille" authorityYear="1796" class="Insecta" family="Gasteruptiidae" genus="Gasteruption" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gasteruption nigrapiculatum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="95" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigrapiculatum">Gasteruption nigrapiculatum</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female, holotype. 331 head lateral 332 mesosoma lateral 333 mesonotum dorsal 334 hind leg 335 head anterior 336 head dorsal 337 fore wing 338 hypopygium ventral 339 apex of ovipositor sheath.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
<paragraph pageId="95" pageNumber="96">
Figures 340-345. 
<taxonomicName authority="Latreille, 1796" authorityName="Latreille" authorityYear="1796" class="Insecta" family="Gasteruptiidae" genus="Gasteruption" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gasteruption nigrapiculatum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="95" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigrapiculatum">Gasteruption nigrapiculatum</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male, paratype. 340 head lateral 341 mesonotum dorsal 342 basal antennal segments 343 head dorsal 344 hind leg 345 genitalia lateral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>