<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ca884005-01b3-4e3d-818b-3e74c244eaaf" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152052589" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-402-67" ID-ZBK="B0ED94FB951A4063BEED7BF5F4E85C39" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-402-67" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 402" ModsDocTitle="A taxonomic review of the Neoserica (sensu lato) septemlamellata group (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Sericini)" checkinTime="1451245971557" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Ahrens, Dirk, Liu, Wan-Gang, Fabrizi, Silvia, Bai, Ming &amp; Yang, Xing-Ke" docDate="2014" docId="5908ABF18EEF3B1761EF2959B5CC73B7" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 402: 67-102" docOrigin="ZooKeys 402" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360" docTitle="Neoserica septemfoliata Moser 1915" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="84" masterDocId="FFA3FFF0EF455B38FF99D505E866FFC3" masterDocTitle="A taxonomic review of the Neoserica (sensu lato) septemlamellata group (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Sericini)" masterLastPageNumber="102" masterPageNumber="67" pageId="15" pageNumber="82" updateTime="1643527573623" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A taxonomic review of the Neoserica (sensu lato) septemlamellata group (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Sericini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ahrens, Dirk</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liu, Wan-Gang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fabrizi, Silvia</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bai, Ming</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Yang, Xing-Ke</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>402</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>67</mods:start>
<mods:end>102</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.402.7360</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-402-67</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">B0ED94FB951A4063BEED7BF5F4E85C39</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B0ED94FB951A4063BEED7BF5F4E85C39</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152052589" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:5908ABF18EEF3B1761EF2959B5CC73B7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5908ABF18EEF3B1761EF2959B5CC73B7" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="15" pageNumber="82">
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="82" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Neoserica_septemfoliata" authority="Moser, 1915" authorityName="Moser" authorityYear="1915" class="Insecta" family="Melolonthidae" genus="Neoserica" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neoserica septemfoliata" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="septemfoliata">Neoserica (s.l.) septemfoliata Moser, 1915</taxonomicName>
Figs 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–H">E-H</normalizedToken>
, 7
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="82" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Melolonthidae" genus="Neoserica" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neoserica septemfoliata" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="septemfoliata">Neoserica septemfoliata</taxonomicName>
Moser, 1915b: 381.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="82" type="type material examined">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">Lectotype (here designated): ♂ &quot;Yunnan/ Neoserica septemfoliata Mos. Type Mos.&quot; (ZMHB).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="82" type="additional material examined">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">1 ♂ &quot;Coll. R.I.Sc.N.B. Chine/ Sud Yunnan Tche-Ping-Tcheou/ Coll. P. Guerry Le Moult vendit&quot; (ISNB).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="15" pageNumber="82" type="redescription">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">Redescription.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="82">Length: 8.4 mm, length of elytra: 6.6 mm, width: 5.2 mm. Body oblong, black, antennal club yellowish brown, dorsal surface shiny, nearly glabrous except a few long setae on head.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="83">
<pageBreakToken pageId="16" pageNumber="83" start="start">Labroclypeus</pageBreakToken>
trapezoidal, distinctly wider than long, widest at base, lateral margins weakly convex and convergent anteriorly, anterior angles moderately rounded, anteriorly weakly sinuate medially, margins moderately reflexed; surface slightly convex and shiny, basis without dull tomentum, punctation dense, small punctures mixed with coarse ones each bearing a long erect seta; frontoclypeal suture indistinctly incised, not elevated and distinctly angled medially; smooth area anterior to eye approximately 2.5 times as wide as long; ocular canthus moderately long (length = 1/3 of ocular diameter) and wide, with a few minute punctures and a few long setae. Frons shiny, with coarse and fine, dense punctures, densely covered with long erect setae. Eyes moderately large, ratio diameter/interocular width: 0.64. Antenna with ten antennomeres, club with seven antennomeres, moderately reflexed, 2.5 times as long as remaining antennomeres combined; antennomere 4 subequal to two thirds of length of club, antennomere 3 half as long as pedicellus. Mentum elevated and slightly flattened anteriorly.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="83">Pronotum subrectangular, widest shortly before base, lateral margins evenly convex and moderately convergent anteriorly, slightly narrowed basally, anterior angles sharp and distinctly produced, posterior angles blunt, slightly rounded at tip; anterior margin convexly produced medially, marginal line incomplete medially; surface densely and coarsely punctate, only with minute setae; setae of anterior and lateral border fine and sparse; hypomeron distinctly carinate basally, carina not produced. Scutellum narrow and long, dull, with coarse, dense punctures and minute setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="83">
Elytra oblong, widest in posterior third, striae weakly impressed, finely and densely punctate, intervals weakly convex, finely and densely punctate, punctures concentrated along striae, with only very minute setae, otherwise glabrous; epipleural edge wide, ending at widely rounded apical angle of elytra, epipleura densely setose, apical border narrowly membranous, with a fine fringe of microtrichomes (visible at 100
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="83">Ventral surface dull, coarsely and densely punctate, metasternum moderately setose; metacoxa glabrous, with a few long setae laterally, posterior margin straight; abdominal sternites finely and densely punctuate, minutely setose, with a transverse row of coarse punctures each bearing a robust, long seta. Mesosternum between mesocoxae half as wide as mesofemur. Ratio of length of metepisternum/metacoxa: 1/1.49. Pygidium moderately convex and shiny, coarsely and densely punctate, with a narrow smooth midline, with a few long erect setae along apical margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="16" pageNumber="83">
Legs moderately slender and not very long; femora with two longitudinal rows of setae, finely and sparsely punctate, nearly glabrous; metafemur dull, anterior margin acute, immediately behind anterior edge with a continuously serrated line, punctures and setae of anterior longitudinal row complete, posterior margin in apical half ventrally smooth and not widened, posterior margin smooth dorsally, not serrated, with dense, short setae. Metatibia moderately slender and long, widest at apex, ratio of width/length: 1/3.2; dorsal margin sharply carinate, with three groups of spines, basal group shortly before middle, median one shortly behind middle, and apical group at 4/5 of metatibial length, basally with a few robust but single setae; beside dorsal margin with a continuously serrated line being subparallel with dorsal margin 4/5 of metatibial length; lateral face longitudinally convex, finely and sparsely punctate, with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="17" pageNumber="84" start="start">out</pageBreakToken>
convex subdorsal longitudinal carina on lateral face; ventral margin finely serrated, with four robust equidistant setae; medial face smooth, apex indistinctly sinuate interiorly near tarsal articulation. Tarsomeres with dense, short setae ventrally, not carinate laterally, smooth dorsally; metatarsomeres with a strongly serrated ventral ridge and a sharp subventral carina immediately beside it, first metatarsomere distinctly shorter than following two tarsomeres combined and slightly longer than dorsal tibial spur. Protibia short, tridentate, basal tooth blunt; anterior claws symmetrical, basal tooth of inner claw sharply truncate at apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="84">
Aedeagus: Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–G">E-G</normalizedToken>
. Female unknown.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="17" pageNumber="84" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="84">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="84">We designate here the lectotype for the species, since in the original description it is not mentioned on how many specimens it was based.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>