<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.150.1881" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d2c4ccdd-3645-48ce-8e4c-1db50a5208d6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152032364" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-150-231" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CD50600C-901E-46CA-840F-D4FEA863AF0E" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-150-231" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 150" ModsDocTitle="Bush Blitz aids description of three new species and a new genus of Australian beeflies (Diptera, Bombyliidae, Exoprosopini)" checkinTime="1451249547159" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lambkin, Christine L. &amp; Bartlett, Justin S." docDate="2011" docId="AD27D30F13337A7D27EAD3F420167DFF" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 150: 231-280" docOrigin="ZooKeys 150" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.150.1881" docTitle="Palirika mackenziei Lambkin, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="CD50600C-901E-46CA-840F-D4FEA863AF0E" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="241" masterDocId="FFA1F460FFC6FF902646A767FFD5FFBB" masterDocTitle="Bush Blitz aids description of three new species and a new genus of Australian beeflies (Diptera, Bombyliidae, Exoprosopini)" masterLastPageNumber="280" masterPageNumber="231" pageId="7" pageNumber="238" updateTime="1643715017211" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bush Blitz aids description of three new species and a new genus of Australian beeflies (Diptera, Bombyliidae, Exoprosopini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lambkin, Christine L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bartlett, Justin S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>150</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>231</mods:start>
<mods:end>280</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.150.1881</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.150.1881</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-150-231</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">90084A21-1988-455F-AB04-D6BFE3E38D5C</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152032364" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CD50600C-901E-46CA-840F-D4FEA863AF0E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AD27D30F13337A7D27EAD3F420167DFF" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="241" pageId="7" pageNumber="238">
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="238" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="238">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CD50600C-901E-46CA-840F-D4FEA863AF0E" authority="Lambkin" class="Insecta" family="Bombyliidae" genus="Palirika" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Palirika mackenziei" order="Diptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="238" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mackenziei">Palirika mackenziei Lambkin</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="7" pageNumber="238">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
23611
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="238" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="238">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="238">
Holotype.Queensland: ♀, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="92" value="-26.728333">26°43.7'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="92" value="142.65167">142°39.1'E</geoCoordinate>
, Plevna Downs, Tompilly Hill summit, 13 Dec 2007, C. Lambkin, N. Starick &amp; R. Mackenzie, 15454, sweep net, hilltopping, 220m, [dissected], PS1893, A007533, T152481 (QM). Condition: Good.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="240" pageId="8" pageNumber="239" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="239">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="239" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="239">Wing length 9.0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="240" pageId="8" pageNumber="239">
Small dark flies with heavily infuscated wings, hyaline only apically and medial spot. Face orange with shiny reddish-brown scales, frons black with shiny black scales. Collar yellow. Narrow laterothoracic stripe of whitish scales. Scutum black with dull lime-green metallic scales except pinkish metallic scales anterolaterally and posteromedially. Scutellum dark brown, darker basally with royal-blue metallic scales, purple metallic scales laterally and posteriorly. Widened base of costa with shiny reddish-brown scales, no paler scales posteriorly. Wing pattern broadly dimidiate (Fig. 6A); black with hyaline areas, apically and medially. Apical hyaline area covering extreme apex of r1, apex of first r2+3, apical half of second r2+3, all r4, and extreme apex r5. Medial hyaline area covering middle of dc extending from M1 across m-cu and into m2. Paler prediscoidal opaque area distinct. Alula and squama edged with long broad grey scales. T1 with white Ma; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="240" start="start">long</pageBreakToken>
white flattened scales posterolaterally. Tergites black with royal-blue metallic scales that reflect purple (Fig. 6D). Female T8 A short, plate-like support distinct.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="240" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="240">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="240">
Female. Head.(Figs 6
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–E">B-E</normalizedToken>
). Face orange with shiny reddish-brown scales, frons black with shiny black scales; setae black, longest below distinct frontal depression. Antennal scape red, 3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of pedicel, with long black setae dense laterally and ventrally; pedicel red with black setae shorter and sparser dorsally; PP conical, 5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of pedicel, black with silvery pruinescence, distinct apical joint; BSM rod-like, expanded apically, reddish-brown, 2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of pedicel; ASM reddish, conical, length less than width of BSM (Fig. 6E). Occiput with shiny black scales broadly filling indentation.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="240">
Thorax. (Figs 6
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
). Collar yellow. Narrow laterothoracic stripe of whitish scales. Long white flattened scales posteromedially. Scutum black with dull lime-green metallic scales except pinkish metallic scales anterolaterally and posteromedially; black setae. AN with black Ma, long yellow setae anteriorly; long, lightly iridescent scales at base of wing black. Prealar bristles strong, black and long. Postalar bristles strong, black and reaching almost apex of scutellum. Pleural hairs black with reddish iridescence. Ma of LT black, reddish-brown dorsally. Tympanal ridge and PL with yellowish flattened scales. Scutellum dark brown, darker basally with royal-blue metallic scales, purple metallic scales laterally and posteriorly; strong, black apical bristles. Legs. Reddish-brown, tarsi darker; scales and setae black. Pulvilli sharp, curved, half length of mid- and hind-tarsal claws. Halter knob dark reddish-brown, posteromedial edge broadly yellow. Wing (Fig. 6A), cup open. Widened base of costa with shiny reddish-brown scales, no paler scales posteriorly. Wing pattern broadly dimidiate; black with hyaline areas, apically and medially. Apical hyaline area covering extreme apex of r1, apex of first r2+3, apical half of second r2+3, all r4, and extreme apex r5. Medial hyaline area covering middle of dc extending from M1 across m-cu and into m2. Paler prediscoidal opaque area distinct. Anal edged with long black scales basally. Alula edged with long broad grey scales. Squama edged with dense overlapping long grey scales.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="240">
Abdomen. (Figs 6
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–D">C-D</normalizedToken>
). T1 with white Ma; long white flattened scales posterolaterally. Tergites black with royal-blue metallic scales that reflect purple when not viewed dorsally, pleura with lateral tufts of long black setae on T2-7. Sternites black, with black scales and setae. Genitalia (Fig. 6
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
). Dorsal T8 A short, plate-like support distinct; T10 with 4 pairs of stout AC spines. Furca with 2 long broad posteriorly directed arms with small recurved hook-like dorsal extensions apically.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="240">Male. Unknown.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="240">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="240">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Bombyliidae" genus="Palirika" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Palirika mackenziei" order="Diptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="240" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mackenziei">Palirika mackenziei</taxonomicName>
sp. n., Female holotype. A Wing B Head lateral C Adult, lateral D Adult, dorsal; Male genitalia: E Antennae lateral; Genitalia: F Dorsal G Lateral H Dorsal, furca.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="241" pageId="9" pageNumber="240" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="240">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="241" pageId="9" pageNumber="240">
This species is named mackenziei to acknowledge the enthusiasm and interest in all kinds of natural history by the Mackenzie family of Plevna Downs Station where the type, and only, specimen was collected. Since 2007, following the discovery of dinosaurs on their property, together with a large undescribed spider, CLL and Noel Starick have been welcomed by the Mackenzie family. Robyn Mackenzie was thrilled to be helping catch hill-topping beeflies on the summit of Tompilly Hill when the only female specimen of this unusual 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Bombyliidae" genus="Palirika" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Palirika" order="Diptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="240" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Palirika</taxonomicName>
was captured (Fig. 1A). We have happily instructed the family, the local Natural History Society, students, teachers, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="241" start="start">regional</pageBreakToken>
property owners and community members on the ins and outs of biodiversity of arid areas, especially the insects.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="241" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="241">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="241">(Fig. 11). This species has only been collected from the type locality in remote far south-western Queensland.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>