<document ID-DOI="10.1206/0003-0090(2002)271&lt;0001:AROTAG&gt;2.0.CO;2" ID-ISSN="0003-0090" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5396112" approvalRequired="590" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="16" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="543" approvalRequired_for_treatments="31" checkinTime="1630325540508" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="PLATNICK, NORMAN I." docDate="2002" docId="03EAE52AFF66A69B80C92450DA5048C9" docLanguage="en" docName="B271.pdf" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 2002 (271)" docSource="http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/0003-0090%282002%29271%3C0001%3AAROTAG%3E2.0.CO%3B2" docStyle="DocumentStyle:A43B19FFA58259A0316161A0DF14F014.1:BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type2" docStyleId="A43B19FFA58259A0316161A0DF14F014" docStyleName="BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type2" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Boolathana PLATNICK 2002, new genus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="195" masterDocId="FFD39D52FFA6A65883742265DB214D2A" masterDocTitle="A Revision Of The Australasian Ground Spiders Of The Families Ammoxenidae, Cithaeronidae, Gallieniellidae, And Trochanteriidae (Araneae: Gnaphosoidea)" masterLastPageNumber="1" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="192" pageNumber="1" updateTime="1630618863538" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A Revision Of The Australasian Ground Spiders Of The Families Ammoxenidae, Cithaeronidae, Gallieniellidae, And Trochanteriidae (Araneae: Gnaphosoidea)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>PLATNICK, NORMAN I.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2002</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2002-09-19</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2002</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>271</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/0003-0090%282002%29271%3C0001%3AAROTAG%3E2.0.CO%3B2</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.1206/0003-0090(2002)271&lt;0001:AROTAG&gt;2.0.CO;2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0003-0090</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5396112</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EAE52AFF66A69B80C92450DA5048C9" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03EAE52AFF66A69B80C92450DA5048C9" lastPageId="195" pageId="192">
<subSubSection box="[957,1241,1589,1613]" pageId="192" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="192.[957,1241,1589,1613]" box="[957,1241,1589,1613]" pageId="192">
<heading box="[957,1241,1589,1613]" centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="192" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[957,1104,1589,1613]" pageId="192">
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2002" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" box="[957,1098,1589,1613]" class="Arachnida" family="Trochanteriidae" genus="Boolathana" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="192" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus" status="new genus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[957,1098,1589,1613]" italics="true" pageId="192">Boolathana</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1114,1241,1590,1613]" pageId="192" rank="genus">new genus</taxonomicNameLabel>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="192" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="192.[835,1363,1638,1837]" pageId="192">
<typeStatus box="[864,921,1638,1661]" pageId="192">TYPE</typeStatus>
SPECIES: 
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2002" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" box="[1051,1291,1639,1662]" class="Arachnida" family="Trochanteriidae" genus="Boolathana" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="192" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spiralis" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[1051,1291,1639,1662]" italics="true" pageId="192">Boolathana spiralis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="192" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="192" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="192.[835,1363,1638,1837]" pageId="192">ETYMOLOGY: The generic name is taken from a locality at which the genus occurs, and is considered feminine in gender.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="193" pageId="192" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="192.[835,1363,1638,1837]" pageId="192">DIAGNOSIS: Males are easily recognized by the complete coil formed by the tip of the</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5396565" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5396565" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5396565/files/figure.png" pageId="193" startId="193.[245,293,1013,1034]" targetBox="[217,1327,284,992]" targetPageId="193">
<paragraph blockId="193.[219,1323,1013,1061]" pageId="193">
Figs. 525–528. 
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2002" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" box="[433,637,1014,1035]" class="Arachnida" family="Trochanteriidae" genus="Fissarena" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="193" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="arcoona" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[433,637,1014,1035]" italics="true" pageId="193">Fissarena arcoona</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[655,790,1013,1034]" pageId="193" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[806,852,1013,1034]" pageId="193">525.</emphasis>
Left male palp, ventral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1200,1246,1013,1034]" pageId="193">526.</emphasis>
Same, retrolateral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[408,454,1040,1061]" pageId="193">527.</emphasis>
Epigynum, ventral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[734,780,1040,1061]" pageId="193">528.</emphasis>
Same, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="193.[219,748,1110,1837]" pageId="193">median apophysis (figs. 533, 534), and females by the similarly coiled epigynal ducts (figs. 535, 536). The enlarged anterior lateral eyes, situated on distinct mounds, are also diagnostic.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="195" pageId="193" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="193.[219,748,1110,1837]" lastBlockId="194.[259,788,1140,1837]" lastPageId="194" pageId="193">DESCRIPTION: Large spiders, total length of males 13–14, of females 10–14. Carapace flattened, without tubercles, with rebordered lateral and posterior margins, evenly coated with scattered, dark, stiff, erect setae interspersed among white, recumbent setae; longer, erect, dark setae present only in ocular area and on clypeus; thoracic groove long, Y­shaped, wider anteriorly than posteriorly; cephalic groove pronounced, additional intercoxal grooves almost obsolete. Eight eyes in two rows, anterior laterals much larger than other eyes, on distinct mounds, posterior medians smallest; anterior medians circular, light, posterior medians circular, lenses slightly flattened, canoe­shaped tapetum apparently lost, laterals oval; from above and from front, both eye rows slightly recurved; anterior medians separated by more than their diameter, about as far from anterior lat­ erals; posterior medians separated by about seven times their diameter, slightly closer to posterior laterals; anterior and posterior laterals separated by more than their diameters; median ocular quadrangle much wider in back than in front or than long. Chelicerae porrect, divergent, with distinct oblique groove just below clypeus; anterior surface coated with stiff setae; chilum very wide, triangular, unipartite but with small area of unsclerotized cuticle along ventral one­third of midline area, accompanied by second, elongated, posterior chilum (narrow, I­shaped sclerite separating bases of chelicerae posteriorly); chelicerae with distinct lateral boss, promargin with series of long setae originating in line along base of fang, those nearest base of fang bent; promargin with three teeth, proximal tooth smaller than others, distalmost tooth separated from other two, retromargin with two widely separated teeth; presumptive cheliceral gland openings near base of proximal tooth. Labium rectangular, flat, posterior one­quarter narrowed, anterior margin truncate. Endites long, divergent, with oblique depression restricted to their median edge; serrula absent, long, oval, sieve plate conspicuous under light microscopy; anteromedian edges and apex bearing wide patch of long, stiff, dark setae. Sternum flat, with rebordered, slightly depressed lateral margins, not expanded anteriorly, with slight extensions to coxae, extensions between coxae represented by four pairs of small triangular sclerites separated from sternal margin by unsclerotized cuticle; surface smooth, with few long setae, posterior margin not rebordered, separating coxae IV. One weakly sclerotized epimeric sclerite on each side, not extending between coxae, not fused to carapace. Pedicel composed of two dorsal sclerites (anterior sclerite without deep posterior invagination, posterior sclerite without beakshaped anterior extension) and weak, invert­ ed v­shaped ventral sclerite with anteriorly unexpanded head not reaching posterior tip of sternum.</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5396567" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5396567" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5396567/files/figure.png" pageId="194" startId="194.[285,333,1019,1040]" targetBox="[266,1356,283,998]" targetPageId="194">
<paragraph blockId="194.[259,1363,1018,1093]" pageId="194">
Figs. 529–532. 529, 530. 
<taxonomicName authority="(Hogg)" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" baseAuthorityName="PLATNICK" baseAuthorityYear="1896" box="[582,872,1019,1040]" class="Arachnida" family="Trochanteriidae" genus="Fissarena" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longipes">
<emphasis box="[582,785,1019,1040]" italics="true" pageId="194">Fissarena longipes</emphasis>
(Hogg)
</taxonomicName>
. 531, 532. 
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2002" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" box="[995,1104,1019,1040]" class="Arachnida" family="Trochanteriidae" genus="Fissarena" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="barrow" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[995,1104,1019,1040]" italics="true" pageId="194">F. barrow</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1120,1252,1019,1040]" pageId="194" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1264,1310,1018,1039]" pageId="194">529.</emphasis>
Left male palp, ventral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[526,572,1045,1066]" pageId="194">530.</emphasis>
Same, retrolateral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[844,890,1045,1066]" pageId="194">531.</emphasis>
Epigynum, ventral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1171,1217,1045,1066]" pageId="194">532.</emphasis>
Same, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="194.[259,788,1140,1837]" lastBlockId="194.[835,1364,1140,1837]" pageId="194">Abdomen without dorsal or anterior scutum; cuticle with weak, recumbent setae; epi­ gastric scutum weakly sclerotized, with wellmarked booklung openings at sides but without postepigastric sclerites, booklung covers gently ridged; colulus represented only by scattered setae situated near narrow posterior spiracle; males apparently with scattered short epiandrous spigots. Anterior lateral spinnerets short, conical, separated by about their diameter at base, with two articles, distal article with two major ampullate gland spigots and several small, unmodified piriform gland spigots; posterior median spinnerets with several aciniform gland spigots and apparently only one larger minor ampullate gland spigot, those of males triangular, those of females bipartite, enlarged posterior portion with two parallel rows, each row with about five large cylindrical gland spigots; posterior lateral spinnerets with two articles, apparently without minor ampullate gland spigots, those of males seemingly with aciniform gland spigots only, those of females with two large cylindrical gland spigots in addition.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="195.[219,748,289,1507]" pageId="195">Legs laterigrade, subequal in length, most surfaces with long setae; coxae and trochanters without dorsal tubercles, fourth trochanters slightly elongated; anterior coxae without protuberant posterolateral corners; trochanters very slightly notched, producing sharp point at ventralmost edge; anterior metatarsi and tarsi with undivided scopula composed of short, straight setae; posterior metatarsi without distal preening brushes; tarsi with two long, smooth claws bearing no ventral teeth, strong claw tufts composed of two large pads of narrow setae; tarsi without cuticular cracks, relatively short; morphologically dorsal surface with modified proximal margin consisting of patch of unsclerotized cuticle followed by strong cuticular ridge, that ridge opposing distinct distal extensions situated at distal edge of metatarsi; trichobothria present, in three rows on tarsi, two on metatarsi and tibiae. Female palpal femur with strong dorsal spines, distal segments with weaker but longer spines; female palpal tarsus with long claw bearing several tiny ventral teeth, without ventral scopula. Typical leg spination pattern (counts refer to morphological surfaces, only surfaces bearing spines listed): femora: I–III d1­1­0, p1­1­0, r0­1­1; IV d1­1­0, p1­0­0, r0­0­1; tibiae: I– III v2­2­2; IV v2­2­2, r1­1­1; metatarsi: I, II v2­0­0; III v2­0­2; IV v2­2­2, r1­1­0.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="195.[219,748,289,1507]" pageId="195">Male palpal tibia with basal apophysis represented by tiny ledge at posterior edge of segment, situated just proximal of deeply excavated, lightly sclerotized area, distal apophysis bipartite, with rounded ventral and pointed dorsal lobes; cymbium with thick distal scopula; cymbial surface invaginated at base; ventral portion of median apophysis with distinctive distal coil. Epigynum with coiled ducts.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>