<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5469335" ID-ISSN="0003-0090" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5469335" approvalRequired="590" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="16" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="543" approvalRequired_for_treatments="31" checkinTime="1630325540508" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="PLATNICK, NORMAN I." docDate="2002" docId="03EAE52AFF91A660820E27E6D9F44B69" docLanguage="en" docName="B271.pdf" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 2002 (271)" docSource="http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/0003-0090%282002%29271%3C0001%3AAROTAG%3E2.0.CO%3B2" docStyle="DocumentStyle:A43B19FFA58259A0316161A0DF14F014.1:BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type2" docStyleId="A43B19FFA58259A0316161A0DF14F014" docStyleName="BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type2" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Peeto PLATNICK 2002, new genus" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="56" masterDocId="FFD39D52FFA6A65883742265DB214D2A" masterDocTitle="A Revision Of The Australasian Ground Spiders Of The Families Ammoxenidae, Cithaeronidae, Gallieniellidae, And Trochanteriidae (Araneae: Gnaphosoidea)" masterLastPageNumber="1" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="55" pageNumber="1" updateTime="1630932429997" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A Revision Of The Australasian Ground Spiders Of The Families Ammoxenidae, Cithaeronidae, Gallieniellidae, And Trochanteriidae (Araneae: Gnaphosoidea)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>PLATNICK, NORMAN I.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2002</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2002-09-19</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2002</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>271</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/0003-0090%282002%29271%3C0001%3AAROTAG%3E2.0.CO%3B2</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.1206/0003-0090(2002)271&lt;0001:AROTAG&gt;2.0.CO;2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0003-0090</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5396112</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5469335" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5469335" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EAE52AFF91A660820E27E6D9F44B69" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03EAE52AFF91A660820E27E6D9F44B69" lastPageId="56" pageId="55">
<subSubSection box="[378,587,1411,1435]" pageId="55" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="55.[378,587,1411,1435]" box="[378,587,1411,1435]" pageId="55">
<heading box="[378,587,1411,1435]" centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="55" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[378,451,1411,1435]" pageId="55">
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2002" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" box="[378,444,1411,1435]" class="Arachnida" family="Gallieniellidae" genus="Peeto" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus" status="new genus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[378,444,1411,1435]" italics="true" pageId="55">Peeto</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[461,587,1411,1434]" pageId="55" rank="genus">new genus</taxonomicNameLabel>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[248,748,1462,1486]" pageId="55" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="55.[219,748,1462,1837]" box="[248,748,1462,1486]" pageId="55">
<typeStatus box="[248,305,1462,1485]" pageId="55">TYPE</typeStatus>
SPECIES: 
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2002" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" box="[415,586,1463,1486]" class="Arachnida" family="Gallieniellidae" genus="Peeto" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rodmani" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[415,586,1463,1486]" italics="true" pageId="55">Peeto rodmani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[601,744,1462,1485]" pageId="55" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="55" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="55.[219,748,1462,1837]" pageId="55">ETYMOLOGY: The generic name refers to the National Science Foundation’s PEET (Partnerships for Enhancing Expertise in Taxonomy) program, which has supported this work, and is considered masculine in gender.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="55" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="55.[219,748,1462,1837]" pageId="55">
DIAGNOSIS: Members of this genus resemble those of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2002" box="[395,477,1697,1720]" class="Arachnida" family="Gallieniellidae" genus="Questo" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[395,477,1697,1720]" italics="true" pageId="55">Questo</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
in having cheliceral teeth, but can be distinguished by the complex retrolateral tibial apophysis of males (fig. 142) and the large, u­shaped epigynal septum of females (fig. 143).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="56" pageId="55" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="55.[795,1324,289,1837]" pageId="55">DESCRIPTION: Small spiders, total length of males and females 2.8–4.3. Carapace glabrous, without tubercles, with sparsely scattered, short, erect, dark setae and longer, erect setae on clypeus; thoracic groove long, longitudinal, not expanded anteriorly. Eight eyes in two rows, anterior medians smallest, circular, dark, posterior medians irregularly rectangular, flattened, laterals subequal in size, oval; from above, both eye rows slightly recurved, from front, both rows procurved; anterior medians separated by about their radius, about as far from anterior laterals; posterior medians separated by more than their diameter, separated by more than their diameter from posterior laterals; anterior and posterior laterals separated by less than their diameter; median ocular quadrangle wider in back than in front and than long. Chelicerae porrect, anterior surface with few scattered, strong setae; chilum unipartite, triangular, fused to clypeus, accompanied by second, elongated, posterior chilum (extremely narrow, I­shaped sclerite separating bases of chelicerae posteriorly); chelicerae with distinct lateral boss, promargin with series of short setae originating in line along base of fang plus three longer setae originating near base of fang, extending far from base before bending toward midline; promargin with five teeth, retromargin with two denticles, one near base of fang, second at level between two most proximal promarginal teeth. Labium wide, very short, extending only about one­third length of endites, bipartite, posterior portion short, flat, anterior portion steeply inclined; posterolateral corners heavily sclerotized, anterior margin invaginated at middle. Endites with weak oblique depression, without median groove, serrula present, apex bearing narrow patch of long, stiff, dark setae. Sternum flat, with weak lateral margins, not expanded anteriorly, without extensions to or between coxae; surface smooth, with few long setae. One weakly sclerotized epimeric sclerite on each side, with heavily sclerotized strips above coxae I, II but not extending between them, not fused to carapace. Pedicel composed of two narrow dorsal sclerites and weak, inverted y­shaped ventral sclerite, reaching almost to posterior tip of sternum.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="55.[795,1324,289,1837]" lastBlockId="56.[259,788,289,1603]" lastPageId="56" pageId="55">Abdomen without dorsal scutum; cuticle with weak, recumbent setae; epigastric scutum weakly sclerotized, that of males with posteriorly produced margin at middle, with very narrow spiracles at sides, without postepigastric sclerites; colulus represented by setae; posterior spiracle wide, anterior of colular setae. Anterior lateral spinnerets small, widely separated at base, with two articles; posterior median spinnerets of males cylindrical, of females triangular, posterior portion with about three large cylindrical gland spigots; posterior lateral spinnerets with two articles, those of females with at least one large cylindrical gland spigot.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="56.[259,788,289,1603]" pageId="56">Leg formula 4123; leg spination not greatly reduced, typical leg spination pattern (only surface bearing spines listed): femora I–IV d1­0­0; tibiae: I v0­1p­0; III d1­0­0, p1­1­0, v1p­2­1p, r1­1­1, IV d1­1­0, p1­1­0, v2­2­1p, r1­1­1; metatarsi: I, II v2­0­0; III d0­1­0, p0­ 1­1, v2­1p­2, r0­1­2; IV p2­2­1, v2­2­1p, r1­ 2­2; most surfaces with normal, long setae; coxae and trochanters without dorsal tubercles; anterior coxae without protuberant posterolateral corners; trochanters unnotched; metatarsi and tarsi I, II with weak, undivided scopulae; posterior metatarsi without distal preening brushes; tarsi with two basally dentate claws, no claw tufts; at least tarsi IV with cuticular cracks at about two­thirds of their length; trichobothria present, in two rows, on tarsi, metatarsi, and tibiae. Female palpal tibia with weak dorsal spines; female palpal tarsus with long dentate claw and scattered spines.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="56.[259,788,289,1603]" pageId="56">Male palp with large, complex retrolateral tibial apophysis bearing three prongs (two distal, one proximal); cymbial surface deeply excavated at base, opposite tibial apophysis; tegulum rounded, with proximally originating, gradually narrowing embolus closely associated with partially translucent conductor, median apophysis absent. External epigynum with wide, u­shaped median septum; spermathecae bipartite, situated posteriorly.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>