<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.93.12125" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e6ebc383-e9f0-4bdd-8a90-580314a2d81a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127875084" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-0743-2-189" ID-ZBK="95D58718953F44B2AA39C5D1EF4B36BC" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7E6DE7E7-4892-4526-B42B-A2414895D665" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1860-0743-2-189" ModsDocOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 93 (2)" ModsDocTitle="Two new species of Jesogammarus from Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Anisogammaridae), with comments on the validity of the subgenera Jesogammarus and Annanogammarus" checkinTime="1489820724786" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Tomikawa, Ko, Nakano, Takafumi &amp; Hanzawa, Naoto" docDate="2017" docId="26FA89A3BF310AE4246842949CE3A591" docLanguage="en" docName="ZoosystEvol 93(2): 189-210" docOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 93 (2)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.93.12125" docTitle="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) uchiyamaryui Tomikawa, Nakano &amp; Hanzawa, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="7E6DE7E7-4892-4526-B42B-A2414895D665" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="196" masterDocId="3F586311E00B9425305FFF8B7062FFFB" masterDocTitle="Two new species of Jesogammarus from Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Anisogammaridae), with comments on the validity of the subgenera Jesogammarus and Annanogammarus" masterLastPageNumber="210" masterPageNumber="189" pageId="4" pageNumber="193" updateTime="1643567840362" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Two new species of Jesogammarus from Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Anisogammaridae), with comments on the validity of the subgenera Jesogammarus and Annanogammarus</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tomikawa, Ko</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Nakano, Takafumi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Hanzawa, Naoto</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zoosystematics and Evolution</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>93</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>189</mods:start>
<mods:end>210</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.93.12125</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.93.12125</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-0743-2-189</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">95D58718953F44B2AA39C5D1EF4B36BC</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">95D58718953F44B2AA39C5D1EF4B36BC</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127875084" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7E6DE7E7-4892-4526-B42B-A2414895D665" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/26FA89A3BF310AE4246842949CE3A591" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="196" pageId="4" pageNumber="193">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="193" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="193">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/7E6DE7E7-4892-4526-B42B-A2414895D665" class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="193" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="4" pageNumber="193">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="194" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="194" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
materials.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
Holotype: Male (10.3 mm), NSMT-Cr 25474, Tanie River (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="33.82136">33°49′16.9″N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="129.73344">129°44′0.4″E</geoCoordinate>
), Ashibe, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan, 8 March 2012, collected by K. Tomikawa and S. Tashiro. Paratypes: 1 ovigerous female (9.2 mm), NSMT-Cr 25475, 1 male (12.1 mm), KUZ Z1803, 1 male (12.0 mm), KUZ Z1804, data same as for holotype; 1 male (8.6 mm), KUZ Z1805, 1 male (9.1 mm), KUZ Z1806, Mukata (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="32.715195">32°42′54.7″N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="128.83868">128°50′19.3″E</geoCoordinate>
), Goto, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan, 15 December 2015, collected by K. Tomikawa and S. Tashiro.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="194" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">Japan, Nagasaki Prefecture: Iki, Ashibe, Tanie River.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="196" pageId="5" pageNumber="194" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
Male [NSMT-Cr 25474, 10.3 mm]. Head (Fig. 9) with short rostrum; ventral margin of lateral cephalic lobe weakly concave; antennal sinus rounded; eyes reniform, major axis 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
height of head. Dorsal surfaces of pereonites smooth (Fig. 9). Dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3 (Fig. 10
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
) each with 2 setae. Posterior margin of epimeral plate 1 rounded with seta, posteroventral corner with seta, anteroventral to ventral margin with 7 setae (Fig. 10D); posterior margin of plate 2 weakly sinusoid with seta, posteroventral corner quadrate with seta, ventral margin and submargin with 3 and 2 robust setae, respectively (Fig. 10E); posterior margin of plate 3 slightly waved with seta, posteroventral corner weakly pointed with seta, anteroventral to ventral margin with 4 robust and 1 small setae (Fig. 10F). Urosomites 1-3 (Fig. 10
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–I">G-I</normalizedToken>
) with 10, 6, and 6 robust setae on dorsal margins.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male (10.3 mm), NSMT-Cr 25474. Habitus, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
Antenna 1 (Fig. 10J): length 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
body length; peduncular articles 1-3 in length ratio of 1.0: 0.7: 0.5; posterodistal corner of peduncular article 1 with robust seta, posterior margin of peduncular article 1 with single seta, posterior margin of peduncular article 2 with 1 cluster and 1 pair of setae, posterior margin of peduncular article 3 with pair of setae; accessory flagellum 5-articulate; primary flagellum 28-articulate, each article with 1 aesthetasc.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
Antenna 2 (Fig. 10K): length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
antenna 1; posterior margin of peduncular article 4 with 2 clusters and 1 pair of setae, posterior margin of peduncular article 5 with 2 clusters of setae; flagellum 14-articulate, calceoli present (Fig. 10L).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male (10.3 mm), NSMT-Cr 25474. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3, respectively, dorsal views; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
epimeral plates 1-3, respectively, lateral views; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–I">G-I</normalizedToken>
dorsal margins of urosomites 1-3, respectively, dorsal views; J peduncular articles 1-3, accessory flagellum, and flagellar articles 1-3 of antenna 1, medial view; K peduncular articles 1-5 and flagellar articles 1-3 of antenna 2, medial view; L calceolus of antenna 2, medial view; M upper lip, anterior view; N left mandible, medial view; O incisor and lacinia mobilis of left mandible, lateral view; P incisor and lacinia mobilis of right mandible, lateral view; Q lower lip, ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="195" pageId="5" pageNumber="194">
Mouthparts. Upper lip (= labrum) (Fig. 10M) with rounded distal margin, bearing fine setae. Mandibles (Fig. 10
<normalizedToken originalValue="N–P">N-P</normalizedToken>
) with left and right incisors 5- and 4-dentate, respectively, left lacinia mobilis 5-dentate, right one bifid, bearing many teeth; molar process triturative, with plumose seta; accessory setal rows of left and right mandibles each with 6 blade-like setae; palp 3-articulate with length ratio of 1.0: 2.3: 2.0, palp article 1 bare, article 2 with 16 setae, article 3 with 1 cluster and 2 pairs of A-se 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="195" start="start">tae</pageBreakToken>
, single B-seta, and many C-, D-, and E-setae. Lower lip (= labium) (Fig. 10Q) with broad outer lobes, inner lobes indistinct. Maxilla 1 (Fig. 11A) with inner and outer plates and palp; medial margin of inner plate with 16 plumose setae 2 plumose setae, apical submargin with 4 setae; outer plate subrectangular, with 11 serrate teeth apically (Fig. 11B); palp 2-articulate, longer than outer plate, article 1 lacking marginal setae, article 2 with 5 robust setae and 1 slender seta on its apical margin and 4 slender setae on its submargin, outer margin with 2 setae. Maxilla 2 (Fig. 11C) with oblique inner row of 16 plumose setae on inner plate; outer plate slightly longer than inner plate. Maxilliped (Fig. 11D) with inner and outer plates and palp; inner plate with 3 and 2 robust setae on apical and inner margins, respectively; outer plate with plumose setae on apical margin and robust setae on inner margin; palp 4-articulate, article 2 with inner marginal and submarginal rows of setae, article 3 with facial setae, article 4 slightly curved inward, with slender nail.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 11E): coxa with 12 setae on anterodistal to to posterodistal margin; anterior and posterior margins of basis with long setae; carpus length 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, anterior margin with single seta; propodus length 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
carpus and 1.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, anterior margin with 2 clusters of setae and single seta, palmar margin oblique, weakly convex, with 15 peg-shaped robust setae (Fig. 11F); dactylus as long as palmar margin.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="195" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male (10.3 mm), NSMT-Cr 25474. A maxilla 1, dorsal view; B outer plate of maxilla 1, dorsal view; C maxilla 2, dorsal view; D maxilliped, dorsal view; E gnathopod 1, lateral view; F palmar margin of propodus of gnathopod 1, lateral view; G gnathopod 2, lateral view; H palmar margin of propodus of gnathopod 2, lateral view; I pereopod 3, lateral view; J pereopod 4, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 11G): coxa with 8 marginal setae on anterodistal to posterodistal margin, medial surface with 2 setae; anterior and posterior margins of basis with long setae; carpus length 1.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, anterior margin with 1 pair of setae; propodus length 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
carpus and 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, respectively, anterior margin with 1 cluster and 1 pair of setae, palmar margin oblique, weakly convex, with 14 peg-shaped robust setae (Fig. 11H); dactylus as long as palmar margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Pereopod 3 (Fig. 11I): coxa with 4 and 2 marginal setae on anterodistal and posterodistal parts, respectively; anterior and posterior margins of basis with long setae, anterodistal corner of basis without robust seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 11J): coxa expanded with posterior concavity, bearing 2 setae on anterodistal corner and 4 setae on ventral margin; anterior and posterior margins of basis with long setae, anterodistal corner with robust seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Pereopod 5 (Fig. 12A): coxa bilobed, anterior lobe with 2 apical setae, ventral margin of posterior lobe with 2 setae, posterodistal corner not pointed with seta; posterior margin of basis weakly expanded, with 9 setae; anterior and posterior margins of merus to propodus with robust and slender setae.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Figure 12. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="195" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male (10.3 mm), NSMT-Cr 25474. A 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 5, lateral view; B 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view; C 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 7, lateral view; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–I">D-I</normalizedToken>
coxal gills on gnathopod 2 and pereopods 3-7, lateral views; J pleopod 1, lateral view, distal parts of rami omitted; K bifid plumose seta (clothes-pin seta) on inner basal margin of inner ramus of pleopod 1, lateral view; L retinacula on peduncle of pleopod 1, lateral view; M uropod 1, dorsal view; N uropod 2, dorsal view; O uropod 3, dorsal view; P telson, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Pereopod 6 (Fig. 12B): coxa bilobed, anterior lobe with apical seta, anterior margin with long setae, ventral margin of posterior lobe with 2 setae, posterodistal corner weakly pointed with seta; posterior margin of basis weakly expanded with 9 setae, posterodistal corner with robust seta; anterior and posterior margins of merus to propodus with robust and slender setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Pereopod 7 (Fig. 12C): ventral margin of coxa weakly concave, bearing 3 setae on anterior margin and 4 setae on posteroventral margin; posterior margin of basis weakly expanded with 7 setae, posterodistal corner with 2 robust setae; anterior and posterior margins of merus to propodus with robust and slender setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Coxal gills on gnathopod 2 and pereopods 3-5 (Fig. 12
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–G">D-G</normalizedToken>
) with 2 accessory lobes, both anterior and posterior lobes short, subequal, gills on pereopods 6 and 7 (Fig. 12H, I) each with 1 accessory lobe.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Pleopods 1-3 (Fig. 12J) each with paired retinacula (Fig. 12L) on inner margin of peduncle, and bifid plumose setae (= clothes-pin setae) (Fig. 12K) on inner basal margin of inner ramus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Uropods. Uropod 1 (Fig. 12M): peduncle with robust seta on basofacial part, inner and outer margins with 4 and 2 setae, respectively, inner and outer distal corners with 1 and 2 robust setae, respectively; inner ramus length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
peduncle, inner margin with 2 robust setae and outer margin with 1 robust and 1 small setae; outer ramus length 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
inner ramus, inner and outer margins each with robust seta. Uropod 2 (Fig. 12N): inner and outer margins of peduncle each with 2 setae, outer distal corner with robust seta; inner ramus length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
peduncle, its inner and outer margins each with robust seta; outer ramus length 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
inner ramus, marginally bare. Uropod 3 (Fig. 12O): peduncle length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus; inner ramus length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus, with inner marginal seta and apical seta; outer ramus 2-articulate, inner and outer margins of article 1 each with 4 clusters of setae, some of which robust, both inner and outer margins with plumose setae, article 2 length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 1, with simple setae apically.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Telson (Fig. 12P) almost as long as wide, cleft for 63% of length; each lobe with 2 or 3 robust setae and slender setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Female [NSMT-Cr 25475, 9.2 mm]. Antenna 1 (Fig. 13A): peduncular articles 1-3 in length ratio of 1.0: 0.7: 0.4; posterior margin of peduncular article 1 with 2 single setae, posterior margin of peduncular article 2 with 2 pairs of setae, posterior margin of peduncular article 3 with cluster of setae; accessory flagellum 6-articulate; primary flagellum 31-articulate.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Figure 13. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="195" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype, female (9.2 mm), NSMT-Cr 25475. A peduncular articles 1-3, accessory flagellum, and flagellar articles 1-3 of antenna 1, medial view; B peduncular articles 1-5 and flagellar articles 1-3 of antenna 2, medial view; C gnathopod 1, lateral view; D palmar margin of propodus of gnathopod 1, lateral view; E gnathopod 2, lateral view; F palmar margin of propodus of gnathopod 2, lateral view; G brood plate of gnathopod 2, lateral view; H 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 5, lateral view; I 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view; J 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 7, lateral view; K uropod 3, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">Antenna 2 (Fig. 13B): posterior margin of peduncular article 4 with 2 clusters of setae, posterior margin of peduncular article 5 with 2 pairs of setae and single seta; flagellum 13-articulate, calceoli absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 13C): posterior margin of coxa with many setae; carpus length 1.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width; propodus length 1.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
merus and 1.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, respectively; palmar margin (Fig. 13D) with 5 robust setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="196" pageId="6" pageNumber="195">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 13E): posteroproximal part of coxa with numerous setae; carpus length 2.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="196" start="start">propodus</pageBreakToken>
length 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
merus and 2.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, respectively; palmar margin (Fig. 13F) with 1 robust and 10 pectinate robust setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
Posterior margin of bases of pereopods 5-7 more expanded than in male (Fig. 13
<normalizedToken originalValue="H–J">H-J</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">Brood plates (Fig. 13G): broad, with numerous marginal setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
Uropod 3 (Fig. 13K): peduncle length 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus; inner ramus length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus; inner and outer margins of article 1 of outer ramus with 5 and 3 clusters/pairs of setae, article 2 length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 1.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">Egg number 154.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="196" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
The specific name honors Mr Ryu Uchiyama (nature photographer), who provided many photos of living amphipods throughout 
<normalizedToken originalValue="KT’s">KT's</normalizedToken>
amphipodological study.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="196" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">Distribution and habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">This species is known from Iki and Fukue Islands, Nagasaki Prefecture. The specimens were collected from river mouths subject to tidal action. An ovigerous female was collected in March.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="196" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
is morphologically similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
Tomikawa, 2015 in having 1) dorsal margin of pereonites 5-7 without setae, 2) a few (&lt;4) setae on dorsal margin of pleonites 1-3, 3) large eyes, robust seta on posterodistal corner of peduncular article 1 of antenna 1, and 4) mandibular palp article 1 without robust setae. However, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
by the following features (features of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
in parentheses): 1) posterior margin of peduncular article 2 of antenna 1 with two (three or four) setae, 2) accessory lobes of coxal gills on gnathopod 2 and pereopods 3-5 short and straight (long and curved), 3) ventral margins of coxae of female gnathopods 1 and 2 and pereopod 3 with numerous long setae (a few short setae), and 4) inner ramus of uropod 3 shorter than 0.2 (0.2-0.3) times as long as outer ramus. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
is also similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus spinopalpus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinopalpus">Jesogammarus spinopalpus</taxonomicName>
Morino, 1985 in having 1) short accessory lobes of coxal gills on gnathopod 2 and pereopods 3-5 and 2) densely setose ventral margins of coxae of female gnathopods 1 and 2. However, the former differs from the latter by the following features (features of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus spinopalpus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinopalpus">Jesogammarus spinopalpus</taxonomicName>
in parentheses): 1) eyes large (small), 2) dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3 each with two setae (numerous), 3) the mandibular palp article 1 without robust setae (present), 4) inner ramus of uropod 3 shorter than 0.2 times as long as outer ramus (longer than 0.3), and 5) posterior margin of bases of female pereopods 5-7 with short (long) setae.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
Figure 14. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
sp. n., not preserved, precopula pair (male: upper, female: lower). Photographed by Ryu Uchiyama.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<subSection pageId="7" pageNumber="196" type="molecular phylogenies">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">Molecular phylogenies</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
The BI tree (mean ln L = −8918.44; Fig. 15) had an almost identical topology to that of the ML tree (ln L = −9156.46; not shown). The monophyly of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Jesogammarus</taxonomicName>
was well-supported (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0). The genus 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Jesogammarus</taxonomicName>
consisted of three monophyletic lineages: 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="uchiyamaryui">Jesogammarus uchiyamaryui</taxonomicName>
lineage (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0), the 
<taxonomicName infraspecific-rank="subgenus" lsidName="(Annanogammarus)" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" rank="subGenus" subGenus="Annanogammarus">subgenus Annanogammarus</taxonomicName>
lineage (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0), and the 
<taxonomicName infraspecific-rank="subgenus" lsidName="(Jesogammarus)" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" rank="subGenus" subGenus="Jesogammarus">subgenus Jesogammarus</taxonomicName>
lineage (BS = 99%, PP = 1.0). However, our phylogenetic analyses failed to resolve precise the phylogenetic relationships among these three lineages.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">Figure 15. Bayesian inference tree for 1,499 bp of nuclear 28S rRNA and mitochondrial COI and 16S rRNA markers. Numbers on nodes represent bootstrap values for maximum likelihood and Bayesian posterior probabilities.</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="196">
The monophyly of the four species within the 
<taxonomicName authority="Bousfield, 1979" authorityName="Bousfield" authorityYear="1979" class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Annanogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Annanogammarus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Annanogammarus</taxonomicName>
lineage inhabiting Japan was well supported (BS = 94%, PP = 1.0). The 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Jesogammarus</taxonomicName>
lineage comprised four subclades; however, the detailed phylogenetic relationships among these four lineages remain unresolved. The first subclade (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0) contains the Chinese 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus hebeiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hebeiensis">Jesogammarus hebeiensis</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus spinopalpus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinopalpus">Jesogammarus spinopalpus</taxonomicName>
from the Boso Peninsula on Honshu, Japan (locality #12 in Fig. 1). The second subclade (BS = 91%, PP = 0.99) comprised 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus hinumensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hinumensis">Jesogammarus hinumensis</taxonomicName>
Morino, 1993 inhabiting brackish habitats of Japan and 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
from Iki Island. The third lineage (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0) included Japanese 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus mikadoi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mikadoi">Jesogammarus mikadoi</taxonomicName>
Tomikawa, Morino &amp; Mawatari, 2003 and four species defined as the 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus jesoensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jesoensis">Jesogammarus jesoensis</taxonomicName>
complex by Tomikawa et al (2016): the monophyly of the 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus jesoensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jesoensis">Jesogammarus jesoensis</taxonomicName>
complex was well-supported (BS = 97%, PP = 1.0). 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus paucistulosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="paucistulosus">Jesogammarus paucistulosus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus bousfieldi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bousfieldi">Jesogammarus bousfieldi</taxonomicName>
formed the last subclade (BS = 98%, PP = 1.0). 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus paucistulosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="paucistulosus">Jesogammarus paucistulosus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus bousfieldi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bousfieldi">Jesogammarus bousfieldi</taxonomicName>
formed a well-supported clade (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0; respectively). The 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus paucistulosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="paucistulosus">Jesogammarus paucistulosus</taxonomicName>
specimens were divided into two lineages: individuals collected from the southern part of Ibaraki Prefecture (#10, 11) formed a well-supported lineage (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0), and the remainder inhabiting the northern part of Ibaraki (#8) formed the other well-supported clade (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0). The 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus bousfieldi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="7" pageNumber="196" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bousfieldi">Jesogammarus bousfieldi</taxonomicName>
specimens were also split into two lineages. Individuals from Mamurogawa (#3) formed a well-supported clade (BS = 100%, PP = 1.0), while the other amphipods inhabiting the southern part of Yamagata Prefecture (#5, 6) grouped with a monophyletic lineage (BS = 100%, PP = 0.99).
</paragraph>
</subSection>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>