<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6234367" ID-GBIF-Dataset="0b2e6f14-1075-4e4e-b62f-57b13f1955ee" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6234367" checkinTime="1459848496087" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Sarnat, Eli M." docDate="2008" docId="DF17786EFF9DFFF453C32B21FBF4D950" docLanguage="en" docName="zt01767p036.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1767" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@747d1932" docStyleName="zootaxa.2007.monograph" docTitle="Pheidole roosevelti" docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" masterDocId="232E0016FF97FFFF53542A5CFFA8DA5A" masterDocTitle="A taxonomic revision of the Pheidole roosevelti - group (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in Fiji" masterLastPageNumber="36" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" updateTime="1645581731635" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A taxonomic revision of the Pheidole roosevelti - group (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in Fiji</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sarnat, Eli M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2008</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1767</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>36</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.182030</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">0b2e6f14-1075-4e4e-b62f-57b13f1955ee</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">182030</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6234367" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6234367" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:DF17786EFF9DFFF453C32B21FBF4D950" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DF17786EFF9DFFF453C32B21FBF4D950" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,623,381,407]" box="[151,623,381,407]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,623,381,407]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,623,381,407]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Diagnosis of 
<taxonomicName box="[310,538,381,407]" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Pheidole" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="roosevelti">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[310,538,381,407]" italics="true" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Pheidole roosevelti</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
-group
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1437,450,2036]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,265,450,476]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<collectionCode box="[151,261,450,476]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">MAJOR</collectionCode>
.
</emphasis>
Head, in full face view, subquadrate in shape, broadest at about 
<number box="[1034,1049,450,476]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="2.0">2</number>
/ 
<number box="[1059,1072,450,476]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="3.0">3</number>
length, posterior margin triangularly emarginate; in profile vertex weakly concave. Eyes in full face view convex, situated in anterior 
<number box="[1367,1378,490,516]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="1.0">1</number>
/ 
<number box="[1389,1404,490,516]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="3.0">3</number>
of head, breaking outline of head; in profile distance between eye and mandibular insertion approximately twice length of eye. Mandibles triangular, masticatory margin bidentate both apically and basally on younger individuals (older individuals often edentate). Hypostoma with one median tooth, two inner teeth and two outer teeth. Frontal lobes well developed, overhanging antennal insertions. Frontal carinae distinct and elevated, overhanging antennal scrobes, terminating at about 
<number box="[772,787,690,716]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="2.0">2</number>
/ 
<number box="[797,810,690,716]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="3.0">3</number>
length of head before reaching posterolateral lobes. Antennal scrobes weakly impressed, bounded mesally by frontal carinae and laterally by longitudinal carinae. Clypeus distinctly concave between frontal lobes, anterior margin concave medially. Antennae 
<number box="[1304,1332,770,796]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="12.0">12</number>
-merous. Antennal scapes reaching approximately half the distance from antennal insertions to corners of posterolateral lobes, slender and arcuate basally, thickened at distal third. Funicular segments 
<number box="[1112,1157,850,876]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="5.0" valueMax="8.0" valueMin="2.0">2–8</number>
about twice as long as broad. Antennal club 
<number box="[406,418,890,916]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="3.0">3</number>
-segmented and slender, distinctly shorter than remainder of funiculus. Promesonotum forming a high dome. Mesonotum with a posterior process that often overhangs anterior portion of propodeal dorsum. Mesonotal declivity concave. Pronotal humeri indistinct or obtusely angulate. Metanotal groove impressed. Propodeal spines extending approximately to level of mesonotal process, often bifurcate or bent apically so that they project posteriorly at an oblique angle; in dorsal view moderately divergent. Petiolar peduncle elongate and thick. Petiole broadly cuneate, dorsum of node excised. Postpetiole, in dorsal view, with lateral projections, much broader than long.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1437,450,2036]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Sculpture varying strongly among species. Mandibles weakly striate with scattered piligerous pits. Scapes striate. Metapleuron rugose. Erect long, fine and yellow hairs abundant on all body surfaces. Body dark reddish-brown with lighter appendages; color of head sometimes redder than rest of body.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1437,450,2036]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[198,310,1290,1316]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<collectionCode box="[198,305,1290,1316]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">MINOR</collectionCode>
.
</emphasis>
Head ovate, subcordate or subquadrate with sides weakly to strongly convex; posterior margin, in full face view, roundly convex, truncate or weakly bilobed; in profile, posterior margin weakly to strongly dorsoventrally pinched, dorsum and venter meeting at an obtuse to acute angle. Eyes in full face view convex, in front of midline, break outline of head. Mandibles triangular, masticatory margin with 
<number box="[1224,1268,1410,1436]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="7.5" valueMax="8.0" valueMin="7.0">7–8</number>
teeth. Frontal carinae short and weak, either terminating near eye level or integrating with other face sculpture. Clypeus with anterior margin convex laterally and flat to weakly concave medially. Antenna 
<number box="[1185,1213,1490,1516]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="12.0">12</number>
-merous. Antennal scapes distinctly surpassing posterolateral corners, slender and weakly arcuate basally, thickened at distal third. Funicular segments 
<number box="[466,511,1570,1596]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="5.0" valueMax="8.0" valueMin="2.0">2–8</number>
approximately twice as long as broad, 
<number box="[992,1004,1570,1596]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" value="3.0">3</number>
-segmented club slender, as long as remainder of funiculus. Mesonotum with a posterior process that often overhangs anterior portion of propodeal dorsum. Mesonotal declivity concave. Pronotal humeri inconspicuous. Metanotal groove occasionally impressed. Propodeal spines, in profile, obtaining height approximately level with mesonotal process, often bifurcate or bent apically so that they project posteriorly at an oblique angle; in dorsal view moderately divergent. Petiolar peduncle elongate and thin. Petiole cuneate, dorsum of node flat. Postpetiole, in profile, subtriangular with rounded dorsum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1437,450,2036]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Sculpture varying strongly among species. Mandibles weakly striate with scattered piligerous pits. Scapes smooth and shining. Erect long, fine and yellow hairs abundant on all body surfaces. Body dark reddishbrown to light reddish brown with lighter appendages and occasionally lighter waist and gaster.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1437,450,2036]" lastBlockId="11.[151,1437,152,778]" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[198,310,1970,1996]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<collectionCode box="[198,305,1970,1996]" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">QUEEN</collectionCode>
.
</emphasis>
Head with sides subparallel or diverging posteriorly, subquadrate to subtriangular in shape, posterior margin moderately to strongly concave. Eyes, in full face view, large convex, situated in front of midline, breaking outline of head. Mandibles triangular, masticatory margin bidentate both apically and basally. Frontal lobes weakly overhanging antennal insertions. Frontal carinae distinct, diverging, overhanging antennal scrobes, terminating at about 
<number box="[554,569,232,258]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="2.0">2</number>
/ 
<number box="[579,592,232,258]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="3.0">3</number>
length of head before reaching posterolateral lobes. Antennal scrobes weakly impressed, bounded mesally by frontal carinae and laterally by longitudinal carinae. Clypeus distinctly concave between frontal lobes, anterior margin convex laterally and concave medially. Antennal scapes reaching approximately half the distance from antennal insertions to corners of posterolateral lobes, slender and arcuate basally, thickened at distal third. Antenna 
<number box="[874,902,392,418]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="12.0">12</number>
-merous. Funicular segments 
<number box="[1249,1294,392,418]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="5.0" valueMax="8.0" valueMin="2.0">2–8</number>
about twice as long as broad. Antennal club 
<number box="[539,551,432,458]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="3.0">3</number>
-segmented and slender, shorter than remainder of funiculus. Mesoscutum either small without obscuring pronotum in dorsal view, or large and obscuring pronotum in dorsal view. Scutellum produced as a weakly elevated circular to subtriangular plate. Metanotum transversely striate. Propodeal spines often bent apically so that they project posteriorly at an oblique angle; in dorsal view moderately divergent. Petiolar peduncle elongate and thick. Petiole broadly cuneate, dorsum of node weakly concave to strongly excised. Postpetiole, in dorsal view, with lateral projections, much broader than long.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,152,778]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Sculpture varying strongly among species. Mandibles weakly striate with scattered piligerous pits. Scapes striate. Metapleuron rugose. First gastral tergite and sternite sculptured basally. Erect long, fine and yellow hairs abundant on all body surfaces. Body reddish-brown with lighter appendages.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>