<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.813.30336" ID-GBIF-Dataset="41ef3c31-d959-4168-b2b7-e46c299b5fc6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154127178" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-813-111" ID-ZBK="AF1D1300BD4B4C1795B48567EFAD850C" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="1313-2970-813-111" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 813" ModsDocTitle="Descriptions of immature stages of four species of the genera Graptus, Peritelus, Philopedon, and Tanymecus and larval instar determination in Tanymecus (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae)" checkinTime="1546956053860" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gosik, Rafal, Sprick, Peter &amp; Morris, Michael G." docDate="2019" docId="00598DB1F641176F15C5D653E5E7BE76" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 813: 111-150" docOrigin="ZooKeys 813" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.813.30336" docTitle="Philopedon plagiatum" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="126" masterDocId="FFC0C23F067AFFEF9E0FFFAFFF97FFAC" masterDocTitle="Descriptions of immature stages of four species of the genera Graptus, Peritelus, Philopedon, and Tanymecus and larval instar determination in Tanymecus (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae)" masterLastPageNumber="150" masterPageNumber="111" pageId="12" pageNumber="123" updateTime="1643463028591" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Descriptions of immature stages of four species of the genera Graptus, Peritelus, Philopedon, and Tanymecus and larval instar determination in Tanymecus (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Entiminae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gosik, Rafal</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sprick, Peter</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Morris, Michael G.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>813</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>111</mods:start>
<mods:end>150</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.813.30336</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.813.30336</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-813-111</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">AF1D1300BD4B4C1795B48567EFAD850C</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AF1D1300BD4B4C1795B48567EFAD850C</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="154127178" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:00598DB1F641176F15C5D653E5E7BE76" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/00598DB1F641176F15C5D653E5E7BE76" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="126" pageId="12" pageNumber="123">
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="123" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="123">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Philopedon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Philopedon plagiatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="123" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plagiatum">Philopedon plagiatum</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="124" pageId="12" pageNumber="123" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="123">Specimens examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="123">
6 premature larvae: Germany, Niedersachsen, Hannover-Vahrenheide, Kugelfangtrift, nutrient-poor sandy grassland, collected at sparsely grown sites under 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Plantaginaceae" genus="Plantago" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Plantago lanceolata" order="Lamiales" pageId="12" pageNumber="123" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="lanceolata">Plantago lanceolata</taxonomicName>
, 02.10.2011: 3 ex., 11.11.2011: 3 ex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="124">
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="124" start="start">3</pageBreakToken>
mature larvae: same site as before, 02.10.2011: 1 ex., 11.11.2011: 1 ex.; Denmark, Syddanmark, Emmerlev Klev near 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Højer">Hojer</normalizedToken>
, moraine at the sandy sea shore of the North Sea, collected on 13.08.2015: 1 ex., between the roots of 
<taxonomicName authority="L." class="Magnoliopsida" family="Plantaginaceae" genus="Plantago" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="subsp." kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Plantago maritima" order="Lamiales" pageId="13" pageNumber="124" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="subSpecies" species="maritima" subSpecies="maritima">Plantago maritima L. subsp. maritima</taxonomicName>
, very probably; 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. lanceolata" pageId="13" pageNumber="124" rank="species" species="lanceolata">P. lanceolata</taxonomicName>
was also present nearby.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="126" pageId="13" pageNumber="124" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="124">Description of the mature larva.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="124">Body length: 6.5-8.2 mm, body width at the widest part (level of first abdominal segment): 2.4-3.4 mm, head width: 0.97-1.03 mm, head height: 0.75-0.83 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="126" pageId="13" pageNumber="124">
Body (Figs 7-9). Slender, elongate, slightly narrowed bilaterally dorso-ventrally. Prothorax slightly smaller than mesothorax; metathorax as wide as mesothorax. Abdominal segments 1-7 of almost equal length. Abdominal segment 8 wide, flattened posteriorly, with conical lateral lobes. Abdominal segment 9 strongly reduced, consisting of 4 well-isolated lobes, ventral almost rounded, lateral conical, dorsal semicircular. Abdominal segment 10 consists of 4 anal lobes of almost equal size. Anus located ter 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="125" start="start">minally</pageBreakToken>
, covered by lobes of abdominal segment 9. Apical parts of lateral lobes of the segments 6-8 and all lobes of segment 9 darkly sclerotized (Figs 46-48). Spiracles (of thoracic and abdominal segments 1-8) annular. Chaetotaxy well developed, setae capilliform, variable in length, yellowish to brown. Each side of prothorax (Fig. 44) with 9 prns of unequal length, placed on the weakly sclerotized pronotal sclerite; 2 ps and 1 eus very short. Meso- and metathorax (Fig. 44) on each side with 1 moderately long 
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="126" start="start">prs</pageBreakToken>
and 4 pds, variable in length (first, second and fourth short, third moderately long), 2 short as, 3 minute (various in length) ss, 1 moderately long eps, 1 short ps and 1 eus. Each pedal area of thoracic segments with 9 pda, variable in length. Abd. segment 1-8 (Figs 45-48) on each side with 1 short prs and 5 pds, almost equal in length, arranged along the posterior margin of each segment, 1 minute and 1 long ss (segment 8 with 1 minute ss only), 4 eps (segment 6 with 3 eps, segments 7 and 8 with 2 eps) and 2 ps, equal in length, 1 lsts and 2 short eus. Abdominal setae increase slightly and gradually from segment 1 to 8. Abd. segment 9 (Figs 46-48) on each side with 2 moderately long ds, located near the posterior margin of the segment, 1 moderately long ps and 2 short sts. Anal lobes without setae.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
Figures 44-48. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Philopedon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Philopedon plagiatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plagiatum">Philopedon plagiatum</taxonomicName>
mature larva, habitus and chaetotaxy. 44 Thoracic segments lateral view 45 First abdominal segment lateral view 46 Abdominal segments 7-10 lateral view 47 Abdominal segments 7-10 ventral view 48 Abdominal segments 7-10 dorsal view. Abbreviations: Th. 1-3 - thoracic segments 1-3, Abd. 1-10 - abdominal segments 1-10, setae: as - alar, ps - pleural, eps - epipleural, ds - dorsal, lsts - laterosternal, eus - eusternal, pda - pedal, pds - postdorsal, prns - pronotal, prs - prodorsal, sps - spiracular, sts - sternal.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
Head (Fig. 49). Greyish to light yellow, suboval, slightly oblate bilaterally; frontal suture almost invisible, endocarina absent. Setae on head capilliform; des1, 2, 3, 5 long, equal in length, des4 very short; des1 and des2 located in the central part of epicranium, des3 and des4 placed on epicranium close to des3, des5 located anterolaterally; fs4, 5 equal in length, fs3 very short; fs3 placed medially, fs4 located anteromedially, fs5 anterolaterally, close to epistome; les1 and les2 equal in length, slightly shorter than des1. Single ves moderately long. Postepicranial area with 4 very short pes (Fig. 49). Antenna (Figs 50, 51) located at the end of frontal suture; antennal segment membranous, bearing sensorium usually cushion-like, truncate at apex (Se) (Fig. 50) or occasionally conical-like (Fig. 51), and 5 sensilla: 2 ampullacea (sa) and 3 basiconica (sb). Labrum (regular) (Figs 52, 53) (deformed) (Fig. 54) almost semicircular, anterior margin doubly sinuate; 3 pairs of lrs almost equal in length; lrs1 placed medially, lrs2 anteromedially, lrs3 anterolaterally. Clypeus (Figs 52, 53) trapezoid, anterior margin of clypeus straight; 2 pairs of cls almost as long 
<normalizedToken originalValue="aslrs–cls">aslrs-cls</normalizedToken>
1 located posterolaterally, cls2 posteromedially; clss clearly visible placed posteriorly, between cls. Epipharynx (Fig. 53) with 3 pairs of finger-shaped als of various lengths; 3 pairs of rod-shaped ams: ams1 and ams3 short, ams2 moderately long; 2 pairs of rod-shaped mes, equal in length, both placed anteromedially very close to ams. Surface of epipharynx (especially close to margin) covered with asperities. Labral rods short, rounded, slightly converging posteriorly. Mandibles (Fig. 55) curved, narrow, with divided apex (teeth different in length). There is an elongated protuberance on the cutting edge between the apex and the middle of the mandible; both mds capilliform, almost equal in length. Maxilla (Figs 56-58) with 1 stps and 2 pfs of equal length; mala with 8 finger- or rod-like dms (Fig. 57) and 4 vms, both varied in length (Fig. 58); mbs very short. Maxillary palpi with 2 palpomeres, basal with short mps; distal palpomere apically with a group of sensilla, each palpomere with a pore. Basal palpomere wider than distal, both of almost equal length. Prelabium (Fig. 56) cup-like with 1 long prms, located medially. Ligula with 2 pairs of ligs, various in length. Premental sclerite clearly visible, trident-shaped (median branch weakly sclerotized), posterior extension with elongated apex. Labial palpi 2-segmented; apex of distal palpomere with some sensilla; each palpomere with a pore. Basal palpomere slightly wider and shorter than distal. Postlabium (Fig. 56) with 3 capilliform pms, the first pair located anteromedially, the remaining 2 pairs posterolaterally; pms1 minute, pms2 very long, pms3 moderately long. Surface of postlabium and stipes partially covered with asperities.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
Figure 49. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Philopedon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Philopedon plagiatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plagiatum">Philopedon plagiatum</taxonomicName>
mature larva, head, frontal view. Abbreviations: at - antenna, setae: des - dorsal epicranial, fs - frontal, les - lateral epicranial, pes - postepicranial, ves - ventral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
Figures 50-51. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Philopedon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Philopedon plagiatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plagiatum">Philopedon plagiatum</taxonomicName>
mature larva, right antenna. 50 Cushion-like 51 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Conical–shaped">Conical-shaped</normalizedToken>
. Abbreviations: Se - sensorium, sa - sensillum ampullaceum, sb - sensillum basiconicum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
Figures 52-54. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Philopedon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Philopedon plagiatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plagiatum">Philopedon plagiatum</taxonomicName>
mature larva, body parts. 52 Clypeus and labrum 53 Epipharynx 54 Clypeus and labrum, deformed. Abbreviations: clss - clypeal sensorium, lr - labral rods, setae: als - anterolateral, ams - anteromedial, cls - clypeal, lrs - labral, mes - median.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
Figure 55. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Philopedon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Philopedon plagiatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plagiatum">Philopedon plagiatum</taxonomicName>
mature larva, left mandible. Abbreviations: mds - mandibular seta.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="126">
Figures 56-58. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Philopedon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Philopedon plagiatum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="126" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plagiatum">Philopedon plagiatum</taxonomicName>
mature larva, body parts. 56 Maxillolabial complex ventral aspect 57 Right maxilla apical part dorsal aspect 58 Right maxilla apical part ventral aspect. Abbreviations: setae: dms - dorsal malar, ligs - ligular, mbs - malar basiventral, mps - maxillary palp, pfs - palpiferal, prms - prelabial, pms - postlabial, stps - stipal, vms - ventral malar.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>