<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.258.4391" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bc20385b-4f8c-4f6f-97ed-604d2dd3e761" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152039659" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-258-53" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:167E8FC9-C0F9-43E0-AC83-F3BD559B316D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-258-53" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 258" ModsDocTitle="Hispaniolan Hemilophini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)" checkinTime="1451247770178" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lingafelter, Steven W." docDate="2013" docId="C2B7059B67460CB324BE5F8AD145E278" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 258: 53-83" docOrigin="ZooKeys 258" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.258.4391" docTitle="Oedudes anulatus Lingafelter, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="167E8FC9-C0F9-43E0-AC83-F3BD559B316D" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="61" masterDocId="FFD1D90E482EFFCF440FFF87FFFE4208" masterDocTitle="Hispaniolan Hemilophini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="83" masterPageNumber="53" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" updateTime="1643695520060" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Hispaniolan Hemilophini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lingafelter, Steven W.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>258</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>53</mods:start>
<mods:end>83</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.258.4391</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.258.4391</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-258-53</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">6345CDDA-80A0-4C66-8699-62876D1C4CFE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152039659" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:167E8FC9-C0F9-43E0-AC83-F3BD559B316D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C2B7059B67460CB324BE5F8AD145E278" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="7" pageNumber="60">
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="60" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="60">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:167E8FC9-C0F9-43E0-AC83-F3BD559B316D" authority="Lingafelter" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oedudes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oedudes anulatus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="anulatus">Oedudes anulatus Lingafelter</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="7" pageNumber="60">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1a; 3b-d; Map 1
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="60" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="60">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="60">
This species is easily distinguished from all other Hispaniolan hemilophines by the bidentate elytral apices and bold red or orange pattern of pubescence on the pronotum and elytra. This species is similar to the Cuban 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oedudes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oedudes ramsdeni" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ramsdeni">Oedudes ramsdeni</taxonomicName>
(Fisher), but differs in having the pronotal black spots at the middle and posterior portions of the pronotum (not concentrated only at the base as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oedudes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oedudes ramsdeni" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ramsdeni">Oedudes ramsdeni</taxonomicName>
); the legs, including the femora, most of the tibiae, and most of the tarsi pale reddish (not dark reddish-brown to black as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oedudes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oedudes ramsdeni" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ramsdeni">Oedudes ramsdeni</taxonomicName>
); the black fascia at the base of the elytron is large and extends to the suture and laterally down the length of the elytron (in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oedudes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oedudes ramsdeni" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ramsdeni">Oedudes ramsdeni</taxonomicName>
, it is relatively small and does not extend to the suture or lateral margin); and in having the antennae bicolored with pale annulations at the bases of at least antennomeres 2-6 (uniformly black in all other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oedudes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oedudes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Oedudes</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="60">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="7" pageNumber="60">
Size: 9.0-12.0 mm long; 2.9-4.2 mm wide between humeri. Head with dense vestiture of appressed yellow, orange, or red setae, thickened at base, almost scale-like, dense throughout except on gena and posterior to upper eye lobes. Punctures indistinct or hidden by pubescence except on fronto-clypeal margin. Frons not bulging, level to slightly convex between eyes, without medial impression. Gena below lower eye lobe and mandibular base about one-half height of lower eye lobe; frontal-genal ridge absent; ante-clypeal sulcus obsolete. Eye large, slightly bulging laterally on lower lobe, finely faceted, upper lobe connected to lower lobe by 3-4 facets at nar 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="61" start="start">rowest</pageBreakToken>
point, lower lobe much larger than upper lobe, occupying about one-half of head from lateral view. Interantennal region not impressed, antennal tubercles weakly elevated. Antenna slender, extending beyond elytral apex by 1 antennomere in females (males unknown). Antenna with moderately dense, appressed, short pubescence of two colors, white and black, and scattered, sparse, long setae on venter of basal segments. Antennomeres mostly black with pale yellow or orange annulations on basal portions of at least 2-6. Antennomere 3 very long (longer than scape + 2; nearly as long as 4+5), subsequent antennomeres gradually decreasing in length. Prothorax cylindrical, slightly broader than long (1.8-2.5 mm long; 2.1-3.0 mm wide), distinctly narrower than elytral base, with very slight lateral protuberance at middle, densely covered with red or orange scale-like pubescence (fading to yellow in some pinned specimens) covering most of integument, sparse punctures visible in regions with black maculae around middle and base; pronotum without dorsal calli or tubercles, about one-fifth length of body. Prosternum integument dark brown, with sparse, short, white and translucent setae. Prosternal process broadly expanded at apex, closing procoxal cavities posteriorly. Elytron with distinct punctures strongest at base, becoming shallower at middle, mostly absent at apical third, dense, scale-like red or orange pubescence (fading to yellow in some dried specimens) present in bold pattern around scutellum and in transverse, slightly posteriorly angled fascia at middle and near apex, otherwise, elytra black. Humerus strongly projecting anterolaterally, often with extreme apex glabrous. Elytral apices bidentate, with concavity between sutural and apicolateral points. Elytron 6.8-9.0 mm long; 1.5-2.1 mm wide; elytral length/width: 4.2-4.5. Scutellum broadly rounded posteriorly, densely covered in orange or red (fading to yellow). Legs with femora and tibiae sublinear, only weakly thickened apically. Metafemora short, extending to about third ventrite. Moderately dense, translucent or pale pubescence on tibiae; femora sparsely pubescent. Legs pale orange or pale testaceous throughout except meso- and metafemur, tibial apices, and apices of tarsomeres which are dark brown to black. Venter mostly densely pubescent and dark brown or yellow-orange with denser patches of reddish-orange (fading to yellow in some dried specimens) pubescence on posterolateral margins of metasternum and ventrites 2-4 or 2-5. Apex of fifth ventrite of females broadly truncate with small median notch (males unknown).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">The specific epithet is a Latin adjective, nominative case, masculine gender, meaning ringed, and refers to the pale basal annulations on most antennomeres.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="notes">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Notes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
The genus 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oedudes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oedudes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Oedudes</taxonomicName>
is now represented by 8 species in the Neotropics and this is the first record for the genus in Hispaniola. It is known from 3 specimens.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="material">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Holotype (female): Dominican Republic: Peravia Prov., 5 km W of road to El Rio, S. of Pedregal, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="19.084867">19째05.092'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-70.59773">70째35.864'W</geoCoordinate>
, 52 m, 23 June 2005, Steven W. Lingafelter (USNM). Paratypes (2 females): Dominican Republic, Pico Duarte Trail, 3300', Los Tablones - day coll., 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="19.137033">19째08.222'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-70.462265">70째27.736'W</geoCoordinate>
, 29 June 2004, D. Perez (USNM); Dominican Republic, La Vega Province, Parque Nacional Armando Bermudez, 1-3 km along trail W of La Cienaga, 900-1100 m, June 22, 2005, Specimen ID 7643, Nearns &amp; Lingafelter (ENPC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>