<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458862" ID-ISSN="1942-1354" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5458862" ID-ZooBank="C5755CDB-84E4-4685-BC33-85B923440590" approvalRequired="22" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="22" checkinTime="1630210951173" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Wappes, James E. &amp; Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2020" docId="03A38E56FFA87B08FF1228EDFBC54677" docLanguage="en" docName="0769.pdf" docOrigin="Insecta Mundi 2020 (769)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:6D85C66E4B52897F25DA165649BC06DC.1:InsectaMundi.2009-2020.journal_article" docStyleId="6D85C66E4B52897F25DA165649BC06DC" docStyleName="InsectaMundi.2009-2020.journal_article" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Rileyellus panamensis Wappes and Santos-Silva 2020, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="12" masterDocId="FF9AF62EFFA47B05FFD22A75FFD6403D" masterDocTitle="Taxonomic contributions to Neotropical Lamiinae (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae) including a new genus, five new species and a new synonym" masterLastPageNumber="21" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" updateTime="1630870235920" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-NC-3.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Taxonomic contributions to Neotropical Lamiinae (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae) including a new genus, five new species and a new synonym</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wappes, James E.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>American Coleoptera Museum 8734 Paisano Pass San Antonio, TX 78255 - 3523, USA</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Museu de Zoologia Universidade de São Paulo São Paulo, SP, Brazil</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Insecta Mundi</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2020-05-29</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2020</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>769</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>21</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458862</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1942-1354</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5458862</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">C5755CDB-84E4-4685-BC33-85B923440590</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03A38E56FFA87B08FF1228EDFBC54677" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03A38E56FFA87B08FF1228EDFBC54677" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<subSubSection box="[192,1028,664,689]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1028,664,721]" box="[192,1028,664,689]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<heading bold="true" box="[192,1028,664,689]" fontSize="10" level="2" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" reason="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,1028,664,689]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<taxonomicName authority="Wappes and Santos-Silva" authorityName="Wappes and Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2020" box="[192,851,664,689]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Rileyellus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="panamensis" status="new species">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,498,664,689]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Rileyellus panamensis</emphasis>
Wappes and Santos-Silva
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[865,1028,664,689]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1028,664,721]" box="[192,338,697,721]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
(
<figureCitation box="[201,330,697,721]" captionStart="Figures 35–38" captionStartId="22.[192,287,1405,1427]" captionTargetBox="[192,1440,213,1373]" captionTargetId="figure-40@22.[192,1440,213,1373]" captionTargetPageId="22" captionText="Figures 35–38. Rileyellus panamensis, holotype male.35) Dorsal habitus.36) Ventral habitus.37) Lateral habitus. 38) Head, frontal view." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458878" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458878/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Fig. 35–38</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[190,1441,745,1058]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,442,745,769]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Description. Male.</emphasis>
Head mostly dark brown; mouthparts reddish-brown, with palpomeres yellowishbrown (apex pale-yellow); scape and pedicel dark brown; antennomeres III–XI brown, slightly lighter toward distal segments, especially in basal area. Pronotum, sides of prothorax, and sides of prosternum dark brown to dark reddish-brown (depending on light intensity), with apex of pronotal tubercles black; remaining surface of prosternum reddish-brown, with margins of procoxae and prosternal process nearly black. Ventral surface of meso- and metathorax dark reddish-brown, with margins and metathoracic discrimen dark brown, almost black. Elytra dark reddish-brown basally, gradually nearly orangishbrown toward apex, with area of tubercles nearly black. Legs reddish-brown, with base of tibiae narrowly black. Basal abdominal ventrites dark reddish-brown and remaining segments gradually nearly orangish-brown, with anterior margin of I black, and apex of I–IV yellowish-brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[190,1442,1082,1845]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,272,1082,1106]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Head.</emphasis>
Frons finely, abundantly punctate; with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integu- ment, with minute, thick yellowish-brown seta emerging from some punctures, and a few long, erect yellowish-brown setae close to eyes. Vertex and area behind eyes with sculpturing and pubescence as on frons, including minute short seta within some punctures (pubescence sparser close to prothorax, denser close to upper eye lobes); with a few long, erect yellowish-brown setae close to upper eye lobes. Genae 0.65 times length of inner margin of lower eye lobe; finely, sparsely punctate; with yellowishbrown pubescence, sparser than on frons, with minute, thick yellowish-brown seta within punctures. Antennal segments finely, abundantly punctate (punctures finer than on frons); pubescence as on frons, with minute, thick seta emerging from basal punctures. Gulamentum glabrous close to prothorax, with yellowish-white pubescence anteriorly. Postclypeus with sculpturing and pubescence as on frons in wide central area (nearly lacking minute thick setae), smooth and glabrous laterally; with a few long, erect yellowish-brown setae on sides of wide central area. Labrum finely rugose-punctate posteriorly, finely punctate anteriorly; with long, erect, sparse pale setae. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.36 times length of scape (0.32 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.68 times length of scape (0.61 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 2.5 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex near apex of antennomere VI. Scape with yellowish-brown pubescence nearly obscuring integument (more pale-yellow depending on light intensity). Pedicel, anterior 3/4 of antennomere III, and anterior half of antennomere IV with pubescence as on scape, and posterior quarter of III and posterior half of IV with shorter, brownish pubescence not obscuring integument except apex of III with yellowish-brown pubescence (darker than in anterior area). Remaining antennomeres with narrow pale-yellow pubescent ring basally, with slightly conspicuous brownish pubescence on remaining surface. Antennomeres III–IV with a few long, erect dark setae ventrally. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.87; pedicel = 0.15; IV = 0.92; V = 0.67; VI = 0.64; VII = 0.59; VIII = 0.57; IX = 0.54; X = 0.52; XI = 0.64.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[190,1440,1870,1926]" lastBlockId="13.[190,1442,215,1219]" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,300,1870,1894]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax with small, blunt tubercle near posterolateral angles (with one long, erect dark seta emerging from each one). Transverse crest of pronotum connecting lateral tubercles of prothorax, with some tubercles on its top (tubercles flattened anteroposteriorly); with two small, blunt tubercles on each side of area between crest and posterior margin; coarsely, abundantly punctate; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, denser from anterior margin to crest, especially closer to crest, except glabrous apices of tubercles; with a minute, thick yellowish-brown seta within each puncture. Sides of prothorax with sculpturing as on pronotum; pubescence similar to pronotum (including minute setae), but denser close to posterior margin. Prosternum with sculpturing and pubescence similar to sides of prothorax (including minute setae), but punctures and pubescence sparser centrally. Prosternal process with dense yellowish-brown pubescence centrally, glabrous close to margins; narrowest area 0.27 times width of procoxa. Mesoventrite coarsely, abundantly punctate; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, distinctly denser close to mesepisternum. Mesepisternum and mesepimeron coarsely, abundantly punctate; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and minute, thick yellowish-brown seta with punctures. Metepisternum and sides of metaventrite coarsely, abundantly punctate, with yellowish-brown pubescence obscuring integument, but exposing punctures, and minute, thick yellowish-brown setae within punctures; remaining surface of metaventrite coarsely, abundantly punctate, with sparse yellowish-brown pubescence, and minute, thick yellowish-brown seta within some punctures. Scutellum with dense yellowish pubescence. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[893,987,705,729]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Elytra.</emphasis>
Humerus with short, blunt tubercle on apex; sides with some small, blunt tubercles from humerus to near apex (more distinct in anterior quarter); centrobasal crest moderately elevated, with one to two small, blunt tubercles in its anterior area, and one elevated, acute tubercle near its apex (posterior margin of this tubercle dentate); with a few small, blunt tubercles on sides of anterobasal crest; dorsal surface with arched crest about apex of anterior third (somewhat fused with the line formed by the lateral small tubercles), reaching suture, with two tubercles on top of its side (outermost more elevated and acute, innermost blunt); posterior half with two oblique, irregularly tuberculate crests, more distal slightly more distinct, but much less than that in anterior half; coarsely, abundantly punctate in anterior third, punctures sparser toward apex; apex truncate; basal area with dense yellowish-brown pubescence and a minute, thick yellowish-brown seta within each puncture; remaining surface with pale-yellow pubescence not obscuring integument, distinctly denser close to anterior margin of crests, especially that in anterior half; nearly all tubercles with long, erect dark seta emerging from them. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[753,824,1097,1121]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Legs.</emphasis>
With yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, obscuring on basal 2/3 of tibiae; tibiae with short, erect, sparse dark setae; excavated ventral area of protibia with bristly, dense brownish setae; posterior third of dorsal surface of mesotibiae with bristly, nearly golden setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[192,1440,1244,1366]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,329,1244,1268]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites coarsely, abundantly punctate (punctures gradually shallower toward V); with pale-yellow pubescence partially obscuring integument laterally, but exposing punctures; with minute, thick pale-yellow seta within each puncture; with a few long, erect pale-yellow setae interspersed. Apex of ventrite V truncate (slightly concave centrally).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[192,1441,1390,1480]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,455,1390,1415]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Dimensions in mm.</emphasis>
Total length 9.4; prothoracic length 2.2; anterior prothoracic width 1.9; posterior prothoracic width 2.3; widest prothoracic width (between apices of lateral tubercles) 3.1; humeral width 3.3; elytral length 6.7.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="12" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="13.[192,1440,1504,1561]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,399,1504,1529]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation collectingDate="1993-05-20" collectionCode="TAMU" collectorName="E. Riley" country="Panama" location="Igar" municipality="Nusagandi area" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Panama" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[410,521,1505,1529]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry box="[674,800,1505,1529]" name="Panama" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">PANAMA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis box="[816,920,1505,1528]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<collectingRegion box="[816,920,1505,1528]" country="Panama" name="Panama" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Panama</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<collectingMunicipality box="[938,1143,1505,1529]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Nusagandi area</collectingMunicipality>
, I.K.U.S.A. 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03A38E56FFA87B08FF1228EDFBC54677:8ED5699BFFA97B08FAC32F94FA9345C4" box="[1297,1349,1505,1529]" country="Panama" municipality="Nusagandi area" name="Igar" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" stateProvince="Panama">Igar</location>
(trail), 
<date box="[192,317,1537,1561]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" value="1993-05-20">
<collectingDate box="[192,317,1537,1561]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" value="1993-05-20">20.V.1993</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName box="[329,426,1537,1561]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">E. Riley</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode box="[489,578,1537,1561]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">TAMU</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[192,1043,1586,1611]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="13.[192,1043,1586,1611]" box="[192,1043,1586,1611]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,347,1586,1610]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Etymology.</emphasis>
Named for the country (
<collectingCountry box="[648,751,1586,1610]" name="Panama" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Panama</collectingCountry>
) where it was collected.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>