<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.45.5114" ID-GBIF-Dataset="393b05f8-affb-49fc-87d9-17977a454834" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152018155" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1314-2607-45-87" ID-ZBK="B074B63DC75F477988282C1DCEAD7EDD" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:75883CED-2170-4068-91D1-F5139D21B5E5" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1314-2607-45-87" ModsDocOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 45" ModsDocTitle="The genus Gyrodonta Cameron, with description of a new species and a key to species (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae)" checkinTime="1451252182183" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Sheng, Mao-Ling, Cui, Zhen-Qiang &amp; Riedel, Matthias" docDate="2015" docId="B461DE37816BDE88EB56C3DFFB21BC6A" docLanguage="en" docName="JourHymenoptRes 45: 87-95" docOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 45" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.45.5114" docTitle="Gyrodonta motuoica Sheng &amp; Riedel, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="75883CED-2170-4068-91D1-F5139D21B5E5" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="90" masterDocId="BC428744FFCAFFFEFFF070443779FFD9" masterDocTitle="The genus Gyrodonta Cameron, with description of a new species and a key to species (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae)" masterLastPageNumber="95" masterPageNumber="87" pageId="2" pageNumber="89" updateTime="1643633222799" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The genus Gyrodonta Cameron, with description of a new species and a key to species (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sheng, Mao-Ling</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cui, Zhen-Qiang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Riedel, Matthias</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of Hymenoptera Research</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>45</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>87</mods:start>
<mods:end>95</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.45.5114</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.45.5114</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1314-2607-45-87</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">B074B63DC75F477988282C1DCEAD7EDD</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B074B63DC75F477988282C1DCEAD7EDD</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152018155" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:75883CED-2170-4068-91D1-F5139D21B5E5" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B461DE37816BDE88EB56C3DFFB21BC6A" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="2" pageNumber="89">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="89" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Ichneumonidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="89" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/75883CED-2170-4068-91D1-F5139D21B5E5" authority="Sheng &amp; Riedel" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Gyrodonta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gyrodonta motuoica" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="motuoica">Gyrodonta motuoica Sheng &amp; Riedel</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="89">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1-6, 7-13
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="89" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">The specific name is derived from the type locality</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="89" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Holotype, female, collected on blacklit sheet in the night by Tao Li on 10 July 2013, China: Motuo County, 1976m, Xizang Autonomous Region.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="89" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Basal half of mandible longitudinally concave medially, with sparse, fine punctures; upper marginal tooth (Figure 3) located at center. Median longitudinal carinae of propodeum weak, incomplete, vestigial (Figure 11). Costula absent. Second tergite 1.25 times as long as apical width, with fine punctures (Figure 13). Mesosoma black, with white spots. Tergites almost entirely brownish red.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="89">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">
Figures 1-6. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Gyrodonta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gyrodonta motuoica" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="motuoica">Gyrodonta motuoica</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype. Female 1 Habitus, lateral view 2 Head, anterior view 3 Head, dorsal-anterior view 4 Head, lateral view 5 Frons 6 Antenna.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="89">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">
Figures 7-13. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Gyrodonta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gyrodonta motuoica" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="motuoica">Gyrodonta motuoica</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype. Female 7 Head and pronotum, lateral view 8 Mesoscutum 9 Mesosoma, lateral view 10 Hind tarsus 11 Propodeum 12 First tergite, lateral view 13 Tergites 1-3, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="2" pageNumber="89" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Female. Body length approximately 15.0 mm. Forewing length approximately 11.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Head. Face (Figure 2) slightly concave, with sparse, weak punctures; median portion with indistinct longitudinal wrinkles; upper margin with weak median triangular convexity; from outside of antennal socket to inner side of clypeal foveae with distinct oblique groove. Clypeus with different texture from face, shiny, irregularly longitudinally convex medially; subapical portion with sparse, indistinct, fine punctures; median section of apical margin almost truncate. Mandible large, basal half longitudinally concave medially, with sparse, fine punctures; upper marginal tooth (Figure 3) located at center. Malar area finely alutaceous; malar space approximately 0.9 times as long as basal width of mandible. Gena (Figures 4, 7) almost shiny, with distinct punctures, lower portion with indistinct wrinkles. Vertex with distinct, fine punctures. Interocellar area with distinct longitudinal groove. Postocellar line approximately 0.5 times as long as ocular-ocellar line, 0.87 times maximum diameter of posterior ocellus. Frons (Figure 5) deeply concave, with distinct transverse wrinkles; lower portion with distinct median longitudinal carina. Antenna (Figure 6) slightly longer than head and mesosoma combined, with 38 flagellomeres; apical portion of flagellum distinctly flattened below; ratio of length from first to fifth flagellomeres: 7.0:6.0:5.5:5.2:5.0. Occipital carina complete, lower end joining hypostomal carina slightly above base of mandible.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Mesosoma. Pronotum (Figure 7) with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.2-1.5 times their diameter; lateral concavity broad, almost shiny, upper-anterior portion with weak transverse oblique wrinkles, lower-posterior with short transverse wrinkles. Epomia strong. Mesoscutum (Figure 8) slightly convex, with dense, distinct punctures, distance between punctures 0.5-2.0 times their diameter. Notaulus absent. Scutoscutellar groove narrow, deep. Scutellum almost flat, shiny, with distinct, fine punctures, distance between punctures 0.5-3.0 times their diameter. Postscutellum transversely convex, with deep, small anterior-lateral pit. Mesopleuron (Figure 9) with fine punctures, upper-anterior, under subtegular ridge, and lower-posterior portions with transverse oblique wrinkles. Speculum with distinct punctures. Upper end of epicnemial carina not reaching anterior margin of mesopleuron. Metapleuron slightly convex, upper-anterior portion with distinct punctures, remainder with indistinct oblique wrinkles. Submetapleural carina complete, strong. Wings slightly brownish, hyaline. Fore wing with vein 1cu-a slightly distal to 1-M, distance between them approximately as long as width of vein. Areolet pentagonal, receiving vein 2m-cu at middle. 2-Cu approximately 2.0 times as long as 2cu-a. Hind wing with vein 1-cu about 3.3 times as long as cu-a. Anterior tibia slightly compressed, anterior profile with dense thorn-like spines. Hind femur 2.8 times as long as maximum width. Hind tarsus (Figure 10) approximately 1.3 times as long as tibia. Ratio of length of hind tarsomeres 1:2:3:4:5 is 18.5:10.6:7.8:4.7:10.1. Propodeum (Figure 11) without costula, median longitudinal carinae weak, vestigial; lateral longitudinal, pleural and apical transverse carinae complete; area posteroexterna complete; area superomedia coarse, with indistinct, fine transverse wrinkles; anterior portions of lateral areas with distinct punctures, median with weak transverse wrinkles; area petiolaris with dense transverse wrinkles; area lateralis reticulate; spiracle elongate, approximately three times as long as wide.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="89">Metasoma. First tergite approximately 3 times as long as apical width, dorsal profile of petiole with sparse punctures, lateral with indistinct longitudinal wrinkles (Figure 12). Postpetiole (Figure 13) with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.5-2.5 times their diameter; lateral and apical portions shiny, very sparsely punctate. Second tergite (Figure 13) approximately 1.25 times as long as apical width, with fine punctures, distance between punctures 1.0-3.0 times their diameter. Third tergite approximately 0.9 times as long as apical width, with fine indistinct punctures. Ovipositor sheath reaching to apex of metasoma.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="2" pageNumber="89">
Color (Figure 1). Head mainly brownish black; face and clypeus reddish brown; inner orbits irregularly, malar area, lower portion of gena, flagellomeres (apical portion of 9)10-16 white; median longitudinal portion of mandible, scape, apical ventral profile of flagellum dark brown. Mesosoma black. Dorsal anterior margin, upper margin and lower anterior corner of pronotum, longitudinal band of tegula, scutellum almost entirely, subtegular ridge, large median spot of mesopleuron, posterior lateral portion of propodeum white. Sublateral longitudinal band of mesoscutum dark brown. Femora, tibiae, main portion of anterior and mid coxae, anterior-basal spot of hind coxa, lower profiles 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="90" start="start">of</pageBreakToken>
anterior and mid trochanters brownish red. Main portions of anterior and mid coxae, dorsal profiles of trochanters, apical margin and dorsal spot of hind coxa white. Tarsus buff. Tergites brown red. Basal portion of first tergite, hind margins of fourth and subsequent tergites more or less darkish brown. Pterostigma brown. Veins brownish black.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="90" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="90">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="90">
This new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Gyrodonta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gyrodonta concava" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="concava">Gyrodonta concava</taxonomicName>
(Uchida, 1937) but can easily be distinguished from the latter by the following combination of characters: apical portion of flagellum distinctly flattened below; upper marginal tooth of mandible located at middle; propodeum without costula, median longitudinal carinae vestigial; second tergite (Figure 13) 1.25 times as long as apical width, with distinct, fine punctures. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Gyrodonta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gyrodonta concava" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="concava">Gyrodonta concava</taxonomicName>
: apical portion of flagellum cylindrical; upper marginal tooth of mandible located subbasally; propodeum with distinct costula and median longitudinal carinae; second tergite almost 1.1 times as long as apical width, finely coriaceous, without punctures.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>