<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.743.22815" ID-GBIF-Dataset="638c63db-262a-4446-9eab-dcd1d6face0c" ID-GBIF-Taxon="142283999" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-743-43" ID-ZBK="1B595A67C56F4F11BA5723A28F2E67C8" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4838F7D1-79AA-44E9-BC1E-EB3DFBF13145" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-743-43" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 743" ModsDocTitle="The family Lohmanniidae (Acari, Oribatida) II: two new Oribatid mites, Meristacarusperikopesis sp. n. from Costa Rica and Torpacaruseidikoterai sp. n. from Kenya" checkinTime="1521107533249" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Fernandez, Nestor, Theron, Pieter, Leiva, Sergio &amp; Jordaan, Anine" docDate="2018" docId="7B0EF29C35AF208E0487E04ACC851B86" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 743: 43-66" docOrigin="ZooKeys 743" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.743.22815" docTitle="Meristacarus perikopesis Fernandez, Theron, Leiva &amp; Jordaan, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="4838F7D1-79AA-44E9-BC1E-EB3DFBF13145" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="47" masterDocId="FF85FFA8FF9AFFB8C404FFA3FFE0FFDE" masterDocTitle="The family Lohmanniidae (Acari, Oribatida) II: two new Oribatid mites, Meristacarusperikopesis sp. n. from Costa Rica and Torpacaruseidikoterai sp. n. from Kenya" masterLastPageNumber="66" masterPageNumber="43" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" updateTime="1643517423549" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The family Lohmanniidae (Acari, Oribatida) II: two new Oribatid mites, Meristacarusperikopesis sp. n. from Costa Rica and Torpacaruseidikoterai sp. n. from Kenya</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fernandez, Nestor</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Theron, Pieter</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Leiva, Sergio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jordaan, Anine</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>743</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>66</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.743.22815</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.743.22815</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-743-43</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">1B595A67C56F4F11BA5723A28F2E67C8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">1B595A67C56F4F11BA5723A28F2E67C8</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="142283999" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4838F7D1-79AA-44E9-BC1E-EB3DFBF13145" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7B0EF29C35AF208E0487E04ACC851B86" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="47" pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/4838F7D1-79AA-44E9-BC1E-EB3DFBF13145" class="Arachnida" family="FAMILIA" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus perikopesis" order="ORDO" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perikopesis">Meristacarus perikopesis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="43">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1-7, 8-10, 11-13, 14-18, 19-22, 23-28
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
The specific epithet 
<taxonomicName lsidName="perikopesis" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" rank="species" species="perikopesis">perikopesis</taxonomicName>
is derived from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="perikopés">perikopes</normalizedToken>
, (Περικοπές in Greek meaning cuts in English) by the characteristic cross-cut grooves present on the cuticle.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Holotype.♀&quot;CR 0978 Tu 15 Costa Rica Turrialba foret naturelle du Catie alt.560 m. Triage 
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’humus">d'humus</normalizedToken>
pied arbre 
<normalizedToken originalValue="à">a</normalizedToken>
contreforts. 11. IX. 1978. LEG P.WERNER&quot;; material conserved in 70 % ethanol, deposited in MHNG. Paratypes. 2 ♀♀, same data and locality, deposited in MHNG; preserved in 70 % ethanol.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Diagnosis</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
(adult female). Integument. Very complex with irregular cross-shaped grooves on prodorsum and notogaster. Smooth surfaces: anterior zone prodorsum extending to rostrum; zone posterior to b.sj; subcapitulum; anterolateral zone of prodorsum; epimeral zones; genital plate; preanal plate. Pusticulate surfaces (porose areas) on prodorsum, notogaster. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Reticulate–foveate">Reticulate-foveate</normalizedToken>
: Sb, S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6, S7, S8, S9, S10 transversal bands, notogaster. Colliculate: basal subcapitulum region; areas surrounding 1a epimeral setae; v.sj; anal-adanal zone and BPDA; legs I, II, III, IV. Undulate on lateral epimeral zone. Punctate: entire prodorsum and notogaster. Sulcate: bothridial ring.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Prodorsum. Flat smooth chitinous edge, external to exa, exp, and le setae, postbothridial transverse band sb hardly discernible.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Notogaster. Sixteen pairs of primary notogastral setae: c1, c2, c3, d1, d2, d3, e1, e2, f1, f2, h1, h2, h3, p1, p2, p3;tentransversal bands: S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6, S7, S8, S9, S10. Transversal bands S4, S5, S7, S10 not crossing medial notogastral plane; prodorsal, notogastral setae barbate; adoral setae: or1 large, teardrop-shaped; or2 elongate, wide acutely terminating tip; or3 long, thin, sharply tipped.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="44" start="start">Description</pageBreakToken>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
(Adult female).Measurements 887 (876-920) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
376 (351-386) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(n: 3).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Shape. Oval (Figure 1).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Colour. Yellow to light reddish yellow; slightly shiny when observed in reflected light.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Figures 1-7. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus perikopesis" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perikopesis">Meristacarus perikopesis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Adult with cerotegumental layer. SEM micrographs. 1 dorsal view 2 dorsal prodorsal margin 3 notogastral setae, lateral view 4 cuticular microsculpture 5 sensillus, general view 6 bothridium detail 7 cuticular microsculpture, high magnification. Abbreviations: See &quot;Material and methods&quot;. Scale bars: 500 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(1); 20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(2); 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(3); 30 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(4); 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(5); 6 20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(6); 2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(7).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Cerotegument. Mostly absent, on some regions (e.g., near the bothridium (Figure 6, indicated by solid upwards arrow) observed as very thick smooth layer; on some epimeral zones and legs, gives the impression of randomly distributed dust (Figures 14, 26, indicated by white and black upwards white bar arrow). The cerotegumental layer was most probably degraded during the long period of preservation in alcohol.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Integument. Very complex. Irregular cross-shaped grooves (Figures 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 13, indicated by solid leftwards arrow) present on entire prodorsum and notogaster, as well as on pusticulate surfaces. Smooth surfaces, anterior zone of prodorsum up to rostrum (Figure 12 indicated by solid rhombus); zone posterior to b.sj (Figure 1 indicated by solid rhombus); subcapitulum (Figures 14, 19, 21 indicated by solid rhombus); anterolateral region of prodorsum (Figure 2 indicated by solid rhombus); epimeral zone (Figure 14 indicated by solid rhombus); genital plate (Figure 15 indicated by solid rhombus); preanal plate (Figure 16 indicated by solid rhombus). Pusticulate surfaces: prodorsum, notogaster, and epimeral region (Figures 1, 8, 9, 10, 12, 13 indicated by white sun with rays) (See Remarks); pustules between 7-20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
in diameter (Figure 4, pustules indicated by surrounding small squares). 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Reticulate–foveate">Reticulate-foveate</normalizedToken>
on Sb, S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6, S7, S8, S9, S10 (Figures 5, 23 indicated by outlined rightwards arrow). This microsculpture is also observed, irregularly distributed, in vicinity of pustules (Figure 4 indicated by outlined rightwards arrow) and cross-shaped grooves (Figure 7 indicated by outlined rightwards arrow). Colliculate: subcapitulum basal zone; surrounding 1a epimeral setae (Figure 18 indicated by diamond shape made up of 4 smaller black diamonds); surrounding vsj (Figure 14 indicated by diamond shape made up of 4 smaller black diamonds); adanal plate and BPDA (Figure 16 indicated by) diamond shape made up of 4 smaller black diamonds; legs I, II, III, IV (Figures 23, 25, 26, 28, indicated by diamond shape made up of 4 smaller black diamonds). Undulate: lateral epimeral zone (Figure 14 indicated by interrupted outlined arrow); punctate on prodorsum and notogaster (Figure 7 indicated by narrow dashed arrow); sulcate: bothridial ring (Figure 6).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Figures 8-10. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus perikopesis" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perikopesis">Meristacarus perikopesis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Adult, optical microscopy. 8 lateral view 9 dorsal view 10 ventral view. Scale bar: 600 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Setation (legs not included). Simple, smooth: epimeral (Figures 14, 18); subcapitular a (Figure 20); genital (Figure 15). Simple, barbed: prodorsum (Figures 12, 13), notogaster (Figure 3); subcapitular h, m1, m2 (Figure 19); adanal (Figure 17). Numerous long barbs, principally situated on one side of the seta (Figures 3, 13), sometimes on the opposite side, a few very small barbs can be observed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Prodorsum. Shape: triangular, rounded apex in dorsal view (Figures 1, 9); triangular in lateral view (Figures 8, 11); in frontal view, triangular with curved sides (Figure 12). Rostrum ovoid (Figures 12, 14); flat smooth chitinous edge present on either side of prodorsal area, externally to exa, exp, and le setae, derived from margin of lateral depression housing legs (Figures 2, 12, indicated by solid upwards arrow); region between level of rosetal insertion and rostrum, smooth, elongate, clearly delimited by flat chitinous edge (Figure 12 indicated by solid rhombus); ro setae large, length 155 (148-171) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
directing forward (Figures 1, 11, 12); le setae directing forward, length 200(196-221) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(Figure 1, 12); in setae upright, 91 (86-101) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; exa setae 201(195-228) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
; exp setae 91 (87-98) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Figures 11-13. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus perikopesis" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perikopesis">Meristacarus perikopesis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Adult with cerotegumental layer. SEM micrographs.11 lateral view 12 frontal view 13 notogastral anterior lateral view. Scale bars: 500 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(11); 400 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(12); 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(13).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Bothridium (bo) ring-shaped, rounded, with particular microsculpture slightly elevated from the cuticular surface (Figures 5, 6), opening directed upwards with slight lateral tilt. Sensillus (Si) pectinate, some pectines elevated but most slanted along main body of Si (Figures 1, 5). Si stem longitudinally sulcate (Figure 6). Postbothridial transverse band sb hardly discernible, situated posterior to bo; in setae situated on sb margin (Figures 1, 5, 11, 12).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Notogaster. Sixteen pairs of primary notogastral setae clearly discernible: c1, c2, c3, d1, d2, d3, e1, e2, f1, f2, h1, h2, h3, p1, p2, p3 (Figures 1, 8, 9, 11). Ten transversal bands: S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6, S7, S8, S9, S10 (Figures 1, 5, 8, 9, 11). S1 anterior to setae c1,c2, c3, crossing transverse medial notogastral plane (Figures 1, 8, 9, 11, 12); S2 crossing transverse medial notogastral plane, extending slightly beyond c2 setae, terminating near c3 in a large ovoid tip; S3 situated behind c setal alignment and in front of d setal alignment, crossing medial notogastral plane (Figure 11); S4 behind d1, d2 setal alignment, not crossing medial notogastral plane;S5 oblique, exceeding d1 setal insertion level, terminating in rounded end (Figures 1, 8, 9, 11), not crossing medial notogastral plane; S6 crossing medial notogastral plane, thin band surpassing e2 setal insertion level, laterally extending to unsclerotized lateral longitudinal line; S7at level f1, f2 setal insertion, not crossing medial notogastral plane, terminating near f1 setal insertion; S8 behind f2 setal level, extending obliquely to f1 setal insertion, crossing medial notogastral plane; S9 situated at h setal insertion level, crossing medial notogastral plane; S10 in front of p1 insertion level, not crossing medial notogastral plane.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Figures 14-18. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus perikopesis" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perikopesis">Meristacarus perikopesis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Adult with cerotegumental layer. SEM micrographs. 14 ventral view 15 genital zone 16 ano-adanal region 17 adanal setae 18 epimeral setae 1a. Scale bars: 500 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(14); 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(15); 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(16); 25 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(17); 30 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(18).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Five pairs of lyrifissures present: ia, ip, im, ips, ih; ips situated on adanal fold band (BPDA) (Figure 10); im near e2 setae and ih behind p3.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Lateral region. In lateral view certain transverse bands are hardly discernible, principally S8, S9, S10 (Figure 11). Flat smooth prodorsal margin present on either side of cavities housing legs I-IV when retracted. Anterior notogastral zone presenting conspicuous tectum and clearly defined unsclerotized lateral longitudinal line (Figure 8).In posterior notogastral zone, where unsclerotized line is absent, notaspis and pleuraspis not delimited (Figure 8).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Ventral region. Subcapitulum more or less triangular, posterior zone ovoid. Four pairs of subcapitular setae, a, m1, m2, h. Smooth elevated triangular structure (Figure 19 indicated by*) containing m2, m1, a setae determined by oblique line from subcapitular marginal zone to medial longitudinal plane, with h setae situated outside triangle in a depressed area (Figure 19). Cuticle smooth in central zone of this depressed area, but colliculate microsculpture observed bordering the triangular elevated zone (containing m2, m1, h setae). Adoral setae (Figures 19, 20):or1 large, teardrop-shaped; or2 elongate, wide, terminating in acute tip; or3, long and thin, sharply tipped. Coxisternal region divided into two parts by ventrosejugal groove (Figures 14, 21). Apodemes clearly visible; epimeral setal formulae 3-1-3-4 (Figure 10). Genital plate rounded, undivided, usually with ten pairs of setae, but sometimes only nine pairs (Figures 14, 15); six simple setae paraxially and three or four antiaxially. Preanal plate more or less triangular, rounded central zone (Figures 14, 15, 16).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Figures 19-22. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus perikopesis" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perikopesis">Meristacarus perikopesis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Adult female with cerotegumental layer. SEM micrographs. 19 subcapitulum 20 adoral setae 21 epimeral zone 22 rostrum and anterior zone of chelicera and palp. Scale bars: 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(19); 40 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(20); 200 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(21); 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(22).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Adanal plate with four pairs of setae (Figure 16); setae with very small barbs (Figure 17). Band BPAD clearly visible; lyrifissure ips present near margin of this band (Figure 10).</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
Legs. Two types of femora can be distinguished. Femora legs I and II displaying large ventral blade (Figure 14), femora legs III and IV with poorly developed ventral 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="45" start="start">blade</pageBreakToken>
. Setae u laterally flattened on all legs (Figures 23, 24, 25, 26, 27), with flap housing s setae on claw (Figure 27 indicated by Solid upwards arrow). Famulus spur-shaped (Figure 28), setal formulae I (0-4-2-2-16-1) (2-1-2); II (0-5-4-4-15-1) (1-1-1); III (2-4-3-4-13-1) (1-1-0); IV (2-3-2-3-13-1(1-0-0).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="47" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="46" start="start">Remarks</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="47" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
The porose area indicated by 
<bibRefCitation author="Grandjean, F" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin de la Societe zoologique de France" pageId="7" pageNumber="50" pagination="12 - 44" title="La notation des poils gastronotiques et des poils dorsaux du propodosoma chez les Oribates (Acariens)." volume="59" year="1934">Grandjean 1934</bibRefCitation>
: 37 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“…">&quot;...</normalizedToken>
et par sesairesporeuses au nombre de plusieurscentaines, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="répartiessurtoute">repartiessurtoute</normalizedToken>
la surface du corps&quot; describing 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus porcula" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="porcula">Meristacarus porcula</taxonomicName>
, is referred to as pusticulate cuticular microsculpture (diameter of pustules between 20-7μm) in this paper. These structures were studied using optical microscopy in order to confirm their similarity to the description given by 
<bibRefCitation author="Alberti, G" editor="Mitchell, R" journalOrPublisher="Ohio Biological Survey Columbus, Ohio, vol" pageId="6" pageNumber="49" pagination="277 - 283" title="Porose areas and related organs in oribatid mites (Oribatida)." volume="1" volumeTitle="Acarology IX. Proceedings of the 9 th International Congress of Acarology." year="1996">Alberti et al. 1996</bibRefCitation>
: 280 &quot; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="47" start="start">In</pageBreakToken>
lohmanniid mites numerous distinct porose areas may be seen in certain taxa (e.g. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Meristacarus</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Mixacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mixacarus" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Mixacarus</taxonomicName>
)&quot;. In 1997 
<bibRefCitation pageId="4" pageNumber="47">Alberti et al. 1997</bibRefCitation>
: 58-63: indicated: &quot;In light microscopy they appear as distinct patches of higher transparency and show the fine striation perpendicular to the surface, that is typical of porose areas (Fig. 29)&quot; and referred to SEM studies: &quot;This similarity is also evident with SEM (Fig. 30 A) the porose areas are not visible from the exterior but very shallow depressions indicate sometimes their location&quot;.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
Our results are markedly different to 
<bibRefCitation pageId="4" pageNumber="47">Alberti et al. 1997</bibRefCitation>
(Fig. 30A) as, although the porose areas and/or shallow depressions are not visible under SEM, well-defined pustules are clearly discernible. Also, the irregular cross-shaped grooves differ from those described by 
<bibRefCitation author="Alberti, G" editor="Mitchell, R" journalOrPublisher="Ohio Biological Survey Columbus, Ohio, vol" pageId="6" pageNumber="49" pagination="277 - 283" title="Porose areas and related organs in oribatid mites (Oribatida)." volume="1" volumeTitle="Acarology IX. Proceedings of the 9 th International Congress of Acarology." year="1996">Alberti et al. 1996</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation pageId="4" pageNumber="47">1997</bibRefCitation>
, where reference was made to pores, for example 
<bibRefCitation author="Alberti, G" editor="Mitchell, R" journalOrPublisher="Ohio Biological Survey Columbus, Ohio, vol" pageId="6" pageNumber="49" pagination="277 - 283" title="Porose areas and related organs in oribatid mites (Oribatida)." volume="1" volumeTitle="Acarology IX. Proceedings of the 9 th International Congress of Acarology." year="1996">Alberti et al. 1996</bibRefCitation>
: 281, indicates, with reference to function &quot;Such a glandular function is certain in the typical porose areas (octotaxic system, areas of part of the prosoma) in the medio dorsal porose areas of Acrogalumna males and the numerous areas of 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Mixacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mixacarus" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Mixacarus</taxonomicName>
&quot; and &quot;The latter two types are remarkable in being innervated. The secretions pass through the inner layers of the epicuticle (no open pores) and are presumably lipids&quot; and later: &quot;This statement can now be modified in such a way that organs with one or another functions -respiration on the one hand or secretory on the other hand
<normalizedToken originalValue="…”">...&quot;</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
Figures 23-28. 
<taxonomicName class="Arachnida" family="Lohmanniidae" genus="Meristacarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Meristacarus perikopesis" order="Sarcoptiformes" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="perikopesis">Meristacarus perikopesis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Adult female with cerotegumental layer. SEM micrographs. 23 leg IV paraxial view 24 leg II paraxial view 25 leg III 26 apical zone, leg II 27 ventral apical zone, leg II 28 tarsus I, famulus and solenidion zone. Scale bars: 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(23-25); 20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(26); 5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(27, 28).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>