<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744" ID-GBIF-Dataset="dce6ec3b-3df0-419f-955d-e877c8f32fa6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152048808" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-343-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:026F8151-FE51-47F0-9E4D-9D67E3D1274D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-343-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 343" ModsDocTitle="A systematic revision of Baconia Lewis (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Exosternini)" checkinTime="1451246799544" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Caterino, Michael S. &amp; Tishechkin, Alexey K." docDate="2013" docId="F7F7B97BF07C65556F0467E3BB4043F6" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 343: 1-297" docOrigin="ZooKeys 343" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744" docTitle="Baconia maquipucunae Caterino &amp; Tishechkin, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="026F8151-FE51-47F0-9E4D-9D67E3D1274D" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="198" lastPageNumber="199" masterDocId="FFCEFFE1717FD230FF94FFCEFF9CE450" masterDocTitle="A systematic revision of Baconia Lewis (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Exosternini)" masterLastPageNumber="297" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="197" pageNumber="198" updateTime="1643701416415" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A systematic revision of Baconia Lewis (Coleoptera, Histeridae, Exosternini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Caterino, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tishechkin, Alexey K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>343</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>297</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.343.5744</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-343-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">541A802C-21F2-4A14-9428-F5F46FFE4760</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152048808" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:026F8151-FE51-47F0-9E4D-9D67E3D1274D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F7F7B97BF07C65556F0467E3BB4043F6" lastPageId="198" lastPageNumber="199" pageId="197" pageNumber="198">
<subSubSection pageId="197" pageNumber="198" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="197" pageNumber="198">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/026F8151-FE51-47F0-9E4D-9D67E3D1274D" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Baconia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Baconia maquipucunae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="197" pageNumber="198" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maquipucunae">Baconia maquipucunae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="197" pageNumber="198">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 54H55C, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="K–LMap">K-LMap</normalizedToken>
17
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="197" pageNumber="198" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="197" pageNumber="198">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="197" pageNumber="198">
ECUADOR: Pichincha: Maquipucuna Forest Reserve [
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="555" value="0.05">0.05°N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="555" value="-78.68">78.68°W</geoCoordinate>
].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="197" pageNumber="198" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="197" pageNumber="198">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="197" pageNumber="198">Holotype male: &quot;ECUADOR:Pichincha Maquipucuna For. Res. 50 km NW Quito, 1660 m 21 Dec. 1991, C.Carlton R.Leschen #22, ex:FIT&quot; / &quot;SEMC0903647 KUNHM-ENT&quot; (SEMC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="198" lastPageNumber="199" pageId="197" pageNumber="198" type="diagnostic description">
<paragraph pageId="197" pageNumber="198">Diagnostic description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="198" lastPageNumber="199" pageId="197" pageNumber="198">
Length: 1.7mm, width: 1.6mm; body slightly elongate, rounded, convex, especially elytra, glabrous; color rufescent, shining; head with frons slightly elevated over antennal bases, weakly depressed at middle, ground punctation fine, inconspicuous, with coarser punctures at middle and along dorsal margin, frontal and supraorbital striae absent; antennal scape short, club slightly oblong; epistoma truncate; labrum about 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×wider">xwider</normalizedToken>
than long, apical margin emarginate; mandibles short, right mandible with small, acute basal tooth; pronotum with sides convergent in basal two-thirds, rounded to apex, lateral marginal stria descending to ventral edge of pronotal margin one-third from apex, extending around anterior corner, detached from median part of anterior marginal stria, which diverges from margin behind eye, lateral submarginal stria present in basal three-fourths, very close to marginal stria, pronotal disk narrowly but strongly depressed in anterolateral corners, ground punctation inconspicuous, middle of disk impunctate, with small secondary punctures only in anterolateral corners; elytral humeri prominent, elytra more strongly convex than pronotum, with two epipleural striae, outer and inner subhumeral striae absent, dorsal striae 1-5 restricted to basal half of elytra, 4th stria strongly arched toward scutellum at base, 5th stria very short, sutural stria impressed along about middle one-fourth of suture, elytral disk with small secondary punctures sparsely scattered in apical one-third; venter markedly convex, prosternal keel ascending anterad, distinctly emarginate at base, with carinal striae weakly converging anterad, obsolete in anterior one-third; prosternal lobe about two-thirds keel length, apical margin rounded, deflexed, marginal stria obsolete at sides, both prosternal lobe and keel densely punctate at sides; mesoventrite produced at middle, with marginal stria narrowly interrupted; mesometaventral stria transverse, weakly crenulate, continuous laterally with inner lateral metaventral stria, which extends obliquely posterad toward inner third of metacoxa, outer lateral metaventral stria absent; metaventral disk densely punctate at sides, with numerous small punctures in front of metacoxa; abdominal ventrite 1 with single abbreviated lateral stria, with small median discal punctures sparsely scattered in anterior two-thirds, ventrites 2-5 with fine punctures, those of ventrite 4 moderately dense across middle; protibia narrow, lacking denticles along margin, with apical denticle only, margin very finely serrulate; meso- and metatibial margins smooth, lacking marginal spines; propygidium lacking basal stria, with fine ground punctation uniformly interspersed with small, ocellate secondary punctures, propygidial gland openings inconspicuous; pygidium with fine ground punctation only in apical two-thirds, with small secondary 
<pageBreakToken pageId="198" pageNumber="199" start="start">punctures</pageBreakToken>
principally in basal one-third. Male genitalia (Figs 55C, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="K–L">K-L</normalizedToken>
): T8 as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Baconia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Baconia gibbifer" order="Coleoptera" pageId="198" pageNumber="199" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gibbifer">Baconia gibbifer</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 55A); S8 short, basal emargination broad and deep, sides rounded, apices subtruncate, lateral thirds well-sclerotized and bearing short fringe of setae, inner corners weakly produced, middle third subacutely emarginate; T9 as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Baconia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Baconia piluliformis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="198" pageNumber="199" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="piluliformis">Baconia piluliformis</taxonomicName>
(Fig. 55E), but bearing 2-3 inconspicuous subapical setae; S9 stem narrow, strongly dorsoventrally keeled, head gradually widened to apex, apical emargination shallow and sinuate; tegmen rather narrow, sides subparallel in basal half, strongly narrowed to apex, thick, more or less evenly curving ventrad over entire length, with eversible subapical denticles ventrally; median lobe simple, about one-third tegmen length; basal piece one-third tegmen length.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="198" pageNumber="199" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="198" pageNumber="199">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="198" pageNumber="199">This species may be separated from others in the group by the presence of a short fragment of the 5th elytral stria, the rather strongly narrowed pronotum which is strongly depressed in the anterior corners, the weakly produced frontal corners, the broad prosternal keel (Fig. 54H), and the strongly convex metaventrite.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="198" pageNumber="199" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="198" pageNumber="199">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="198" pageNumber="199">This species named for its type locality, the Maquipucuna Forest Reserve, on the high western slopes of the Ecuadorian Andes.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>