<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2f6b7408-685c-4ad6-aac4-7e42b84abbc7" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152036066" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-202-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-202-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 202" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the Afrotropical Oberthuerellinae (Cynipoidea, Liopteridae)" checkinTime="1451248949478" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Buffington, Matthew L. &amp; Noort, Simon van" docDate="2012" docId="D288E8E82E5725B35AB2B5E54D8B78A6" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 202: 1-154" docOrigin="ZooKeys 202" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136" docTitle="Oberthuerella lenticularis Saussure" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" masterDocId="FFA0FFA1FFCFFF87602FB655FF993C24" masterDocTitle="Revision of the Afrotropical Oberthuerellinae (Cynipoidea, Liopteridae)" masterLastPageNumber="154" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" updateTime="1643539830100" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the Afrotropical Oberthuerellinae (Cynipoidea, Liopteridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Buffington, Matthew L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Noort, Simon van</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>202</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>154</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-202-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">4E2F5872-37BF-4ECB-8518-29E40735F4B3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152036066" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:D288E8E82E5725B35AB2B5E54D8B78A6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D288E8E82E5725B35AB2B5E54D8B78A6" lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<subSubSection pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:181556" authority="Saussure" authorityName="Saussure" class="Hexapoda" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis Saussure</taxonomicName>
Figures 17-18
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
Saussure, 1890: plate 20; fig. 8. Redescription by 
<bibRefCitation author="Kieffer, J-J" journalOrPublisher="Entomologisk Tidskrift" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" pagination="107 - 110" title="Beitriige zur Kenntnis der Insektenfauna von Kamerun. N: 026. Beschreibung einer neuer Cynipide aus Kamerun." volume="25" year="1904">Kieffer (1904)</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Coloration of head and mesosoma, black to dark brown; metasoma and legs yellow-orange. Sculpture on vertex, lateral surface of pronotum and mesoscutum present, deeply foveate laterally on head, pronotum; deeply horizontally striate on mesoscutum.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="36" lastPageNumber="37" pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Head. Broadly triangular, in anterior view. Pubescence on head present, sparse setae scattered over head. Sculpture along lateral margin of occiput many costulae. Gena (measured from compound eye to posterolateral margin of head) short, ratio of length of gena to length of compound eye in dorsal view &lt;0.3, in dorsal view. Sculpture of gena present, gently striate. Lateral margin of occiput defined by distinctly angled, raised, sharp carina. Occiput (except extreme lateral margin) smooth. Ocelli small, ratio of maximum diameter of a lateral ocellus to shortest distance between lateral ocelli 0.2-0.4. Anterior ocellus close to posterior ocelli, posterior margin of anterior ocellus behind or subcontig 
<pageBreakToken pageId="35" pageNumber="36" start="start">uous</pageBreakToken>
with a transverse line running through anterior margins of posterior ocelli. Relative position of toruli close to ocelli, ratio of vertical distance between inner margin of torulus and ventral margin of clypeus to vertical distance between anterior ocellus and torulus &lt;2.0. Median keel of face present, short, not extending beyond toruli. Vertical carina adjacent to ventral margin of torulus absent. Facial sculpture present, punctate-rugose, transversely striate; striations meeting at midline of face. Facial impression absent, face flat. Antennal scrobe absent. Anterior tentorial pits large. Vertical delineations on lower face absent. Ventral clypeal margin laterally, close to anterior mandibular articulation, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="36" pageNumber="37" start="start">distinctly</pageBreakToken>
angled. Ventral clypeal margin medially emarginate. Clypeus foveate-punctate. Malar space adjacent to anterior articulation of mandible evenly rounded, striate. Malar sulcus absent. Compound eye close to posterior ocellus, ratio of distance between compound eye and posterior mandibular articulation to distance between posterior ocellus and compound eye&gt; 1.2. Compound eye, in dorsal view, distinctly protruding from the surface of the head, particularly laterally. Pubescence on compound eye absent. Orbital furrows absent. Lateral frontal carina of face absent. Dorsal aspect of vertex deeply foveate. Posterior aspect of vertex smooth. Hair punctures on lateral aspect of vertex absent. Posterior surface of head almost flat, not deeply impressed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">Labial-maxillary complex. Apical segment of maxillary palp with pubescence, consisting only of erect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="36" pageNumber="37">Antenna. Articulation between flagellomeres in antenna connate with articles broadly joined. Female antenna composed of 11 flagellomeres. Female F1 shorter than F2; black. Flagellomeres of female antenna cylindrical, not widened towards apex, non-clavate. Placoidal sensilla absent. Distal flagellomeres of female antenna not conspicuously enlarged compared to proximal flagellomeres.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="37" lastPageNumber="38" pageId="36" pageNumber="37">
Pronotum. Macrosculpture on lateral surface of pronotum present, foveate. Pubescence on lateral surface of pronotum absent. Anterior flange of pronotal plate distinctly protrud 
<pageBreakToken pageId="37" pageNumber="38" start="start">ing</pageBreakToken>
anteriorly, centrally smooth, longitudinally striate laterally. Carinae extending posteriorly from lateral margin of pronotal plate absent. Lateral pronotal carina present. Pronotal crest absent. Dorsal margin of pronotal plate (in anterior view) rounded. Submedian pronotal depressions closed laterally, deep. Lateral margin of pronotal plate defined all the way to the dorsal margin of the pronotum. Pronotal plate wide, almost as wide as head.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Mesoscutum. Mesoscutal surface convex, evenly curved. Sculpture on mesoscutum present, foveate-punctate, with remnants of transverse costae. Notaulus present, marked by series of deep subcontiguous pits of uniform width. Median mesoscutal carina absent. Anterior admedial lines present, with adjacent cuticular surface foveate. Median mesoscutal impression present, medium in length, reaching 1/4 length of mesoscutum. Parascutal carina distinctly sinuate, posteriorly ending in posteroventrally directed projection.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">Mesopleuron. Dorsally irregularly horizontally costate with occasional fovea, ventrally smooth. Subpleuron entirely smooth with long, white setae on ventral half. Lower mesopleuron medially smooth, glabrous; costate laterally, ventrally. Epicnemial carina present, running from mesoscutum to anterior margin of mesopleural carina, ventrally bulbous. Lateroventral mesopleural carina present, marking abrupt change of slope of mesopectus. Mesopleural triangle absent. Subalar pit large and well defined, lying in posterior end of subalar groove. Speculum present, distinctly reticulate. Mesopleural carina present, incomplete, composed of one straight carina indicated anteriorly, otherwise smooth. Anterior end of mesopleural carina inserting above notch in anterior margin of mesopleuron.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
Scutellum. Dorsal surface of scutellum foveate-areolate. Circumscutellar carina absent. Posterior margin of axillula marked by distinct ledge, axillula distinctly impressed adjacent to ledge. Lateroventral margin of scutellum posterior to auricula entirely smooth. Dorsoposterior part of scutellum produced posteriorly into sharp spine, greater than 1.0
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of petiole. Dorsal part of scutellum entirely rugose. Scutellar plate absent. Scutellar foveae present, two, each with two longitudinal divisions resulting in transverse row of 6 longitudinally elongate subfovea. Longitudinal scutellar carinae absent. Single longitudinal carina separating scutellar foveae present, long, continuing posteriorly to scutellar spine. Lateral bar smooth, narrow.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="38" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="37" pageNumber="38">
Metapectal-propodeal complex. Metapectal cavity anterodorsal to metacoxal base present, ill-defined. Anterior margin of metapectal-propodeal complex separated from mesopleuron by deep, broad, uninterrupted marginal impression. Posteroventral corner of metapleuron (in lateral view) rounded, not drawn out posteriorly. Anterior impression of metepimeron present, narrow, linear impression, not broadened ventrally. Posterior margin of metepimeron distinct, separating metepimeron from propodeum. Subalar area slightly broadened anteriorly, with distinct laterally protruding lobe ventrally. Calyptra present, blunt, lobe-like, polished posteriorly with setiferous punctures anteriorly. Dorsellum present, smooth, glabrous. Anterior impression of metepisternum, immediately beneath anterior end of metapleural carina, present, small and narrow. Pubescence consisting of few scattered hairs on posterior part of metapleuron and lateral part of propodeum. Propodeal spurs present, crenulate. Lateral propodeal carinae present, not reaching scutellum. Ventral end of lateral propodeal carina termina 
<pageBreakToken pageId="38" pageNumber="39" start="start">ting</pageBreakToken>
before reaching nucha. Inter propodeal carinae space glabrous, costulate. Petiolar foramen removed from metacoxae, directed posteriorly. Horizontal carina running anteriorly from lateral propodeal carina absent. Lateral propodeal carina curved distally. Calyptra, in lateral view, elongate. Propodeum relatively short, not drawn out posteriorly. Calyptra, in posterior view, dorsoventrally elongate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Legs. Pubescence posterolaterally on metacoxa sparse to moderately dense, confined dense hair patch absent. Microsculpture on hind coxa absent. Longitudinal carina on the posterior surface of metatibia absent. Metafemoral spine present, elongate, extending distally as low keel along ventral femoral margin. Distal mesotibial spurs shorter than medial spurs. Distal metatibial spurs shorter than medial spurs. Ratio of first metatibial segment to remaining 4 segments greater than 1.0. Pubescence on outer surface of metatarsal claw sparse, consisting of few setae. Outer surface of metatarsal claw entirely smooth. Apical seta of metatarsal claw positioned on outer surface below dorsal margin. Base of metatarsal claw weakly expanded, apex slightly bent, ratio width of base to length of apex &lt;0.6.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Forewing. Pubescence of forewing present, sparse across entire wing surface. Apical margin of female forewing rounded. Rs+M of forewing tubular. Mesal end of Rs+M vein situated closer to posterior margin of forewing, directed towards posterior end of basalis. Vein R1 tubular along at least basal part of anterior margin of marginal cell. Basal abscissa of R1 (the abscissa between 2r and the forewing margin) of forewing as broad as adjacent wing veins. Forewing entirely lightly infuscate. Marginal cell of forewing membranous, similar to other wing cells. Areolet present, incomplete, open posteriorly. Hair fringe along apical margin of forewing present, very short.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
Petiole. Slightly elongate, 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2×">-2x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide. Surface of petiole longitudinally costate, ventral keel absent. Posterior part of female petiole not abruptly widened. Ventral flange of annulus of female petiole absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Metasoma. Setal band (hairy ring) at base of tergum 3 absent, base of metasoma glabrous. Tergum 3 distinctly smaller than tergum 4. Posterior margin of tergum 3 smoothly rounded. Posterior margin of tergum 4 arcuate. In lateral view, sternum 3 exposed, ventral border of T2-T7 visible. Sculpture on metasomal terga present, dorsally finely punctate, posteriorly with distinct bands of setiferous pits. Syntergum absent, all postpetiolar terga free. Annulus absent. Peg-like setae on T6-T7 present. Posteroventral cavities of female metasoma T7 present, glabrous save for few, long setae. Female posteroventral margin of T6-T7 distinctly sinuate. Terebrum and hypopygium (in lateral view) straight, pointing posteriorly.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Ovipositor. First valvula of ovipositor narrowing gradually, not broadened apically, serrate at tip. Ovipositor clip absent.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
Figure 17. 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
Saussure A lateral habitus B habitus, dorsal view C head and mesosoma, lateral view D mesosoma, dorsal view E head and pronotum, lateral view F meso- and metapleurae.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
Figure 18. 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
Saussure A scutellum, dorsal view B head, anterior view C head and pronotum, lateral view D posterior margin or metasoma, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
Distinguished from other species of 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Oberthuerella</taxonomicName>
by the extremely short vertical keel on the face, not extending beyond the toruli; this feature is also shared with 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella triformis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="triformis">Oberthuerella triformis</taxonomicName>
, but in this latter species, the scutellar spine is remarkably short, whereas in 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
, the scutellar spine is roughly equal in length to the petiole. Finally, the pronotal and mesoscutal sculpture in 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
is deeply foveate, so much so that the general appearance of this species is craggy.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="note">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Note.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
This name was originally published as an image with an associated name in a larger volume on Madagascar (Saussure, 1890). Article 12.2.7 of IZCN (2000) stipulates the image of 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
satisfies indication of a new genus and species, even though no description nor holotype was provided. Thus, the genus and species names are available, and the illustration of 
<bibRefCitation pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Saussure (1890)</bibRefCitation>
serves as the holotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Ivory Coast, Madagascar, Malawi, South Africa. Link to Distribution Map. [http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=181556]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="38" pageNumber="39" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="38" pageNumber="39">
Other material: (4 females) AFRICA: no date, J. Wahlberg (1 female, MCZC 0011 (MCZC). IVORY COAST: Adiopodoume [
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="5.341111">05°20'28&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-4.1316667">04°07'54&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
], 8.6.49, H.B Jover (1 female, MNHN).MADAGASCAR: Toamasina Auto. Prov., Rogez, XI-1931, A. Seyrig (1 female, USNM ENT 00764775 (USNM); Region du Sud-Est, Vallee du Fanjahira Isaka, [
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-24.911667">24°54'42&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="46.88556">046°53'08&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
], Ch. Alluaud, Dec 1901, 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
Sauss. Det Weld 1931; 
<taxonomicName authority="Saussure, 1890" authorityName="Saussure" authorityYear="1890" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Oberthuerella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oberthuerella lenticularis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="38" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lenticularis">Oberthuerella lenticularis</taxonomicName>
S. Female, det J. Quinlan, 1978 (1 female MNHN). (Further material listed in Quinlan, 1979)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>