<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6294105" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3fc50716-3f1c-4903-b672-28bcaeaee724" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125136343" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6294105" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6AF3936F-B1C9-4A72-8217-1E10B08F4565" checkinTime="1439764468610" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Goode, G. B. &amp; Bean, T. H." docDate="1883" docId="2B29870481F2BB235193A99025287FEA" docLanguage="en" docName="goode_Bean_1883_188042100200024991.htm.xml" docOrigin="Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard College 10 (5)" docTitle="Prionotus alatus Goode &amp; Bean, 1883, new species" docType="treatment" docUuid="6AF3936F-B1C9-4A72-8217-1E10B08F4565" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="8" lastPageNumber="211" masterDocId="5B7296A6F34C923B9F5FBB9D7E3D1B3E" masterDocTitle="Reports on the results of dredging under the supervision of Alexander Agassiz, on the east coast of the United States, during the summer of 1880, by the U. S. coast survey steamer “ Blake, ” Commander J. R. Bartlett, U. S. N., commanding." masterLastPageNumber="226" masterPageNumber="183" pageNumber="210" updateTime="1645849994371" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Reports on the results of dredging under the supervision of Alexander Agassiz, on the east coast of the United States, during the summer of 1880, by the U. S. coast survey steamer “ Blake, ” Commander J. R. Bartlett, U. S. N., commanding.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Goode, G. B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bean, T. H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard College</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1883</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>10</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>5</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>183</mods:start>
<mods:end>226</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.28095</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">3283BFE8-BAA3-437C-90F2-B33A8DF5125E</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6294105" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125136343" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6294105" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6AF3936F-B1C9-4A72-8217-1E10B08F4565" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2B29870481F2BB235193A99025287FEA" lastPageNumber="211" pageNumber="210">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="210" type="mainText">
<pageBreakToken pageId="27" pageNumber="210" start="start">26</pageBreakToken>
. 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Triglidae" genus="Prionotus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Scorpaeniformes" pageId="27" pageNumber="210" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="alatus" status="new species">Prionotus alatus</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="210" type="mainText">
A single specimen of a 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
of 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Triglidae" genus="Prionotus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Scorpaeniformes" pageId="27" pageNumber="210" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Prionotus</taxonomicName>
was obtained off Charleston,
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="210" type="mainText">
S. C., in the same haul with the pleuronectoid described above under the name 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Pleuronectidae" genus="Notosema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Pleuronectiformes" pageId="27" pageNumber="210" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="dilecta">Notosema dilecta</taxonomicName>
. This species belongs to the group referred by Jordan to the subgenus Ornichthys of Swainson.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="210" type="mainText">
Description.-A 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Triglidae" genus="Prionotus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Scorpaeniformes" pageId="27" pageNumber="210" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Prionotus</taxonomicName>
with the body normal in form, rather robust: its greatest height equal to one fourth its length without caudal, and nearly equal to one tilth of the total length; its greatest width one fifth of its greatest length without caudal; the least height of tail contained twelve times, or nearly so, in the standard body length, and three times in the height of the body.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="210" type="mainText">Scales small and much pectinate, there being in the lateral line about one hundred vertical rows of scales, about fifty of which are tube-bearing and specialized. The number of rows, counting diagonally around the body from the origin of the anal, is twenty-one below and seven above the lateral line. The length of the head to the tip of the preopercular spine is contained two and a half times in the standard body length, and very little more than three times in the total length. The width of the head is equal to its height. The upper limb of the orbit encroaches upon the upper profile of the head, and the centre of the pupil is equidistant from the tip of the snout and the tip of the prolonged preopercular spine. The length of the snout, measured obliquely from the anterior margin of the orbit, is equal to that of the postorbital portion of the head to the end of the opercular spine. At the. lower angle of the preoperculum is a robust spine, curving slightly upwards, the length of which is equal to that of the first dorsal ray. This spine is serrated upon its outer edge, and has a small spine at its base, which is also serrated. The tip of the spine extends to the perpendicular from the centre of the interspace between the third and fourth dorsal spines; while that of the humeral spine extends to the perpendicular from the interspace between the fourth and fifth, and that of the opercular, to the perpendicular from the centre of the base of the third. There is a strong scapular spine, which extends back to the posterior edge of the second dorsal spine.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="210" type="mainText">The length of the upper jaw is equal to one third that of the head. The palatine teeth are in short feeble bands, hardly perceptible even with a strong maimifyincc-glass. Gill rakers, six in number, besides several rudimentary ones, five being below tlie angle, and the longest equal in length to one third the diameter of the eye.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="27" pageNumber="210" type="mainText">The first, dorsal fin is inserted above the tip of the upper opercular spine, and at a distance from the snout equal to twice the length of the fourth dorsal spine. The height of the first dorsal spine, which is equal to that of the third, and slightly less than that of the second, equals half the length ol the head.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">
<pageBreakToken pageId="28" pageNumber="211" start="start">Its</pageBreakToken>
anterior margin is strongly serrated, while those of the second and third spines are less markedly so. The length of base of first dorsal equals the greatest height of body: the distance between its insertion and that of the second dorsal fin is equal to the length of the longest and superior detached pectoral ray. The second dorsal fin is inserted in the perpendicular over the interspace between the second and third anal rays: the length of its longest ray equals twice the least height of tail, and the length of its base equals the greatest length of the ventral rays. Its first ray is conspicuously serrated on its anterior edge.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">The insertion of the anal fin is in the perpendicular below the end of the first dorsal fin: the length of its longest ray is equal to half that of the middle caudal rays.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">The caudal is truncated, very slightly emarginate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">The pectoral is very peculiar in structure, its longest ray, the 9th, reaching to the base of the caudal rays, and equal in length to four times that of the fourth dorsal spine. The 10th ray is a little bit shorter, extending nearly to the end of the soft dorsal. The 11th, 12th, and 13th rays are graduated, decreasing in regular proportion, the 13th being less than one fourth as long as the 10th. The 8th is about midway between the 10th and lltli: the 1st is slightly longer than the 12th, and those intermediate between the 1st and the 8th are graduated in length, so as to form a rounded outline lor the anterior, or upper, portion of the fin. The pectoral appendages are slender, the third being slightly greater in length than the 13th ray, being two thirds as long, as the first, while the second is intermediate between the other two.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">The ventral is inserted directly under the base t)f the pectoral appendages: its first spine about equal in length to the preopercular spine from the base of the supplemental spines; its longest, the third and fourth, exactly equal in length to the base of the second dorsal.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">Color, brownish above, with about four indistinct transverse band-like blotches, one of which is on the base of the caudal; whitish beneath. Vertical tins uniform, the tips of the caudal rays blackish, with two indistinct cloud-like bands in advance of the terminal band thus formed. A black blotch, with whitish anterior margin on the membrane between the fourth and fifth dorsal spines; a very inconspicuous blackish spot on the membrane between the lilth and sixth; others still less conspicuous on the succeeding interspaces. The pectoral blotched and clouded with blackish brown and white.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">Radial formula: D. X, 12; A. 11; C. 3 - 7 + 5 - 4; P. 13 -f 3; V. I, 5.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="mainText">L. lat. about 100. Tube-bearing scales, about 50.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="28" pageNumber="211" type="table">
<table border="1" pageId="28" pageNumber="211">
<tr pageId="28" pageNumber="211">
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">Station.</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">N. Lat.</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">W. Long.</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">Fathoms.</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">Specimen.</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="28" pageNumber="211">
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">313</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">32° 31' 00&quot;</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">78° 40'</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">75</td>
<td pageId="28" pageNumber="211">1</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>