<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.669.12608" ID-GBIF-Dataset="dbfccdc4-e5a8-42d2-a706-cfa0062ebe65" ID-GBIF-Taxon="128687981" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-669-29" ID-ZBK="7BC01A4ED22C44B38D2DA0DF2CD53AA4" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-669-29" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 669" ModsDocTitle="Taxonomic revision of the endemic Bornean genera Anexodus Pascoe and Pantilema Aurivillius (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)" checkinTime="1492772871763" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gabris, Radim, Trnka, Filip, Wahab, Rodzay Abdul &amp; Kundrata, Robin" docDate="2017" docId="D46BA4839B340A468ACF234B27CBC30C" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 669: 29-51" docOrigin="ZooKeys 669" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.669.12608" docTitle="Pantilema Aurivillius 1911" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageNumber="33" masterDocId="BD7AE331C048FFACFF95FFF3FFF6FFFF" masterDocTitle="Taxonomic revision of the endemic Bornean genera Anexodus Pascoe and Pantilema Aurivillius (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="51" masterPageNumber="29" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" updateTime="1643478963743" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Taxonomic revision of the endemic Bornean genera Anexodus Pascoe and Pantilema Aurivillius (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gabris, Radim</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Trnka, Filip</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wahab, Rodzay Abdul</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kundrata, Robin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>669</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>29</mods:start>
<mods:end>51</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.669.12608</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.669.12608</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-669-29</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">7BC01A4ED22C44B38D2DA0DF2CD53AA4</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">7BC01A4ED22C44B38D2DA0DF2CD53AA4</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="128687981" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:D46BA4839B340A468ACF234B27CBC30C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D46BA4839B340A468ACF234B27CBC30C" lastPageNumber="33" pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="33" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
Genus 
<taxonomicName authority="Aurivillius, 1911" authorityName="Aurivillius" authorityYear="1911" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pantilema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pantilema" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pantilema Aurivillius, 1911</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="33" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pantilema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pantilema" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pantilema</taxonomicName>
Aurivillius, 1911: 196.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="33" type="type species">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">Type species.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pantilema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pantilema angustum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="angustum">Pantilema angustum</taxonomicName>
Aurivillius, 1911.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="33" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pantilema" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pantilema" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pantilema</taxonomicName>
differs from the remaining Bornean 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" rank="tribe" tribe="Morimopsini">Morimopsini</taxonomicName>
by having a slender, narrow, parallel-sided body (body length/width ratio = 3.5), tibial spurs 1-1-2, truncate elytral apex, and tubercles only in the apical half of the elytra (Figs 35-36).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="33" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">Body slender, elongate, densely clothed with very short pubescence; coloration brown, with some parts paler, yellowish, antennae and legs reddish-brown (Figs 35-36).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">Head about the same width as anterior margin of pronotum; genae convex at frontal view; frontoclypeus with distinct midline running from interantennal groove to labrum, sparsely punctured; antennal tubercles prominent with narrow, deep depression in between; antennal cavities opened dorsally; anterior margin of anteclypeus shallowly emarginate, with sparse long yellowish semi-erect setae. Labrum free, transverse, glabrous, with a row of distinct punctures and sparsely and irregularly distributed additional less distinct punctures, with sparse long semi-erect setae (Fig. 38). Eyes small, distinctly elongate vertically, narrow, about four times as long as wide, slightly emarginate at antennal insertions, lower parts distinctly narrower than genae (Fig. 36). Antennae filiform, 11-segmented, shorter than body; scape and first half of pedicel covered with very short dense light brown pubescence; the rest of antenna with much sparser pubescence; scape enlarged, swollen, reaching the first half of pronotum, subparallel-sided, apically slightly widened, pedicel short, apical antennomere simple, less than two times as long as penultimate antennomere (Fig. 37). Mandibles short and broad, apex unidentate (Fig. 38). Maxillary palpi tetramerous, apical palpomere fusiform. Labial palpi trimerous, apical palpomere of same shape as maxillary one.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">Prothorax about as long as wide, subparallel-sided at anterior half, widest slightly medially, then gradually narrowed towards posterior margin, laterally with one very weakly developed tubercle; pronotal disc weakly convex, sparsely covered with deep punctures, not smooth, without tubercles (Fig. 38), anterior and posterior angles obtuse. Prosternum in front of coxae slightly shorter than diameter of coxal cavity, procoxal cavities circular, with lateral extension, narrowly separated. Scutellum transverse, subtriangular, about three times as wide as long. Elytra elongate, twice as long as wide at widest part, basally as wide as posterior pronotal margin, without distinct humeral bulges, widest near middle, fused along the elytral suture, apically truncate; with tubercles present only at apical third of elytra; tubercles arranged in two rows, apical tubercles forming large transverse irregularly shaped bulge (Fig. 35), elytra sparsely covered with large deep punctures arranged in slightly irregular rows; outer elytral margin distinctly curved at lateral view (Fig. 36). Mesoventrite with anterior edge on different plane than metaventrite; mesocoxal cavities circular, separated slightly wider than in procoxal cavities. Metaventrite transverse, more than two times as wide as long. Metacoxal cavities extending laterally to meet elytra. Hind wings absent. Legs long, slender; femora weakly swollen distally, tibial spurs 1-1-2, protibiae with pubescent groove (antennal cleaner) on inner face, mesotibiae with pubescent groove on outer face, metatibiae without groove; tarsal formula 4-4-4, last tarsomere with four long erected setae at ventral face, claws simple, empodium absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="33">Abdomen with five visible ventrites, first ventrite (excluding intercoxal process) almost 1.5 times longer than second; intercoxal process subparallel-sided basally, narrowed and broadly rounded apically. Fifth ventrite with apex truncate, margin with sparse semi-erect pubescence. Male genitalia with tegmen elongate, widest at apical third, basally with long strut; parameres moderately long, setose apically. Penis relatively long, with dorsal struts diverged from about two fifths of penis length (Fig. 39). Internal sac long, with paired medial sclerites and distinct complex of flagellar sclerites.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>