<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047613" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C0B96CD8-566E-4683-AE35-E1E9F1366348" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="49B6439FE3A766C038A50044AD2CDB47" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio foliorum Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="C0B96CD8-566E-4683-AE35-E1E9F1366348" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="87" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047613" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C0B96CD8-566E-4683-AE35-E1E9F1366348" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/49B6439FE3A766C038A50044AD2CDB47" lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/C0B96CD8-566E-4683-AE35-E1E9F1366348" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio foliorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="foliorum">Oxyscelio foliorum Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="83" pageNumber="84">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 113-118; Morphbank49
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="85" lastPageNumber="86" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Female. Body length 4.6 mm (n=1).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Radicle color and shade: same as scape, both yellowish or reddish. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: as long as broad. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, complete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="85" lastPageNumber="86" pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: with a series of arched carinae, posterodorsal corner with weak longitudinal rugae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: transversely rugose; umbilicate punctate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: 
<pageBreakToken pageId="84" pageNumber="85" start="start">umbilicate</pageBreakToken>
foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: punctate. Mesoscutellar rim: expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching base of T5. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metaso 
<pageBreakToken pageId="85" pageNumber="86" start="start">mal</pageBreakToken>
depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="85" pageNumber="86">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: present. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: present as slightly protruding sharp corners. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: present as strongly protruding acuminate flanges. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate; longitudinally striate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: with medially truncate emargination, sloping down to apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: present, broad and elongate, with slight lateral incisions near midlength. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: present, posteriorly complete. S6 apex in relation to T6: exposed to dorsal view by T6 emargination. S6 apex: truncate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="85" pageNumber="86">Male. Body length 4.1 mm (n=1). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: punctate. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching apex of T5. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: obscured by other raised sculpture. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: present as strongly protruding acuminate flanges. T6 metasomal flanges: present as strongly protruding acuminate flanges. T7: M-shaped, with a triangular median emargination.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="85" pageNumber="86">
<paragraph pageId="85" pageNumber="86">
Figures 113-118. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio foliorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="85" pageNumber="86" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="foliorum">Oxyscelio foliorum</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 376702) 113 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 114 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 115 Head, anterior view 116 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 376701) 117 Antenna 118 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank49
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="85" pageNumber="86" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="85" pageNumber="86">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="85" pageNumber="86">
Both sexes: Frontal depression deep, all carinae complete medially, carinae present above dorsal separator; submedian carina very strong. Hyperoccipital carina absent. Occipital carina complete, medially weakly convex. Mesoscutal midlobe with strong transverse carinae. Mesoscutellar rim expanded and strongly sculptured, without median notch. Metascutellum pentagonal and shovel-like, projecting dorsally. Coxa darker than rest of leg. Postmarginal vein absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4, A5 broader than long. T4 with small sharp metasomal flanges. T5, T6 with elongate, flat and sharp metasomal flanges. T6 broadly and deeply emarginate, truncate or roundly concave medially. S6 exposed to dorsal view, truncate apically. Male: A3, A11 longer than broad; A4 slightly broader than long. Mesoscutellum and mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly with small foveae, mesoscutellum without smooth area medially. T5, T6 with long sharp metasomal flanges. T7 with flat sharp metasomal flanges, deeply emarginate medially, posterior margin deeply M-shaped. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio foliorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="foliorum">
<pageBreakToken pageId="86" pageNumber="87" start="start">Oxyscelio</pageBreakToken>
foliorum
</taxonomicName>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio limbi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limbi">Oxyscelio limbi</taxonomicName>
in several ways, but differs in the short and flat metasoma with elongate, leaf-like metasomal flanges.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“leaves.”">&quot;leaves.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307079]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="associations">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">Associations.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
On flower of 
<taxonomicName authority="Spreng., 1825" authorityName="Spreng." authorityYear="1825" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sapindaceae" genus="Heterodendron" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Heterodendron oleifolium" order="Sapindales" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="oleifolium">Heterodendron oleifolium</taxonomicName>
Desf.: [
<taxonomicName genus="Sapindales" lsidName="Sapindales" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" rank="genus">Sapindales</taxonomicName>
: 
<taxonomicName genus="Sapindaceae" lsidName="Sapindaceae" pageId="86" pageNumber="87" rank="genus">Sapindaceae</taxonomicName>
]
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="86" pageNumber="87" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: SA, nr. Ikara (Wilpena Pound) Valley, Edeowie Homestead, 29.X.1972, H. E. Evans, OSUC 376702 (deposited in MCZC). Paratype: AUSTRALIA: 1 male, OSUC 376701 (MCZC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>