<document ID-ISSN="0003-0090" approvalRequired="213" approvalRequired_for_originalDoi="1" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="5" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="205" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630256240807" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Forero, D." docDate="2008" docId="6F44420725EBFF338913FC0FFE531881" docLanguage="en" docName="B312.pdf" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 2008 (312)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:2B34016C1EBFE58B07368F9517618743.1:BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type1" docStyleId="2B34016C1EBFE58B07368F9517618743" docStyleName="BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type1" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Origonema Forero 2008, gen. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageId="141" lastPageNumber="142" masterDocId="937D3A7F2561FFBE881AFF9DFFA81B4E" masterDocTitle="Revision And Phylogenetic Analysis Of The Hadronema Group (Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini), With Descriptions Of New Genera And New Species, And Comments On The Neotropical Genus Tupimiris" masterLastPageNumber="172" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" updateTime="1630256273215" updateUser="felipe" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision And Phylogenetic Analysis Of The Hadronema Group (Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini), With Descriptions Of New Genera And New Species, And Comments On The Neotropical Genus Tupimiris</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Forero, D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2008</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2008-06-06</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2008</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>312</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>172</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0003-0090</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6F44420725EBFF338913FC0FFE531881" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6F44420725EBFF338913FC0FFE531881" lastPageId="141" lastPageNumber="142" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<subSubSection box="[265,516,914,935]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="138.[265,516,914,935]" box="[265,516,914,935]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<heading box="[265,516,914,935]" centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" reason="2">
<taxonomicName authority="Forero, 2008" authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[265,391,914,935]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus" status="gen. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[265,391,914,935]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[408,516,914,935]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" rank="genus">gen. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[128,651,959,979]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="138.[128,651,959,979]" box="[128,651,959,979]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<typeStatus box="[128,181,960,979]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Type</typeStatus>
species: 
<taxonomicName authority="Gibson, 1918" authorityName="Gibson" authorityYear="1918" box="[274,646,959,979]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="species" species="splendida">
<emphasis box="[274,495,959,979]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Hadronema splendida</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Gibson, E. H." box="[503,646,959,978]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" pagination="81 - 85" refId="ref127168" refString="Gibson, E. H. 1918. The genus Hadronema Uhl. (Miridae, Heteroptera). Canadian Entomologist 50: 81 - 85." type="journal article" year="1918">Gibson, 1918</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="138" pageNumber="139" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="138.[128,654,1002,1759]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">DIAGNOSIS: Recognized by the dark bristlelike setae on dorsum (figs. 3, 42D); the gray dorsum with dark brown spots at the base of the bristlelike setae (fig. 3); the subtle subbasal expansion on the ventral surface of mesotibia of males (fig. 42F, arrow); the vesica with two lateral spicules, the left one with two subapical rami (fig. 43); the long, narrow, capitate dorsal lobes of the interramal sclerites in the females (fig. 44); and the weakly corrugated interramal sclerites (fig. 44).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="138.[128,654,1002,1759]" lastBlockId="138.[701,1228,213,1759]" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[157,283,1357,1378]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[157,283,1357,1378]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is most similar to 
<taxonomicName box="[519,653,1356,1379]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[519,653,1356,1379]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
due to the dark erect bristlelike setae on dorsum, and shape of head and thorax. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[128,254,1445,1466]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[128,254,1445,1466]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from it by the structure of the right paramere with an enlarged apex (fig. 43) and a medial flange projecting ventrad (fig. 43), the front femora of the males nearly cylindrical, without any tubercles on its ventral surface, and the first tarsal segment of the foreleg cylindrical. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[128,254,1650,1671]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[128,254,1650,1671]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
females can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName box="[128,262,1678,1701]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[128,262,1678,1701]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the narrower and longer dorsal lobes of the interramal sclerites with a capitate apex (fig. 44), and by the mem- branous anterior wall (fig. 44). 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[1101,1227,213,234]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1101,1227,213,234]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
females may be confused with 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Uhler" authorityYear="1894" box="[1087,1227,241,264]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="species" species="decorata">
<emphasis box="[1087,1227,241,264]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">D. decorata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
due to the overall hemelytral coloration, but can be distinguished from it by the orange femora (fig. 3), which are black in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Uhler" authorityYear="1894" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="species" species="decorata">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">D. decorata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[814,940,360,381]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[814,940,360,381]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
can be further separated from all the remaining genera of the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
group by the structure of the male genitalia, the subbasal expansion on the ventral surface of the mesotibia in the males, and by the weakly sclerotized sigmoid process, corrugated interramal sclerites, and capitate dorsal lobes of the interramal sclerites in the females.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="140" lastPageNumber="141" pageId="138" pageNumber="139" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="138.[701,1228,213,1759]" lastBlockId="140.[701,1228,213,1759]" lastPageId="140" lastPageNumber="141" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">
DESCRIPTION: 
<emphasis box="[908,978,623,646]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="139">Male:</emphasis>
Medium-sized, total length 2.87–3.19. COLORATION: Gray dorsum with white, orange, and black markings (fig. 3). SURFACE AND VESTI- TURE: Surface dull, densely beset with microtrichia; dark erect bristlelike setae on dorsum (fig. 42D). STRUCTURE: HEAD (fig. 42A): Transverse, declivent, ovate in lateral view; clypeus not prominent, basally protruding, barely visible in dorsal view, with a medial longitudinal area of irregular shiny spots, and apically with sparse bristlelike setae; frons convex; vertex almost flat, weakly convex, vertex and frons with sparse bristlelike setae; transverse carina elevated, strongly impressed, with a row of bristlelike setae; mandibular and maxillary plates occupying about half the height of the head, apices weakly rounded, almost truncate; gena with a row of simple setae extending from behind eyes to middle of buccula; gula short; eyes oval in lateral view, weakly projecting laterally in dorsal view, adjacent to anterior margin of pronotum; buccula not produced laterally, with a few simple setae; labrum as long as buccula, apex acute; labium surpassing mesocoxa, almost reaching metacoxa, segments I–II with very short setae, other segments glabrous, segment I dull, II–IV shiny; antennal segment I weakly greater in diameter than II, III weakly lesser in diameter than II, III and IV subequal in diameter, segment II barely longer than III, about three times as long as I, I and IV subequal in length. THORAX: Collar narrow, flat; pronotum trapezoidal, almost bellshaped, lateral margins sinuate, posterior margin straight, anterior angles broadly rounded, posterior angles rounded and oblique, surface gently inclined, posterior lobe weakly rugose; mesoscutum usually covered by posterior margin of pronotum; scutellum nearly equilateral, apex rounded, disc flat, weakly rounded toward lateral margins; pleural area with sparse simple setae; metepisternum densely covered with macrotrichia; metathoracic scent-gland evaporatory area extremely reduced, composed of a few evaporatory units visible only in lateral view; peritreme greatly enlarged (fig. 42B). 
<emphasis box="[792,923,1736,1759]" italics="true" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">Hemelytra:</emphasis>
Nearly parallel; clavus weakly elevated with respect to corium; corium weakly deflexed laterally from medial fracture; cuneus weakly longer than wide, not deflected; membrane about half as long as hemelytron. 
<emphasis box="[279,343,331,352]" italics="true" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">Legs:</emphasis>
Coxae elongate, procoxa with medium-sized length simple setae on anterior surface; trochanters ovoid, with sparse simple setae longer than trochanter width; pro- and mesofemur about the same length, metafemur barely longer; femora basally enlarged, gently narrowing distally, weakly compressed anteroposteriorly; profemur with bristlelike setae ventrally on proximal half; mesofemur with numerous delicate long simple setae on ventral surface; metafemur with short simple setae; tibiae straight; protibia weakly greater in diameter than mesotibia, subequal in length to mesotibia, protibia with dense short simple setae on distal half of ventral surface, also with a few long bristlelike setae; mesotibia with a subtle subbasal ventral expansion covered with dense short bristlelike setae, with a few longer bristlelike setae on remaining ventral surface (fig. 42F); metatibia uniformly covered with short simple setae and sparse longer bristlelike setae; tarsi cylindrical, first tarsomere subequal to second, third the longest; first tarsomere of pro- and mesotarsus densely covered with small simple setae; pretarsi as in figure 42C. ABDOMEN: Sternites covered with short and long simple setae. GENITALIA (fig. 43): Genital capsule subtriangular in dorsal view; aperture big, inclined, weakly turned to the left, anterior margin weakly sclerotized; right ventrolateral projection weakly produced, barely surpassing apex of cuplike sclerite, apex rounded; proctiger reaching posterior margin of genital capsule (fig. 42E); cuplike sclerite not reaching posterior margin of genital capsule, right portion more produced posteriorly and more elevated than left portion, bases barely surpassing supragenital bridge anteriorly; supragenital bridge narrow, located above insertions of parameres; insertion of right paramere above of left one relative to horizontal plane (fig. 42E); left paramere sickle-shaped, apicoventral process blunt; right paramere hatchet-shaped in medial view, body largely elongate, small dorsal medially directed process blunt, weakly denticulate, apex of paramere broadly rounded, weakly produced cephalad, paramere with an medioventral flange; phallotheca cylindrical, without protuberances on surface, not forming a completely sclerotized tube, only dorsal and ventrodistal portions well sclerotized, ventroproximal portion weakly so, opening large, almost reaching phallobase, reclined, oval, directed to the left; vesica composed of two separate sclerotized spicules, left and right; left spicule enlarged apically, apex rounded, with two preapical cephalad projections (rami) inserted next to each other, both rami expanded apically and denticulate, not reaching apex of right spicule; right spicule about half as long as left, strongly curving upward on apical half, apex flat, denticulate, weakly curved to the left over the base of the left spicule, and apically weakly denticulate; sclerotized part of ductus seminis long, about as long as right spicule, located at base of insertion of spicules.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="139" pageNumber="140" startId="139.[116,155,1459,1478]" targetBox="[96,1189,210,1428]" targetPageId="139">
<paragraph blockId="139.[93,1194,1458,1531]" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">
Fig. 42. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" baseAuthorityName="Gibson" baseAuthorityYear="2008" box="[218,431,1458,1479]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="139" pageNumber="140" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="splendida">
<emphasis box="[218,431,1458,1479]" italics="true" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">Origonema splendida</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[443,461,1459,1478]" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">A</emphasis>
. Head, lateral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[672,688,1459,1478]" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">B</emphasis>
. Mesepimeron and metepisternum. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1060,1078,1459,1478]" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">C</emphasis>
. Pretarsus. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[93,112,1486,1505]" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">D</emphasis>
. Vestiture on hemelytron. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[409,425,1486,1505]" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">E</emphasis>
. Genital capsule, posterior view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[795,810,1486,1505]" pageId="139" pageNumber="140">F</emphasis>
. Middle leg, male; arrow indicates subbasal enlargement.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="140.[701,1228,213,1759]" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">
<emphasis box="[731,822,828,851]" italics="true" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">Female:</emphasis>
Similar to male but more ovoid, total length 3.19–3.48. COLORATION: Similar to male (fig. 3). SURFACE AND VESTITURE: As in male. STRUCTURE: THORAX: 
<emphasis box="[822,886,946,967]" italics="true" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">Legs:</emphasis>
Coxae with short simple setae; tibiae with uniform short simple setae. GENITALIA (fig. 44): Subgenital plate triangular, longer than wide, apex roundly acute, reaching middle of sternite VIII; base of ovipositor located at longitudinal midpoint of abdomen; interramal sclerites oblong, well sclerotized, surface nearly rugulose; dorsal lobes of interramal sclerites long, narrow, with nearly parallel margins, capitate, apex nearly rounded with a few microtrichia; sigmoid process and dorsal margin of interramal sclerite covered with sparse microtrichia, sigmoid process weakly sclerotized; medial process neither distinct nor sclerotized; dorsal labiate plate without any sclerotized or modified structures; sclerotized rings well sclerotized, long, subquadrangular, nearly parallel-sided, medial posterior projection greatly enlarged caudad, lateral margin broad, recurved, and well sclerotized; accessory sclerite narrow, acute; ventral labiate plate without any conspicuous modifications or folds; inner margins of first gonapophyses symmetrical; anterior wall simple, membranous.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="140" pageNumber="141" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="140.[701,1228,213,1759]" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">
DISTRIBUTION: From central 
<collectingRegion box="[1078,1227,1708,1730]" country="United States of America" name="New Mexico" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">New Mexico</collectingRegion>
(
<collectingCountry box="[709,770,1737,1759]" name="United States of America" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">USA</collectingCountry>
) to northern 
<collectingCountry box="[932,1019,1737,1759]" name="Mexico" pageId="140" pageNumber="141">Mexico</collectingCountry>
(fig. 41).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="141" pageNumber="142" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="141.[93,620,211,975]" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
HOST ASSOCIATIONS: Host-plant data for this taxon are scanty. Apparently 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[493,619,243,264]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[493,619,243,264]" italics="true" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is associated with 
<taxonomicName box="[329,442,272,294]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="family">Fabaceae</taxonomicName>
, which agrees with observations on other members of the 
<taxonomicName box="[93,227,330,353]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[93,227,330,353]" italics="true" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
group.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="141" pageNumber="142" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="141.[93,620,211,975]" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
ETYMOLOGY: 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[294,421,362,383]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[294,421,362,383]" italics="true" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is formed from the Latin ‘‘origo’’, origin, and ‘‘nema’’, an arbitrary combination of letters from part of the name ‘‘ 
<taxonomicName box="[228,362,449,472]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[228,362,449,472]" italics="true" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
’’; gender is feminine. The name alludes to the apparently simplified external morphology of the 
<typeStatus box="[425,475,509,530]" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">type</typeStatus>
species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="141" pageNumber="142" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="141.[93,620,211,975]" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">
DISCUSSION: 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" baseAuthorityName="Gibson" baseAuthorityYear="2008" box="[296,551,539,562]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="splendida">
<emphasis box="[296,551,539,562]" italics="true" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Origonema splendida</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
was included by 
<bibRefCitation author="Gibson, E. H." box="[251,425,569,591]" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" pagination="81 - 85" refId="ref127168" refString="Gibson, E. H. 1918. The genus Hadronema Uhl. (Miridae, Heteroptera). Canadian Entomologist 50: 81 - 85." type="journal article" year="1918">Gibson (1918)</bibRefCitation>
in 
<taxonomicName box="[478,612,568,591]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[478,612,568,591]" italics="true" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, and although it externally resembles that genus mainly due to its vestiture and head structure, it does not share any of the synapomorphies of 
<taxonomicName box="[329,463,686,709]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="141" pageNumber="142" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[329,463,686,709]" italics="true" pageId="141" pageNumber="142">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(see ‘‘Phylogenetic Analysis’’ below). Among the most relevant differences are the membranous simple anterior wall; the weakly corrugated interramal sclerites of the female (fig. 44); the nearly cylindrical profemur without ventral tubercles of males; cylindrical first tarsomere of the protarsus of males; and the right spicule of the vesica lateral respect to the left, with strongly curved apex (fig. 43).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>