<document ID-ISSN="0003-0090" approvalRequired="213" approvalRequired_for_originalDoi="1" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="5" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="205" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630256240807" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Forero, D." docDate="2008" docId="6F444207255FFFFF8B4DFC4CFD061DC0" docLanguage="en" docName="B312.pdf" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 2008 (312)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:2B34016C1EBFE58B07368F9517618743.1:BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type1" docStyleId="2B34016C1EBFE58B07368F9517618743" docStyleName="BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type1" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Daleapidea Knight" docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="66" masterDocId="937D3A7F2561FFBE881AFF9DFFA81B4E" masterDocTitle="Revision And Phylogenetic Analysis Of The Hadronema Group (Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini), With Descriptions Of New Genera And New Species, And Comments On The Neotropical Genus Tupimiris" masterLastPageNumber="172" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" updateTime="1630256273215" updateUser="felipe" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision And Phylogenetic Analysis Of The Hadronema Group (Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini), With Descriptions Of New Genera And New Species, And Comments On The Neotropical Genus Tupimiris</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Forero, D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2008</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2008-06-06</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2008</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>312</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>172</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0003-0090</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6F444207255FFFFF8B4DFC4CFD061DC0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6F444207255FFFFF8B4DFC4CFD061DC0" lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="66" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<subSubSection box="[855,1074,977,1000]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="62.[855,1074,977,1000]" box="[855,1074,977,1000]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<heading box="[855,1074,977,1000]" centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" reason="2">
<taxonomicName authority="Knight" authorityName="Knight" box="[855,1074,977,1000]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[855,983,977,1000]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Daleapidea</emphasis>
Knight
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="62.[701,1228,1022,1150]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<typeStatus box="[701,754,1023,1042]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Type</typeStatus>
species: 
<taxonomicName authority="Knight, 1968" authorityName="Knight" authorityYear="1968" box="[850,1185,1022,1042]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="daleae">
<emphasis box="[850,1037,1022,1042]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Daleapidea daleae</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Knight, H. H." box="[1046,1185,1023,1042]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" pagination="1 - 282" refId="ref128169" refString="Knight, H. H. 1968. Taxonomic review: Miridae of the Nevada test site and the western United States. Brigham Young University Science Bulletin Biological Series 9 (3): 1 - 282." type="journal article" year="1968">Knight, 1968</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
(by original designation).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="62.[701,1228,1022,1150]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<treatmentCitationGroup pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<treatmentCitation author="Knight, H. H." box="[701,1010,1076,1096]" page="101" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" year="1968">
<taxonomicName authority="Knight, 1968: 101" authorityName="Knight" authorityPageNumber="101" authorityYear="1968" box="[701,1010,1076,1096]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[701,815,1076,1096]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Daleapidea</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Knight, H. H." box="[823,1010,1077,1096]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" pagination="1 - 282" refId="ref128169" refString="Knight, H. H. 1968. Taxonomic review: Miridae of the Nevada test site and the western United States. Brigham Young University Science Bulletin Biological Series 9 (3): 1 - 282." type="journal article" year="1968">Knight, 1968: 101</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
</treatmentCitation>
[n. gen.]; 
<treatmentCitation author="Henry, T. J. &amp; A. G. Wheeler, Jr." page="407" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" year="1988">
<bibRefCitation author="Henry, T. J. &amp; A. G. Wheeler, Jr." pageId="62" pageNumber="63" refId="ref127468" refString="Henry, T. J., and A. G. Wheeler, Jr. 1988. Family Miridae Hahn, 1833 (5 Capsidae Burmeister, 1835) .. In T. J. Henry and R. C. Froeschner (editors), Catalog of the Heteroptera, or True bugs of Canada and the continental United States: 251 - 507. Leiden: E. J. Brill." type="book" year="1988">Henry and Wheeler, 1988: 407</bibRefCitation>
</treatmentCitation>
[catalog]; 
<treatmentCitation author="Schuh, R. T." box="[1045,1227,1104,1123]" page="159" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" year="1989">
<bibRefCitation author="Schuh, R. T." box="[1045,1227,1104,1123]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" pagination="159 - 166" refId="ref129356" refString="Schuh, R. T. 1989. Review of Daleapidea Knight (Heteroptera: Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini). Journal of the New York Entomological Society 97 (2): 159 - 166." type="journal article" year="1989">Schuh, 1989: 159</bibRefCitation>
</treatmentCitation>
[revision]; 
<treatmentCitation author="Schuh, R. T." box="[837,1017,1131,1150]" page="102" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" year="1995">
<bibRefCitation author="Schuh, R. T." box="[837,1017,1131,1150]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" refId="ref129394" refString="Schuh, R. T. 1995. Plant bugs of the world (Insecta: Heteroptera: Miridae). Systematic catalog: distributions, host list, and bibliography. New York: New York Entomological Society, 1329 pp." type="book" year="1995">Schuh, 1995: 102</bibRefCitation>
</treatmentCitation>
[catalog].
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="62.[701,1228,1173,1759]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">DIAGNOSIS: Recognized by the elongate genital capsule (figs. 20F, 21); the basally enlarged first antennal segments of male (figs. 2, 20A); and the apically enlarged and ventrally flattened front tibiae laterally beset with enlarged setae (fig. 20C).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="62.[701,1228,1173,1759]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
<taxonomicName box="[731,859,1352,1375]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[731,859,1352,1375]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Daleapidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is easily distinguished from other members of the 
<taxonomicName box="[973,1107,1382,1405]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[973,1107,1382,1405]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
group by the enlarged genital capsule and the particular modifications on the fore tibia. Other members of the 
<taxonomicName box="[900,1034,1470,1493]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[900,1034,1470,1493]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
group have the genital capsule subquadrangular or subtriangular but never elongate, and the fore tibia is mostly cylindrical and never expanded apically. 
<taxonomicName box="[782,910,1588,1611]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[782,910,1588,1611]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Daleapidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
females are difficult to identify without associated males, as they might resemble females of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[1040,1166,1648,1669]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1040,1166,1648,1669]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, but coloration alone can help sort them out.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="66" pageId="62" pageNumber="63" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="62.[701,1228,1173,1759]" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">
REDESCRIPTION: 
<emphasis box="[941,1011,1707,1730]" italics="true" pageId="62" pageNumber="63">Male:</emphasis>
Robust, medium to moderately large species, total length 3.78–
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="63" pageNumber="64" startId="63.[116,155,1470,1489]" targetBox="[94,1192,211,1439]" targetPageId="63">
<paragraph blockId="63.[93,1193,1469,1542]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
Fig. 20. 
<taxonomicName box="[222,410,1469,1489]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="63" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="daleae">
<emphasis box="[222,410,1469,1489]" italics="true" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">Daleapidea daleae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[426,444,1469,1488]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">A</emphasis>
. Head, lateral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[671,687,1470,1489]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">B</emphasis>
. Mesepimeron and metepisternum. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1073,1091,1469,1488]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">C</emphasis>
. Foreleg, with inset of detailed expanded apical tibia, male. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[633,652,1496,1515]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">D</emphasis>
. Vestiture on hemelytron. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[941,957,1496,1515]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">E</emphasis>
. Pretarsus. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1085,1100,1496,1515]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">F</emphasis>
. Genital capsule in posterior view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="63.[93,619,1589,1759]" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">4.59. COLORATION: Black or dark orange, with gray, orange, and pale markings (fig. 2). SURFACE AND VESTITURE: Surface dull, smooth, beset with microtrichia; simple short or very short decumbent setae on dorsum (fig. 20D). STRUCTURE: HEAD</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="63.[667,1194,1589,1759]" lastBlockId="65.[93,620,213,1759]" lastPageId="65" lastPageNumber="66" pageId="63" pageNumber="64">
(fig. 20A): Transverse, declivent, ovoid in lateral view, dull or shiny, scattered setae on surface; clypeus protruding basally, almost vertical; frons convex; vertex weakly convex, posterior margin not raised; mandibular and maxillary plates occupying half of height of head, rounded at apex; gena with scattered short simple setae; gula barely shorter than buccula; buccula sometimes laterally expanded, with short or long setae, dense or not; eyes large, ovate, in dorsal view close to the anterior margin of pronotum; labrum subequal or shorter than buccula, narrow, acute apically; labium almost or reaching mesocoxa, II more densely setose than other segments; antennal segment I enlarged subbasally, at least twice as wide as II, II the longest, sometimes apex flattened, expanded, and covered with dense short setae, III shorter than II, and similar in diameter as II, IV the shortest and smallest in diameter. THORAX: Collar short, flattened; pronotum trapezoidal, weakly convex, not strongly inclined, anterior angles rounded, posterior angles oblique, broadly rounded, calli not distinct, not elevated, with scattered shiny spots, posterior lobe weakly rugose; mesoscutum usually hidden by pronotum; scutellum triangular, nearly equilateral, barely elevated, disc flat or weakly convex with anterior margin weakly concave; pleural area with scattered setae; proepisternum beset with long setae or nearly glabrous, sometimes weakly protruding laterally; metepisternum with macrotrichia, sometimes densely covered; metepisternal scent-gland evaporatory area from present to absent, if present, dorsal margin almost rounded and posteriorly weakly triangular, not reaching level of dorsal portion of metacoxae; peritreme from normally developed to absent (fig. 20B), if present, rounded, weakly protruding; prosternum glabrous. 
<emphasis box="[335,465,1267,1290]" italics="true" pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Hemelytra:</emphasis>
Nearly parallel, weakly sinuate before cuneus, as long as abdomen; clavus weakly elevated respect to corium; corium deflexed laterally from medial fracture; cuneus not deflexed, barely longer than wide; membrane about half as long as hemelytron. 
<emphasis box="[384,448,1445,1466]" italics="true" pageId="64" pageNumber="65">Legs:</emphasis>
Coxae elongate, nearly cylindrical, beset with sparse or dense short setae; trochanters globose, with short, sparse or dense setae; profemur weakly compressed anteroposteriorly, barely greater in diameter basally, about as long as mesofemur, ventral surface with very short setae, sometimes covered with setae as long as width of femur; mesofemur similar to profemur, less enlarged basally; metafemur wider than pro- and mesofemur, enlarged basally, weakly curved posteriorly in dorsal view, sometimes ventrally weakly excavated and curved ventrally but not posteriorly, and beset apically with numerous setae as long as femoral width; protibia cylindrical, wider than mesotibia, distal half weakly curved inward, apex with a ventral flat expanded area laterally covered densely or not with short, enlarged setae, medially weakly excavated (fig. 20C); mesotibia of subequal length as protibia, but narrow, straight; metatibia as thick as mesotibia, longer than pro- and mesotibia; first tarsal segment the shortest, third the longest, sometimes mesotarsus laterally with numerous long delicate setae; pretarsus as in figure 20E. ABDOMEN: Sternites with very short sparse setae, sometimes with denser and longer setae; segments III–VI barely keeled medially, sometimes area flat. GENITALIA: Genital capsule elongated, approximately twice as long as wide; aperture inclined, small and ovate, curved to the left, anterior margin strongly sclerotized; ventrolateral right projection narrow or wide, truncate or rounded; proctiger surpassing apex of genital capsule; cuplike sclerite not surpassing ventrolateral projection, bases delicate, long, not reaching anterior margin of aperture, right and left portions subequal in length, right portion narrow, left one wider, weakly elevated; supragenital bridge thick, heavily sclerotized, located above insertions of parameres; insertion of right paramere weakly above left; left paramere sickle-shaped, apicoventral process blunt or acute, sometimes dorsal medial surface projecting as a long dorsal lobe bearing apically stout setae, and sometimes apex of paramere with a flattened truncate dorsad projection (fig. 21); right paramere hatchet-shaped in medial view, body elongated, small or medium-sized tubercle on dorsal angle projecting medially, apically blunt or acute, apex of paramere broadly rounded with a cephalad projected margin, or more rounded, or narrow; phallotheca almost cylindrical, without any protuberances on surface, well sclerotized on dorsal and ventrodistal surfaces, weakly so on basal third, opening long, ovate elongate, directed to the left, inclined, more than half as long as phallotheca (fig. 21); vesica with two well-sclerotized spicules, left and right, located at base of sclerotized piece of ductus seminis; left spicule gradually enlarged apically, apically rounded without denticles, with two projections (rami), apical and preapical, directed cephalad, expanded distally, variously denticulate; right spicule about half as long as left one, enlarged basally, constricted at middle, narrowing distally, variously denticulate at apex, strongly or gently curved upward, and weakly directed to the left; sclerotized part of ductus seminis long, about as long as left spicule.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[93,620,213,1759]" lastBlockId="65.[667,1193,212,1377]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<emphasis box="[122,213,565,588]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Female:</emphasis>
Similar to male, but wider and larger, total length 4.22–4.81. COLORA- TION: Similar to male (fig. 2). SURFACE AND VESTITURE: As in male. STRUC- TURE: HEAD: Scapus not incrassate as in male. THORAX: 
<emphasis box="[276,340,712,733]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Legs:</emphasis>
Fore tibia apically less expanded; mesotarsus without long setae laterally. ABDOMEN: Segments III–VI not keeled. GENITALIA: Subgenital plate short, nearly as long as wide, broadly triangular, apex rounded (fig. 23), reaching middle of segment VIII; base of ovipositor located nearly at longitudinal midpoint of abdomen; interramal sclerites oblong or subquadrangular, edges usually not well defined (fig. 22); dorsal lobes of interramal sclerites ovate or oblong, inner margin sinuate, subbasally enlarged medially and curved inward, outer margin curved gently medially distally, apically acute, covered with small microtrichia mostly arranged homogeneously in a scalelike fashion (fig. 22); sigmoid process and dorsal margin of interramal sclerites covered with microtrichia (fig. 22); medial process neither distinct nor sclerotized; dorsal labiate plate without any sclerotized modified structures; sclerotized rings subrectangular, external margin laterally recurved, medial posterior margin sometimes produced and weakly sclerotized, lateral small accessory sclerite from almost inconspicuous to acute or enlarged (fig. 22); internal surface of seminal depository anterior to sclerotized rings usually covered with small microtrichia; caudal ventral margin of ventral labiate plate forming a medium-sized ventral protuberance, weakly covering part of the anterior wall in posterior view (fig. 23), sometimes distally weakly sclerotized; inner margin of first gonapophyses symmetrical; anterior wall membranous, without conspicuous folds or sclerotizations.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="65" pageNumber="66" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="65.[667,1193,212,1377]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
DISTRIBUTION: Western 
<collectingCountry box="[1018,1193,271,293]" name="United States of America" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">United States</collectingCountry>
from the Great Basin and Mohave Deserts to the 
<taxonomicName box="[746,815,330,352]" class="Actinopterygii" family="Scombridae" genus="Sierra" kingdom="Animalia" order="Perciformes" pageId="65" pageNumber="53" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">Sierra</taxonomicName>
<collectingRegion box="[824,917,330,352]" country="United States of America" name="Nevada" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Nevada</collectingRegion>
, south to 
<collectingRegion country="Mexico" name="Baja California" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Baja California</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[719,809,359,381]" name="Mexico" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Mexico</collectingCountry>
, to about 
<geoCoordinate box="[933,993,359,381]" degrees="28" direction="north" orientation="latitude" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" precision="55555" value="28.0">
28 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[960,971,359,380]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">°</emphasis>
N
</geoCoordinate>
(fig. 19).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="65" pageNumber="66" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="65.[667,1193,212,1377]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
HOST ASSOCIATIONS: All 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="undetermined">
<emphasis box="[1008,1136,388,411]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Daleapidea</emphasis>
species
</taxonomicName>
are associated with 
<taxonomicName box="[958,1068,418,440]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="family">Fabaceae</taxonomicName>
species of the genus 
<taxonomicName authority="(Schuh, 1989)" baseAuthorityName="Schuh" baseAuthorityYear="1989" box="[793,1134,447,470]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Psorothamnus" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[793,955,447,470]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Psorothamnus</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Schuh, R. T." box="[974,1125,447,469]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" pagination="159 - 166" refId="ref129356" refString="Schuh, R. T. 1989. Review of Daleapidea Knight (Heteroptera: Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini). Journal of the New York Entomological Society 97 (2): 159 - 166." type="journal article" year="1989">Schuh, 1989</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Daleapidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
was named by 
<bibRefCitation author="Knight, H. H." box="[945,1110,476,498]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" pagination="1 - 282" refId="ref128169" refString="Knight, H. H. 1968. Taxonomic review: Miridae of the Nevada test site and the western United States. Brigham Young University Science Bulletin Biological Series 9 (3): 1 - 282." type="journal article" year="1968">Knight (1968)</bibRefCitation>
due to its association with ‘‘ 
<taxonomicName box="[928,995,505,528]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Dalea" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[928,995,505,528]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Dalea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
’’ plants and by the apparent resemblance to 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Carvalho" baseAuthorityYear="1958" box="[1023,1115,534,557]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Lopidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1023,1115,534,557]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Lopidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. ‘‘ 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Dalea" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Dalea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
’’ species associated with 
<taxonomicName box="[998,1126,564,587]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[998,1126,564,587]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Daleapidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
mentioned by Knight are now all segregated in the genus 
<taxonomicName authority="(Barneby, 1977)" baseAuthorityName="Barneby" baseAuthorityYear="1977" box="[783,1139,622,645]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Psorothamnus" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[783,945,622,645]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Psorothamnus</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Barneby, R. C." box="[959,1131,623,645]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" pagination="1 - 891" refId="ref125763" refString="Barneby, R. C. 1977. Daleae imagines: an illustrat- ed revision of Errazuriza Philippi, Psorothamnus Rydberg, Marina Leibmann, and Dalea Lucanus emend. Barneby, including all species of Leguminosae tribe Amorpheae Borissova ever referred to Dalea. Memoirs of the New York Botanical Garden 27: 1 - 891." type="journal article" year="1977">Barneby, 1977</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
. Old labels mentioning ‘‘ 
<taxonomicName box="[914,982,651,674]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Dalea" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[914,982,651,674]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Dalea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
’’ as host plants cannot unambiguously be identified and may be any of the segregated genera, or one of the more than 160 described species of 
<taxonomicName box="[1125,1193,739,762]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Dalea" kingdom="Plantae" order="Fabales" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1125,1193,739,762]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Dalea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Barneby, R. C." box="[675,848,769,791]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" pagination="1 - 891" refId="ref125763" refString="Barneby, R. C. 1977. Daleae imagines: an illustrat- ed revision of Errazuriza Philippi, Psorothamnus Rydberg, Marina Leibmann, and Dalea Lucanus emend. Barneby, including all species of Leguminosae tribe Amorpheae Borissova ever referred to Dalea. Memoirs of the New York Botanical Garden 27: 1 - 891." type="journal article" year="1977">Barneby, 1977</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Barneby, R. C." box="[861,920,769,791]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" pagination="89 - 91" refId="ref125821" refString="Barneby, R. C. 1990. Two new taxa in Dalea (Fabaceae: Amorpheae) from southern Mexico and northern Chile. Brittonia 42 (2): 89 - 91." type="journal article" year="1990">1990</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="65" pageNumber="66" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="65.[667,1193,212,1377]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
DISCUSSION: 
<bibRefCitation author="Schuh, R. T." box="[856,1013,798,821]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" pagination="159 - 166" refId="ref129356" refString="Schuh, R. T. 1989. Review of Daleapidea Knight (Heteroptera: Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini). Journal of the New York Entomological Society 97 (2): 159 - 166." type="journal article" year="1989">Schuh (1989)</bibRefCitation>
in his revision of 
<taxonomicName box="[702,830,827,850]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[702,830,827,850]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Daleapidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
documented for the first time the distinctive structure present in the fore tibia. This distal flattened area on the ventral surface of the fore tibia has a set of setae on its lateral margins that vary with respect to their density. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Van Duzee" authorityYear="1918" box="[825,1065,973,996]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="albescens">
<emphasis box="[825,1065,973,996]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Daleapidea albescens</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is the only species in which the setae are not densely set.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[667,1193,212,1377]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<bibRefCitation author="Schuh, R. T." box="[696,843,1033,1055]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" pagination="159 - 166" refId="ref129356" refString="Schuh, R. T. 1989. Review of Daleapidea Knight (Heteroptera: Miridae: Orthotylinae: Orthotylini). Journal of the New York Entomological Society 97 (2): 159 - 166." type="journal article" year="1989">Schuh (1989</bibRefCitation>
: fig. 5L) presented a schematic illustration for the phallotheca of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Uhler" authorityYear="1894" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="species" species="decorata">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">D. decorata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. This structure was misinterpreted in the provided drawing as being completely open dorsally with overlapping lateral margins. Nevertheless, the phallotheca of the three described species of 
<taxonomicName box="[973,1101,1208,1231]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Daleapidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[973,1101,1208,1231]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Daleapidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
share a particular configuration (fig. 21), similar to the 
<typeStatus box="[722,772,1267,1288]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">type</typeStatus>
found in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[920,1074,1266,1289]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Aoplonemella" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[920,1074,1266,1289]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Aoplonemella</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(fig. 17), 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Forero" authorityYear="2008" box="[667,793,1296,1317]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Origonema" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[667,793,1296,1317]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Origonema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(fig. 43), and particularly to the form found in 
<taxonomicName box="[835,969,1324,1347]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronema" kingdom="Fungi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Ascomycota" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[835,969,1324,1347]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Hadronema</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName box="[1026,1193,1324,1347]" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Hadronemidea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="65" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[1026,1193,1324,1347]" italics="true" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">Hadronemidea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(figs. 28, 29, 39).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="65" pageNumber="66" type="key">
<key pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<keyStep pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<paragraph blockId="65.[667,685,1472,1491]" box="[667,685,1472,1491]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<keyLead box="[667,685,1472,1491]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">1.</keyLead>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="65.[667,692,1553,1572]" box="[667,692,1553,1572]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<keyLead box="[667,692,1553,1572]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">—</keyLead>
</paragraph>
</keyStep>
<paragraph blockId="65.[667,686,1659,1678]" box="[667,686,1659,1678]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<keyLead box="[667,686,1659,1678]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">
<keyStep box="[667,686,1659,1678]" pageId="65" pageNumber="66">2.</keyStep>
</keyLead>
</paragraph>
</key>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>