<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2e39a8a5-7b47-46af-a42a-b9bc4ef05b38" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051661" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-390-1" ID-ZBK="5518417F69B745CC92C3C402055D5851" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-390-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 390" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the Neotropical bark mantis genus Liturgusa Saussure, 1869 (Insecta, Mantodea, Liturgusini)" checkinTime="1451246163705" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Svenson, Gavin J." docDate="2014" docId="F4C0EE7326FF08D3466F299F2E515E15" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 390: 1-214" docOrigin="ZooKeys 390" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661" docTitle="Fuga fluminensis Piza 1965" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="124" lastPageNumber="125" masterDocId="A2413846FFC2FFA59948CC63FFBF7E4D" masterDocTitle="Revision of the Neotropical bark mantis genus Liturgusa Saussure, 1869 (Insecta, Mantodea, Liturgusini)" masterLastPageNumber="214" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" updateTime="1643526401697" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the Neotropical bark mantis genus Liturgusa Saussure, 1869 (Insecta, Mantodea, Liturgusini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Svenson, Gavin J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>390</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>214</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.390.6661</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-390-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">5518417F69B745CC92C3C402055D5851</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5518417F69B745CC92C3C402055D5851</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051661" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F4C0EE7326FF08D3466F299F2E515E15" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F4C0EE7326FF08D3466F299F2E515E15" lastPageId="124" lastPageNumber="125" pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<subSubSection pageId="121" pageNumber="122" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Fuga_fluminensis" authority="Piza, 1965" authorityName="Piza" authorityYear="1965" class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Fuga" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fuga fluminensis" order="Mantodea" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fluminensis">
<pageBreakToken pageId="121" pageNumber="122" start="start">Fuga</pageBreakToken>
fluminensis (Piza, 1965)
</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="121" pageNumber="122" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Hagiomantis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hagiomantis fluminensis" order="Mantodea" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fluminensis">Hagiomantis fluminensis</taxonomicName>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="Piza de Toledo, S Jr" journalOrPublisher="Revista de Agricultura" pageId="150" pageNumber="151" title="Nova Especie Brasileira de Liturgusina (Mantidae)" volume="40" year="1965">Piza 1965</bibRefCitation>
: 130; 
<bibRefCitation author="Terra, PS" journalOrPublisher="Revista Brasileira de Zoologia" pageId="152" pageNumber="153" pagination="13 - 94" title="Revisao Sistematica Dos Generos De Louva-A-Deus Da Regiao Neotropical (Mantodea)." volume="39" year="1995">Terra 1995</bibRefCitation>
: 54; 
<bibRefCitation author="Ehrmann, R" journalOrPublisher="Natur und Tier-Verlag GmbH, Muenster" pageId="148" pageNumber="149" title="Mantodea: Gottesanbeterinnen der Welt." year="2002">Ehrmann 2002</bibRefCitation>
: 163; 
<bibRefCitation author="Otte, D" journalOrPublisher="Association of Insect Diversity, Philadelphia" pageId="150" pageNumber="151" title="Mantida Species File" volumeTitle="Catalog of the Mantids of the World" year="2005">Otte and Spearman 2005</bibRefCitation>
: 129.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="121" pageNumber="122" type="type">
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">Type.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">Holotype Male. Universidade de Sao Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="121" pageNumber="122" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">Brazil: Itaipu, E. da Guanabara, Col: D. Lacombe - 5-2-61 (Lat. -22.950912, Long. -43.036068).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="121" pageNumber="122" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Fuga" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fuga fluminensis" order="Mantodea" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fluminensis">Fuga fluminensis</taxonomicName>
(Piza, 1965).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<table pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<th colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">Sex</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">Type</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">Country</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">Label</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">Latitude Longitude</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">Code</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<td colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">-22.950912, -43.036068</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<td colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">-25.668076, -48.750323</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<td colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">-22.604492, -43.222469</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<td colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">-19.959049, -40.646506</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<td colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">-22.503159, -43.183477</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<td colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">-22.034612, -43.228938</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
<td colspan="1" pageId="121" pageNumber="122" rowspan="1">-23.944261, -46.343691</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="122" pageNumber="123" type="taxonomic history">
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">
<pageBreakToken pageId="122" pageNumber="123" start="start">Taxonomic</pageBreakToken>
history.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">
Described in 1965 by Piza as a species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Hagiomantis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hagiomantis" order="Mantodea" pageId="122" pageNumber="123" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Hagiomantis</taxonomicName>
, the species has since received no attention taxonomically.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="122" pageNumber="123" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Medium size species, mottling pattern highly contrasting with light and dark browns, no white, black, or green included. Costal region of the forewing one of the widest in the genus relative to the wing length, banded with regular alternating patterning between pale and dark brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="123" lastPageNumber="124" pageId="122" pageNumber="123" type="redescription">
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Redescription.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Male. (Figs 33A, 37A) N=2: Body length measurement not possible; forewing length 14.57-16.47 (15.53); hindwing length 11.34-11.89 (11.61); pronotum length 5.87-6.53 (6.20); prozone length 1.92-2.12 (2.02); pronotum width 2.21-2.42 (2.32); pronotum narrow width 1.72-1.77 (1.75); head width 4.54-4.88 (4.71); head vertex to clypeus 1.59-1.86 (1.73); frons width 1.49-1.63 (1.56); frons height 0.58-0.65 (0.62); prothoracic femur length 6.04-6.39 (6.21); mesothoracic femur length 8.67; mesothoracic tibia length 7.00; pronotal elongation measure 0.33; pronotal shape measure 0.37-0.38 (0.37); head shape measure 0.35-0.38 (0.37); frons shape measure 0.39-0.40 (0.40); anteroventral femoral spine count 15-17 (17); anteroventral tibial spine count 9; posteroventral tibial spine count 8.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="122" pageNumber="123">
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">
Figure 33. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Liturgusidae" genus="Fuga" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fuga fluminensis" order="Mantodea" pageId="122" pageNumber="123" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fluminensis">Fuga fluminensis</taxonomicName>
(Piza, 1965), dorsal habitus: A male (BMNH 010) B female from Espirito Santo, Brazil (ZMUH 011).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Head (Fig. 45G): Juxta-ocular protuberances small, the middle being the most pronounced; the vertex between the parietal sutures is slightly concave; vertex slightly lower than the dorsal margin of the eyes. Frontal suture with a curved carina medially with an obvious angle. Ocelli small with the central ocellus oriented anteriorly while the lateral are oriented slightly off 90 degrees from the central axis of the head; protruding slightly on cuticular mounds. Frons narrowed between the antennal insertion sites and depressed below the central ocellus; a transverse carina present below the central ocellus, running from lateral margins under the antennal insertion sites medially in a dorsally oriented curve. Upper margin of clypeus slightly convex, lower margin slightly concave; a central protruding ridge strongly defined; the lateral margins tapering, widest at the upper margin. Antennae pale proximally and fading to black distally. Varying levels of black markings across the anterior surface of head, variable within the species; the vertex and juxta-ocular protuberances dark brown; two black spots medial to the parietal sutures. Palpi are pale.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Pronotum (Fig. 50C): Slightly elongate with a slightly defined supra-coxal bulge; dorsal surface mostly smooth, but with a few very small tubercles; prozone with parallel lateral margins prior to a rounded anterior margin. Metazone with concave lateral margins with a slight medial bulge, exhibiting small denticles in the posterior two thirds; posterior margin of the metazone with angled margins leading to a straight or slightly concave posterior margin, no noticeable medial emargination; the dorsal surface of the posterior half of the metazone depressed. Supra-coxal sulcus strongly defined. The lateral margins of the pronotum slightly expanded to form a small ledge. Colored with black and pale markings that vary across specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Prothoracic Legs: Femur robust with a straight or slightly concave dorsal margin; anteroventral spines black, posteroventral spines pale basally with black terminus. Black and pale mottling on posterior (external) surface of femur with less than 10 tubercles; anterior (internal) surface entirely black; ventral surface entirely black. Well developed femoral pit on the ventral surface to accommodate terminal posteroventral tibial spine positioned medial to and slightly proximal to the most proximal posteroventral spine; pit is black. Posterior prothoracic femoral genicular spine smaller than posteroventral spines, originating at the beginning of the genicular lobe. Prothoracic posteroventral tibial spines with the first and second most proximal and fourth through seventh shorter than the proximal third and terminal spines; the anteroventral spines longest at distal end and shortening proximally. Posterior surface of the prothoracic tibiae smooth and dark; anterior surface black, the ventral surface brown. Prothoracic coxae smooth with varying black markings on the posterior and ventral surface, the anterior surface with a medial black stripe.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Meso- and Metathoracic Legs: Femora with pronounced dorsal and ventral carinae; posterior (upper) surface smooth. Tarsi missing.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="123" pageNumber="124">
<pageBreakToken pageId="123" pageNumber="124" start="start">Wings</pageBreakToken>
: Longer than the abdomen. Forewings mottled with contrasting regions of light and dark brown; the costal region alternating regularly from pale to dark its entire length; the costal region slightly widened. The forewings may be colored asymmetrically, one being mottled as described above while the other is much darker. Hindwings opaque and smoky with near black veins; the costal region and the anterior margin of the discoidal region pigmented with a darker reddish or rust coloration; the terminus of the discoidal region projecting well beyond the distal margin of anal region, giving an elongate appearance.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="123" pageNumber="124">Abdomen: Elongate, tubular, and smooth. Tergites without posterolateral projections. Supra-anal plate transverse, evenly rounded. Subgenital plate rounded and without styli.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="123" pageNumber="124">Genital Complex (Fig. 53B.1-B.2): The main body of ventral left sclerite (L4A) with a prominent, robust, curved distal process (pda) that tapers quickly to a point, the entire structure curving laterally and back onto the L4A. The apofisis falloid (afa) of the main body of dorsal left sclerite (L4B) small and curved, terminating with a blunt end; the apical process (paa) cylindrical and curved, terminating in a rounded end, slightly bulbous; a large, long membranous lobe originating between the apofisis falloid (afa) and the apical process (paa). Right phallomere (R1) too damaged for accurate description.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="124" lastPageNumber="125" pageId="123" pageNumber="124" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="123" pageNumber="124">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="123" pageNumber="124">Female. (Fig. 33B) N=8: Body length 25.26-29.89 (27.22); forewing length 17.65-20.82 (19.07); hindwing length 14.11-16.07 (14.77); pronotum length 6.69-7.85 (7.38); prozone length 2.17-2.62 (2.45); pronotum width 2.73-3.04 (2.92); pronotum narrow width 2.14-2.34 (2.25); head width 5.48-6.14 (5.92); head vertex to clypeus 2.12-2.39 (2.29); frons width 2.02-2.18 (2.10); frons height 0.73-0.88 (0.79); prothoracic femur length 6.97-8.17 (7.73); mesothoracic femur length 7.92-9.92 (9.15); mesothoracic tibia length 6.16-8.28 (7.38); mesothoracic tarsus length 6.16-7.53 (6.92); metathoracic femur length 8.38-10.01 (9.26); metathoracic tibia length 9.35-11.50 (10.46); metathoracic tarsus length 9.90-10.94 (10.42); pronotal elongation measure 0.32-0.34 (0.33); pronotal shape measure 0.37-0.42 (0.40); head shape measure 0.37-0.40 (0.39); frons shape measure 0.35-0.40 (0.38); anteroventral femoral spine count 14-16 (15); anteroventral tibial spine count 9-10 (9); posteroventral tibial spine count 8.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="123" pageNumber="124">Head (Fig. 45H): Juxta-ocular protuberances pronounced, the apex in the middle; the vertex between the parietal sutures is straight or slightly concave; vertex higher than the dorsal margin of the eyes. Frontal suture with a curved carina forming a continuous arc. Antennae pale proximally and fading to black or dark brown distally. Varying levels of black markings across the anterior surface of head, variable within the species; the vertex and juxta-ocular protuberances dark brown; two black spots medial to the parietal sutures. Terminus of palpi are darkened.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="123" pageNumber="124">Pronotum (Fig. 50D): Slightly elongate with a somewhat defined supra-coxal bulge; dorsal surface mostly smooth, but a few very small tubercles are present; prozone with parallel or divergent lateral margins prior to a rounded anterior margin; metazone with concave lateral margins with a medial bulge, exhibiting sparse small denticles in the posterior two thirds; posterior margin of the metazone rounded irregularly with a slight medial emargination. Supra-coxal sulcus strongly defined. The lateral margins of the pronotum slightly expanded to form a small ledge. Colored with black and pale markings that vary across specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
<pageBreakToken pageId="124" pageNumber="125" start="start">Prothoracic</pageBreakToken>
Legs: Black and pale banding on posterior surface of femur with less than 10 tubercles; anterior (inner) surface with a proximal black stripe as well as a distal black stripe medially; ventral surface with a black mark distally and a black mark just medial to second most proximal posteroventral spine. Posterior prothoracic femoral genicular spine slightly smaller than posteroventral spines, originating just distal to the beginning of the genicular lobe. Prothoracic posteroventral tibial spines with the first and second most proximal and fifth through seventh shorter than the proximal third, fourth and terminal spines; the anteroventral spines longest at distal end and shortening proximally. Posterior surface of the prothoracic tibiae smooth with few black marks; anterior surface pale with black marks on dorsal margin, the ventral surface pale. Prothoracic coxae smooth with varying black markings on the posterior and ventral surface, the anterior surface with two black markings of varying size, one in the proximal half and one in the distal half.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Meso- and Metathoracic Legs: Mesotarsi with first segment as long as the remaining segments combined. Metatarsi with first segment slightly longer than remaining segments combined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Wings: Fully developed, longer than the abdomen. Forewings mottled with contrasting regions of light and dark brown; the costal region alternating regularly from pale to dark its entire length; the costal region widened, the widest part being in the middle of the wing. The forewings have not been observed to be asymmetrically colored.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Abdomen: Broad and smooth, widening from first segment until the beginning of the distal half (segments 4-5) when the lateral margins narrow gradually to the terminus, the middle being the broadest region. Tergites without posterolateral tergal projections. Cerci cylindrical, long and setose, tapering to a point. Supra-anal plate as long as wide, rounded.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>