<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bdfb4b8e-4c36-4386-a7d0-7437b44fcba1" ModsDocID="21061" checkinTime="1252706925963" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Heterick, B. E." docDate="2006" docId="AF83148EA5652CE6776CD8A8BDE24E18" docLanguage="en" docName="21061.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 57" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf" docTitle="Monomorium robertsoni Heterick, 2006, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="94" masterDocId="3A2C4F9A5833769B5007E7556E53E380" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="202" masterPageNumber="69" pageNumber="93" updateTime="1569525778780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Heterick, B. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>69</mods:start>
<mods:end>202</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">21061</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:AF83148EA5652CE6776CD8A8BDE24E18" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF83148EA5652CE6776CD8A8BDE24E18">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="93">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196244" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium robertsoni Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium robertsoni Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="93" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robertsoni">Monomorium robertsoni Heterick</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="93">Figs. 14, 37.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="etymology">
<paragraph pageNumber="93">Etymology.- In honour of Dr. Hamish Robertson (South African Museum).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="93">Material examined.- Holotype: Prov. Toliara, Ranobe, 23째02'03&quot;S, 43째36'43&quot;E, 30 m., 13-19.ii.2002, Frontier Project, MGF056/sifted litter spiny forest/thicket/ CASENT 0003501 MGF056(5) (CAS). Paratypes: Prov. Toliara: one [[worker]] with same collection data as holotype, collection code MGF054 (MCZ); two [[worker]]&quot;s, Mandarano [&quot;Manderano&quot;], 23째31'38&quot;S, 44째05'15&quot;E, 70m, 10.v.2002 Frontier Project, MGF030/ sifted litter gallery forest (1 [[worker]] - CAS) (1 [[worker]] - BMNH).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="93">Other material examined: Ifaly, 17.ix.1993 W.E. Steiner and R. Andriamasimanana (4 [[worker]]) (MCZ).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="93">Worker description.- Head: Head square; vertex planar; frons finely striolate throughout; pilosity of frons a mixture of well-spaced, erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with appressed setulae only. Eye large, eye width 1.5x greater than greatest width of antennal scape; (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set around midline of head. Antennal segments 12; club three-segmented. Clypeal carinae indistinct; anteromedian clypeal margin broadly convex; paraclypeal setae moderately long and fine, curved; posteromedian clypeal margin approximately level with antennal fossae. Anterior tentorial pits situated nearer antennal fossae than mandibular insertions. Frontal lobes straight, parallel. Psammophore absent. Palp formula 5,3. Mandibular teeth five; mandibles triangular and striate; masticatory margin of mandibles approximately vertical or weakly oblique; basal tooth approximately same size as t4 (five teeth present).</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="94" pageNumber="93">Mesosoma: Promesonotum finely striolate throughout; in profile broadly convex anteriad, convexity reduced posteriad; promesonotal setae seven to twelve; standing promesonotal setae consisting of short, erect or semi-erect bristles; appressed promesonotal setulae few, mainly on dorsum of promesonotum. Metanotal groove vestigial. Propodeum uniformly finely striolate; propodeal dorsum flat throughout most of its length; always smoothly rounded, no separation between dorsal and declivitous faces when seen in profile; standing propodeal setae absent; appressed propodeal setae very scarce or absent; propodeal spiracle nearer declivitous face of propodeum than metanotal groove; vestibule of propodeal spiracle absent or not visible; propodeal lobes present as rounded flanges.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="94">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle laterodorsal and situated slightly anteriad of petiolar node. Node (viewed in profile) conical, vertex tapered; appearance of node shining and smooth throughout; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) about 1:1. Anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; ventral petiolar lobe absent. Height ratio of petiole to postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; height-length ratio of postpetiole about 1:1; postpetiole shining and smooth; postpetiolar sternite depressed near its junction with gaster, and sloping anteriad at angle of 45-60 to form large conspicuous lip at its anterior end.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="94">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting mainly of short, appressed setulae, together with a few erect and semi-erect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="94">General characters: Color of head, mesosoma and nodes orange, legs, mandibles and apical portion of gaster straw-colored, basal portion of gaster brown. Worker caste monomorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="94">Holotype measurements: HML 1.50 HL 0.53 HW 0.45 CeI 86 SL 0.45 SI 100 PW 0.32.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="94">Paratype worker measurements: HML 1.50-1.82; HL 0.53-0.61; HW 0.45-0.54; CeI 83-88; SL 0.45-0.52; SI 97-104; PW 0.32-0.40 (n=3).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="94">Other worker measurements: HML 1.49-1.67; HL 0.52-0.58; HW 0.43-0.49; CeI 81-84; SL 0.44-0.51; SI 99-107; PW 0.32-0.36 (n=4).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="94">
Remarks.- This species appears to have a very restricted distribution. The few known specimens are all workers, and have been collected from Ifaly, Mandarano and Ranobe in south-western Toliara Province. Collections have been made in sifted litter in spiny forest and associated thickets, in a pitfall trap at the base of a baobab, and in a malaise trap. The latter capture suggests this species may forage arboreally. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196244" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium robertsoni Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium robertsoni Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="94" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robertsoni">Monomorium robertsoni</taxonomicName>
is characterized by its low propodeum, which lacks a separate dorsal and declivitous face, and by its finely striolate exoskeleton.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>