<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287553" ID-GBIF-Dataset="939dfda0-3d37-400f-b2b5-69f995df6ce0" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116708" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287553" checkinTime="1264779951501" checkinUser="claudia" docAuthor="Clark, J." docDate="1930" docId="6282A6CB6E16E4AD6A7BE86C4093C416" docLanguage="en" docName="6104_tx1.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria 43" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf" docTitle="Polyrhachis (Campomyrma) flavibasis" docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageNumber="17" masterDocId="2071CBAF3E24268ACFB8E3A7809C48AD" masterDocTitle="New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species." masterLastPageNumber="25" masterPageNumber="2" pageNumber="16" updateTime="1645821640147" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New Formicidae, with notes on some little-known species.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Clark, J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1930</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>2</mods:start>
<mods:end>25</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6104/6104.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6104</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6287553" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116708" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6287553" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6282A6CB6E16E4AD6A7BE86C4093C416" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6282A6CB6E16E4AD6A7BE86C4093C416" lastPageNumber="17" pageNumber="16">
<subSubSection pageNumber="16" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph>
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:143174" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Polyrhachis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="16" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" source="9CC41C281A16865C4DC38882B180B524,D16005DF748AAECEAF280A0BF3A392F8,F55A52C4D73F8B811E098800ED1A5C2F" species="flavibasis" subGenus="Campomyrma">Polyrhachis (Campomyrma) flavibasis</taxonomicName>
, n. sp. (Text-fig. 1, Nos. 13, 13a.)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageNumber="16" type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="16">Worker.-Length, 7-7.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="16">Head, thorax and node black. Anterior border of the mandibles, funiculus, knees, tarsi and gaster brown. Femora, tibia,. base of the first segment and posterior margin of the other segments of the gaster yellow. Posterior coxae more or less splashed with yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="16">Shining. Head and thorax very finely, densely and irregularly, reticulate, slightly coarser on the thorax, reticulate-punctate on. the sides. Declivity smooth and shining. Anterior and posterior faces of the node superficially reticulate. Gaster microscopically punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="16">Hair yellow, erect, very sparse, confined to the front of the head and apical segments of the gaster. Pubescence yellow, very sparse on the gaster and antennae, not apparent elsewhere.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="16">Head longer than broad, convex behind and on the sides. Frontal carinae short. Clypeus convex, with a faint carina in the middle in front, the anterior border produced and almost straight. Eyes large and convex, placed at the posterior third of the sides. Scapes extending beyond the occipital border by barely half their length; first segment of the funiculus one-third longer than the second. Mandibles armed with five strong, sharp teeth. Thorax one and three-quarters times longer than broad, the sutures strongly impressed. Pronotum as long as broad, strongly convex in front and on the sides, the latter submarginate,. feebly convex above. Mesonotum broader than long, broader in front than behind, submarginate on the sides. Epinotum square, as long as broad, the sides submarginate, the posterior border sharply marginate. Declivity face steep, concave near the bottom, longer than the dorsum, the sides rounded. Node almost twice as broad as long, the lateral angles sharp, the top edge high and narrow, furnished with two broad, triangular teeth. Gaster longer than broad, the anterior border feebly concave below. Legs short and robust.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="16">Female.-Length, 9 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="16">Larger and more robust than the worker. Sculpture a little coarser, more reticulate-punctate. Parapsidal furrows well impressed. Mayrian furrows not defined. Colour identical. Wings hyaline with a brownish tinge.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageNumber="17" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="17">Habitat.-New South Wales: Brooklana and Dorrigo (W. W. Froggatt).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageNumber="17" type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="17">Notes on the Ants of the Horn Expedition.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="17">The collection, here re-examined, was dealt with by Mr. W. F. Kirby, Results of the Horn Expedition, Part I, Supplement, pp- 203-207, 1896. In each case the number and name given by Kirby are stated first, notes and corrections follow.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>