<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6202b897-11c1-4686-99d8-94b8174ac809" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359749" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-55-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-55-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 55" ModsDocTitle="Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) – review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America" checkinTime="1451251020634" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gary A. P., Gibson" docDate="2010" docId="33AD8ADDF3EC4D80A4C3387DCC414D82" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 55: 1-75" docOrigin="ZooKeys 55" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490" docTitle="Calosota bicolorata P., 2010, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="26" masterDocId="FF9456530D10AC187F08FFB0FC42FFD0" masterDocTitle="Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) - review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America" masterLastPageNumber="75" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="23" pageNumber="24" updateTime="1643559592688" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) - review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gary A. P., Gibson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>55</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>75</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-55-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359749" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:33AD8ADDF3EC4D80A4C3387DCC414D82" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/33AD8ADDF3EC4D80A4C3387DCC414D82" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">
<subSubSection pageId="23" pageNumber="24" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="23" pageNumber="24">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7DA1C5D0-750E-4395-AB3F-4555681F2E8F" class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota bicolorata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="23" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolorata">Calosota bicolorata</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="23" pageNumber="24">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 111630, 34496175
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="23" pageNumber="24" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="23" pageNumber="24">
From the Latin words bi, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘two’">'two'</normalizedToken>
, and color, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘hue’">'hue'</normalizedToken>
, in reference to the conspicuously different color of the mesoscutum and scutellum of females.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="24" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="23" pageNumber="24" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="24" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">
HOLOTYPE ♀ (CNC type no. 23925). [USA] CAL. Riverside Co., Menifee Vly (hills on W end), 33°9'N; 117°13'W, 1800' el., 1-15.VI.1980, John 
<pageBreakToken pageId="24" pageNumber="25" start="start">D</pageBreakToken>
. Pinto; CNC SEM 2009-38; CNC Photo 2009-11; Holotype 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota bicolorata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="24" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolorata">Calosota bicolorata</taxonomicName>
Gibson. ALLOTYPE♂ (UCDC). [USA] Batchelder Spr., Cal., Inyo Co., VII.11.1969, R.O. Schuster Colr.; CNC Photo 2009-12; Allotype 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota bicolorata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="24" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolorata">Calosota bicolorata</taxonomicName>
Gibson.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="24" pageNumber="25">Additional paratypes. USA. California: Imperial Co., Glamis, Hwy 78, 28.III.80, J. Woolley (1♀ CNC). Lone Pine, 2 mi. E, 19.V.70, E.E. Grissell (1♀ UCDC); Movie Rd, 1390 m., on Eriogonum fasic., 36°35'55N; 118°6'57W, 30.V.04, D. Yanega, UCR Ent. Res. Mus. 97429 (1♀ UCRC). Nevada: Nye Co., Mercury, N.T.S., B.Y.U. - A.E.C., Code CS-A-5, Coll. No. 36, 3.IX.59, Ref. No. 778 (1♂ USNM, CNC Photo 2009-46, CNC SEM 2009-45).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="24" pageNumber="25" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="24" pageNumber="25">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="24" pageNumber="25">FEMALE (Figs 16, 34). HOLOTYPE: length 4.2 mm. Color. Head (Fig. 11) bluish-green, including spot below anterior ocellus, or with limited purplish luster under some angles of light, but vertex with coppery region between posterior ocelli extending from ocelli to level of outer orbits (Fig. 16), and upper face with M-like coppery region below anterior ocellus, the lateral arm of region inconspicuously tapered to outer margin of ocellus dorsally and slightly separated from inner orbit ventrally (Fig. 11). Maxillary and labial palpi dark. Antenna dark brown except scape with slight bluish-purple luster under some angles of light. Tegula dark. Mesoscutum (Fig. 16) bluish-green similar to head except anteroadmedian and parapsidal lines dark with slight coppery luster; scutellar-axillar complex black but reticulations shiny with slight coppery luster under some angles of light. Acropleuron primarily reddish-brown except for slight greenish luster anteriorly. Legs (Fig. 34) with front leg extensively brown but trochantellus, knee, tibia apically and tarsus yellowish; middle leg almost uniformly yellowish-orange beyond coxa though femur somewhat more orange and tibia and tarsus more yellowish; hind leg with most of femur brown and tarsus and most of tibia yellowish, but about apical one-fifth of femur yellowish and tibia brownish dorsomedially. Fore wing hyaline except for brownish region behind marginal and stigmal veins anterior to mediocubital fold; setae uniformly brownish within hyaline regions. Gaster (Fig. 34) mostly brown except terga with slight bluish-purple lusters laterally.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="24" pageNumber="25">
Structure/setation. Head in dorsal view about 2.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, with IOD about 0.36
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
head width; IOD: MPOD: OOL: POL: LOL = 57: 13: 7: 18: 13; in frontal view about 1.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high, with dorsal margin of torulus at level of lower orbits; malar space about 0.52
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
eye height. Head (Fig. 11) with frontovertex and parascrobal region very shallowly meshlike reticulate to about level of dorsal limit of interantennal region, medially the reticulations tapered ventrally between dorsal limits of smooth and shiny scrobes; lower parascrobal region coriaceous-alutaceous; interantennal region finely coriaceous-alutaceous dorsally to meshlike coriaceous ventrally; clypeal region microcoriaceous and paraclypeal region obliquely coriaceous to very shallowly reticulate-alutaceous toward inner orbit. Head with inconspicuous, mostly brownish setae on frontovertex and more conspicuous white setae on parascrobal region, interantennal region and lower face. Antenna (Fig. 34) with flagellum clavate; length of flagellum + pedicel about 1.4
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
head width; scape: pedicel: fu1-fu8: clava = 75(13): 28(10): 13(8), 17(9), 21(10), 20(10), 17(10), 16(10), 15(10), 15(10): 50(13). Mesoscutum (Figs 16, 75) with inclined anterior surface alutaceous-coriaceous, inclined lateral surface shallowly mes 
<pageBreakToken pageId="25" pageNumber="26" start="start">hlike</pageBreakToken>
reticulate, and dorsal surface more deeply meshlike reticulate, with quite conspicuous and dense, very slightly lanceolate white setae; notauli obscure, but anteroadmedian lines and parapsidal lines more distinct as lines of differentiated sculpture and color. Axillae very small, separated by about 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
own maximum width (Fig. 75). Scutellum convex, quadrate; elongate reticulate-strigose with deep, much smaller reticulations than on mesoscutum (Fig. 75); with inconspicuous dark setae. Mesopleuron with exposed, bare lower mesepimeron; acropleuron meshlike coriaceous or coriaceous-reticulate anterior to oblique microsculptured region and very finely, slightly elongate meshlike coriaceous posteriorly. Fore wing with cc: mv: stv: pmv = 50: 22: 10: 13; basal cell entirely setose; cubital area bare but closed by setae along posterior margin over about apical quarter; disc setose except for slender, arcuate bare region along basal fold, the region separated from cubital area by setose mediocubital fold. Metacoxa quite densely and conspicuously setose dorsally and ventrolaterally, the ventrally setose region broadening basally to restrict longitudinal bare band on outer surface within dorsal half. Propodeum with callus densely and conspicuously setose to posterior margin; anteriorly with single white setae midway between spiracle and foramen. Gaster (Figs 16, 34) about 1.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as mesosoma; with hairlike to very slightly lanceolate white setae, the basal terga more sparsely setose dorsally but apical terga and tergal laterally relatively densely and uniformly setose; penultimate tergum with posterior margin extending distinctly beyond level of cerci (partly an artifact of abnormally inflated gaster as a result of critical-point drying); syntergum about 1.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as transcercal width, uniformly convex, and subequal in length to penultimate tergum (measurements approximate because of inflated gaster).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">MALE (Fig. 49). ALLOTYPE: length about 3.1 mm. Similar to holotype except as follows. Color. Head (Fig. 30) mostly reddish-coppery, though under some angles of light interocellar region indistinctly and scrobes more distinctly greenish, and interantennal region with bluish-purple spot between toruli; mesoscutum (Fig. 30) extensively reddish-coppery similar to head except convex, inclined lateral surface of lateral lobes more greenish under most angles of light and parapsidal lines dark; scutellar-axillar complex narrowly reddish-coppery anteriorly, but scutellum mostly dark except for reddish-coppery frenal area; acropleuron irregularly reddish-coppery with slight greenish lusters under some angles of light; legs (Fig. 49) entirely yellowish-orange beyond coxae; gaster dark brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
Structure/setation. Head in dorsal view (Fig. 30) about 1.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, with IOD: MPOD: OOL: POL: LOL = 62: 16: 8: 18: 12; in frontal view about 1.15
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high, with ventral margin of torulus about at level of lower orbits; malar space about 0.58
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
eye height. Antenna with flagellum robust, about same width throughout and with setae much shorter than width of flagellomere, length of flagellum + pedicel about 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
head width, and fu1 distinctly widening apically; scape: pedicel: fu1-fu8: clava = 60(20): 32(12): 9(10), 15(13), 17(13), 17(12), 16(12), 13(12), 14(12), 13(12): 42(12). Fore wing (Fig. 61) with cc: mv: stv: pmv = 43: 24: 10: 10; basal cell mostly bare with only a few scattered setae, the basal fold completely and mediocubital fold broadly bare apical to basal fold and almost completely bare basal to basal fold, hence slender arcuate bare band on disc continuous with basal cell and cubital area. Propodeum (left side) with 2 setae anteriorly between spiracle and foramen.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Females range in length from about 2.5-3.7 mm and the two known males from 2.9-3.1 mm. All females are quite similar in color except the coppery band behind the ocelli (Fig. 16) varies from being almost completely absent to forming a transverse band behind the posterior ocelli between the inner orbits, the M-like band on the upper face usually does not extend to the anterior ocellus, the interantennal region usually is not differentiated in color ventrally, the mesoscutum sometimes has an obscure coppery medial band extending posteriorly, and the scutellar-axillar complex is often entirely dark. Smaller females are somewhat less conspicuously setose than the holotype. Although the head of the non-allotype male is extensively reddish-coppery, it is quite distinctly green within the interocellar region and under some angles of light lateral to the anterior ocellus as well as ventrally on the parascrobal region, and the mesoscutum dorsally is also somewhat more extensively greenish. The fore wing of the non-allotype male is somewhat more extensively setose than for the allotype, but the basal fold and mediocubital folds are extensively bare so that the bare region of the disc along the basal fold is broadly continuous with the cubital area (Fig. 61).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="biology">
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Nearctic: southwestern USA (Map 1) and likely northern Mexico.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="recognition">
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Recognition.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
As indicated in the key, females are most similar to those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota aestivalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aestivalis">Calosota aestivalis</taxonomicName>
. The key also uses leg color as the primary feature to differentiate males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota bicolorata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolorata">Calosota bicolorata</taxonomicName>
from those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota aestivalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aestivalis">Calosota aestivalis</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
, but fore wing setal pattern may be a better feature. Both known males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota bicolorata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolorata">Calosota bicolorata</taxonomicName>
have the fore wing much less setose basally than those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota aestivalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aestivalis">Calosota aestivalis</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
, the basal fold and the mediocubital fold basal and apical to the basal fold being extensively bare (Fig. 61). However, additional males are required to determine whether this setal pattern is truly diagnostic for males of the species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>