<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.92.20482" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ca4f85c1-4485-446b-89a1-690b7e36893f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="135562802" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-0743-2-343" ID-ZBK="3BF8AEA9F0F54B219DD1C716C3142B65" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:013A64BF-2A20-4579-AB6B-D691D95BBF76" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1860-0743-2-343" ModsDocOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 92 (2)" ModsDocTitle="Pseudorchomeneboreoplebs, a new lysianassid amphipod from Korean waters (Crustacea, Amphipda, Lysianassoidea)" checkinTime="1509549722907" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Jung, Tae Won, Coleman, Charles Oliver &amp; Yoon, Seong Myeong" docDate="2017" docId="0209CC830B04A86088A03CF336EEDFF4" docLanguage="en" docName="ZoosystEvol 93(2): 343-352" docOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 92 (2)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.92.20482" docTitle="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs Jung, Coleman &amp; Yoon, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="013A64BF-2A20-4579-AB6B-D691D95BBF76" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="345" masterDocId="FFC0FFBACA26F67FFFD0FFDA8962FFDC" masterDocTitle="Pseudorchomeneboreoplebs, a new lysianassid amphipod from Korean waters (Crustacea, Amphipda, Lysianassoidea)" masterLastPageNumber="352" masterPageNumber="343" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" updateTime="1643587466718" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Pseudorchomeneboreoplebs, a new lysianassid amphipod from Korean waters (Crustacea, Amphipda, Lysianassoidea)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jung, Tae Won</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Coleman, Charles Oliver</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Yoon, Seong Myeong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zoosystematics and Evolution</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>92</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>343</mods:start>
<mods:end>352</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.92.20482</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.92.20482</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-0743-2-343</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">3BF8AEA9F0F54B219DD1C716C3142B65</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">3BF8AEA9F0F54B219DD1C716C3142B65</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="135562802" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:013A64BF-2A20-4579-AB6B-D691D95BBF76" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0209CC830B04A86088A03CF336EEDFF4" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="345" pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="343" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/013A64BF-2A20-4579-AB6B-D691D95BBF76" class="Malacostraca" family="Lysianassidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="343">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 Korean Name: Buk-bang-gae-gin-pal-yeop-sae-u, new
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="343" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Near Daejin Port, Daejin-ri Hyeonnae-myeon Goseong-gun Gangwon-do South Korea. The specimens were collected from fishery nets of this port. According to the statements of fishermen, these nets were brought out within a 5 km radius from Daejin Port and the nets were deployed in about 1-2 km depth (The precise coordinates were uncertain).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="343" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Holotype: female, 27.1 mm (NIBRIV0000806535), paratypes: two males, 15.5-18.0 mm and two females, 15.9-23.5 mm (NIBRIV0000807159); collected from fishery nets in Daejin Port, 11 Mar 2016, by TW Jung.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="343" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
The composite epithet of the specific name, 
<taxonomicName genus="Lysianassoidea" lsidName="Lysianassoidea boreoplebs" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
is a combination of the Latin borealis and the specific name of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene plebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plebs">Pseudorchomene plebs</taxonomicName>
(Hurley, 1965). This name refers to a 'similar species to 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
living in the northern 
<normalizedToken originalValue="region’">region'</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="343" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Eyes red or brown in life. Antenna 2 not reduced in both sexes. Gnathopod 1 stocky; basis largely expanded, 2.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; palm transverse, convex, margin serrated. Gnathopod 2 carpus 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis, 3.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; propodus 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, weakly angulated anterodistally. Pereopod 5 coxa wider than long; merus posterior lobe well developed, lined with slender setae only (without robust setae). Uropod 3 inner ramus not reaching distal end of proximal article of outer ramus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="345" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Description of holotype female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Head (Fig. 1B) lateral cephalic lobes rounded, expanded anteriorly; eyes pyriform, large, ommatidea small, red or brown in life.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (27.1 mm), NIBRIV0000806535. A habitus; B head; C antenna 1, lateral; D antenna 1, medial; E antenna 2; F upper lip, lateral; G left mandible; H right mandible. Scale bars 0.2 mm (F), 0.5 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–E">C-E</normalizedToken>
, G, H), 1.0 mm (B), 2.0 mm (A).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Antenna 1 (Fig. 1C, D) half as long as antenna 2, as long as head to pereonite 1 combined; peduncular article 1 swollen anteriorly; accessory flagellum 5-articulate; flagellum article 1 distinctly elongate; calceoli absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Antenna 2 (Fig. 1E) not reduced, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as body; peduncular articles moderate; flagellum 36-articulate; calceoli absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Upper lip (Fig. 1F) epistome convex in lateral view, not separated from upper lip; upper lip produced downward.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Mandible (Fig. 1G, H) incisor smooth but bearing blunt denticles on both sides; lacinia mobilis present on left side only, narrowly cylindrical (finger-like), nearly slender; three small raker setae present on each left and right mandibles, with an patch of setules between molar process and raker setae; molar process narrow, triturative, with an lateral setigerous crest; palp attached proximal to molar process, 3-articulate, article 2 longest, not expanded, with an oblique row of 24 setae distally, article 3 weakly falcate, 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as article 2, with 26 setae along medial margin and one group of four setae at apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">Maxilla 1 (Fig. 2A, B) inner plate narrowing distally, not short, setose, with two plumose setae apically; outer plate with eleven toothed setae apically in 7/4 arrangement; palp bi-articulate, distal article swollen laterodistally, apical margin lined with 13 robust setae and one simple seta.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="0" pageNumber="343" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (27.1 mm), NIBRIV0000806535. A maxilla 1; B apical setae on outer plate of maxilla 1; C maxilla 2; D, E maxilliped; F gnathopod 1. Scale bars 0.1 mm (G), 0.2 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–E">A-E</normalizedToken>
), 0.5 mm (F).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Maxilla 2 (Fig. 2C) inner plate slender, tapering distally, with one row of simple setae and one row of dentate setae overlapped on mediodistal margin, with one long plumose seta at middle of medial margin; outer plate 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as inner plate, not narrow, also tapering distally and with two rows of simple and dentate setae on mediodistal margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Maxilliped (Fig. 2D, E) inner plate rectangular, with one row of nine plumose setae on medial margin distally, with three nodular setae on apical margin; outer plate well developed, subovoid, somewhat elongate, apex not reaching end of palp article 3, lined with 29 small nodular setae on mediodistal margin and with two elongate nodular setae on apex, with one row of ten surficial setae along medial margin; palp 4-articulate, article 1 wider, article 2 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as article 1, lined with many long setae on medial margin, article 3 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 2, article 4 falcate, half as long as article 3, with minute setae along medial margin and distal surface, apical seta short.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="344" pageId="0" pageNumber="343">
Pereon.Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 2F, G) stout, subchelate; coxa large, triangular, strongly divergent, rounded ventrally, angulate posteroventrally; basis 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as coxa, 2.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, anterior margin straight, lined 
<pageBreakToken pageId="1" pageNumber="344" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
slender setae, posterior margin well expanded, only with one group of setae subdistally; ischium half as long as basis; carpal lobe developed; propodus 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis, subrectangular, width gradually diminished distally, posterior margin forming weak lobe distally along palm, palm distinct, convex, serrated, with one pair of defining robust setae; dactylus falcate, exceeding palm.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
) slender, minutely chelate; coxa subrectangular, weakly divergent distally, slightly produced posteroventrally; basis linear, as long as coxa, weakly winding at distal 1/3 length, with short setae along anterior and posterior margins; ischium elongate, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis; merus half as long as ischium, covered with short setae posteriorly, with one group of elongate setae at rounded corner posterodistally; carpus 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis, 3.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, anterior margin nearly straight, covered with short setae distally at 2/3 length, with one group of many elongate setae distally, posterior lobe shallow but broad, also covered with minute setae, with one group of elongate setae on mediodistal surface; propodus 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, slightly expanded distally, densely covered with short setae distally on 2/3 length, anterior margin with several rows of elongate setae distally at half length, forming blunt angle distally, palm distinct but short, weakly produced forward, with one seta near hinge of dactylus and one small protrusion forming cavity bearing one dentate basket, one locking seta located at distal notch; dactylus also short, reaching end of palm, anchored at middle of distal margin of propodus, inner margin weakly serrate distally; oostegite linear, as long as coxa.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="344" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (27.1 mm), NIBRIV0000806535. A gnathopod 2; B coxa 2; C palm and dactylus of gnathopod 2; D oostegite of gnathopod 2; E pereopod 3; F oostegite of pereopod 3. Scale bars 0.1 mm (C), 0.5 mm (A, B, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
Pereopod 3 (Fig. 3E, F) ordinary; coxa subrectangular, 3.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, slightly curved and produced posteroventrally; basis 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as coxa, subtrapezoidal, somewhat expanded posterodistally, posterior margin with one group of setae distally; ischium, merus, and carpus with many elongate setae posteriorly; ischium elongate, 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as basis, anterior lobe weak; merus anterior margin expanded, with only one group of setae at anterodistal corner weakly produced; carpus 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus, anterior margin slightly convex, without setae; propodus 1.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, with seven minute setae anteriorly, posterior margin lined with many paired or triplet robust setae, with one pair of locking setae posterodistally; dactylus falcate, 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed; oostegite linear, 1.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as that of gnathopod 2.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 4A, B) coxa deeper than wide, expanded posteroventrally; other articles and oostegite nearly similar with those of pereopod 3.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="344" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (27.1 mm), NIBRIV0000806535. A pereopod 4; B oostegite of pereopod 4; C pereopod 5; D oostegite of pereopod 5; E pereopod 6; F pereopod 7. Scale bars 1.0 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
Pereopod 5 (Fig. 4C, D) coxa large, 1.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, weakly bilobate, anterior and posterior margins not angulate, posterior lobe more expanded downward; basis subovoid, smaller than coxa, slightly wider than long, anterior margin angulate proximally, lined with 27 short setae and with one group of setae distally; posterior lobe largely expanded, rounded, its distal end reaching middle of merus, margin with 15 weak crenellations; ischium short, with a group of setae at anterodistal corner, posterior lobe weak; merus expanded, anterior margin straight, with two robust setae marginally and one group of robust and slender setae distally, posterior lobe well developed, lined with seven slender setae, distal corner produced, with a short seta apically, not exceeding middle of carpus; carpus 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus, rectangular, 2.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, anterior margin lined with robust setae; posterior margin somewhat rounded but not expanded, only with one group of setae distally; propodus 1.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, anterior margin lined with many single and paired robust setae, with one pair of locking setae distally, posterior margin only with one group of setae distally; dactylus falcate, 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed; oostegite linear, 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as that of pereopod 4.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
Pereopod 6 (Fig. 4E) 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as pereopod 5; coxa subquadrate, slightly concave anteriorly and convex posteriorly, bilobate, posterior lobe larger and more expanded ventrally, with six minute setae; basis slightly larger than coxa, longer than wide, anterior margin forming weak hump proximally, lined with 15 robust setae, with one group of setae distally, posterior lobe largely expanded, rounded, its distal end slightly exceeding ischium, margin with 15 weak crenellations; ischium anterior margin lined with robust setae marginally and with a group of robust and slender setae distally; merus expanded, anterior margin straight, with ten robust and two slender setae on anterior margin, posterior lobe well developed, distal corner produced, lined with five robust setae; carpus 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus, rectangular, 2.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, anterior margin lined with robust setae, posterior margin somewhat rounded but not expanded, only with one group of setae distally; propodus 1.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, anterior margin lined with many paired and triplet robust setae, with one pair of locking setae distally, posterior margin with only one group of setae distally; dactylus falcate, 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="344">
Pereopod 7 (Fig. 4F) 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as pereopod 6; coxa unilobate, oblique anteroventrally; basis larger than that of pereopod 6, anterior margin forming weak hump proximally and slightly concave distally at 2/3 length, lined with 14 robust setae marginally and with one group of setae distally, posterior lobe largely expanded, rounded, its distal end not exceeding ischium, margin with 24 weak crenellations; ischium anterior margin lined with four robust setae marginally and with one group of robust setae distally; merus expanded, anterior margin straight, lined with ten robust setae irregularly and with one group of setae distally, posterior lobe well developed, with seven robust setae distally on half length, distal corner produced, its end reaching proximal 1/3 length of carpus; carpus 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as merus, rectangular, 2.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, anterior margin lined with 15 robust setae irregularly and with one group of robust setae distally, posterior margin somewhat rounded proximally but not expanded, with only one group of setae distally; propodus 1.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as carpus, anterior margin lined with many paired and triplet robust setae, with one pair of locking setae distally, posterior margin with only one group of setae distally; dactylus falcate, 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as propodus, unguis developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="345" start="start">Pleon</pageBreakToken>
.Epimeron 1 subquadrate, somewhat produced anteroventrally, ventral margin straight, posterior margin convex, with an oblique ridge on surface. Epimeron 2 larger than epimeron 1 anteroventral corner rounded, weakly produced, ventral margin concave, posteroventral corner subquadrate, with an oblique ridge on surface. Epimeron 3 largest, somewhat expanded antero- and posteroventrally, posterior margin rounded. Urosomite 1 with deep dorsal depression and mid-dorsal carina (Fig. 5A).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (27.1 mm; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–E">A-E</normalizedToken>
), NIBRIV0000806535 and paratype male (18 mm; F), NIBRIV0000807159. A pleon, lateral; B uropod 1; C uropod 2; D uropod 3; E telson; F habitus of male. Scale bars 0.5 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–E">B-E</normalizedToken>
), 1.0 mm (A), 2.0 mm (F).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
Uropod 1 (Fig. 5B) longest; peduncle 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as rami, with twelve short setae (including distal short seta) distally on half of dorsomedial margin and 31 elongate setae along dorsolateral margin; outer ramus almost as long as inner ramus, with 13 lateral and nine medial setae; inner ramus with two lateral and 15 medial short setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
Uropod 2 (Fig. 5C) 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as uropod 1; peduncle as long as outer ramus, with nine small setae on dorsomedial and seven elongate setae on dorsolateral margin; outer ramus with 14 lateral and ten medial setae; inner ramus 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer ramus, with 14 medial setae only.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
Uropod 3 (Fig. 5D) 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as uropod 2; peduncle 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as inner ramus; each ramus with plumose setae on medial margin; outer ramus bi-articulate, distal article 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as proximal article; inner ramus 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer ramus, not reaching distal end of proximal article of outer ramus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
Telson (Fig. 5E) 2.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide, cleft to about 70%, each lobe with one weak notch bearing one robust and one simple seta apically and five setae dorsolaterally.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="345" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">Description of paratype male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">Body length between 15.5-18.0 mm, smaller than those of females (15.9-23.5 mm). Not sexually dimorphic in both sexes.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="345" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="345">
Among five valid species of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pseudorchomene</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. coatsi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="coatsi">P. coatsi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. debroyeri" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="debroyeri">P. debroyeri</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. lophorachis" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="lophorachis">P. lophorachis</taxonomicName>
are similar to each other in sharing a characteristic gnathopod 1: the convex anterior margin of the basis and the elongate and extremely slender articles from ischium to dactylus (
<bibRefCitation author="Chilton, C" journalOrPublisher="Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh" pageId="3" pageNumber="346" pagination="455 - 520" title="The Amphipoda of the Scottish National Antarctic Expedition." volume="48" year="1912">Chilton 1912</bibRefCitation>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Udekem">d'Udekem</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Acoz">d'Acoz</normalizedToken>
and Haverman, 2012). The remaining two species, 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rossi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="rossi">P. rossi</taxonomicName>
show a quite different, short and stocky shaped gnathopod 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n. also has a stocky gnathopod 1, but this new species can be readily distinguished from 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rossi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="rossi">P. rossi</taxonomicName>
by the following differences: 1) the color of the eyes in life is red or brown (vs. black in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rossi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="rossi">P. rossi</taxonomicName>
), 2) the basis of gnathopod 1 is more expanded, 3) the coxa of pereopod 5 is wider than that of 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rossi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="rossi">P. rossi</taxonomicName>
and the posterior lobe is more produced downward in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. boreoplebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">P. boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 4) the merus of pereopod 5 is less expanded, it has slender tapering setae posteriorly (vs. robust setae only in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rossi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="rossi">P. rossi</taxonomicName>
), and the carpus of pereopod 5 is not expanded posteriorly (vs. expanded posterodistally in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rossi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="rossi">P. rossi</taxonomicName>
), 5) the merus and carpus of pereopods 5 and 6 are less or not expanded, 6) the anteroventral corner of pleonal epimeron 1 is more produced, and 7) the apex of the inner ramus on uropod 3 is not reaching the distal end of the outer ramus (vs. subequal in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. rossi" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="rossi">P. rossi</taxonomicName>
) (
<bibRefCitation author="Walker, AO" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Linnean Society of London, Zoology" pageId="3" pageNumber="346" pagination="38 - 64" title="Amphipoda of the &quot; Southern Cross &quot; Antarctic Expedition." url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1903.tb00425.xw" volume="29" year="1903">Walker 1903</bibRefCitation>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Udekem">d'Udekem</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Acoz">d'Acoz</normalizedToken>
and Haverman, 2012). 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Tryphosidae" genus="Pseudorchomene" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudorchomene boreoplebs" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boreoplebs">Pseudorchomene boreoplebs</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is quite similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
, but could be distinguished by the following differences: 1) the distal palp article of maxilla 1 is swollen laterally and has 13 robust setae and one simple seta on apical margin (vs. curved, but not swollen and eight robust setae only in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
, see the 
<bibRefCitation author="Hurley, DE" journalOrPublisher="Transactions of the Royal Society of New Zealand" pageId="3" pageNumber="346" pagination="107 - 113" title="A common but hitherto undescribed species of Orchomenella (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Family Lysianassidae) from the Ross Sea." volume="6" year="1965">Hurley 1965</bibRefCitation>
), 2) the carpus of gnathopod 2 is 3.5 times as long as wide (vs. 2.6 times as long as wide in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
), 3) the propodus on gnathopod 2 is slightly angulate anterodistally (vs. convex anterodistally in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
, see 
<bibRefCitation author="Hurley, DE" journalOrPublisher="Transactions of the Royal Society of New Zealand" pageId="3" pageNumber="346" pagination="107 - 113" title="A common but hitherto undescribed species of Orchomenella (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Family Lysianassidae) from the Ross Sea." volume="6" year="1965">Hurley 1965</bibRefCitation>
), 4) the posterior margin of the coxa on pereopod 5 is more convex, wider and not angulate (vs. slightly angulate posteroventrally in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
), 5) the posterior margin of the merus on pereopod 5 has slender setae only (vs. has robust and slender setae in 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. plebs" pageId="2" pageNumber="345" rank="species" species="plebs">P. plebs</taxonomicName>
), and 6) the anteroventral corner of epimeron 1 is more produced (
<bibRefCitation author="Hurley, DE" journalOrPublisher="Transactions of the Royal Society of New Zealand" pageId="3" pageNumber="346" pagination="107 - 113" title="A common but hitherto undescribed species of Orchomenella (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Family Lysianassidae) from the Ross Sea." volume="6" year="1965">Hurley 1965</bibRefCitation>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Udekem">d'Udekem</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Acoz">d'Acoz</normalizedToken>
and Haverman, 2012).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>