<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280225" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120161" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280225" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="CBE91A856760BA9F588514E84C36F228" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys covina Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="675" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="675" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280225" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120161" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280225" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:CBE91A856760BA9F588514E84C36F228" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CBE91A856760BA9F588514E84C36F228" lastPageNumber="675" pageNumber="675">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155854" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys covina Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys covina Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="covina">Strumigenys covina Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="675">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 3.0, HL 0.74, HW 0.53, CI 72, ML 0.32, MI 43, SL 0.44, SI 82, PW 0.35, AL 0.77. Characters of chroa-complex. Mandibles almost straight and at full closure parallel except at base. Basal half of proximal preapical mandibular tooth confluent with a lamella on inner margin which extends to base of mandible; in full-face view inner margin of lamella more or less straight. Upper scrobe margin a narrow lamella that is about half as wide as scape. Maximum diameter of eye about equal to maximum width of scape. Hairs on leading edge of scape slender and filiform. Cephalic dorsum with rows of curved narrow spatulate to spoon-shaped ground-pilosity, the upper scrobe margins fringed with a dense row of hairs which are the same shape and size as those on the dorsum. Cephalic dorsum with 6 simple standing hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Pronotal humeral hair filiform with a pointed apex. Anterior margin of mesonotum with a pair of stout filiform hairs; posterior mesonotum with 2 additional pairs which are similar in shape but shorter. Propodeum with a pair of narrow filiform hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Ground-pilosity on alitrunk sparse and similar in size and shape as on head. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and more or less flat posteriorly; posterior portion of mesonotum slightly depressed below the anterior margin of propodeum. Anterior mesonotum with a lamellate extension above the mesothoracic spracle. Propodeal tooth broadly triangular, lamellate and pointed apically; propodeal lamella relatively broad. Alitrunk dorsum reticulate-punctate; pleurae mostly smooth and shiny, peripherally reticulate-punctate. Disc of postpetiole smooth and shiny; in dorsal view, exposed cuticle of postpetiole node conspicuously broader than long. Ventral and lateral spongiform tissue of petiole and postpetiole moderately developed. Base of first gastral tergite with short costulae radiating on each side of a broad central clear area. Dorsal surfaces of petiole, postpetiole and gaster with standing filiform hairs. Colour dull yellowish brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="675">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 3.0, HL 0.74, HW 0.53, CI 72, ML 0.31, MI 42, SL 0.43, SI 80, PW 0.35, AL 0.78. (1 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="675">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 5.3 km. SSE Ambanizana, Andranobe, 15 Â° 40 ' S, 49 Â° 58 ' E, 425 m., 21. xi. 1993, sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood), rainforest, # 926 (32) - ll (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ). Paratype. 1 worker with same data as holotype but coded (33) - 9 (BMNH).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="675">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: R. S. Manongarivo, 14.5 km. 220 Â° SW Antanambao, 1175 m. (B. L. Fisher).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="675">Measurements of this specimen extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.73, HW 0.56, CI 76, ML 0.31, MI 42, SL 0.46, SI 83.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155854" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys covina Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys covina Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="covina">S. covina</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from other species in the chroa-complex by a lamellate upper scrobe margin and filiform hairs on pronotal humerus, petiole, postpetiole and first gastral tergite.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>