<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284668" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5f96e565-1778-4154-8f67-81830690657d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135915" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284668" ModsDocID="6751" checkinTime="1243377290804" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Brown, W. L." docDate="1975" docId="7578F7F48BA6982893F62F2FCB0266C8" docLanguage="en" docName="6751" docOrigin="Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station 15" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf" docTitle="Cerapachys besucheti Brown, 1975, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="73" masterDocId="5EF94453F8BE2CD657C7B1F34B08FD04" masterDocTitle="Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini." masterLastPageNumber="115" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="73" updateTime="1645811814098" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Brown, W. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1975</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>15</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>115</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6751</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">45422C7B-83F2-4F5A-9EE4-74C51F2C2BFE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284668" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135915" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284668" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:7578F7F48BA6982893F62F2FCB0266C8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7578F7F48BA6982893F62F2FCB0266C8" lastPageNumber="73" pageNumber="73">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="73">
[64] 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27872" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys besucheti Brown" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys besucheti Brown" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="besucheti">Cerapachys besucheti</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="73">(Figs. 79 - 83, 86)</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Holotype worker: TL 4.4, HL 0.86, HW 0.79 (CI 92), ML 0.10, scape L 0.52, greatest diameter of eye 0.05, WL 1.17, petiolar node L 0.41, W 0.46, postpetiole L 0.41, W 0.52 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Paratype workers (8) range downward in body size from that of holotype; where only one measurement is given for a structure, it is the smallest made: TL 4.1, HL 0.80, HW 0.71 (CI 88 - 92), ML 0.09 - 0.12, scape L 0.48, greatest diameter of eye 0.05 - 0.06, WL 1.05, petiolar node L 0.37, W 0.41, postpetiole L 0.40, W 0.47 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Description based on all 9 workers from the type series: A robust member of the fragosus group, with 11 antennal segments and small but convex eyes with 20 - 30 distinct facets in the worker. Details of body form, sculpture, and pilosity are shown well in the figures, so I shall discuss only those characters that do not show well there and those that require emphasis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Head broadest at just about its midlength, at the level of the compound eyes, tapering markedly in front of this, and only slightly behind. Posterior border of head transverse, shallowly concave in full-face view of head, at least in the middle. Anteromedian part of clypeus without a distinct median cannula or tooth. Mandibles triangular with acute apices and sharp, concave, edentate, masticatory borders; external borders straight at midlength; surfaces densely punctate, opaque, but apical third smooth and shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Petiole and postpetiole both broader than long, as seen from above subtrapezoidal, wider behind, with the posterolateral angles subtuberculate, especially in postpetiole. Anterior margin of petiolar node strongly convex, of postpetiole, transverse. Petiole and postpetiole reduced nearly to myrmicine proportions in relation to the enlarged first gastric segment, which dominates the gaster, even when, as in the specimen of fig. 83, the apical gastric segments are extended.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Head, trunk, and both nodes densely reticulate-punctate and prevailingly opaque; gaster also densely and coarsely punctate, but less deeply so, shagreened, the spaces between punctures becoming appreciable only toward the rear of the first tergum, and even then only weakly shining, at most. The short but dense erect and suberect pilosity is supplemented by a still shorter, appressed to decumbent pubescence, best seen in fig. 82 between the larger pilosity hairs. Legs and antennae densely and finely punctulate, opaque or nearly so.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Color even dark reddish brown; light reddish brown in 2 specimens, probably still partly callow; legs scarcely lighter in color than body.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Queen (ergatoid): TL 4.7, HL 0.85, HW 0.77 (CI 91), ML 0.10, scape L 0.46, greatest diameter of eye 0.12, WL 1.22, petiolar node L 0.42, W 0.46, postpetiole L 0.48, W 0.56 mm. Workerlike, but larger and with relatively slightly more robust gaster; vertex with 3 distinct ocelli.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="73">A second ergatoid is even larger: TL 5.1, HL 0.91, HW 0.86 (CI 95), ML 0.11, scape L 0.52, WL 1.36, petiolar node L 0.46, W 0.52, postpetiole L 0.52, W 0.64 mm. In this specimen, the anteromedian ocellus is well developed, but the paired posterior ocelli are indistinct, especially the one on the right side. Compound eyes with many facets, diameter 0.13 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="73">Holotype (MHN — Geneva) and paratypes from a small series taken mixed with other species of ants in a sample of soil and litter (run through a Winkler apparatus) from below Aliyar Dam in the Anaimalai Hills, 1150 m., Madras State, India, by the team of Besuchet, Loebl, and Mussard of MHN — Geneva, 18 November 1972. The species is named for Dr. Claude Besuchet, one of the collectors, a prominent specialist on pselaphid beetles and curator in charge of the famous Forel Collection of ants at the Geneva museum. In this latter capacity, Dr. Besuchet has played a key role in ant systematics through his cheerful and efficient accommodation of myrmecologists seeking aid with respect to the collection.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="73">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27872" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys besucheti Brown" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys besucheti Brown" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="besucheti">C. besucheti</taxonomicName>
is clearly related to the 11 - segmented species of the 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27910" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys fragosus (Roger)" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys fragosus (Roger)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fragosus">fragosus</taxonomicName>
group-----C. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27910" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys fragosus (Roger)" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys fragosus (Roger)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fragosus">fragosus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27883" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys coecus (Mayr)" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys coecus (Mayr)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="coecus">C. coecus</taxonomicName>
[65], but differs in being much larger, with larger, multifacetted eyes and broader, differently shaped petiolar and postpetiolar nodes; the head is also relatively broader and more tapered anteriad. Paratypes in MHN-Geneva, MCZ, BMNH- London and ANIC-Canberra.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>