<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.64.464" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6b201dfe-5a6c-4f3d-a08b-d149b0595eaf" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159360441" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-64-33" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F1778548-C8BC-4EE4-A1BF-0CB5923EFD96" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-64-33" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 64" ModsDocTitle="New species and new records of Mydidae from the Afrotropical and Oriental regions (Insecta, Diptera, Asiloidea)" checkinTime="1451250921296" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Dikow, Torsten" docDate="2010" docId="8866928B9F40DC2E3671F508F7C3EEBA" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 64: 33-75" docOrigin="ZooKeys 64" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.64.464" docTitle="Vespiodes phaios Dikow, 2010, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="F1778548-C8BC-4EE4-A1BF-0CB5923EFD96" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="6" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="46" masterDocId="4628053AE3231F40CA513918057EFFF9" masterDocTitle="New species and new records of Mydidae from the Afrotropical and Oriental regions (Insecta, Diptera, Asiloidea)" masterLastPageNumber="75" masterPageNumber="33" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" updateTime="1643559448288" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species and new records of Mydidae from the Afrotropical and Oriental regions (Insecta, Diptera, Asiloidea)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Dikow, Torsten</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>64</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>33</mods:start>
<mods:end>75</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.64.464</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.64.464</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-64-33</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">6350B33C-AA6C-4202-99B1-DB248DF0D8C3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="159360441" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F1778548-C8BC-4EE4-A1BF-0CB5923EFD96" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8866928B9F40DC2E3671F508F7C3EEBA" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F1778548-C8BC-4EE4-A1BF-0CB5923EFD96" class="Insecta" family="Mydidae" genus="Vespiodes" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Vespiodes phaios" order="Diptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="phaios">Vespiodes phaios</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="12" pageNumber="45">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 13-153548
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">Etymology:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">phaios Greek adjective = brown. Referring the overall brown coloration of this attractive species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">Diagnosis:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">The species is distinguished from congeners by the predominantly apruinose and asetose scutum, the asetose abdominal tergites, features of the male terminalia, and its apparent distribution in south-eastern coastal Kenya.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="description male">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">Description Male:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
Head: brown, in general silver pruinose; width distinctly greater than thorax, interocular distance on vertex larger than at ventral eye margin, vertex between compound eyes slightly depressed, parafacial area less than 
<normalizedToken originalValue="½">1/2</normalizedToken>
the width of central facial gibbosity; facial gibbosity distinct, well-developed and discernible in lateral view; mystax white, covering only lateral facial gibbosity (asetose medially); frons predominantly apruinose, vertex apruinose, postgenae lightly silver pruinose; setation: vertex white, frons white, ocp setae brown or white, pocl setae white; ocellar triangle apruinose; proboscis brown, long, projecting beyond fronto-clypeal suture; labella large, much wider than prementum, about 
<normalizedToken originalValue="½">1/2</normalizedToken>
length of prementum, unsclerotised laterally; maxillary palpi laterally compressed (leaflike), brown or light brown, shorter than length of pedicel.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
Antenna: brown or orange, scape and pedicel white setose dorsally and ventrally; postpedicel cylindrical in proximal 
<normalizedToken originalValue="½">1/2</normalizedToken>
, symmetrically bulbous in distal 
<normalizedToken originalValue="½">1/2</normalizedToken>
, &amp;ge; 11.0 times as long as combined length of scape and pedicel; apical 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‚seta-like‘">'seta-like'</normalizedToken>
sensory element situated apically in cavity on postpedicel.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
Thorax: brown, predominantly apruinose; scutum medially dark brown, laterally brown, surface macrorugose, predominantly apruinose, small antero-lateral spots and extreme lateral margins (dorsal to supero-posterior anepisternum) silver pruinose, scutal setation comprised of distinct rows of long dorsocentral setae and lateral scutal setae; dc setae pre- and postsuturally white, acr setae absent, lateral scutal setae white, npl, spal, and pal setae absent; postpronotal lobe light brown, partly silver pruinose; proepisternum, lateral postpronotum, and postpronotal lobes long brown setose or long white setose; scutellum apruinose, asetose, apical scutellar setae absent; mesopostnotum, anatergite, and katatergite apruinose, mesopostnotum asetose, anatergite asetose, katatergite long white setose; katatergite 
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
flat; anterior anepisternum asetose, supero-posterior anepisternum asetose; posterior anepimeron asetose, katepimeron asetose; metepimeron evenly elevated, same colour as T1, grey pruinose, asetose; metepisternum grey pruinose, asetose.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
Leg: brown, setation predominantly brown; pro coxa apruinose, short white setose, mes coxa apruinose, short white setose, met coxa grey pruinose, white setose; met trochanter setose medially; femora brown, met femur proximally yellow, met femora distinctly clubbed in distal ⅔, in distal 
<normalizedToken originalValue="½">1/2</normalizedToken>
macrosetose, 1 antero-ventral and 1 postero-ventral row of macrosetae; all tibiae laterally arched, met tibia cylindrical, ventral keel absent; pro and mes tarsomere 1 as long as combined length of tarsomeres 2-3, met tarsomere 1 slightly longer than tarsomere 2, tarsomeres 1 and 2 longer than tarsomeres 3 and 4 combined; pulvilli well-developed, as long as well-developed claws, and as wide as base of claws; empodium absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">
Wing: length = 
<quantity metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.59" unit="mm" value="15.9">15.9 mm</quantity>
; slightly brown stained, darker brown stained anterior to and distal to M veins, veins brown, microtrichia absent; cells r1, r4, r5, m3, + cup closed; C terminates at junction with R1; R4 terminates in R1; R5 terminates in R1; stump vein 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="46" start="start">(</pageBreakToken>
<collectionCode>R</collectionCode>
3) at base of R4 present, long but not reaching R2; R4 and R5 widest apart medially; r-m distinct, R4+5 and M1 apart, connected by crossvein; M1 curves anteriorly at r-m, M1 (or 
<collectionCode>M</collectionCode>
1+
<collectionCode>M</collectionCode>
2) terminates in R1; CuA1 and CuA2 split proximally to m-cu (cell m3 narrow proximally); M3+CuA1 do not terminate together in C; A1 undulating, cell a1 wide, A1 and wing margin further apart proximally than distally, alula well-developed; halter brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Abdomen: brown and yellow; setation comprised of scattered white and brown setae, surface entirely smooth; T1 brown, T2-4 brown with yellow anterior margins; T1-3 sparsely white setose; T predominantly apruinose; S1 brown, S2-4 brown with yellow anterior margins; S1 asetose, S2-3 sparsely white setose; S predominantly apruinose; T2-4 distinctly narrowed, forming a waist, abdomen vespiform; bullae on T2 brown, transversely elongate, surface entirely smooth, T2 surface anterior to bullae smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">
Male terminalia: T1-7 well-developed, entirely sclerotised, T8 postero-medially weakly sclerotised, with anterior transverse sclerotised bridge connecting lateral sclerites; T7-8 anteriorly with 2 lateral apodemes; S6 regular, without any special setation postero-medially, S8 well-developed and simple, not fused to T8 dorso-laterally, entire (undivided) ventro-medially; epandrium formed by single sclerite (fused medially 
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
entirely), blunt, evenly rounded; subepandrial sclerite without lateral or median protuberances; hypandrium strongly concave, cup-shaped, entirely sclerotised ventrally (forming a single sclerite), partially fused with gonocoxite anteriorly; gonocoxites dorso-ventrally flattened in distal 
<normalizedToken originalValue="½">1/2</normalizedToken>
, higher in proximal 
<normalizedToken originalValue="½">1/2</normalizedToken>
, without median or lateral protuberance, gonocoxal apodeme present, short (at most slightly extending hypopygium anteriorly); 2 functional aedeagal prongs, short and wide, medio-distally connected; aedeagal epimere present, distally simple, evenly rounded; lateral ejaculatory processes absent; ejaculatory apodeme formed by single dorso-ventrally oriented plate; ventro-median margin of dorsal aedeagal sheath heavily sclerotised (appearing entirely closed); dorsal aedeagal sheath long, sperm sac entirely covered; sperm sac appearing 
<normalizedToken originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
heavily sclerotised.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="46" type="description female">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Description Female:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="46" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">Material examined:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2818988341" collectingDate="2000-03-03" collectionCode="NMKE" collectorName="R. Copeland" country="Kenya" latitude="-4.3247223" location="Muhaka Forest" longLatPrecision="21" longitude="39.524166" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" stateProvince="Coast Province" typeStatus="holotype">
<collectingCountry name="Kenya" value="Kenya">Kenya</collectingCountry>
: 
<collectingRegion>Coast Province</collectingRegion>
: 
<specimenCount type="male">1 ♂</specimenCount>
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:8866928B9F40DC2E3671F508F7C3EEBA:4DEA590B19FD5DBC6059F6F7ED6241A7" country="Kenya" latitude="-4.3247223" longLatPrecision="21" longitude="39.524166" name="Muhaka Forest" stateProvince="Coast Province">Muhaka Forest</location>
, 
<geoCoordinate degrees="04" direction="south" minutes="19" orientation="latitude" precision="15" seconds="29" value="-4.3247223">04°19'29&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate degrees="039" direction="east" minutes="31" orientation="longitude" precision="15" seconds="27" value="39.524166">039°31'27&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, 
<date value="2000-03-03">
<collectingDate value="2000-03-03">3.iii.2000</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName>R. Copeland</collectorName>
(AAM-000153 1 ♂ 
<typeStatus>holotype</typeStatus>
, 
<collectionCode collectionName="Kenya, Nairobi, National Museum of Kenya">NMKE</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="46" type="type locality and distribution">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">
<typeStatus>Type</typeStatus>
locality and distribution:
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="46">
Muhaka Forest (
<geoCoordinate degrees="04" direction="south" minutes="19" orientation="latitude" precision="15" seconds="29" value="-4.3247223">
04°19'29&quot;
<collectionCode>S</collectionCode>
</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate degrees="039" direction="east" minutes="31" orientation="longitude" precision="15" seconds="27" value="39.524166">
039°31'27&quot;
<collectionCode>E</collectionCode>
</geoCoordinate>
), Kenya (Fig. 48). Biodiversity hotspot/high-biodiversity wilderness area: Coastal Forest of Eastern Africa/-.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>