<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.795.28036" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d42ad8e9-98f9-4448-8edf-95f99174b1b0" ID-GBIF-Taxon="149603632" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-795-83" ID-ZBK="B1D0C7E48AAE4A07B193F33761C27D4F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:98D3BEF9-A361-40BF-BDE0-2B9400875C49" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-795-83" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 795" ModsDocTitle="Australobiustracheoperspicuus sp. n., the first subterranean species of centipede from southern China (Lithobiomorpha, Lithobiidae)" checkinTime="1541774111323" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Li, Qing, Pei, Su-jian, Guo, Xuan, Ma, Hui-qin &amp; Chen, Hui-ming" docDate="2018" docId="874081C26219D4A61F7532101835B4B1" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 795: 83-91" docOrigin="ZooKeys 795" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.795.28036" docTitle="Australobius tracheoperspicuus Li, Pei, Guo, Ma &amp; Chen, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="98D3BEF9-A361-40BF-BDE0-2B9400875C49" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="88" masterDocId="FFB5FF9DB96FFF8AFFCBFF90FFAAFFC9" masterDocTitle="Australobiustracheoperspicuus sp. n., the first subterranean species of centipede from southern China (Lithobiomorpha, Lithobiidae)" masterLastPageNumber="91" masterPageNumber="83" pageId="2" pageNumber="85" updateTime="1643532498372" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Australobiustracheoperspicuus sp. n., the first subterranean species of centipede from southern China (Lithobiomorpha, Lithobiidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Qing</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Pei, Su-jian</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Guo, Xuan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ma, Hui-qin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chen, Hui-ming</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>795</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>83</mods:start>
<mods:end>91</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.795.28036</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.795.28036</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-795-83</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">B1D0C7E48AAE4A07B193F33761C27D4F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B1D0C7E48AAE4A07B193F33761C27D4F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="149603632" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:98D3BEF9-A361-40BF-BDE0-2B9400875C49" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/874081C26219D4A61F7532101835B4B1" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="85" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/98D3BEF9-A361-40BF-BDE0-2B9400875C49" class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius tracheoperspicuus" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="2" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tracheoperspicuus">Australobius tracheoperspicuus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="85">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-11, Table 1
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="85" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">Material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
Type material. Holotype: male, Cave of the brickyard of Gaofeng village, Yancang Town, Yi-Hui-Miao Autonomous County of Weining, Bijie City, Guizhou Province, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="26.908596">26°54'30.95&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="104.40383">104°24'13.78&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, alt. 2430 m a.s.l., 19 V 2017, Huiming Chen leg. Paratypes: 1 ♀, 1 ♂, same data as holotype. Other material. 4♂♂(larvae), the Gaodiping Cave of Dashan village, shaanqiao street, Yi-Hui-Miao Autonomous County of Weining, Bijie City, Guizhou Province, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="26.84862">26°50'55.03&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="104.28578">104°17'08.81&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, alt. 2175 m a.s.l., 23 IV 2017, Huiming Chen leg.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="85" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
Antennae with 26 articles, no ocelli, anterior margin of the coxosternite with 5+5 teeth, more or less developed, porodonts slender, between fourth and fifth outer teeth. Tergites without posterior triangular projections, trachea connected to the valve of the T III clearly visible from the dorsal side. Coxal pores 4-6. Tarsal articulation well defined on legs 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–XV">I-XV</normalizedToken>
. No secondary sexual modifications on legs XIV and XV of male. Female gonopods with simple claw, 2+2 spurs. Male gonopods short and small blunt cone bulge, apically slightly sclerotized.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="2" pageNumber="85" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
Body length 17.43 -19.24 mm, cephalic plate 1.76-1.93 mm long, 1.77-1.97 mm wide; the whole body pale 
<normalizedToken originalValue="yellow–brownish">yellow-brownish</normalizedToken>
, tarsus II of all legs more darker, proximal parts of forcipules and the teeth of the anterior margin of the coxosternite brown, all claws of legs 
<normalizedToken originalValue="yellow–brown">yellow-brown</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">Antennae with 26+26 articles; basal article slightly longer than wide, subsequent articles markedly longer than wide, distal article up to 2.5 times as long as wide. Abundant long setae on antennal surface, less so on basal articles, gradual increase in density of setae to about the fourth article, then more or less constant. Length of antenna 7.3-7.4 times width of cephalic plate, and often extending close to posterior edge of T XI (Figure 1).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
Figures 1-12. 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius tracheoperspicuus" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="2" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tracheoperspicuus">Australobius tracheoperspicuus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (holotype male 1-5, 7-9, 11-12 paratype female 6 and 10) 1 Habitus, dorsal view 2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tömösváry’s">Toemoesvary's</normalizedToken>
organ, lateral view 3 Cephalic plate, dorsal view 4 Cephalic plate, ventral view 5 Forcipular coxosternite, ventral view 6 T III of female 7 T III of male 8SS 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–V">I-V</normalizedToken>
9SS VI and VII 10 Posterior segments and gonopods of female, ventral view 11 Posterior segments and gonopods in male, ventral view 12 Living specimen of 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius tracheoperspicuus" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="2" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tracheoperspicuus">Australobius tracheoperspicuus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 13 Cave of the brickyard of Gaofeng village.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
No ocelli on each side of the cephalic plate. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tömösváry’s">Toemoesvary's</normalizedToken>
organ ovate, situated at anterolateral margin of the cephalic plate (Figure 2).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">Cephalic plate smooth, convex, very slightly wider than long; tiny setae emerging from pores scattered very sparsely over whole surface; frontal marginal ridge with shallow anterior median furrow; from short to long setae scattered along marginal ridge of cephalic plate, there more setae close to the antenna; lateral marginal ridge discontinuous (Figure 3).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
Forcipular coxosternite subtrapezoidal (Figure 4), anterior margin broad, external side lightly longer than internal side; median diastema moderately narrow, deeply 
<normalizedToken originalValue="V–shaped">V-shaped</normalizedToken>
; anterior margin with 5+5 blunt teeth; porodonts slender, lying between the fourth and fifth outer teeth, and more closer to the fourth tooth, the innermost tooth more posterior, and the interdental distance gradually increases from the internal side to the external side (Figure 5); some short setae scattered on the ventral side of coxosternite; usually there are more setae near the dental margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="2" pageNumber="85">
All tergites with wrinkles, central backside slightly hunched, T I posterolaterally narrower than anterolaterally, generally trapeziform, narrower than cephalic plate, broader than T III. Trachea connected to the valve of the T III is clearly visible from 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="86" start="start">the</pageBreakToken>
dorsal side (Figs 6-7). Posterior margin of T I slightly concave, posterior margin of TT III, V, VII, VIII, X, XII, XIV and XV concave. Marginal ridge of TT II, IV, VI, IX, X, XI, XII, XIII, XIV and XV bulging; lateral marginal ridge of all tergites 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="87" start="start">continuous</pageBreakToken>
; all posterior angles generally rounded, without triangular projections; tiny setae scattered very sparsely over surface, more densely on anterior and posterior angles (Figure 1). All the tergites more longer than the congeneric species, T X is the longest, at most up to 1.3 times as long as wide.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
Posterior side of sternites narrower than anterior one, generally trapeziform, comparatively smooth, long and thick setae emerging from pores scattered sparsely on surface, more setae on surface of the SS 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–V">I-V</normalizedToken>
(Figure 8), there are two irregular rows short and slightly thinker setae along the posterior margin of the SS VI and VII (Figure 9), few setae on surface of the following SS.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
Legs long and slender, tarsal articulation well defined on legs I-IV; all legs with fairly long curved claws; anterior and posterior accessory spurs on legs 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–XIII">I-XIII</normalizedToken>
anterior accessory spurs moderately long and slender, forming an angle of about 45° with tarsal claws; posterior one slightly strong, forming an angle of about 30° with tarsal claws; no accessory spurs on legs XIV and XV. Comparatively long setae scattered very sparsely over surface of prefemur, femur, tibia and tarsus of legs 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–XIII">I-XIII</normalizedToken>
, more setae scattered on surface of tarsus; dorsal setae slightly longer than ventral, however, more setae in ventral; setae scattered on surface of legs XIV and XV clearly scarcer and short and fine than on other legs. Legs XIV and XV hardly thicker and stronger in both male and female, tarsus I about 6.3-6.6 times as long as wide in legs XV. Tarsus I of legs XV 5.0-5.6 times as long as wide in male, tarsus I of legs XV 5.0-5.6 times as long as wide in male. Leg plectrotaxy as in Table 1.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-Table-UUID="D25CC7DCBFEFB3F2BC7A88DCFB8E6E58" httpUri="http://table.plazi.org/id/D25CC7DCBFEFB3F2BC7A88DCFB8E6E58" pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
Table 1. Leg plectrotaxy of 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius tracheoperspicuus" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tracheoperspicuus">Australobius tracheoperspicuus</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
<table pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="2">Legs</th>
<th colspan="5" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">Ventral side</th>
<th colspan="5" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">Dorsal side</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">C</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">Tr</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">P</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">F</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">
<abbrev id="ABBRID0EQAAE" pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Ti</abbrev>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">C</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">Tr</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">P</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">F</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rowspan="1">
<abbrev id="ABBRID0EEBAE" pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Ti</abbrev>
</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Coxal pores 4-6, most of them round, few ovate, 5-5-6-5 or 5-6-5-5 in female, 4-5-5-4 or 4-4-4-4 in male, coxal pore field set in a relatively shallow groove, fringe of coxal pore field with eminence, moderately long setae scattered sparsely over surface of eminence.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Female S XV anterolaterally broader than posterolaterally, generally trapeziform, posteromedially straight; sternite of genital segment usually well chitinised; posterior margin of genital sternite deeply concave between condyles of gonopods, except for a small, median bulge; long setae scattered over ventral surface of genital segment, regularly fringed, with longer setae along posterior margin. Gonopods: first article fairly broad, second moderately long and slender, coniform spurs in right, inner spur obviously larger than outer one (Figure 10); apical claw of third article simple, slender and sharp (Figure 11). Many long setae on surface of all segments of gonopods.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Male S XV posterolaterally narrower than anterolaterally, posterior edge straight, sparsely covered with long setae; sternite of genital segment smaller than in female, usually well sclerotised. Posterior margin quite deeply concave between gonopods, without a medial bulge; comparatively long setae scattered on ventral surface of genital segment, few slender setae near S XV, setae gradually increasing in density from anterior to posterior, gonopods short and small blunt cone bulge, apically slightly sclerotised (Figure 10).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="87" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">The specific name refers to the trachea connected to the valve of the T III that is clearly visible from the dorsal side.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="87" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">The specimens were collected on the limestone walls and bedrock floor of the cave.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" type="discussion">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="87">Discussion.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="4" pageNumber="87">
The new species resembles 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. magnus" pageId="4" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="magnus">A. magnus</taxonomicName>
(Trozina&gt;, 1894) from North-Western China in having the coxal pores numbering 6-7, no accessory spurs on legs 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="88" start="start">XIV</pageBreakToken>
and XV, DaC spine present on legs 
<normalizedToken originalValue="XIII–XV">XIII-XV</normalizedToken>
, apical claw of female gonopods simple. However, the new species can be easily distinguished by the following characters: trachea connected to the valve of the TIII clearly visible from the dorsal side in new species instead of the trachea connected to the valve of the TIII is invisible from the dorsal side in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. magnus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="magnus">A. magnus</taxonomicName>
; absence of ocellus on each side of the cephalic plate vs. 8-9 ocelli in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. magnus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="magnus">A. magnus</taxonomicName>
; DaC spine being only present on the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="XIIIth–XVth">XIIIth-XVth</normalizedToken>
legs in contrast to being present or absent on 
<normalizedToken originalValue="VIIIth–Xth">VIIIth-Xth</normalizedToken>
legs, present on Xth -XVth legs in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. magnus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="magnus">A. magnus</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
On the other hand, several diagnostic features of the recently described Chinese species that are routinely used in the diagnosis of species of 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Australobius</taxonomicName>
Chamberlin, 1920 are variable within the framework of the original description, perhaps the most conspicuous variation pertains to the number of teeth on the anterior margin of the coxosternite and the numbers of the antennal articles and the ocelli. For example, in the original description of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Australobius</taxonomicName>
, the number of antennal articles is mostly 20, some species more than 24 articles, whereas in many species occurring in China it is higher (Table 2). The same is true for the number of the ocelli, which is few (e.g., 1+3-1+6) or in some species more than 8 in the original description of the genus, whereas in many species occurring in China it is higher (Table 2), and for the number of coxosternal teeth, which is at least 3+3 in the original description, whereas in many species occurring in China it is more variable (Table 2).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
Table 2. Numbers of examined specimens, distribution and main morphological characters of the have known Chinese species of 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Australobius</taxonomicName>
Chamberlin, 1920. Abbreviation: DaC spine, anterior spine of dorsal of coxa.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<table pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. anamagnus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="anamagnus">A. anamagnus</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. apicicornis" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="apicicornis">A. apicicornis</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. magnus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="magnus">A. magnus</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. nodulus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="nodulus">A. nodulus</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. tetrophthalmus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="tetrophthalmus">A. tetrophthalmus</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. tracheoperspicuus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="tracheoperspicuus">A. tracheoperspicuus</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</th>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Ma, H" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="7" pageNumber="90" url="https://doi.org/10.3157/0013-872X(2007)118[77:HPBTCT]2.0.CO;2" year="2008 a">Ma et al. 2008a</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Qin, W" journalOrPublisher="Biologia" pageId="7" pageNumber="90" pagination="1601 - 1605" title="A new species of Australobius (Lithobiomorpha: Lithobiidae) from the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, China." url="https://doi.org/10.2478/s11756-014-0459-4" volume="69" year="2014">Qin et al. 2014</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Trotzina, A" journalOrPublisher="Horae Societatis Entomologicae Rossicae" pageId="7" pageNumber="90" pagination="247 - 253" title="Vier neue Lithobius-Arten aus Central Asia." volume="28" year="1894">Trotzina 1894</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Ma, H" journalOrPublisher="Oriental Insects" pageId="7" pageNumber="90" pagination="335 - 340" title="A new species of Australobius Chamberlin, 1920 (Lithobiomorpha: Lithobiidae) from China." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00305316.2008.10417558" volume="42" year="2008 b">Ma et al. 2008b</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Loksa, I" journalOrPublisher="Acta Zoologica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae" pageId="6" pageNumber="89" pagination="135 - 148" title="Einige neue Diplopoden-und Chilopoden-Arten aus Chinesischen Hoehlen." volume="6" year="1960">Loksa 1960</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Eason, EH" journalOrPublisher="Arthropoda Selecta" pageId="6" pageNumber="89" pagination="117 - 121" title="On some Lithobiomorpha from the mountains of Kirghizia and Kazakhstan (Chilopoda)." volume="6" year="1997">Eason 1997</bibRefCitation>
<bibRefCitation author="Dyachkov, YuV" journalOrPublisher="Ukrainian Journal of Ecology" pageId="6" pageNumber="89" pagination="440 - 443" title="New data on the Australobiusmagnus (Trotzina, 1894) (Chilopoda: Lithobiomorpha: Lithobiidae) from Southern Kazakhstan." url="http://dx.doi.org/10.15421/2017_139" volume="7" year="2017">Dyachkov 2017</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Eason, EH" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Zoology" pageId="6" pageNumber="89" pagination="21 - 34" title="On Lithobiidae from the Seychelles with description of two new species of the subgenusAustralobius, genus Lithobius (Chilopoda: Lithobiomorpha)." url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-7998.1978.tb03263.x" volume="184" year="1978">Eason 1978</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">DaC spine</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">thth</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">thth</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">thththth</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">thth</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">thth</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">th</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">th</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
To assist in the identification of the Chinese species of 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Australobius</taxonomicName>
, numbers of examined specimens, distribution and main morphological characters of the known species of this genus in China is presented (Table 2) and key to the known Chinese species of the genus is presented, these characters are specific only to adults of the taxa occurring in China.
</paragraph>
<subSection pageId="5" pageNumber="88" type="key to the known chinese species of the genus australobius chamberlin, 1920">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
Key to the known Chinese species of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Lithobiidae" genus="Australobius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Australobius" order="Lithobiomorpha" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Australobius</taxonomicName>
Chamberlin, 1920
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<table pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. tracheoperspicuus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="tracheoperspicuus">A. tracheoperspicuus</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. tetrophthalmus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="tetrophthalmus">A. tetrophthalmus</taxonomicName>
(Loksa, 1960)
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. apicicornis" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="apicicornis">A. apicicornis</taxonomicName>
Qin, Lin, Zhao, Li, Xie, Ma, Su &amp; Zhang, 2014
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. magnus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="magnus">A. magnus</taxonomicName>
(Trozina, 1894)
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. anamagnus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="anamagnus">A. anamagnus</taxonomicName>
Ma, Song &amp; Zhu, 2008
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="5" pageNumber="88">
<td colspan="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. nodulus" pageId="5" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="nodulus">A. nodulus</taxonomicName>
Ma, Song &amp; Zhu, 2008
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSection>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>