<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bdfb4b8e-4c36-4386-a7d0-7437b44fcba1" ModsDocID="21061" checkinTime="1252706925963" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Heterick, B. E." docDate="2006" docId="CCA2C200F672A1C01A30D146DAD0B700" docLanguage="en" docName="21061.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 57" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf" docTitle="Monomorium willowmorense" docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="108" masterDocId="3A2C4F9A5833769B5007E7556E53E380" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="202" masterPageNumber="69" pageNumber="107" updateTime="1569525778780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Heterick, B. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>69</mods:start>
<mods:end>202</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">21061</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:CCA2C200F672A1C01A30D146DAD0B700" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CCA2C200F672A1C01A30D146DAD0B700">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="107">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31762" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium willowmorense Bolton" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium willowmorense Bolton" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="willowmorense">Monomorium willowmorense Bolton</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="107">(Fig. 16)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageNumber="107">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31762" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium willowmorense Bolton" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium willowmorense Bolton" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="willowmorense">Monomorium willowmorense Bolton</taxonomicName>
1987:364, fig. 54. South Africa: Willowmore (BMNH, MHNG) [material pertaining to &quot;willowmorensis&quot; and &quot;belli examined].
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="107">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="Upload Failed" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium salomonis subsp. herrero var. willowmorensis" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium salomonis subsp. herrero var. willowmorensis" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="salomonis" subSpecies="herrero" variety="willowmorensis">Monomorium salomonis r. herrero var. willowmorensis Forel</taxonomicName>
1914:245 [unavailable name]. Syntype [[worker]]&quot;s, South Africa: Willowmore (BMNH, MHNG).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="107">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:230058" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium salomonis r. herrero var. belli" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium salomonis r. herrero var. belli" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="salomonis" subSpecies="herrero" variety="belli">Monomorium salomonis r. herrero var. belli Forel</taxonomicName>
1914:245 [unavailable name]. Syntype [[worker]]&quot;s (lectotype for the taxon &quot;willowmorense&quot; here designated from the &quot;belli material [MHNG], the remaining &quot;belli and &quot;willowmorense&quot; material becoming paralectotypes) South Africa: Willowmore (BMNH, MHNG, MCZ).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="107">
Material examined.- Lectotype: [[worker]] (unavailable name &quot;belli&quot;), South Africa, Cape Province, Willowmore, 8. 1. 1914 [G] Arnold (MHNG). A lectotype has been chosen to fix the name, &quot; 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31762" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium willowmorense Bolton" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium willowmorense Bolton" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="willowmorense">Monomorium willowmorense</taxonomicName>
&quot; for the taxon, which is morphologically similar to 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31728" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium subopacum (Smith)" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium subopacum (Smith)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subopacum">M. subopacum</taxonomicName>
. The specimen, originally on a pin holding three pointed specimens, has been transferred to a single pin and the original labels and a lectotype label have been appended to that pin. Paralectotypes: (i) Two workers (&quot;belli&quot;), data the same as for the lectotype (MHNG). Repinned with photocopies of the original labels. (ii) Two workers (&quot;belli&quot;) on separate pin, data as for lectotype (MHNG). (iii) Five workers (unavailable name &quot;willowmorensis&quot;), on two separate pins (i.e., 12 (both damaged) + 13) coll. 1.1.1914, otherwise data same as for lectotype (MHNG). (NB. The measurements of twelve workers from the then syntype series are provided in Bolton 1987).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="107">Other material examined: Prov. Toamasina: S.F Tampolo, 10 km NNE Fenoarivo Atn. 10.iv.1997 B.L. Fisher (1 [[worker]]).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="108" pageNumber="107">Worker description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex planar or weakly concave; frons shining and finely striolate and microreticulate; pilosity of frons consisting of abundant, incurved, appressed setulae only. Eye large, eye width 1.5x greater than greatest width of antennal scape; (in full-face view) eyes set above midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set around midline of head capsule; eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin. Antennal segments 12; antennal club three-segmented. Clypeal carinae weakly to strongly defined; anteromedian clypeal margin broadly convex; paraclypeal setae moderately long and fine, curved; posteromedian clypeal margin extending slightly beyond level of posterior margin of antennal fossae. Anterior tentorial pits situated nearer antennal fossae than mandibular insertions. Frontal lobes sinuate, divergent posteriad. Psammophore absent. Palp formula2,2. Mandibular teeth four; mandibles with sub-parallel inner and outer margins, striate; masticatory margin of mandibles strongly oblique; basal tooth a small to minute denticle or angle, much smaller than t3 (four teeth present).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="108">Mesosoma: Promesonotum shining and microreticulate, microreticulation reduced on humeri; (viewed in profile) promesonotum broadly convex anteriad, convexity reduced posteriad; promesonotal setae absent; standing promesonotal setae consisting of three pairs of longer, incurved, erect or semi-erect setae with occasionally a shorter seta between first anterior pair; appressed promesonotal setulae well-spaced over entire promesonotum. Metanotal groove strongly impressed, with distinct transverse costulae. Propodeum shining and densely microreticulate, distinct striolae present on metapleuron; propodeal dorsum slightly elevated anteriad and sloping away posteriad, propodeal angles not raised; propodeum angulate, propodeal angle blunt; standing propodeal setae absent; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle equidistant from metanotal groove and declivitous face of propodeum. Vestibule of propodeal spiracle absent or not visible. Propodeal lobes present as vestigial flanges or small strips of cuticle only.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="108">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated within anterior sector of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) conical, vertex rounded; appearance of node shining and faintly microreticulate; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) about 1:1; anteroventral petiolar process present as a thin flange tapering posteriad; ventral petiolar lobe present; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole about 4:3; height-length ratio of postpetiole about 1:1; postpetiole shining and microreticulate; postpetiolar sternite not depressed at midpoint, its anterior end an inconspicuous lip or small carina.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="108">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting mainly of short, appressed setulae, together with a few erect and semi-erect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="108">General characters: Color reddish- brown, gaster chocolate. Worker caste monomorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="108">Lectotype measurements: HML 1.54, HL 0.60, 0.49, CeI 82, SL 0.46, SI 94, PW 0.32.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="108">Other worker measurements: HML 1.50 HL 0.60 HW 0.47 CeI 78 SL 0.45 SI 96 PW 0.31 (n=1).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="108">Remarks.- One worker of this otherwise South African species is known from Toamasina Province.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>