<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13552" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e4fd74ce-920a-439a-876d-68e8f6900a08" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648983" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-685-49" ID-ZBK="3D61C25ACF1D4CA2BADBDC2223BCB6AB" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:47BB2E0E-EEB6-4946-816E-954337D32012" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-685-49" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 685" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the genus Amphirhachis Townes, 1970 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Banchinae) from Japan" checkinTime="1502744497386" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Watanabe, Kyohei" docDate="2017" docId="B660ADEBC85B394BD5268A636D4A0264" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 685: 49-64" docOrigin="ZooKeys 685" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13552" docTitle="Amphirhachis fujiei Watanabe, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="47BB2E0E-EEB6-4946-816E-954337D32012" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="53" masterDocId="FFD674026C67F425692B4C33AC696006" masterDocTitle="Revision of the genus Amphirhachis Townes, 1970 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Banchinae) from Japan" masterLastPageNumber="64" masterPageNumber="49" pageId="2" pageNumber="51" updateTime="1643576627272" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the genus Amphirhachis Townes, 1970 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Banchinae) from Japan</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Watanabe, Kyohei</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>685</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>49</mods:start>
<mods:end>64</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13552</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13552</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-685-49</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">3D61C25ACF1D4CA2BADBDC2223BCB6AB</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">3D61C25ACF1D4CA2BADBDC2223BCB6AB</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648983" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:47BB2E0E-EEB6-4946-816E-954337D32012" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B660ADEBC85B394BD5268A636D4A0264" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="53" pageId="2" pageNumber="51">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="51" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/47BB2E0E-EEB6-4946-816E-954337D32012" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amphirhachis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Amphirhachis fujiei" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="51" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fujiei">Amphirhachis fujiei</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="51">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-3, 4-6
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="51" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Clypeus 0.5 times as long as wide. Face 0.6 times as long as wide, without a narrow longitudinal depression between eye and antennal socket. Antenna with 45-47 flagellomeres. Hind femur 5.7-6.1 times as long as maximum depth in lateral view, black. T1 1.8-1.9 times as long as maximum width. Base of T1 without yellow area or spots. T2 0.9-1.0 times as long as maximum width. T2-T7 black with or without white band(s), without red area. Ovipositor sheath 0.3 times as long as hind tibia. Face sometimes without a pair of yellow stripes along inner orbit in female, or entirely yellow in male. Metasomal tergite nearly entirely black in female.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="51" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Female (n = 18). Body length 7.5-11.0 (HT: 9.0) mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Head 0.6 times as long as wide. Clypeus 0.5 times as long as wide. Face slightly convex medially, 0.6 times as long as wide, without a narrow longitudinal depression between eye and antennal socket (Fig. 2). Frons without a longitudinal area before anterior ocellus without punctures. POL 1.0 times as long as OOL. MSL 0.6-0.7 (HT: 0.7) times as long as BWM. Antenna with 45-47 (HT: 45) flagellomeres. F1 1.5-1.8 (HT: 1.8) times as long as F2.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Mesosoma. Mesopleuron without a speculum. Pleural carina present anteriorly, absent posteriorly. Fore wing length 8.0-9.5 (HT: 8.5) mm. Hind femur 5.7-6.1 (HT: 6.0) times as long as maximum depth in lateral view. Hind TS1 2.0 times as long as TS2.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Metasoma. T1 1.8-1.9 (HT: 1.8) times as long as maximum width. T2 0.9-1.0 (HT: 0.95) times as long as maximum width. Ovipositor sheath 0.3 times as long as hind tibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Colouration (Figs 1-3). Body (excluding wings and legs) black, except for: ventral part of clypeus, a pair of spots along inner orbit of face, vertex with a pair of spots between lateral ocellus and eye, mandible excluding apex and base, a median band of flagellum, and a pair of median spots of collar white to whitish yellow. The spot of face sometimes elongated along orbit. Wings hyaline; veins and pterostigma blackish brown to brown except for yellow wing base. Legs black except for: fore and mid femora, tibiae and tarsi partly blackish brown to reddish brown and hind TS2-TS4 white to whitish yellow.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="51">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">
Figures 1-3. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amphirhachis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Amphirhachis fujiei" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="51" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fujiei">Amphirhachis fujiei</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female (holotype). 1 lateral habitus 2 head, anterior view 3 head, mesosoma and metasoma, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Male (n = 9). In body structure, similar to female except for: POL 1.1-1.4 times as long as OOL, MSL 0.5-0.6 times as long as BWM, antenna with 45-50 flagellomeres, F1 1.4-1.6 times as long as F2, hind femur 5.4-6.2 times as long as maximum depth in lateral view, hind TS1 1.9-2.0 times as long as TS2, and T1 1.9-2.1 times as long as maximum width. In colouration, similar to the pattern of female but largely differed (Figs 4-6). Clypeus, face and malar space entirely yellow. Vertex with a pair of yellow spots between lateral ocellus and eye. Palpi, ventral spot of scape and pedicel, median band of flagellum yellow. Collar, posterodorsal corner of pronotum, subalar prominence, dorsal area of mesepimeron and posterior transverse stripe of T2-T7 whitish yellow to yellow. Mesoscutum sometimes with a pair of yellow anterolateral spots. Scutellum sometimes with a pair of yellow spots. Fore and mid legs whitish yellow to reddish yellow. Hind leg black to blackish brown except for whitish yellow trochanter and trochantellus, basal yellowish area of tibia, and TS2-TS5.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="2" pageNumber="51">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">
Figures 4-6. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amphirhachis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Amphirhachis fujiei" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="51" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fujiei">Amphirhachis fujiei</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male (paratype). 4 lateral habitus 5 head, anterior view 6 head, mesosoma and metasoma, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="53" pageId="2" pageNumber="51" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="51">Specimens examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="53" pageId="2" pageNumber="51">
JAPAN: [Holotype] F, Wakayama Pref., Tanabe City, Ryujin Vil., Ryujin, 23. VI. 2012, S. Fujie leg. (KPMNH). [Paratypes] 1 F, Hokkaido, Sapporo City, Mt. Soranuma-dake, 14. VI. - 4. VII. 2007, A. Ueda leg. (MsT) 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="52" start="start">(</pageBreakToken>
KPMNH); 1 M, Hokkaido, Kuriyama Town, 31. VIII. - 13. IX. 2007, A. Ueda leg. (MsT) (KPMNH); 1 M, Hokkaido, Yubari City, Oyubari, 31. VIII. - 13. IX. 2007, A. Ueda leg. (MsT) (KPMNH); 1 M, Hokkaido, Horikanai Town, Moshiri, Uryu, 11-17. VII. 2012, K. Watanabe et al. leg. (MsT) (KPMNH); 1 M, Hokkaido, Mt. Tarumae-san, 12-21. VII. 1998, K. Konishi leg. (MsT.) (NIAES); 1 F, Ibaraki Pref., Kitaibaraki, Ogawa, 27. VI. - 9. VII. 1996, K. Maeto leg. (MsT) (NIAES); 2 F, same locality and collector, 9-25. IX. 1996 (MsT) (NIAES); 1 M, same locality and collector, 20. VIII. - 4. IX. 1996 (MsT) (NIAES); 3 M, Tochigi Pref., Yaita, 30. VI. - 15. VII. 1989, K. Konishi leg. (MsT) (NIAES); 1 F, Kanagawa Pref., Odawara, 4. VI. 1987, H. Makihara leg. (NIAES); 1 F, Kanagawa Pref., Mt. Tanzawa-san, 6. VI. 2013, T. Taniwaki leg. (FIT) (KPMNH); 1 F, Kanagawa Pref., Mt. Oomuro-yama, 16. VI. 2013, T. Taniwaki leg. (FIT) (KPMNH); 1 F, Kanagawa Pref., Mt. Komotsurushi-yama, 21. VI. 2013, T. Taniwaki leg. (FIT) (KPMNH); 1 M, Yamanashi Pref., Hokuto City, Masutomi, Biwakubo-sawa, 28. VII. 2007, T. Ban leg. (KPMNH); 1 F, Yamanashi Pref., Tsuru City, Matsuhime-toge, 28. VII. - 9. VIII. 2008, T. Sakurai &amp; T. Zakoji leg. (KPMNH); 1 F, Yamanashi Pref., Koushu City, Yamato Town, Tokusa, 7. VIII. 2008, T. Muraki leg. (KPMNH); 1 F, Nagano Pref., Shimashima-dani, 28. VII. 1980, H. Takemoto leg. (NIAES); 1 F, Nagano Pref., Outaki Vil., Mt. Ontake-san, Hakkaisan, 8-9. VIII. 2014, S. Shimizu leg. (MsT.) (KPMNH); 1 F, Hyogo 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="53" start="start">Pref</pageBreakToken>
., Kami Town, Niiya, Mikata-kogen (710 m alt.), 26. VI. - 18. VII. 2011, S. Fujie leg. (MsT) (KPMNH); 1 F, Tottori Pref., Mt. Daisen, 24. VI. 1978, Y. Yoneda leg. (NIAES); 1 F, Tottori Pref., Wakasa Town, Mt. Hyonosen, Oodanganaru, 6. VIII. 2011, K. Watanabe leg. (LT) (KPMNH); 1 F, Ehime Pref., Odamiyama, 25. VII. 1995, E. Yamamoto leg. (LT) (NIAES); 1 F, Fukuoka Pref., Mt. Hiko, 5-6. VII. 1979, K. Maeto leg. (NIAES).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="53" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">Japan (Hokkaido, Honshu, Shikoku and Kyushu).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="53" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">
The specific name is from my friend, Mr. Shunpei Fujie, who is a taxonomist of Japanese 
<taxonomicName family="Braconidae" lsidName="" pageId="4" pageNumber="53" rank="family">Braconidae</taxonomicName>
and a collector of types.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="53" type="bionomics">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">Bionomics.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">Host is unknown. The specimens collected from Hyogo (Mt. Hyonosen) and Shikoku were collected by light trap.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="53" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="53">
This species resembles 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. nigra" pageId="4" pageNumber="53" rank="species" species="nigra">A. nigra</taxonomicName>
in the body colouration, but it can be distinguished by the T1 1.8-2.1 times as long as maximum width (2.2-2.8 times in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. nigra" pageId="4" pageNumber="53" rank="species" species="nigra">A. nigra</taxonomicName>
), T2 0.9-1.0 times as long as maximum width (1.1-1.3 times in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. nigra" pageId="4" pageNumber="53" rank="species" species="nigra">A. nigra</taxonomicName>
), the body length 7.0-7.5 mm (54-58 flagellomeres in 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. nigra" pageId="4" pageNumber="53" rank="species" species="nigra">A. nigra</taxonomicName>
) and T2 without a posterior white band in female (usually with a white band in female of 
<taxonomicName genus="A." lsidName="A. nigra" pageId="4" pageNumber="53" rank="species" species="nigra">A. nigra</taxonomicName>
). Males were collected only from Hokkaido and Honshu.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>