<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4800" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4cecba31-25a8-4a32-8866-d41f1c6fd71e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043500" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-294-57" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BE636DF4-CDA8-40D8-98F2-8ECA078706FD" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-294-57" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 294" ModsDocTitle="Afroprinus cavicola gen. et sp. n. from the Afrotropical region with notes on cave-dwelling Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" checkinTime="1451247358633" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lackner, Tomas" docDate="2013" docId="D5D2DE8E877F2085C019E09F4A52FC50" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 294: 57-73" docOrigin="ZooKeys 294" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4800" docTitle="Afroprinus cavicola Lackner, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="BE636DF4-CDA8-40D8-98F2-8ECA078706FD" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="67" masterDocId="D004FFD88B5DA64AFA70A101FFD0FFCB" masterDocTitle="Afroprinus cavicola gen. et sp. n. from the Afrotropical region with notes on cave-dwelling Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" masterLastPageNumber="73" masterPageNumber="57" pageId="2" pageNumber="59" updateTime="1643695674362" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Afroprinus cavicola gen. et sp. n. from the Afrotropical region with notes on cave-dwelling Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lackner, Tomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>294</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>57</mods:start>
<mods:end>73</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4800</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4800</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-294-57</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8F30C8A8-8678-4F29-A44E-A141E507B68B</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043500" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BE636DF4-CDA8-40D8-98F2-8ECA078706FD" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D5D2DE8E877F2085C019E09F4A52FC50" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="2" pageNumber="59">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="59" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BE636DF4-CDA8-40D8-98F2-8ECA078706FD" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Afroprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Afroprinus cavicola" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cavicola">Afroprinus cavicola</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="59">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 121
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="59" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Kenya, Chyulu Hills.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="59" type="type specimens examined">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Type specimens examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">
Holotype, ♂, side-mounted on a triangular mounting card with male genitalia glued to the same card; &quot;KENYA: / Chyulu Hills / Univ. of Nairobi&quot; [written]; &quot;bat droppings / in cave&quot; [written]; &quot;Brit. Mus. / 1972-215&quot; [printed-written]; &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Gnathoncus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gnathoncus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Gnathoncus</taxonomicName>
sp. / P.M. Hammond / det. 1972&quot; [written-printed]; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“09-071”">&quot;09-071&quot;</normalizedToken>
[yellow label, pencil-written, added during the present study]; &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Afroprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Afroprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Afroprinus</taxonomicName>
/ cavicola / n. gen. &amp; sp. / HOLOTYPE / det. T. 
<bibRefCitation pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
&quot; [red label, written] (NMH). Paratypes, 4 ♂♂ and 2 ♀♀, idem, but without the identification label by P.M. Hammond (NMH; 1 ♂ PT in TLAN).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="63" pageId="2" pageNumber="59" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Male and female.Body length: PEL: 2.125-2.375 mm; APW: 0.75-0.875 mm; PPW: 1.625-1.75 mm; EL: 1.375-1.50 mm; EW: 1.875-2.00 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Body (Figs 1, 2) ovoid, convex, ventral surface slightly flattened, cuticle matte, dark brown; legs, mouthparts and antennomeres I and II rufous; remaining part of antenna somewhat lighter.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="59">Antennal scape (Fig. 4) with several short setae; antennal club (Figs 3, 14) round, without visible articulation, somewhat flattened dorso-ventrally; approximately distal half of its surface with thick short sensilla; proximal half with imbricate microsculpture, sensilla absent; sensory structures of antennal club (Fig. 14) with tiny sensory area accompanied by a tiny stipe-shaped vesicle on internal distal margin of antennal club.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="2" pageNumber="59">
Mouthparts. Mandibles (Fig. 12) with rounded outer margin strongly curved inwardly, apically pointed; sub-apical tooth on inner margin of left mandible large, al 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="60" start="start">most</pageBreakToken>
perpendicular; disc of labrum (Fig. 13) convex, labral pits each with two setae; terminal labial palpomere elongate, four times as long as broad; cardo of maxilla with several short setae, stipes triangular, with three long setae; mentum quadrate, anterior 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="61" start="start">margin</pageBreakToken>
with deep median notch, anterior and lateral margins with a row of sparse short ramose setae, disc of mentum with several short setae; terminal maxillary palpomere (Fig. 5) elongate, five times as long as broad, approximately 2.5 times as long as penultimate palpomere.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Anterior margin of clypeus (Fig. 4) slightly elevated, surface punctate, slightly depressed medially; frontal stria well impressed, curved outwardly, carinate, complete; continued as carinate supraorbital stria; disc of frons (Fig. 4) entirely densely and coarsely punctate, punctures separated by spaces shorter than half of their diameter, sparser near margins; eyes flattened, visible in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Pronotal sides (Fig. 1) moderately narrowing anteriorly, anterior angles blunt; marginal pronotal stria complete, slightly carinate, visible along its entire length in dorsal view; pronotal disc entirely punctate, punctures separated by spaces 1-2 times as wide as puncture diameter; pronotal hypomeron setose; scutellum small, inconspicuous.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Elytra: epipleuron with fine scattered punctures; marginal epipleural stria complete; marginal stria straight, well impressed, carinate, continued as intermittent apical stria. Humeral stria well impressed on basal third, somewhat obliterated by coarse punctuation; inner subhumeral stria well developed, visible as long median fragment posteriorly nearly reaching first dorsal stria; with carinate dorsal striae 1-4 (some specimens with a vague fragment of fifth stria on fourth elytral interval); striae 1-3 sub-equal in length, posteriorly reaching approximately five-sixths of elytral length, fourth dorsal stria slightly shorter, anteriorly well-connected with carinate sutural stria; sutural stria straight, well impressed, posteriorly connected with fragmented apical stria; between sutural stria and suture with row of microscopic punctures. Entire surface coarsely and densely punctate, punctures separated by spaces sub-equal to their diameter or shorter, periscutellar area with slightly sparser punctuation; interspaces with isodiametric microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Propygidium (Fig. 7) completely exposed, its punctuation similar to that on elytra and pygidium.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Antero-median margin of prosternum (Fig. 8) straight, rounded laterally; pre-apical foveae deep, connected by marginal prosternal stria; prosternal process apically convex, rounded; carinal prosternal striae (Fig. 8) almost parallel-sided, apically reaching approximately half-length of prosternal process; lateral prosternal striae carinate, terminating in large pre-apical foveae; entire prosternal process with scattered punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Antero-median margin of mesoventrite straight; discal marginal mesoventral stria well impressed, emarginate anteriorly, complete; disc of mesoventrite with scattered round punctuation; meso-metaventral sutural stria undulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Intercoxal disc of metaventrite slightly convex, entirely covered with scattered fine punctures separated by spaces 2-3 times as wide as their diameter, anteriorly punctures becoming coarser and denser, in male more so; lateral metaventral stria (Fig. 10) straight, carinate, almost reaching metacoxa; lateral disc of metaventrite slightly impressed, with deep round punctures; metepisternum + fused metepimeron with distinctly denser punctures; marginal metepisternal stria complete, deeply impressed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Intercoxal disc of first abdominal sternite with complete lateral striae, disc with scattered fine punctures, separated spaces as wide as 3 times puncture diameter.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="63" pageId="5" pageNumber="62">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="62" start="start">Protibia</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 11) slightly dilated; outer margin with 6 short teeth, each topped by short rounded denticle gradually reducing in size towards base of tibia, followed by a minute denticle; setae of outer row sparse, short; setae of median row even shorter; pro 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="63" start="start">tarsal</pageBreakToken>
groove deep; anterior protibial stria carinate, shortened apically; protibial spur minuscule, approximate to tarsal insertion; outer part of posterior surface of protibia smooth, demarcated from median part by distinct straight line; posterior protibial stria complete, terminating in two inner posterior denticles, separating median part of posterior surface from smooth inner part of posterior surface; inner margin of protibia with dense row of lamellate setae that gradually increase in size towards tibial apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Mesotibia (Fig. 6) slender, outer margin with a single row of short denticles gradually increasing in size towards tibial apex; setae of outer row moderately long, sparse, lightly sclerotized; setae of median row much thinner and sparser; posterior stria almost complete and only slightly shortened distally; anterior surface with a row of short denticles on outer margin, surface otherwise smooth; anterior stria complete; apical spur short; apical margin of with several stout denticles; claws of terminal tarsomere slightly bent, shorter than half tarsomere length.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Metatibia (Fig. 9) more slender than mesotibia, its denticles sparser than those of mesotibia, otherwise similar to it.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Male genitalia: Eighth sternite (Figs 15-16) divided longitudinally; vela present, with dense brush of long setae; apex of eighth sternite with one or two short setae (Fig. 15); eighth tergite and eighth sternite fused laterally (Fig. 17). Ninth tergite (Fig. 18) not longitudinally divided medially; spiculum gastrale (Fig. 18) almost parallel-sided, abruptly dilated apically; basal end broadly rounded, spatulate. Aedeagus (Figs 20-21) almost parallel-sided, slightly broadening apically, in apical third curved ventrad; basal piece short, ratio of its length to length of parameres 1: 4; parameres fused almost along their basal two-thirds.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Figures 1-11. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Afroprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Afroprinus cavicola" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cavicola">Afroprinus cavicola</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n., SEM micrographs. 1 habitus, dorsal view 2 ditto, ventral view 3 antennal club, dorso-lateral view 4 head, dorsal view 5 ditto, ventral view 6 mesotibia, dorsal view 7 propygidium and pygidium 8 prosternum 9 metatibia, dorsal view 10 lateral disc of metaventrite + metepisternum 11 protibia, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Figures 12-14. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Afroprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Afroprinus cavicola" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cavicola">Afroprinus cavicola</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n., mouthparts and sensory structures of the antenna. 12 mandibles, dorsal view 13 labrum, left half showing dorsal view; right half showing ventral view 14 antennal club showing sensory structures of the antenna
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Figures 15-21. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Afroprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Afroprinus cavicola" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cavicola">Afroprinus cavicola</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n., male terminalia. 15 eighth sternite and tergite, ventral view 16 ditto, dorsal view 17 ditto, lateral view 18 ninth and tenth tergites, dorsal view; spiculum gastrale, ventral view 19 ninth, tenth tergites and spiculum gastrale, lateral view 20 aedeagus, dorsal view 21 ditto, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
The specific epithet was derived using a compounding method of word formation, by stringing together Latin word 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘caverna’">'caverna'</normalizedToken>
meaning cave and combining element of Latin origin 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘-cola’">'-cola'</normalizedToken>
(orig. colo, ere to inhabit) meaning inhabitant, referring to the cavernicolous habitat of this new species. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="‘Cavicola’">'Cavicola'</normalizedToken>
is a noun in apposition, which is in accordance with ICZN rules; Article 11.9.1.2
</paragraph>
<subSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="key to identification of afrotropical genera of saprininae">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Key to identification of Afrotropical genera of 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Saprininae">Saprininae</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="64" pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
This key is preliminary and in future will be revised, especially in regard to the ill-defined and heterogeneous genera 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hypocacculus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hypocacculus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Hypocacculus</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Chalcionellus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalcionellus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Chalcionellus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pholioxenus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pholioxenus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pholioxenus</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pholioxenus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pholioxenus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pholioxenus</taxonomicName>
shows a discontinuous distribution, with about two-thirds of its species living nidiculously inside burrows and faecal chambers of small ground mammals in the Palaearctic region and one-third found free-living in South Africa, Namibia etc., with a single species of unknown biology (
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pholioxenus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pholioxenus trichoides" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichoides">Pholioxenus trichoides</taxonomicName>
Kapler, 1992) described from north Sudan (
<bibRefCitation pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Mazur 2011</bibRefCitation>
). Revision of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pholioxenus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pholioxenus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pholioxenus</taxonomicName>
is in preparation (Lackner, manuscript). Subgenera, with exceptions of 
<taxonomicName authority="Wenzel, 1962" authorityName="Wenzel" authorityYear="1962" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hesperosaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hesperosaprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Hesperosaprinus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authority="Bickhardt, 1909" authorityName="Bickhardt" authorityYear="1909" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Neosaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neosaprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Neosaprinus</taxonomicName>
of the Nearctic and mainly Neotropical genus 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Euspilotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euspilotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Euspilotus</taxonomicName>
which are pertinent to this key, are excluded, since they fall within the limits of their respective genera. Limits of the Afrotropical region are according to 
<bibRefCitation author="Loebl, I &amp; Smetana A" journalOrPublisher="Apollo Books, Stenstrup" pageId="12" pageNumber="69" title="Catalogue of Palaearctic Coleoptera, Vol. 2, Hydrophiloidea-Histeroidea-Staphylinidea." year="2004">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Löbl">Loebl</normalizedToken>
and Smetana (2004)
</bibRefCitation>
and encompass the 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="64" start="start">entire</pageBreakToken>
continent of Africa south of Sahara, the island of Madagascar, along with Cape Verde Archipelago, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="São">Sao</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Tomé">Tome</normalizedToken>
&amp; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Príncipe">Principe</normalizedToken>
, Seychelles, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Réunion">Reunion</normalizedToken>
, Comoros, island of Saint Helena and other smaller islands.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<table lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="7" pageNumber="64">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
1
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="7" pageNumber="64">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">Fig. 22</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pilisaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pilisaprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pilisaprinus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Lackner, T" journalOrPublisher="Folia Heyrovskyana, Series A" pageId="12" pageNumber="69" pagination="43 - 72" title="Revision of the genus Terametopon, with description of new species (Coleoptera: Histeridae)." volume="17" year="2009">Lackner 2009</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Terametopon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Terametopon" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Terametopon</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicName authority="Gomy &amp; Vienna, 1996" authorityName="Gomy &amp; Vienna" authorityYear="1996" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Psammoprinus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Psammoprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Psammoprinus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Gnathoncus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gnathoncus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Gnathoncus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">Fig. 8</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">Fig. 23</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Euspilotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euspilotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Euspilotus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicName authority="Bickhardt, 1909" authorityName="Bickhardt" authorityYear="1909" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Neosaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neosaprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Neosaprinus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">Fig. 24</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Euspilotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euspilotus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Euspilotus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicName authority="Wenzel, 1962" authorityName="Wenzel" authorityYear="1962" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hesperosaprinus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hesperosaprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Hesperosaprinus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">Fig. 4</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation author="Lackner, T" journalOrPublisher="Folia Heyrovskyana, Series A" pageId="12" pageNumber="69" pagination="43 - 72" title="Revision of the genus Terametopon, with description of new species (Coleoptera: Histeridae)." volume="17" year="2009">Lackner 2009</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Terametopon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Terametopon" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Terametopon</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Terametopon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Terametopon" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Terametopon</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">Fig. 4</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="7" pageNumber="64">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
2
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="7" pageNumber="64">
<td colspan="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="64" rowspan="1">Fig. 25</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="65" start="start">Fig</pageBreakToken>
. 26Fig. 25
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pachylopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pachylopus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pachylopus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 27</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Neopachylopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neopachylopus secqi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="secqi">Neopachylopus secqi</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 1</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 28Fig. 29</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Parahypocaccus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parahypocaccus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Parahypocaccus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 30Fig. 31Fig. 32</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Paraphilothis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paraphilothis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Paraphilothis</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 4</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 4</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pholioxenus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pholioxenus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pholioxenus</taxonomicName>
3
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="8" pageNumber="65">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Chalcionellus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalcionellus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Chalcionellus</taxonomicName>
4
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 1</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Afroprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Afroprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Afroprinus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="8" pageNumber="65">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 33</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Dahlgrenius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dahlgrenius" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Dahlgrenius</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="65">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="65" rowspan="1">Fig. 4</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="9" pageNumber="66">
<td colspan="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="66" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) caeruleatus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="caeruleatus" subGenus="Saprinus">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="66" start="start">Saprinus</pageBreakToken>
(Saprinus) caeruleatus
</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="67" start="start">Lackner</pageBreakToken>
2010
</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">Fig. 34Fig. 35</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Exaesiopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Exaesiopus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Exaesiopus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="10" pageNumber="67">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hypocaccus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hypocaccus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Hypocaccus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">
<bibRefCitation pageId="10" pageNumber="67">Lackner 2010</bibRefCitation>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Hypocacculus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Hypocacculus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Hypocacculus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<td colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pholioxenus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pholioxenus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pholioxenus</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
Figures 22-29. Assorted 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Saprininae">Saprininae</taxonomicName>
characters. 22 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Pilisaprinus) verschureni" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="verschureni" subGenus="Pilisaprinus">Saprinus (Pilisaprinus) verschureni</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Thérond">Therond</normalizedToken>
, 1959, prosternum 23 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Euspilotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euspilotus (Neosaprinus) rubriculus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rubriculus" subGenus="Neosaprinus">Euspilotus (Neosaprinus) rubriculus</taxonomicName>
(Marseul, 1855), prosternum 24 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Euspilotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euspilotus (Hesperosaprinus) modestus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="modestus" subGenus="Hesperosaprinus">Euspilotus (Hesperosaprinus) modestus</taxonomicName>
(Erichson, 1834), prosternum 25 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pachylopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pachylopus dispar" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dispar">Pachylopus dispar</taxonomicName>
Erichson, 1834, female, ventral view 26 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Pachylopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pachylopus dispar" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dispar">Pachylopus dispar</taxonomicName>
Erichson, 1834, protibia, dorsal view 27 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Neopachylopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neopachylopus secqi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="secqi">Neopachylopus secqi</taxonomicName>
Kanaar, 1998, protobia, dorsal view 28 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Parahypocaccus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parahypocaccus weyerichi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="weyerichi">Parahypocaccus weyerichi</taxonomicName>
Vienna, 1995, prosternum 29 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Parahypocaccus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parahypocaccus weyerichi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="weyerichi">Parahypocaccus weyerichi</taxonomicName>
Vienna, 1995, head, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="67">
Figures 30-35. Assorted 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Saprininae">Saprininae</taxonomicName>
characters. 30 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Paraphilothis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paraphilothis mirabilis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirabilis">Paraphilothis mirabilis</taxonomicName>
Vienna, 1994, head, dorsal view 31 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Paraphilothis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paraphilothis mirabilis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirabilis">Paraphilothis mirabilis</taxonomicName>
Vienna, 1994, protibia, dorsal view 32 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Paraphilothis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paraphilothis mirabilis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirabilis">Paraphilothis mirabilis</taxonomicName>
Vienna, 1994, habitus, dorsal view 33 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Dahlgrenius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dahlgrenius aurosus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aurosus">Dahlgrenius aurosus</taxonomicName>
(Bickhardt, 1921), head, dorsal view 34 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Exaesiopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Exaesiopus laevis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laevis">Exaesiopus laevis</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Thérond">Therond</normalizedToken>
, 1964, protibia, dorsal view 35 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Exaesiopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Exaesiopus laevis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laevis">Exaesiopus laevis</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken originalValue="Thérond">Therond</normalizedToken>
, 1964, metatibia, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSection>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>