<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914" ID-GBIF-Dataset="0e37f739-024b-4e12-a7e0-1aaaaf571dfc" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031410" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-136-47" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A0935C7F-E1D7-4211-8B4F-CDE0A020869A" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-136-47" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 136" ModsDocTitle="Larvae and a new species of Ancyronyx Erichson, 1847 (Insecta, Coleoptera, Elmidae) from Palawan, Philippines, using DNA sequences for the assignment of the developmental stages" checkinTime="1451249787770" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Freitag, Hendrik &amp; Balke, Michael" docDate="2011" docId="13783224FEE2018B6CC3FD47DC27B81F" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 136: 47-82" docOrigin="ZooKeys 136" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914" docTitle="Ancyronyx montanus Freitag, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="A0935C7F-E1D7-4211-8B4F-CDE0A020869A" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="69" masterDocId="FF89FF98C22CFFB4FFFBFFDEF932FFB9" masterDocTitle="Larvae and a new species of Ancyronyx Erichson, 1847 (Insecta, Coleoptera, Elmidae) from Palawan, Philippines, using DNA sequences for the assignment of the developmental stages" masterLastPageNumber="82" masterPageNumber="47" pageId="19" pageNumber="66" updateTime="1643721589485" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Larvae and a new species of Ancyronyx Erichson, 1847 (Insecta, Coleoptera, Elmidae) from Palawan, Philippines, using DNA sequences for the assignment of the developmental stages</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Freitag, Hendrik</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Balke, Michael</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>136</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>47</mods:start>
<mods:end>82</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-136-47</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">39E11554-5C45-4B0A-97EC-3387391E9027</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031410" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A0935C7F-E1D7-4211-8B4F-CDE0A020869A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/13783224FEE2018B6CC3FD47DC27B81F" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="69" pageId="19" pageNumber="66">
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="66" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="66">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A0935C7F-E1D7-4211-8B4F-CDE0A020869A" authority="Freitag" class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx montanus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="montanus">Ancyronyx montanus Freitag</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="19" pageNumber="66">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 7, 816
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–P17A–K">A-P17A-K</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="66" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="66">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="66">
Holotype ♂ (NMW [FR012]) &quot;PHIL.: Palawan, P.Princesa; Concepcion, Taranaban R. trib.;mount.creek c.8km upstr.; dist. prim. forest; riffle;rocks, boulders,roots; c.450m asl 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="10.083333">10°05'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="119.01667">119°01'E</geoCoordinate>
, 28.1.1995 leg. Freitag (16f)M&quot;, terminal parts of abdomen incl. aedeagus glued separately, two tarsi lacking. Paratypes: 1♀ (NMW), 1L (0.37) (ZSM [FR038]): same data as holotype; 2♂, 4L (0.30, 0.31, 0.36, 0.37) (SMTD, UPLB, NMW, CFP) &quot;PHIL.: Palawan, Roxas, Bgy.Dumarao downstr. New Rizal Falls, sec. forest, c. 120m asl; boulders, sand, CPOM; 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="10.469444">10°28'10&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="119.33111">119°19'52&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
05.12.1994, leg. Freitag (135)M&quot;.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="19" pageNumber="66" type="adult description">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="66">Adult description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="66">Body 1.82-1.88 mm long (CL), 0.79-0.83 mm broad (EW), 2.2-2.4 times as broad as wide (CL/EW). Body form elongate, moderately convex dorsally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="66">Colouration (Fig. 7) predominantly dark brown to black; legs pale brown to dark brown, (articulations slightly darker); claws and antennae pale brown (distal antennal segment darker); elytra without pale patches; ventral side slightly paler than dorsal, but still dark brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="66">Head (Figs 7; 16A, B) 0.41-0.45 mm broad (HW); ID 0.28-0.26 mm; labrum (Fig. 16A) micropunctate, moderately densely covered with long and trichoid setae; frons (Fig. 16A) punctate; clypeus (Fig. 16A) reticulate, moderately densely pubescent; frontoclypeal suture almost straight, slightly impressed. Eyes protruding (Figs 16A, B). Antennae (Fig. 16A) 11-segmented, slender, very slightly longer than head broad. Gula (Fig. 16B) microreticulate, moderately pubescent; gular sutures inconspicuous.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="20" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="19" pageNumber="66">
Pronotum (Figs 7; 16C) 0.54-0.65 mm long (PL), 0.52-0.57 mm broad (MW), slightly longer than wide (PL/MW), widest at about posterior 0.2, distinctly narrower than elytra, anteriorly attenuate; anterior margin slightly acuate; margin between pronotum and hypomeron inconspicuous; anterior transverse groove distinct and moderately 
<pageBreakToken pageId="20" pageNumber="67" start="start">deeply</pageBreakToken>
impressed, medially shallower; anteriorly and posteriorly of transverse groove gently vaulted; posterolateral oblique grooves shallow, inconspicuous; pronotal surface entirely distinctly reticulate; hypomeron reticulate. Prosternum (Fig. 16D) reticulate; prosternal process distinctly narrower medially, medially impressed, posterior margin obtuse.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="20" pageNumber="67">
Scutellum subpentagonal, anteriorly slightly impressed, glabrous. Elytra (Figs 7; 16E) elongate, 1.16-1.35 mm long (EL), c. 1.6-1.8 times as long as wide (EL/EW), almost parallel-sided in anterior 0.1-0.7, posteriorly roundly convergent to apices; elytral apices separately rounded; with c. 10 longitudinal, quite regular, deeply impressed rows of punctures (five strial rows between suture and shoulder); punctures large and deeply impressed; interstices and intervals convex, granulous; lateral elytral gutter moderately broad; humeri prominent. Mesoventrite (Fig. 16D) very short, with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="21" pageNumber="68" start="start">longitudinal</pageBreakToken>
impression, with few deep punctures. Metaventrite (Fig. 16F) prominent, with distinct discrimen, subanteriorly and medially impressed along the groove, lateral parts punctate to reticulate; anepisternum 3 prominent, with two irregular rows of punctures. Hind wings present; venation not examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">Legs slightly longer than body; pro- and mesocoxae large, globular; metacoxae only slightly protruding laterally; femora, tibiae, and tarsi (except distal tarsal segment) covered with elongate setiferous tubercles; tibiae distally with a distinct rim of setae; claws (Fig. 16G) well developed, rather gently curved; base of each claw with three teeth, distal one largest, basal one shortest.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Ventrites 1-4 almost glabrous, posteromedially punctate, reticulate anteriorly and laterally; ventrite 5 (Figs 16
<normalizedToken originalValue="H–J">H-J</normalizedToken>
), moderately densely covered with short adpressed setae emerging from flat tubercles; lateral projection small and inconspicuous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">Sternite IX (spiculum gastrale) as in Fig. 16K; apical margin almost straight, only very slightly emarginate; paraprocts short, not reaching apical margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Aedeagus (Figs 16
<normalizedToken originalValue="L–N">L-N</normalizedToken>
) very similar to that of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx punkti" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="punkti">Ancyronyx punkti</taxonomicName>
(see Freitag &amp; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
, 2007: Figs 13a, b), but distinctly larger, 440-490 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long. Median lobe moderately long and slender, distinctly widened subapically (c. 80 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
broad), slightly curved ventrad, with numerous distinct microtube-like structures ending sublateroapically; ventral sac weekly sclerotized; fibula well sclerotized, conspicuous in transillumination (Fig. 16L); corona well developed. Phallobase asymmetrical, slightly widened ventrally, with conspicuous, strongly sclerotized margin; basolateral (penile) apophyses rather short. Parameres elongately subtriangular with basal margin strongly emarginate (lateral view, Fig. 16N), reaching about basal 0.63 of aedeagus, not contiguous ventrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Ovipositor (Fig. 16O). Total length c. 620 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
. Stylus slender, slightly bent outwards (partly broken off in specimen examined). Coxite long and slender, distal portion distinctly elongate, with several comparably long, lanceolate setae, most densely set at apex; mesal margin densely pubescent; basal portion c. half as long as distal portion, with same type of setae in distinct patterns as in Fig. 16O. Valvifer about as long as coxite; fibula (mesal, longitudinal sclerotisation) genus typical as in Fig. 16O.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">Secondary sexual characters. Sternite VIII in female (Fig. 16P) with median strut apically widened, almost truncate, posterior portion slightly pubescent; sternite VIII in male weakly sclerotized, median strut distinctly shorter than in female. Ventrite 5 in female subtriangular (Fig. 16I), in male (Fig. 16J) shorter and suboval. Tergite VIII in female (Fig. 16Q) longer than broad; condyles more or less straight and prominent; reticulations only conspicuous laterally. Tergite VIII in male (Fig. 16R) broader than long, reticulation more developed than in female covering apical half; basal half patterned with lines of asperities; condyles not distinctly curved, overreaching anterior margin.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Figure 16. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx montanus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="montanus">Ancyronyx montanus</taxonomicName>
Freitag &amp; Balke, sp. n., (SEM photographs with grey background, stereo microscope photographs with white background) adult male: A head, dorsal, B head, ventral, C pronotum, dorsal, D pro-, meso-, and metaventrite, ventral, E elytra, dorsal, F meso- and metacoxae, metaventrite, ventrites 1-2, ventral, G hind claw, H ventrite 5, ventral; adult female: I ventrite 5, ventral; adult male: J ventrite 5, ventral, K sternite IX, L &amp; M aedeagus, ventral, N aedeagus, lateral; adult female: O ovipositor, ventral, P sternite VIII, ventral, Q tergite VIII, dorsal; adult male: R tergite VIII, dorsal.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Figure 17. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx montanus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="montanus">Ancyronyx montanus</taxonomicName>
Freitag &amp; Balke, sp. n., larva (SEM photographs), A abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="VI–VIII">VI-VIII</normalizedToken>
, dorsal, B lateral and parts of median sclerites of abdominal venter, with different types of setae and lateral projections, C posterolateral abdominal projection with trichoid tooth, D head, dorsolateral, E head, dorsal, F head, ventral, G prothorax, ventral, H thoracic and first abdominal segments, ventral, I hindleg, lateral, J operculum, ventral, K abdominal segments VIII and IX, dorsal.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="21" pageNumber="68" type="adult differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">Adult differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx montanus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="montanus">Ancyronyx montanus</taxonomicName>
superficially resembles dark specimens of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx patrolus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="patrolus">Ancyronyx patrolus</taxonomicName>
(Freitag &amp; 
<bibRefCitation pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
2004
</bibRefCitation>
: Fig. 4), from which it can be easily distinguished by the larger size, slenderer body (EL/EW), the entirely reticulate pronotal surface that lacks any glabrous areas, the medially narrowed prosternal process and its genital characters.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="21" pageNumber="68" type="larval description (based on 6th instar)">
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">Larval description (based on 6th instar).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Colour as in Fig. 8: very similar to that of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx patrolus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="patrolus">Ancyronyx patrolus</taxonomicName>
, but overall darker and somewhat shiny; legs entirely pale brown to yellowish. Mouthparts and surrounding portions not distinctly darker than dorsal and ventral head portions. Without pale pattern at dorsal thoracic and abdominal segments; only apex of abdominal segment slightly paler. Ventral side pale brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
HW 0.37-0.41 mm; entire larva up to 3.3 mm long. Body shape as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx patrolus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="patrolus">Ancyronyx patrolus</taxonomicName>
, except for the following: entire body more vaulted in cross section; dorsal sagittal area flat, with rather indistinct sagittal line, without carina at all thoracic and abdominal segments. Setiferous tubercles at dorsal side rather flat, not as elevated as in the other species (Fig. 17A), those of ventral side very flat and inconspicous (Fig. 17B). Setae originated from tubercles (Figs 17
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
) lanceolate to trichoid and distinctly longer than in the previous species. Posterolateral abdominal projections comparably small, attenuate, distinctly larger at anterior abdominal segments (Figs 8, 17C). Trichoid teeth not reaching middle of subsequent abdominal segment when that retracted.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Head (Figs 8, 17D-F) basically as in the previous species, but with the following varying characters: broadest posterior 0.25, laterally slightly convex. Glabrous area with stemmata not exposed. With few long, trichoid setae on lateral sides and one dorsolateral pair of long double setae (Figs 17
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
). Entire head more or less densely covered with squamose to fascicular setae originated from slightly elevated tubercles and additionally with several moderately long trichoid setae (Figs 17
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–F">E-F</normalizedToken>
). Frontal suture V-shaped. Fasciculate setae at subbasal fringe of clypeus very long, overreaching labrum (Fig. 17E); labrum with large fasciculate setae (Fig. 17E). Gula, maxillae and labium (Fig. 17F) almost as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx minerva" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minerva">Ancyronyx minerva</taxonomicName>
, but with few squamose setae and shorter maxillary and labial palpi. Mandibles as in Fig. 17E. Antennae (Fig. 17E) almost as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx patrolus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="patrolus">Ancyronyx patrolus</taxonomicName>
, scapus with large plumose setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Pro-, meso- and metathorax as in Figs 8 and 17G, H. Thoracic terga with small round signa in sublateral portions; sagittal line rather inconspicuous. Thoracic venters (Figs 17G, H) with asperities and irregularly distributed setiferous tubercles; anterior sclerites and posterior portion of lateral sclerites of prothorax (Fig. 17G) densely covered with tubercles. Posteromedial sclerite bald and rugulose. Meso- and metathorax with scattered setiferous tubercles at distal portions of all sclerites, lateral sclerite portions densely covered with asperities (Fig. 17H). Legs (Fig. 17I) similar to those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx patrolus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="68" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="patrolus">Ancyronyx patrolus</taxonomicName>
, but with comparably long and slender femora (c. as long as tibiae); coxae with distinct asperities; other surfaces rather glabrous. Claws slender and long, moderately bent (Fig. 17I).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="68">
Abdomen (Figs 8; 17
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="J–K">J-K</normalizedToken>
) without any elevations or carinae at dorsal sagittal area; segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–VI">I-VI</normalizedToken>
with a pair submedian trichoid setae, that are distinctly longer than surrounding lanceolate to trichoid setae (Fig. 17A). Ventral sclerite of first segment without sagittal ridge (Fig. 17H). Apex of segment IX distinctly emarginate (Fig. 17K). Operculum (Fig. 17J) subovate, medially slightly impressed, with scattered lanceolate setae in apical and lateral portions.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="variation between larval instars">
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">
<pageBreakToken pageId="22" pageNumber="69" start="start">Variation</pageBreakToken>
between larval instars.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">The two specimens of prefinal instar stage vary most conspicuously from the above description by the overall paler brown colour, the more conspicuous dorsal setiferous tubercles that let the pronotal signa appear clearly as well as the slightly crested (in cross-section subtriangular) abdominal segment IX.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="larval differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">Larval differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">The species is easily distinguishable from other Palawan species by the lack of any dorsosagittal carinae or elevations, the dark, shiny dorsal colour, its rather large size and the rather shallow dorsal tubercles bearing comparably long, lanceolate to trichoid setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">Only known from the type locality in central Palawan and one site in northern Palawan (Fig. 20).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="22" pageNumber="69">The species is named in reference to the remote mountainous river habitats where it was exclusively recorded from.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>