<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4333517" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f31ce7c7-fd74-4fcd-a871-1c9686763142" ID-GBIF-Taxon="167293012" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4333517" ID-ZooBank="B6053570-C067-45A8-9124-AA703777A045" checkinTime="1598055659936" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Sanborn, Allen F." docDate="2019" docId="03EE0B02B0724A00FF6647E35DB6E822" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4614.3.1.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4614 (3)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Selymbria chevauxensis Sanborn 2019, n. sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="8" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="412" masterDocId="FFD7737AB07A4A0BFFF1453A5D42EB7D" masterDocTitle="The cicada genus Selymbria Stå 1, 1861 (Hemiptera: Cicadidae: Tibicininae: Selymbrini): redescription including ten new species and a key to the genus" masterLastPageNumber="448" masterPageNumber="401" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" updateTime="1632022006054" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The cicada genus Selymbria Stå 1, 1861 (Hemiptera: Cicadidae: Tibicininae: Selymbrini): redescription including ten new species and a key to the genus</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sanborn, Allen F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2019-06-11</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4614</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>3</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>401</mods:start>
<mods:end>448</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4614.3.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">f31ce7c7-fd74-4fcd-a871-1c9686763142</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">3995202</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B6053570-C067-45A8-9124-AA703777A045</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4333517" ID-GBIF-Taxon="167293012" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4333517" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EE0B02B0724A00FF6647E35DB6E822" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03EE0B02B0724A00FF6647E35DB6E822" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="412" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
<subSubSection box="[151,516,729,756]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,516,729,791]" box="[151,516,729,756]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,516,729,756]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,516,729,756]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[151,442,729,756]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="chevauxensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,442,729,756]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Selymbria chevauxensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[449,516,729,755]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,236,765,791]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,516,729,791]" box="[151,236,765,791]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
(
<figureCitation box="[160,227,765,791]" captionStart="FIGURE 2" captionStartId="10.[151,250,1908,1933]" captionTargetBox="[203,1384,170,1896]" captionTargetId="figure@10.[203,1384,170,1896]" captionTargetPageId="10" captionText="FIGURE 2. Selymbria chevauxensis n. sp.: A, holotype male and paratype female habitus; B, holotype male dorsum; C, holotype male timbal cover; D, paratype male operculum; E, paratype female operculum; F, holotype male lateral view of genitalia; G, holotype male posterior view of genitalia; H, paratype female lateral view of genitalia; I, paratype female ventral view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 5 mm; C–E, 2 mm; F–G, 1 mm; H–I, 2 mm." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3995206" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3995206/files/figure.png" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Fig. 2</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="409" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,1437,836,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
<collectionCode box="[151,311,837,863]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">TYPE MATERIAL</collectionCode>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2847252318" collectingDate="2013-05-25" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="Soc. Ent. Antilles-Guyane" country="French Guiana" location="Montagne des Chevaux" municipality="Gemlight" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" specimenCount="1" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[325,433,837,863]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Holotype</typeStatus>
. “ 
<collectingCountry box="[452,681,837,863]" name="French Guiana" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">FRENCH GUIANA</collectingCountry>
/ 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EE0B02B0724A00FF6647E35DB6E822:8E98ECCFB0724A03FD4C467F5E87E822" box="[701,965,837,863]" country="French Guiana" municipality="Gemlight" name="Montagne des Chevaux" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Montagne des Chevaux</location>
/ 
<collectingMethod box="[984,1227,837,863]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Automatic Light Trap</collectingMethod>
/ 
<collectingMunicipality box="[1248,1354,837,863]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Gemlight</collectingMunicipality>
<date pageId="8" pageNumber="409" value="2013-05-25">
<collectingDate pageId="8" pageNumber="409" value="2013-05-25">25–V– 2013</collectingDate>
</date>
/ 
<collectorName box="[231,525,873,899]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Soc. Ent. Antilles-Guyane</collectorName>
coll.” male (
<collectionCode box="[672,748,873,899]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2847252313" collectingDate="2013-08-31" collectionCode="AFSC" collectorName="Soc. Ent. Antilles-Guyane" country="French Guiana" location="Montagne des Chevaux" municipality="Gemlight" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" specimenCount="1" typeStatus="paratype">
<typeStatus box="[768,877,873,899]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Paratypes</typeStatus>
. “ 
<collectingCountry box="[901,1131,873,899]" name="French Guiana" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">FRENCH GUIANA</collectingCountry>
/ 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EE0B02B0724A00FF6647E35DB6E822:8E98ECCFB0724A03FB73465358CFE8FE" box="[1154,1421,873,899]" country="French Guiana" municipality="Gemlight" name="Montagne des Chevaux" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Montagne des Chevaux</location>
/ 
<collectingMethod box="[151,396,909,935]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Automatic Light Trap</collectingMethod>
/ 
<collectingMunicipality box="[417,523,909,935]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Gemlight</collectingMunicipality>
<date box="[530,690,909,935]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" value="2013-08-31">
<collectingDate box="[530,690,909,935]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" value="2013-08-31">31–VIII–2013</collectingDate>
</date>
/ 
<collectorName box="[712,1004,909,935]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Soc. Ent. Antilles-Guyane</collectorName>
coll.” one female (
<collectionCode box="[1218,1294,909,935]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">AFSC</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="409" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,1437,836,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
ETYMOLOGY. The name is a combination of 
<emphasis box="[716,833,945,971]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">chevaux—</emphasis>
for the 
<typeStatus box="[923,971,945,971]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">type</typeStatus>
locality and— 
<emphasis box="[1148,1204,946,971]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">ensis</emphasis>
(L. suffix denoting place).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="412" pageId="8" pageNumber="409" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,1437,836,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">DESCRIPTION. Ground color of head and thorax tawny marked with piceous in male, ochraceous marked with piceous and fuscous in female, male abdomen castaneous and ochraceous, female abdomen ochraceous. Color may be chemically altered from a more greenish or greenish-tawny in fresh or live specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,1437,836,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
<emphasis box="[199,267,1125,1151]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Head.</emphasis>
Head wider than pronotal collar lateral angles and mesonotum, frons piceous, lateral ocelli surrounded by piceous, mark extending anteriorly along anterior arm of epicranial suture and posteriorly lateral to epicranial suture to posterior margin of head, triangular piceous mark extending and widening from anterior terminus of anterior arm of epicranial suture onto vertex and posteromedial supra-antennal plate, marks reduced in 
<typeStatus box="[1259,1355,1233,1259]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
so that anterior arm of epicranial suture is ground color, fuscous transverse mark on posterior head except across posterior epicranial suture, absent in 
<typeStatus box="[457,556,1305,1331]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
, piceous medial and anteromedial margin to eye, posterior to eye piceous, posterior eye edged in piceous in 
<typeStatus box="[483,583,1341,1367]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
. Long silvery pile posterior to eye. Ocelli rosaceous, eyes testaceous. Ventral head tawny, piceous fascia expanding medially from margin of eye, reduced to spot along eye margin in 
<typeStatus box="[1333,1432,1377,1403]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
, piceous from posterior eye terminating on ventral eye, long silvery pile on lorum and gena. Postclypeus tawny with a castaneous fasciae along midline of central sulcus expanding anteriorly, reduced in 
<typeStatus box="[1122,1221,1449,1475]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
, piceous triangular mark on dorsal postclypeus, with nine transverse grooves, most dorsal transverse groove piceous, second and third transverse grooves piceous in lateral half, next three transverse grooves with medial castaneous fasciae, long silvery pile on lateral postclypeus. Anteclypeus with transverse castaneous fascia across posterior carina, small piceous spots in posterolateral corners, covered with silvery pile. Mentum and proximal half of lateral labium tawny, castaneous medial labium becoming piceous distally except for castaneous tip, tip not reaching to posterior of middle leg coxae, with sparse short silvery pile, denser near tip. Scape and proximal pedicel tawny, distal pedicel and flagellar segments piceous, castaneous in 
<typeStatus box="[519,619,1701,1727]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[151,1437,836,2015]" lastBlockId="9.[151,1437,153,2015]" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="410" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">
<emphasis box="[199,288,1737,1763]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">Thorax.</emphasis>
Dorsal thorax tawny, ochraceous in 
<typeStatus box="[697,797,1737,1763]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
. Pronotum with triangular piceous mark on either side of anterior midline extending along anterior margin through ambient fissure to obtusely angled mark extending to posterior paramedian fissure, extends laterally onto entire lateral part of pronotal collar, dark castaneous within lateral fissures, dark castaneous mark near anterior paramedical fissure extending posterolaterally onto scute, longer sinuate mark extending posteriorly from middle of paramedian suture across scute, fasciae lighter in 
<typeStatus box="[1231,1331,1881,1907]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
. Pronotal collar tawny, piceous in ambient fissure expands onto medial pronotal collar lateral angle, lateral part of pronotal collar piceous, only lateral margin marked in 
<typeStatus box="[664,763,1953,1979]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
, pronotal collar with short silvery pile on lateral portions of pronotal collar lateral angles and lateral part of pronotal collar. Mesonotum tawny, ochraceous in 
<typeStatus box="[1251,1350,1989,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="409">paratype</typeStatus>
, angled piceous fasciae along anteromedial submedian sigillae, mottling along lateral portion of lateral sigillae, curved Yshaped mark enclosing posterior submedian sigilla extending parallel to midline and curving laterad posterior to light castaneous scutal depression before terminating on distal anterior arm of cruciform elevation, mark lighter and extends lateral to parapsidal suture in 
<typeStatus box="[634,733,261,287]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">paratype</typeStatus>
, castaneous fascia along lateral mesonotum not reaching posterolateral curve, only along anterior half of mesonotum in 
<typeStatus box="[819,919,297,323]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">paratype</typeStatus>
. Cruciform elevation ground color, left lateral margin piceous in 
<typeStatus box="[361,462,333,359]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">holotype</typeStatus>
, unicolorous ochraceous in 
<typeStatus box="[778,877,333,359]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">paratype</typeStatus>
, wing groove ground color with piceous spots on anteromedial and anterolateral margins. Metanotum ground color with piceous spot at hind wing base. Silvery pile on lateral margin, on lateral cruciform elevation and anteriorly between the arms of the cruciform elevation. Ventral thoracic segments tawny, ochraceous in 
<typeStatus box="[603,702,441,467]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">paratype</typeStatus>
, with small piceous spot on medial anepisternum 2, covered with sparse silvery pile.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<emphasis box="[199,275,514,539]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Wings.</emphasis>
Fore wings hyaline with eight apical cells, hind wings hyaline with six apical cells. Cubitus anterior 1 of the fore wing is curved rather than being straight between the split with cubitus anterior 2 and the mediocubital crossvein. Venation tawny except piceous anal vein 2 + 3 and piceous ambient vein of apical cell 8. Basal cell longer than broad, hyaline. Pterostigma present. Infuscation on distal wing veins and ambient veins of apical cells 1–4, infuscation expanding on wing margin from anterior to distal to apical cell 4. Basal membrane of fore wing gray with dark gray posterior margin. Venation of hind wing tawny proximally, becoming piceous in apical cells and crossveins, cubitus posterior piceous, proximal anal veins 2 and 3 piceous.Anal cell 3 and anal cell 2 along anal vein 3 gray, anal cell 2 along anal vein 2 gray. Light infuscation along outer edge of wing margins.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<emphasis box="[199,260,802,827]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Legs.</emphasis>
Legs tawny, ochraceous in 
<typeStatus box="[583,682,801,827]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">paratype</typeStatus>
, distal posterior margin of fore trochanter piceous, short, curving piceous fascia on proximal posterior fore femur, distal tibiae and tarsi castaneous except proximal metatarsus of fore leg. Fore femora proximal spine castaneous, thin, elongate and adpressed against femur, secondary spine piceous, triangular, upright, large for the genus, and small, piceous, angled apical spine. Tarsal claws tawny castaneous at base becoming castaneous with piceous tips, tibial spurs and comb castaneous with darker tips. Legs covered with long and short silvery pile.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<emphasis box="[199,332,1017,1043]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Operculum.</emphasis>
Male operculum tawny with piceous spot on lateral base, lateral margin parallel to body axis joining to smoothly rounded posterolateral margin, posterior margin transverse not covering tympanal cavity. Medial margin rounded, extending to medial meracanthus. Meracanthus tawny, pointed, reaching to anterior of sternite II. Female operculum ochraceous with castaneous lateral margin at base, with straight lateral margin curved posterolateral margin and straight posterior margin forming an obtuse angle with the lateral margin, terminating medially at middle of meracanthus, reaching to middle of sternite II. Female meracanthus ochraceous, pointed, almost as long as operculum. Opercula with long silvery pile.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<emphasis box="[199,313,1269,1295]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Abdominal tergites castaneous with tawny anterior and posterior margins except castaneous not reaching midline of tergite 2 and anterior of castaneous region piceous extending along timbal cavity and enclosing auditory capsule in male, castaneous lighter and piceous absent in 
<typeStatus box="[892,988,1341,1367]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">paratype</typeStatus>
female, anterior auditory capsule edged in castaneous, tergites with short silvery extending from posterior of tergites. Timbal cover recurved exposing timbal, piceous, short golden pile radiating posteriorly from timbal cover. Timbal with eleven long and ten intercalary ribs. Female abdominal segment 9 ochraceous with castaneous dorsal beak, stigma, and short fascia on anterolateral margin, covered with long, silvery pile. Posterior margin of female abdominal segment 9 sinuate. Sternites tawny with transverse castaneous mark on medial sternites becoming larger in posterior segments, covering the complete medial sternites VI–VII, forming a medial castaneous fascia, sternite VIII U-shaped, radiating long silvery pile. Female sternites with similar castaneous marks beginning on sternite IV and castaneous mark laterally. Epipleurites tawny. Female sternite VII with a deep medial notch, V-shaped anteriorly, lateral angle increasing about half way to posterior margin. Long silvery pile radiating from sternites.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">
<emphasis box="[199,313,1701,1727]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Genitalia.</emphasis>
Male pygofer castaneous with piceous dorsal beak, with long, silvery pile ventrolaterally and at base of dorsal beak, with rounded distal shoulder, dorsal beak elongated, pointed, slightly curved when viewed from the side. Pygofer basal lobe indistinct, radiating golden pile medially, pygofer upper lobes absent. Anal styles piceous, extending beyond dorsal beak, anal tube castaneous. Uncus lobe dark castaneous, flattened, lateral surfaces parallel at base, expanding laterally before angling to slightly rounded terminus.Aedeagus dark castaneous, terminus hidden in 
<typeStatus box="[180,282,1881,1907]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="9" pageNumber="410">Female gonocoxite IX castaneous with piceous lateral margin, gonapophyses castaneous. Gonocoxite X castaneous extending to length of dorsal beak but not as far as anal styles, with radiating silvery pile. Anal styles ochraceous.</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3995206" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3995206" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3995206/files/figure.png" pageId="10" pageNumber="411" startId="10.[151,250,1908,1933]" targetBox="[203,1384,170,1896]" targetPageId="10">
<paragraph blockId="10.[151,1437,1908,2029]" pageId="10" pageNumber="411">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,275,1908,1933]" pageId="10" pageNumber="411">FIGURE 2.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[282,525,1908,1932]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="411" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="chevauxensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[282,525,1908,1932]" italics="true" pageId="10" pageNumber="411">Selymbria chevauxensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[531,589,1908,1932]" pageId="10" pageNumber="411">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[531,589,1908,1932]" pageId="10" pageNumber="411" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
: A, holotype male and paratype female habitus; B, holotype male dorsum; C, holotype male timbal cover; D, paratype male operculum; E, paratype female operculum; F, holotype male lateral view of genitalia; G, holotype male posterior view of genitalia; H, paratype female lateral view of genitalia; I, paratype female ventral view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 5 mm; C–E, 2 mm; F–G, 1 mm; H–I, 2 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,152,863]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
MEASUREMENTS (
<subScript attach="right" box="[382,417,160,176]" fontSize="7" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">MM</subScript>
). N = one male or one female, mean (range). Length of body: male 23.5, female 24.1; length of fore wing: male 32.2, female 32.6; width of fore wing: male 11.1, female 10.9; length of head: male 4.2, female 4.2; width of head including eyes: male 8.6, female 8.5; width of pronotum including suprahumeral plates: male 8.1, female 8.3; width of mesonotum: male 6.85, female 6.7.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="412" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,152,863]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
DIAGNOSIS. This is the only known species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Stal" authorityYear="1861" box="[725,839,297,323]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[725,839,297,323]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">Selymbria</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
where the fore femur primary spine is adpressed to the femur rather than being angled above it, cubitus anterior 1 of the fore wing is curved rather than being straight between the split with cubitus anterior 2 and the mediocubital crossvein, and the male operculum does not cover the tympanal cavity completely. In addition, 
<emphasis box="[619,975,405,431]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Ramos &amp; Wolda" authorityYear="1985" box="[619,837,405,431]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ahyetios">Selymbria ahyetios</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Distant" authorityYear="1911" box="[850,975,405,431]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pandora">S. pandora</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Stal" baseAuthorityYear="1862" box="[1032,1196,405,431]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subolivacea">
<emphasis box="[1032,1196,405,431]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. subolivacea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished from this species by the lack of infuscation on the apex of their fore wing. The infuscation of the fore wing is found on the apex of the fore wing and on basal apical cells 1–3 and/or on the radiomedial cross vein in 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[1273,1436,477,503]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boliviaensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[1273,1436,477,503]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. boliviaensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,215,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[151,215,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2011" box="[230,368,513,539]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="danieleae">
<emphasis box="[230,368,513,539]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. danieleae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[383,559,513,539]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ecuadorensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[383,559,513,539]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. ecuadorensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[566,630,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[566,630,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[645,805,513,539]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="iguazuensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[645,805,513,539]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. iguazuensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[813,876,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[813,876,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[891,1042,513,539]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="loretoensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[891,1042,513,539]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. loretoensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1050,1114,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1050,1114,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[1129,1358,513,539]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="madredediosensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[1129,1358,513,539]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. madredediosensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1365,1429,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1365,1429,513,539]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[151,360,549,575]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puntarenasensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[151,360,549,575]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. puntarenasensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[367,430,549,575]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[367,430,549,575]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Germar" baseAuthorityYear="1834" box="[485,630,549,575]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="stigmatica">
<emphasis box="[485,630,549,575]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. stigmatica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. The meracanthus tip is straight, the uncus is thin and reaching just past the anal styles and the notch in female sternite VII is angled laterally along the entire length in this species which distinguishes it from 
<emphasis box="[388,659,621,647]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Ramos &amp; Wolda" authorityYear="1985" box="[388,512,621,647]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ahyetios">S. ahyetios</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[524,659,621,647]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cinctifera" status="n. sp.">S. cinctifera</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[666,729,621,647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[666,729,621,647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[743,931,621,647]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guatemalensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[743,931,621,647]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. guatemalensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[938,1001,621,647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[938,1001,621,647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[1015,1163,621,647]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guianensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[1015,1163,621,647]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. guianensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1170,1233,621,647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1170,1233,621,647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Ramos &amp; Wolda" authorityYear="1985" box="[1295,1419,621,647]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pluvialis">
<emphasis box="[1295,1419,621,647]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. pluvialis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,152,863]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
The shape of the meracanthus can distinguish the three species found in 
<collectingCountry box="[1032,1204,657,683]" name="French Guiana" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">French Guiana</collectingCountry>
. The meracanthus is broadly triangular in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2011" box="[385,521,693,719]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="danieleae">
<emphasis box="[385,521,693,719]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. danieleae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, the extended tip is straight in 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[858,1033,693,719]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="chevauxensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[858,1033,693,719]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. chevauxensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1039,1100,693,719]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[1039,1100,693,719]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
and the extended tip is curved mediad in 
<taxonomicName authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[269,417,729,755]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guianensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis box="[269,417,729,755]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">S. guianensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[424,487,729,755]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[424,487,729,755]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="412" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="11.[151,1437,152,863]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2847252310" country="French Guiana" location="Montagne de Chevaux in May" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" specimenCount="1">
DISTRIBUTION. The species is known only from the 
<typeStatus box="[764,812,765,791]" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">type</typeStatus>
series collected in 
<collectingCountry box="[1027,1197,765,791]" name="French Guiana" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">French Guiana</collectingCountry>
. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2011" box="[1207,1436,765,791]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="412" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="danieleae">
<emphasis box="[1207,1436,765,791]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">Selymbria danieleae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
has also been collected on 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EE0B02B0724A00FF6647E35DB6E822:8E98ECCFB0714A00FE3A461B5E65E846" box="[459,807,801,827]" country="French Guiana" name="Montagne de Chevaux in May" pageId="11" pageNumber="412">Montagne de Chevaux in May</location>
but us a smaller species that is obviously marked with piceous
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>