<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.153.2106" ID-GBIF-Dataset="08abcaaf-c699-425b-8160-8173fa1605f5" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152032590" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-153-57" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-153-57" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 153" ModsDocTitle="Glenea coomani Pic, 1926 and its related species of South China with description of a new species" checkinTime="1451249504702" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lin, Meiying &amp; Yang, Xingke" docDate="2011" docId="C5D1E522C9DF53888961CBF110BB32FF" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 153: 57-71" docOrigin="ZooKeys 153" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.153.2106" docTitle="Glenea neohumerosa Lin &amp; Yang, 2011, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="63" masterDocId="FFF31B499715FF93997FF54CE75CFFC8" masterDocTitle="Glenea coomani Pic, 1926 and its related species of South China with description of a new species" masterLastPageNumber="71" masterPageNumber="57" pageId="4" pageNumber="61" updateTime="1643554033068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Glenea coomani Pic, 1926 and its related species of South China with description of a new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lin, Meiying</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Yang, Xingke</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>153</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>57</mods:start>
<mods:end>71</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.153.2106</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.153.2106</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-153-57</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152032590" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:C5D1E522C9DF53888961CBF110BB32FF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C5D1E522C9DF53888961CBF110BB32FF" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="63" pageId="4" pageNumber="61">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="61" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9C4BC446-D2E5-4E4E-9BDD-F66245CC93C5" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea neohumerosa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="neohumerosa">Glenea neohumerosa</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="4" pageNumber="61">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1223
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="4" pageNumber="61" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Male (Figs 14, 14h, 16-18): length: 8.4-10.8 mm, humeral width: 2.3-3.0 mm. Female (Figs 12-13, 15, 15h): length:10.5-13.0 mm, humeral width: 3.2-3.9 mm. Body black, in part provided with thick, white (dry and old specimens, Figs 14-15) to yellow (alive or fresh specimens, Figs 12-13) pubescent maculae. Head black, frons with two white or yellow stripes (almost fused in male, Fig. 14h) from inner side of antennae insertions along eyes and genae to clypeus (Fig. 15h), temple white or yellow (Fig. 12a), vertex with two parallel stripes (usually fused) between upper eye lobes; antennae black, scattered with short, black bristles on undersides of first seven segments. Prothorax with a medial white or yellow stripe, each side white or yellow except a transverse black vitta (Fig. 12a). Scutellum white or yellow. Elytra without surural stripes, each disc with 5 white or yellow maculae: two spots at basal 1/4, the one near suture much bigger than the one near margin; a moderate sized oval spot at middle, near suture; the fourth one smaller than middle one, closer to lateral margin than to suture, at the centre of apical half; an oblique transverse band just before apex. Ventral surface covered with dense white or yellow pubescence, thinly so along middle. Legs black, thinly pubescent. Pronotum and elytral bases with sparse, erect, black bristles.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="61">Head hardly broader than prothorax, deeply, and in part closely punctured, feebly concave at vertex. Eyes deeply emarginate, inferior eye lobes subequal to (female) or 2 times as high as (male) genae below it, width much less than half of frons. Antennae longer than body, male longer than female; scape thicknened apical without cicatrix not a ridge; antennomere ratio (male): 12: 3: 18: 15: 14: 13: 13: 12: 12: 11: 12; (female): 13: 3: 21: 17: 16: 15: 14: 14: 13: 12: 13. Prothorax almost as broad as long (male) or broader than long (female), swollen laterally before middle, disc convex and somewhat deeply and closely punctured. Elytra rounded at humeri, slightly narrowed apically, each with 2 humeral longitudinal ridges beginning after humeri and reaching close to apex, truncated apically, with short and small teeth at the suture, long and sharp spine at the outer angle, surface with coarse and irregular punctures. Legs stout, middle tibiae grooved, hind femur reaching middle to apex of third abdominal segment, first hind tarsal segment longer than (male), or nearly as long as (female) following two segments combined. Male claws: the anterior claws of the mid tarsi with a short (half of the normal claw) tooth (Figs 17-18), fore and hind tarsi with simple claws (Fig. 16). Female claws simple.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="4" pageNumber="61">
Male genitalia (Figs 19-21): Tegmen length about 1.9 mm; lateral lobes slender, each about 0.6 mm long and 0.2 mm wide, with finely haired ridge at the base (in ventral view, Fig. 20), apex obliquely rounded and with fine setae which are shorter than lateral lobes; ringed part elbowed in the widest portion, converging; basal piece 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="62" start="start">bifurcated</pageBreakToken>
distally; median lobe plus median struts moderately curved, subequal to tegmen in length; the median struts about one half of the whole length of median lobe; dorsal plate shorter than ventral plate; apex of ventral plage (Fig. 20) pointed, apex not so sharp and not curved to right side; median foramen elongated with a projection in lateral view (Fig. 19b); internal sac about 3 times as long as median lobe plus median struts, with 4 pieces of basal armature, 2 bands of supporting armature and 3 rods; the two longer rods each about 1.2 mm, shorter than tegmen, the short middle rod about 0.7 mm long. Ejaculatory duct single. Tergite VIII (Fig. 21c) longer than broad, apex rounded, setae near lateral corner dense and long, and sparse and short around middle.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="62">Female genitalia (Figs 22-23): spermathecal gland located at the base of spermathecal capsule. Spermathecal capsule with a curved basal stalk and a rounded apical orb, stalk more than twice the length of capsule.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="62">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="62">
Figures 12-18. Habitus, 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea neohumerosa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="neohumerosa">Glenea neohumerosa</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 12-13 paratype, female, from Hainan, China, showing yellow coloration of fresh material (not to scale) (taken by Wenxuan Bi in June, 2011) 14 holotype, male, from Guangxi, China 14h head of male, frontal view 15 female, from Hainan, China 15h head of female, frontal view. Scale 2 mm 16 simple claw, showing claw of front tarsus of male. 17-18 showing claw of mid tarsus of male (not to scale).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="62">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="62">
Figures 19-23. Terminalia of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea neohumerosa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="neohumerosa">Glenea neohumerosa</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 19 male genitalia. 20 showing ridges in base of lateral lobes and apex of ventral plate of median lobe (not to scale) 21 tergite VIII and sternite VIII &amp; IX a ventral view b lateral view c dorsal view 22-23 female genitalia 22 spermathecal capsule distorted (not to scale). Scale 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="62" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="62">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="62">
Differs from long spine elytron (Fig. 35) species 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea laodice" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laodice">Glenea laodice</taxonomicName>
Thomson, 1879 (Fig. 27) and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea subalcyone" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subalcyone">Glenea subalcyone</taxonomicName>
Breuning, 1964 (Figs 28-29) in elytron having five white or yellow maculae instead of six, and their positions different. Differs from 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea coomani" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="coomani">Glenea coomani</taxonomicName>
and other short tooth elytron (Fig. 34) species in elytral apex having a long and sharp spine at the outer angle. Differs from 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea coomani" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="coomani">Glenea coomani</taxonomicName>
also in male terminalia: tergite VIII with apex rounded instead of truncated; lateral lobes of tegmen slender, the length ratio of lateral lobes to tegmen much bigger; apex of ventral plate not so sharp and not curved to right side.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="63" start="start">Etymology</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Named derived on similarity to and misidentification as 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Glenea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glenea humerosa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="humerosa">Glenea humerosa</taxonomicName>
by Gressitt and Hua (based on material deposited in SYSU and IZAS).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">The yellow color of the pubescence turns into white when the specimens are dried.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">China: Guangxi, Hainan, Fujian; Vietnam (Tonkin).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="63" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="63">
Holotype: male (10.2 mm long), Guangxi, Jinxiu, Shengtangshan, alt. 900 m, 1999.V.17, leg. Xingke Yang (IZAS, IOZ(E)1859448). Paratypes: China:Guangxi: 2 males, Jinxiu, Luoxiang, alt. 400 m, 1999.V.14, 15, leg. Decheng Yuan (IZAS, IOZ(E)1859449, 1859447); 1 male, Guangxi, Nanning, Wuming county, Mt. Damingshan [
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="23.4">23°24'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="108.46667">108°28'E</geoCoordinate>
], alt. 1200 m, 2011.VII.11, coll. Yanquan Lu (CWD). Hainan: 1 female, Hainan Exp. 1934.IV.18 (IZAS, IOZ(E)1859445); 1 male, Hainan Exp. 1934.III.26 (IZAS, IOZ(E)1859446); 1 male 1 female, Hainan, Lingshui county, Diaoluoshan, alt. 1000 m, 2010.IV.23, leg. Ziwei Yin (SHEM); 1 female, Hainan, Ledong, Jiangfengling, Mingfenggu, 2011.V.25, alt. 1000 m, leg. Wenxuan Bi (CBWX); 1 female, Hainan, Ledong, 1962.IX.17, leg. Yaoquan Li (SYSU, En-366130); 1 male, Ledong, Jianfengling, Tianchi, 1948.VII.27, leg. Yi Liang (SYSU, En-366148). Fujian: 1 female, Wuyishan Nature Reserve, 2009.VII.10-17, leg. Ming Jin (CJM). Vietnam: 1 female, Tonkin, Backan, 1907, leg. Lemee (IZAS, ex MNHN, ex Coll. R. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Oberthür">Oberthuer</normalizedToken>
, 1952, IOZ(E)1859450).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>