<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047588" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5BB83EC9-B496-4FCF-8A8F-B79A42A5C3C6" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="88722B8E70639C85D0D6823118697DDD" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio circulorum Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="5BB83EC9-B496-4FCF-8A8F-B79A42A5C3C6" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="44" lastPageNumber="45" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047588" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5BB83EC9-B496-4FCF-8A8F-B79A42A5C3C6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/88722B8E70639C85D0D6823118697DDD" lastPageId="44" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<subSubSection pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/5BB83EC9-B496-4FCF-8A8F-B79A42A5C3C6" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio circulorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="circulorum">Oxyscelio circulorum Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="41" pageNumber="42">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 37-42; Morphbank34
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Female. Body length 3.25 mm (n=1).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: longer than broad. A5: longer than broad.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Ventral clypeal margin: concave. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: with transverse ledge, face sharply receding below it. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: present. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: present as multiple regular elevations. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: present laterally, absent medially. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate punctate; absent. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate punctate; absent. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent; granulate. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: with narrow curved smooth elevations. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe 
<pageBreakToken pageId="42" pageNumber="43" start="start">anteriorly</pageBreakToken>
: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with a median carina, otherwise 
<pageBreakToken pageId="43" pageNumber="44" start="start">weakly</pageBreakToken>
sculptured. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">T1 horn: present. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1 lateral carina: straight. T2 sculpture: densely foveolate, longitudinal sculpture irregular. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Male. Body length 2.85-3 mm (n=3). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: granulate. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 6 or more. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: truncate.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
Figures 37-42. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio circulorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="circulorum">Oxyscelio circulorum</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 225606) 37 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 38 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 39 Head, anterior view 40 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 148409) 41 Antenna 42 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank34
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
Both sexes: Frontal depression nearly flat, surrounded by many transverse curved rugae; submedian carina indicated by a set of rugae. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by many transverse carinae. Occipital carina incomplete, lateral portions approaching hyperoccipital carina. Occiput irregularly sculptured. Metascutellum broad and very short, concave, with a distinct median carina. Postmarginal vein present. Coxa and rest of leg bicolored. T1 lateral carina not expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4, A5 longer than broad. Mesoscutellum with setiferous puncta. T1 midlobe with very weak anterior horn, no complete longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach beyond metasomal apex. T6 broader than long. Male: Fore wing long enough to exceed metasomal apex. T7 tiny, truncate. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio circulorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="circulorum">Oxyscelio circulorum</taxonomicName>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio tubi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tubi">Oxyscelio tubi</taxonomicName>
, but has a much shorter T1 horn and metasoma.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“rings.”">&quot;rings.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="43" pageNumber="44">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307124]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="44" pageNumber="45" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="44" pageNumber="45">
<pageBreakToken pageId="44" pageNumber="45" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="44" pageNumber="45">
Holotype, female: NEW CALEDONIA: Nord Prov., 5km WSW Pouebo, Mount Mandjelia, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="55" value="-20.397">20.397°S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="55" value="164.528">164.528°E</geoCoordinate>
, 780m, 9.XII-15.XII.2000, malaise trap, M. E. Irwin, OSUC 225606 (deposited in MNHN). Paratypes: NEW CALEDONIA: 2 females, 1 male, OSUC 77540-77541 (OSUC); OSUC 148409 (QMBA).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>