<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.61.487" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c5524068-5c76-44cb-aa4c-6e0dca4bb27b" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159360109" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-61-11" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0C398A2C-6009-4673-B3BF-49F072AEBB64" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-61-11" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 61" ModsDocTitle="The genus Nelcyndana Stål (Hemiptera, Cicadidae, Taphurini) with description of three new species from Borneo" checkinTime="1451250950362" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Duffels, Joannes Petrus" docDate="2010" docId="2AC5CDB39AD6FA5C811BC2D3D8794DC5" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 61: 11-31" docOrigin="ZooKeys 61" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.61.487" docTitle="Nelcyndana vantoli Duffels, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="0C398A2C-6009-4673-B3BF-49F072AEBB64" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="20" masterDocId="353D2903285C193F9A3FFFABFF87A05F" masterDocTitle="The genus Nelcyndana Stal (Hemiptera, Cicadidae, Taphurini) with description of three new species from Borneo" masterLastPageNumber="31" masterPageNumber="11" pageId="9" pageNumber="20" updateTime="1643722113871" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The genus Nelcyndana Stal (Hemiptera, Cicadidae, Taphurini) with description of three new species from Borneo</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Duffels, Joannes Petrus</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>61</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>11</mods:start>
<mods:end>31</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.61.487</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.61.487</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-61-11</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">0299DA16-000F-49E7-957C-B427AE0E3DDB</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="159360109" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0C398A2C-6009-4673-B3BF-49F072AEBB64" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2AC5CDB39AD6FA5C811BC2D3D8794DC5" lastPageNumber="20" pageId="9" pageNumber="20">
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="20" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:" authority="Duffels" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Nelcyndana" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nelcyndana vantoli" order="Hemiptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vantoli">Nelcyndana vantoli Duffels</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="9" pageNumber="20">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 4810
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="20" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">2♂. Holotype ♂: Malaysia: Sabah: &quot;RMNH Leiden E SABAH / Lahad Datu, 60 km W of: / Danum Valley Field Centre / at junction Sg Segama and / Sg Palum Tambun, 150 m / 4°58&quot;N 117°48'E&quot;, &quot;At light. Bridge of Segama. / 26 Mar 1987, 18.30-21.30. / Clearing, edge of untouched / evergr. lowl. rainforest / leg. Van Tol &amp; Huisman&quot; (RMNH). Paratype: Indonesia: Kalimantan Timur: Long Tua, edge of Bahau River, 3°10'N 115°47'E, 440 m, 5-9.iv.1994, UV light, B. Hubley &amp; D.C. Darling, IIS 940526, 1♂ (ROM).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="20">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">
Figure 8-9. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Nelcyndana" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nelcyndana vantoli" order="Hemiptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vantoli">Nelcyndana vantoli</taxonomicName>
, holotype. 8 male abdomen in ventral view 9 male pygofer in ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="20" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">This species is dedicated to my colleague and friend Dr Jan Tol, odonatologist of the Leiden museum, for his significant contribution to our knowledge of the cicadas of Borneo.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="20" type="description of male holotype">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Description of male holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Ground colour yellowish to reddish brown. Marking black or black variegated with reddish brown. Ventral side of body with short silvery setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Head. (Fig. 4). Vertex reddish brown with a pair of paramedian, squarish, black markings, separated by a median reddish brown triangle at posterior margin of head and reaching from posterior margin of head to two thirds of vertex length beyond the paired ocelli. Frons black-brown. Postclypeus protruding fairly weakly, black variegated with reddish brown, medial part reddish brown from its glabrous nose ventrally to clypeal suture and dorsally to frontoclypeal suture; anterior and ventral parts of postclypeus black with 6 pairs of distinct, black transverse ridges, lateral margins of ventral part yellowish brown. Anteclypeus medially reddish brown, with dark brown mark at two thirds of keel, and turning to dark brown laterad. Rostrum brown with dark brown apical part reaching anterior margin of hind coxae. Lorum black with exception of brownish anterior angle. Gena black but brownish around antenna. Antennae, supra-antennal plate and vertex lobe yellowish to reddish brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Thorax. Pronotum (Fig. 4). A pair of large, rounded rectangular, black markings, sometimes slightly variegated with reddish brown, is enclosed by a narrow, yellowish to greenish fascia along anterior pronotal margin, the pronotum collar of the same colour, and a broad median fascia of the same colour that strongly widens to the anterior margin of the pronotum and to the pronotum collar.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Mesonotum (Fig. 4) with a pair of paramedian, juxtaposed, black, obconical spots at anterior margin, reaching to one fourth of mesonotum disk. Scutal depressions in front of cruciform elevation covered with small round, brown spots. Lateral sigillae mainly black, anteriorly 1.5 times as broad as anterior part of paramedian obconical spots, gradually narrow from base to distal end; basomedial part of sigillae variegated with the ground colour. Cruciform elevation yellowish.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Legs. Yellow-brown to greenish. Fore femora with four reddish brown spines: a long spine at proximal end of lower ridge, a second spine, two-thirds as long as proximal spine, at two thirds of lower ridge, a third spine, half as long as proximal spine at four fifths and a very short, triangular spine near distal end of lower ridge.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Tegmina and wings. Hyaline. Costa and basal half of radius + subcosta of tegmen reddish brown, radius anterior and distal half of subcosta reddish to dark brown. Remaining venation of tegmina and wings light to dark brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Operculum. (Fig. 8). Sickle-shaped with rounded apex reaching to three-fourths of timbal cavity, strongly narrowed from base to one fourth of its length, about equally wide in apical three fourths. Surface of operculum with sparse, adjacent setae and apical one third with very long setae especially along margins of operculum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Abdomen. (Figs 4, 8). Timbal with 6 somewhat irregular evenly spaced long ribs and faint intercalary ribs. Tergite 1 black-brown, tergite 2 dark brown to black with a pair of paramedian, transverse, reddish brown markings close to posterior margin, tergites 3-8 with a laterally widening, dark brown to black fascia along anterior margin medially reaching to half or two thirds of segment length, a laterally narrowing reddish brown fascia at about half-length of tergite and a narrow yellowish fascia along posterior margin. Sternite 2 brownish black, sternites 3-5 brownish black from anterior sternite margin to about three fourths of sternite length but with lateral reddish stripes, posterior margin yellowish; sternites 6-7 brownish black, sternite 8 light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Genitalia. (Fig. 9). Pygofer with convex lateral sides. Dorsal beak about equitriangular, reddish, with long and narrow, brown apex. Basal pygofer lobe long and convex, and reaching just beyond apex of anal segment. Upper pygofer lobe fused with basal pygofer lobe, narrowly rounded apically and about one fifth as long as apical part of basal lobe measured from base of upper pygofer lobe to its apex.Clasper basally round and flat with a medial, long and narrow, slightly flattened, incurved spine, a shorter slightly curved lateral spine and a round protrusionat its proximal margin; medial spines of both claspers juxtaposed and of unequal length. Theca chitinized, apically with a long and fairly slender, curved chitinized appendage, and a somewhat shorter and thinner appendage; the broadest appendage with very thin spine arising from its base. Aedeagal basal plates in ventral view divided in rounded, oval lobes.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="20" type="measurements">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Measurements</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">(in mm; 2♂). Body length 10.4-10.7; tegmen length 10.8-12.0; head width 3.2-3.3; pronotum width 2.9-3.1.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="20" type="remark on paratype">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Remark on paratype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">The paratype from Kalimantan Timur is alike to the holotype in the male genitalia, but the marking on the body is more extended and black instead of black-brown. The head is black with exception of the medial triangle at posterior margin of head, the nose of the postclypeus and the supra-antennal plates, which are reddish brown. The pronotum has a pair of black squarish markings, the mesonotum is entirely black, and the abdomen has a similar marking as the holotype, but the marking is black instead of brownish black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="20" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">Distribution</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">
(Fig. 10). 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Nelcyndana" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nelcyndana vantoli" order="Hemiptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vantoli">Nelcyndana vantoli</taxonomicName>
seems to have a restricted range in northeastern Borneo. It is known from a specimen from Danum Valley N.P. in northeastern Sabah and a specimen from Long Tua in the northeastern part of Kalimantan Timur.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="20">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="20">
Figure 10. Distribution of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Nelcyndana" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nelcyndana vantoli" order="Hemiptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vantoli">Nelcyndana vantoli</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>