<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887" ID-GBIF-Taxon="182235008" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-415-217" ID-Pensoft-UUID="6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468" ID-Zenodo-Dep="578301" ID-ZooBank="287A4DC80EFC42C6AA55DBB4D7A3441B" ModsDocID="1313-2970-415-217" checkinTime="1451245774308" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Smith, Aaron D., Dornburg, Rebecca &amp; Wheeler, Quentin D." docDate="2014" docId="E45B2FA48A2B5565938AC165EA65D9A1" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 415: 217-268" docOrigin="ZooKeys 415" docPubDate="2014-06-12" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887" docTitle="Eleodes (Caverneleodes) wheeleri Eleodes Aalbu, Smith, &amp; Triplehorn 2012" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" id="6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="226" masterDocId="6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468" masterDocTitle="Larvae of the genus Eleodes (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae): matrix-based descriptions, cladistic analysis, and key to late instars" masterLastPageNumber="268" masterPageNumber="217" pageId="8" pageNumber="225" updateTime="1643518370047" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Larvae of the genus Eleodes (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae): matrix-based descriptions, cladistic analysis, and key to late instars</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Smith, Aaron D.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Northern Arizona University, PO Box 5640, Flagstaff, AZ, 86011 - 5640, USA</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Dornburg, Rebecca</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Arizona State University, PO Box 874501, Tempe, AZ, 85287 - 4501, USA</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wheeler, Quentin D.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>SUNY College of Environmental Science and Forestry, 1 Forestry Drive, Syracuse, NY 13210, USA</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2014-06-12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>415</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>217</mods:start>
<mods:end>268</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.415.5887</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-415-217</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">287A4DC80EFC42C6AA55DBB4D7A3441B</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-UUID">6C204B3EFFF8FFF7FFE4FFF3FFC13468</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">578301</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="182235008" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:E45B2FA48A2B5565938AC165EA65D9A1" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E45B2FA48A2B5565938AC165EA65D9A1" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="226" pageId="8" pageNumber="225">
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="225" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="225">
<taxonomicName LSID="E45B2FA4-8A2B-5565-938A-C165EA65D9A1" authority="Eleodes Aalbu, Smith, &amp; Triplehorn, 2012" authorityName="Eleodes Aalbu, Smith, &amp; Triplehorn" authorityYear="2012" class="Insecta" family="Tenebrionidae" genus="Eleodes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eleodes (Caverneleodes) wheeleri" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="225" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="wheeleri" subGenus="Caverneleodes">Eleodes (Caverneleodes) wheeleri Eleodes Aalbu, Smith, &amp; Triplehorn, 2012</taxonomicName>
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 2" captionStartId="F2" captionText="Figure 2. Dorsal habitus of four Eleodes species: A Eleodes (Caverneleodes) wheeleri; B Eleodes (Eleodes) armatus C Eleodes (Eleodes) caudiferus D Eleodes (Eleodes) tribulus. Scale bar = 5 mm." httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/29485" pageId="8" pageNumber="225">Figs 2A</figureCitation>
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 4" captionStartId="F4" captionText="Figure 4. Lateral habitus of three Eleodes species: A Eleodes (Blapylis) nigropilosus B Eleodes (Caverneleodes) wheeleri C Eleodes (Eleodes) armatus. Scale bar = 5 mm." httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/29487" pageId="8" pageNumber="225">, 4B</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="225" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="225">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="225">
Larval E. wheeleri specimens were reared from adults with the following collecting information: &quot;USA: Arizona: Gila Co. / Tonto Natural Bridge SP / 
<geoCoordinate degrees="34.3214" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="5" value="34.3214">N34.3214</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate degrees="111.4569" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="5" value="-111.4569">W111.4569</geoCoordinate>
/ 11.IX.2010, ADSmith&quot;. A total of 15 eggs and larvae were reared and examined for this study, with all surviving until the 2nd instar or beyond. The following description is based on a detailed examination of five 8-11th instar specimens.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="226" pageId="8" pageNumber="225" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="225">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="225">Measurements: TL: 18.0-23.9 mm, PL: 1.6-2.1 mm, PW: 2.1-2.7 mm, HW: 1.8-2.3 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="226" pageId="8" pageNumber="225">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="225">Head.</emphasis>
Prognathous or weakly declined; weakly dorsoventrally flattened; width nearly equal to prothorax; sides rounded; strongly constricted before occipital foramen; color light tan, same or nearly the same as body segments; punctation minute, dense, separated by 1-2 puncture diameters. Epicranial suture stem length approximately onethird head capsule length; frontal arms sinuate, not obscured by sculpturing. Frons weakly rugose. Epicranial plates weakly rugose dorsally; lateral portions sparsely setose; ventral portion of each plate with row of six or more long setae along anterior margin near buccal cavity confluent with setae on lateral portions of plates, and a patch of short setae medially, forming a triangular pattern with its base near the anterior margin. Two stemmata present on each epicranial plate, pigmented spots often faded. Clypeus trapezoidal, swollen, darker medially in basal half, minutely punctate, punctation moderately dense, separated by 2-4 puncture diameters. Labrum swollen, sides rounded, basal half more darkly pigmented, medial setal row with six to seven erect setae, subapical setal row with seven to eight erect setae, anterior margin straight to weakly emarginate. Epipharynx anterior setal row with six stout spiniform setae, ante 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="226" start="start">rolateral</pageBreakToken>
margins with micro-setation; four anterior sensory papillae present, arranged in two irregular longitudinal rows; four subanterior sensory papillae present arranged as a transverse row subtended by two spinose setae; eight posterior sensory papillae present, arranged in an irregular cluster. Tormae asymmetric, left torma smaller. Ligula apex lacking microsetae, two long subapical setae present ventrally, eight or more subapical setae present dorsally. Hypopharyngeal sclerome pentagonal, tricuspidate. Gula distinct, weakly trapezoidal, nearly rectangular. Antenna three segmented, cylindrical, first segment length subequal to second.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="226">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="226">Thorax.</emphasis>
Thoracic tergites light tan, prothoracic sternite anterior to legs light brown, thoracic sternites posterior to prolegs light tan to brown. Prothoracic tergum wider than long, 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
or more length of meso- or metaterga; anterior transverse striated band present, darker than protergal disc; lateral margins with very faint granulated band, nearly concolorous with protergal disc. Posterior transverse striated band present on all thoracic tergites, unicolorous brown. Meso- and metathoracic tergites wider than long, each with a faintly indicated sclerotized transverse line present on anterior fifth. Thoracic tergites sparsely setose on dorsal surfaces, lateral margins more densely setose. Mesothoracic spiracle simple, ovate, approximately 1.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
size of abdominal spiracles; reduced metathoracic spiracle visible, less than one-fourth size of mesothoracic spiracle. Legs. Prothoracic leg slightly longer, much thicker than meso- and metathoracic legs; prothoracic tarsungulus strongly sclerotized and sickle-shaped; prothoracic trochanter with two stout spines ventromedially; prothoracic femur with ventromedial row of four spines, dorsal surface with faintly indicated basal sclerotized band; prothoracic tibia with ventromedial row of five to six spines, dorsal surface slightly more sclerotized than ventral surface. Mesotibia with four to five ventromedial spines.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="226">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="226">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Abdominal tergites and sternites light tan with slightly darker transverse striated bands present along posterior margins of segments I-VIII, forming near contiguous unicolorous band around segments. Abdominal sternite I sparsely clothed in long erect setae along anterior margin. Abdominal laterotergites concolorous with tergites, lacking distinct pigmented margins. Abdominal segment IX (pygidium) triangular in dorsal view, gradually reflexed to apex, urogomphi absent, apex forming a small tooth, sparsely clothed in short and mid length erect setae, sclerotized uniformly throughout, lacking maculations; marginal row of 14-18 socketed spines present, arranged as single row around posterior two-thirds to one half of segment. Abdominal sternites I-VIII lacking longitudinal tomentose bands along lateral margins. Pygopods short, subconical, each with 11-15 erect setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="226" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="226">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="226">Eleodes wheeleri larvae can be separated from the other currently known Eleodes species by the pentagonal hypopharyngeal sclerome, the lack of a distinct apical tooth on the pygidium, the presence of two long subapical ventral setae on the ligula with eight or more setae present dorsally, and the lateral margins of the protergum with a very faint granulated band, nearly concolorous with protergal disc.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="226" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="226">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="226">
Eleodes wheeleri was recently described (
<bibRefCitation author="Aalbu, RA" journalOrPublisher="Annales Zoologici" pageId="36" pageNumber="253" pagination="199 - 216" publicationUrl="10.3161/000345412X652729" refId="B1" refString="Aalbu, RA, Smith, AD, Triplehorn, CA, 2012. A revision of the Eleodes subgenus Caverneleodes with new species and notes on cave breeding Eleodes (Tenebrionidae: Amphidorini). Annales Zoologici 62: 199 - 216, DOI: 10.3161/000345412X652729" title="A revision of the Eleodes subgenus Caverneleodes with new species and notes on cave breeding Eleodes (Tenebrionidae: Amphidorini)." url="10.3161/000345412X652729" volume="62" year="2012">Aalbu et al. 2012</bibRefCitation>
) from Tonto Natural Bridge Caverns in Arizona and is known only from the type locality.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>