<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d152d656-ef98-4767-b61b-d7a3c93f4df2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902676" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-657-43" ID-ZBK="7C34835207274F90915A5D5CBA9A9F83" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4730BB01-67A4-4AF9-9942-27E5FA1B3580" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-657-43" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 657" ModsDocTitle="On some new species of Ancorabolidae Sars, 1909 from the Gulf of California: the genera Ceratonotus Sars, 1909, and Dendropsyllus Conroy-Dalton, 2003 (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)" checkinTime="1487401282446" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gomez, Samuel &amp; Diaz, Karen" docDate="2017" docId="4B5D5519BF0BEF8B6F06FF05596588B7" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 657: 43-65" docOrigin="ZooKeys 657" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725" docTitle="Dendropsyllus californiensis Gomez &amp; Diaz, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="4730BB01-67A4-4AF9-9942-27E5FA1B3580" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="57" masterDocId="FFB1A87FFFCCB62CFFCA5E18FFA7FFD5" masterDocTitle="On some new species of Ancorabolidae Sars, 1909 from the Gulf of California: the genera Ceratonotus Sars, 1909, and Dendropsyllus Conroy-Dalton, 2003 (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="43" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" updateTime="1643558546598" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>On some new species of Ancorabolidae Sars, 1909 from the Gulf of California: the genera Ceratonotus Sars, 1909, and Dendropsyllus Conroy-Dalton, 2003 (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gomez, Samuel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Diaz, Karen</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>657</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-657-43</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">7C34835207274F90915A5D5CBA9A9F83</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">7C34835207274F90915A5D5CBA9A9F83</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902676" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4730BB01-67A4-4AF9-9942-27E5FA1B3580" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4B5D5519BF0BEF8B6F06FF05596588B7" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="57" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/4730BB01-67A4-4AF9-9942-27E5FA1B3580" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Dendropsyllus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dendropsyllus californiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="californiensis">Dendropsyllus californiensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="9" pageNumber="52">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">One female holotype as follows: body partially dissected (leaving cephalothorax, left antennule and antenna, left P1-P5, abdomen, anal somite and caudal rami intact) and preserved in alcohol (ICML-EMUCOP-100207-02), pair of mandibles, maxillules, maxillae and maxillipeds, and right P1-P5 dissected and mounted on four slides (ICML-EMUCOP-100207-03).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Southern Trough of Guaymas Basin, Gulf of California, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="México">Mexico</normalizedToken>
(
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="26.685">26°41'06&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-111.2">111°12'W</geoCoordinate>
), 1759 m depth (see Fig. 1); coll. S. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Gómez">Gomez</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Diagnosis</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
(based on the female only). 
<taxonomicName family="Ancorabolidae" lsidName="" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" rank="family">Ancorabolidae</taxonomicName>
. Cephalothorax with bilateral anterior constriction; with two sensilla and one tube-pore on distal corners; with paired dorsal processes anteriorly, lateroventrally, and posteriorly. Rostrum fused to cephalothorax. P2-P5-bearing somites with paired dorsal dendroid processes. Second and third urosomites fused ventrally, distinct dorsally, without dendroid processes. Caudal rami divergent, around 7.5 times as long as wide; with seven setae. Antennule three-segmented. Antenna with allobasis bearing a reduced abexopodal seta; without exopod; free endopodal segment with eight setae/spines. Mandible with one-segmented palp bearing five setae. Maxillule with two surface setae and five spines on praecoxal arthrite; coxal endite with two setae; basis with six setae; exopod represented by two, endopod by three elements. Maxilla with two syncoxal endites bearing three setae each; allobasis drawn out into strong claw, accompanied by five elements; endopod one-segmented, with two setae. Maxilliped with one seta on syncoxa; endopodal claw with one accessory seta. Exopod of P1 two-segmented, of P2-P4 three-segmented. First endopodal segment of P1 small, second segment elongate, close to 4.3 times as long as first segment, and 7.6 times as long as wide. P2 without endopod. First endopodal segment of P3 and P4 very small, second segment around 8.6 and 4.4 times as long as first segment, and 8.6 and 4 times as long as wide, respectively. P5 with baseoendopod and exopod fused; endopodal lobe a small pedestal with one naked seta and one tube-pore; exopod slender, 7.7 times as long as wide, with long subdistal tube-pore and three elements.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="57" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Description of female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Total body length, 670 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
measured from anterior outer corner of cephalothorax to posterior margin of caudal rami; length of caudal rami, 145 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
(ca. 22% total body length). Body cylindrical, tapering posteriorly, without clear demarcation between prosome and urosome; integument moderately chitinised; well-developed dendroid processes as for the genus (Fig. 7A). Cephalothorax with bilateral anterior constriction (Fig. 7A); anterior corners with sensory triplet consisting of two sensilla and associated tube-pore (Fig. 8C); with paired sensillate processes as follows: paired dorsal dentate conical processes anteriorly, pair of dentate processes lateroventrally accompanied by anterior small sensillum-bearing processes, and paired dorsal dendroid processes posteriorly seemingly without tube-pore (Fig. 7A). Rostrum fused to cephalothorax, absorbed into anteroventral surface of cephalothorax, with paired sensilla-bearing tubercles, and with well-developed midventral tube-pore (Figs 7A, 8C). P2-P4-bearing somites with conspicuous dorsal tube-pore; with paired dorsal dendroid processes as shown, each with a sensillum halfway along length of process (Fig. 7A). P5-bearing somite seemingly without dorsal tube-pore; with paired dorsal dendroid processes less developed than in preceding somites.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Second and third urosomites fused ventrally forming genital double-somite, distinct dorsally, with dorsal sensilla-bearing tubercles as shown (Fig. 7A, C); proximal half (second urosomite) of genital double somite without sensory ornamentation, genital field as shown (Fig. 7C); distal half (third urosomite) of genital double-somite with paired tube-pores and posterior sensilla as shown. Fourth urosomite with dorsal and ventral sensilla as shown, with set of four strong ventral spinules medially (Fig. 7C). Fifth urosomite without sensilla, posterior margin with fine spinules (Fig. 7A, B), dorsally with paired pores as shown, ventrally with set of medial strong spinules close to posterior margin (Fig. 7C). Anal somite (Fig. 7A, B, C) partly cleft medially; dorsally with rounded and smooth anal operculum, and two sensilla; with two anterolateral, and two posteroventral tube-pores; with few small spinules on ventral hind margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="53" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Caudal rami (Fig. 7A, B) elongate, divergent, close to 7.5 times as long as wide; with lateral tube-pore on proximal third of ramus; ornamented with spinules as shown; with seven setae; seta I and II arising half way along lateral margin of ramus, the former minute and ventral to the latter; seta III somewhat longer than seta II, arising in distal 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="53" start="start">seventh</pageBreakToken>
; setae IV and V broken off in Fig. 7B; seta VI small, arising on distal inner corner; dorsal seta VII triarticulate, situated close to distal margin of ramus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="53">Antennule (Fig. 8A) three-segmented, segments elongate and slender. Armature formula as follows: 1-[9], 2-[8+(1+ae)], 3-[8+acrothek].</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="54">
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="54" start="start">Antenna</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 8B), with allobasis; original division of basis and first endopodal segment indicated by membranous insert; basal and endopodal halves with small inner spinules as shown; endopodal half with one reduced abexopodal seta. Exopod absent. Free endopodal segment with inner spinules and two pinnate spines; outer margin with two frills subdistally; apically with two pinnate spines, two pinnate geniculate setae, and one pinnate geniculate seta with additional outer spinules halfway its length and fused basally to small seta.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="54">Mandible (Fig. 9A) with robust coxa; gnathobase with teeth as figured, with two setae one of which bifid. Palp one-segmented, with spinules as shown, with two inner (basal), and three apical (endopodal) setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="54">Maxillule (Fig. 9B) with quadrate praecoxal arthrite bearing two surface setae and five distal spines. Coxal endite with one spinulose and one bare seta, with some spinules distally. Proximal endite of basis with four, distal endite with two setae. Exopod represented by one long and one tiny seta. Endopod represented by three elements.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="11" pageNumber="54">
Maxilla (Fig. 9C). Syncoxa with spinulose patches as depicted; with two endites; proximal endite with three setae, one of which spinulose and basally fused to endite; distal endite with three spinulose elements. Allobasis drawn out into strong claw, the 
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="55" start="start">latter</pageBreakToken>
with subdistal spinules, accompanied by two outer elements, one strong spine, and two naked setae. Endopod very small, one-segmented, with two setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="55">Maxilliped (Fig. 9D) subchelate. Syncoxa with some inner spinules apically and one spinulose seta on distal inner corner. Basis with spinules as depicted. Endopod drawn out into long spinulose spine with one accessory seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="55">P1 (Fig. 10A). Coxa trapezoid, with small lobate process bearing several spinules. Basis transversely elongate, with tube-pore midway along anterior margin, with one outer and one inner setae. Exopod two-segmented, ornamented with spinules and setules as depicted; first segment visibly shorter than second, with long outer pinnate spine; second segment elongate, without inner armature, with two apical geniculate setae, and with two outer geniculate elements and one bipinnate spine. Endopod two-segmented; first segment small, slightly longer than wide; second segment elongate, nearly 4.3 times as long as first segment, and almost 7.6 times as long as wide, with one apical seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="57" pageId="12" pageNumber="55">
P2-P4 (Fig. 10
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
). Coxa trapezoid, with outer lobate process ornamented with some spinules (as for P3, see Fig. 10C). Basis transversely elongate, with tube-pore close to outer seta, the latter bipinnate. Exopod three-segmented, exopodal segments 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="56" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
spinular ornamentation as shown; first segment without inner armature, with long bipinnate outer spine; second segment with inner seta and outer bipinnate spine; third segment of P2 and P3 with, of P4 without inner seta, with two apical setae and 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="57" start="start">two</pageBreakToken>
outer bipinnate spines. Endopod of P2 absent; endopod of P3 and P4 two segmented, first segment very small, nearly as long as wide, second segment elongate, the latter 8.6 and 4.4 times as long as first segment and 8.6 and 4 times as long as wide in P3 and P4, respectively.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">Armature formula as follows:</paragraph>
<caption ID-Table-UUID="D5445B8059FB17B64D22C4594E94167C" httpUri="http://table.plazi.org/id/D5445B8059FB17B64D22C4594E94167C" pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">. &amp;nbsp;</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<table pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<tr pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<th colspan="1" pageId="14" pageNumber="57" rowspan="1">EXP</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="14" pageNumber="57" rowspan="1">ENP</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">P5 (Fig. 10E) with fused baseoendopod and exopod; outer basal seta naked, with accompanying tube-pore. Endopodal lobe represented by small pedestal with one naked seta accompanied by tube-pore. Exopod slender, elongate, 7.7 times as long as wide, with long subdistal tube-pore, with one outer, one distal (longest) and one inner (shortest) element.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="57" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">Description of male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="57" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">The specific epithet, californiensis, makes reference to the Gulf of California, where the species was found.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Dendropsyllus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dendropsyllus californiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="14" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="californiensis">Dendropsyllus californiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A habitus, dorsal B anal somite and right caudal ramus, dorsal, showing insert of lateral view of seta I and II C urosome, ventral, P5 bearing-somite and caudal rami omitted.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
Figure 8. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Dendropsyllus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dendropsyllus californiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="14" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="californiensis">Dendropsyllus californiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A antennule B antenna C distal outer corner of cephalothorax.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Dendropsyllus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dendropsyllus californiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="14" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="californiensis">Dendropsyllus californiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A mandible, showing detached palp B maxillule C maxilla D maxilliped.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="57">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Dendropsyllus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dendropsyllus californiensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="14" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="californiensis">Dendropsyllus californiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A P1, anterior B P2, anterior C P3, anterior, outer spine-like element of second endopodal segment indicated with an arrow D P4, anterior E P5, lateral, arrows showing tube pores.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>