<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.584.8319" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6b5f471a-7ade-4faf-a251-bcc0df3b9962" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902158" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-584-95" ID-ZBK="0D009063FF44484BAEF403DF98367E72" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BFD41F88-9B9F-4088-94D4-200BB7FE9BC1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-584-95" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 584" ModsDocTitle="Keylimepiepeckorum gen. n. and sp. n., (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from southern Florida, U.S., the first known brachypterous member of the subfamily Microgastrinae" checkinTime="1461684345894" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Fernandez-Triana, Jose &amp; Boudreault, Caroline" docDate="2016" docId="C24ACADACC088A5F349BD34481003B3C" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 584: 95-107" docOrigin="ZooKeys 584" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.584.8319" docTitle="Keylimepie peckorum Fernandez-Triana, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="BFD41F88-9B9F-4088-94D4-200BB7FE9BC1" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="101" masterDocId="FF8D047AFFBF457CFFD22C5CFFD7FF71" masterDocTitle="Keylimepiepeckorum gen. n. and sp. n., (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from southern Florida, U. S., the first known brachypterous member of the subfamily Microgastrinae" masterLastPageNumber="107" masterPageNumber="95" pageId="3" pageNumber="98" updateTime="1643602207707" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Keylimepiepeckorum gen. n. and sp. n., (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from southern Florida, U. S., the first known brachypterous member of the subfamily Microgastrinae</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fernandez-Triana, Jose</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Boudreault, Caroline</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>584</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>95</mods:start>
<mods:end>107</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.584.8319</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.584.8319</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-584-95</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">0D009063FF44484BAEF403DF98367E72</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">0D009063FF44484BAEF403DF98367E72</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902158" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BFD41F88-9B9F-4088-94D4-200BB7FE9BC1" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C24ACADACC088A5F349BD34481003B3C" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="101" pageId="3" pageNumber="98">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="98" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="98" start="start">Taxon</pageBreakToken>
classification Animalia Hymenoptera Braconidae
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="98" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/BFD41F88-9B9F-4088-94D4-200BB7FE9BC1" authority="Fernandez-Triana" authorityName="Fernandez-Triana" authorityYear="2016" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Keylimepie" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Keylimepie peckorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="98" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peckorum">Keylimepie peckorum Fernandez-Triana</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="3" pageNumber="98">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-6, 7-12, 14-17
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="98" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">
Female, CNC. UNITED STATES, Florida, Monroe County, North Key Largo, Sec., 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="25.289722">25°17'23&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-80.306946">80°18'25&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
, 3.IV.1985, Malaise trap, S. &amp; J. Peck (colls). Holotype voucher code: CNC483649.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="98" type="paratypes">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">Paratypes.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">
3 ♀, 56 ♂ (CNC). United States, Florida, Monroe County. All specimens collected by S. &amp; J. Peck in the following localities and dates: Big Pine Key, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Watson’s">Watson's</normalizedToken>
Hammock, 24.716667 -81.304167, 28.viii.1986, voucher code CNC483646; Everglades National Park, Royal Palm Hammock, 25.381667 -80.609722, Malaise trap, 3.iv.1985, coll., voucher codes CNC483647, CNC483648; Fat Deer Key, 24.735344 -81.011853, 18.x.1985-25.ii.1986, voucher codes CNC483464, CNC483465, CNC483468; Malaise trap, 18.xi.1985-25.ii.1986, voucher codes CNC489922, CNC489923, CNC489928, CNC489929, CNC489931-CNC489933, CNC489937, CNC489938, CNC489940, CNC489941, CNC489944, CNC489945, CNC489947; 2.viii-16.xi.1985, voucher codes CNC489955, CNC489959, CNC489962, CNC489965; 24.ii-4.vi.1985, voucher codes CNC483624, CNC483625; 3.iv.1985, voucher codes CNC483627, CNC483630, CNC483634-CNC483636; 4.v-4.viii.1985, voucher codes CNC489874, CNC489876, CNC489877; Malaise trap, iii.1985, voucher codes CNC483626, CNC483628, CNC483629, CNC483631-CNC483633; Fat Deer Key, 24.735344 -81.011853, Hammock, Malaise trap, 24.ii-4.vi.1986, voucher code CNC491265; North Key Largo, Sec., 25.289722 -80.306944, Malaise trap, 3.iv.1985, voucher code CNC483615; N. Key Largo, Sec., 25.289722 -80.306944, Malaise trap, 3.iv.1985, voucher codes CNC483637-CNC483645, CNC483649; North Key Largo, S35, 25.289722 -80.306944, Hammock forest, Malaise trap, 4.v-4.viii.1985, voucher codes CNC483452, CNC483455, CNC483456, CNC483458; Sugar Loaf Key, Kichings, 24.644000 -81.563000, Malaise trap, 3.v-3.viii.1985, voucher codes CNC489899, CNC489907, CNC489913; Vaca Key, Marathon, 24.716936 -81.073308, flight interception trap, 31.viii-15.xii.1986, voucher code CNC483448.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="100" pageId="3" pageNumber="98" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="98">Female.Color. Body mostly orange yellow, with mediotergites 4-8, laterotergites 4-8, sternites 4-8 and hypopygium darker, mostly brown. Antenna with anterior 6-7 flagellomeres yellow, and posterior 9-10 flagellomeres dark brown. Metatibia and metafemur mostly to completely brown. Anteromesoscutum, propodeum and metapleuron varying from entirely orange-yellow to partially dark brown. Wings mostly infumated, except for small central white band; veins mostly brown, pterostigma with a pale spot anteriorly or mostly brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="3" pageNumber="98">
Head. Coarsely sculptured, in lateral view strongly projecting forward below antennal sockets. Head in frontal view with maximum width right below the eyes (due to bulging gena). Gena in lateral view wider than eye width. Anterior tentorial pits large, 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as clypeus width. Malar line long, more than 2.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
mandibular width. Eye small, its height 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
head height. Ocelli relatively small, diameter of posterior 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="99" start="start">ocelli</pageBreakToken>
about half of both OOL and POL. Anatomical line tangent to posterior margin of anterior ocellus, crossing well above the anatomical line tangent to anterior margin of posterior ocelli. Antenna about same length as body.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="100" start="start">Mesosoma</pageBreakToken>
. Pronotum rather narrow, with one broad, transverse pronotal sulcus. Propleuron flange sharply defined by carina. Notauli very faintly marked by slightly coarser sculpture than rest of anteromesoscutum. Scutoscutellar sulcus with seven carinae. Mesoscutellum with lateral face mostly strongly striated, with polished area (mesoscutellum lunula) very narrow, 0.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
lateral face height. Scutellum with posteromedian band weakly rugose. Mesopleuron sculptured on anterior half, smooth posteriorly. Mesopleural scrobe extending to almost 0.5 of mesopleuron width. Metapleuron mostly smooth anterior to metapleural scrobe but with strong transverse striation posterior to scrobe. Propodeum with complex sculpture pattern, including partial median longitudinal carina (sometimes obscured by other sculpture), traces of transverse carina and partial areola with only the posterior carinae of areola defined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
Metasoma. T1 relatively short, its medial length 1.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
its width at anterior margin. T1 more or less parallel-sided for anterior 0.5, then narrowing towards posterior margin (width at anterior margin 2.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width at posterior margin). T1 without median sulcus, with anterior 0.5 rather depressed and concave, and posterior 0.5 with strong transversal striation. T2 trapezoidal, its width at posterior margin 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
its medial length. T2 and T3 with strong longitudinal striation; T4-T8 smooth. Hypopygium small, inflexible and unfolded. Ovipositor sheaths mostly smooth, with few, short setae on posterior 0.2-0.3. Ovipositor short, 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as metatibia.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
Legs. Metacoxa of moderate size, not surpassing posterior margin of T2; metafemur 5.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide. Metatibia with inner and outer spurs subequal (inner 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as outer) and 0.35-0.40 as long as metatarsal segment 1.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
Wings. Fore wing relatively short (0.6-0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
body length and 1.1-1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
metasoma length), with small to almost obliterated, 4-sided areolet, and with vein R1 shorter than pterostigma length and only 2.0-2.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as the distance between its posterior end and posterior end of vein M.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Holotype measurements (some measurements of female paratypes between parentheses). Body length: 2.2 mm (1.9- 2.1, 2.4-2.5 mm). Fore wing length: 1.3 mm (1.2, 1.6-1.8 mm). Metasoma length: 1.1 mm (0.9-1.0, 1.2-1.3 mm). Mandible width: 0.06 mm. Malar line: 0.17 mm. Clypeus length/ width: 0.15 mm/0.045 mm. Tentorial pit width: 0.05 mm. Head maximum width: 0.58 mm. Head height: 0.48 mm. Eye height: 0.27 mm. Eye maximum width (lateral view): 0.15 mm. Gena maximum width (lateral view): 0.20 mm. OOL: 0.09 mm; POL: 0.09 mm; diameter of posterior ocellus: 0.05 mm. Flagellomere 2 lenght/width: 0.20 mm/0.065 mm. Flagellomere 14 length/width: 0.14/0.07. T1 width at anterior margin/width at posterior margin: 0.39 mm/0.19 mm. T2 length/width at posterior margin: 0.34 mm/0.52 mm. Metacoxa length: 0.42 mm. Metafemur length/width: 0.75/0.15. Metatibia length: 0.82 mm. Metatibial spurs length, inner/outer: 0.17 mm/0.15 mm. First segment of metatarsus length: 0.40 mm. Ovipositor length: 0.15 mm.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Figures 1-6. 1-3 Female holotype. 1 Habitus lateral 2 Fore wing 3 Habitus dorsal 4-6 Male paratype 4 Fore wing 5 Habitus dorsal 6 Habitus lateral..</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Figures 7-12. Female holotype. 7 Head, pronotum and propleuron, lateral 8 Head and antenna, frontal 9 Metatibia and first segment of metatarsus 10 Head and mesosoma, dorso-lateral 11 Heard, dorsal 12 Metasoma, lateral 13 Female paratype. Head, ventral.</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Figures 14-17. 14-16 Female paratypes. 14 and 15 Propodeum and metasomal tergites 1-4, dorsal 16 Mesosoma, dorsal 17 Female holotype. Metasoma, dorsal.</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Male. As in female except for uniformly brown antenna, longer fore wing, lighter-coloured wings (hyaline or slightly infumated), and darker body color which in some cases becomes dark brown to black in areas of the head and mesosoma.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="distibution">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Distibution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Southern Florida (Florida Keys and Everglades National Park, Fig. 18).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Figure 18. Map showing the distribution of the species.</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="biology">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="101" start="start">Biology</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
Unknown. All specimens were collected in hammock forests from February to November. Based on the labels, the species would seem to be more abundant in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="April–June">April-June</normalizedToken>
and November. However, the collecting device, a Malaise trap, was not emptied regularly (at times running for months), and so the actual flight dates for the species cannot be considered as very precise.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Named after Stewart and Jarmila Peck, tireless insect collectors over the last 30+ years and the ones finding the species back in 1985 and1986. Also in recognition of their great knowledge as entomologists and as an appreciation for the important papers published by Stewart on the insect fauna of southern Florida.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
In females, smaller specimens tend to have shorter wings, a smaller areolet and pterostigma in the fore wing, and lighter color than larger specimens. Males also show variation in the extent of darker areas, but are always darker than females. Although numerous specimens (60) were found and are included as part of the type series, it should be noted that all of them were collected during two collecting trips made in 1985 and 1986 (see 
<bibRefCitation author="Peck, SB" journalOrPublisher="Florida Entomologist" pageId="9" pageNumber="104" pagination="603 - 612" title="A survey of insects of the Florida Keys: post-Pleistocene land-bridge islands." url="10.2307/3495034" volume="72" year="1989">Peck (1989)</bibRefCitation>
for details). Based on the specimens collected, males outnumber females in a proportion of 14: 1. This is an artifact of the collecting method used (a Malaise trap), which is better suited for rather strong fliers. Evidently females do not fly well, if at all.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>