<document id="1C003CB338FE9E80A050E1727D86BD23" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b92acfc0-9d67-42c4-9e37-ebd5a53d24b5" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200948" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-719-75" ID-ZBK="36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-719-75" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 719" ModsDocTitle="A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World" checkinTime="1555319501509" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2017" docId="01CFDD0986FB298EBCE962472D3F8809" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 719: 75-157" docOrigin="ZooKeys 719" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253" docTitle="Monophylla pallipes Schaeffer 1908" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="131" masterDocId="5C2D8118751DD235197A6569FFE59A6E" masterDocTitle="A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World" masterLastPageNumber="157" masterPageNumber="75" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" updateTime="1643480888860" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="0A06240167C6A6F3972F4DF34AA6006F" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="7013FE7ADFE845EBDE2E60048523734E">
<mods:title id="E430EDA72AE6694F0F3B4B4C311A5E31">A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="4E75EFB50D24FCCFD3F14026FDB81C32" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3381B5167620C930583DE8D31E60FA11">
<mods:roleTerm id="77AA0B4B74952227A93EBC57647172E1">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="359581832FD59347F38CB8A940187CB7">Burke, Alan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="A6DCC9D21E3B5B24A46CE81AFCC6636A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AC780AB1A0FC81EB05F4ADEE66900684">
<mods:roleTerm id="090F7E5AE9CAD636316AF59C5B883FF6">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="CCEDAB29F5FF6004F78F085C1E5EBD63">Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="5F543BDD539138C0EBC2442FA0DAE912">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="A192B9D131DF0364F7C1570EB572A3B2" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="F055489281E1578360BD2A39429FF0AC">
<mods:title id="F877695BED4416ADE6B473A18F221DA2">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="3FE7EE0AE595C8C49FDC615F5D68AE41">
<mods:date id="FBE2C1FF043F6661386E5F24C2B89986">2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="B6CD3EED4EA9439C13473574CA5D6950" type="volume">
<mods:number id="B0FB8F8D53CC65B72BE5E3504F770084">719</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="2FE1854DFC8A982F791C839C679F3D7A" unit="page">
<mods:start id="82E49E5EF402B1BB3A9CD43F319A247D">75</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B4EC1A68D40577C04E43BD88852BAECD">157</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="46A63D7B2A36EDD15D666F2F34595FC8">
<mods:url id="04CCE602AAC6BE6445A0C3FF2BB4831C">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="4F3A966E775C79F22F9FA3DF2A5FCCEA">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C1C37A47432ABB1F36EADFBF5B7D648A" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="C52E5A065EC6760FC99749BB7C4059A1" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-719-75</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="1CD056771F299D7BE314EF42F7AE42EC" type="ZBK">36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="188AD51C6B2CA8F8CEE93F10516E4BE1" type="ZooBank">36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="01CFDD0986FB298EBCE962472D3F8809" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200948" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:01CFDD0986FB298EBCE962472D3F8809" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/01CFDD0986FB298EBCE962472D3F8809" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="131" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">
<subSubSection id="9DBBF5EB330EB2DEB0B188F216B41A27" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="47DC61ABD8C7FAAA816DB175BC878302" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">
<taxonomicName id="B7F61E63A20BFA140CB6C2804D99348A" authority="Schaeffer, 1908" authorityName="Schaeffer" authorityYear="1908" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Monophylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monophylla pallipes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pallipes">Monophylla pallipes Schaeffer, 1908</taxonomicName>
Figs 4C, 20C
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="280E835142FA06260CFBE4236F7872F8" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" type="type material">
<paragraph id="4C7075F5A7CBE891B00C4A1F6A975302" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Type material not examined.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="019A45691859BF21E1E60E24C6A7304F" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" type="type locality">
<paragraph id="3AA15E1E91B5F32D73C7C33469B42224" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7147AF7CB9D20AEB81CB185A6EFF2665" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Brownsville, Texas. Type depository: United States National History Museum (USNM).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D3E6C9EFD4B85E71BB0302AF76746FA9" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">
Holotype lost. Lectotype designated by 
<bibRefCitation id="09E3E11FB4804F120C81ABFA03649E34" author="Chapin, EA" journalOrPublisher="Smithsonian Miscellaneous Collection" pageId="75" pageNumber="150" pagination="1 - 12" title="Type material of the species of clerid beetles described by Charles Schaeffer." volume="11" year="1949">Chapin (1949)</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="37A20343DD146232787596FF438D64CD" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="2B0016A354AEE06A2245AA6DD7575A82" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D9526E34DA25DA1FD8B0136C7461FA47" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">USA: AZ, CA, TX; Mexico: Chiapas, Jalisco, Morelos, Quintana Roo, San Luis Potosi, Sinaloa, Tamaulipas, Yucatan; Central America: Costa Rica, Guatemala, Honduras; South America: Chile (introduced).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="97E5065D79EFB273A6EF30D77B4D117F" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph id="B803BADFBAF891A235DDF816D9CD1E68" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6F7F06E2DC2D5FBB06248499D1FD5F68" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">
<taxonomicName id="36C02025DBD828C3CC68C2FC7FF99442" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Monophylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monophylla pallipes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pallipes">Monophylla pallipes</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName id="1B7C1A8726659AC7C9DF5CD534B1AE08" genus="M." lsidName="M. californica" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" rank="species" species="californica">M. californica</taxonomicName>
. The two species are sympatric in distribution; therefore, they can be misidentified when collected simultaneously. Diagnostic characters are provided in the diagnosis of 
<taxonomicName id="8B20BBC55988640275183616E8577FCC" genus="M." lsidName="M. californica" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" rank="species" species="californica">M. californica</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="CB8764CE57E88BEAEBF035C7EA90AEBF" lastPageId="55" lastPageNumber="130" pageId="54" pageNumber="129" type="redescription">
<paragraph id="8E16335E5EF4645A7CD4DBF6AA24179F" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Redescription.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3E9CA393CC3C515A7FFB9B6443FF31FF" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Male. Form: Small to moderately large, slender individuals. Color: Head, antennae, pronotum, scutellum and legs dark testaceous to almost piceous; the anterior and posterior margins of the pronotum have a narrow ferrugineous to testaceous band; thorax ferrugineous to almost black; elytra testaceous to piceous, each elytron may have a pale to yellowish fascia on the median region of the elytral disc that initiates on the epipleural fold and does not reach the elytral suture; mouthparts fuscous, abdominal segments light testaceous to fuscous (Fig. 4C).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D150EF0B225F1FBBCB1AA54C5667F0AF" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Head: Including eyes narrower than pronotum; eyes small, taller than wide, feebly bulging laterally, antennal notch in front of eye emargination; integument coarsely to slightly punctate; clothed with fine, pale, semirecumbent and semi-erect setae intermixed with some scattered erect, pale setae; antennae consisting of 10 antennomeres; second antennomeres robust, rather short, antennomeres 3-4 small, conspicuously compacted; antennomeres 5-9 serrate, serration and size gradually increasing toward distal end, last antennomeres noticeably enlarged, conspicuously compressed laterally, much longer than remaining antennomeres combined (Fig. 4C); last antennomere sexually dimorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E89B483A8A6A337DECBAD71C738D9A82" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Thorax: Pronotum subparallel, widest at middle, constricted toward posterior margin; pronotal surface moderately to conspicuously punctate, rugose to rugulose; pronotal disc flat; clothed with fine, short, pale and dark, semirecumbent setae interspersed with some long and very long, erect, dark setae; anterior transverse depression feebly impressed, subbasal tumescence absent. Prosternum as long as wide; strongly punctate; punctation fine, shallow; surface feebly clothed. Mesoventrite: Surface moderately to coarsely punctate; punctations wide, deep; vested with fine, pale, semi-erect setae. Metepisterna visible throughout their length, not covered by elytra. Metaventrite: Convex; integument punctate laterally; punctation wide and shallow; moderately clothed with fine, pale, recumbent setae; longitudinal depression present, metaventral process absent. Scutellum wide, clothed with pale, fine, recumbent setae, compressed medially.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="715DAA8DC4E4F86A55A1C1920FDEAEF4" pageId="54" pageNumber="129">Elytra: Anterior margin slightly broader than pronotum; elongate; subparallel, humeri inconspicuously indicated, rounded; sides gradually expanding toward distal end, widest on middle third then narrowing toward apex; elytral apices subtriangular; inconspicuously dehiscent; elytral declivity gradual; surface clothed with fine, short, pale and dark, semi-erect and erect setae; conspicuously punctate, punctations small and shallow, irregularly arranged, punctations reaching the elytral apex; interstices smooth, narrow. Epipleural fold gradually narrowing toward apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1BB544B9BBA2EB12EB38EA72E5988BBC" pageId="55" pageNumber="130">
<pageBreakToken id="D9534E2B6D5B1B2A4C0339F2A6A3D43D" pageId="55" pageNumber="130" start="start">Legs</pageBreakToken>
: Femora rugulose to smooth; expanded behind middle; laterally compressed; clothed with some pale, fine, semi erect setae; surface feebly, shallowly punctate. Tibiae rugulose, slender, puncticulate; vestiture consisting of fine, pale, semi-erect setae mingled with some pale, semirecumbent setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CA44589B2C0848554F0CC4B615A9DBDF" pageId="55" pageNumber="130">Abdomen: Six visible ventrites. Ventrites 1-4 convex, smooth, shiny. First visible ventrite longer than second visible ventrite, feebly rugulose; ventrites 2-4 subquadrate; punctate; vested with fine, long, pale, recumbent setae; not compressed laterally; posterior margins truncate. Fifth visible ventrite convex; subquadrate; surface rugulose; puncticulate; vested with fine, pale, recumbent setae; lateral margins subparallel, arcuate; posterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate. Sixth visible ventrite subquadrate; surface slightly to moderately rugulose, convex to almost flat; feebly compressed on the median-posterior region; clothed with some long, erect setae, vestiture more abundant on anterolateral margins; lateral margins oblique, slightly arcuate; posterior margin broadly, deeply emarginate, U-shaped emarginate, posterolateral angles round. Fifth tergite subquadrate, surface convex; posterior margin truncate. Sixth tergite subquadrate; finely rugulose; surface convex posterior median region compressed; clothed with long, fine, pale and dark recumbent setae; lateral margins oblique; posterior margin broadly, moderately deeply emarginate, U-shaped emargination, posterolateral angles rounded. Sixth tergite slightly extending beyond apical margin of sixth visible ventrite, covering sixth ventrite in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="414C6EC466FEFA4C87626383DF7E9449" pageId="55" pageNumber="130">Aedeagus: Phallobasic apodeme present; phallus with copulatory piece swollen at apex; phallic plate armed with a row of denticles; intraspicular plate present, elongate; phallobasic apodeme conspicuously short, expanded distally; phallobase sinuate; parameres free; tegmen incomplete, partially covering the phallus; parameres pointed anteriorly; endophallic struts long, conspicuously robust distally (Fig. 20C).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C8BC914179D23567D48EC987CDBEC080" pageId="55" pageNumber="130">
Sexual dimorphism: Females of 
<taxonomicName id="50D4628D38FEAC9449170A4E2BB86DEA" genus="M." lsidName="M. pallipes" pageId="55" pageNumber="130" rank="species" species="pallipes">M. pallipes</taxonomicName>
differ from males based on the following characters: the tenth antennomere of females is shorter than in males; antennomeres 6-9 are larger and moderately serrate in females, but conspicuously reduced and compressed in males; and females have the last abdominal segment broadly rounded to feebly truncate, while males have this segment subquadrate in shape and emarginate posteriorly.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A46FAC1F71FD661F1DE0ACE8F92F553F" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="131" pageId="55" pageNumber="130" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="67B79ECA1300842D2D35736D27E2865B" pageId="55" pageNumber="130">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="349DAE9D48A0F2DC33E110D5B0C37D20" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="131" pageId="55" pageNumber="130">
2 males, 2 females: Hidalgo Co., TX, IV-7-1950, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males, 6 females: Brownsville, TX, V-25-1934, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males, 5 females: Brownsville, TX, V-14, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Brewster Co., TX, V-26-1948; 1 female: Cameron Co., TX, VI-4-1950, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 females: Corpus Christy, TX, III-30-1961, D. J. and J. N. Knull; l male: Gillespie Co., TX, IV-23, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 2 females: Hidalgo Co., TX, III-20-1952, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 1 female: Hidalgo Co., TX, III-29-1963, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Hidalgo Co., TX, III-26-1953, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 1 female: Starr Co., TX, IV-9-1963, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males: Starr Co., TX, III-20-1952, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Hidalgo Co., TX, 7-IV-1950, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 1 female: Hidalgo Co., TX, V-23-1953, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males: Jackson Co., TX, V-22, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males, 1 female: Brownsville, TX, V-19, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 3 males, 2 females: Uvalde Co., TX, VI-13-1949, J. 
<pageBreakToken id="6F749332D74AC1331DAFE195FD4ABA5D" pageId="56" pageNumber="131" start="start">N</pageBreakToken>
. Knull; 1 female: Santa Cruz Co., CA, Glenwood road, VI-16-1968, W. H. Tyson; 1 female: Gillespie Co., TX, VI-1, J. N. Knull; 1 male: Brownsville, TX, V-12, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Brownsville, TX, V-5, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Brownsville, TX, XI-19-1911, in pasture, Garden; 1 female: Cameron Co., TX, 2 mi E Los Indios, V-13-1978, N. M. Downie; 1 female: Cameron Co., TX, Sabal Palm Grove, IV-20-30-1986, D. H. Heffern; 2 males, 3 females: San Patricio Co., TX, Welder Wildlife Ref., VII-10-20-1981, R. H. Turnbow; 3 males: Cameron Co., TX, Sabal Palm Grove Sanctuary, III-16-1981, R. H. Turnbow; 2 males: Cameron Co., TX, Palm Groove Sanctuary, Brownsville, I-1977, F. T. Hovore; 1 female: Hidalgo Co., TX, Santa Ana National Refugee vic., Willow Lake, T. C. MacRae; 1 male: Starr Co., TX, Rio Grande City, X-10-1972, E. Giesbert; 1 female: San Patricio Co., TX, Welder Wildlife Refuge, V-10-12-1977, E. Giesbert; 1 male: TX, reared from mesquite logs, emerged X-10-1955, H. F. Howden; 1 male, 1 female: TX, Lake Corpus Christy State Park, VI-19-1971; G. H. Nelson; 1 male: Cameron Co., TX, Sabal Palm Grove Sanctuary, III-20-1982, R. Turnbow. MEXICO: 1 male: Sinaloa, Mexico, 3 km E El Marmol, VIII-8-1983, E. Giesbert; 1 male, 2 females: San Luis 
<normalizedToken id="1BF8059B672FCB6E4655497FE6A9AFD2" originalValue="Potosí">Potosi</normalizedToken>
, Mexico, 69.5 km N Tamazunchale, VI-5-1987, R. H. Turnbow; 2 males, 3 females: Jalisco, Mexico, 1.2 km S of La Cumbre, VII-19-2011, R. H. Turnbow; 2 males, 1 female: Tamaulipas, Mexico, 1-2 mi E Nuevo Morelos, VI-2-1982, R. H. Turnbow; 1 male: Guerrero, Mexico, 7.3 km NW Ixtapa, VII-17-1985, R. Turnbow; 2 males, 2 females: Quintana Roo, Mexico, highway 186, 17 km S jct. 307, V-30-1984, R. Turnbow; 1 female: Yucatan, Mexico, 2 km E Chichen Itza, V-26-1984, R. Turnbow; 1 female: Chiapas, Mexico, 4 mi NW of Pueblo Nuevo River Bajada, VII-15-1965, G. H. Nelson. CENTRAL AMERICA: 1 female: El Paraiso, Honduras, 31.5 km W Danli, VII-20-1995, R. Turnbow.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A57F95F2CA4C15543352160FEE6DD148" pageId="56" pageNumber="131" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="CB671B37F2A2ED8CF50699A257A9339F" pageId="56" pageNumber="131">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5641F390E47C87CA1C3622618D518CB2" pageId="56" pageNumber="131">
The holotype of 
<taxonomicName id="D810C625AC8DD0768D20DA6C5F1C2C4C" genus="M." lsidName="M. pallipes" pageId="56" pageNumber="131" rank="species" species="pallipes">M. pallipes</taxonomicName>
was lost and a lectotype was designated by 
<bibRefCitation id="CAE5549DD5B600FF9E3A66BFFEA159B9" author="Chapin, EA" journalOrPublisher="Smithsonian Miscellaneous Collection" pageId="75" pageNumber="150" pagination="1 - 12" title="Type material of the species of clerid beetles described by Charles Schaeffer." volume="11" year="1949">Chapin (1949)</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>