<document id="499C409AC8FC241629E6FD6E4FB810A6" ID-ISSN="1175­5334" _generate="retained" approvalRequired="19" approvalRequired_for_originalDoi="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="17" approvalRequired_for_treatments="1" checkinTime="1629733388720" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Berniker, Lily, Szerlip, Sigurd, Forero, Dimitri &amp; Weirauch, Christiane" docDate="2011" docId="03A43D516F11FFC4FE19FDB0EB91DDE7" docLanguage="en" docName="zt02949p113.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2949" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1.1:Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleId="D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Apiomerus peninsularis Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch 2011, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="23" masterDocId="FF9D45296F04FFD2FFCEFF87E946DD48" masterDocTitle="2949" masterLastPageNumber="113" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" updateTime="1630079104463" updateUser="GgImagineBatch" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="E09F5CF232E55DCAE2D742D123E2A449" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="49DBB933DB0C7F7412953ED90D731C97">
<mods:title id="8289845D454EA16026EB3AE1F934979B">2949</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="25940BA8D4C8E02AADBC2E1F5F29A38A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A7B89CCF0C5664D89E03562411FAAEAF">
<mods:roleTerm id="866E333E8B67BD4720BE99D497E53259">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="57C9E084272D0FD82933D4A9C7139565">Berniker, Lily</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="13AF992B033D77C064C645FB4A6A6409" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A96B350B3F5429C4DE400B1F907F8881">
<mods:roleTerm id="ED3C9E2D915A7D4F51D33C6478F58BC0">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="D801897A9087C3822EEBF4EFCD066866">Szerlip, Sigurd</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="DDC69C4D386DC5249161EABA112DFF70" type="personal">
<mods:role id="323B20B18EB0EF7FAB9F259344FFCBD1">
<mods:roleTerm id="6218372CABCCA72A91CA10EAC8464AB0">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2F37C24A0B68D0A9378BBDB430A3B4A8">Forero, Dimitri</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="EA88EE4FB5FE76B52FF923F328AE153A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3A246844FD978BA0B9B9142A77534C62">
<mods:roleTerm id="0440EA0A6E450632E5E0885B60BC7D0D">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="BB6C1602888517DF48D6AD4115924FFD">Weirauch, Christiane</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="0B591EC5DF72FBD7B5EB3125D00EAAE6">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="4404862CD121C07BA4C52D63B9F1D78A" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="79F8ADA712879F23F820564AF1EA2C87">
<mods:title id="820B4E0C7D48D5F4558FAFC6D446DB71">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="81EB55B83CD18226F8FFFC39EB5B8A99">
<mods:date id="AC4F8CAAF998DD0EC6D37F3A800BB3EF">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="177A3D751B34340FC7D9633F819762EA" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="1A3E71B4371E3D2B61BD51003CDE44D6">2011-07-08</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="5E6A47307249DECAE02E7A84D9ED6199" type="volume">
<mods:number id="EF3D13C200D13490289963E4D0420AC3">2949</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="F7FD1AE99BE8778DA248ACC11A2E5DEA" unit="page">
<mods:start id="F26EA3A814E2A1D1AA2ACC58050F31A3">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="AE3911CDFE2FEBEC5195A968F5A755AA">113</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="811D3A618FF2DD4829DF9E37F52B0F13">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="211F58D1D0476EB172AD51F78D268EDF" type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03A43D516F11FFC4FE19FDB0EB91DDE7" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03A43D516F11FFC4FE19FDB0EB91DDE7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03A43D516F11FFC4FE19FDB0EB91DDE7" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="23" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<subSubSection id="C317DFCC6F11FFC7FE19FDB0EA3ADF3A" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FE19FDB0EA3ADF3A" blockId="21.[471,1115,567,626]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FE19FDB0ED1DDF19" bold="true" box="[471,1115,567,593]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FE19FDB0EAB7DF19" authority="Berniker &amp; Szerlip" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" box="[471,1009,567,593]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peninsularis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FE19FDB0EBBFDF19" bold="true" box="[471,761,567,593]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Apiomerus peninsularis</emphasis>
Berniker &amp; Szerlip
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A24AED2E6F11FFC7FC30FDB0ED1DDF19" box="[1022,1115,567,593]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FD78FDDDEA6EDF3A" box="[694,808,602,626]" captionStart-0="FIGURE 1" captionStart-1="FIGURE 2" captionStart-10="FIGURE 11" captionStart-11="FIGURE 12" captionStart-12="FIGURE 13" captionStart-13="FIGURE 14" captionStart-14="FIGURE 15" captionStart-2="FIGURE 3" captionStart-3="FIGURE 4" captionStart-4="FIGURE 5" captionStart-5="FIGURE 6" captionStart-6="FIGURE 7" captionStart-7="FIGURE 8" captionStart-8="FIGURE 9" captionStart-9="FIGURE 10" captionStartId-0="32.[151,244,1889,1910]" captionStartId-1="33.[151,244,1880,1901]" captionStartId-10="42.[151,244,1893,1914]" captionStartId-11="43.[151,244,1126,1147]" captionStartId-12="43.[151,244,1951,1972]" captionStartId-13="44.[151,244,1844,1865]" captionStartId-14="45.[151,244,1846,1867]" captionStartId-2="34.[151,244,1878,1899]" captionStartId-3="35.[151,244,1878,1899]" captionStartId-4="36.[151,244,1856,1877]" captionStartId-5="37.[151,244,1891,1912]" captionStartId-6="38.[151,244,1893,1914]" captionStartId-7="39.[151,244,1114,1135]" captionStartId-8="40.[151,244,1110,1131]" captionStartId-9="41.[151,244,1834,1855]" captionTargetBox-0="[211,1379,155,1873]" captionTargetBox-1="[209,1377,151,1869]" captionTargetBox-10="[209,1377,153,1871]" captionTargetBox-11="[151,1436,155,1102]" captionTargetBox-12="[184,1390,1281,1925]" captionTargetBox-13="[226,1360,155,1823]" captionTargetBox-14="[226,1360,157,1825]" captionTargetBox-2="[209,1377,151,1867]" captionTargetBox-3="[209,1377,151,1865]" captionTargetBox-4="[218,1369,151,1837]" captionTargetBox-5="[209,1377,151,1869]" captionTargetBox-6="[209,1377,153,1871]" captionTargetBox-7="[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetBox-8="[151,1436,155,1088]" captionTargetBox-9="[226,1360,151,1813]" captionTargetId-0="figure-119@32.[211,1380,155,1873]" captionTargetId-1="figure-143@33.[209,1378,151,1869]" captionTargetId-10="figure-123@42.[209,1378,153,1871]" captionTargetId-11="figure-171@43.[151,1436,155,1104]" captionTargetId-12="figure-174@43.[151,1436,1239,1951]" captionTargetId-13="figure-170@44.[226,1360,155,1823]" captionTargetId-14="figure-154@45.[226,1360,157,1825]" captionTargetId-2="figure-158@34.[209,1378,149,1867]" captionTargetId-3="figure-157@35.[209,1378,147,1865]" captionTargetId-4="figure-169@36.[218,1369,145,1837]" captionTargetId-5="figure-133@37.[209,1378,151,1869]" captionTargetId-6="figure-118@38.[209,1378,153,1871]" captionTargetId-7="figure-227@39.[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetId-8="figure-132@40.[151,1436,155,1088]" captionTargetId-9="figure-185@41.[226,1360,145,1813]" captionTargetPageId-0="32" captionTargetPageId-1="33" captionTargetPageId-10="42" captionTargetPageId-11="43" captionTargetPageId-12="43" captionTargetPageId-13="44" captionTargetPageId-14="45" captionTargetPageId-2="34" captionTargetPageId-3="35" captionTargetPageId-4="36" captionTargetPageId-5="37" captionTargetPageId-6="38" captionTargetPageId-7="39" captionTargetPageId-8="40" captionTargetPageId-9="41" captionText-0="FIGURE 1. Habitus images of males (left) and females (right) of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani Costa Lima, Campos Seabra, and Hathaway new status, D, A. crassipes (Fabricius), E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis (Fallou), I, A. spissipes (Say), J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris Herrich-Schaeffer and L, A. pictipes Herrich-Schaeffer. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 5mm." captionText-1="FIGURE 2. Caudal views of the pygophores of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus, showing the median process of the pygophore. Members of the crassipes species group have rami of the median process in a U shape; pictipes group members have rami of the median process nearly horizontal. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-10="FIGURE 11. Syntergite 9/10 of females of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. The arrow indicates the distal margin of the syntergite, which in some species is emarginate. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes.. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm" captionText-11="FIGURE 12. Gonocoxa 8 of females of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-12="FIGURE 13. Gonoplac of A. wygodzinskyi, sp. nov., showing the dorso-medial projection (dmp) and ventral projection (vp). In females of both the crassipes and pictipes species groups of Apiomerus, the dmp is short and reaches approximately half the height of the apex of the ventral projection. The number in the box refers to the USI with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 0.5 mm." captionText-13="FIGURE 14. Dorsal view of the bursa copulatrix of females of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. See terminology for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. Arrows in A-J point to the transverse sclerotized folds in the bursa. The number of arrows indicates the number of folds. The arrow in K points to the dorsal-most transverse fold which in females of the pictipes group protrudes over the other folds. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-14="FIGURE 15. Ventral view of the bursa copulatrix of females of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. See terminology for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. Arrows in B-K point to gonapophysis 8 and the anterior portion of gonapohysis 8, showing that they are two separate sclerites. The two sclerites are adjacent and almost entire in D, I, and K. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-2="FIGURE 3. Lateral views of the pygophores of members of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. Members of the crassipes species group have the median process of the pygophore oriented nearly vertical in this view, perpendicular to the long axis of the pygophore, whereas the pictipes group members have the median process nearly horizontal, parallel to the long axis of the pygophore. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-3="FIGURE 4. Ventral views of the pygophores of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. Arrows point to the apex of the rami which have an acute projection in the members of the crassipes group (as seen in A, D, E, G, and J), but which are not produced in the members of the pictipes group (as seen in K and L). A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-4="FIGURE 5. Dorsal views of the pygophores of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. In the crassipes species group, the inner margin of the genital opening has sclerotized protuberances (A-J). In the pictipes species group the inner margin of the genital opening is smooth without protuberances (K-L). Tergite 9 has been removed in F, J and L. Arrows in B point to the protuberances on the inner margin of the pygophore. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-5="FIGURE 6. Aedeagus of the members of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus in dorsal view. The arrow in L points to the sclerotized median dorsal lobe. See terminology section for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-6="FIGURE 7. Aedeagus of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus in lateral view. See terminology for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." captionText-7="FIGURE 8. Close view of the aedeagus of males of the crassipes (A-C) and pictipes (D) species groups of Apiomerus. A. An example of dorso-lateral lobes (dltlb) that are not divided into proximal and distal portions, but present as a single folded sclerite, a tongue shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs) and a pointed posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). B. An example of dorsal lateral lobes that are divided with a semi-circular proximal portion (pdltlb) and an entire and elongated distal portion (ddltlb), and a pyramid shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs). C. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided and in which the proximal (pdltlb) and distal (ddltlb) portions are both tongue shaped and the distal is short and entire. D. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided, with a tongue shaped proximal portion (pdltlb) and in which the distal portion (ddltlb) is subdivided into medial and lateral lobe, a median dorsal lobe (mdlb) that is sclerotized, and a rounded posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). A, A.californicus, sp. nov., B, A. crassipes, C, A. wygodzinskyi, sp. nov., and D, A. flaviventris. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT." captionText-8="FIGURE 9. Parameres of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. Males of the crassipes species group have parameres that are strongly curved, whereas males of the pictipes species group have parameres that are weakly curved. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale, 1mm." captionText-9="FIGURE 10. Caudal view of the abdomen of females of the crassipes and pictipes species groups of Apiomerus showing tergite 8 and syntergite 9/10. The arrow in A points to the lateral margin of tergite 8, which is expanded into deflexed lobes in nearly the same plane as syntergite 9/10. Females in the crassipes species group have lobes which are concave medially and extend to roughly half the length of syntergite 9/10 (A-J). Females in the pictipes species group have lobes which are shorter, extending only slightly beyond the margin of syntergite 9/10 and nearly flat medially (K-L). A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Figs 1–15</figureCitation>
, Map 1
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C317DFCC6F11FFC7FF59FD24E8BFDF94" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59FD24E8BFDF94" blockId="21.[151,505,674,732]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<treatmentCitationGroup id="AB1DAB696F11FFC7FF59FD24E8BFDF94" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FF59FD24E839DFF2" authorityName="Det. by" baseAuthorityName="Fabricius" baseAuthorityYear="1803" box="[151,383,675,699]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="crassipes">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59FD24E839DFF2" box="[151,383,675,699]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Apiomerus crassipes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(in part) 
<treatmentCitation id="0AACAA566F11FFC7FF09FD41E82BDF94" author="Uhler, P. R." box="[199,365,710,732]" page="284" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" year="1894">
<bibRefCitation id="EF9CF1B66F11FFC7FF09FD41E82BDF94" author="Uhler" box="[199,365,710,732]" firstAuthor="Uhler" page="284" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" pagination="223 - 295" refId="ref29565" refString="Uhler, P. R. (1894) Observations upon the Heteropterous Hemiptera of Lower California, with descriptions of new species. Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences, (2) 4, 223 - 295." type="journal article" year="1894">Uhler 1894: 284</bibRefCitation>
</treatmentCitation>
(distribution)
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C317DFCC6F11FFC4FF59FC8DEB91DDE7" lastPageId="22" lastPageNumber="23" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59FC8DEAC4DEC5" blockId="21.[151,1436,777,909]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59FC8DE845DE69" box="[151,259,777,801]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Type data</emphasis>
: 
<typeStatus id="54B632E56F11FFC7FEDFFC8EE838DE69" box="[273,382,777,801]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Holotype</typeStatus>
: 
<specimenCount id="9D0B47CE6F11FFC7FE46FC8EE8F6DE69" box="[392,432,777,801]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" type="male">1 ♂</specimenCount>
; 
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FE71FC8EEB73DE6A" bold="true" box="[447,565,777,802]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<collectingCountry id="F31ACCD76F11FFC7FE71FC8EEB73DE6A" box="[447,565,777,802]" name="Mexico" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">MEXICO</collectingCountry>
</emphasis>
: 
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FD8DFC8EEA68DE6A" bold="true" box="[579,814,777,802]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<collectingRegion id="49C942A56F11FFC7FD8DFC8EEA68DE6A" box="[579,814,777,802]" country="Mexico" name="Baja California Sur" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Baja California Sur</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<quantity id="4CF521A26F11FFC7FCF2FC8EEA2BDE69" box="[828,877,777,801]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="9.656064" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" unit="mi" value="6.0">6 mi</quantity>
N of 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FC63FC8EED69DE69" authority="Anita" authorityName="Anita" box="[941,1071,777,801]" class="Insecta" family="Hesperiidae" genus="Santa" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Santa Anita</taxonomicName>
[
<geoCoordinate id="EE39EA806F11FFC7FBF2FC8EED81DE69" box="[1084,1223,777,802]" degrees="23.23606" direction="north" orientation="latitude" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" precision="1" value="23.23606">
23.23606 
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FB66FC8EEDF5DE6A" bold="true" box="[1192,1203,777,802]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">°</emphasis>
N
</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate id="EE39EA806F11FFC7FB00FC8EEC29DE69" box="[1230,1391,777,802]" degrees="109.71657" direction="west" orientation="longitude" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" precision="1" value="-109.71657">
109.71657 
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FA8AFC8EEC09DE6A" bold="true" box="[1348,1359,777,802]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">°</emphasis>
W
</geoCoordinate>
], 
<date id="FFB3AA876F11FFC7FA4FFC8EE9B9DE0D" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" value="1967-09-11">11 Sep 1967</date>
/ J. Chemsak, A. &amp; M. Michelbacher Collectors / 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FCFFFCAAEDDDDE0D" authority="(Fab.) Det." authorityName="Det. by" baseAuthorityName="Fabricius" baseAuthorityYear="1803" box="[817,1179,813,837]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="crassipes">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FCFFFCAAED5FDE0D" box="[817,1049,813,837]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Apiomerus crassipes</emphasis>
(Fab.) Det.
</taxonomicName>
by S. L. Szerlip 1972 / Univ. Calif. Insect Survey Specimen # 149859 / 
<typeStatus id="54B632E56F11FFC7FD76FCD6EA0ADE21" box="[696,844,849,873]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">HOLOTYPE</typeStatus>
<specimenCount id="9D0B47CE6F11FFC7FC9AFCD5EA2FDE21" box="[852,873,850,873]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" type="male">♂</specimenCount>
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FCBEFCD6ED3CDE21" authority="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch, 2011" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" box="[880,1146,849,873]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peninsularis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FCBEFCD6ED3CDE21" box="[880,1146,849,873]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Apiomerus peninsularis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A24AED2E6F11FFC7FB4DFCD5EDF9DE21" box="[1155,1215,850,873]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Berniker &amp; Szerlip Det. by: Berniker &amp; Szerlip 2011 / (
<collectionCode id="ED1C14826F11FFC7FDE6FCF2EB24DEC5" box="[552,610,885,909]" country="USA" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:15736" name="University of California" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" type="Herbarium">UCR</collectionCode>
_ENT 00033611) (
<collectionCode id="ED1C14826F11FFC7FCF8FCF2EA33DEC5" box="[822,885,885,909]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/wq7v-amgw" name="University of California at Berkeley" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">UCB</collectionCode>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59FC39E89AD955" blockId="21.[151,1436,957,1053]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59FC39E84FDE9D" box="[151,265,958,981]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Diagnosis</emphasis>
: Recognized by its relatively small size (
<quantity id="4CF521A26F11FFC7FD1FFC3AEA3FDE9D" box="[721,889,957,981]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.35" metricValueMax="1.45" metricValueMin="1.25" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" unit="mm" value="13.5" valueMax="14.5" valueMin="12.5">12.5–14.5 mm</quantity>
), dark red body and legs, orange posterior pronotal margin, red hemelytra (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FE08FC66EB59DEB1" box="[454,543,993,1017]" captionStart="FIGURE 1" captionStartId="32.[151,244,1889,1910]" captionTargetBox="[211,1379,155,1873]" captionTargetId="figure-119@32.[211,1380,155,1873]" captionTargetPageId="32" captionText="FIGURE 1. Habitus images of males (left) and females (right) of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani Costa Lima, Campos Seabra, and Hathaway new status, D, A. crassipes (Fabricius), E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis (Fallou), I, A. spissipes (Say), J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris Herrich-Schaeffer and L, A. pictipes Herrich-Schaeffer. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 5mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 1G</figureCitation>
), and the dorsolateral lobes of the endosoma not clearly divided into proximal and distal portions (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FEBBFB82E889D955" box="[373,463,1029,1053]" captionStart="FIGURE 6" captionStartId="37.[151,244,1891,1912]" captionTargetBox="[209,1377,151,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-133@37.[209,1378,151,1869]" captionTargetPageId="37" captionText="FIGURE 6. Aedeagus of the members of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus in dorsal view. The arrow in L points to the sclerotized median dorsal lobe. See terminology section for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 6G</figureCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59FBC9ED48D8B9" blockId="21.[151,1437,1101,1629]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59FBC9E85DD92D" box="[151,283,1102,1125]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Description</emphasis>
: Male: Small, total length 
<quantity id="4CF521A26F11FFC7FD89FBCAEBABD92D" box="[583,749,1101,1125]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.29" metricValueMax="1.33" metricValueMin="1.25" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" unit="mm" value="12.9" valueMax="13.3" valueMin="12.5">12.5–13.3 mm</quantity>
. COLORATION: 
<collectionCode id="ED1C14826F11FFC7FC77FBCAED4DD92D" box="[953,1035,1101,1125]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">HEAD</collectionCode>
: Dark red to black. THORAX: Pronotum and scutellum dark red, margin of posterior pronotal lobe orange, thoracic pleura, corium and all legs dark red. ABDOMEN: including pygophore dark red to black, connexivum orange. STRUCTURE: 
<collectionCode id="ED1C14826F11FFC7FB13FB12EC69D9E5" box="[1245,1327,1173,1197]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">HEAD</collectionCode>
: about as long as pronotum, head width about 5 times width of eye, length of eye in dorsal view about 1/5 of head length. THORAX: pronotum 1.3 times wider than long, anterolateral angle truncate, disc of anterior lobe with paired greatly convex lobes, posterior margin straight. ABDOMEN: pygophore about 1/5 length of abdomen, median pygophore process U-shaped in caudal view, ramus longer than base width (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FC30FAA2ED1FD875" box="[1022,1113,1317,1341]" captionStart="FIGURE 2" captionStartId="33.[151,244,1880,1901]" captionTargetBox="[209,1377,151,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-143@33.[209,1378,151,1869]" captionTargetPageId="33" captionText="FIGURE 2. Caudal views of the pygophores of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus, showing the median process of the pygophore. Members of the crassipes species group have rami of the median process in a U shape; pictipes group members have rami of the median process nearly horizontal. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Figs 2G</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FBA9FAA2EDCED875" box="[1127,1160,1317,1341]" captionStart="FIGURE 3" captionStartId="34.[151,244,1878,1899]" captionTargetBox="[209,1377,151,1867]" captionTargetId="figure-158@34.[209,1378,149,1867]" captionTargetPageId="34" captionText="FIGURE 3. Lateral views of the pygophores of members of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. Members of the crassipes species group have the median process of the pygophore oriented nearly vertical in this view, perpendicular to the long axis of the pygophore, whereas the pictipes group members have the median process nearly horizontal, parallel to the long axis of the pygophore. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">3G</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FB58FAA2EDF1D875" box="[1174,1207,1317,1341]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="35.[151,244,1878,1899]" captionTargetBox="[209,1377,151,1865]" captionTargetId="figure-157@35.[209,1378,147,1865]" captionTargetPageId="35" captionText="FIGURE 4. Ventral views of the pygophores of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. Arrows point to the apex of the rami which have an acute projection in the members of the crassipes group (as seen in A, D, E, G, and J), but which are not produced in the members of the pictipes group (as seen in K and L). A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">4G</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FB0AFAA2EDACD875" box="[1220,1258,1317,1341]" captionStart="FIGURE 5" captionStartId="36.[151,244,1856,1877]" captionTargetBox="[218,1369,151,1837]" captionTargetId="figure-169@36.[218,1369,145,1837]" captionTargetPageId="36" captionText="FIGURE 5. Dorsal views of the pygophores of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. In the crassipes species group, the inner margin of the genital opening has sclerotized protuberances (A-J). In the pictipes species group the inner margin of the genital opening is smooth without protuberances (K-L). Tergite 9 has been removed in F, J and L. Arrows in B point to the protuberances on the inner margin of the pygophore. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">5G</figureCitation>
). GENITALIA: distal portion of tergite 9 with setae on entire distal portion, posterior margin of dorsal phallothecal sclerite pointed in dorsal view (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FE88FAEAE8E6D8CD" box="[326,416,1389,1413]" captionStart="FIGURE 8" captionStartId="39.[151,244,1114,1135]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetId="figure-227@39.[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetPageId="39" captionText="FIGURE 8. Close view of the aedeagus of males of the crassipes (A-C) and pictipes (D) species groups of Apiomerus. A. An example of dorso-lateral lobes (dltlb) that are not divided into proximal and distal portions, but present as a single folded sclerite, a tongue shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs) and a pointed posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). B. An example of dorsal lateral lobes that are divided with a semi-circular proximal portion (pdltlb) and an entire and elongated distal portion (ddltlb), and a pyramid shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs). C. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided and in which the proximal (pdltlb) and distal (ddltlb) portions are both tongue shaped and the distal is short and entire. D. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided, with a tongue shaped proximal portion (pdltlb) and in which the distal portion (ddltlb) is subdivided into medial and lateral lobe, a median dorsal lobe (mdlb) that is sclerotized, and a rounded posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). A, A.californicus, sp. nov., B, A. crassipes, C, A. wygodzinskyi, sp. nov., and D, A. flaviventris. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 8A</figureCitation>
), apex in dorsal view narrow, less than half the width of dorsal phallothecal sclerite, endosomal struts fused at base and apex, or almost fused at apex, but not medially, dorsolateral lobes a single folded sclerite, not divided into proximal and distal portions (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FCC7FA32EA23D885" box="[777,869,1461,1485]" captionStart="FIGURE 8" captionStartId="39.[151,244,1114,1135]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetId="figure-227@39.[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetPageId="39" captionText="FIGURE 8. Close view of the aedeagus of males of the crassipes (A-C) and pictipes (D) species groups of Apiomerus. A. An example of dorso-lateral lobes (dltlb) that are not divided into proximal and distal portions, but present as a single folded sclerite, a tongue shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs) and a pointed posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). B. An example of dorsal lateral lobes that are divided with a semi-circular proximal portion (pdltlb) and an entire and elongated distal portion (ddltlb), and a pyramid shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs). C. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided and in which the proximal (pdltlb) and distal (ddltlb) portions are both tongue shaped and the distal is short and entire. D. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided, with a tongue shaped proximal portion (pdltlb) and in which the distal portion (ddltlb) is subdivided into medial and lateral lobe, a median dorsal lobe (mdlb) that is sclerotized, and a rounded posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). A, A.californicus, sp. nov., B, A. crassipes, C, A. wygodzinskyi, sp. nov., and D, A. flaviventris. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 8A</figureCitation>
), median basal sclerotization tongue shaped (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FAA0FA32E9FAD8B9" captionStart="FIGURE 8" captionStartId="39.[151,244,1114,1135]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetId="figure-227@39.[151,1436,153,1093]" captionTargetPageId="39" captionText="FIGURE 8. Close view of the aedeagus of males of the crassipes (A-C) and pictipes (D) species groups of Apiomerus. A. An example of dorso-lateral lobes (dltlb) that are not divided into proximal and distal portions, but present as a single folded sclerite, a tongue shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs) and a pointed posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). B. An example of dorsal lateral lobes that are divided with a semi-circular proximal portion (pdltlb) and an entire and elongated distal portion (ddltlb), and a pyramid shaped median basal sclerotization (mbs). C. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided and in which the proximal (pdltlb) and distal (ddltlb) portions are both tongue shaped and the distal is short and entire. D. An example of dorso-lateral lobes that are divided, with a tongue shaped proximal portion (pdltlb) and in which the distal portion (ddltlb) is subdivided into medial and lateral lobe, a median dorsal lobe (mdlb) that is sclerotized, and a rounded posterior margin of the dorsal phallothecal sclerite (pdps). A, A.californicus, sp. nov., B, A. crassipes, C, A. wygodzinskyi, sp. nov., and D, A. flaviventris. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 8A</figureCitation>
), distal dorsal lobe with two parallel rows of strong denticles (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FCB8FA5EEA97D8B9" box="[886,977,1497,1521]" captionStart="FIGURE 6" captionStartId="37.[151,244,1891,1912]" captionTargetBox="[209,1377,151,1869]" captionTargetId="figure-133@37.[209,1378,151,1869]" captionTargetPageId="37" captionText="FIGURE 6. Aedeagus of the members of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus in dorsal view. The arrow in L points to the sclerotized median dorsal lobe. See terminology section for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Figs 6G</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FC12FA5EED44D8B9" box="[988,1026,1497,1521]" captionStart="FIGURE 7" captionStartId="38.[151,244,1893,1914]" captionTargetBox="[209,1377,153,1871]" captionTargetId="figure-118@38.[209,1378,153,1871]" captionTargetPageId="38" captionText="FIGURE 7. Aedeagus of males of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus in lateral view. See terminology for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">7G</figureCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF09FA7AEBE1DB15" blockId="21.[151,1437,1101,1629]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
Female: Total length 
<quantity id="4CF521A26F11FFC7FE0EFA7AEBC0DB5D" box="[448,646,1533,1557]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.398" metricValueMax="1.454" metricValueMin="1.342" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" unit="mm" value="13.98" valueMax="14.54" valueMin="13.42">13.42–14.54 mm</quantity>
. STRUCTURE: ABDOMEN syntergite 9/10 with distal margin flat (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FF51F9A6E84EDB71" box="[159,264,1569,1593]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="42.[151,244,1893,1914]" captionTargetBox="[209,1377,153,1871]" captionTargetId="figure-123@42.[209,1378,153,1871]" captionTargetPageId="42" captionText="FIGURE 11. Syntergite 9/10 of females of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. The arrow indicates the distal margin of the syntergite, which in some species is emarginate. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes.. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 11G</figureCitation>
). GENITALIA: gonapophysis 8 with two distinct sclerotizations (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FC36F9A6ED27DB71" box="[1016,1121,1569,1593]" captionStart="FIGURE 15" captionStartId="45.[151,244,1846,1867]" captionTargetBox="[226,1360,157,1825]" captionTargetId="figure-154@45.[226,1360,157,1825]" captionTargetPageId="45" captionText="FIGURE 15. Ventral view of the bursa copulatrix of females of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. See terminology for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. Arrows in B-K point to gonapophysis 8 and the anterior portion of gonapohysis 8, showing that they are two separate sclerites. The two sclerites are adjacent and almost entire in D, I, and K. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 15G</figureCitation>
), bursa copulatrix with two narrow, transverse sclerotized folds (
<figureCitation id="133690C26F11FFC7FDFCF9C2EBDDDB15" box="[562,667,1605,1629]" captionStart="FIGURE 14" captionStartId="44.[151,244,1844,1865]" captionTargetBox="[226,1360,155,1823]" captionTargetId="figure-170@44.[226,1360,155,1823]" captionTargetPageId="44" captionText="FIGURE 14. Dorsal view of the bursa copulatrix of females of the crassipes (A-J) and pictipes (K-L) species groups of Apiomerus. See terminology for abbreviations and text for discussion of characters. Arrows in A-J point to the transverse sclerotized folds in the bursa. The number of arrows indicates the number of folds. The arrow in K points to the dorsal-most transverse fold which in females of the pictipes group protrudes over the other folds. A, A. californicus sp. nov., B, A. cazieri sp. nov., C, A. cooremani new status, D, A. crassipes, E, A. floridensis, sp. nov., F, A. montanus, sp. nov., G, A. peninsularis sp. nov., H, A. rufipennis, I, A. spissipes, J, A. wygodzinskyi sp. nov., K, A. flaviventris, and L, A. pictipes. Numbers in each box refer to USIs with the prefix UCR_ENT. Scale 1mm." pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Fig. 14G</figureCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59F90AEBAADBED" blockId="21.[151,748,1677,1701]" box="[151,748,1677,1701]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59F90AE849DBED" box="[151,271,1677,1701]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Etymology</emphasis>
: Named for the 
<collectingRegion id="49C942A56F11FFC7FE08F90AEB34DBED" box="[454,626,1677,1701]" country="Mexico" name="Baja California" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Baja California</collectingRegion>
peninsula.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59F952ECD0DBA5" blockId="21.[151,1430,1749,1774]" box="[151,1430,1749,1774]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59F952E9A8DBA5" box="[151,238,1749,1773]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Biology</emphasis>
: Specimens examined were collected between May and November at elevations between 285 and 
<quantity id="4CF521A26F11FFC7FAF4F952ECD7DBA5" box="[1338,1425,1749,1773]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.83" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" unit="m" value="1830.0">1830 m</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59F89AEB95DA7D" blockId="21.[151,723,1821,1845]" box="[151,723,1821,1845]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59F89AE866DA7D" box="[151,288,1821,1845]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Distribution</emphasis>
: 
<collectingRegion id="49C942A56F11FFC7FEE0F89AEB4FDA7D" box="[302,521,1821,1845]" country="Mexico" name="Baja California Sur" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Baja California Sur</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingCountry id="F31ACCD76F11FFC7FDDBF89AEB2CDA7D" box="[533,618,1821,1845]" name="Mexico" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Mexico</collectingCountry>
(Map 1).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F11FFC7FF59F8E1EA0FDAA1" blockId="21.[151,1436,1893,2025]" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FF59F8E1E854DA35" box="[151,274,1894,1917]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Discussion</emphasis>
: The only species that overlaps in range with 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FCE8F8E2EA94DA35" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" box="[806,978,1893,1917]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peninsularis">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FCE8F8E2EA94DA35" box="[806,978,1893,1917]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">A. peninsularis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FC38F8E2ED25DA35" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" box="[1014,1123,1893,1917]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cazieri">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FC38F8E2ED25DA35" box="[1014,1123,1893,1917]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">A. cazieri</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FBBAF8E2ECC7DA35" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" box="[1140,1409,1893,1917]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peninsularis">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FBBAF8E2ECC7DA35" box="[1140,1409,1893,1917]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">Apiomerus peninsularis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is fairly uniform in color, and though individuals of 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FD1CF80EEA78DAE9" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" box="[722,830,1929,1953]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cazieri">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FD1CF80EEA78DAE9" box="[722,830,1929,1953]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">A. cazieri</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
found on the Baja Peninsula are similar in size to 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FA4AF80EE864DA8D" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peninsularis">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FA4AF80EE864DA8D" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">A. peninsularis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, they do not have the characteristic dark red body and hemelytra, or orange pronotal margin of 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FA85F82AE9BFDAA1" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="peninsularis">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FA85F82AE9BFDAA1" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">A. peninsularis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(see 
<taxonomicName id="4C0DF7C46F11FFC7FEFAF856E8D9DAA1" authorityName="Berniker &amp; Szerlip &amp; Forero &amp; Weirauch" authorityYear="2011" box="[308,415,2001,2025]" class="Insecta" family="Reduviidae" genus="Apiomerus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="22" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cazieri">
<emphasis id="B97950556F11FFC7FEFAF856E8D9DAA1" box="[308,415,2001,2025]" italics="true" pageId="21" pageNumber="22">A. cazieri</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
discussion regarding color variation).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB28C476F12FFC4FF59FF1EEB91DDE7" blockId="22.[151,727,151,176]" box="[151,727,151,176]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<emphasis id="B97950556F12FFC4FF59FF1EE84FDDF8" box="[151,265,153,176]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<typeStatus id="54B632E56F12FFC4FF59FF1EE84FDDF8" box="[151,265,153,176]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Paratypes</typeStatus>
</emphasis>
: See Appendix; 
<specimenCount id="9D0B47CE6F12FFC4FE0AFF10EB1DDDE7" box="[452,603,151,175]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" type="generic">55 specimens</specimenCount>
examined.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>