<document id="B2553DFBD987AA83C4890751E678106B" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3681291" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8eaddec8-ce52-4222-a97c-a77d380cb09e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="162238180" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3681291" _generate="added" approvedBy="valdenar" checkinTime="1582225522033" checkinUser="valdenar" docAuthor="Gonçalves, Rodrigo Barbosa" docDate="2019" docId="03AF1274FFDDFF955E598B6F458FFAF7" docLanguage="en" docName="REVBRASENTOMOL.63.1.91–100.pdf" docOrigin="Revista Brasileira de Entomologia 63" docStyle="DocumentStyle{}" docTitle="Ceratalictus inflexus Gonçalves 2019, sp. nov" docType="treatment" docVersion="7" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="99" masterDocId="FF966A0CFFDAFF9D5E0C8D65406FFFAC" masterDocTitle="Systematics, Morphology and Biogeography Phylogeny of the Augochlora clade with the description of four new species (Hymenoptera, Apoidea)" masterLastPageNumber="100" masterPageNumber="91" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" updateTime="1643455391237" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-NC-ND-4.0">
<mods:mods id="5A0A5637E122A1955F79DC08E602EBA5" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="0EB81621F9F4AF5EC67FEEBA6FA091D8">
<mods:title id="BA4F7B4AE7388CF8048366C080DA7C65">Systematics, Morphology and Biogeography Phylogeny of the Augochlora clade with the description of four new species (Hymenoptera, Apoidea)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="083686315878118031FEA3F1B74BE7C2" type="personal">
<mods:role id="C697B3905F6F6A4E61185F1D44BDA1B8">
<mods:roleTerm id="1B91F4EE74732281870EEB0897480FCD">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="83C879560A65A6841FC4B211111D86E7">Gonçalves, Rodrigo Barbosa</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="3077031D60446F6F24950F1E0E9A25DB">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="7EAEDA6159354041203C9F7A6ADAD853" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="0300641B8DCA4E65CF3938255E918FDF">
<mods:title id="0BA5C489A16013D4D14162C06BDC0311">Revista Brasileira de Entomologia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="60D8595EEF7E25F58B4BB1A22F0637A5">
<mods:date id="6337DCCD38BE29D62D2DF419F8C1FF05">2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="994D8787B047854A7912EA0791314E6E" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="20239FB403DA26AE32A2BAF920EDCB59">2019-01-03</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="996CFB6A6DD12A56F433C2F0FEE0ADAF" type="volume">
<mods:number id="5ACA31D3C3B7D62A57976250896D5831">63</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="B46A776A999DBCCD417083B1C09E622B" unit="page">
<mods:start id="D0B3EC5228497B1685856116E822CE08">91</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F315D8D87433D02CFA80C1E6E9C46038">100</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="C0B3B0EB7D0E58F1C73C79DD037B470E">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="61D9B780C6F67CDA6732932280DCCF7E" type="DOI">10.1016/j.rbe.2018.12.003</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="BCE10F596E0A9A0EFD88EA744AFA00B9" type="GBIF-Dataset">8eaddec8-ce52-4222-a97c-a77d380cb09e</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B0E8C9B64CDB9961C80D2BD29BC998B4" type="Zenodo-Dep">3677410</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03AF1274FFDDFF955E598B6F458FFAF7" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3681291" ID-GBIF-Taxon="162238180" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3681291" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03AF1274FFDDFF955E598B6F458FFAF7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03AF1274FFDDFF955E598B6F458FFAF7" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">
<subSubSection id="C31CF0E9FFDDFF9A5E598B6F4103F9B2" box="[85,364,1546,1566]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFDDFF9A5E598B6F4103F9B2" blockId="7.[85,757,1546,1985]" box="[85,364,1546,1566]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">
<heading id="D0F1140EFFDDFF9A5E598B6F4107F9B2" box="[85,360,1546,1566]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">
<taxonomicName id="4C06D8E1FFDDFF9A5E598B6F4176F9B2" authority="Gonçalves, 2019" authorityName="Gonçalves" authorityYear="2019" box="[85,281,1546,1566]" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Ceratalictus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="inflexus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5E598B6F4176F9B2" box="[85,281,1546,1566]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Ceratalictusinflexus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A241C20BFFDDFF9A5F128B6E4107F9B2" box="[286,360,1547,1566]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" rank="species">sp. nov</taxonomicNameLabel>
</heading>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C31CF0E9FFDDFF9A5E798B42416DF996" box="[117,258,1575,1594]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFDDFF9A5E798B42416DF996" blockId="7.[85,757,1546,1985]" box="[117,258,1575,1594]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">
(
<figureCitation id="133DBFE7FFDDFF9A5E718B4240D2F996" box="[125,189,1575,1594]" captionStart="Fig" captionStartId="7.[85,112,880,894]" captionTargetBox="[133,708,149,849]" captionTargetId="figure@7.[132,708,149,849]" captionTargetPageId="7" captionText="Fig. 8. Holotype female of Ceratalictus inflexus sp. nov.(A) Habitus; (B) frontal view of head; (C) dorsal view of mesosoma. Scale bar: 0.5mm." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3677428" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3677428/files/figure.png" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Figs. 8</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation id="133DBFE7FFDDFF9A5EE18B424095F996" box="[237,250,1575,1594]" captionStart="Fig" captionStartId="7.[804,831,603,617]" captionTargetId="figure@7.[851,1427,149,572]" captionTargetPageId="7" captionText="Fig.9. Paratypemale ofCeratalictus inflexus sp.nov.(A) Dorsal view;(B)frontal view of head; (C) ventral view of genitalia. Scale bar: A and B at 0.5 mm, C at 0.25 mm." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3685820" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3685820/files/figure.png" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">9</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C31CF0E9FFDDFF9A5E598B27419BF8B5" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFDDFF9A5E598B27419BF8B5" blockId="7.[85,757,1546,1985]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5E598B2740D3F9F9" bold="true" box="[85,188,1602,1621]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Diagnosis</emphasis>
. 
<taxonomicName id="4C06D8E1FFDDFF9A5ECB8B2441E5F9F9" authority="Gonçalves, 2019" authorityName="Gonçalves" authorityYear="2019" box="[199,394,1601,1621]" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Ceratalictus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="inflexus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5ECB8B2441E5F9F9" box="[199,394,1601,1621]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Ceratalictus inflexus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A241C20BFFDDFF9A5F9C8B2641B2F9FA" box="[400,477,1603,1622]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is distinguished from other 
<taxonomicName id="4C06D8E1FFDDFF9A5E598B3840A7F9DD" authorityName="Moure" authorityYear="1943" box="[85,200,1629,1649]" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Ceratalictus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5E598B3840A7F9DD" box="[85,200,1629,1649]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Ceratalictus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
bythe combinationoflateralangle of pronotumobtuse; surface of mesoscutal diskweakly microreticulate; carinae of metapostnotum not reaching edge posteriorly; metapostnotum similar with metanotum in length and shape, and by the metasoma with blue reflections (
<figureCitation id="133DBFE7FFDDFF9A5F0D8BAB412EF94D" box="[257,321,1742,1761]" captionStart="Fig" captionStartId="7.[85,112,880,894]" captionTargetBox="[133,708,149,849]" captionTargetId="figure@7.[132,708,149,849]" captionTargetPageId="7" captionText="Fig. 8. Holotype female of Ceratalictus inflexus sp. nov.(A) Habitus; (B) frontal view of head; (C) dorsal view of mesosoma. Scale bar: 0.5mm." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3677428" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3677428/files/figure.png" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Figs. 8</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation id="133DBFE7FFDDFF9A5F788BAB41EEF94D" box="[372,385,1742,1761]" captionStart="Fig" captionStartId="7.[804,831,603,617]" captionTargetId="figure@7.[851,1427,149,572]" captionTargetPageId="7" captionText="Fig.9. Paratypemale ofCeratalictus inflexus sp.nov.(A) Dorsal view;(B)frontal view of head; (C) ventral view of genitalia. Scale bar: A and B at 0.5 mm, C at 0.25 mm." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3685820" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3685820/files/figure.png" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">9</figureCitation>
). The female has the basal elevation occupying all the longitudinal portion of labrum, the male has the antennae with sensilla placodea patches.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C31CF0E9FFDDFF955E598A474518FDE2" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="7" pageNumber="98" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFDDFF955E598A47458FFE72" blockId="7.[85,757,1546,1985]" lastBlockId="8.[833,1504,152,1371]" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5E598A4740BEF899" bold="true" box="[85,209,1826,1845]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Description</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5EEE8A4741F8F899" bold="true" box="[226,407,1826,1845]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">
<typeStatus id="54BD1DC0FFDDFF9A5EEE8A47412CF899" box="[226,323,1826,1845]" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Holotype</typeStatus>
female
</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5FA48A444216F899" box="[424,633,1825,1845]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Measurements (mm)</emphasis>
. Eye notch width: 1.5; head length: 1.7; glossa length: 0.4; clypeus width: 0.8; clypeus length: 0.4; supraclypeal length: 0.3; clypeus ocellar distance: 1.1; intertegular distance: 1.5; T1 width: 2.0; T2 width: 2.2; body length: 8.0. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5F8F8AF541DAF808" box="[387,437,1936,1956]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Head</emphasis>
. Labrum basal elevation orbicular, black. Mandible black with subapical amber spot; subapical tooth not strongly produced; long setae (2–3 OD) on outer and ventral margins. Epistomal angle obtuse. Clypeus coarsely punctate, microreticulate; erect setae with 1–1.5 OD; apical surface darkened, blue green. Supraclypeal area sparsely punctate, microreticulate; fine erect setae; blue green. Paraocular area coarsely punctate becoming conflected, strongly microreticulate; blue green; branched setae with 1–1.5 OD. Antennae, scape dark brown with very weak metallic highlights, flagellomeres amber ventrally, especially on F9–10; F1–2 and base of F3 setose, with inconspicuous sensilla, remaining flagellomeres with conspicuous sensilla. Frons not depressed; conflected punctate, strongly microreticulate; dark blue green; short and fine setae. Preoccipital ridge carinate, carina not reaching the gena. Vertex coarsely punctate becoming rugose near ridge; long plumose (short branches) setae. Gena puncticulate, microlineate on postgena; blue green, dark green on postgena; white plumose setae (1.5–2 OD).Hypostomal ridge carinate. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFDDFF9A5AA78902457DFBD7" box="[1195,1298,1127,1147]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="98">Mesosoma</emphasis>
. Pronotum dorsal ridge weakly carinate; lateral angle not projected, rounded; lateral ridge rounded; dorsal surface lineate and puncticulate; blue green; with few tomentum on dorsal surface. Propleura brown with green highlights. Prosternum green. Fore leg coxa dark green, remaining leg dark brown; long white setae on coxa to femur, yellow erect setae on tibia and tarsus. Mesoscutum anterior border weakly acuminate; median sulcus well impressed; parapsidal lines weakly impressed; punctate laterally, more sparse on median surface, punctures with different diameters intermixed, microlineations only on anterior surface and near median sulcus; blue green; short (=OD) and sparse white setae. Scutellum median sulcus very weakly impressed; irregularly punctate, rugulose posteriorly; blue green; longersetae (2–2.5 OD) onposterior margin.Mesepisternum rugulose on preepisternum, sulci foveate, densely to conflected punctate, microreticulate; blue green, blue ventrally; covered with plumose setae (1.5 OD). Mid leg light brown; yellow setae on femur to tarsus. Tegula concentric lineate; dark amber, weak green reflections anteriorly. Fore wing, marginal cell apexrounded; membrane hyaline; black microtrichia. Metanotummedian sulcus veryweakly impressed; puncticulate to rugulose; blue green; longplumose setae (2–3 OD). Metepisternum lineate above superior metapleural pit, rugulose–punctate below; green with copper and bluish reflections. Hind leg, basitibial plate apex rounded; tibial spur serrate; brown; long plumose setae on ventral coxa to femur, ventral tibial setae not too long and with short branches. Hind wing hyaline. Metapostnotum weakly inclined; weakly depressed; apex rounded; less twice as long as metanotum; carinate to irregularly carinate, carinae not reaching posterior margin, microreticulate; blue green. Propodeum posterior surface puncticulate, few scattered setose punctures, microreticulate; blue green; short plumose and some erect (1–2 OD) setae. Propodeum lateral surface puncticulate, few scattered punctures, microreticulate; blue green; with thicker and longer (3–4 OD) setae. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955FDF8DAA4256FF4F" box="[467,569,207,227]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Metasoma</emphasis>
. T1 anterior and dorsal surfaces not angled between; sparsely punctate, microlineate; blue green with some amber to brown portions on median surface; short. T2 puncticulate, weakly microreticulate; blue green, black on marginal area; short. T3–T4 puncticulate, weakly microreticulate; blue green, black on marginal area; short. T5 punctate; dark brown; covered with black long erect setae. Pygidial plate short, truncate. S1 without tubercle; lineate; amber with green highlights on median surface; very long branched setae (=3 OD) on median surface. S2–S4 lineate; brown to light brown; subapical branched setae very long (about 4 OD). S5 lineate; brown; long setae (about 4 OD), plumose. S6 lineate; brown; yellowish setae on apical margin. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955E7E8F7A4161FD9E" bold="true" box="[114,270,543,562]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
<typeStatus id="54BD1DC0FFD2FF955E7E8F7A40BEFD9E" box="[114,209,543,562]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paratype</typeStatus>
male
</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955F178F784187FD9D" box="[283,488,541,561]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Measurements (mm)</emphasis>
. Eye notch width: 1.3; head length: 1.8; clypeus width: 0.6; clypeus length: 0.5; supraclypeal length: 0.3; clypeus ocellar distance: 1.1; intertegular distance: 1.6; T1 width: 1.9; T2 width: 2.0; body length: 8.0. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955C888F1442D9FD29" box="[644,694,625,645]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Head</emphasis>
. Labrum and mandible brown. Clypeus, epistomal angle obtuse; punctate, weakly microreticulate; white setae on middle, longer setae on apex; yellow stripe on apical margin, green. Supraclypeal area sparsely punctate, microreticulate; green. Paraocular area sparsely punctate, microreticulate; green; long (&gt;2 OD) branched setae, yellow. Antennae F2 = F1, remaining flagellomeres relatively longer; scape and pedicel light brown, flagellomeres yellowed ventrally; F11 not flattened; F3–11 with sensilla placodea patches. Frons not depressed above antennal sockets; coarsely punctate; green with bluish iridescence; few erect setae. Preoccipital ridge carinate, some portions lamellate. Vertex punctate becoming rugose near ridge; very long plumose (short branches) setae. Gena puncticulate weakly lineate on postgena; green, copper reflections on postgena; white plumose setae (1.5–2 OD). Hypostomal area, ridge carinate. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955F47897641DDFB8B" box="[331,434,1043,1063]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Mesosoma</emphasis>
. Pronotum dorsal ridge carinate; lateral angle almost orthogonal; lateral ridge rounded; dorsal surface rugose; green; with some plumose setae on dorsal surface. Fore leg coxa to femur with green reflections, tibia and tarsus brown; short yellow erect setae. Mesoscutum anterior border slightly projected over pronotum, weakly lobed; median sulcus wellimpressed; parapsidallines wellimpressed; punctate, sparsely median surface, microreticulations only on lateral surface; green; posterior margin weakly covered with plumose setae. Scutellum median sulcus weakly impressed; punctate, rugulose on posterior margin, polished; green, blue iridescence posteriorly, weak copper reflections on middle surface; anterior surface covered with plumose setae. Mesepisternum punctate, densely microreticulate; green with some copper reflections; short plumose setae. Mid leg coxa brown with metallic reflections, remaining leg brown; short yellow erect setae. Tegula concentric lineate; brown, greenreflections anteriorly. Forewing weakly infuscate on apex. Metanotum median sulcus weakly impressed; puncticulate, polished; bright blue green; anterior surface densely covered with erect setae. Metepisternum lineate above superior metapleural pit, rugulose–punctate below; blue green. Hind leg coxa with metallic reflections, remaining leg brown; short yellow erect setae, shorterthan diameterof sclerites. Metapostnotumweaklyinclined; weakly depressed; 1.5× as long as metanotum; apex rounded; carinate to irregularly carinate, carinae not reaching posterior margin, microreticulate; blue green. Propodeum posterior surface posterior pit shallow, densely punctate, microreticulate, blue green, with fine setae; lateral surface punctate, blue green, with thicker setae. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955EB88A444170F899" box="[180,287,1825,1845]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Metasoma.</emphasis>
T1 anterior surface not punctate, dorsal surface punctate, polished; blue green, dark marginal area short. T2–5 punctate, microreticulate; dark blue green, marginal area black; vestiture white, with weak row of long white setae on basis. T6 green; long setae. T7 black; short black setae. S1 margin straight; sparsely punctate, microlineate; light brown; with very short setae. S2–3 straight; brown; covered with short white setae on median surface, posterior surface with longsetae (&gt;4 OD). S4 apical margin straight; without median patch of setae; lateral setae short. S5 as S2. S6 weakly concave; brown; black setae on apical margin. S7 with median process. S8 apical margin bilobed. 
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955B8E8C6345B5FEB6" box="[1410,1498,262,282]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Genitalia</emphasis>
. Gonapophysis broad; longer than gonostylus; without dorsal crest; with large ventral prong; with lateral teeth. Gonobase short (0.6 times gonocoxite length); dorsal lobes weakly produced; ventral bridge narrow. Gonostylus basal process absent; parapenial lobe present, short; ventral process with outer and inner lobes, inner lobe transversal setose on apex; dorsal lobe transversal. Volsella longer than wider; oblique, corners mostly rounded; without hook.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFD2FF955D4D8C824518FDE2" blockId="8.[833,1504,152,1371]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955D4D8C8243CAFE56" bold="true" box="[833,933,487,506]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Variation</emphasis>
. Most examined material is blue green but some specimens from 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955DBD8F664399FDBA" box="[945,1014,515,534]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paraná</collectingRegion>
and 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A288F6644DFFDBA" box="[1060,1200,515,534]" country="Brazil" name="Espirito Santo" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Espírito Santo</collectingRegion>
are green. The blue reflections vary among specimens, including some violet reflections. The mesoscutum punctuation is sparser in some specimens.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C31CF0E9FFD2FF955D4D8F324487FA8F" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFD2FF955D4D8F3245D9FC2C" blockId="8.[833,1504,152,1371]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955D4D8F3243B6FDC5" bold="true" box="[833,985,598,618]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Type material</emphasis>
. 
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955DE58F334496FD0D" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667819" collectingDate="2003-12-12" collectionCode="DZUP" collectorName="G. A. R. Melo &amp; R. B. Goncalves" country="Brazil" location="Estadual de Vila Velha" municipality="Parque" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-female="1" stateProvince="Parana" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="54BD1DC0FFD2FF955DE58F334429FDC5" box="[1001,1094,598,617]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Holotype</typeStatus>
<specimenCount id="9D0068EBFFD2FF955A5E8F3344F8FDC5" box="[1106,1175,598,617]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="female">female</specimenCount>
(
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955AA48F324489FDC6" box="[1192,1254,599,618]" collectionName="Brazil, Parana, Curitiba, Universidade Federal do Parana, Museu de Entomologia Pe. Jesus Santiago Moure" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/5xp9-edpx" name="Universidade Federal do Parana, Colecao de Entomologia Pe. Jesus Santiago Moure" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="University or college">DZUP</collectionCode>
), “PEVV\ 0439” “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955BAE8F3345B3FDC5" box="[1442,1500,598,617]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955D4D8F1743E7FD29" box="[833,904,626,645]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paraná</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingMunicipality id="6BDD3918FFD2FF955D908F16438CFD2A" box="[924,995,627,646]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Parque</collectingMunicipality>
\ 
<location id="8ED9F5B9FFD2FF955DF18F17456FFD29" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03AF1274FFDDFF955E598B6F458FFAF7:8ED9F5B9FFD2FF955DF18F17456FFD29" box="[1021,1280,626,645]" country="Brazil" municipality="Parque" name="Estadual de Vila Velha" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" stateProvince="Parana">Estadual de Vila Velha</location>
,\ 25 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955B348F0B452FFDD0" attach="left" box="[1336,1344,622,636]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
14S 49 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955B9D8F0B45F6FDD0" attach="none" box="[1425,1433,622,636]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
59‘W,\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955D4D8FEB43DAFD0D" box="[833,949,654,673]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="2003-12-12">
<collectingDate id="EFFC7C4AFFD2FF955D4D8FEB43DAFD0D" box="[833,949,654,673]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="2003-12-12">12.XII.2003</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="26F3C6B4FFD2FF955DB38FEB445DFD0D" box="[959,1074,654,673]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">G.A.R. Melo</collectorName>
&amp;\ 
<collectorName id="26F3C6B4FFD2FF955A5B8FEA4484FD0D" box="[1111,1259,654,674]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">R. B.Gonçalves</collectorName>
”.
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955AF18FEA458FFD75" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667802" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
<typeStatus id="54BD1DC0FFD2FF955AF18FEA450EFD0E" box="[1277,1377,655,674]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paratypes</typeStatus>
(
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955B608FEB45C5FD0D" box="[1388,1450,654,673]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/5xp9-edpx" name="Universidade Federal do Parana, Colecao de Entomologia Pe. Jesus Santiago Moure" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="University or college">DZUP</collectionCode>
), one female, “PEVV\ 1056” “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955A378FCF441AFD11" box="[1083,1141,682,701]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A8F8FCF44A5FD11" box="[1155,1226,682,701]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paraná</collectingRegion>
, Parque\ Estadual de Vila Velha,\ 25 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955DA18FA743DAFD7C" attach="left" box="[941,949,706,720]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
14S 49 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955A058FA7447EFD7C" attach="none" box="[1033,1041,706,720]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
59‘W,\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955A6D8FA344AFFD75" box="[1121,1216,710,729]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="2003-03-07">7.iii.2003</date>
, G. Melo &amp;\ R. Gonçalves”,
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955D4D8F8743C0FC81" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667814" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
one female, “PEVV\ 0072” “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955A5A8F8744FFFD59" box="[1110,1168,738,757]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A948F8744B0FD59" box="[1176,1247,738,757]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paraná</collectingRegion>
, Parque\ Estadual de Vila Velha,\ 25 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955DA08F9F43DBFCA4" attach="left" box="[940,948,762,776]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
14S 49 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955A088F9F4463FCA4" attach="none" box="[1028,1036,762,776]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
59‘W,\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955A578F9B44D0FCBD" box="[1115,1215,766,785]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="2003-10-05">05.x.2003</date>
, G. Melo &amp;\ R. Gonçalves &amp; A. Aguiar”,
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955DBA8E7F458FFCE5" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667804" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
two females “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955A4B8E7F44EEFC81" box="[1095,1153,794,813]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A818E7F44BBFC81" box="[1165,1236,794,813]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paraná</collectingRegion>
, Parque\ Estadual de Vila Velha,\ 25 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955DA68E5443DDFC93" attach="none" box="[938,946,817,831]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
14S 49 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955DF48E54446FFC93" attach="none" box="[1016,1024,817,831]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
59‘W,\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955A418E5344D6FCE5" box="[1101,1209,822,841]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="2002-03-16">16.iii.2002</date>
, G. Melo &amp; R. B.\ Gonçalves”,
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955D4D8E3745D9FC2C" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667808" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
one male “PEVV\ 1161” “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955A448E3444EDFCC8" box="[1096,1154,849,868]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A828E3744BAFCC9" box="[1166,1237,850,869]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paraná</collectingRegion>
, Parque\ Estadual de Vila Velha,\ 25 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955DA58E0C43DEFCDB" attach="none" box="[937,945,873,887]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
14S 49 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955DFB8E0C4390FCDB" attach="none" box="[1015,1023,873,887]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
59‘W,\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955A478E0844C5FC2C" box="[1099,1194,877,896]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="2003-03-07">7.iii.2003</date>
, G. Melo &amp;\ R. Gonçalves”.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFD2FF955D4D8EEC4487FA8F" blockId="8.[833,1504,152,1371]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955D4D8EEC4411FC30" bold="true" box="[833,1150,905,924]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Additionalexamined material</emphasis>
. 
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955A8B8EEC440CFC5C" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667815" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955A8B8EEC44BEFC30" box="[1159,1233,905,924]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">BRAZIL</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955AD58EEC4506FC30" box="[1241,1385,905,924]" country="Brazil" name="Espirito Santo" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Espírito Santo</collectingRegion>
: onefemale (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955D4B8EC043EAFC14" box="[839,901,933,952]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/5xp9-edpx" name="Universidade Federal do Parana, Colecao de Entomologia Pe. Jesus Santiago Moure" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="University or college">DZUP</collectionCode>
), “SANTA TERESA – ES\ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955A848EC044A0FC14" box="[1160,1231,933,952]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">BRASIL</collectingCountry>
22/X/966\ C. and T. Elias leg.”. 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955D768EA4446AFC78" box="[890,1029,961,980]" country="Brazil" name="Minas Gerais" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Minas Gerais</collectingRegion>
: four females (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955A918EA444A2FC78" box="[1181,1229,961,980]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">UFV</collectionCode>
), “Local MEUFV. MG\ Data 19/02/85\ Col. L. Campos”;
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955A628EB844E2FBA0" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667807" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
one female (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955AFB8EB8454AFC5C" box="[1271,1317,989,1008]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">UFV</collectionCode>
) with same data except “18/12/85\ A. A. Soares”;
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955A998E9C458FFBE8" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667817" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
onefemale (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955B188E9C452BFBA0" box="[1300,1348,1017,1036]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">UFV</collectionCode>
), “MEUFV MG\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955D4D897043D9FB84" box="[833,950,1045,1064]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="1987-10-11">11/10/1987</date>
\ A. A. Soares”. 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A40897044F9FB84" box="[1100,1174,1045,1064]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Paraná</collectingRegion>
: onefemale (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955B1489704539FB84" box="[1304,1366,1045,1064]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/5xp9-edpx" name="Universidade Federal do Parana, Colecao de Entomologia Pe. Jesus Santiago Moure" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="University or college">DZUP</collectionCode>
), “ANTONINA 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955D4D89544334FBE8" box="[833,859,1073,1092]" country="Brazil" name="Para" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">PR</collectingRegion>
\ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955D62895443C8FBE8" box="[878,935,1073,1092]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955DBC89544472FBE8" box="[944,1053,1073,1092]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="1966-01-20">20–I–1966</date>
\ Marinoni [and] Azevedo”. 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955B48895445B3FBE8" box="[1348,1500,1073,1092]" country="Brazil" name="Rio de Janeiro" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Rio de Janeiro</collectingRegion>
:
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955D4D89284497FBD7" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667810" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
onefemale (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955DC28928447BFBCC" box="[974,1044,1101,1120]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34871" name="Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="Museum">USNM</collectionCode>
), “RdJaneiro\ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955ABC89284485FBCC" box="[1200,1258,1101,1120]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brazil</collectingCountry>
\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955B0F89284521FBCC" box="[1283,1358,1101,1120]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="1938-10">X 1938</date>
””YelFevServ\ MESBrazil\ RCShannon“. 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A5F890C449AFBD7" box="[1107,1269,1128,1148]" country="Brazil" name="Santa Catarina" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Santa Catarina</collectingRegion>
:
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955B0B890C43FAFB1F" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667809" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
onefemale (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955B9A890C45B9FBD0" box="[1430,1494,1129,1148]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34264" name="University of Kansas - Biodiversity Institute" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="Museum">SEMC</collectionCode>
), “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955D4589E143FDFB3B" box="[841,914,1156,1175]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">BRAZIL</collectingCountry>
\ 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955DAF89E14458FB3B" box="[931,1079,1156,1175]" country="Brazil" name="Santa Catarina" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Santa Catarina</collectingRegion>
\ Nova Teutonia\ 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955AE289E14515FB3B" box="[1262,1402,1156,1175]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="1955-09-15">15 Sept. 1955</date>
\ (F. Plaumann)“;
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955D9289C4456BFB63" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667816" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
two females (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955A2289C54401FB1F" box="[1070,1134,1184,1203]" country="USA" httpUri="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34264" name="University of Kansas - Biodiversity Institute" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="Museum">SEMC</collectionCode>
), “Nova Teutonia,\ 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955B3589C545BDFB1F" box="[1337,1490,1184,1203]" country="Brazil" name="Santa Catarina" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Santa Catarina</collectingRegion>
,\ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955D4D89D94314FB63" box="[833,891,1212,1231]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brazil</collectingCountry>
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955D8E89D943B7FB63" box="[898,984,1212,1231]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="1951-09">IX–1951</date>
\ L. E. Plaumann). 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A9B89D9456FFB63" box="[1175,1280,1212,1231]" country="Brazil" name="Sao Paulo" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">São Paulo</collectingRegion>
:
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955B0689D845C2FB47" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667813" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
two females (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955B9B89D945B9FB63" box="[1431,1494,1212,1231]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
), “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955D4689BD43EBFB47" box="[842,900,1240,1259]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955D9989BD4390FB47" box="[917,1023,1240,1259]" country="Brazil" name="Sao Paulo" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">São Paulo</collectingRegion>
, Iporanga, 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955A7089BD4489FB47" box="[1148,1254,1240,1259]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="2000-09-10">10.ix.2000</date>
, B. H. Dietz col.”,
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation id="3B6EA93FFFD2FF955BB689BD448BFA8F" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2569667803" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
one female (
<collectionCode id="ED173BA7FFD2FF955D9C899143A1FAAB" box="[912,974,1268,1287]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/5xp9-edpx" name="Universidade Federal do Parana, Colecao de Entomologia Pe. Jesus Santiago Moure" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="University or college">DZUP</collectionCode>
), “ 
<collectingCountry id="F311E3F2FFD2FF955DE989914470FAAB" box="[997,1055,1268,1287]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Brasil</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="49C26D80FFD2FF955A2B899144E9FAAB" box="[1063,1158,1268,1287]" country="Brazil" name="Sao Paulo" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">São Paulo</collectingRegion>
\ Cajuru, Faz. Rio\ Grande, 21 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955BAB899545C0FB52" attach="none" box="[1447,1455,1264,1278]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
12S\ 47 
<superScript id="7C730E2AFFD2FF955D568869430DFAB6" attach="none" box="[858,866,1292,1306]" fontSize="6" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">◦</superScript>
09‘W 
<date id="FFB885A2FFD2FF955D938875447FFA8F" box="[927,1040,1296,1315]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" value="1999-12-02">02.xii.1999</date>
,\ Gabriel A. R. Melo”
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C31CF0E9FFD2FF955D4D8849458FFAF7" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="8BB9A362FFD2FF955D4D8849458FFAF7" blockId="8.[833,1504,152,1371]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955D4D884943DCFA93" bold="true" box="[833,947,1324,1343]" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">Etymology</emphasis>
. From the Latin term 
<taxonomicName id="4C06D8E1FFD2FF955A87884F44B9FA92" authorityName="Gonçalves" authorityYear="2019" box="[1163,1238,1322,1342]" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Ceratalictus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="inflexus">
<emphasis id="B9727F70FFD2FF955A87884F44B9FA92" box="[1163,1238,1322,1342]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="99">inflexus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
means bend, curve, in referenceto the form of the inner lobeof ventral processof gonostylus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>