<document id="7F78CF27FE97DF2B37CF05C5769BC756" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5192134" ID-ISSN="1464-5262" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5192134" ID-ZooBank="69BEE81D-D0FA-4B1D-B009-B11D119EA911" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CD39A372-DA10-486E-81D7-973D039CCA04" _generate="added" approvalRequired="5" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="3" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1628735027192" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Botero, Juan Pablo &amp; Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2017" docId="03E187B7FFF08F5FFE5836CEFC81A314" docLanguage="en" docName="JNatHist.51.45-46.2721-2743.pdf" docOrigin="Journal of Natural History (J. Nat. Hist.) 51 (45 - 46)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222933.2017.1395093" docStyle="DocumentStyle:485A7191CD41D6261F41521A3380DC73.9:JNatHist.2017-.journal_article.1cover" docStyleId="485A7191CD41D6261F41521A3380DC73" docStyleName="JNatHist.2017-.journal_article.1cover" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Eurysthea antonkozlovi Botero &amp; Santos-Silva 2017, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docUuid="CD39A372-DA10-486E-81D7-973D039CCA04" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="2727" masterDocId="FFD8FFCFFFF48F58FF913425FFA6A67F" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Eurysthea Thomson, 1861 (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae: Cerambycinae)" masterLastPageNumber="2743" masterPageNumber="2721" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724" updateTime="1628805404697" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="ADE27F5DB283004B7EA8712E7A3C06AA" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="306556E9F29EB5E6327E8E91EF69BBDC">
<mods:title id="964AF41180299A151108C20ADE603694">Review of the genus Eurysthea Thomson, 1861 (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae: Cerambycinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="07D8662D496F208325A33DE6A24BCEA8" type="personal">
<mods:role id="711E07987C1B602EC1CA29A59B80D825">
<mods:roleTerm id="E255679E523321E1B83C0DE4CC011565">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="76A8928F5D87951A59B3740A1FFBBE45">Botero, Juan Pablo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="662EFAB7B5298ABA31D678BC93DA6D94" type="personal">
<mods:role id="45B94B767C831D52A530991483F3283A">
<mods:roleTerm id="B5961E2905DBB967E68BEB724E58E1F3">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1CD6D30055F62230E2E46EB406F04A03">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="B45466210CF1DF8F6DA46D7C348035CD">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="AC210512A7D5ACDC9064ECFDB54445E9" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="0AF2531EBDACBDDFEA72E423BA882E61">
<mods:title id="59FD70CE3D567D4A11A0B061B61CC59C">Journal of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="6C8848C4CD5D7D4A5332411630B33E6A">
<mods:date id="80FC07E94111164742A550817D77B6BD">2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="8FF05801A667191F2D879D943D7B50E8" type="series">
<mods:title id="FB65261DAD22EF0A26E344FE1FC0A186">J. Nat. Hist.</mods:title>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="0199F69D2B43E71C15F87DAC4EFE09C1" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="ADC77F572F4C131B03DFB4BA2A57CD39">2017-11-27</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="6EFC985881A6F71F447358F560B6BB4A" type="volume">
<mods:number id="511DE57098A5A87BA3159B2805A3C111">51</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="C106BA30DCAEA71394D1D3753162FFCD" type="issue">
<mods:number id="7CEA9525B0820C63DB06213FB7216D89">45 - 46</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="0E0B52C7FCF05C70EB54118ED54331FF" unit="page">
<mods:start id="78DD80ABFFCAD406283B5F232C129455">2721</mods:start>
<mods:end id="976EB9F0DE6D6C8E05ED43421499EB10">2743</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="E7F00C88ED2BD9253F2E427636069359">
<mods:url id="D5F50331C86A7D31121C5FA9CD6282D6">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222933.2017.1395093</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="ABA129804132FCE9C538817EE40F97C8">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="F865BC63BAC93339868500EED068762F" type="DOI">10.1080/00222933.2017.1395093</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="27D766ADE8AAEC12A8ADFF3B94CC3BEA" type="ISSN">1464-5262</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="9DE1045FEB8C848606387012AD7B7652" type="Zenodo-Dep">5183940</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="5895A1DF8BA01EAAC9C2D5C8CA403E59" type="ZooBank">69BEE81D-D0FA-4B1D-B009-B11D119EA911</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03E187B7FFF08F5FFE5836CEFC81A314" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5192134" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5192134" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CD39A372-DA10-486E-81D7-973D039CCA04" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E187B7FFF08F5FFE5836CEFC81A314" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="2727" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">
<subSubSection id="C352652AFFF08F5CFE5836CEFCFFA57A" box="[457,857,747,773]" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF08F5CFE5836CEFCFFA57A" blockId="4.[457,857,747,808]" box="[457,857,747,773]" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">
<heading id="D0BF81CDFFF08F5CFE5836CEFCFFA57A" bold="true" box="[457,857,747,773]" centered="true" fontSize="11" level="2" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724" reason="3">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF08F5CFE5836CEFCFFA57A" bold="true" box="[457,857,747,773]" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF08F5CFE5836CEFD4AA57A" authority="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva, 2017" authorityName="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2017" box="[457,748,747,773]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF08F5CFE5836CEFD4AA57A" bold="true" box="[457,748,747,773]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">Eurysthea antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20F57C8FFF08F5CFD6736C9FCFFA57A" box="[758,857,748,773]" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C352652AFFF08F5FFD80372AFC95A7FE" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="2727" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF08F5CFD80372AFCB4A557" blockId="4.[457,857,747,808]" box="[529,786,782,808]" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">
(
<figureCitation id="13732A24FFF08F5CFD88372AFD09A557" box="[537,687,782,808]" captionStart="Figure 1" captionStartId="8.[160,225,1659,1682]" captionTargetBox="[164,1152,143,1627]" captionTargetId="figure-1@8.[163,1153,142,1628]" captionTargetPageId="8" captionText="Figure 1. (a–c) Eurysthea antonkozlovi sp. nov., holotype female: (a) dorsal habitus; (b) ventral habitus; (c) lateral habitus. (d–f) Eurysthea barsevskisi sp. nov., holotype male: (d) dorsal habitus; (e) ventral habitus; (f) lateral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5183944" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5183944/files/figure.png" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">Figures 1a–c</figureCitation>
and 
<figureCitation id="13732A24FFF08F5CFD7F372AFCACA557" box="[750,778,783,808]" captionStart="Figure 3" captionStartId="21.[160,225,1548,1571]" captionTargetBox="[165,1152,397,1517]" captionTargetId="figure-34@21.[163,1153,396,1518]" captionTargetPageId="21" captionText="Figure 3. Detail of elytra. (a) Eurysthea antonkozlovi sp. nov.; (b) Eurysthea barsevskisi sp. nov.; (c) Eurysthea tatianakozlovae sp. nov.; (d) Eurysthea nearnsi sp. nov. Arrows show the lanceolate setae." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5183948" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5183948/files/figure.png" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">3a</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF08F5CFF313744FE80A505" blockId="4.[160,1156,865,1167]" box="[160,294,865,890]" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF08F5CFF313744FE80A505" bold="true" box="[160,294,865,890]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">Description</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF08F5CFF3137A1FC67A2F0" blockId="4.[160,1156,865,1167]" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF08F5CFF3137A1FF5AA5E2" bold="true" box="[160,252,900,925]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">Female.</emphasis>
Integument black; mouthparts reddish-brown; scape dark reddish-brown; pedicel and antennomeres III–XI light reddish-brown; femora dark reddish-brown, blackish on extreme apex; tibia and tarsi yellowish-brown; elytra with four yellowish-brown areas: epipleura; one large band starting at middle of epipleura, obliquely directed toward middle of dorsal side on apex of basal quarter, abruptly, obliquely directed toward suture on middle; one large band starting at distal quarter of epipleura, following obliquely toward base of distal third of suture (enlarged near epipleura); one small, irregular area placed on apex, slightly projected forward along suture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF08F5DFF3130E4FB9BA04C" blockId="4.[160,1156,1217,1727]" lastBlockId="5.[160,1156,142,1587]" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="2725" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF08F5CFF3130E4FF42A2A5" bold="true" box="[160,228,1217,1242]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="2724">Head.</emphasis>
Frons minutely, abundantly punctate except on smooth lobe on each side of coronal suture at anterior margin; with short, decumbent golden setae, more distinct laterally, interspersed with white, decumbent, long lanceolate setae laterally. Area between antennal tubercles minutely, abundantly punctate, interspersed with coarse punctures, except on smooth narrow band along coronal suture; with short, decumbent golden setae, not obscuring integument. Area between upper eye lobes and prothoracic margin centrally with narrow, smooth, slightly elevated carina (continuing coronal suture), distinctly, triangularly enlarged toward prothorax (triangular area moderately coarsely, sparsely punctate); area between upper eye lobes minutely, abundantly punctate, interspersed with coarse punctures close to eyes, except on irregular, smooth areas between eyes and centre; with oblique, slightly depressed area on each side of central carina; with golden, decumbent setae, not entirely obscuring integument, interspersed with some long, erect, fine setae and some long, lanceolate, white setae, glabrous on smooth areas, triangular enlargement close to prothorax and lateral areas close to prothorax. Area behind upper eye lobes minutely, abundantly punctate, interspersed with coarse punctures close to superior area of eye, finely, confluently punctate on entire region close to base of lower eye lobe and margin of prothorax; with band with golden setae on central region, continuing that on slight depression of vertex, interspersed with some long, fine, yellowish setae and lanceolate, white setae; remaining surface almost glabrous. Area behind lower eye lobes almost smooth close to eye, striate punctate close to prothorax; area close to eye glabrous toward upper eye lobe, with short, yellowish, very sparse setae on central area, with some white, lanceolate setae toward ventral side; remaining surface glabrous. Coronal suture distinct from clypeus to area between upper eye lobes. Antennal tubercles minutely, abundantly punctate, interspersed with some fine punctures, except on smooth, narrow area close to apex; with band of golden, short setae centrally, interspersed with some white, long, lanceolate setae, with minute, slightly distinctly golden setae on basal region, glabrous on smooth region. Genae finely, sparsely punctate; with short, yellowish, sparse setae laterally, with white, long, lanceolate setae ventrally. Gulamentum smooth close to prothorax, transversely striate centrally, striate-punctate toward anterior margin (punctures coarser laterally); anterior half with short, sparse, yellowish setae interspersed with long, erect, yellowish setae and white, lanceolate, long setae laterally. Postclypeus centrally with sub-triangular plate, longitudinally sulcate, distinctly elevated on each side of plate; plate finely punctate, with short golden setae laterally, smooth, glabrous centrally; area between plate and elevated area with golden, abundant, short setae; sides minutely punctate, with minute golden setae close to central plate, smooth, glabrous on remaining surface; narrow area close to anteclypeus, finely, confluently punctate, with one long, white, lanceolate seta on each side. Labrum minutely punctate on transverse central area, smooth on remaining surface; with long, yellowish setae on punctate region (mainly laterally) and on anterior margin. Mandibles coarsely, confluently punctate laterally on basal 3/4, smooth dorsally and lateral distal quarter; outer margin distinctly dentate at apex of punctate region; with short and long yellowish setae on punctate lateral area, glabrous on remaining surface. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.55 times length of scape; distance between lower eye lobes in frontal view 0.80 times length of scape. Antennae 1.45 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at distal third of antennomere X, antennomeres not carinate. Scape slightly enlarged toward apex; finely, moderately abundant punctate on base, gradually sparser toward apex; with short, decumbent, sparse yellowish setae interspersed with long, erect, fine, yellowish setae and long, white, lanceolate setae. Pedicel with long, erect, fine, yellowish setae and long, white, lanceolate setae. Antennomere III with long spine at inner apex (as long as 0.35 times length of antennomere, half length of antennomere IV); with yellowish, decumbent setae interspersed with long, fine, erect yellowish setae and long, thick, whitish setae. Antennomere IV with short spine at inner apex (as long as 0.1 times length of antennomere); setae as on antennomere III. Antennomeres V–X unarmed at apex; short setae gradually denser and long setae sparser toward distal segments. Antennal formula (ratio) based on antennomere III (without spine): scape = 0.60; pedicel = 0.15; IV = 0.74; V = 0.77; VI = 0.76; VII = 0.77; VIII = 0.65; IX = 0.62; X = 0.55; XI = 0.58.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF18F5EFF313244FCEFA361" blockId="5.[160,1156,1633,1727]" lastBlockId="6.[160,1156,142,1310]" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="2726" pageId="5" pageNumber="2725">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF18F5DFF313244FF5FA005" bold="true" box="[160,249,1633,1658]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="2725">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax slightly wider than long (1.05 excluding lateral tubercles), distinctly narrowed from base to apex. Sides of prothorax with large, spiniform tubercle before middle (apex rounded), another smaller, rounded, very distinct, placed at middle of anterior half; sides coarsely, partially confluently punctate, except on sub-striate area close to anterior margin (this area enlarged toward ventral side); with golden, short setae, more abundant on area closer to lateral tubercles, interspersed with long, white, lanceolate setae. Pronotum with 5 isolated tubercles: two subcircular, elevated, placed on each side of posterior third, with narrow projection forward; two subconical, highest, placed on each side of anterior third; one elongated, lowest, placed on centre, carina-shaped between distal tubercles, slightly enlarged toward anterior margin. Pronotal surface with small depression between lateroposterior tubercles; area between tubercles coarsely, confluently punctate; transverse basal plate coarsely, sparsely punctate (punctures finer than area between tubercles); area closer to anterior margin sub-smooth; area on tubercles smooth; sides coarsely, partially confluently punctate; with short, sparse, decumbent, golden setae centrally from base to apex of distal tubercles, distinctly denser laterally and sides of anterior third; with long, sparse, white lanceolate and thick setae. Prosternum coarsely, moderately sparsely punctate on posterior 2/3, elevated, transversely striate on anterior third (centre of base of this region with gibbosity); with minute, moderately sparse (mainly on anterior third), golden setae interspersed with some long, white, lanceolate setae. Prosternal process smooth, glabrous centrally on basal half, minutely punctate with minute golden setae on remaining surface. Mesoventrite sub-smooth, except for some shallow punctures laterally; area closer to procoxal cavities with transverse, slight depression on each side of centre, that is distinctly elevated (this area separated from remaining surface by narrow carina); large central area almost glabrous; sides and narrow area close to mesocoxal cavities with minute, whitish setae interspersed with long, white, lanceolate setae. Mesepimeron and mesanepisternum with moderately abundant, whitish setae (not obscuring integument), interspersed with long, white, lanceolate setae. Mesoventral process slightly depressed on each side of centre; centre longitudinally sulcate, with low carina on each side of sulcus; apex with lobe slight projected under mesocoxa; with moderately sparse, whitish setae interspersed with short, white, lanceolate setae. Metanepisternum with abundant, whitish setae (not obscuring integument), interspersed with long, white, lanceolate setae. Metaventrite finely, sparsely punctate; laterally with whitish setae (not obscuring integument), interspersed with long, white, lanceolate setae; remaining surface with short, sparse whitish setae interspersed with long, fine and lanceolate setae (mainly toward metacoxal cavities). Scutellum with short, decumbent, abundant golden setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF28F5EFF31316EFF41A06E" blockId="6.[160,1156,1355,1553]" pageId="6" pageNumber="2726">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF28F5EFF31316EFF4CA31B" bold="true" box="[160,234,1355,1380]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="2726">Elytra.</emphasis>
Moderately coarsely, abundantly punctate on central region of anterior third, finer, sparser toward sides and apex; with long, moderately abundant, white lanceolate setae interspersed with long, fine, white setae; with longitudinal, irregular carina from apex of basal quarter to distal third (less distinct toward its apex); apex with long spine at outer angle, obliquely truncate toward slightly projected sutural angle.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF28F5EFF31321BFD17A0C0" blockId="6.[160,1156,1598,1727]" pageId="6" pageNumber="2726">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF28F5EFF31321BFF7DA028" bold="true" box="[160,219,1598,1623]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="2726">Legs.</emphasis>
Meso- and metacoxa with long, white, lanceolate setae. Femora with long, thick, white setae interspersed with long, lanceolate setae. Tibiae with long, erect, thick setae, interspersed with some lanceolate setae, except on ventral side of distal third with golden setae. Tarsi with golden setae dorsally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF3134ABFD5FA693" blockId="7.[160,1155,142,236]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF3134ABFEBEA6D8" bold="true" box="[160,280,142,167]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with long, erect, sparse, yellowish-white setae centrally, more abundant, thicker laterally, mainly toward distal area. Ventrite V 0.8 times as long as IV; apex sub-rounded, slightly emarginated centrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF313506FC95A7FE" blockId="7.[160,1156,291,385]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF313506FE4DA743" bold="true" box="[160,491,291,316]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Dimensions in mm (female).</emphasis>
Total length, 17.60; prothorax length, 2.50; anterior width, 2.10; posterior width, 2.50; largest prothoracic width (between apices of spiniform tubercles), 3.15; humeral width, 4.05; elytral length, 12.90.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C352652AFFF38F5FFF31359DFE83A446" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF31359DFEE3A7AE" blockId="7.[160,1156,440,569]" box="[160,325,440,465]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF31359DFEE3A7AE" bold="true" box="[160,325,440,465]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Type material</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF3135F9FE83A446" blockId="7.[160,1156,440,569]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<materialsCitation id="3B203CFCFFF38F5FFF3135F9FE83A446" collectingDate="2015-10-28" collectingDateMax="2015-10-30" collectingDateMin="2015-10-28" collectionCode="V, MZSP" collectorName="Sinyaev &amp; J. Machado" country="Colombia" elevation="2911" latitude="4.7927775" location="Bosque" longLatPrecision="21" longitude="-73.77583" municipality="Vereda la Concepcion" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Cundinamarca" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="54F38803FFF38F5FFF3135F9FEA1A78B" box="[160,263,476,500]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Holotype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry id="F35F7631FFF38F5FFE2035F9FD89A78B" box="[433,559,476,500]" name="Colombia" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">COLOMBIA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFDAE35F9FD79A78B" box="[575,735,476,500]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<collectingRegion id="498CF843FFF38F5FFDAE35F9FD79A78B" box="[575,735,476,500]" country="Colombia" name="Cundinamarca" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Cundinamarca</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<collectingMunicipality id="6B93ACDBFFF38F5FFD6235F9FC52A78B" box="[755,1012,476,500]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Vereda la Concepción</collectingMunicipality>
(
<location id="8E97607AFFF38F5FFB9635F9FBFAA78B" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E187B7FFF08F5FFE5836CEFC81A314:8E97607AFFF38F5FFB9635F9FBFAA78B" box="[1031,1116,476,500]" country="Colombia" latitude="4.7927775" longLatPrecision="21" longitude="-73.77583" municipality="Vereda la Concepcion" name="Bosque" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" stateProvince="Cundinamarca">Bosque</location>
<collectingRegion id="498CF843FFF38F5FFBFB35F9FF54A468" country="Colombia" name="La Guajira" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">La Guajira</collectingRegion>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="EE7C5066FFF38F5FFF6F35DAFECDA468" box="[254,363,510,535]" degrees="4" direction="north" minutes="47" orientation="latitude" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" precision="15" seconds="34" value="4.7927775">
4°47 
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFEA135DBFE90A469" bold="true" box="[304,310,510,534]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">ʹ</emphasis>
34 
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFEC035DBFEFDA469" bold="true" box="[337,347,510,534]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">ʺ</emphasis>
N
</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate id="EE7C5066FFF38F5FFEE235DAFE5FA468" box="[371,505,510,535]" degrees="73" direction="west" minutes="46" orientation="longitude" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" precision="15" seconds="33" value="-73.77583">
73°46 
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFE2435DBFE1DA469" bold="true" box="[437,443,510,534]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">ʹ</emphasis>
33 
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFE4735DBFE46A469" bold="true" box="[470,480,510,534]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">ʺ</emphasis>
W
</geoCoordinate>
; 
<quantity id="4CB09B44FFF38F5FFD9435DAFDF8A468" box="[517,606,511,535]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.911" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" unit="m" value="2911.0">
<elevation id="0065D192FFF38F5FFD9435DAFDF8A468" box="[517,606,511,535]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.911" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" unit="m" value="2911.0">2911 m</elevation>
</quantity>
), 
<date id="FFF61061FFF38F5FFDE235DAFCF8A468" box="[627,862,510,535]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" value="2015-10-28" valueMax="2015-10-30" valueMin="2015-10-28">
<collectingDate id="EFB2E989FFF38F5FFDE235DAFCF8A468" box="[627,862,510,535]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" value="2015-10-28" valueMax="2015-10-30" valueMin="2015-10-28">28–30 October 2015</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectionCode id="ED59AE64FFF38F5FFCFA35DAFCDAA468" box="[875,892,511,535]" country="Canada" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:13946" name="Royal British Columbia Museum - Herbarium" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" type="Museum">V</collectionCode>
. 
<collectorName id="26BD5377FFF38F5FFC1835DAFC79A468" box="[905,991,511,535]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Sinyaev</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName id="26BD5377FFF38F5FFB9335DAFB22A468" box="[1026,1156,511,535]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">J. Machado</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode id="ED59AE64FFF38F5FFF443604FEBDA446" box="[213,283,545,569]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C352652AFFF38F5FFF313655FEBBA4B1" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF313655FEBBA4F6" blockId="7.[160,1155,624,718]" box="[160,285,624,649]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF313655FEBBA4F6" bold="true" box="[160,285,624,649]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Etymology</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF3136B1FEBBA4B1" blockId="7.[160,1155,624,718]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">The new species is named after Anton Olegovich Kozlov, who sent and donated the specimens.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C352652AFFF38F5FFF313720FC81A314" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF313720FEA0A561" blockId="7.[160,1156,773,1387]" box="[160,262,773,798]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF313720FEA0A561" bold="true" box="[160,262,773,798]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Remarks</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF31370CFCF0A229" blockId="7.[160,1156,773,1387]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
In 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFF2C370CFE80A53E" authorityName="Thomson" authorityYear="1861" box="[189,294,809,833]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF2C370CFE80A53E" box="[189,294,809,833]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Eurysthea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
there are only four species with elytra having 
<specimenCount id="9D4EFD28FFF38F5FFCA2370CFC04A53E" box="[819,930,809,833]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" type="generic" typeStatus="types">two types</specimenCount>
of pubescence that include long, erect setae and shorter, lanceolate setae: 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFCD5376EFC57A51C" authority="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva, 2017" authorityName="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2017" box="[836,1009,843,867]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFCD5376EFC57A51C" box="[836,1009,843,867]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20F57C8FFF38F5FFB91376EFBC6A51C" box="[1024,1120,843,867]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
; 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFBE0376EFEB5A5F9" authority="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva, 2017" authorityName="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2017" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="barsevskisi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFBE0376EFEB5A5F9" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. barsevskisi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20F57C8FFF38F5FFE8D374BFED1A5F9" box="[284,375,878,902]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
; 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFE12374BFE49A5F9" baseAuthorityName="Fonseca-Gessner" baseAuthorityYear="1990" box="[387,495,878,902]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robertsi">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFE12374BFE49A5F9" box="[387,495,878,902]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. robertsi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
; and 
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFDA0374BFC75A5F9" box="[561,979,878,902]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFDA0374BFD6FA5F9" authorityName="Elytra" baseAuthorityName="Martins" baseAuthorityYear="1967" box="[561,713,878,902]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="squamifera">E. squamifera</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFD44374BFC75A5F9" authority="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva, 2017" authorityName="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2017" box="[725,979,878,902]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">Eurysthea antonkozlovi</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20F57C8FFF38F5FFC4C374BFB93A5F9" box="[989,1077,878,902]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
differs from all of them by the head, prothorax and elytra black or reddish-black (reddish-brown in the others) and by the spine of the inner apex of the antennomere III longer, as long as half the length of antennomere IV (in the other species is shorter). It differs from 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFBE037F3FEBCA26E" authorityName="Elytra" baseAuthorityName="Martins" baseAuthorityYear="1967" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="squamifera">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFBE037F3FEBCA26E" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. squamifera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFEC937DCFE41A26E" authorityName="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2017" box="[344,487,1017,1041]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="barsevskisi">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFEC937DCFE41A26E" box="[344,487,1017,1041]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. barsevskisi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the prothorax with lateral spines (absent in 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFB8737DCFB25A26E" baseAuthorityName="Fonseca-Gessner" baseAuthorityYear="1990" box="[1046,1155,1017,1041]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robertsi">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFB8737DCFB25A26E" box="[1046,1155,1017,1041]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. robertsi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFF48303EFED2A24C" authorityName="Elytra" baseAuthorityName="Martins" baseAuthorityYear="1967" box="[217,372,1051,1075]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="squamifera">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF48303EFED2A24C" box="[217,372,1051,1075]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. squamifera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
). It can be separated from 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFD41303EFCE4A24C" baseAuthorityName="Fonseca-Gessner" baseAuthorityYear="1990" box="[720,834,1051,1075]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robertsi">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFD41303EFCE4A24C" box="[720,834,1051,1075]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. robertsi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFC1A303EFB83A24C" authorityName="Elytra" baseAuthorityName="Martins" baseAuthorityYear="1967" box="[907,1061,1051,1075]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="squamifera">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFC1A303EFB83A24C" box="[907,1061,1051,1075]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. squamifera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the lanceolate setae on the elytra (squamiform in these species).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF736A1FFF38F5FFF513044FC81A314" blockId="7.[160,1156,773,1387]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFF513044FE1AA206" authority="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva, 2017" authorityName="Botero &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2017" box="[192,444,1121,1145]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFF513044FE1AA206" box="[192,444,1121,1145]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">Eurysthea antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20F57C8FFF38F5FFE523044FDBCA206" box="[451,538,1121,1145]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is also similar to 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFD483044FBF6A206" authority="Fonseca-Gessner, 1990" authorityName="Fonseca-Gessner" authorityYear="1990" box="[729,1104,1121,1145]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="martinsi">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFD483044FCEDA206" box="[729,843,1121,1145]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. martinsi</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFD94B50FFF38F5FFCC03044FBF6A206" author="Fonseca-Gessner AA" box="[849,1104,1121,1145]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" pagination="817 - 856" refId="ref11615" refString="Fonseca-Gessner AA. 1990. Revisao taxonomica do genero Paramallocera Aurivillius, 1912 (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Cerambycinae, Sphaerionini) [Taxonomic revision of the genus Paramallocera Aurivillius, 1912 (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Cerambycinae, Sphaerionini)]. Rev Brasil Entomol. 34: 817 - 856." type="journal article" year="1990">Fonseca-Gessner, 1990</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
, but differs as follows: body with lanceolate setae, mainly dorsally; spine of the inner apex of the antennomere III notably longer; upper eye lobes narrower, with 5–6 rows of ommatidia; elytral punctures finer and sparser; distal area of elytra with irregular yellowish-brown area. In 
<taxonomicName id="4C484D22FFF38F5FFEE930CEFE4BA37C" authorityName="Fonseca-Gessner" authorityYear="1990" box="[376,493,1259,1283]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eurysthea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="martinsi">
<emphasis id="B93CEAB3FFF38F5FFEE930CEFE4BA37C" box="[376,493,1259,1283]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727">E. martinsi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
the body has no lanceolate setae, the spine of the inner apex of the antennomere III is shorter (see 
<bibRefCitation id="EFD94B50FFF38F5FFD1C312BFCB0A359" author="Bezark LG" box="[653,790,1294,1318]" pageId="7" pageNumber="2727" refId="ref11451" refString="Bezark LG. 2016. A photographic Catalog of the Cerambycidae of the New World. [accessed 2016 Nov]. https: // apps 2. cdfa. ca. gov / publicApps / plant / bycidDB / wsearch. asp? w = n" type="url" year="2016">Bezark 2016</bibRefCitation>
), the upper eye lobes are wider with 8 rows of ommatidia, the elytral punctures are coarser and denser (mainly on basal third), and the elytral apex has no yellowish-brown area.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>