<document id="A3050E9655BEF8D748B560A691F280E9" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" _generate="added" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C84119AD5DFF7533F0B291A153" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Obtusodonta equitatoria" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="79" lastPageNumber="676" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="2DF83A3A7245407D85DC0AFDF045A8E0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6AD90200A76948A5EBF289535E68F02A">
<mods:title id="A67FD0C4940EF0E3BD1C7AA2003D470D">Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="F4036A0CC1BEA3265FC44FFEF61552A4" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9732C818DED634D7799D2C7F5C0A4A27">
<mods:roleTerm id="D2712E2C5B2B2C0696A9BBDB37CAD842">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="13401FBF0F4B968C91F1C9A35B87797E">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="C4FA1CCC17BA0D807AEF08EC489080EE">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3BA3AFEFB4E1A665524265770FC48661" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="DDDEDEA7AFA036095DA5DE8BB10C48A8">
<mods:title id="B47EEA278A9A83A69A1EDA56A5176768">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D82BF52DCA39677A9B857A5E693B5431">
<mods:date id="CB87BDC1741ACD59DFA9E783F7A08291">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D0AEE29E57B48860BABED5B3E2DDD31B" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="0CDF3F930CBE7BB6F1E104CDD058C2BE">2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="BB8888A50C1A068E35815DA222F245C8" type="volume">
<mods:number id="F285D28B01645A8B0D8CA369E9E86CD9">43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="33950811CBAE4EF7E4CDD32DEEC0A801" type="issue">
<mods:number id="438A226A5E28501B8985BC5B02B26168">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1C8D4B9662FD62FABBDE83CA82E362DA" unit="page">
<mods:start id="5B4F2CE458A18FE23C7B710288036591">597</mods:start>
<mods:end id="ACEF9E6A873453964AB3F98C8CD4656D">711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="0C648A377AE8BD086C92FF60D34E293C">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C8583B03EA2739C5376FE019FBC17CE5" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0D77A3B05722257FCB1F36D3C79C75EB" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="56FFB81AE1AEC68FA76E2F940E2292D3" type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03E687C84119AD5DFF7533F0B291A153" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C84119AD5DFF7533F0B291A153" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C84119AD5DFF7533F0B291A153" lastPageId="79" lastPageNumber="676" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<subSubSection id="C35565554119AD5CFF7533F0B0A0A63B" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF7533F0B391A7F9" blockId="78.[178,648,216,238]" box="[178,648,216,238]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<heading id="D0B881B24119AD5CFF7533F0B391A7F9" box="[178,648,216,238]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFF7533F0B391A7F9" bold="true" box="[178,648,216,238]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4119AD5CFF7533F0B302A7F9" authority="(PANZER)" baseAuthorityName="PANZER" box="[178,539,216,238]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Obtusodonta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="equitatoria">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFF7533F0B0A9A7F9" bold="true" box="[178,432,216,238]" italics="true" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">Obtusodonta equitatoria</emphasis>
(PANZER)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 14)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF753228B0A0A63B" blockId="78.[178,1085,256,378]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFF753228B088A603" box="[178,401,256,276]" italics="true" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4119AD5CFF753228B00EA603" box="[178,279,256,276]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Ichneumon</taxonomicName>
equitatorius
</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFDE4B2F4119AD5CFE5A3228B306A603" author="PANZER G" box="[413,543,256,276]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" pagination="50 - 58" refId="ref60964" refString="PANZER G. W. F. (1786): Die Forlphalaene (Phal. Noct. Piniperda) nebst den der Larve derselben nachstellenden Insekten. In: Kob J. A. &quot; Die wahre Ursache der Baumtrockniss der Nadelwalder durch die Naturgeschichte der Forlphalane (Phalaena Noct. Piniperdae) erwiesen und durch einige Versuche erortert &quot; - Nurnberg Bischoff: 50 - 58." type="book chapter" year="1786">PANZER 1786</bibRefCitation>
- In KOB: Die wahre Ursache der Baumtrockniss der Nadelwälder…: 
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFEB93230B08CA63B" bold="true" box="[382,405,280,300]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">56</emphasis>
,.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35565554119AD5DFF75321AB291A153" lastPageId="79" lastPageNumber="676" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF75321AB224A651" blockId="78.[178,1085,256,378]" box="[178,829,306,326]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFF75321AB091A651" box="[178,392,306,326]" italics="true" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4119AD5CFF75321AB00FA651" box="[178,278,306,326]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Amblyteles</taxonomicName>
equitatorius
</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFDE4B2F4119AD5CFE52321AB33DA651" author="HEINRICH G" box="[405,548,306,326]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" pagination="305 - 326" refId="ref60321" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1929): Beitrage zur Kenntnis der Insektenfauna Nordpersiens. - Deutsch. Ent. Zeitschr.: 305 - 326." type="book chapter" year="1929">HEINRICH 1929</bibRefCitation>
- Deutsch. Ent. Zeitschr.: 319.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF753264B2CAA677" blockId="78.[178,1085,256,378]" box="[178,979,332,352]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFF753264B091A677" box="[178,392,332,352]" italics="true" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4119AD5CFF753264B00FA677" box="[178,278,332,352]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Amblyteles</taxonomicName>
equitatorius
</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFDE4B2F4119AD5CFE523264B36CA677" author="SCHMIEDEKNECHT O" box="[405,629,332,352]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" pagination="1 - 140" refId="ref61208" refString="SCHMIEDEKNECHT O. (1930): Opuscula Ichneumonologica. Supplement-Band. Fasc. VII-VIII. - Blankenburg Thuringen: (Genus Amblyteles Wesm.) 1 - 140." type="book chapter" year="1930">SCHMIEDEKNECHT 1930</bibRefCitation>
- Opusc. Ichneum., Suppl. 1 
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFC473264B292A677" bold="true" box="[896,907,332,352]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">8</emphasis>
: 83-84.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF75324EB248A66D" blockId="78.[178,1085,256,378]" box="[178,849,358,378]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4119AD5CFF75324EB322A66D" authority=": RASNITSYN 1981" authorityName="RASNITSYN" authorityYear="1981" box="[178,571,358,378]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Obtusodonta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="78" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="equitatoria">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFF75324EB08BA66D" box="[178,402,358,378]" italics="true" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">Obtusodonta equitatoria</emphasis>
: RASNITSYN 1981
</taxonomicName>
- Opr. Faun. SSSR 
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4119AD5CFD36324EB3E5A66D" bold="true" box="[753,764,358,378]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">3</emphasis>
(3): 621.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF7532A4B03DA6B6" blockId="78.[178,292,395,417]" box="[178,292,395,417]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF753299B0F4A54E" blockId="78.[178,1086,432,601]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">F l a g e l l u m: Rather slender, bristle-shaped, with 42 segments, not broadened and only just flattened behind middle, red-brown up to middle, without white annulus; segments distinctly differentiated, first segment short, 1,4 times longer than the width at apex, already segment 3 square from lateral, last but one square; flagellum from middle to apex, or its apical third black. Flagellum 1,3 times shorter than the front wing and 1,9 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5CFF753140B035A2A5" blockId="78.[178,1086,616,1458]" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">H e a d: Head contour from front almost roundly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, only 1,1 times wider than height; genae (malar space) rather short, from front 5 times shorter of height of an eye (0,2), genae visible on third of eye height; head contour from above transverse, 2 times wider than length in middle and 1,8 times along an external contour, roundly narrowed backwards behind eyes. Vertex from lateral linearly sloping from ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, in middle 1,4 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye, at low half parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina sharp all round, from above deeply roundly impressed, but far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, at the bottom merged with hypostomal carina far from mandible base; abscissula high, sharp, 1,5 times shorter than mandible base width, genae above abscissula slightly impressed; hypostomal carina high and sharp, visible from lateral to level of low border of an eye; malar space 1,5 times shorter than the mandible base width; mandibles rather broad, gradually curved from base to apex, parallel-sided on the larger part, with blunted rounded apex, without lower tooth or with only just visible its rudiment; clypeus slightly convex, 2,4 times wider than length, with straight impressed and thinned front margin and distinct lateral corners, separated from middle field of face by slight broad impression; clypeal foveae elongated, deep; labrum some narrower than front margin of clypeus, short, rounded, with long pubescence along front margin; middle field of face only just elevated, in middle equal to breadth of convex lateral fields; antennal cavities extremely strongly impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, with indistinct lateral tubercles and broad tooth between antennal fossae; front margins of antennal fossae moderately elevated above face surface; ocelli rather large, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,6 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle slightly, but distinctly elevated. Surface of face and clypeus with big, smoothed punctures; middle field only with separate superficial punctures; clypeus along front margin with row of punctures; face and clypeus shining, without microsculpture; frons above antennal cavities punctured by big smoothed punctures with slight microsculpture; temples shining with smoothed big punctures; face with long, sparse pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4119AD5DFF7536E9B2C5A5E1" blockId="78.[178,1086,1472,1581]" lastBlockId="79.[178,1086,218,758]" lastPageId="79" lastPageNumber="676" pageId="78" pageNumber="675">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum from above long with straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum shallow, rather narrow; pronotal ridge not swollen, narrow; epomiae sharp, high; pronotal base smoothly curved; upper half of pronotum with sparse superficial punctures. Mesonotum only just convex (flattened), 1,1 times longer than width; notauli not developed, only in a form of very slight impressions at base; surface of mesonotum punctured by smoothed, sparse punctures, shining; axillary tongue only just marked; prepectal carina sharp, upwardly not reach front margin of mesonotum; subalarum moderately thick, high, not sharpened; mesopleurae at upper half in front strongly swollen; speculum slightly superficially punctured; mesopleural fovea distinctly expressed, area of mesopleural fovea sharply impressed; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by slight ribs; mesopleurae at bottom without distinct bend (break); sternauli or only just marked in a form of a some flattened surface, or absent; surface of mesopleurae shining, lower half longitudinally wrinkled, upper one with superficial sculpture; scutellum slightly (only just) elevated above postscutellum, from above flat, laterally not carinated. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangular projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral with angular break, length of horizontal part 1,7 timer shorter than the length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum with exception of costulae and lateral carinae of area posteromedia distinct, costulae slightly marked; basal area short and deep; area superomedia slightly elongated from rectangular to slightly hexagonal (slightly narrowed in front and backwards from rudimentary costulae); areae dentiparae at apices without teeth; spiracles big, along external contour 3 times longer than width. Horizontal surface of propodeum slightly wrinkled; metapleurae longitudinally wrinkled; surface of propodeum shining, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4118AD5DFF75302EB200A40C" blockId="79.[178,793,773,795]" box="[178,793,773,795]" pageId="79" pageNumber="676">L e g s: Moderately stout. Claws slightly uniformly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4118AD5DFF753003B3BAA4A4" blockId="79.[178,1086,810,947]" pageId="79" pageNumber="676">W i n g s: Areolet big, pentagonal, almost symmetrical, sometimes external vein of apex shorter than internal one; stigma sort and broad, dark; radial cell long, radius curved at apex; nervulus slightly postfurcal; ramulus only just marked, or not expressed; all veins dark; membrane of wing slightly infuscated. Front wing distinctly longer than length of flagellum and shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4118AD5DFF7530EAB3FFA29F" blockId="79.[178,1086,962,1416]" pageId="79" pageNumber="676">A b d o m e n:Semiamblypygous, from above oval, narrowed to apex, sometimes with slightly compressed from sides apex, sixth and seventh tergites visible from above on considerable length; second tergite transverse, at apex 1,5 times wider than length; sheath of ovipositor not visible from above or only just protrude. First tergite from lateral with distinct bend between petiolus and postpetiolus, narrow at base; lateral carinae of first tergite smoothed but distinct, petiolus from lateral with smoothed transversal ribs; from above petiolus sharply broadened to almost rectangular behind spiracles postpetiolus; distance between spiracles 1,4 times more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus distinct, but slightly elevated and not carinated, 2,3 times wider than lateral fields, its surface delicately longitudinally striated. Gastrocoeli short, slightly impressed, square, 2,3 times narrower than interval between them, with distinct thyridia; lunulae only just marked, small; surface of second tergite up to apex very densely superficially punctured to slightly wrinkled medially; third tergite superficially punctured by small punctures, other tergites smooth. Hypopygium triangular from lateral, often compressed from sides, uniformly covered by long bristles; sternites sclerotized slightly, sternites 2-4 with longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4118AD5DFF7536BFB0BFA137" blockId="79.[178,1085,1431,1568]" pageId="79" pageNumber="676">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black with reach, variable red pattern; red: scapus and flagellum to apical third; head with exception of black lateral fields of face, antennal cavities and vertex, collar of pronotum, tegulae, sometimes spots on mesonotum; abdomen red with darkened base of tergites 3-4, sometimes tergite 2. Scutellum yellow. Legs, with exception of coxae, red.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4118AD5DFF753507B291A153" blockId="79.[178,904,1583,1605]" box="[178,904,1583,1605]" pageId="79" pageNumber="676">
S i z e: Body length: 13,2 (12-14); front wing: 9,5; flagellum: 
<quantity id="4CB79B3B4118AD5DFCF33507B29DA153" box="[820,900,1583,1605]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="7.1" pageId="79" pageNumber="676" unit="mm" value="7.1">7,1 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>