<document id="B0620F3EB9D8002549E69B26841144DD" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" _generate="added" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C8410EAD4EFF753642B084A6A7" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Triptognathops bicolor KRIECHBAUMER" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="92" lastPageNumber="689" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="2DF83A3A7252406E85DC0F4FF250AF14" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6AD90200A77E48B6EBF28CE15C7DF7DE">
<mods:title id="A67FD0C49419F0F0BD1C7F10022840F9">Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="F4036A0CC1A9A3355FC44A4CF4005550" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9732C818DEC134C4799D29CD5E1F4DD3">
<mods:roleTerm id="D2712E2C5B3C2C1596A9BE6935DFDFB6">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="13401FBF0F5C969F91F1CC1159927E8A">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="C4FA1CCC17AD0D937AEF0D5E4A85871A">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3BA3AFEFB4F6A676524260C50DD18195" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="DDDEDEA7AFB7361A5DA5DB39B3194F5C">
<mods:title id="B47EEA278A8D83B59A1EDFE4A702609C">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D82BF52DCA2E67699B857FEC6B2E53C5">
<mods:date id="CB87BDC1740DCD4ADFA9E231F5B58565">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D0AEE29E57A38873BABED001E0C8D4EF" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="0CDF3F930CA97BA5F1E1017FD24DC54A">2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="BB8888A50C0D069D3581581020E7423C" type="volume">
<mods:number id="F285D28B01735A980D8CA6DBEBFD6B2D">43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="33950811CBB94EE4E4CDD69FECD5AFF5" type="issue">
<mods:number id="438A226A5E3F50088985B9E900A7669C">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1C8D4B9662EA62E9BBDE867880F6652E" unit="page">
<mods:start id="5B4F2CE458B68FF13C7B74B08A166265">597</mods:start>
<mods:end id="ACEF9E6A872353854AB3FC3E8EC16299">711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="0C648A377AFFBD1B6C92FAD2D15B2EC8">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C8583B03EA3039D6376FE5ABF9D47B11" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0D77A3B05735256CCB1F3361C589721F" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="56FFB81AE1B9C69CA76E2A260C379527" type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03E687C8410EAD4EFF753642B084A6A7" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C8410EAD4EFF753642B084A6A7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C8410EAD4EFF753642B084A6A7" lastPageId="92" lastPageNumber="689" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">
<subSubSection id="C3556555410EAD4BFF753642B34FA269" box="[178,598,1386,1408]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410EAD4BFF753642B34FA269" blockId="89.[178,598,1386,1408]" box="[178,598,1386,1408]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">
<heading id="D0B881B2410EAD4BFF753642B34FA269" box="[178,598,1386,1408]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" reason="2">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D410EAD4BFF753642B34FA269" authority="KRIECHBAUMER" authorityName="KRIECHBAUMER" box="[178,598,1386,1408]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Triptognathops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolor">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410EAD4BFF753642B34FA269" bold="true" box="[178,598,1386,1408]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410EAD4BFF753642B0BBA297" bold="true" box="[178,418,1386,1408]" italics="true" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">Triptognathops bicolor</emphasis>
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410EAD4BFE6F3642B34FA269" bold="true" box="[424,598,1386,1408]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">KRIECHBAUMER</emphasis>
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3556555410EAD4BFF7536B9B525A2E6" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410EAD4BFF7536B9B524A2CE" blockId="89.[178,1085,1425,1545]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D410EAD4BFF7536B9B337A2B2" authority="KRIECHBAUMER 1882" authorityName="KRIECHBAUMER" authorityYear="1882" box="[178,558,1425,1445]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolor">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410EAD4BFF7536B9B044A2B2" box="[178,349,1425,1445]" italics="true" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">Amblyteles bicolor</emphasis>
KRIECHBAUMER 1882
</taxonomicName>
- Ent. Nahr.: 240,. 
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D410EAD4BFF753683B328A2A8" authority=": HEINRICH 1978" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1978" box="[178,561,1451,1471]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Triptognathops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolor">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410EAD4BFF753683B08BA2A8" box="[178,402,1451,1471]" italics="true" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">Triptognathops bicolor</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFDE4B2F410EAD4BFE583683B328A2A8" author="HEINRICH G" box="[415,561,1451,1471]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" pagination="1 - 81" refId="ref60736" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1978): [Eastern Palaearctic Hymenopterous insects of the subfamily Ichneumoninae.] (in Russian). - Leningrad: 1 - 81." type="book chapter" year="1978">HEINRICH 1978</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
. - East. Pal. Ichn.: 63-64. M a t e r i a l e x a m i n e d:: Vladim. Gub., leg. Kokuev.: Turkmenia, 
<quantity id="4CB79B3B410EAD4BFC7036EDB2EAA2CE" box="[951,1011,1477,1497]" metricMagnitude="4" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.5" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" unit="km" value="15.0">15 km</quantity>
to west
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410EAD4BFF2036F5B525A2E6" blockId="89.[178,1085,1425,1545]" box="[231,1084,1501,1521]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">
of Firusa, Dushak, 18.05.198 8, leg. А. Barkalov.: Lagodekhi, Gruzija, 
<date id="FFF1101E410EAD4BFC6136F5B525A2E6" box="[934,1084,1501,1521]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" value="1893-07-15" valueMax="1893-07-23" valueMin="1893-07-15">15-23. 07. 1893</date>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3556555410EAD4EFF2036DDB084A6A7" lastPageId="92" lastPageNumber="689" pageId="89" pageNumber="686" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410EAD4BFF2036DDB0A8A11E" blockId="89.[178,1085,1425,1545]" box="[231,433,1525,1545]" pageId="89" pageNumber="686">(Vinogradov-Nikitin).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410DAD48FF7533F3B03DA7E7" blockId="90.[178,292,219,241]" box="[178,292,219,241]" pageId="90" pageNumber="687">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410DAD48FF753228B1E1A6BF" blockId="90.[178,1086,256,424]" pageId="90" pageNumber="687">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, slender, with 54-55 segments, first segment long, 3,5 times longer than the width at apex, without white annulus, not widened and very slightly flattened ventrally beyond middle; only segments of the middle of flagellum square; segments of the base sharply separated from each other (differentiated), other more or less merged. Flagellum 1,4 times shorter than front wing and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410DAD48FF753290B010A209" blockId="90.[178,1087,439,1310]" pageId="90" pageNumber="687">
H e a d: Head contour from front strongly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, only 1,3 times wider than height; genae from front (malar space) 5,3 times shorter than height of an eye (0,2), genae not swollen, visible from front up to 0,2 from base of an eye, linearly narrowed; head contour from above transverse, 1,9 times wider than length in middle and 1,7 times along an external contour, sharply and linearly narrowed backwards behind eyes. Vertex from lateral linearly sloping from hind border of ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, in the middle 1,2 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye, below middle parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina sharp all round, from above sharp, high elevated and bent, uniformly roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, from lateral bent up to level of eye’s middle; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral, merged with occipital carina far before base of mandible; abscissula high, equal by length to mandible base width; malar space equal by length to mandible base width; mandibles rather narrow, evenly narrowed from base to apex, with sharpened apex, without lower tooth or even slight notch on its place, from base to middle strongly bordered from below; clypeus slightly convex, 2,1 times wider than length, with strongly impressed thinned front margin, distinct medioapical impression and rounded lateral corners, separated from middle field of face by impression; clypeal foveae small, deep; labrum rather long, rounded, almost equal by width to front margin of clypeus; middle field of face distinctly elevated, in middle only just wider than lateral fields; antennal cavities short, rather deeply impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, with distinct lateral tubercles and with very slight tubercle between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae high elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,2 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle slightly expressed, not spread on vertex up to occipital carina. Surface of clypeus densely punctured by smoothed punctures of moderate size, middle field with more deep rough and big punctures, lateral fields wrinkly-punctured; frons above antennal cavities roughly transversely wrinkled; vertex and temples longitudinally wrinklypunctured, striation of vertex sharp; surface of head without microsculpture. Frons, face and temples in lower half with long darkened pubescence (more short than in 
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D410DAD48FC0537C4B524A216" authority="A.M, 2011" authorityName="A.M" authorityYear="2011" box="[962,1085,1259,1281]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Triptognathops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="90" pageNumber="687" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gobiensis" status="nov.sp.">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410DAD48FC0537C4B524A216" box="[962,1085,1259,1281]" italics="true" pageId="90" pageNumber="687">T. gobiensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20857B7410DAD48FF753621B1E7A209" box="[178,254,1289,1310]" pageId="90" pageNumber="687" rank="species">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410DAD49FF753607B523A59D" blockId="90.[178,1086,1326,1582]" lastBlockId="91.[178,1086,219,650]" lastPageId="91" lastPageNumber="688" pageId="90" pageNumber="687">
T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum from above short, with more or less straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum very deep; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp, high; lateral surface of pronotum with rough sculpture and slight shine; pronotal base gradually curved, slightly sinuous. Mesonotum moderately convex, some (1,2 times) longer than width; notauli only just marked at base, practically absent; lateral furrow of mesonotum deep; surface of mesonotum densely punctured with more big smoothed punctures on middle lobe, without microsculpture, shining; axillary tongue distinct; prepectal carina at upper part not reach pronotum; subalarum high, not sharpened; speculum strongly convex with big punctures; mesopleural fovea sharply expressed, deep, without longitudinal impression around; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs; mesopleurae at bottom with bend from lower third before sternauli; sternauli in a shape of broad triangular impression up to hind third of mesopleurae; mesosternal suture deep, not strongly broadened backwards; surface of mesopleurae on the larger part roughly-wrinkled to cellular at lower third, dull or with slight shine; scutellum from lateral moderately elevated above postscutellum, from above almost flat, laterally not carinated, its surface punctured by smoothed punctures. Hind margin of metanotum with strong triangular projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Length of horizontal part of propodeum 1,9 times less than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum with exception of costulae and coxal carinae sharp; basal area short and deep; area superomedia rectangular, slightly transverse; all carinae of horizontal part high and sinuous; areae dentiparae at apex with strong teeth (more narrow than in 
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D410CAD49FC653135B008A547" authority="A.M, 2011" authorityName="A.M" authorityYear="2011" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Triptognathops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="91" pageNumber="688" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gobiensis" status="nov.sp.">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410CAD49FC653135B008A547" italics="true" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">Triptognathops gobiensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20857B7410CAD49FEDF3113B07CA547" box="[280,357,571,592]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688" rank="species">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
); spiracles long, slit-shaped, along external contour 4 times longer than width at middle. Surface of propodeum, including metapleurae, roughly-wrinkled, without microsculpture; vertical parts of propodeum with dark, rather sparse pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410CAD49FF7531B2B2C8A5FD" blockId="91.[178,1086,666,746]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">L e g s: Slender and long, hind tarsi long and slender. All tibiae with long thin spinules, all tarsi with dense spinules ventrally; first segment of hind tarsi compressed from sides. Hind coxae elongated. Claws very narrow and long, slightly uniformly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410CAD49FF7531D2B30AA492" blockId="91.[178,1086,762,901]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, big with narrow base, practically symmetrical, external vein of apex shorter than internal one; stigma rather broad, long, dark; radial cell long; radius slightly curved; nervulus slightly postfurcal; ramulus rather long; all veins dark; membrane of wing darkened. Front wing 1,1 times longer than length of flagellum and 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410CAD49FF7530BCB323A253" blockId="91.[178,1085,916,1348]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">A b d o m e n: Amblypygous, from above broad rather strongly narrowed to apex, apical tergites not hidden, sheath of ovipositor from above not protrude; second tergite transverse, at apex 1,4 times wider than length in middle. First tergite from lateral with distinct smoothed bend between petiolus and postpetiolus, from lateral sharply bordered by carinae and with strong transversal ribs between them; from above petiolus sharply broadened to postpetiolus, rectangular behind spiracles; distance between spiracles 1,8 times more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus sharply expressed and high elevated, more than 2 times wider than lateral fields, its surface roughly longitudinally striated, lateral fields of postpetiolus also with longitudinal wrinkles. Gastrocoeli small, only just impressed and approached to base of second tergite, many times narrower than interval between them; thyridia absent; lunulae weak, of moderate size; interval between gastrocoeli and surface of second tergite very densely and indistinctly superficially punctured, more densely in middle, with slight shine; tergite 3 shagreen. Only sternite 2 only just visible less sclerotized than subsequent ones; only sternites with sparse short pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410CAD49FF75367BB529A27E" blockId="91.[178,1072,1363,1385]" box="[178,1072,1363,1385]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black, tergites 2-3 of abdomen red to fully black (Turkmenia).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410CAD49FF753650B256A299" blockId="91.[178,847,1400,1422]" box="[178,847,1400,1422]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">
S i z e: Body length: 15,0; front wing: 12,0; flagellum: 
<quantity id="4CB79B3B410CAD49FD283650B252A299" box="[751,843,1400,1422]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.08" pageId="91" pageNumber="688" unit="mm" value="10.8">10,8 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410CAD49FF7536B6B1E7A2A4" blockId="91.[178,254,1438,1460]" box="[178,254,1438,1460]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410CAD49FF7536EBB527A126" blockId="91.[178,1086,1475,1585]" pageId="91" pageNumber="688">Flagellum with closely merged segments on the larger part, with big elongate-oval dark tyloides on (8)9-22(23) segments. Notauli at base of mesonotum more strongly impressed; scutellum more high elevated. Tergites 2-3 very densely and roughly punctured, dull. Pubescence of a body considerably more weak than in females. Paramerae broad</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF7533F3B036A619" blockId="92.[178,1086,219,270]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">with blunt rounded apex; hypopygium without elongate process, with cut apex, trapeziform.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF753235B051A69C" blockId="92.[178,1085,285,395]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">Body black, only tergites 2-3 of abdomen brownish-black. Margins of face broadly white, clypeus with white lateral spots, some segments of maxillary palps marked with white, scutellum white. Legs, with exception of black coxae and trochanters, red; hind tarsi darkened.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF7532B2B084A6A7" blockId="92.[178,413,410,432]" box="[178,413,410,432]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">Body length: 16,0 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>