<document id="3DC1B7B4AF37158FABCA90BD8081C922" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" _generate="added" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C84114AD57FF753789B2CAA265" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Ctenichneumon funereus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="666" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="2DF83A3A7248407785DC0E84F01EABD6" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6AD90200A76448AFEBF28D2A5E33F31C">
<mods:title id="A67FD0C49403F0E9BD1C7EDB0066443B">Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="F4036A0CC1B3A32C5FC44B87F64E5192" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9732C818DEDB34DD799D28065C514911">
<mods:roleTerm id="D2712E2C5B262C0C96A9BFA23791DB74">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="13401FBF0F46968691F1CDDA5BDC7A48">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="C4FA1CCC17B70D8A7AEF0C9548CB83D8">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3BA3AFEFB4ECA66F5242610E0F9F8557" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="DDDEDEA7AFAD36035DA5DAF2B1574B9E">
<mods:title id="B47EEA278A9783AC9A1EDE2FA54C645E">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D82BF52DCA3467709B857E2769605707">
<mods:date id="CB87BDC17417CD53DFA9E3FAF7FB81A7">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D0AEE29E57B9886ABABED1CAE286D02D" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="0CDF3F930CB37BBCF1E100B4D003C188">2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="BB8888A50C170684358159DB22A946FE" type="volume">
<mods:number id="F285D28B01695A810D8CA710E9B36FEF">43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="33950811CBA34EFDE4CDD754EE9BAB37" type="issue">
<mods:number id="438A226A5E2550118985B82202E9625E">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1C8D4B9662F062F0BBDE87B382B861EC" unit="page">
<mods:start id="5B4F2CE458AC8FE83C7B757B885866A7">597</mods:start>
<mods:end id="ACEF9E6A8739539C4AB3FDF58C8F665B">711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="0C648A377AE5BD026C92FB19D3152A0A">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C8583B03EA2A39CF376FE460FB9A7FD3" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0D77A3B0572F2575CB1F32AAC7C776DD" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="56FFB81AE1A3C685A76E2BED0E7991E5" type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03E687C84114AD57FF753789B2CAA265" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C84114AD57FF753789B2CAA265" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C84114AD57FF753789B2CAA265" lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="666" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">
<subSubSection id="C35565554114AD51FF753789B3ACA3A0" box="[178,693,1185,1207]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4114AD51FF753789B3ACA3A0" blockId="67.[178,693,1185,1207]" box="[178,693,1185,1207]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">
<heading id="D0B881B24114AD51FF753789B3ACA3A0" box="[178,693,1185,1207]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FF753789B3ACA3A0" bold="true" box="[178,693,1185,1207]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4114AD51FF753789B351A3A0" authority="(GEOFFROY)" baseAuthorityName="GEOFFROY" box="[178,584,1185,1207]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ctenichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funereus">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FF753789B0A4A3A0" bold="true" box="[178,445,1185,1207]" italics="true" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">Ctenichneumon funereus</emphasis>
(GEOFFROY)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 11)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35565554114AD51FF7537E1B24CA23C" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4114AD51FF7537E1B27EA3CA" blockId="67.[178,995,1225,1323]" box="[178,871,1225,1245]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4114AD51FF7537E1B313A3CA" authority="FOURCROY 1785" authorityName="FOURCROY" authorityYear="1785" box="[178,522,1225,1245]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funereus">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FF7537E1B072A3CA" box="[178,363,1225,1245]" italics="true" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">Ichneumon funereus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFDE4B2F4114AD51FEB637E1B313A3CA" author="FOURCROY A" box="[369,522,1225,1245]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" pagination="1 - 544" refId="ref60267" refString="FOURCROY A. F (1785): Entomologia parisiensis, sive catalogus insectorum quae in agro Parisiensi reperiunrur. - Paris: 1 - 544." type="book chapter" year="1785">FOURCROY 1785</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Entomologia parisiensis …: 406,.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4114AD51FF7537CBB262A206" blockId="67.[178,995,1225,1323]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4114AD51FF7537CBB311A3E0" authority=": WESMAEL 1844" authorityName="WESMAEL" authorityYear="1844" box="[178,520,1251,1271]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funereus">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FF7537CBB070A3E0" box="[178,361,1251,1271]" italics="true" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">Amblyteles funereus</emphasis>
: WESMAEL 1844
</taxonomicName>
- Nouv. Mém. Acad. Sci., 
<collectingRegion id="498BF83C4114AD51FD3837CBB24FA3E0" box="[767,854,1251,1271]" country="Belgium" name="Region de Bruxelles-Capitale" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">Bruxelles</collectingRegion>
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FC9B37CBB26AA3E0" bold="true" box="[860,883,1251,1271]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">18</emphasis>
: 136,,. 
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4114AD51FF7537D5B34DA206" authority=": TOWNES et al. 1965" authorityName="TOWNES" authorityYear="1965" box="[178,596,1277,1297]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ctenichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funereus">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FF7537D5B08DA206" box="[178,404,1277,1297]" italics="true" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">Ctenichneumon funereus</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFDE4B2F4114AD51FE6737D5B34DA206" author="TOWNES H &amp; MOMOI S" box="[416,596,1277,1297]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" pagination="1 - 661" refId="ref61469" refString="TOWNES H. K., MOMOI S. &amp; M. TOWNES (1965): A catalogue and reclassification of the eastern Palaearctic Ichneumonidae. - Mem. American Ent. Inst. 5: 1 - 661." type="journal article" year="1965">TOWNES et al. 1965</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mem. Amer. Ent. Inst. 
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FCFC37D5B25FA206" bold="true" box="[827,838,1277,1297]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">5</emphasis>
: 507.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4114AD51FF75363FB24CA23C" blockId="67.[178,995,1225,1323]" box="[178,853,1303,1323]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4114AD51FF75363FB326A23C" authority=": RASNITSYN 1981" authorityName="RASNITSYN" authorityYear="1981" box="[178,575,1303,1323]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ctenichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funereus">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FF75363FB08DA23C" box="[178,404,1303,1323]" italics="true" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">Ctenichneumon funereus</emphasis>
: RASNITSYN 1981
</taxonomicName>
- Opr. Faun. SSSR 
<emphasis id="B93BEACC4114AD51FD32363FB219A23C" bold="true" box="[757,768,1303,1323]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">3</emphasis>
(3): 620.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35565554114AD57FF753614B2CAA265" lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="666" pageId="67" pageNumber="664" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4114AD51FF753614B03DA246" blockId="67.[178,292,1340,1362]" box="[178,292,1340,1362]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4114AD51FF75364AB51DA2FB" blockId="67.[178,1086,1377,1516]" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, with 43 segments, strongly attenuated to apex, first segment 2,8-3 times longer than the width at apex, with white semiannulus on segments (6)7-11(12), slightly widened and very slightly flattened ventrally beyond white annulus; segments elongated slightly, already segment 6 square from lateral. Flagellum approximately equal by length to front wing and 1,7 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4114AD56FF7536D4B069A4FD" blockId="67.[178,1085,1531,1583]" lastBlockId="68.[178,1086,219,1002]" lastPageId="68" lastPageNumber="665" pageId="67" pageNumber="664">H e a d: Head contour from front uniformly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, only 1,2 times wider than height; genae from front visible only just above of eye’s base, genae length from front (malar space) 3,4 times shorter than height of an eye (0,3); head contour from above transverse, 2,1 times wider than length in middle and 1,8 times along an external contour, sharply roundly, almost straightly narrowed backwards behind eyes. Vertex from lateral linearly abrupt from hind border of ocelli to occipital carina; temples in middle 1,2 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye, parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina sharp all round, from above deeply and roundly impressed, but not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral, occipital carina meeting with hypostomal one before base of mandible; abscissula 1,1 times shorter than mandible base width; malar space equal by length to mandible base width; mandibles rather broad, parallel-sided in middle part, with long upper tooth and short lower one, separated by narrow impression; clypeus only just convex, 2,2 times wider than length, with straight (slightly concave) thinned front margin and distinct only just rounded lateral corners, distinctly separated from middle and lateral fields of face by suture; clypeal foveae sharp, deep; labrum protrude from under clypeus, rounded, some narrower than front margin of clypeus; middle field of face distinctly but slightly elevated above lateral fields, in middle equal by breadth to lateral fields, distinctly separated from them by slight impressions; antennal cavities not big, sharply and very deeply impressed, merged on the larger part, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, with polished surface, laterally above antennal fossae with tubercles and with sharp interantennal tubercle; margins of antennal fossae distinctly but slightly elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,3 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle slightly but distinctly elevated. Surface of clypeus densely punctured at base and laterally and shining apically; middle and most part of lateral fields densely punctured by almost merging punctures, lower part of lateral fields shining; frons above antennal cavities sharply irregularly-wrinkled; vertex and temples on top slightly wrinkled, most part of temples densely punctured by smoothed punctures, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4113AD57FF7530D1B048A669" blockId="68.[178,1086,1016,1608]" lastBlockId="69.[178,1085,218,382]" lastPageId="69" lastPageNumber="666" pageId="68" pageNumber="665">
T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum from above rather short with straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum narrow, deep; pronotal ridge not swollen, narrow, pronotum impressed to border with mesonotum; epomiae sharp, short; pronotal base gradually curved; lateral surface of pronotum at lower part strongly longitudinally-wrinkled and at upper one densely punctured by small punctures. Mesonotum strongly convex, 1,2 times longer than width; notauli sharply impressed in front third; surface of mesonotum very densely punctured, by small punctures, shining medially; axillary tongue developed; considerable part of prepectus visible from lateral, prepectal carina almost reach pronotum; subalarum narrow, high, almost sharpened; speculum smooth, shining; mesopleural fovea sharp, deep, area of mesopleural fovea narrowly deeply impressed; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by rather slight ribs; mesopleurae at bottom with rather distinct but smoothed bend; sternauli in a form of very indistinct broad impressions at base; surface of mesopleurae densely punctured by small punctures to wrinkly-punctured in hind lower third, shining, upper third punctured in front, area under subalarum wrinkled; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, gradually sloped backwards with slightly convex horizontal part, laterally not carinated. Hind margin of metanotum with triangular projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral gradually convex, but distinctly box-shaped with strongly elevated area superomedia; length of horizontal part of propodeum 1,7 times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum, with exception of costulae, sharply expressed, high at the apex of horizontal part; basal area short and deep without tubercle; area superomedia big quadrangular, only just transverse, 1,3 times wider than length; areae dentiparae at apices without teeth, external carina of area dentipara almost parallel to carina metapleuralis (remind 
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D4112AD57FECD323BB0DDA63E" box="[266,452,275,297]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="69" pageNumber="666" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="tribe" tribe="Protichneumonini">Protichneumonini</taxonomicName>
); spiracles big, long, along external contour 2,4 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum from punctured in front part of lateral fields to densely wrinkled on the larger part; metapleurae wrinkly-punctured; surface shining, without microsculpture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4112AD57FF7532A5B05FA6A8" blockId="69.[178,1085,397,447]" pageId="69" pageNumber="666">L e g s: Slender, long. Claws thin, sharply curved almost at right angle. Hind coxae without scopa.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4112AD57FF7532E6B02BA541" blockId="69.[178,1085,462,598]" pageId="69" pageNumber="666">W i n g s: Areolet big, pentagonal, slightly asymmetrical (external vein of apex shorter than internal one); stigma normal, dark; radial cell narrow, long; radius slightly sinuous; nervulus postfurcal; ramulus not expressed (only just marked); veins dark; membrane of wing hyaline. Front wing almost equal by length to flagellum and 1,5 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4112AD57FF75314CB2E3A32D" blockId="69.[178,1085,612,1082]" pageId="69" pageNumber="666">A b d o m e n Amblypygous, from above longish-oval, apical tergites not hidden, tergite 7 far protrude from under 6; second tergite slightly elongated, width at apex 1,1 times less than length in middle; tergites 2-4 separated by sharp constrictions, strongly convex medially; sheath of ovipositor not protrude from above. First tergite from lateral with distinct bend between petiolus and postpetiolus; dorsolateral carina only just marked, dorsal and ventro-lateral carinae sharp, from lateral petiolus sculptured by sharp transversal ribs; from above petiolus sharply broadened to postpetiolus; distance between spiracles many more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus distinctly elevated and carinated; dorsal carinae at level of spiracles high elevated; middle field some wider than lateral fields, its surface regularly longitudinally striated. Gastrocoeli deep, 2 times narrower than interval between them, interval equal by breadth to middle field of postpetiolus, thyridia practically not developed; lunulae distinct, not big; interspace between thyridia with sharp longitudinal striation, surface of second tergite medially almost up to hind third longitudinally wrinkly-punctured, other part of tergite 2 and tergite 3 entirely densely punctured by small punctures, shining, other tergites smooth. Hypopygium long, with slightly blunted apex; all sternites strongly sclerotized without longitudinal fold, only sternite 2 slightly unsclerotized in front.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4112AD57FF753760B27AA349" blockId="69.[178,867,1096,1118]" box="[178,867,1096,1118]" pageId="69" pageNumber="666">C o l o r a t i o n: Body, with exception of white scutellum, black.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4112AD57FF753744B25AA396" blockId="69.[178,835,1132,1154]" box="[178,835,1132,1154]" pageId="69" pageNumber="666">
S i z e: Body length: 16,0; front wing: 10,5; flagellum: 
<quantity id="4CB79B3B4112AD57FD283744B226A396" box="[751,831,1132,1154]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="9.5" pageId="69" pageNumber="666" unit="mm" value="9.5">9,5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4112AD57FF7537B8B1E7A3B2" blockId="69.[178,254,1168,1190]" box="[178,254,1168,1190]" pageId="69" pageNumber="666">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4112AD57FF75379CB2CAA265" blockId="69.[178,1085,1204,1394]" pageId="69" pageNumber="666">Flagellum ribbed ventrally from third segment, with narrow tyloides on segments 5- 16(17), without white annulus. Scutellum more high elevated than in females, area superomedia more than 1,5 times wider than length, propodeum shorter. Hypopygium elongated and broadly rounded from base. White coloration more expanded: lateral fields of face almost entirely, spot on scape, margins of labrum, spots in hind corners of pronotum, spots on tegulae and at base of front wings and scutellum; front and middle tibiae and segments of tarsi with white spots dorsally, hind tibiae with white annulus.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>