<document id="78749B9DC4252789B21148B66090F54F" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" _generate="added" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C8411DAD5EFF7536ABB317A34D" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Amblyteles armatorius" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="673" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="2DF83A3A7241407E85DC0FA6F1C3AAFE" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6AD90200A76D48A6EBF28C085FEEF234">
<mods:title id="A67FD0C4940AF0E0BD1C7FF901BB4513">Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="F4036A0CC1BAA3255FC44AA5F79350BA" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9732C818DED234D4799D29245D8C4839">
<mods:roleTerm id="D2712E2C5B2F2C0596A9BE80364CDA5C">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="13401FBF0F4F968F91F1CCF85A017B60">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="C4FA1CCC17BE0D837AEF0DB7491682F0">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3BA3AFEFB4E5A6665242602C0E42847F" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="DDDEDEA7AFA4360A5DA5DBD0B08A4AB6">
<mods:title id="B47EEA278A9E83A59A1EDF0DA4916576">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D82BF52DCA3D67799B857F0568BD562F">
<mods:date id="CB87BDC1741ECD5ADFA9E2D8F626808F">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D0AEE29E57B08863BABED0E8E35BD105" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="0CDF3F930CBA7BB5F1E10196D1DEC0A0">2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="BB8888A50C1E068D358158F9237447D6" type="volume">
<mods:number id="F285D28B01605A880D8CA632E86E6EC7">43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="33950811CBAA4EF4E4CDD676EF46AA1F" type="issue">
<mods:number id="438A226A5E2C50188985B90003346376">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1C8D4B9662F962F9BBDE8691836560C4" unit="page">
<mods:start id="5B4F2CE458A58FE13C7B74598985678F">597</mods:start>
<mods:end id="ACEF9E6A873053954AB3FCD78D526773">711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="0C648A377AECBD0B6C92FA3BD2C82B22">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C8583B03EA2339C6376FE542FA477EFB" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0D77A3B05726257CCB1F3388C61A77F5" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="56FFB81AE1AAC68CA76E2ACF0FA490CD" type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03E687C8411DAD5EFF7536ABB317A34D" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C8411DAD5EFF7536ABB317A34D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C8411DAD5EFF7536ABB317A34D" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="673" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">
<subSubSection id="C3556555411DAD58FF7536ABB39AA28E" box="[178,643,1411,1433]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411DAD58FF7536ABB39AA28E" blockId="74.[178,643,1411,1433]" box="[178,643,1411,1433]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">
<heading id="D0B881B2411DAD58FF7536ABB39AA28E" box="[178,643,1411,1433]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC411DAD58FF7536ABB39AA28E" bold="true" box="[178,643,1411,1433]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D411DAD58FF7536ABB30FA28E" authority="(FORSTER)" baseAuthorityName="FORSTER" box="[178,534,1411,1433]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armatorius">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC411DAD58FF7536ABB084A28E" bold="true" box="[178,413,1411,1433]" italics="true" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">Amblyteles armatorius</emphasis>
(FÖRSTER)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 13)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3556555411DAD58FF753682B2C4A2CE" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411DAD58FF753682B2A1A2A9" blockId="74.[178,989,1450,1497]" box="[178,952,1450,1470]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D411DAD58FF753682B314A2A9" authority="FORSTER 1771" authorityName="FORSTER" authorityYear="1771" box="[178,525,1450,1470]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armatorius">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC411DAD58FF753682B09BA2A9" box="[178,386,1450,1470]" italics="true" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">Ichneumon armatorius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFDE4B2F411DAD58FE403682B314A2A9" author="FORSTER J" box="[391,525,1450,1470]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" pagination="81 - 85" refId="ref60237" refString="FORSTER J. R. (1771): Novae species insectorum. Centuria I. - London, 1 - 100 (Ichneumonidae: 81 - 85)." type="book chapter" year="1771">FÖRSTER 1771</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Novae species insectorum, Centula 
<emphasis id="B93BEACC411DAD58FCA23682B269A2A9" bold="true" box="[869,880,1450,1470]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">1</emphasis>
: 82,.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411DAD58FF7536EDB2C4A2CE" blockId="74.[178,989,1450,1497]" box="[178,989,1477,1497]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D411DAD58FF7536EDB333A2CE" authority=": HOLMGREN 1856" authorityName="HOLMGREN" authorityYear="1856" box="[178,554,1477,1497]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Amblyteles" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="armatorius">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC411DAD58FF7536EDB099A2CE" box="[178,384,1477,1497]" italics="true" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">Amblyteles armatorius</emphasis>
: HOLMGREN 1856
</taxonomicName>
- Svenska Vetensk. Akad. Handl. 
<emphasis id="B93BEACC411DAD58FCA236EDB265A2CE" bold="true" box="[869,892,1477,1497]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">75</emphasis>
: 39,,.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3556555411DAD5EFF7536C2B317A34D" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="673" pageId="74" pageNumber="671" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411DAD58FF7536C2B03DA2E8" blockId="74.[178,292,1513,1535]" box="[178,292,1513,1535]" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411DAD59FF753527B2A1A63C" blockId="74.[178,1085,1551,1602]" lastBlockId="75.[178,1085,219,299]" lastPageId="75" lastPageNumber="672" pageId="74" pageNumber="671">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, with 50 segments, moderately thick, first segment rather short, only three times longer than the width at apex, without white annulus, only just widened, very slightly flattened ventrally beyond middle, strongly attenuated to apex; segments slightly elongated, already segment 14 square from lateral. Flagellum 1,3 times shorter than the front wing and 1,4-1,5 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411CAD59FF753213B0EAA4C3" blockId="75.[178,1086,314,980]" pageId="75" pageNumber="672">H e a d: Head contour from front quite strongly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, only 1,2 times wider than height; genae from front (malar space) 3,2 times shorter than height of an eye (0,3); head contour from above strongly transverse, 2,3 times wider than length in middle and 1,8 times along an external contour, strongly, almost linearly narrowed backwards behind eyes. Vertex from lateral sloping nearly linearly from hind border of ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, in middle 1,2 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye, parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina sharp all round, from above slightly roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral, occipital carina meeting with hypostomal carina far before base of mandible; malar space 1,3 times longer than the mandible base width; mandibles narrow, evenly narrowed from base to apex, upper tooth considerably longer than lower one, lower tooth weak; clypeus moderately convex, two times wider than length, with straight front margin and distinctly expressed lateral corners, separated from face, by slight impression; clypeal foveae small, deep; labrum equal by breadth to front margin of clypeus, rounded, moderately long; middle field of face slightly expressed, in middle narrower than the lateral fields; antennal cavities quite deeply impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, laterally above antennal fossae without tubercles and with slight but distinct interantennal tubercle; margins of antennal fossae slightly elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,7 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle practically not elevated. Surface of clypeus with big punctures; lateral fields wrinkly-punctured; frons roughly wrinkly-punctured; temples densely punctured; surface of head without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411CAD59FF7530CCB289A11E" blockId="75.[178,1087,996,1545]" pageId="75" pageNumber="672">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long, from above with straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum deep, narrow; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp; pronotal base gradually curved. Mesonotum moderately convex, only just (1,1 times) longer than width; notauli in a form of very slight impressions of some different sculpture; surface of mesonotum densely wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture; axillary tongue not developed; subalarum high, thick; speculum densely wrinkly-punctured, same as other part of upper third of mesopleurae; mesopleural fovea sharply expressed, deep; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs; mesopleurae at bottom without sharp bend; sternauli in a form of indistinct impressions in front third; lower part of mesopleurae wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture; scutellum with slightly convex horizontal surface, high elevated above postscutellum, laterally not carinated. Hind margin of metanotum with triangular projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Length of horizontal part of propodeum 2 times less than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum expressed, with exception of costulae and coxal carina (indistinct), but indistinct because of general roughly-wrinkled sculpture of surface of propodeum; basal area short and deep; area superomedia rectangular, transverse, two times wider than length; areae dentiparae at apices with strong apophysises; spiracles long, slit-shaped, along external contour 4 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum, including metapleurae, roughly-wrinkled to cellular, shining, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411CAD5EFF753531B347A65F" blockId="75.[178,1018,1560,1582]" lastBlockId="76.[178,1086,219,328]" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="673" pageId="75" pageNumber="672">L e g s: Slender. Hind tibiae with sparse spinules. Claws long, uniformly curved. W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, practically symmetrical; stigma broad, light; radial cell broad, radius very slightly sinuous, almost straight; nervulus sharply postfurcal; ramulus long; all veins light; membrane of wing slightly yellowish. Front wing longer than length of flagellum and shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411BAD5EFF753270B0C6A5C0" blockId="76.[178,1086,344,727]" pageId="76" pageNumber="673">A b d o m e n: Amblypygous, from above broadly-oval, apical tergites not hidden; second tergite transverse, at apex 1,4 times wider than length; sheath of ovipositor not protrude. First tergite from lateral with sharp bend between petiolus and postpetiolus, from lateral sharply bordered by carinae and with strong transversal ribs between them; from above petiolus sharply broadened to triangle postpetiolus; distance between spiracles many more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus sharply expressed and high elevated, 1,5 times wider than lateral fields, its surface roughly longitudinally striated. Gastrocoeli small, only just impressed, short, oblique; thyridia not developed; lunulae very distinct, elongated; surface of second tergite up to apex very densely punctured to slightly wrinkled, shining; tergites 3-4 densely superficially punctured by very small punctures, apical tergites shagreen. Hypopygium triangular from lateral, not compressed from sides; sternites 2-3 completely unsclerotized medially, sternite 4 with fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411BAD5EFF7531CFB34DA44F" blockId="76.[178,1086,743,856]" pageId="76" pageNumber="673">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black with reach yellow pattern: internal orbits, collar and hind corners of pronotum, subalarum and scutellum completely, bands along front margin of tergites 2-3 and apically of other tergites, all trochanters and femora partially and tibiae of all the legs; tarsi reddish-brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411BAD5EFF75304FB25AA46A" blockId="76.[178,835,871,893]" box="[178,835,871,893]" pageId="76" pageNumber="673">S i z e: Body length: 14,0; front wing: 11,2; flagellum: 8,0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411BAD5EFF7530A5B1E7A4B5" blockId="76.[178,254,908,930]" box="[178,254,908,930]" pageId="76" pageNumber="673">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE411BAD5EFF75309AB317A34D" blockId="76.[178,1062,946,1114]" pageId="76" pageNumber="673">Flagellum of male with yellow bacilliform tyloides on segments 4-19; clypeus flat; interspace between dorsal and ventro-lateral carinae of petiolus punctured, without transversal ribs. Middle field of postpetiolus from sharply striated to densely longitudinally wrinkly-punctured. Hypopygium slightly elongated at central part, with rounded apex. Yellow coloration more expanded: face completely, front half of second and third tergite completely and so on.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>