<document id="14D221CCA3AB33D362DC5AAE2FFC9C72" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5324836" _generate="added" approvalRequired="75" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="2" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="71" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630150516268" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2011" docId="03E687C8410BAD4CFF7532F3B004A6E3" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2011.43.1.597-711.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 43 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Triptognathops gobiensis A.M 2011, nov.sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="94" lastPageNumber="691" masterDocId="FFDFFFB04157AD12FFC73328B119A717" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)" masterLastPageNumber="711" masterPageNumber="597" pageId="92" pageNumber="689" updateTime="1630242846893" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="2DF83A3A7257406C85DC0BFEF2D0AF50" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6AD90200A77B48B4EBF288505CFDF79A">
<mods:title id="A67FD0C4941CF0F2BD1C7BA102A840BD">Illustrated key to the genera of the subtribe Amblytelina of Palaearctic (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae, Ichneumonini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="F4036A0CC1ACA3375FC44EFDF4805514" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9732C818DEC434C6799D2D7C5E9F4D97">
<mods:roleTerm id="D2712E2C5B392C1796A9BAD8355FDFF2">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="13401FBF0F59969D91F1C8A059127ECE">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="C4FA1CCC17A80D917AEF09EF4A05875E">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3BA3AFEFB4F3A674524264740D5181D1" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="DDDEDEA7AFB236185DA5DF88B3994F18">
<mods:title id="B47EEA278A8883B79A1EDB55A78260D8">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D82BF52DCA2B676B9B857B5D6BAE5381">
<mods:date id="CB87BDC17408CD48DFA9E680F5358521">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D0AEE29E57A68871BABED4B0E048D4AB" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="0CDF3F930CAC7BA7F1E105CED2CDC50E">2011-07-25</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="BB8888A50C08069F35815CA120674278" type="volume">
<mods:number id="F285D28B01765A9A0D8CA26AEB7D6B69">43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="33950811CBBC4EE6E4CDD22EEC55AFB1" type="issue">
<mods:number id="438A226A5E3A500A8985BD58002766D8">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1C8D4B9662EF62EBBBDE82C98076656A" unit="page">
<mods:start id="5B4F2CE458B38FF33C7B70018A966221">597</mods:start>
<mods:end id="ACEF9E6A872653874AB3F88F8E4162DD">711</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="0C648A377AFABD196C92FE63D1DB2E8C">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C8583B03EA3539D4376FE11AF9547B55" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5324836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0D77A3B05730256ECB1F37D0C509725B" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="56FFB81AE1BCC69EA76E2E970CB79563" type="Zenodo-Dep">5324836</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03E687C8410BAD4CFF7532F3B004A6E3" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03E687C8410BAD4CFF7532F3B004A6E3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E687C8410BAD4CFF7532F3B004A6E3" lastPageId="94" lastPageNumber="691" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">
<subSubSection id="C3556555410BAD4EFF7532F3B249A539" pageId="92" pageNumber="689" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF7532F3B360A6E6" blockId="92.[178,633,475,497]" box="[178,633,475,497]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">
<heading id="D0B881B2410BAD4EFF7532F3B360A6E6" box="[178,633,475,497]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="92" pageNumber="689" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410BAD4EFF7532F3B360A6E6" bold="true" box="[178,633,475,497]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D410BAD4EFF7532F3B0A0A6E6" authority="A.M, 2011" authorityName="A.M" authorityYear="2011" box="[178,441,475,497]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Triptognathops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="92" pageNumber="689" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gobiensis" status="nov.sp.">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410BAD4EFF7532F3B0A0A6E6" bold="true" box="[178,441,475,497]" italics="true" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">Triptognathops gobiensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A20857B7410BAD4EFE0732F3B315A6E6" box="[448,524,475,497]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689" rank="species">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Plate 17)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF75312AB249A539" blockId="92.[178,1047,514,558]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">
H o l o t y p e, Kholt, sev. Gobi, Mongolija, 10.06.192 6, Kozlov. The 
<typeStatus id="54F4887C410BAD4EFC6C312AB2E2A501" box="[939,1019,514,534]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">holotype</typeStatus>
is deposited in the collection of Zoologycal Institute of 
<collectingRegion id="498BF83C410BAD4EFD0D3132B255A539" box="[714,844,538,558]" country="Russia" name="Saint Petersburg" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">St. Petersburg</collectingRegion>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3556555410BAD4CFF753117B004A6E3" lastPageId="94" lastPageNumber="691" pageId="92" pageNumber="689" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF753117B369A565" blockId="92.[178,1084,575,626]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">
Female of describing species is differed from the 
<typeStatus id="54F4887C410BAD4EFD773168B3C5A542" box="[688,732,576,597]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">type</typeStatus>
species of the genus by unusually large ocelli and white annulus on flagellum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF7531AAB03DA580" blockId="92.[178,292,641,663]" box="[178,292,641,663]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4EFF75318FB50EA425" blockId="92.[178,1085,679,818]" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, slender, with 5(?8) segments, first segment long, 3 times longer than the width at apex, with white annulus on 10-14 segments, not widened and very slightly flattened ventrally beyond middle; all segments elongated; segment 1-4 of base sharply separated from each other (differentiated), other segments more or less merged. Flagellum almost equal by length to front wing and shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410BAD4FFF75306AB3A5A619" blockId="92.[178,1087,833,1587]" lastBlockId="93.[178,1086,219,270]" lastPageId="93" lastPageNumber="690" pageId="92" pageNumber="689">H e a d: Head contour from front quite strongly narrowed downwards, only just transverse, only 1,1 times wider than height; genae from front (malar space) 6,4 times shorter than height of an eye (0,2), genae not swollen, visible from front on distance of 0,1 from base of an eye, linearly narrowed; head contour from above transverse, 2 times wider than length in middle and 1,9 times along an external contour, almost linearly narrowed backwards behind eyes. Vertex from lateral sloping linearly from hind border of ocelli to occipital carina; temples long, at middle 1,2 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye, below middle parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina sharp all round, from above sharp, high elevated and bent, uniformly roundly impressed, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral, merged with occipital carina far before base of mandible; abscissula high, equal by length to mandible base width; malar space 1,4 times shorter than mandible base width; mandibles rather narrow, evenly narrowed from base to apex, with sharpened apex, without lower tooth or even slight notch on its place, mandible from base to middle strongly bordered from below; clypeus convex at base, 2,3 times wider than length, with slightly concaved and thinned front margin and rounded lateral corners, separated from face by suture and impression; clypeal foveae small, deep; labrum short, narrow and rounded; middle field of face distinctly elevated, in middle 1,4 times more by width than lateral fields; antennal cavities short, rather deeply impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, with big slight lateral tubercles and with very slight tubercle between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae high elevated above face surface; frons under front ocellus with longitudinal impression; ocelli strongly convex and large, diameter of lateral ocellus 2 times more than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle strongly elevated and bordered laterally by impression, on vertex expressed up to occipital carina. Surface of clypeus densely punctured by big smoothed punctures, middle field of face in upper part to wrinkly-punctured, lateral fields with big smoothed punctures; frons above antennal cavities roughly-wrinkled; temples smoothly wrinkly-punctured. Frons, face and temples in lower part with long darkened pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410AAD4FFF753236B32FA318" blockId="93.[178,1086,285,1039]" pageId="93" pageNumber="690">
T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum from above short, with rounded front margin; hind margin above furrow sharp, transverse furrow of pronotum very deep and wide; pronotal ridge not swollen; epomiae sharp, high; lateral surface of pronotum with very rough sculpture and slight shine; pronotal base gradually curved, slightly sinuous. Mesonotum slightly convex, only just (1,1 times) longer than width; notauli marked at base; lateral furrow of mesonotum deep; surface of mesonotum densely punctured with more big punctures on middle lobe, without microsculpture, shining; axillary tongue distinct; prepectal carina at upper part not reach pronotum; subalarum high, not sharpened; speculum strongly convex with big punctures; mesopleural fovea sharply expressed, deep with narrow sharp impression around; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs; mesopleurae at bottom with bend from lower third before sternauli; sternauli sharp, in a form of narrow cellular furrow up to hind third of mesopleurae, situated on broad triangle impression up to hind third of mesopleurae; mesosternal suture (in contrast to 
<taxonomicName id="4C4F4D5D410AAD4FFCE33155B52DA586" authority="KRIECHBAUMER" authorityName="KRIECHBAUMER" box="[804,1076,636,658]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Triptognathops" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="93" pageNumber="690" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolor">
<emphasis id="B93BEACC410AAD4FFCE33155B290A585" box="[804,905,636,658]" italics="true" pageId="93" pageNumber="690">T. bicolor</emphasis>
KRIECHBAUMER
</taxonomicName>
) evenly broadened backwards, forming triangle impression before middle coxae; surface of mesopleurae on the larger part roughly-wrinkled, without microsculpture, with slight shine; scutellum from lateral moderately elevated above postscutellum, from above slightly convex, laterally not carinated, its surface punctured by smoothed punctures. Hind margin of metanotum with strong triangular projections opposite of lateral longitudinal carinae. Length of horizontal part of propodeum 1,5 times less than length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum with exception of costulae and coxal carinae expressed; basal area short and deep; area superomedia rectangular, slightly narrowed backwards with equal length and width; carinae, enclosing areae dentiparae high and sinuous, areae dentiparae at apex with strong flat teeth; spiracles long, slitshaped, along external contour 3,8 times longer than width in middle. Surface of propodeum, including metapleurae, roughly-wrinkled, without microsculpture; propodeum with rather long and sparse dark hairs.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410AAD4FFF753737B2ECA378" blockId="93.[178,1086,1054,1135]" pageId="93" pageNumber="690">L e g s: Slender and long, hind tarsi long and slender. All tibiae with long thin spinules, all tarsi with dense spinules ventrally; first segment of hind tarsi compressed from sides. Hind coxae elongated, without scopa. Claws very narrow, long, uniformly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410AAD4FFF753757B0F4A21E" blockId="93.[178,1085,1150,1289]" pageId="93" pageNumber="690">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, big with narrow base, practically symmetrical, external vein of apex shorter than internal one; stigma more or less broad, long, dark; radial cell long; radius slightly sinuous; nervulus slightly postfurcal; ramulus rather long; all veins dark; membrane of wing darkened. Front wing longer than length of flagellum and 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE410AAD4CFF75363FB2AFA648" blockId="93.[178,1085,1303,1605]" lastBlockId="94.[178,1085,217,351]" lastPageId="94" lastPageNumber="691" pageId="93" pageNumber="690">A b d o m e n: Amblypygous, from above broadly-oval, rather strongly narrowed to apex, apical tergites not hidden, sheath of ovipositor from above not protrude; second tergite transverse, at apex 1,6 times wider than length in middle. First tergite from lateral with distinct smoothed bend between petiolus and postpetiolus, from lateral sharply bordered by carinae and with strong transversal ribs between them; from above petiolus sharply broadened to rectangular behind spiracles postpetiolus; distance between spiracles 1,5 times more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus sharply expressed and high elevated, (1,7)-2 times wider than lateral fields, its surface roughly longitudinally striated, lateral fields of postpetiolus also with longitudinal wrinkles. Gastrocoeli small, only just impressed and approached to base of second tergite, many times narrower than interval between them; thyridia practically absent or only just marked; lunulae slight, of moderate size; interval between gastrocoeli with very slight longitudinal striation at base of tergite, surface of second tergite very densely and indistinctly punctured, with slight shine, tergite 3 shagreen between sparse superficial punctures. Hypopygium more or less uniformly covered by long dark bristles; only sternite 2 with longitudinal fold; only sternites with sparse pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4109AD4CFF753247B297A692" blockId="94.[178,910,367,389]" box="[178,910,367,389]" pageId="94" pageNumber="691">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black, tergites 2-3 of abdomen red, legs black.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4109AD4CFF7532BCB278A6BE" blockId="94.[178,865,404,426]" box="[178,865,404,426]" pageId="94" pageNumber="691">S i z e: Body length: 15,5; front wing: 12,0; flagellum: 1[1],0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4109AD4CFF753292B1E7A6D8" blockId="94.[178,254,441,463]" box="[178,254,441,463]" pageId="94" pageNumber="691">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF036DE4109AD4CFF7532F6B004A6E3" blockId="94.[178,285,478,500]" box="[178,285,478,500]" pageId="94" pageNumber="691">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>