<document id="C92DAFE55AE14D9691F440038A44DBF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4333519" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f31ce7c7-fd74-4fcd-a871-1c9686763142" ID-GBIF-Taxon="167293024" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4333519" ID-ZooBank="B6053570-C067-45A8-9124-AA703777A045" _generate="added" checkinTime="1598055659936" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Sanborn, Allen F." docDate="2019" docId="03EE0B02B0534A27FF6646535820EAF6" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4614.3.1.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4614 (3)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Selymbria puntarenasensis Sanborn 2019, n. sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="8" lastPageId="44" lastPageNumber="445" masterDocId="FFD7737AB07A4A0BFFF1453A5D42EB7D" masterDocTitle="The cicada genus Selymbria Stå 1, 1861 (Hemiptera: Cicadidae: Tibicininae: Selymbrini): redescription including ten new species and a key to the genus" masterLastPageNumber="448" masterPageNumber="401" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" updateTime="1632022006054" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="750DD7FEF4D6B10BE5FEFA58B76DB40E" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="3650BFFF98425568CAE28F6ED764B832">
<mods:title id="BFC1E8E88281D57C04AA4DF3E3CD1FAE">The cicada genus Selymbria Stå 1, 1861 (Hemiptera: Cicadidae: Tibicininae: Selymbrini): redescription including ten new species and a key to the genus</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="C39A90CF1E780719440FBF6F55BDBCAE" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B2BE54B0F432FCB3C512E0F2C2F6B59A">
<mods:roleTerm id="72B1064DFF6C2EA60CB7E5899547436A">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0B5AE92714514F1ECA06DE386788F630">Sanborn, Allen F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="8279005170A66498597FE8FE188FD406">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="41A7487D706352B394CF914A899481CB" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="B8E2359B2A0BAA463F0DEA0012246845">
<mods:title id="2F1B2C50A306E1F5B4B50F5E0A16E1C1">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="A0C4359492080A1F07C8F756CAA6F1AF">
<mods:date id="F64CCA6675913CBEAAA3C0971BA00922">2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D2639EBC4AD0036B39AFE1B7934DCB1D" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="530EE8A64E095C6E13F1B7B8EE3DAD0C">2019-06-11</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="9C20A04DAA845DEE4A5FA44BF8275911" type="volume">
<mods:number id="8FFD951646A648FB8A55BCE178C437BA">4614</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="9CB3F0AA63A27833BB9B9EF105061570" type="issue">
<mods:number id="90AEF2BF99208A4A61AEEA22F1268F08">3</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="8198431B7C0035211EB31C53CB22C197" unit="page">
<mods:start id="3B889CAB9AD1F4430D709CD2E7260467">401</mods:start>
<mods:end id="66CBAC3C9DB630645CB5DADE6EB45073">448</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="4A9F37DCB772DF19FBE1C0366D8ECA85">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="A08E95E3C8E33D992424A8F95F7CA728" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4614.3.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="42549F5B8995DE2F13431E636FD45076" type="GBIF-Dataset">f31ce7c7-fd74-4fcd-a871-1c9686763142</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="AAD8BB571F904D7C5C82BBF766840EE6" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="A7CEBB1B3C1D844A2E3104609AF09A9A" type="Zenodo-Dep">3995202</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="69E10B5C6506839F031BAA3A9515125D" type="ZooBank">B6053570-C067-45A8-9124-AA703777A045</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03EE0B02B0534A27FF6646535820EAF6" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4333519" ID-GBIF-Taxon="167293024" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4333519" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EE0B02B0534A27FF6646535820EAF6" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03EE0B02B0534A27FF6646535820EAF6" lastPageId="44" lastPageNumber="445" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
<subSubSection id="C35DE99FB0534A22FF6646535F6AE8FE" box="[151,552,873,900]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0534A22FF6646535F6AE8FE" blockId="41.[151,552,873,935]" box="[151,552,873,900]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
<heading id="D0B00D78B0534A22FF6646535F6AE8FE" bold="true" box="[151,552,873,900]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" reason="1">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0534A22FF6646535F6AE8FE" bold="true" box="[151,552,873,900]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0534A22FF6646535C9CE8FE" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[151,478,873,900]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puntarenasensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0534A22FF6646535C9CE8FE" bold="true" box="[151,478,873,900]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Selymbria puntarenasensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0534A22FE1446535F6AE8FE" box="[485,552,873,899]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35DE99FB0534A22FF6646B75DB8E8DA" box="[151,250,909,935]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0534A22FF6646B75DB8E8DA" blockId="41.[151,552,873,935]" box="[151,250,909,935]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
(
<figureCitation id="137CA691B0534A22FF5146B75DB3E8DA" box="[160,241,909,935]" captionStart="FIGURE 10" captionStartId="43.[151,250,1689,1714]" captionTargetBox="[151,1434,170,1678]" captionTargetId="figure@43.[151,1434,170,1678]" captionTargetPageId="43" captionText="FIGURE 10. Selymbria puntarenasensis n. sp. A, holotype female habitus; B, holotype female dorsum; C, holotype female operculum; D, holotype female lateral view of genitalia; E, holotype female ventral view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 5 mm; C–E, 2 mm." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3995222" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3995222/files/figure.png" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Fig. 10</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35DE99FB0534A22FF6646EF5921EF6E" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0534A22FF6646EF5921EF6E" blockId="41.[151,1437,981,2015]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
<materialsCitation id="3B2FB049B0534A22FF6646EF5921EF6E" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2847252403" collectingDate="2012-01-16" collectionCode="TYPE, MATERIAL, FSCA" country="Costa Rica" location="At Light" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Puntarenas" typeStatus="holotype">
<collectionCode id="ED5622D1B0534A22FF6646EF5C7AE890" box="[151,312,981,1007]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">TYPE MATERIAL</collectionCode>
. 
<typeStatus id="54FC04B6B0534A22FEB646EF5CF1E892" box="[327,435,981,1007]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Holotype</typeStatus>
. “ 
<collectingCountry id="F350FA84B0534A22FE3A46EF5F33E892" box="[459,625,981,1007]" name="Costa Rica" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">COSTA RICA</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="498374F6B0534A22FD8D46EF5FB5E892" box="[636,759,981,1007]" country="Costa Rica" name="Puntarenas" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Puntarenas</collectingRegion>
/ Prov.: 
<collectingRegion id="498374F6B0534A22FCA846EF5E96E892" box="[857,980,981,1007]" country="Costa Rica" name="Puntarenas" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Puntarenas</collectingRegion>
Co. / 
<collectingRegion id="498374F6B0534A22FBEB46EF5994E892" box="[1050,1238,981,1007]" country="Costa Rica" name="Puntarenas" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Puntarenas Dist.</collectingRegion>
; “Tiskita / Jungle Lodge”. 
<location id="8E98ECCFB0534A22FF0946C35C1AEF6E" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EE0B02B0534A27FF6646535820EAF6:8E98ECCFB0534A22FF0946C35C1AEF6E" box="[248,344,1017,1043]" country="Costa Rica" name="At Light" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" stateProvince="Puntarenas">At Light</location>
<date id="FFF99CD4B0534A22FEAF46C35F64EF6E" box="[350,550,1017,1043]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" value="2012-01-16">
<collectingDate id="EFBD653CB0534A22FEAF46C35F64EF6E" box="[350,550,1017,1043]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" value="2012-01-16">16 / January 2012</collectingDate>
</date>
Anthony / Martin Deczynski” one female (
<collectionCode id="ED5622D1B0534A22FBFA46C35915EF6E" box="[1035,1111,1017,1043]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35DE99FB0534A22FF3641275CFEEF21" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0534A22FF3641275CFEEF21" blockId="41.[151,1437,981,2015]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
ETYMOLOGY. The name is a combination of 
<emphasis id="B9336606B0534A22FD4141245E04EF4A" box="[688,838,1054,1079]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">puntarenas—</emphasis>
for the province of origin of the 
<typeStatus id="54FC04B6B0534A22FB474127585AEF4A" box="[1206,1304,1053,1079]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">holotype</typeStatus>
and— 
<emphasis id="B9336606B0534A22FA95412458DEEF4A" box="[1380,1436,1054,1079]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">ensis</emphasis>
(L. suffix denoting place).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35DE99FB0534A21FF36415F5F78ECA2" lastPageId="42" lastPageNumber="443" pageId="41" pageNumber="442" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0534A22FF36415F5FC4EFBA" blockId="41.[151,1437,981,2015]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">DESCRIPTION. Ground color of head castaneous marked with piceous, and thorax tawny and castaneous marked with piceous, abdomen castaneous marked with piceous marked with castaneous and tawny. Tawny appears to have faded or was chemically altered from green.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0534A22FF3641EB5C8AEC7A" blockId="41.[151,1437,981,2015]" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0534A22FF3641EB5C49EF96" box="[199,267,1233,1259]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Head.</emphasis>
Head wider than pronotal collar lateral angles and mesonotum, dorsal head piceous except for castaneous anterolateral vertex not reaching anterior eye, mark extends posteriorly towards posterior cranial depression reducing piceous region, posterior cranial depression, mark continues laterally along posterior head towards but not reaching eye, supra-antennal plates castaneous, piceous posterior to eye. Long silvery pile posterior to eye, short golden pile on vertex, denser in sutures. Ocelli red, eyes testaceous. Ventral head castaneous with piceous transverse fascia between eye and postclypeal margin, anterior lorum piceous, posterior lorum castaneous, long silvery pile ventral to eye, on gena and on lorum, white pubescence on ventral head. Postclypeus with eight transverse grooves, central sulcus narrow at apex expanding laterally on posteroventral surface, tawny with castaneous fascia along midline over apex, with dorsal surface posterior to transverse grooves, within expanded region of central sulcus except for anterior region near apex, within transverse grooves, except for lateral portion of first transverse groove on dorsal surface, and ventroposterior piceous, white pubescence laterally, long silvery pile on ventral surface, short silvery pile in central sulcus. Anteclypeus piceous with tawny lateral regions connecting across posterior carina anterior to posterior margin, covered with white pubescence and long silvery pile. Mentum greenish tawny, medial and distal labium castaneous, lateral labium piceous, tip reaching to posterior of middle leg coxae, with sparse short silvery pile, denser near tip. Scape and dorsoproximal pedicel ground color, distal and ventroproximal pedicel and flagellar segments piceous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0534A21FF36422B5E81EAAE" blockId="41.[151,1437,981,2015]" lastBlockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" lastPageId="42" lastPageNumber="443" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0534A22FF36422B5C62EC56" box="[199,288,1809,1835]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="442">Thorax.</emphasis>
Dorsal thorax ground color. Pronotum ground color with median longitudinal castaneous fascia extending onto anteromedial scutes, with triangular piceous marks on anterior disks on either side of anterior midline, transverse mark on posterior disk with angled medial margin extending laterally to posterior lateral fissure, ambient fissure piceous from anterior lateral fissure to posterior mark. Pronotal collar tawny mottled with green, short golden pile radiating from lateral margin of lateral part of pronotal collar, white pubescence in posterolateral ambient fissure extending onto pronotal collar. Mesonotum ground color, piceous on disk surrounding sigillae except anterior margins of sigillae, posterolateral margin of the lateral sigillae, mark along medial submedian sigilla incomplete on right sigilla, mark between sigillae extending medially angling posteriorly connecting to median central fascia on disk that narrows anteriorly between submedian sigillae and expands laterally between anterior arms of cruciform elevation, scutal depressions piceous, anterolateral margin and posterior mesothorax piceous. Cruciform elevation ground color with piceous mark posterior to anterior arm of cruciform elevation, wing groove green with piceous spot on anteromedial and anterolateral margins. Metanotum castaneous with ground color dorsum and posterior margin, dense pile radiating from posterior margin. Short golden pile on disk between anterior arms of cruciform elevation and on lateral cruciform elevation, long silvery pile in posterior wing groove and on posterior margin. Ventral thoracic segments ground color, covered with white pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0504A21FF3644E45F28E8FE" blockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0504A21FF3644E45C51EA8A" box="[199,275,478,503]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">Wings.</emphasis>
Fore wings hyaline with eight apical cells, hind wings hyaline with six apical cells. Cubitus anterior 1 of the fore wing straight between the split with cubitus anterior 2 and the mediocubital crossvein. Venation ground color at base becoming piceous in distal veins of apical cells, subcostal vein distal to node and spot on proximal base of anal vein 2 + 3 piceous. Basal cell longer than broad, hyaline with slight greenish tint. Pterostigma present, mottled with red. Infuscation on distal subcostal vein, radius anterior 1, radius anterior 2 and distal radius posterior, infuscation extending onto ambient vein from subcostal vein to posterior of radius posterior vein extending to wing apex, second infuscation expanding from middle of subcostal vein across pterostigma, proximal apical cells 1–2, distal half of ulnar cell 1, and anterodistal ulnar cell 2 including entire radial and most of radiomedial crossveins. Basal membrane of fore wing gray with dark gray posterior margin. Venation of hind wing similarly colored with anal veins 2 and 3 castaneous, anal vein 3 piceous around base. Anal cell 3 and anal cell 2 along anal vein 3 gray, anal cell 2 along anal vein 2 gray, gray area margined with infuscation in anal cells 2 and 3, spot of infuscation on wing margin distal to apical cells 1 and 2.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0504A21FF3646B45E5CEF02" blockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0504A21FF3646B45C46E8DA" box="[199,260,910,935]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">Legs.</emphasis>
Coxae, trochanters, femora and proximal tibiae ground color, distal tibiae and tarsi castaneous, medial mesotarsus lighter. Fore femora proximal spine forming acute angle to femur with narrower base than secondary spine, secondary spine broadly triangular, upright to femoral axis, about as long as primary spine, and small, angled apical spine, primary spine ground color at base, piceous in middle with castaneous tip, secondary spine with piceous base except distal ground color spot and castaneous tip, apical spine ground color, long silvery pile radiating from ridge between spines. Tarsal claws dark castaneous with piceous tips, tibial spurs and comb castaneous with darker tips. Legs covered with long and short silvery pile.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0504A21FF3641B35931EE72" blockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0504A21FF3641B35C0EEFDE" box="[199,332,1161,1187]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">Operculum.</emphasis>
Female operculum ground color, straight lateral angled slightly mediad, sinuate when viewed from the side, posterolateral angle obtuse, posterior margins curving anteriorly in medial half, terminating medially at medial meracanthus, reaching to middle of sternite II. Female meracanthus ground color with castaneous medial spot, triangular, curving mediad, longer than operculum. Opercula radiating silvery pile.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0504A21FF3640235915EDC2" blockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0504A21FF3640235C7BEE4E" box="[199,313,1305,1331]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Tergites castaneous with piceous anterolateral region, percentage reducing in posterior tergites, piceous mark on lateral tergite 2 margin, tergites 4–7 with lighter posterior margins, tergite 8 with lighter dorsolateral regions, may be ground color in fresh specimens, auditory capsule castaneous with piceous anterior spot on margin, tergites covered with silvery pile, denser on lateral tergites. Female abdominal segment 9 light castaneous, dark castaneous dorsolaterally, piceous on stigma and ventrally lateral to margin covering of gonocoxites and continuing to posteroventral margin, covered with short silvery pile on dorsolateral surfaces, long golden pile on ventral and ventrolateral surfaces. Posterior margin of female abdominal segment 9 straight. Sternites castaneous with dark castaneous transverse fascia on posterior midline, covered with long and short silvery pile. Epipleurites castaneous covered with silvery pile. Female sternite VII with a deep medial notch, V-shaped anteriorly, angled laterally to about half sternite length where angle reduces and arches to posterior margin to semicircular posterior margin, lateral margin sinuate constricting posterior extension in middle of lateral margin, castaneous, lighter on distal posterior extension, covered with silvery pile, dense golden pile radiating from either side of notch center.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0504A21FF3643F35DB6EC32" blockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0504A21FF3643F35C7BED9E" box="[199,313,1737,1763]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">Genitalia.</emphasis>
Female gonocoxite IX dark castaneous medially with piceous lateral margin, gonapophyses castaneous, gonapophyses X with piceous tip. Gonocoxite X piceous not extending to length of anal styles which do not reach to terminus of dorsal beak, with radiating golden pile. Anal styles piceous with lighter ventral side, anal tube piceous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0504A21FF3642635CD3EC0E" blockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" box="[199,401,1881,1907]" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">Male is unknown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0504A21FF3642475F78ECA2" blockId="42.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">
MEASUREMENTS (
<subScript id="17C3B851B0504A21FE7042BE5CE6ECE9" attach="right" box="[385,420,1924,1940]" fontSize="7" pageId="42" pageNumber="443">MM</subScript>
). N = one female, mean. Length of body: 18.55; length of fore wing: 24.0; width of fore wing: 7.8; length of head: 3.15; width of head including eyes: 6.95; width of pronotum including suprahumeral plates: 6.3; width of mesonotum: 5.6.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<caption id="DF38EA9CB0514A20FF6643A35C05ED8F" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3995222" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3995222" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3995222/files/figure.png" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" startId="43.[151,250,1689,1714]" targetBox="[151,1434,170,1678]" targetPageId="43">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0514A20FF6643A35C05ED8F" blockId="43.[151,1437,1689,1778]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FF6643A35C60EDCF" bold="true" box="[151,290,1689,1714]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">FIGURE 10.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FEDB43A05F7FEDCF" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[298,573,1690,1714]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puntarenasensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FEDB43A05F7FEDCF" box="[298,573,1690,1714]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">Selymbria puntarenasensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FDB543A05FC2EDCF" bold="true" box="[580,640,1690,1714]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0514A20FDB543A05FC2EDCF" box="[580,640,1690,1714]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
A, holotype female habitus; B, holotype female dorsum; C, holotype female operculum; D, holotype female lateral view of genitalia; E, holotype female ventral view of genitalia. Scale bar: A, 2 cm; B, 5 mm; C–E, 2 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<subSubSection id="C35DE99FB0514A27FF3642135840EA1A" lastPageId="44" lastPageNumber="445" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0514A27FF3642135840EA1A" blockId="43.[151,1437,1832,2039]" lastBlockId="44.[151,1437,153,395]" lastPageId="44" lastPageNumber="445" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
DIAGNOSIS. Although it is not preferable to describe a species from a single female, the characteristics of this specimen preclude it from being classified as one of the other known species. 
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FBFA4276582EEC1B" box="[1035,1388,1868,1894]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FBFA427659A6EC1B" authorityName="Ramos &amp; Wolda" authorityYear="1985" box="[1035,1252,1868,1894]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ahyetios">Selymbria ahyetios</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FB014276582EEC1B" authorityName="Distant" authorityYear="1911" box="[1264,1388,1868,1894]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pandora">S. pandora</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
and 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FF66424A5C7BECF7" baseAuthorityName="Stal" baseAuthorityYear="1862" box="[151,313,1904,1930]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subolivacea">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FF66424A5C7BECF7" box="[151,313,1904,1930]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">S. subolivacea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished from this species by the lack of infuscation on the apex of their fore wing. The infuscation of the fore wing is found only on the apex of the fore wing in 
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FC0142AE586FECD3" box="[1008,1325,1940,1966]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FC0142AE592CECD3" authorityName="Ramos &amp; Wolda" authorityYear="1985" box="[1008,1134,1940,1966]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ahyetios">S. ahyetios</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FB8A42AE586FECD3" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[1147,1325,1940,1966]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="chevauxensis" status="n. sp.">S. chevauxensis</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FAC742AE5835ECD3" bold="true" box="[1334,1399,1940,1966]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0514A20FAC742AE5835ECD3" box="[1334,1399,1940,1966]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FA7642AE5C40ECAF" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cinctifera" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FA7642AE5C40ECAF" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">S. cinctifera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FEF842825C04ECAF" bold="true" box="[265,326,1976,2002]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0514A20FEF842825C04ECAF" box="[265,326,1976,2002]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FEA542825F4DECAF" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[340,527,1976,2002]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guatemalensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FEA542825F4DECAF" box="[340,527,1976,2002]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">S. guatemalensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FDE442825F11ECAF" bold="true" box="[533,595,1976,2002]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0514A20FDE442825F11ECAF" box="[533,595,1976,2002]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FD9142825FB1ECAF" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[608,755,1976,2002]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="guianensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FD9142825FB1ECAF" box="[608,755,1976,2002]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">S. guianensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FD0842825E75ECAF" bold="true" box="[761,823,1976,2002]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0514A20FD0842825E75ECAF" box="[761,823,1976,2002]" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, and 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FC8242825EACECAF" authorityName="Ramos &amp; Wolda" authorityYear="1985" box="[883,1006,1976,2002]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pluvialis">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FC8242825EACECAF" box="[883,1006,1976,2002]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">S. pluvialis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. The fore wing infuscation is found on the radiomedial crossvein and not on basal apical cells 
<quantity id="4CBF17F1B0514A20FCF742E65E0CEC8B" box="[774,846,2012,2038]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.08" metricValueMax="7.62" metricValueMin="2.54" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" unit="in" value="2.0" valueMax="3.0" valueMin="1.0">1–3 in</quantity>
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0514A20FCA742E65EA2EC8B" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2011" box="[854,992,2012,2038]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="43" pageNumber="444" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="danieleae">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0514A20FCA742E65EA2EC8B" box="[854,992,2012,2038]" italics="true" pageId="43" pageNumber="444">S. danieleae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. This new species can be distinguished from the females of 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FE7445A35F68EBCE" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[389,554,153,179]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boliviaensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FE7445A35F68EBCE" box="[389,554,153,179]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. boliviaensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FDC545A35F37EBCE" bold="true" box="[564,629,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FDC545A35F37EBCE" box="[564,629,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FD7745A35E7AEBCE" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[646,824,153,179]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ecuadorensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FD7745A35E7AEBCE" box="[646,824,153,179]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. ecuadorensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FCB345A35EC1EBCE" bold="true" box="[834,899,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FCB345A35EC1EBCE" box="[834,899,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FC6545A35974EBCE" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[916,1078,153,179]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="iguazuensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FC6545A35974EBCE" box="[916,1078,153,179]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. iguazuensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FBB145A359C3EBCE" bold="true" box="[1088,1153,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FBB145A359C3EBCE" box="[1088,1153,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FB6345A35869EBCE" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[1170,1323,153,179]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="loretoensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FB6345A35869EBCE" box="[1170,1323,153,179]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. loretoensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FAC445A35834EBCE" bold="true" box="[1333,1398,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FAC445A35834EBCE" box="[1333,1398,153,179]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FA7645A35C1DEBAA" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="madredediosensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FA7645A35C1DEBAA" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. madredediosensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FE9645875CE4EBAA" bold="true" box="[359,422,189,215]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FE9645875CE4EBAA" box="[359,422,189,215]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, and 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FE1445875F35EBAA" box="[485,631,189,215]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="stigmatica">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FE1445875F35EBAA" box="[485,631,189,215]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. stigmatica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the medial margin of the notch in the posterior extension of sternite VII curving laterad while it is straight or curving mediad in these species. The piceous region on the dorsal head is not reduced between lateral ocelli and eye in 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FD67443F5E7BEA62" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[662,825,261,287]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boliviaensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FD67443F5E7BEA62" box="[662,825,261,287]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. boliviaensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FCB1443F5E3DEA62" bold="true" box="[832,895,261,287]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FCB1443F5E3DEA62" box="[832,895,261,287]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FC7F443F597FEA62" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[910,1085,261,287]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ecuadorensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FC7F443F597FEA62" box="[910,1085,261,287]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. ecuadorensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FBB5443F59C6EA62" bold="true" box="[1092,1156,261,287]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FBB5443F59C6EA62" box="[1092,1156,261,287]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FB62443F5870EA62" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[1171,1330,261,287]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="iguazuensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FB62443F5870EA62" box="[1171,1330,261,287]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. iguazuensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FAC8443F583AEA62" bold="true" box="[1337,1400,261,287]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FAC8443F583AEA62" box="[1337,1400,261,287]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FA76443F5C53EA3E" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="loretoensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FA76443F5C53EA3E" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. loretoensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FEE944135C14EA3E" bold="true" box="[280,342,297,323]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FEE944135C14EA3E" box="[280,342,297,323]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FE9544135F0AEA3E" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[356,584,297,323]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="madredediosensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FE9544135F0AEA3E" box="[356,584,297,323]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. madredediosensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FDBF44135FCFEA3E" bold="true" box="[590,653,297,323]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FDBF44135FCFEA3E" box="[590,653,297,323]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, and 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FD3B44135E19EA3E" box="[714,859,297,323]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="stigmatica">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FD3B44135E19EA3E" box="[714,859,297,323]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. stigmatica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
but is reduced in 
<taxonomicName id="4C47C197B0564A27FBD0441359B0EA3E" authority="Sanborn, 2019" authorityName="Sanborn" authorityYear="2019" box="[1057,1266,297,323]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Selymbria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="puntarenasensis" status="n. sp.">
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FBD0441359B0EA3E" box="[1057,1266,297,323]" italics="true" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">S. puntarenasensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B9336606B0564A27FB0944135875EA3E" bold="true" box="[1272,1335,297,323]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A200DB7DB0564A27FB0944135875EA3E" box="[1272,1335,297,323]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" rank="species">n. sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
It is also the only species with two apical spots of infuscation in each fore wing known from Central America.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C35DE99FB0564A27FF36444B5820EAF6" box="[199,1378,369,395]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="8BF8BA14B0564A27FF36444B5820EAF6" blockId="44.[151,1437,153,395]" box="[199,1378,369,395]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">
<materialsCitation id="3B2FB049B0564A27FF36444B581CEAF6" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2847252354" box="[199,1374,369,395]" country="Costa Rica" location="Puntarenas Province" pageId="44" pageNumber="445" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Puntarenas" typeStatus="holotype">
DISTRIBUTION. The species is known only from the 
<typeStatus id="54FC04B6B0564A27FD0A444B5E1FEAF6" box="[763,861,369,395]" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">holotype</typeStatus>
collected in 
<collectingRegion id="498374F6B0564A27FC1C444B5996EAF6" box="[1005,1236,369,395]" country="Costa Rica" name="Puntarenas" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">Puntarenas Province</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingCountry id="F350FA84B0564A27FB11444B581CEAF6" box="[1248,1374,369,395]" name="Costa Rica" pageId="44" pageNumber="445">Costa Rica</collectingCountry>
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>