<document id="46483A9782BA1A2C594234580AB24387" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5887622" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2c2b0f81-dcfb-4ae5-8d57-be3d9f2fe8f1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="192495242" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5887622" ID-ZooBank="DC9F2DA8-DC30-454A-BAE8-D311DFEF958D" _generate="added" checkinTime="1642751139630" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2022" docId="03F12B6304750D617591FA437C95FE72" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.5092.4.1.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 5092 (4)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Bebelis parana Santos-Silva 2022, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="416" masterDocId="FFC8531B04790D6E7506FF89785AFFFB" masterDocTitle="New species, revalidation, synonymies, and new records in Bebelis Thomson (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Apomecynini)" masterLastPageNumber="428" masterPageNumber="401" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" updateTime="1642777679909" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="21B914E3399952CC6D9F65E77BD5BE79" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="C4CDE6F0D8A94F1268D40CFD920A6BB2">
<mods:title id="7B4F85A4D1F3B35A1B98CDD38FBB2684">New species, revalidation, synonymies, and new records in Bebelis Thomson (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Apomecynini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="8C49CE706E645A31EA86BFF60275D954" type="personal">
<mods:role id="FA5C7C2952414F2095B373D18D92E322">
<mods:roleTerm id="130DA59FF36191EDEC126C51717B7051">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1440C4E303573C49F88B0218384A397C">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="60F47726107B536B6A80F38D86A9061A">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3F4A2068BA5E7287E3F17CBD3C3B176A" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="1D0BA7D3A5A0ECAD0DDB5A3B6D340404">
<mods:title id="3594C6C180B68311E8A5CECA5E195B2B">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="068606480626844635ED1918952FFBF3">
<mods:date id="98881A477F5EE9946DD9434B3E1C42BE">2022</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="137EE2AE79BBE55B00FAC1D41AF88D9E" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="DC5D64A43289E6B0F35A3EA9E1877CE3">2022-01-21</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="458CCF1DBD83E1CC6B6CC95A67EC2B44" type="volume">
<mods:number id="097948161E76DA33B07FD98A7A790571">5092</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="E1E38A275BA561D00649DB330A899C08" type="issue">
<mods:number id="456480265A0E4D5B784A99DBEB5CD1AA">4</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="A63D724F4902BA23EA60FFD1A7593A1B" unit="page">
<mods:start id="BE59837FD1F82F612EB11B7064F1FC4A">401</mods:start>
<mods:end id="6D592F82F4D3F3D4E785773F579D6DB9">428</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="7482CA1191593A833C01A115FDD5FD9B">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="585984BDA354BB1E00CB76F937A0C3FB" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.5092.4.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="2CB388591632FCCCD00296B7AA64DE06" type="GBIF-Dataset">2c2b0f81-dcfb-4ae5-8d57-be3d9f2fe8f1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="1CFB4E29459B3028CE0B9891C403CD40" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="561D6E88603F74374D6075B58C6DE13F" type="Zenodo-Dep">5886400</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="4DC26C140C156121A856E8D045CD6F7B" type="ZooBank">DC9F2DA8-DC30-454A-BAE8-D311DFEF958D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F12B6304750D617591FA437C95FE72" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5887622" ID-GBIF-Taxon="192495242" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5887622" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F12B6304750D617591FA437C95FE72" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F12B6304750D617591FA437C95FE72" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="416" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<subSubSection id="C342C9FE04750D627591FA4379E8FA1E" box="[151,434,1482,1509]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504750D627591FA4379E8FA1E" blockId="12.[151,434,1482,1545]" box="[151,434,1482,1509]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<heading id="D0AF2D1904750D627591FA4379E8FA1E" bold="true" box="[151,434,1482,1509]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" reason="1">
<emphasis id="B92C466704750D627591FA4379E8FA1E" bold="true" box="[151,434,1482,1509]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<taxonomicName id="4C58E1F604750D627591FA437917FA1E" authority="Santos-Silva, 2022" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2022" box="[151,333,1482,1509]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="parana" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B92C466704750D627591FA437917FA1E" bold="true" box="[151,333,1482,1509]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Bebelis parana</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A21FFB1C04750D627452FA4279E8FA1E" box="[340,434,1483,1509]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C342C9FE04750D607591FA667C84FD52" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="415" pageId="12" pageNumber="413" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504750D627591FA667972F9F2" blockId="12.[151,434,1482,1545]" box="[151,296,1519,1545]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
(
<figureCitation id="136386F004750D627599FA667945F9F2" box="[159,287,1519,1545]" captionStart="FIGURES 40–44" captionStartId="14.[151,264,1946,1970]" captionTargetBox="[151,1436,777,1923]" captionTargetId="figure-254@14.[151,1436,777,1923]" captionTargetPageId="14" captionText="FIGURES 40–44. Bebelis parana sp. nov., holotype female: 40) Dorsal habitus; 41) Ventral habitus; 42) Lateral habitus; 43) Head, frontal view; 44) Mesanepisternum." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886416" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886416/files/figure.png" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Figs 40–44</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504750D637591F9BF7B98FF2E" blockId="12.[151,1437,1590,2013]" lastBlockId="13.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="414" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
<emphasis id="B92C466704750D627591F9BF79A5F9AB" bold="true" box="[151,511,1590,1617]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">
Description. 
<typeStatus id="54E324D704750D627434F9BE79C5F9AA" box="[306,415,1591,1617]" pageId="12" pageNumber="413">Holotype</typeStatus>
female.
</emphasis>
Head capsule dark brown, except ventral surface dark reddish brown anteriorly, gradually yellowish brown toward center of posterior region; ventral mouthparts mostly dark reddish brown; labrum dark yellowish brown with irregular blackish areas; scape narrowly black basally, brown on remaining surface, except irregular orangish-brown macula on dorsal surface of basal third; pedicel dark reddish brown anteriorly and posteriorly, dark orangish brown on wide central area; antennomeres III–IX orangish brown with reddish-brown posterior area (reddish-brown area gradually wider toward antennomere IX); antennomeres X–XI reddish brown basally, dark brown on remaining surface; mandibles dark reddish brown on basal 2/3, black on apical third. Pronotum mostly brown, with center of posterior half dark brown, and some areas dark reddish brown. Sides of prothorax, prosternum, ventral surface of meso- and metathorax mostly dark brown, with irregular reddish-brown and dark reddish-brown areas. Elytra brown on center of dorsal surface of basal half, light brown on remaining surface, with some areas more orangish-brown. Femora mostly reddish brown, with irregular, large dark brown areas, and apex of dorsal surface dark orangish brown. Tibiae dark orangish brown, with some areas slightly darker. Tarsomeres reddish-brown, except tarsomeres V orangish brown on basal 2/3, dark reddish brown on apical third. Ventral surface of abdomen dark reddish brown with darker irregular areas interspersed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504740D6375C1FF567BAFFC16" blockId="13.[151,1437,151,2013]" pageId="13" pageNumber="414">
<emphasis id="B92C466704740D6375C1FF567954FF02" bold="true" box="[199,270,223,249]" pageId="13" pageNumber="414">Head.</emphasis>
Frons moderately finely and abundantly punctate; with abundant straw-colored pubescence almost obscuring integument, and one long, erect brown seta on each side close to eyes. Area between antennal tubercles and upper eye lobes finely, abundantly punctate; with abundant pubescence obscuring integument, except glabrous median groove, yellowish-brown close to median groove, straw-colored close laterally. Remaining surface of vertex and area behind upper eye lobes finely, abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, denser on narrow band close to eyes, and short, decumbent white setae interspersed. Area behind lower eye lobes finely, moderately abundantly punctate; with dense pale yellow pubescence partially obscuring integument, partially straw-colored toward ventral surface, and short, decumbent white setae interspersed. Genae finely, sparsely punctate; with abundant pale yellow pubescence not obscuring integument, and short, decumbent white setae interspersed. Wide central area of postclypeus with straw-colored pubescence directed to central region close to frons, and moderately abundant, short straw-colored setae directed forward close to anteclypeus; sides of postclypeus glabrous. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior third, inclined at anterior 2/3; with a few both short and long straw-colored setae on coplanar area, long, erect yellowish-brown setae close to inclined area, and fringe of yellowish-brown setae on anterior margin. Gulamentum smooth glabrous, except a few short yellowish setae close to anterior margin. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.20 times distance between outer margins of eyes; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.56 times distance between outer margins of eyes. Antennae 1.3 times elytral length, almost reaching elytral apex. Scape cylindrical, finely, abundantly punctate; with dense strawcolored pubescence partially obscuring integument, and a few short, erect setae of same color interspersed. Pedicel and antennomeres III–XI with abundant straw-colored pubescence partially obscuring integument, denser, whitish on narrow apical area; with short, erect, sparse straw-colored setae interspersed; ventral surface with moderately long, erect dark setae. Antennal formula based on length of antennomere III: scape = 1.02; pedicel = 0.36; IV = 0.97; V = 0.74; VI = 0.67; VII = 0.61; VIII = 0.51; IX = 0.51; X = 0.46; XI = 0.61.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504740D6375C1FC7E7DC7F8D2" blockId="13.[151,1437,151,2013]" pageId="13" pageNumber="414">
<emphasis id="B92C466704740D6375C1FC7E797DFBEA" bold="true" box="[199,295,1015,1041]" pageId="13" pageNumber="414">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax about as long as wide; sides slightly rounded from anterolateral angles to posterior quarter, then subparallel-sided toward posterolateral angles. Pronotum coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with wide, fusiform pale yellow pubescent band centrally and white setae interspersed, from anterior to posterior margin, with its central region nearly glabrous from anterior quarter to near apex; sides of central pubescent band with moderately narrow brownish pubescent band not obscuring integument, and a few pale yellow setae interspersed; sides with dense yellowish-brown pubescence, except longitudinal, narrow yellowish-white pubescent band from posterior margin to near middle; with a few long, erect dark setae laterally. Sides of prothorax with sculpturing as on pronotum; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, slightly sparser on two longitudinal bands, one close to pronotum, another centrally, and short, decumbent white setae interspersed, except yellowish-white pubescent macula close to posterior margin and another on posterior third of inferior half, and sparser pubescence on postcoxal process. Prosternum coarsely, sparsely punctate; with abundant straw-colored pubescence not obscuring integument, more pale yellow laterally. Prosternal process coarsely, sparsely punctate; with abundant whitish pubescence not obscuring integument, denser on margins; narrowest area 0.25 times procoxal width; apex 1.10 times procoxal width. Mesoventrite coarsely, sparsely punctate, except smooth apex; with abundant yellowishwhite pubescence centrally, pale yellow on sides of anterior region, both not obscuring integument, except glabrous apex. Mesanepisternum coarsely, moderately sparsely punctate; with dense yellowish-brown pubescence close to elytra, distinctly sparser close to mesoventrite, and short white setae interspersed. Mesepimeron with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and white setae interspersed. Mesoventral process coarsely, sparsely punctate; sides gradually convergent toward posterior third, then roundly expanded; with abundant whitish pubescence, denser laterally and on expanded apex. Metanepisternum coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with yellowish brown pubescence not obscuring integument, and white setae interspersed. Metaventrite coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence laterally, and abundant whitish pubescence on wide central area. Scutellum with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence laterally, glabrous centrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504740D607591F8BA79C4FDE2" blockId="13.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastBlockId="14.[151,1437,151,753]" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="415" pageId="13" pageNumber="414">
<emphasis id="B92C466704740D637591F8BA78B0F8B6" bold="true" box="[151,234,1843,1869]" pageId="13" pageNumber="414">Elytra.</emphasis>
Coarsely, abundantly punctate on anterior half, punctures finer on posterior half; with abundant yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument on wide central area, denser close to suture, subglabrous, fragmented longitudinal band on center of dorsal surface, from anterior margin to near posterior third, slightly convergent on anterior fifth, parallel-sided on remaining surface, longitudinal, partially fragmented narrow white pubescent band on anterior quarter, between humerus and subglabrous band, fragmented white pubescent band from anterior sixth to near middle, with its basal half adjacent to glabrous band and its apical half within glabrous band, sides and posterior quarter with abundant pale yellow pubescence, interspersed by longitudinal areas with slightly sparser pubescence and longitudinal white pubescence; apex rounded. 
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D6076BEFF567BADFF02" bold="true" box="[952,1015,223,249]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Legs.</emphasis>
Profemora with abundant yellowishbrown pubescence dorsally, whitish laterally and ventrally; meso- and metafemora with pale yellow pubescence dorsally, except yellowish-brown pubescence on base and apex of femoral club, pale yellow pubescent band on center of sides of femoral club, and whitish pubescence ventrally. Tibiae with abundant yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, except ventral surface of posterior 2/3 of protibiae with yellowish-brown pubescence, posterior half of ventral surface of mesotibiae and posterior third of metatibiae with bristly light yellowish-brown pubescence, and posterior third of dorsal surface of mesotibiae and posterior quarter of dorsal surface of metatibiae with erect, thick yellowish-brown setae (erect setae darker on mesotibiae). Tarsi with pale yellow pubescence, sparser on tarsomere V.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504770D6075C1FDAB7D58FD9A" blockId="14.[151,1437,151,753]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D6075C1FDAB7919FDC7" bold="true" box="[199,323,546,572]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites moderately finely and abundantly punctate; with abundant yellowish-white pubescence partially obscuring integument, forming irregular, longitudinal dense bands on sides of ventrites 2–5.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504770D6075C1FDE37C84FD52" blockId="14.[151,1437,151,753]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D6075C1FDE379FAFD7F" bold="true" box="[199,416,618,644]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Dimensions (mm).</emphasis>
Total length, 6.90; prothoracic length, 1.30; anterior prothoracic width, 1.10; posterior prothoracic width, 1.25; maximum prothoracic width, 1.35; humeral width, 1.70; elytral length, 4.85.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C342C9FE04770D6075C1FD3A79D0FD0A" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504770D6075C1FD3A79D0FD0A" blockId="14.[151,1437,151,753]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D6075C1FD3A7923FD37" bold="true" box="[199,377,690,717]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation id="3B30902804770D607482FD3A79D0FD0A" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3450093343" collectingDate="1989-01-17" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="C. &amp; L. O'Brien" country="Argentina" location="Corrientes" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Corrientes" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="54E324D704770D607482FD3A79B6FD36" box="[388,492,691,717]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Holotype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry id="F34FDAE504770D607788FD3A7B6EFD36" box="[654,820,691,717]" name="Argentina" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">ARGENTINA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D607642FD3A7BE6FD36" box="[836,956,691,717]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">
<collectingRegion id="499C549704770D607642FD3A7BE6FD36" box="[836,956,691,717]" country="Argentina" name="Corrientes" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Corrientes</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<quantity id="4CA0379004770D6076C8FD3A7C51FD36" box="[974,1035,691,717]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="3.0" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" unit="km" value="3.0">3 km</quantity>
W 
<collectingRegion id="499C549704770D60713DFD3A7CE9FD36" box="[1083,1203,691,717]" country="Argentina" name="Corrientes" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Corrientes</collectingRegion>
, 
<date id="FFE6BCB504770D6071C7FD3A7D75FD36" box="[1217,1327,691,717]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" value="1989-01-17">
<collectingDate id="EFA2455D04770D6071C7FD3A7D75FD36" box="[1217,1327,691,717]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" value="1989-01-17">17.I.1989</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="26ADFFA304770D607039FD3A78A9FD0A" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">C. &amp; L. O’Brien</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode id="ED4902B004770D607434FD5E7924FD0A" box="[306,382,727,753]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<caption id="DF27CAFD04770D607591F8137A1FF82D" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886416" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5886416" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886416/files/figure.png" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" startId="14.[151,264,1946,1970]" targetBox="[151,1436,777,1923]" targetPageId="14">
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504770D607591F8137A1FF82D" blockId="14.[151,1436,1946,2006]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D607591F813790FF849" bold="true" box="[151,341,1946,1970]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">FIGURES 40–44.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="4C58E1F604770D60745AF81379ACF849" authority="Santos-Silva, 2022" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2022" box="[348,502,1946,1970]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="parana" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D60745AF81379ACF849" box="[348,502,1946,1970]" italics="true" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">Bebelis parana</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D6074F8F8137A15F849" bold="true" box="[510,591,1946,1970]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A21FFB1C04770D6074F8F8137A15F849" box="[510,591,1946,1970]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, holotype female: 
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D607616F8137B6BF849" bold="true" box="[784,817,1946,1970]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">40)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D6076DDF8137BA6F849" bold="true" box="[987,1020,1946,1970]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">41)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus; 
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D6071ADF8137C97F849" bold="true" box="[1195,1229,1946,1970]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">42)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus; 
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D60707CF8137DC9F849" bold="true" box="[1402,1427,1946,1970]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">43</emphasis>
) Head, frontal view; 
<emphasis id="B92C466704770D607464F83779D9F82D" bold="true" box="[354,387,1982,2006]" pageId="14" pageNumber="415">44)</emphasis>
Mesanepisternum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<subSubSection id="C342C9FE04760D6175C1FF1E795EFF2E" pageId="15" pageNumber="416" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504760D6175C1FF1E795EFF2E" blockId="15.[151,1437,151,393]" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">
<emphasis id="B92C466704760D6175C1FF1E7914FF4A" bold="true" box="[199,334,151,177]" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">Etymology.</emphasis>
The name of the species refers to the 
<collectingRegion id="499C549704760D6177FDFF1E7B1DFF4A" box="[763,839,151,177]" country="Brazil" name="Parana" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">Paraná</collectingRegion>
River, very close to the area where the 
<typeStatus id="54E324D704760D617001FF1E7D33FF4A" box="[1287,1385,151,177]" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">holotype</typeStatus>
was collected.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C342C9FE04760D6175C1FF567C95FE72" pageId="15" pageNumber="416" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="8BE79A7504760D6175C1FF567C95FE72" blockId="15.[151,1437,151,393]" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">
<emphasis id="B92C466704760D6175C1FF567961FF02" bold="true" box="[199,315,223,249]" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="4C58E1F604760D617442FF5679AAFF03" authority="Santos-Silva, 2022" authorityName="Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2022" box="[324,496,223,249]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="416" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="parana" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="B92C466704760D617442FF5679AAFF03" box="[324,496,223,249]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">Bebelis parana</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="B92C466704760D6174FEFF567A0EFF02" bold="true" box="[504,596,223,249]" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A21FFB1C04760D6174FEFF567A0EFF02" box="[504,596,223,249]" pageId="15" pageNumber="416" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
is slightly similar to 
<taxonomicName id="4C58E1F604760D61764FFF567B88FF02" authorityName="Martins &amp; Galileo" authorityYear="1999" box="[841,978,223,249]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="416" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculata">
<emphasis id="B92C466704760D61764FFF567B88FF02" box="[841,978,223,249]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">B. maculata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation id="136386F004760D6176E5FF567C62FF02" box="[995,1080,223,249]" captionStart="FIGURES 26–30" captionStartId="9.[151,264,1635,1659]" captionTargetBox="[152,1436,417,1612]" captionTargetId="figure-135@9.[151,1436,417,1612]" captionTargetPageId="9" captionText="FIGURES 26–30. Bebelis spp. 26–29) B. tinga sp. nov., holotype male: 26) Dorsal habitus; 27) Ventral habitus; 28) Lateral habitus; 29) Head, frontal view. 30) B. maculata Martins &amp; Galileo, 1999, holotype, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5886410" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5886410/files/figure.png" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">Fig. 30</figureCitation>
), but differs as follows: central pubescent band on the pronotum fusiform; white pubescent band on dorsal surface of the elytra longer, slight convergent basally, parallel-sided on remaining surface; and elytral apex rounded. In 
<taxonomicName id="4C58E1F604760D617119FEAE7CFFFEBA" authorityName="Martins &amp; Galileo" authorityYear="1999" box="[1055,1189,295,321]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Bebelis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="416" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculata">
<emphasis id="B92C466704760D617119FEAE7CFFFEBA" box="[1055,1189,295,321]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="416">B. maculata</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, the central pubescent band on the pronotum is not fusiform, white pubescent band on dorsal surface of the elytra shorter, strongly convergent, and the elytral apex is strongly projected on outer angle, and truncate toward sutural angle.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>