<document id="42FB228D4F81A1C931B95D59469177C4" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5940982" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8c3d903d-6d82-45d1-a1c0-b29f5b97d0c1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157145404" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5940982" ID-ZooBank="8A6746BE-616B-4FEC-AA37-E274F8508255" _generate="added" approvalRequired="12" approvalRequired_for_matCits="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="11" checkinTime="1557922264577" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Zhang, Chun-Tian, Shima, Hiroshi, Liang, Hou-Can &amp; Li, He-Nan" docDate="2019" docId="03F4DC05FFC8C8736C86DC88511E833F" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4603.1.1.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4603 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Estheria acuta Portschinsky 1881" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="13" masterDocId="FFCDA47DFFC3C87F6C11DD1A5025827F" masterDocTitle="Four new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from China and Nepal, with a review of the East Palearctic and Oriental species" masterLastPageNumber="38" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" updateTime="1643736677199" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="8F32B5556941D3C64392AEDF5E2C7C03" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="336CA46962D0AC20BAE634A003C13F05">
<mods:title id="6E519DA2C5849308C6C3526978D5AC13">Four new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from China and Nepal, with a review of the East Palearctic and Oriental species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="1944FCD9923B2534DCF424362E550A06" type="personal">
<mods:role id="6F35478F46B384D4FD4E711B064A998A">
<mods:roleTerm id="215460005F3D8197649385840A129AC5">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5CB80D262E28D951175E4BA585EB3A22">Zhang, Chun-Tian</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="2BC0947FC57CC3DF65DAEFBBAA3863BC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="88B28B5FE0D3AF5B8B6193BEAA4F7359">
<mods:roleTerm id="2BEF711921919E70746549B86894BCDA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="354BAB7F4DA3BCEC349998CAC9102F15">Shima, Hiroshi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="2E054BF7D879176BED2F7BE33A98ED89" type="personal">
<mods:role id="DA22DB849199A3B36857998DA56F1ECA">
<mods:roleTerm id="0885D02F105EE6FBEBD13C2182D7ACB0">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0B9DCE113D322A71E25DE7EAA71A9314">Liang, Hou-Can</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="8A156C3A486EDAB48E8584D38DE56BAC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="6B8C431457403A313A8732C1577DF753">
<mods:roleTerm id="095BF13B45904E2284D944D738F961CA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="49B5D1C90BE14B4034BD970FFE191543">Li, He-Nan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="CFB0EC33A391B5EC81E25391992038BD">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="B4F36DEB9ACC836AD27126F9472B1F8D" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="4BF802C0038E9EA4FAE85E7C43F9CE0D">
<mods:title id="08637FF6FA32A1C813CDE4F598E1BDD7">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="5D5913C9A27E2C3F4240F4CE41F41D83">
<mods:date id="708D2A513EF379D0DEA59C3AD7515FCB">2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="448C054CD35082C9512DE6158CF51F10" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="DA281C4BBD6731EFE5DD6383B211DEA1">2019-05-08</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="7BFE9854AA20E4388F41E6E0B82926B8" type="volume">
<mods:number id="26D8735179FAC7096A56CC2546767C20">4603</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="FAD7E436CD7A1129A99CEC844972B86A" type="issue">
<mods:number id="D19FCC19516EED53B6EF8E9A6E19011D">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="DE45B1BC3DB94872E8DF49DC4BAED161" unit="page">
<mods:start id="46DA5C5FFD1D18BF608AA0859F99DB74">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="D2FEA7948E755B1778451AD86865947C">38</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="62A36613D2E731DF3A0BCC3A72FF3C00">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="F29190DFD5822BB40BEE460362E8A814" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4603.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="4072F5A9E49A81D83417C5A30EE7720D" type="GBIF-Dataset">8c3d903d-6d82-45d1-a1c0-b29f5b97d0c1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="68884ED6568BE8105467DB3BA0EC2147" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="2EC5E375E5A435E16CE7A9EEA72250C6" type="Zenodo-Dep">2841928</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8F939EABA73D7471680332134A70CD4A" type="ZooBank">8A6746BE-616B-4FEC-AA37-E274F8508255</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F4DC05FFC8C8736C86DC88511E833F" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5940982" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157145404" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5940982" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFC8C8736C86DC88511E833F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F4DC05FFC8C8736C86DC88511E833F" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="13" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFC8C8746C86DC88526983D3" box="[151,588,402,428]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746C86DC88526983D3" blockId="11.[151,588,402,462]" box="[151,588,402,428]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<heading id="D0AADA7FFFC8C8746C86DC88526983D3" bold="true" box="[151,588,402,428]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" reason="1">
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFC8C8746C86DC88526983D3" authority="(Portschinsky, 1881)" authorityName="Portschinsky" authorityYear="1881" baseAuthorityName="Portschinsky" baseAuthorityYear="1881" box="[151,588,402,428]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746C86DC88526983D3" bold="true" box="[151,588,402,428]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746C86DC88516283D3" bold="true" box="[151,327,402,428]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Estheria acuta</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFC8C8746D47DC88526183D3" author="Portschinsky" box="[342,580,402,428]" firstAuthor="Portschinsky" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" pagination="257 - 284" refId="ref33542" refString="Portschinsky, J. A. (1881) Diptera europaea et asiatica nova aut minus cognita. Pars II da. Horae Societatis Entomologicae Rossicae, 16, 257 - 284." type="journal article" year="1881">Portschinsky, 1881</bibRefCitation>
)
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFC8C8746C86DCAF520483B1" box="[151,545,437,462]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746C86DCAF520483B1" blockId="11.[151,588,402,462]" box="[151,545,437,462]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
(
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746C8EDCAF50C283B1" box="[159,231,437,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–12" captionStartId="27.[151,264,1739,1762]" captionTargetBox="[265,1314,205,1697]" captionTargetId="figure@27.[256,1327,195,1710]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURES 1–12. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in caudal view. 1. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 2. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 3. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 4. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 5. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 6. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 7. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 8. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 9. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 10. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 11. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 12. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841934/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Figs 5</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746CE2DCAC513483B1" box="[243,273,438,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 13–24" captionStartId="28.[151,264,1735,1758]" captionTargetBox="[275,1294,206,1693]" captionTargetId="figure@28.[249,1320,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="28" captionText="FIGURES 13–24. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in lateral view. 13. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 14. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 15. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 16. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 17. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 18. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 19. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 20. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 21. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 22. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 23. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 24. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841940/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">17</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746D0CDCAC511E83B1" box="[285,315,438,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 25–36" captionStartId="29.[151,264,1733,1756]" captionTargetBox="[270,1317,224,1702]" captionTargetId="figure@29.[255,1326,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="29" captionText="FIGURES 25–36. Estheria spp., phallic complexes in lateral view. 25. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 26. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 27. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 28. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 29. E. acuta (Portschinsky), speciumen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 30. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 31. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 32. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 33. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 34. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 35. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 36. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841948/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">29</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746D56DCAC514083B1" box="[327,357,438,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 37–52" captionStartId="30.[151,264,1665,1688]" captionTargetBox="[281,1301,213,1612]" captionTargetId="figure@30.[281,1301,193,1636]" captionTargetPageId="30" captionText="FIGURES 37–52. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. 37–48, 52. Sternite 5 in ventral view. 49–50. Epandrial complex in caudal (49) and lateral (50) views. 51. Phallic complex in lateral view. 37. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 38. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 39. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 40. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 41. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU); 42. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 43. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 44. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 45. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 46. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 47. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 48. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). 49–52. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841952/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">41</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746D60DCAF51AA83B1" box="[369,399,437,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 53–64" captionStartId="31.[151,264,1742,1765]" captionTargetBox="[319,1255,193,1713]" captionTargetId="figure@31.[319,1255,193,1713]" captionTargetPageId="31" captionText="FIGURES 53–64. Estheria spp., male heads in anterior view. 53. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 54. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 55. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 56. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 57. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 58. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 59. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 60. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 61. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 62. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 63. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 64. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841962/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">57</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746D8ADCAC519C83B1" box="[411,441,438,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 83–91" captionStartId="34.[151,264,1795,1818]" captionTargetBox="[270,1275,215,1733]" captionTargetId="figure@34.[234,1351,193,1773]" captionTargetPageId="34" captionText="FIGURES 83–91. Estheria spp., male heads in lateral view. 83. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 84. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 85. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 86. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 87. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 88. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 89. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 90. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS). 91. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars: 0.5 mm (Figs 87–89); 1 mm (Figs 90–91)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841988/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">83</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746DD7DCAF51C183B1" box="[454,484,437,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 92–106" captionStartId="35.[151,264,1719,1742]" captionTargetBox="[267,1298,254,1691]" captionTargetId="figure@35.[258,1309,211,1697]" captionTargetPageId="35" captionText="FIGURES 92–106. Estheria spp., male habitus in dorsal (92–104) and lateral (106) view; head in anterior view (105). 92. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 93. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 94. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 95. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 96. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 97. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden- Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 98. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 99. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 100. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 101. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 102. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 103. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS). 104–106. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841996/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">96</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746DFEDCAC523D83B1" box="[495,536,438,462]" captionStart="FIGURES 107–118" captionStartId="36.[151,264,1749,1772]" captionTargetBox="[239,1323,246,1694]" captionTargetId="figure@36.[239,1341,193,1751]" captionTargetPageId="36" captionText="FIGURES 107–118. Estheria spp., male habitus in lateral view. 107. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 108. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 109. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 110. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 111. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 112. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 113. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 114. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 115. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 116. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 117. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 118. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2842000/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">111</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFC8C8746C86DCE45103802F" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746C86DCE45103802F" blockId="11.[151,1437,509,592]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<treatmentCitationGroup id="AB4D4A3DFFC8C8746C86DCE45103802F" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFC8C8746C86DCE4525D806C" authority="Portschinsky, 1881: 141" authorityName="Portschinsky" authorityPageNumber="141" authorityYear="1881" box="[151,632,509,531]" class="Insecta" family="Pteromalidae" genus="Syntomocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746C86DCE45147806C" box="[151,354,510,531]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Syntomocera acuta</emphasis>
<treatmentCitation id="0AFC4B02FFC8C8746D60DCE7525D806C" author="Portschinsky, J. A." box="[369,632,509,531]" page="141" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" year="1881">
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFC8C8746D60DCE75218806C" author="Portschinsky" box="[369,573,509,531]" firstAuthor="Portschinsky" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" pagination="257 - 284" refId="ref33542" refString="Portschinsky, J. A. (1881) Diptera europaea et asiatica nova aut minus cognita. Pars II da. Horae Societatis Entomologicae Rossicae, 16, 257 - 284." type="journal article" year="1881">Portschinsky, 1881</bibRefCitation>
: 141
</treatmentCitation>
</taxonomicName>
. Type locality: Akstafa (
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFC8C8746F83DCE75422806C" box="[914,1031,509,531]" name="Azerbaijan" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Azerbaijan</collectingCountry>
). 
<typeStatus id="54E6D3B1FFC8C8746831DCE7545B806C" box="[1056,1150,509,531]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Holotype</typeStatus>
<specimenCount id="9D5BA69AFFC8C874689CDCE45485806C" box="[1165,1184,510,531]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="male">♂</specimenCount>
(? 
<collectionCode id="ED4CF5D6FFC8C87468D1DCE754CB806C" box="[1216,1262,509,531]" country="Russia" name="Russian Academy of Sciences, Zoological Institute, Zoological Museum" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="Museum">ZIN</collectionCode>
) not examined. References: 
<treatmentCitation id="0AFC4B02FFC8C8746D56DF0652F9804D" author="Herting, B. &amp; Dely-Draskovits, A." box="[327,732,540,562]" page="363" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" year="1993">
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFC8C8746D56DF065282804D" author="Herting &amp; Dely-Draskovits" box="[327,679,540,562]" firstAuthor="Herting" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" pagination="118 - 458" refId="ref32837" refString="Herting, B. &amp; Dely-Draskovits, A. (1993) Family Tachinidae. In: Soos, A. &amp; Papp, L. (Eds.), Catalog of Palaearctic Diptera. Fol. 13. Anthomyiidae-Tachinidae. Hungarian Natural HistoryMuseum, Budapest, pp. 118 - 458." type="book chapter" year="1993">Herting &amp; Dely-Draskovits (1993</bibRefCitation>
: 363
</treatmentCitation>
; Palearctic catalog); 
<treatmentCitation id="0AFC4B02FFC8C8746FA4DF065534804D" author="Cerretti, P. &amp; Tschorsnig, H. - P." box="[949,1297,540,562]" page="272" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" year="2012">
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFC8C8746FA4DF0654F8804D" author="Cerretti &amp; Tschorsnig" box="[949,1245,540,562]" firstAuthor="Cerretti" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" pagination="271 - 286" refId="ref32552" refString="Cerretti, P. &amp; Tschorsnig, H. - P. (2012) Three new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from the Mediterranean, with a key to the European and Mediterranean species of the genus. Stuttgarter Beitrage zur Naturkunde A, Neue Serie, 5, 271 - 286." type="journal article" year="2012">Cerretti &amp; Tschorsnig (2012</bibRefCitation>
: 272
</treatmentCitation>
, 284; species and key).
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFC8C8746C86DF6D52A480A7" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746C86DF6D52A480A7" blockId="11.[151,1437,631,2027]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746C86DF6D513480EF" bold="true" box="[151,273,631,656]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
Frons of male 
<date id="FFE34BD3FFC8C8746DDDDF62520A80EF" box="[460,559,632,656]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="2010-01-09" valueMax="2010-01-01" valueMin="2010-01-09">1/9–1/10</date>
of head width; three strongest postpronotal setae arranged in a triangle; 4 presutural and 4 postsutural dorsocentral setae; male abdomen usually more or less red-brown in ground colour, female abdomen predominantly red-yellow.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFC8C8746CD6DFFE548C85DC" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746CD6DFFE52988083" blockId="11.[151,1437,631,2027]" box="[199,701,740,765]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746CD6DFFE51518082" bold="true" box="[199,372,740,765]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Redescription.</emphasis>
Body length: 
<quantity id="4CA5C0F6FFC8C8746E05DFFE529C8083" box="[532,697,740,765]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.1" metricValueMax="1.15" metricValueMin="1.05" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" unit="mm" value="11.0" valueMax="11.5" valueMin="10.5">10.5–11.5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746CD6DE1D52D7861A" blockId="11.[151,1437,631,2027]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
Head covered with yellowish-gray pruinosity, frontal vitta dark brown, gena and lunule reddish-brown; antenna reddish-yellow except for 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFC8C8746E39DE3652F6813A" box="[552,723,812,837]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
dark. Frons 0.1–0.11 of head width in male, 1.35–1.60 of head width in female, distinctly narrower than fronto-orbital plate; parafacial about 2.5 times as wide as 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFC8C8746997DE4A510D81F2" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
; facial carina low and indistinct; genal height about 2/3 of eye height; lower facial margin not or only slightly protruding; upper occiput with 1–2 rows of black hairs below postocular setae; 10 frontal setae; ocellar seta strong, longer than frontal seta; inner vertical setae crossed, about 0.6 of eye height or less, outer vertical seta indistinct; vibrissa inserted above lower margin of face. Antenna falling short of lower margin of face by more than antennal length, 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFC8C8746D73D91E52358662" box="[354,528,1028,1053]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
1.2–1.3 times as long as pedicel; pedicel with a strong seta, about as long as arista; arista plumose, aristal hairs 0.8–1.3 times as long as width of 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFC8C8746F8ED932546B863F" box="[927,1102,1063,1088]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
; palpus slender, about as long as prementum; prementum 4–5 times as long as wide.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746CD6D97551958490" blockId="11.[151,1437,631,2027]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
Thorax with yellowish-gray pruinosity, with 4 dark longitudinal vittae on dorsum, inner vitta on presutural scutum about 1/3 width of pruinose area between inner and outer vittae; postpronotal lobe reddish-brown; scutellum reddish-brown except dark base. Postpronotal lobe with 4–6 setae, the three strongest nearly arranged in a triangle; 2 presutural and 2 to 3 postsutural acrostichal setae, 4 presutural and 4 postsutural dorsocentral setae; 3 postsutural intra-alar setae; 4–5 supra-alar setae, the first one short; proepisternum and prosternum bare, prosternum about 2.5 times as long as wide; 5 pairs of marginal scutellar setae, 2–3 pairs of discal scutellar setae, apical scutellar setae crossed and strong, as long as scutellum, subapical setae reaching apex of apical setae, prebasal and lateral setae slightly shorter than apical setae; 3 katepisternal setae, 1 anepimeral seta. 
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746910D877551C87FB" box="[1281,1337,1389,1412]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Wing</emphasis>
hyaline, brownish, brown-clouded along crossveins r-m and dM-Cu; tegula and basicosta dark brown, at most brown; halter yellow except dark brown apex; calypters milk white, yellowish white on outer margin; lower calypter with short hairs on outer margin. Relative lengths of 2nd, 3rd and 4th costal sections approximately 3:7:4; costal spine as long as crossvein r-m; radial node with setulae dorsally and ventrally; cell r 
<subScript id="17D96F56FFC8C8746FD1DB1153FD8466" attach="left" box="[960,984,1547,1561]" fontSize="6" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">4+5</subScript>
closed at wing margin, bend of vein M nearly right-angled, with an appendix which is shorter than crossvein r-m. 
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746FF5DB3E543C8444" box="[996,1049,1572,1595]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Legs</emphasis>
dark brown except tibiae reddishyellow in middle part. Fore tibia with a row of short anterodorsal setae on upper 2/3 and 2 posterior setae; fore claws and pulvilli as long as or longer than 5th tarsomere; mid femur with 3–5 anterior setae, mid tibia with 3 strong anterodorsal, 1 posterodorsal, 2 posterior and 2 ventral setae (upper one short, lower one strong); hind tibia with 4 anterodorsal, 4 posterodorsal and 2 ventral setae, 2 preapical dorsal and 1 preapical anteroventral setae, posteroventral seta short.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746CD6DBE0548C85DC" blockId="11.[151,1437,631,2027]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
Abdomen long-ovate, reddish-brown in ground colour; tergites entirely covered with dense grayish-white to grayish-yellow pruinosity. Syntergite 1+2 medially excavated to posterior margin, without median marginal setae, with 1 lateral marginal seta and 3–4 lateral discal setae; tergite 3 with 2 median marginal setae, 1–2 lateral marginal setae and 1 lateral discal seta; tergite 4 with 2 median discal setae, a row of marginal setae and 1–2 lateral discal setae; tergite 5 with rows marginal and discal setae. 
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746ECFDA9053B185DC" box="[734,916,1930,1955]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Male terminalia</emphasis>
as in 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746FC7DA90543885DC" box="[982,1053,1930,1955]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–12" captionStartId="27.[151,264,1739,1762]" captionTargetBox="[265,1314,205,1697]" captionTargetId="figure@27.[256,1327,195,1710]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURES 1–12. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in caudal view. 1. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 2. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 3. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 4. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 5. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 6. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 7. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 8. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 9. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 10. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 11. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 12. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841934/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Figs 5</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746838DA91546285DC" box="[1065,1095,1931,1955]" captionStart="FIGURES 13–24" captionStartId="28.[151,264,1735,1758]" captionTargetBox="[275,1294,206,1693]" captionTargetId="figure@28.[249,1320,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="28" captionText="FIGURES 13–24. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in lateral view. 13. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 14. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 15. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 16. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 17. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 18. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 19. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 20. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 21. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 22. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 23. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 24. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841940/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">17</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C8746842DA91545785DC" box="[1107,1138,1931,1955]" captionStart="FIGURES 25–36" captionStartId="29.[151,264,1733,1756]" captionTargetBox="[270,1317,224,1702]" captionTargetId="figure@29.[255,1326,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="29" captionText="FIGURES 25–36. Estheria spp., phallic complexes in lateral view. 25. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 26. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 27. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 28. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 29. E. acuta (Portschinsky), speciumen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 30. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 31. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 32. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 33. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 34. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 35. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 36. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841948/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">29</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFC8C874686CDA9154B985DC" box="[1149,1180,1931,1955]" captionStart="FIGURES 37–52" captionStartId="30.[151,264,1665,1688]" captionTargetBox="[281,1301,213,1612]" captionTargetId="figure@30.[281,1301,193,1636]" captionTargetPageId="30" captionText="FIGURES 37–52. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. 37–48, 52. Sternite 5 in ventral view. 49–50. Epandrial complex in caudal (49) and lateral (50) views. 51. Phallic complex in lateral view. 37. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 38. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 39. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 40. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 41. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU); 42. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 43. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 44. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 45. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 46. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 47. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 48. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). 49–52. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841952/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">41</figureCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFC8C8746CD6DAB450D88594" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFC8C8746CD6DAB450D88594" blockId="11.[151,1437,631,2027]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFC8C8746CD6DAB4519585B8" bold="true" box="[199,432,1966,1991]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Material examined.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation id="3B35674EFFC8C8746DA6DAB450DC8594" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2242324059" collectingDate="1985-07-13" collectionCode="SYNU" collectorName="F. Wang" country="China" location="Shanxi" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" specimenCount="3" specimenCount-male="3" stateProvince="Shanxi">
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFC8C8746DA6DAB451DF85B8" box="[439,506,1966,1991]" name="China" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">China</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="4999A3F1FFC8C8746E19DAB4527F85B8" box="[520,602,1966,1991]" country="China" name="Shanxi" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Shanxi</collectingRegion>
: 
<specimenCount id="9D5BA69AFFC8C8746E74DAB5528385B8" box="[613,678,1967,1991]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="male">3 ♂♂</specimenCount>
, Hunyuan, Hunyuan Forestry Center, 
<collectingDate id="EFA7B23BFFC8C8746841DAB454FF85B8" box="[1104,1242,1966,1991]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="1985-07-13">
<date id="FFE34BD3FFC8C8746841DAB454FF85B8" box="[1104,1242,1966,1991]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" value="1985-07-13">13.VII.1985</date>
</collectingDate>
, M.- 
<collectorName id="26A808C5FFC8C874691EDAAA554E85B7" box="[1295,1387,1968,1992]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">F. Wang</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode id="ED4CF5D6FFC8C8746C8EDAC950D78594" box="[159,242,2003,2027]" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">SYNU</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFCFC8736CD6DD8D53A382CF" box="[199,902,151,176]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFCFC8736CD6DD8D53A382CF" blockId="12.[151,1436,151,320]" box="[199,902,151,176]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFCFC8736CD6DD8D514582CF" bold="true" box="[199,352,151,176]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Distribution.</emphasis>
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFCFC8736D76DD8D51C082CF" box="[359,485,151,176]" name="Azerbaijan" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Azerbaijan</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFCFC8736DE1DD8D521D82CF" box="[496,568,151,176]" name="China" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">China</collectingCountry>
*, 
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFCFC8736E5EDD82529782CF" box="[591,690,152,176]" name="Hungary" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Hungary</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFCFC8736EACDD8D530082CF" box="[701,805,151,176]" name="Romania" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Romania</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFCFC8736F21DD8D53A782CF" box="[816,898,151,176]" name="Turkey" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Turkey</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFCFC8736CD6DDA6511E833F" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFCFC8736CD6DDA6511E833F" blockId="12.[151,1436,151,320]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFCFC8736CD6DDA6511E82AA" bold="true" box="[199,315,188,213]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Remarks.</emphasis>
We did not examine the 
<typeStatus id="54E6D3B1FFCFC8736E41DDA6529782AA" box="[592,690,188,213]" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">holotype</typeStatus>
specimens of 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFCFC8736F42DDA7538A82AB" authorityName="Portschinsky" authorityYear="1881" box="[851,943,189,212]" class="Insecta" family="Pteromalidae" genus="Syntomocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFCFC8736F42DDA7538A82AB" box="[851,943,189,212]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">E. acuta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, but identified it using the key of 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFCFC873693BDDA651438287" author="Cerretti &amp; Tschorsnig" firstAuthor="Cerretti" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" pagination="271 - 286" refId="ref32552" refString="Cerretti, P. &amp; Tschorsnig, H. - P. (2012) Three new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from the Mediterranean, with a key to the European and Mediterranean species of the genus. Stuttgarter Beitrage zur Naturkunde A, Neue Serie, 5, 271 - 286." type="journal article" year="2012">Cerretti &amp; Tschorsnig (2012)</bibRefCitation>
. This species appears to be similar to 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFCFC8736F1CDDFB54BE8287" authority="(Robineau-Desvoidy)" authorityName="Robineau-Desvoidy" baseAuthorityName="Robineau-Desvoidy" baseAuthorityYear="1830" box="[781,1179,223,248]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="microcera">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFCFC8736F1CDDFB53BB8287" box="[781,926,225,248]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">E. microcera</emphasis>
(Robineau-Desvoidy)
</taxonomicName>
, but differs in having a wider frons, shorter prementum, 4 presutural and 4 postsutural dorsocentral setae, and reddish-yellow abdomen in ground colour.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>