<document id="C7772B34C307F31323B018F65A1D8B41" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5940995" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8c3d903d-6d82-45d1-a1c0-b29f5b97d0c1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157145393" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5940995" ID-ZooBank="8A6746BE-616B-4FEC-AA37-E274F8508255" _generate="added" approvalRequired="12" approvalRequired_for_matCits="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="11" checkinTime="1557922264577" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Zhang, Chun-Tian, Shima, Hiroshi, Liang, Hou-Can &amp; Li, He-Nan" docDate="2019" docId="03F4DC05FFD3C86E6C86D9BF50D78141" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4603.1.1.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4603 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Estheria maculipennis Herting 1968" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="18" masterDocId="FFCDA47DFFC3C87F6C11DD1A5025827F" masterDocTitle="Four new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from China and Nepal, with a review of the East Palearctic and Oriental species" masterLastPageNumber="38" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" updateTime="1643736677199" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="8F32B555695AD3DB4392ABE85FE57E7D" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="336CA46962CBAC3DBAE6319702083D7B">
<mods:title id="6E519DA2C59F9315C6C3575E791CAE6D">Four new species of Estheria Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Tachinidae) from China and Nepal, with a review of the East Palearctic and Oriental species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="1944FCD992202529DCF421012F9C0878" type="personal">
<mods:role id="6F35478F46A884C9FD4E742C07839BF4">
<mods:roleTerm id="215460005F26818A649380B30BDB98BB">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5CB80D262E33D94C175E4E928422385C">Zhang, Chun-Tian</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="2BC0947FC567C3C265DAEA8CABF161C2" type="personal">
<mods:role id="88B28B5FE0C8AF468B619689AB867127">
<mods:roleTerm id="2BEF7119218A9E6D74654C8F695DBEA4">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="354BAB7F4DB8BCF134999DFDC8D92D6B">Shima, Hiroshi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="2E054BF7D8621776ED2F7ED43B51EFF7" type="personal">
<mods:role id="DA22DB849182A3AE68579CBAA4A61CB4">
<mods:roleTerm id="0885D02F1045E6E6EBD13916831EAECE">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0B9DCE113D292A6CE25DE2DDA6D3916A">Liang, Hou-Can</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="8A156C3A4875DAA98E8581E48C2C69D2" type="personal">
<mods:role id="6B8C4314575B3A2C3A8737F656B4F52D">
<mods:roleTerm id="095BF13B458B4E3F84D941E0393063B4">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="49B5D1C90BFA4B5D34BD9238FFD0173D">Li, He-Nan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="CFB0EC33A38AB5F181E256A698E93AC3">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="B4F36DEB9AD78377D27123CE46E21DF3" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="4BF802C003959EB9FAE85B4B4230CC73">
<mods:title id="08637FF6FA29A1D513CDE1C29928BFA9">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="5D5913C9A2652C224240F1F9403D1FFD">
<mods:date id="708D2A513EE879CDDEA5990DD6985DB5">2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="448C054CD34B82D4512DE3228D3C1D6E" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="DA281C4BBD7C31F2E5DD66B4B3D8DCDF">2019-05-08</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="7BFE9854AA3BE4258F41E3D7B9E024C6" type="volume">
<mods:number id="26D8735179E1C7146A56C91247BF7E5E">4603</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="FAD7E436CD611134A99CE9B348BBBA14" type="issue">
<mods:number id="D19FCC195175ED4EB6EF8BAD6FD00363">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="DE45B1BC3DA2486FE8DF4CEB4A67D31F" unit="page">
<mods:start id="46DA5C5FFD0618A2608AA5B29E50D90A">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="D2FEA7948E6E5B0A78451FEF69AC9602">38</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="62A36613D2FC31C23A0BC90D73363E7E">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="F29190DFD5992BA90BEE43346321AA6A" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4603.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="4072F5A9E48181C53417C0940F2E7073" type="GBIF-Dataset">8c3d903d-6d82-45d1-a1c0-b29f5b97d0c1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="68884ED65690E80D5467DE0CA1252339" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="2EC5E375E5BF35FC6CE7ACD9A6EB52B8" type="Zenodo-Dep">2841928</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8F939EABA726746C680337244BB9CF34" type="ZooBank">8A6746BE-616B-4FEC-AA37-E274F8508255</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F4DC05FFD3C86E6C86D9BF50D78141" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5940995" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157145393" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5940995" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFD3C86E6C86D9BF50D78141" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F4DC05FFD3C86E6C86D9BF50D78141" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="18" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD3C86F6C86D9BF527F86C0" box="[151,602,1189,1215]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD3C86F6C86D9BF527F86C0" blockId="16.[151,602,1189,1249]" box="[151,602,1189,1215]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
<heading id="D0AADA7FFFD3C86F6C86D9BF527F86C0" bold="true" box="[151,602,1189,1215]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" reason="1">
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD3C86F6C86D9BF527F86C0" authority="Herting, 1968" authorityName="Herting" authorityYear="1968" box="[151,602,1189,1215]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculipennis">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6C86D9BF527F86C0" bold="true" box="[151,602,1189,1215]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6C86D9BF518D86C0" bold="true" box="[151,424,1189,1215]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Estheria maculipennis</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFD3C86F6DBED9BF527F86C0" author="Herting" box="[431,602,1189,1215]" firstAuthor="Herting" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" pagination="47 - 64" refId="ref32732" refString="Herting, B. (1968) Ergebnisse der zoologischen Forschungen von Dr. Z. Kaszab in der Mongolei. 137. Tachinidae (Diptera). Reichenbachia, 11, 47 - 64." type="journal article" year="1968">Herting, 1968</bibRefCitation>
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD3C86F6C86D9D2520A869E" box="[151,559,1224,1249]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD3C86F6C86D9D2520A869E" blockId="16.[151,602,1189,1249]" box="[151,559,1224,1249]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
(
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6C8ED9D250C2869F" box="[159,231,1224,1249]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–12" captionStartId="27.[151,264,1739,1762]" captionTargetBox="[265,1314,205,1697]" captionTargetId="figure@27.[256,1327,195,1710]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURES 1–12. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in caudal view. 1. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 2. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 3. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 4. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 5. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 6. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 7. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 8. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 9. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 10. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 11. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 12. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841934/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Figs 9</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6CE2D9D25134869F" box="[243,273,1224,1248]" captionStart="FIGURES 13–24" captionStartId="28.[151,264,1735,1758]" captionTargetBox="[275,1294,206,1693]" captionTargetId="figure@28.[249,1320,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="28" captionText="FIGURES 13–24. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in lateral view. 13. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 14. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 15. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 16. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 17. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 18. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 19. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 20. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 21. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 22. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 23. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 24. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841940/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">21</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6D0CD9D2511E869F" box="[285,315,1224,1248]" captionStart="FIGURES 25–36" captionStartId="29.[151,264,1733,1756]" captionTargetBox="[270,1317,224,1702]" captionTargetId="figure@29.[255,1326,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="29" captionText="FIGURES 25–36. Estheria spp., phallic complexes in lateral view. 25. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 26. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 27. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 28. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 29. E. acuta (Portschinsky), speciumen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 30. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 31. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 32. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 33. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 34. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 35. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 36. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841948/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">33</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6D56D9D25140869E" box="[327,357,1224,1249]" captionStart="FIGURES 37–52" captionStartId="30.[151,264,1665,1688]" captionTargetBox="[281,1301,213,1612]" captionTargetId="figure@30.[281,1301,193,1636]" captionTargetPageId="30" captionText="FIGURES 37–52. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. 37–48, 52. Sternite 5 in ventral view. 49–50. Epandrial complex in caudal (49) and lateral (50) views. 51. Phallic complex in lateral view. 37. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 38. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 39. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 40. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 41. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU); 42. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 43. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 44. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 45. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 46. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 47. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 48. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). 49–52. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841952/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">45</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6D60D9D251AA869E" box="[369,399,1224,1249]" captionStart="FIGURES 53–64" captionStartId="31.[151,264,1742,1765]" captionTargetBox="[319,1255,193,1713]" captionTargetId="figure@31.[319,1255,193,1713]" captionTargetPageId="31" captionText="FIGURES 53–64. Estheria spp., male heads in anterior view. 53. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 54. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 55. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 56. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 57. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 58. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 59. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 60. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 61. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 62. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 63. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 64. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841962/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">61</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6D8AD9D2519C869F" box="[411,441,1224,1248]" captionStart="FIGURES 83–91" captionStartId="34.[151,264,1795,1818]" captionTargetBox="[270,1275,215,1733]" captionTargetId="figure@34.[234,1351,193,1773]" captionTargetPageId="34" captionText="FIGURES 83–91. Estheria spp., male heads in lateral view. 83. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 84. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 85. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 86. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 87. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 88. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 89. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 90. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS). 91. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars: 0.5 mm (Figs 87–89); 1 mm (Figs 90–91)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841988/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">87</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6DD7D9D251D7869F" box="[454,498,1224,1248]" captionStart="FIGURES 92–106" captionStartId="35.[151,264,1719,1742]" captionTargetBox="[267,1298,254,1691]" captionTargetId="figure@35.[258,1309,211,1697]" captionTargetPageId="35" captionText="FIGURES 92–106. Estheria spp., male habitus in dorsal (92–104) and lateral (106) view; head in anterior view (105). 92. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 93. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 94. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 95. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 96. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 97. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden- Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 98. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 99. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 100. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 101. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 102. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 103. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS). 104–106. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841996/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">100</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD3C86F6DECD9D25202869E" box="[509,551,1224,1249]" captionStart="FIGURES 107–118" captionStartId="36.[151,264,1749,1772]" captionTargetBox="[239,1323,246,1694]" captionTargetId="figure@36.[239,1341,193,1751]" captionTargetPageId="36" captionText="FIGURES 107–118. Estheria spp., male habitus in lateral view. 107. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Solukhumbu District, Nepal (BLKU). 108. E. prostata sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 109. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Pianma, Yakou, Lushui, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 110. E. wangi sp. nov., holotype (SYNU). 111. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 112. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 113. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 114. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 115. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 116. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Baishilazi, Kuandian, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 117. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Alashanzuo Qi, Helan Mountain, Halawu, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 118. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Briançon, Nevache, France (SMNS)." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2842000/files/figure.png" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">115</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD3C86F6C86D80A53A0871C" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD3C86F6C86D80A53A0871C" blockId="16.[151,1436,1296,1379]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD3C86F6C86D80A523C8759" authority="Herting, 1968" authorityName="Herting" authorityYear="1968" box="[151,537,1296,1318]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculipennis">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6C86D80A51588759" box="[151,381,1296,1318]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Estheria maculipennis</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFD3C86F6D96D80A523C8759" author="Herting" box="[391,537,1296,1318]" firstAuthor="Herting" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" pagination="47 - 64" refId="ref32732" refString="Herting, B. (1968) Ergebnisse der zoologischen Forschungen von Dr. Z. Kaszab in der Mongolei. 137. Tachinidae (Diptera). Reichenbachia, 11, 47 - 64." type="journal article" year="1968">Herting, 1968</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
, 11: 61. Type locality: 
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFD3C86F6F03D80A53528759" box="[786,887,1296,1318]" name="Mongolia" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Mongolia</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="4999A3F1FFD3C86F6F95D80A543D8759" box="[900,1048,1296,1318]" country="Mongolia" name="Hentiy" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Hentiy Aimag</collectingRegion>
[as “Chentej aimak”], Čandagan tal, Chentej aimak. 
<typeStatus id="54E6D3B1FFD3C86F6D60D83551EA873A" box="[369,463,1327,1349]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Holotype</typeStatus>
<specimenCount id="9D5BA69AFFD3C86F6DCAD82A51CB873A" box="[475,494,1328,1349]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" type="male">♂</specimenCount>
(
<collectionCode id="ED4CF5D6FFD3C86F6E11D8355274873A" box="[512,593,1327,1349]" country="Hungary" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34991" name="Hungarian Natural History Museum (Termeszettudomanyi Muzeum)" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">HNHM</collectionCode>
) not examined. References: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFD3C86F6F97D83554D5873A" author="Herting &amp; Dely-Draskovits" box="[902,1264,1327,1349]" firstAuthor="Herting" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" pagination="118 - 458" refId="ref32837" refString="Herting, B. &amp; Dely-Draskovits, A. (1993) Family Tachinidae. In: Soos, A. &amp; Papp, L. (Eds.), Catalog of Palaearctic Diptera. Fol. 13. Anthomyiidae-Tachinidae. Hungarian Natural HistoryMuseum, Budapest, pp. 118 - 458." type="book chapter" year="1993">Herting &amp; Dely-Draskovits (1993</bibRefCitation>
: 364; Palearctic catalog); 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFD3C86F6D37D85751C1871C" author="Zhang" box="[294,484,1357,1379]" etAl="et al." firstAuthor="Zhang" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" pagination="136 - 142" refId="ref34325" refString="Zhang, C. - T., Cui, L., Zheng, G., Hou, P. &amp; Xu, W. - J. (2013) Checklist of subfamily Dexiinae (Diptera, Tachinidae) from the National Zoological Museum of China, Part 1. Journal of Shenyang Normal University (Natural Science), 31, 136 - 142." type="journal article" year="2013">
Zhang 
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6D7DD8545185871C" box="[364,416,1357,1379]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">et al.</emphasis>
(2013
</bibRefCitation>
: 139; as “ 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD3C86F6E59D8545294871C" authorityName="Mesnil" authorityYear="1967" box="[584,689,1357,1379]" class="Insecta" family="Tachinidae" genus="Estheria" kingdom="Animalia" order="Diptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alticola">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6E59D8545294871C" box="[584,689,1357,1379]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">E. alticola</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
”, misidentification).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD3C86F6C86D88A50F3846B" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD3C86F6C86D88A50F3846B" blockId="16.[151,1436,1424,2025]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6C86D88A513487D6" bold="true" box="[151,273,1424,1449]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
Prementum 6–7 times as long as wide, 3 presutural and 4 postsutural dorsocentral setae, postpronum and scutellum reddish-yellow at least apically, wing brown to dark clouded along crossvein r-m, tegula dark brown, basicosta brown, lower calypter with short fringe on outer margin, tergites 3 and 4 each with a pair of laterodiscal setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD3C86E6CD6DB3A523D8019" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="18" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD3C86F6CD6DB3A52958447" blockId="16.[151,1436,1424,2025]" box="[199,688,1568,1593]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6CD6DB3A51518446" bold="true" box="[199,372,1568,1593]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Redescription.</emphasis>
Body length: 8.0–12.0 mm.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD3C86F6CD6DB5E54B18492" blockId="16.[151,1436,1424,2025]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
Head. Pedicel, base of 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD3C86F6DC6DB5F52A68422" box="[471,643,1604,1629]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
and palpus reddish-yellow. Frons 1/5–1/6 as wide as eye in male, 1.5 times as wide as eye in female; width of parafacial at antennal base about 1/2 of eye width in male and 3/ 
<quantity id="4CA5C0F6FFD3C86F697FDB7255B984FE" box="[1390,1436,1640,1665]" metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.016" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" unit="in" value="4.0">4 in</quantity>
female; genal height about 1/2–3/5 of eye height in male and 4/ 
<quantity id="4CA5C0F6FFD3C86F6F75DB9653AA84DA" box="[868,911,1676,1701]" metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.27" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" unit="in" value="5.0">5 in</quantity>
female. Antenna falling short of lower margin of face by more than 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD3C86F6D8CDBAA526E84B6" box="[413,587,1712,1737]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
length; 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD3C86F6EA4DBAA534784B6" box="[693,866,1712,1737]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
1.2–1.5 times as long as pedicel; arista plumose, aristal hairs about as long as width 1 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD3C86F6E3ADBCF52FF8492" box="[555,730,1748,1773]" pageId="16" pageNumber="17" rank="subSpecies" subSpecies="flagellomere">st flagellomere</taxonomicName>
; prementum 6–7 times as long as wide.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD3C86E6CD6DBE2557883AA" blockId="16.[151,1436,1424,2025]" lastBlockId="17.[151,1437,151,830]" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="18" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">
Thorax black in ground colour, with yellowish-gray or brownish pruinosity; postpronum and apex of scutellum reddish-yellow or yellow, dorsum with 4 longitudinal black vittae, inner vitta about 1/4 width of pruinose area between inner and outer vittae in male, narrower in female. Postpronotom with 3 setae arranged in a triangle and 1–2 weak inner setae; 2 presutural and 2 postsutural acrostichal setae, 3 presutural and 4 postsutural dorsocentral setae, 3 postsutural intra-alar setae; prealar setae weak; 3 katepisternal setae; scutellum with 3 pairs of strong marginal setae, apical scutellar setae crossed. 
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD3C86F6EB9DAB752C585BB" box="[680,736,1965,1988]" italics="true" pageId="16" pageNumber="17">Wing</emphasis>
brown to dark clouded along crossvein r-m, portion beyond dM-Cu brownish. Tegula dark brown, basicosta and halter brown; calypters whitish, lower calypter with short fringe on outer margin. Costal spine weak, as long as crossvein r-m, relative lengths of 2nd, 3rd and 4th costal sectors approximately 1:2:1; base of R 
<subScript id="17D96F56FFD2C86E6E58DDD1524482A6" attach="left" box="[585,609,203,217]" fontSize="6" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">4+5</subScript>
with setulae dorsally and ventrally; section of M between crossveins r-m and dM-Cu about twice as long as section between dM-Cu and bend; vein M from dM-Cu crossvein to bend about as long as distance between bend and wing margin; M at bend with an appendage shorter than crossvein r-m; wing cell r 
<subScript id="17D96F56FFD2C86E6CC3DC2350CF8338" attach="left" box="[210,234,313,327]" fontSize="6" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">4+5</subScript>
closed at margin or with a petiole at most 0.20 times as long as postangular section of M. 
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD2C86E6917DC36551E833C" box="[1286,1339,300,323]" italics="true" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Legs</emphasis>
with all tibiae and ventral apices of femora reddish-yellow or yellow, femora brown to dark in male and entirely reddishyellow in female. Fore tibia with a row of anterodorsal setae and 2 posterior setae; mid femur with 3–4 anterior setae, mid tibia with 3 anterodorsal, 3 posterodorsal and 2 ventral setae; hind tibia with 3 anterodorsal, 5 posterodorsal and 3 ventral setae, 2 preapical dorsal setae. Male claws and pulvilli longer than 5th tarsomere.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD2C86E6CD6DCFB523D8019" blockId="17.[151,1437,151,830]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">
Abdomen dark brown in ground colour in male, wholly covered with pruinosity, with irregular markings. Syntergite 1+2 excavated to posterior margin, without median marginal setae, with 1 lateral marginal seta, 2–3 lateral discal setae; tergites 3 and 4 each with 2 median discal setae and a pair of lateral discal setae. 
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD2C86E6973DF3351298019" italics="true" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Male terminalia</emphasis>
as in 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD2C86E6D5CDF5751B08019" box="[333,405,589,614]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–12" captionStartId="27.[151,264,1739,1762]" captionTargetBox="[265,1314,205,1697]" captionTargetId="figure@27.[256,1327,195,1710]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURES 1–12. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in caudal view. 1. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 2. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 3. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 4. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 5. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 6. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 7. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 8. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 9. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 10. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 11. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 12. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841934/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Figs 9</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD2C86E6DB0DF54519A8019" box="[417,447,590,614]" captionStart="FIGURES 13–24" captionStartId="28.[151,264,1735,1758]" captionTargetBox="[275,1294,206,1693]" captionTargetId="figure@28.[249,1320,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="28" captionText="FIGURES 13–24. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. in lateral view. 13. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 14. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 15. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 16. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 17. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 18. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 19. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 20. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 21. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 22. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 23. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 24. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841940/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">21</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD2C86E6DDADF5451CC8019" box="[459,489,590,614]" captionStart="FIGURES 25–36" captionStartId="29.[151,264,1733,1756]" captionTargetBox="[270,1317,224,1702]" captionTargetId="figure@29.[255,1326,193,1708]" captionTargetPageId="29" captionText="FIGURES 25–36. Estheria spp., phallic complexes in lateral view. 25. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 26. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 27. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 28. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 29. E. acuta (Portschinsky), speciumen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU). 30. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 31. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 32. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 33. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 34. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 35. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 36. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841948/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">33</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation id="13667196FFD2C86E6DE4DF5752318019" box="[501,532,589,614]" captionStart="FIGURES 37–52" captionStartId="30.[151,264,1665,1688]" captionTargetBox="[281,1301,213,1612]" captionTargetId="figure@30.[281,1301,193,1636]" captionTargetPageId="30" captionText="FIGURES 37–52. Male terminalia of Estheria spp. 37–48, 52. Sternite 5 in ventral view. 49–50. Epandrial complex in caudal (49) and lateral (50) views. 51. Phallic complex in lateral view. 37. E. hirtinerva sp. nov., paratype from Geka-Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 38. E. prostata sp. nov., paratype from Gezan, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 39. E. tibetensis sp. nov., paratype from Geka- Echu Mountains, Daocheng, Sichuan, China (SYNU). 40. E. wangi sp. nov., paratype from Napahai wetland, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China (SYNU). 41. E. acuta (Portschinsky), specimen from Hunyuan, Shanxi, China (SYNU); 42. E. cristata (Meigen), specimen from Baden-Willingen, Germany (SMNS). 43. E. decolor (Pandellé), specimen from Dongsheng, Inner Mongolia, China (SYNU). 44. E. flavipennis Herting, specimen from Xi Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 45. E. maculipennis Herting, specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). 46. E. magna (Baranov), specimen from Mt. Fenghuang, Fengcheng, Liaoning, China (SYNU). 47. E. pallicornis (Loew), specimen from Shule, Xinjiang, China (GSFPM). 48. E. petiolata (Bonsdorff), specimen from Kanas Lake, Burqin, Xinjiang, China (SEMCAS). 49–52. E. picta (Meigen), specimen from Dong Ujimqin Qi, Inner Mongolia, China (IZCAS). Scale bars = 0.2 mm." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/2841952/files/figure.png" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">45</figureCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD2C86E6CD6DF6B512780D1" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD2C86E6CD6DF6B512780D1" blockId="17.[151,1437,151,830]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD2C86E6CD6DF6B519780F5" bold="true" box="[199,434,625,650]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Material examined.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation id="3B35674EFFD2C86E6DABDF6B50DB80D1" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2242324131" collectingDate="1971-08-22" collectionCode="IZCAS" collectorName="Y. - S. Shi" country="China" location="Dong Ujimqin Qi" municipality="Wulagai" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" specimenCount="3" specimenCount-male="3" stateProvince="Inner Mongolia">
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFD2C86E6DABDF6B51D880F5" box="[442,509,625,650]" name="China" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">China</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="4999A3F1FFD2C86E6E1DDF6852E480F5" box="[524,705,625,650]" country="China" name="Nei Mongol" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Inner Mongolia</collectingRegion>
: 
<specimenCount id="9D5BA69AFFD2C86E6EDCDF68533480F6" box="[717,785,626,650]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" type="male">3 ♂♂</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingMunicipality id="6B86F769FFD2C86E6F0FDF6B535A80F5" box="[798,895,625,650]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Wulagai</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location id="8E823BC8FFD2C86E6F9ADF68547280F5" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F4DC05FFD3C86E6C86D9BF50D78141:8E823BC8FFD2C86E6F9ADF68547280F5" box="[907,1111,625,650]" country="China" municipality="Wulagai" name="Dong Ujimqin Qi" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" stateProvince="Inner Mongolia">Dong Ujimqin Qi</location>
, 
<collectingDate id="EFA7B23BFFD2C86E6872DF6854DD80F5" box="[1123,1272,626,650]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" value="1971-08-22">
<date id="FFE34BD3FFD2C86E6872DF6854DD80F5" box="[1123,1272,626,650]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" value="1971-08-22">22.VIII.1971</date>
</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName id="26A808C5FFD2C86E6914DF68554F80F5" box="[1285,1386,625,650]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Y.-S. Shi</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode id="ED4CF5D6FFD2C86E6C8EDF8C50D380D1" box="[159,246,662,686]" country="China" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/crjh-4ne1" name="Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">IZCAS</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD2C86E6CD6DFA353EA80AD" box="[199,975,697,722]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD2C86E6CD6DFA353EA80AD" blockId="17.[151,1437,151,830]" box="[199,975,697,722]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD2C86E6CD6DFA3514580AE" bold="true" box="[199,352,697,722]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Distribution.</emphasis>
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFD2C86E6D76DFA3518F80AD" box="[359,426,697,722]" name="China" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">China</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion id="4999A3F1FFD2C86E6DA8DFA0524B80AD" box="[441,622,697,722]" country="China" name="Nei Mongol" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Inner Mongolia</collectingRegion>
), 
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFD2C86E6E90DFA352D480AD" box="[641,753,697,722]" name="Mongolia" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Mongolia</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry id="F34A2D83FFD2C86E6EEADFA3536380AD" box="[763,838,697,722]" name="Russia" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Russia</collectingCountry>
(E Siberia).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3473E98FFD2C86E6CD6DFC750D78141" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="8BE26D13FFD2C86E6CD6DFC750D78141" blockId="17.[151,1437,151,830]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD2C86E6CD6DFC7511E8089" bold="true" box="[199,315,733,758]" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">Remarks.</emphasis>
We identified this species based on 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCC10E2FFD2C86E6ECEDFC753BE8089" author="Herting's" box="[735,923,733,758]" firstAuthor="Herting's" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" pagination="47 - 64" refId="ref32732" refString="Herting, B. (1968) Ergebnisse der zoologischen Forschungen von Dr. Z. Kaszab in der Mongolei. 137. Tachinidae (Diptera). Reichenbachia, 11, 47 - 64." type="journal article" year="1968">Herting’s (1968)</bibRefCitation>
original description. It is similar to 
<taxonomicName id="4C5D1690FFD2C86E692DDFC451188165" authority="(Portschinsky)" authorityName="Portschinsky" baseAuthorityName="Portschinsky" class="Insecta" family="Pteromalidae" genus="Syntomocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acuta">
<emphasis id="B929B101FFD2C86E692DDFC455B9808A" box="[1340,1436,734,757]" italics="true" pageId="17" pageNumber="18">E. acuta</emphasis>
(Portschinsky)
</taxonomicName>
, but differs in having narrower frons, longer prementum, and abdomen dark brown in ground colour in male.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>