<document id="F46AC1231C5A9ADAAE05A2CF27C57108" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84623C74FDAC6FDA4F72DC079" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Cratichneumon unificatus TERESHKIN" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="1373" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E13D395D963AD1F1159CCC3EA" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB77B5D745C552A26297AEC441">
<mods:title id="F639024955E65348C983C65140B7235B">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D112533D818377D8FC077F66" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766545C393E6E4319189B0380">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB62CD0044973107F772DB1180">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A7681851ECC8E633D64004C2">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95EE8DFBE50FDE8759EE3FF0E">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44DCF90DFF547AACF23117247" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB5DBDD3E903B9846E4F14080">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B0C053D2C7019FF41C7E127F">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF31C50B73A2821606C264FC6">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500C63DEC49481CA68F542551D">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA054559201D39651F21D789B5C1558" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB2741BAE3207E30271D234266">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02BB707A9CE92FD21F8B72E96" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA8FCC975675EA8C6133D1DCD">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D61572829316AD8E752499B4AC" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF5BA29C09298659D769B2850">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA8C4CEED63632C999184EBA2" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21FD334FB8EBE9068B32A7301">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16F79052BCD3A67FA6020948D">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F5803A7F75D2C26AF5A8B124FE">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568E4EBE3C5BF578DF352CC3D3" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2AB8623E9D9C7CCBB3EA2AC1" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB4AD9D468CE754B95AC169A8" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F84623C74FDAC6FDA4F72DC079" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84623C74FDAC6FDA4F72DC079" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84623C74FDAC6FDA4F72DC079" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="1373" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">
<subSubSection id="C34665654623C740DAC6FDA4F4E3C41B" box="[178,691,600,622]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4623C740DAC6FDA4F4E3C41B" blockId="55.[178,691,600,622]" box="[178,691,600,622]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">
<heading id="D0AB81824623C740DAC6FDA4F4E3C41B" box="[178,691,600,622]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4623C740DAC6FDA4F4E3C41B" bold="true" box="[178,691,600,622]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4623C740DAC6FDA4F416C419" authority="TERESHKIN" authorityName="TERESHKIN" box="[178,582,600,622]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cratichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="unificatus">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4623C740DAC6FDA4F795C41B" bold="true" box="[178,453,600,622]" italics="true" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">Cratichneumon unificatus</emphasis>
TERESHKIN
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 13)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C34665654623C740DAC6FD83F434C521" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4623C740DAC6FD83F773C4CF" blockId="55.[178,891,640,663]" lastBlockId="55.[178,291,677,698]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4623C740DAC6FD83F410C4E6" authority="TERESHKIN 2003" authorityName="TERESHKIN" authorityYear="2003" box="[178,576,639,659]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cratichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="unificatus">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4623C740DAC6FD83F7CDC4E6" box="[178,413,639,659]" italics="true" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">Cratichneumon unificatus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F4623C740DBD0FD83F410C4E6" author="TERESHKIN A" box="[420,576,639,659]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" pagination="594 - 602" refId="ref143842" refString="TERESHKIN A. M. (2003): Ichneumon flies of the genus Cratichneumon (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) of forest zone. 1. Taxonomic notes. Description of Cratichneumon unificatus sp. n. - Zool. Journ. 82 (5): 594 - 602." type="journal article" year="2003">TERESHKIN 2003</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Zool. Journ. 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4623C740D8BCFD83F48FC4E6" bold="true" box="[712,735,639,659]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">82</emphasis>
(5): 601-602, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD674623C740D916FD7FF53EC4ED" box="[866,878,643,664]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4623C740DAC6FD36F434C521" blockId="55.[178,1085,713,852]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">F l a g e l l u m: Filiform, with 23 segments, strongly thickened to the apex, practically not narrowed beyond middle; first segment from lateral only 1,2 times longer than width at apex, already segment 3 square from lateral, from segment 13 slightly flattened ventrally; white annulus on segments 6-11(12). Flagellum 1,7 times shorter than the front wing and 2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C34665654623C74FDAC6FC98F72DC079" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="1373" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4623C740DAC6FC98F7C4C38B" blockId="55.[178,1085,868,1534]" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">H e a d: Head contour from front slightly narrowed downwards, only just transversal, only 1,1 times wider than length; genae long, from front 2,7 times shorter height of eye; head contour from above stout, transversal, 1,5 times wider than length, slightly roundly narrowed backwards behind eyes; front surface from side strongly convex, forming with frontal surface almost right angle. Vertex from lateral roundly sloping to occipital carina; temples long, 1,5 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, from side strongly broadened toward mandible base; occipital carina sharp all round, from above deeply impressed but not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina only just visible from lateral at lower part, meeting with occipital carina before mandible base; malar space 1,3 times longer than the mandible base width; mandibles long and wide, evenly narrowed from base to apex, upper tooth considerably longer than lower, teeth situated in the same plane and separated by slight notch; clypeus slightly convex, transverse, 2,6 times wider than length, with straight and sharp front margin and oblique lateral margins, separated from face by slight impression; clypeal foveae small, deep, round; labrum not protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face slightly elevated, triangular, in middle equal to lateral fields; antennal cavities deeply impressed, reach borders of eyes and far not reach level of front ocellus, laterally above antennal fossae without tubercles and with sharp tooth between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae slightly elevated above face surface; ocelli small, flat, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,5 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle only just elevated. Surface of clypeus smooth, shining with sparse superficial punctures, frons between front ocellus and antennal cavities densely superficially-punctured; temples strongly shining with sparse punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4623C74FDAC6F9F2F74BC48A" blockId="55.[178,1085,1549,1600]" lastBlockId="56.[178,1085,219,767]" lastPageId="56" lastPageNumber="1373" pageId="55" pageNumber="1372">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long with rounded front margin (from above); transverse furrow of pronotum very shallow, not interrupted by keel; pronotal ridge not swol- len; epomiae sharp; pronotal base gradually curved with moderately acute apex. Mesonotum only just convex, wider than length, laterally bordered by deep groove; notauli practically absent; axillary tongue not developed; middle lobe of mesonotum rather densely superficially-punctured, without microsculpture, lateral lobes with more sparse, smoothed punctures; subalarum high, thin, sharp; speculum shining, smoothly wrinklypunctured; area of mesopleural fovea broadly, but not deeply impressed; mesopleural suture straight, deep, practically not interrupted by ribs; mesopleurae longitudinally wrinkly-punctured without microsculpture; mesopleurae at bottom without sharp bend; sternauli in form of deep impression in front third; scutellum flat, smooth, shining, with sparse shallow punctures, laterally not carinated; postscutellum strongly shining. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Length of horizontal part of propodeum equal to length of area posteromedia in middle; carinae of propodeum sharp, with exception of costulae and slightly expressed carina, limiting basal area from behind; area superomedia elongated, narrowed anteriad; basal area long with strong longitudinal wrinkles, crossing basal furrow of propodeum; spiracles of propodeum long, slit-shaped; area posteroexterna and third pleural area not divided by distinct keel. Surface of propodeum wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture and with rough sculpture, metapleurae densely punctured by big punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE462CC74FDAC6FCECF25BC550" blockId="56.[178,1035,783,805]" box="[178,1035,783,805]" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373">L e g s: Strong; hind coxae with slight scopa. Claws thin, in middle sharply curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE462CC74FDAC6FCC9F4F5C5A8" blockId="56.[178,1085,820,989]" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, asymmetrical, external vein of apex shorter than internal; stigma light; radial cell broad, radius almost straight, curved only at apex; nervulus very slightly postfurcal; ramulus only just marked; all veins dark; external branches of medial and cubital veins unsclerotized in form of slight trace; radius of hind wing strongly unsclerotized; membrane of wing hyaline. Front wing в 1,8 times longer than length of flagellum and 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE462CC74FDAC6FC10F772C37C" blockId="56.[178,1086,1004,1289]" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373">A b d o m e n:Oxypygous, from above longish-oval, apical tergites not hidden; second tergite transversal, at apex 1,4 times wider than length; sheath of ovipositor only just visible protrude. First tergite from lateral with gradual bend between petiolus and postpetiolus; petiolus not flattened at base, from lateral sharply bordered by carinae and indistinctly sculpturated between them by smoothed ribs; from above petiolus gradually broadened to triangle postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus expressed slightly, its surface slightly-wrinkled, with some superficial punctures at apex and at lateral corners. Gastrocoeli superficial, thyridia only just marked; lunulae in form of only just visible trace; tergites 2-3 densely punctured, without microsculpture. Hypopygium compressed from sides.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE462CC74FDAC6FAE5F58FC3B4" blockId="56.[178,1085,1305,1473]" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373">
C o l o r a t i o n: Scapus and flagellum to white annulus light-ferruginous. Head and thorax entirely black. Scutellum entirely pale-yellow. Apex of postpetiolus, tergites 2-3 completely, 4th at base and sternites light-ferruginous; petiolus and tergite 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B462CC74FD9DBFAAFF587C31C" box="[943,983,1363,1385]" metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.016" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373" unit="in" value="4.0">4 in</quantity>
most part darkened, tergites 5-7 completely black. All legs, including coxae, of basic color; hind femora at apex and hind tibiae at apex and at base darkened; tibiae of all legs from outside with large white spots; spot on hind tibiae occupy almost third of its length.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE462CC74FDAC6FA2CF579C393" blockId="56.[178,809,1488,1510]" box="[178,809,1488,1510]" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373">
S i z e: Body length: 5,5; flagellum: 2,8; front wing: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B462CC74FD8A1FA2CF575C393" box="[725,805,1488,1510]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.7" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373" unit="mm" value="4.7">4,7 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE462CC74FDAC6FA0AF72DC079" blockId="56.[178,381,1526,1548]" box="[178,381,1526,1548]" pageId="56" pageNumber="1373">M a l e. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>