<document id="DA3D0ED2B66A0E7B465DE1CBE8CC8B29" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846B0C7D2DAC6FC06F4CAC033" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Hirtolabus alienoris HEINRICH" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="165" lastPageNumber="1482" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E1340954463AD1EB35A2BC3A0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB7726D7D8C552A3C09449C40B">
<mods:title id="F6390249557553D5C983C7F343502311">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D18153A08183767AFFE07F2C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766C75CA43E6E42BB1B7C03CA">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB625E00D997310655713C11CA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A7FB18CCECC8E791D5A70488">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95E7BDF2350FDE9D79D04FF44">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44D5C9042F547AB6D20F6720D" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB548DDA3903B99E4E71640CA">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B053534FC7019E561F991235">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF38F502A3A2820C26FC14F8C">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500CF0DE599481CBCAF6A55557">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA054559292D30B51F21CDA98BB1512" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB27D2BA7E207E31851EC4422C">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02B240734CE92FC83FB502EDC" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA86FC9E8675EA96410DA1D87">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D615E1820E16AD8FD7277EB4E6" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF529295D9298643F757C281A">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA857CE7063632D3B9263EBE8" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21F4034668EBE91CAB0CD734B">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16FEA05B6CD3A665863C794C7">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F580A97FE8D2C26B57AB5624B4">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568EDDBEA15BF5797D36CBC399" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2A2B62A39D9C7D69B00D2A8B" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB43E9DDB8CE7551B592669E2" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F846B0C7D2DAC6FC06F4CAC033" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846B0C7D2DAC6FC06F4CAC033" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846B0C7D2DAC6FC06F4CAC033" lastPageId="165" lastPageNumber="1482" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">
<subSubSection id="C346656546B0C7D3DAC6FC06F431C265" box="[178,609,1018,1040]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B0C7D3DAC6FC06F431C265" blockId="164.[178,609,1018,1040]" box="[178,609,1018,1040]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">
<heading id="D0AB818246B0C7D3DAC6FC06F431C265" box="[178,609,1018,1040]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46B0C7D3DAC6FC06F431C265" bold="true" box="[178,609,1018,1040]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D46B0C7D3DAC6FC06F7A6C27B" authority="HEINRICH" authorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,502,1018,1040]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hirtolabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alienoris">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46B0C7D3DAC6FC06F7D3C265" bold="true" box="[178,387,1018,1040]" italics="true" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">Hirtolabus alienoris</emphasis>
HEINRICH
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 39)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C346656546B0C7D3DAC6FBDDF4C4C2EB" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B0C7D3DAC6FBDDF773C229" blockId="164.[178,830,1057,1081]" lastBlockId="164.[178,291,1095,1116]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D46B0C7D3DAC6FBDDF7AFC240" authority="HEINRICH 1974" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1974" box="[178,511,1057,1077]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hirtolabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alienoris">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46B0C7D3DAC6FBDDF73AC240" box="[178,362,1057,1077]" italics="true" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">Hirtolabus alienoris</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F46B0C7D3DB04FBDDF7AFC240" author="HEINRICH G" box="[368,511,1057,1077]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" pagination="103 - 197" refId="ref142818" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1974): Burmesische Ichneumoninae IX. Tribus Platylabini. - Annales Zoologici Wars. 32, 8: 103 - 197." type="journal article" year="1974">HEINRICH 1974</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ann. Zool. Wars. 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46B0C7D3D8C3FBDDF49EC240" bold="true" box="[695,718,1057,1077]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">32</emphasis>
: 139, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD6746B0C7D3D973FBD9F543C24F" box="[775,787,1061,1082]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B0C7D3DAC6FB90F4C4C2EB" blockId="164.[178,1085,1131,1183]" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">F l a g e l l u m: Not widened beyond middle, with white annulus; basal segments long, first segment 5 times longer than width at apex.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C346656546B0C7D2DAC6FB53F4CAC033" lastPageId="165" lastPageNumber="1482" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B0C7D2DAC6FB53F467C7F6" blockId="164.[178,1085,1198,1600]" lastBlockId="165.[178,1085,219,387]" lastPageId="165" lastPageNumber="1482" pageId="164" pageNumber="1481">H e a d: Head contour from front narrowed downwards, 1,3 wider than height; internal margins of eyes parallel; genae long, 4 times shorter than height of eye; head contour from above transversal, 1,9 times wider than length. Vertex behind hind ocelli from lateral roundly slanting to occipital carina; temples, from above roundly narrowed behind eyes, moderately long, 1,5 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye in middle, from side approximately parallel to hind margin of an eye, widened below middle; occipital carina gradually impressed to ocelli, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, not high, not meeting with hypostomal carina, sharply abrupt at level of genae; hypostomal carina from mandible base to level of occipital carina lamelliform, between abscissula and gena with distinct impression; malar space approximately equal to mandible base width; mandibles gradually narrowed behind base to apex; clypeus convex, transversal, with straight front margin and oblique lateral ones with rounded corners, distinctly separated from face by impression; clypeal foveae of moderate size, deep; labrum not protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face slightly but distinctly elevated; antennal cavities of not large size, deep, laterally not reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, without rounded tubercles laterally and with strong tooth between antennal fossae; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,3 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle slightly elevated. Clypeus and middle field of face with dense punctures, shining; lateral fields also with very dense punctures, frons very densely wrinkly-punctured.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B1C7D2DAC6FE6FF5BBC508" blockId="165.[178,1086,402,893]" pageId="165" pageNumber="1482">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum moderately long, transverse furrow shallow. Mesonotum moderately convex, some wider than length, notauli marked in front third, slightly expressed; surface of mesonotum with very dense rough punctures, punctures almost merged, slightly shining, without microsculpture; subalarum high, thin, at apex not sharpened; speculum wrinkly-punctured; mesopleural fovea deep with not broad triangle impression around; sternauli not expressed; mesopleurae very densely wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture, slightly shining; scutellum moderately (comparatively slightly) elevated above postscutellum, laterally carinated by slightly bent outside carinae; horizontal part of scutellum slightly convex with big smoothed punctures. Hind margin of metanotum with long bacilliform projections bent inside. Propodeum from lateral sloping, without distinct break; horizontal part only just longer than area posteromedia in middle, apical part of propodeum with long white pubescence; costulae and coxal carinae not developed, area superomedia longer than width approximately three times, its lateral carinae not sharp, apical transverse carina high; area dentipara with small denticle at apex; spiracles longish-oval approximately 1,6(1,7) times longer than width, of moderate size (large) (0,4 breadth of field at place of spiracle). Surface of area superomedia cellular, area dentipara and metapleurae densely wrinkly-punctured.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B1C7D2DAC6FC71F504C5D7" blockId="165.[178,852,908,930]" box="[178,852,908,930]" pageId="165" pageNumber="1482">L e g s: Strong (massive), long. Claws long, very slightly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B1C7D2DAC6FC4EF7E0C26A" blockId="165.[178,1085,945,1055]" pageId="165" pageNumber="1482">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, slightly asymmetrical (external veins longer than internal); radius slightly sinuous, long; nervulus interstitial; ramulus expressed, but slightly; stigma dark, membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Front wing 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B1C7D2DAC6FBD2F5A5C3F3" blockId="165.[178,1086,1070,1415]" pageId="165" pageNumber="1482">A b d o m e n From above longish-oval, compressed dorso-ventrally; second tergite shorter than breadth at apex; apical tergites not hidden, visible from above; sheath of ovipositor slightly protrude behind apex of abdomen. Petiolus distinctly flattened, from lateral with gradual transform to postpetiolus, lateral carinae distinct, surface between them with ribs; from above petiolus considerably broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus slightly elevated, but rather distinct, approximately equal by width to lateral fields; surface of postpetiolus shining with sparse wrinkles. Gastrocoeli moderately deepened, rather long with distinct slightly oblique thyridia, interval narrower than breadth each of them; interval with sharp longitudinal wrinkles; lunulae distinct, moderately large; second tergite medially striated almost to middle, other part densely and roughly, 3-4 tergites densely, but delicate punctured; all tergites shining. Hypopygium from below triangle, without longitudinal fold, membranous at apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B1C7D2DAC6FA6AF4FDC054" blockId="165.[178,1086,1430,1569]" pageId="165" pageNumber="1482">C o l o r a t i o n: Head and thorax black; yellow: internal and external orbits, spots at corners of clypeus, upper and lower margins of pronotum, scutellum, subalarum, epimerae (mesepimeron) at upper parts, apical corners of metapleurae above hind coxae. Abdomen red-brown with darkened first and of second tergites at middle and yellow border apically of all tergites, legs reddish-brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46B1C7D2DAC6F9CCF4CAC033" blockId="165.[178,666,1584,1606]" box="[178,666,1584,1606]" pageId="165" pageNumber="1482">S i z e: Body length: 10,5; front wing: 8,0 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>