<document id="B548035586A93FF08A9FE10D038EEDCF" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F8469EC7FBDAC6FC71F477C538" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Linycus exhortator" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="140" lastPageNumber="1457" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E136E956D63AD1EC45A96C6AB" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB7708D7F1C552A3B794F4C100">
<mods:title id="F6390249555B53FCC983C78443ED261A">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D1AF53898183760DFF5D7A27" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766E95C8D3E6E42CC1BC106C1">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB627000F097310622718114C1">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A7D518E5ECC8E7E6D51A0183">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95E55DF0A50FDE9A09DB9FA4F">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44D72906BF547AB1A204B7706" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB566DD8A903B9993E7AB45C1">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B07D5366C7019E211F24173E">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF3A150033A2820B56F7C4A87">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500CDEDE709481CBBDF618505C">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA0545592BCD32251F21CAD98061019" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB27FCBA57207E31F21E794727">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02B0A071DCE92FCF4FBED2BD7" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA841C9C1675EA9131067188C">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D615CF822716AD8FA027C3B1ED" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF50729749298644875C12D11">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA879CE5963632D4C92DEEEE3" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21F6E344F8EBE91BDB0707640">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16FC4059FCD3A662F637A91CC">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F580877FC1D2C26B20ABEB21BF">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568EF3BE885BF5790A3676C692" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2A05628A9D9C7D1EB0B02F80" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB4109DF28CE7556C599B6CE9" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F8469EC7FBDAC6FC71F477C538" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F8469EC7FBDAC6FC71F477C538" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F8469EC7FBDAC6FC71F477C538" lastPageId="140" lastPageNumber="1457" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">
<subSubSection id="C3466565469EC7FDDAC6FC71F43FC5D6" box="[178,623,909,931]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469EC7FDDAC6FC71F43FC5D6" blockId="138.[178,623,909,931]" box="[178,623,909,931]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">
<heading id="D0AB8182469EC7FDDAC6FC71F43FC5D6" box="[178,623,909,931]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC469EC7FDDAC6FC71F43FC5D6" bold="true" box="[178,623,909,931]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D469EC7FDDAC6FC71F450C5D6" authority="(FABRICIUS)" baseAuthorityName="FABRICIUS" box="[178,512,909,931]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Linycus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exhortator">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC469EC7FDDAC6FC71F729C5D6" bold="true" box="[178,377,909,931]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">Linycus exhortator</emphasis>
(FABRICIUS)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 30)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3466565469EC7FDDAC6FC48F25BC2D6" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469EC7FDDAC6FC48F773C27C" blockId="138.[178,879,949,998]" lastBlockId="138.[178,291,1012,1033]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D469EC7FDDAC6FC48F448C5BD" authority="FABRICIUS 1787" authorityName="FABRICIUS" authorityYear="1787" box="[178,536,948,968]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exhortator">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC469EC7FDDAC6FC48F72CC5BD" box="[178,380,948,968]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">Ichneumon exhortator</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F469EC7FDDBF6FC48F448C5BD" author="FABRICIUS J" box="[386,536,948,968]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" pagination="1 - 348" refId="ref142024" refString="FABRICIUS J. C. (1787): Mantissa insectorum. - Hafniae 1: 1 - 348 (Ichneumonidae: 259 - 271)." type="journal article" year="1787">FABRICIUS 1787</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mantissa Insectorum …, 1: 264, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD67469EC7FDD922FC44F532C5B8" box="[854,866,952,973]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
. 
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D469EC7FDDAC6FC32F7A8C597" authority=": HEINRICH 1962" authorityName="HEINRICH" authorityYear="1962" box="[178,504,974,994]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Linycus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exhortator">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC469EC7FDDAC6FC32F70EC597" box="[178,350,974,994]" italics="true" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">Linycus exhortator</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F469EC7FDDB1EFC32F7A8C597" author="HEINRICH G" box="[362,504,974,994]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" pagination="803 - 886" refId="ref142635" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1962): Synopsis of Nearctic Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae with particular reference to the northeastern Region. - Canadian Ent. Suppl. 26: 507 - 671; Suppl. 27: 675 - 802; Suppl. 29: 803 - 886." type="journal article" year="1962">HEINRICH 1962</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
-Canad. Ent. 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC469EC7FDD800FC32F4DAC597" bold="true" box="[628,650,974,994]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">27</emphasis>
: 779-780, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD67469EC7FDD898FC2EF4A8C592" box="[748,760,978,999]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469EC7FDDAC6FBE5F25BC2D6" blockId="138.[178,1085,1048,1187]" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, with 33 segments, strongly and gradually attenuated toward apex, beyond middle practically not widened, with white semiannulus on segments (4)5- 9, beyond white annulus very weakly flattened ventrally, all segments longer than wide, basal segments moderately long, first segment 3,7 times longer than width at apex laterally. Flagellum equal by length to front wing and 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3466565469EC7FBDAC6FB4FF477C538" lastPageId="140" lastPageNumber="1457" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469EC7FCDAC6FB4FF4A0C7C8" blockId="138.[178,1086,1203,1605]" lastBlockId="139.[178,1087,219,446]" lastPageId="139" lastPageNumber="1456" pageId="138" pageNumber="1455">H e a d: Head contour from front narrowed downwards, 1,4 times wider than height, triangular; genae from front almost straightly narrowed downwards, equal 0,3 height of eye; head contour from above strongly transversal, 2 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral rectilinearly and obliquely abrupt just after the ocelli to occipital carina; temples from above short, very strongly roundly narrowed behind eyes, temples length 1,6 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of eye at middle, from side practically parallel to hind margin of eye; occipital carina from above strongly roundly impressed beyond level of eyes, but not reach level of hind ocelli, not high, sharp all round to place of meeting with hypostomal carina not far of mandible base; malar space approximately 1,5 times shorter than mandible base width; mandibles gradually and strongly narrowed behind base; clypeus with straight front margin, strongly transversal, 2,7 times wider than length, distinctly separated from middle field of face; clypeal foveae of average size, deep; labrum roundly rectangular, far protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face distinctly, but slightly elevated, narrow, at middle 1,5 times narrower than lateral fields; antennal cavities small, slightly impressed, far not reach level of front ocellus and borders of eyes, laterally with tubercles and with strong tooth between antennal fossae; margins of antennal fossae high elevated; ocelli small, diameter of lateral ocellus only just more than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle slightly elevated. Clypeus with exception of front margin with rough punctures, middle field wrinkly-punctured in different degree, front surface of head with only just visible shine (on clypeus), surface of antennal cavities from smooth and shining to matt (rarely); surface of head with microsculpture and only just visible shine, practically matt.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469FC7FCDAC6FE32F4D2C23F" blockId="139.[178,1086,461,1098]" pageId="139" pageNumber="1456">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum short with straight front margin (from above); transverse furrow of pronotum narrow and deep. Mesonotum strongly convex, of equal length and breadth, notauli sharp, extend behind middle of mesonotum; middle lobe of mesonotum with dense indistinct punctures to wrinkle-punctured at hind half, lateral lobes with dense smoothed punctures with developed microsculpture and very slight shine; subalarum narrow, sharpened (at hind half); speculum with sparse punctures, shining; area of mesopleural fovea broadly, but not deeply impressed, mesopleural fovea deep; sternauli slightly impressed, distinct in front third; mesopleurae without sharp bend between lateral and ventral parts; mesopleural suture straight, deep with slight transversal ribs; lower part of mesopleurae smoothly longitudinally wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture; scutellum strongly convex, from above triangle, from lateral gradually slanting to postscutellum, laterally sharply carinated up to apex by high carinae; horizontal part of scutellum strongly convex with sparse punctures, shining. Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral strongly slanting backwards, without sharp break; horizontal part 2,5 shorter than length area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum with exception of coxal carina expressed; basal area short and deep; area superomedia transversal, rounded in front, costulae approximately at its middle; area dentipara at apex with small denticle; spiracles of propodeum small, circular, equal to 0,3 breadth of field at place of spiracle, only just longer than width, length of spiracles 1,2-1,5 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum irregularly-wrinkled, shining, without microsculpture; metapleurae smoothly transversally-wrinkled.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469FC7FCDAC6FBA6F5B0C21A" blockId="139.[178,992,1113,1135]" box="[178,992,1113,1135]" pageId="139" pageNumber="1456">L e g s: Legs slender; claws thin, not thickened at base, sharply curved at apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469FC7FCDAC6FB83F507C299" blockId="139.[178,1085,1150,1260]" pageId="139" pageNumber="1456">W i n g s: Areolet distinctly pentagonal, slightly asymmetrical (external vein of apex slightly shorter than internal); stigma broad, light; radial cell short and broad; radius straight, curved only at apex; nervulus interstitial; ramulus absent; membrane of wing hyaline, veins light. Front wing 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE469FC7FBDAC6FB07F7ECC713" blockId="139.[178,1085,1275,1590]" lastBlockId="140.[178,1085,219,358]" lastPageId="140" lastPageNumber="1457" pageId="139" pageNumber="1456">A b d o m e n:Formofabdomen from above rhomboidal; second tergite transversal, at apex 1,2 times wider than length; sheath of ovipositor only just visible protrude behind apex. Petiolus wider than height at base, from lateral gradually curved to postpetiolus; lateral carinae sharp, dorsomedian and dorsolateral carinae merge not far from base of tergite; interspace between dorsolateral and ventrolateral carinae sculpturated by transversal ribs; from above petiolus uniformly broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus slightly elevated, but distinct, approximately equal by breadth to lateral fields; surface of postpetiolus smooth, shining, with only just visible rugosity. Gastrocoeli presented by shallow, slightly sloped impression; thyridia practically not expressed, interval between gastrocoeli at base equal by breadth to middle field of postpetiolus; lunulae big, distinctly elevated; interspace between gastrocoeli wrinkled in different degree; other part of 2nd and middle of tergite 3 with superficial punctures, with developed microsculpture, surface between punctures coriaceous; other tergites smooth, shining; tergites 6 and 7 hidden and only just protrude from under 5; tergites 4-7 with membranous hind margin. Hypopygium from lateral with acute apex, compressed from sides and membranous apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4698C7FBDAC6FE89F746C7B3" blockId="140.[178,1085,373,454]" pageId="140" pageNumber="1457">C o l o r a t i o n: Head black; most part of body mainly ferruginous; tergites 3-7 darkened, tergites 4-7 with white membranous apex; apices of hind femora, tibiae and tarsi darkened.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4698C7FBDAC6FE29F579C79E" blockId="140.[178,809,469,491]" box="[178,809,469,491]" pageId="140" pageNumber="1457">
S i z e: Body length: 7,5; front wing: 6,0; flagellum: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B4698C7FBD8A1FE29F575C79E" box="[725,805,469,491]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.7" pageId="140" pageNumber="1457" unit="mm" value="5.7">5,7 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4698C7FBDAC6FE07F6ADC465" blockId="140.[178,253,506,528]" box="[178,253,506,528]" pageId="140" pageNumber="1457">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4698C7FBDAC6FDE3F54CC405" blockId="140.[178,1085,543,624]" pageId="140" pageNumber="1457">Flagellum of males with white annulus or semiannulus with distinct longish-oval, very narrow, almost bacilliform tyloides on segments 7-18, covered by short dense bristles, segments of apical third distinctly separated from each other.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4698C7FBDAC6FD83F777C4E0" blockId="140.[178,295,639,661]" box="[178,295,639,661]" pageId="140" pageNumber="1457">Variability.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4698C7FBDAC6FD59F477C538" blockId="140.[178,1085,677,845]" pageId="140" pageNumber="1457">The variability especially impressively is shown in distribution of red (yellow) coloration on a body, up to the practically full colored thorax and abdomen. The form of areolet varies from pentagonal to rhomboidal and sculpture of the middle field of postpetiolus from irregularly-wrinkled to completely smooth. The intensity of sculpture of front surface of head varies to a greater or lesser extent. There are considerable variations in the ratio of body length and front wings.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>