<document id="CEC2E95A029AF6F5EA315356FA7121EB" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84640C721DAC6FB6CF43AC5E8" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Trogus lapidator" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="1403" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E13B095B763AD19D95ADBC67B" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB77D6D72BC552A4AA94B9C1D0">
<mods:title id="F639024955855326C983C09943A026CA">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D171535381837110FF107AF7" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766375C573E6E45D11B8C0611">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB62AE002A9731013F71CC1411">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A70B183FECC8E0FBD5570153">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95E8BDFD050FDEEBD9DF4FA9F">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44DAC90B1F547AC07200677D6" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB5B8DD50903B9E8EE7E64511">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B0A353BCC701993C1F6917EE">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF37F50D93A2827A86F314A57">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500C00DEAA9481CCA0F655508C">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA054559262D3F851F21BB0984B10C9" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB2722BA8D207E36EF1E3447F7">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02BD407C7CE92FBE9FBA02B07" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA89FC91B675EAE0E102A185C">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D6151182FD16AD88BD278EB13D" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF5D929AE92986355758C2DC1">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA8A7CE8363632A519293EE33" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21FB034958EBE96A0B03D7690">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16F1A0545CD3A61326337911C">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F580597F1BD2C26C3DABA6216F">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568E2DBE525BF57E17363BC642" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2ADB62509D9C7A03B0FD2F50" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB4CE9D288CE7527159D66C39" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F84640C721DAC6FB6CF43AC5E8" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84640C721DAC6FB6CF43AC5E8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84640C721DAC6FB6CF43AC5E8" lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="1403" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">
<subSubSection id="C34665654640C723DAC6FB6CF407C2D0" box="[178,599,1167,1189]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4640C723DAC6FB6CF407C2D0" blockId="84.[178,599,1167,1189]" box="[178,599,1167,1189]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">
<heading id="D0AB81824640C723DAC6FB6CF407C2D0" box="[178,599,1167,1189]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4640C723DAC6FB6CF407C2D0" bold="true" box="[178,599,1167,1189]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4640C723DAC6FB6CF7B9C2D0" authority="(FABRICIUS)" baseAuthorityName="FABRICIUS" box="[178,489,1167,1189]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Trogus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lapidator">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4640C723DAC6FB6CF730C2D0" bold="true" box="[178,352,1167,1189]" italics="true" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">Trogus lapidator</emphasis>
(FABRICIUS)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 23)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C34665654640C723DAC6FB4AF773C37E" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4640C723DAC6FB4AF493C2BF" blockId="84.[178,824,1206,1252]" box="[178,707,1206,1226]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4640C723DAC6FB4AF45DC2BF" authority="FABRICIUS 1787" authorityName="FABRICIUS" authorityYear="1787" box="[178,525,1206,1226]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lapidator">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4640C723DAC6FB4AF720C2BF" box="[178,368,1206,1226]" italics="true" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">Ichneumon lapidator</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F4640C723DB02FB4AF45DC2BF" author="FABRICIUS J" box="[374,525,1206,1226]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" pagination="1 - 348" refId="ref142024" refString="FABRICIUS J. C. (1787): Mantissa insectorum. - Hafniae 1: 1 - 348 (Ichneumonidae: 259 - 271)." type="journal article" year="1787">FABRICIUS 1787</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Mant. Ins. 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4640C723D8F7FB4AF4DEC2BF" bold="true" box="[643,654,1206,1226]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">1</emphasis>
: 266.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4640C723DAC6FB2CF568C291" blockId="84.[178,824,1206,1252]" box="[178,824,1232,1252]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4640C723DAC6FB2CF7A6C291" authority=": TOSQUINET 1889" authorityName="TOSQUINET" authorityYear="1889" box="[178,502,1232,1252]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Trogus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lapidator">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4640C723DAC6FB2CF71CC291" box="[178,332,1232,1252]" italics="true" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">Trogus lapidator</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F4640C723DB2CFB2CF7A6C291" author="TOSQUINET J" box="[344,502,1232,1252]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" pagination="125 - 148" refId="ref144078" refString="TOSQUINET J. (1889): Documents pour server a la monographie des Ichneumonides de la Russied'Asie. - Annales de la Societe Entomologique de Belgique 33: 125 - 148." type="journal article" year="1889">TOSQUINET 1889</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ann. Soc. Ent. 
<collectingCountry id="F34B767E4640C723D8E1FB2CF4B7C291" box="[661,743,1232,1252]" name="Belgium" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">Belgique</collectingCountry>
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4640C723D898FB2CF553C291" bold="true" box="[748,771,1232,1252]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">33</emphasis>
: 126.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4640C723DAC6FB0AF773C37E" blockId="84.[178,291,1269,1291]" box="[178,291,1269,1291]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">F e m a l e</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C34665654640C721DAC6FAE7F43AC5E8" lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="1403" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4640C723DAC6FAE7F272C3FD" blockId="84.[178,1086,1306,1416]" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, 32-segments, with closely joined segments, practically not widened and not flattened beyond middle, uniformly attenuated toward apex; first segment rather short, only 2,5 times longer than width at apex, without white annulus. Flagellum 1,2 times shorter than the front wing and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4640C722DAC6FA64F574C575" blockId="84.[178,1086,1432,1600]" lastBlockId="85.[178,1086,219,768]" lastPageId="85" lastPageNumber="1402" pageId="84" pageNumber="1401">H e a d: Head comparatively small relative to body; head contour from front strongly narrowed downwards, transversal, 1,4 times wider than height; genae from front long, 2,7 times shorter than height of eye; head from above slightly transversal, 1,8 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral roundly slanting down after the ocelli to occipital carina, behind ocelli with roundish impression; temples long, 1,3 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, from side slightly narrowed from middle toward mandi- ble base, from above behind eyes narrowed almost straightly; occipital carina sharp all round, from above more high, slightly and roundly impressed toward ocelli, far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina visible from lateral, meeting with occipital carina far from mandible base; length of abscissula equal 0,6 breadth of mandible base width; malar space equal by length to mandible base width; mandibles strong, quite sharply curved at middle and narrowed to apex, with two teeth, situated in the same plane; clypeus two times wider than height, convex, with thinned and impressed front margin, quite sharply separated from face by suture; clypeal foveae small, areae around foveae slightly impressed; labrum far protrude from under clypeus, triangular, equal by breadth to clypeus front margin; middle field of face sharply limited, convex, in middle, 1,4 times wider than lateral fields; antennal cavities sharply and deeply impressed, reach borders of eyes and not reach front ocellus level, without lateral tubercles and only just visible tubercle between antennal fossae; frons between antennal cavities dorsally with two hornshaped projections; margins of antennal fossae high elevated above face surface; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,5 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle distinctly elevated. Surface of clypeus with big punctures, without microsculpture, lateral fields very densely punctured slightly or strongly shining and with or without visible microsculpture; top of frons slightly wrinkled, temples punctured by slightly impressed punctures, shining, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4641C722DAC6FCECF4BCC31A" blockId="85.[178,1087,783,1391]" pageId="85" pageNumber="1402">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum comparatively long with straight (from above) and very high elevated front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum very deep, not interrupted by keel (rarely medially with tubercle); pronotal ridge not thickened; epomiae very strong, sharp; pronotal base sharply sinuous. Mesonotum moderately convex, 1,3 times longer than width; notauli absent; axillary tongue not developed; middle lobe of mesonotum densely punctured by big smoothed punctures, shining, without microsculpture, lateral lobes with dense small punctures; subalarum high, thick, not sharpened; speculum and area of mesopleural fovea smooth, polished; area of mesopleural fovea deeply impressed; mesopleural suture straight, deep, interrupted by sharp ribs; lower part of mesopleurae with distinct bend; sternauli absent; upper front half of mesopleurae punctured, lower part longitudinally wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture; scutellum high, conical from lateral, slanted backwards and not carinated laterally, its surface densely punctured. Hind margin of metanotum with broad triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral triangle, shortened in extreme form, area posteromedia almost reach upper point of propodeum, with strong median longitudinal carina; area posteroexterna absent, area superomedia replaced by smooth, transverse, curved or triangle carina, propodeum very abruptly sloping forward and backwards to apex of propodeum; lateral carinae of basal area absent even in a form of trace; coxal carina practically absent, other carinae of propodeum sharp, high; spiracles large, slit-shaped. Surface of propodeum, with exception of punctured front dorsal half and of metapleurae, sharply transversally wrinkly-punctured, without microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4641C722DAC6FA83F7FEC3C4" blockId="85.[178,1085,1406,1457]" pageId="85" pageNumber="1402">L e g s: Slender and long. Hind coxae of female without scopa. Claws long, thin, strongly curved, smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4641C722DAC6FA3DF26DC05B" blockId="85.[177,1085,1472,1582]" pageId="85" pageNumber="1402">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, with tendency to petiolation, slightly asymmetrical, external veins longer than internal, external intercubitus curved out; stigma long, narrow, slightly darkened; radial cell narrow and long, radius in most part straight, strongly curved only at base and apex; nervulus slightly postfurcal; ramulus not developed; all</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4642C721DAC6FF27F52FC77B" blockId="86.[178,1085,219,270]" pageId="86" pageNumber="1403">veins dark; membrane of wing hyaline, slightly yellowish. Length of front wing 1,3 times longer than length of flagellum and 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4642C721DAC6FEE1F6B2C49F" blockId="86.[178,1085,285,746]" pageId="86" pageNumber="1403">A b d o m e n:Fromabove broad, at most part parallel sided, strongly sculpturated and with sharp constrictions between segments and impressions on dorsal surface, crosssection of abdominal tergites pentagonal, abdomen amblypygous; second tergite from above transversal, at apex 1,4 times wider than length. First tergite from lateral very thick with gradual transform of petiolus to postpetiolus; dorsomedian, dorsolateral and ventrolateral carinae sharp at all distance; lateral surface of petiolus with dense big punctures and distinct ribs at ventrolateral carina; from above petiolus sharply broadened to triangle postpetiolus; distance between spiracles equal to distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus sharply elevated and carinated, wider than lateral fields, impressed medially; surface of postpetiolus punctured by rough punctures, middle field roughly wrinkly-punctured. Gastrocoeli very deep and short, perpendicular to longitudinal axis of a body; thyridia distinct, 3,7 times narrower than interval between them; lunulae absent; middle part of tergite elevated; surface of tergites of abdomen with sharp longitudinal rugosity, wrinkles very sharp (almost carinae). Apex of hypopygium not protrude, ovipositor hidden; only second sternite with longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4642C721DAC6FD06F4E4C558" blockId="86.[178,1085,762,813]" pageId="86" pageNumber="1403">C o l o r a t i o n: Body black, with slight violet tint. Legs with exception of coxae and trochanters I rusty-red, tarsi of hind legs darkened.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4642C721DAC6FCC0F51FC527" blockId="86.[178,847,828,850]" box="[178,847,828,850]" pageId="86" pageNumber="1403">
S i z e: Body length: 17,0; front wing: 13,8; flagellum: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B4642C721D89AFCC0F51BC527" box="[750,843,828,850]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.04" pageId="86" pageNumber="1403" unit="mm" value="10.4">10,4 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4642C721DAC6FC9EF6ADC502" blockId="86.[178,253,866,888]" box="[178,253,866,888]" pageId="86" pageNumber="1403">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4642C721DAC6FC7BF43AC5E8" blockId="86.[178,618,903,925]" box="[178,618,903,925]" pageId="86" pageNumber="1403">Flagellum of male ribbed, without tyloides.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>