<document id="DEC52545A353E310C6920F85C45C6550" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F8465EC73BDAC6FCFEF247C7BB" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Protichneumon pisorius" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="1393" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E13AE95AD63AD1E4B5CA6C428" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB77C8D731C552A33892C4C383">
<mods:title id="F6390249559B533CC983C70B45DD2499">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D16F534981837682F96D78A4" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766295C4D3E6E42431DF10442">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB62B00030973106AD77B11642">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A7151825ECC8E769D32A0300">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95E95DFCA50FDE92F9B89F8CC">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44DB290ABF547AB95267B7585" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB5A6DD4A903B991CE19B4742">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B0BD53A6C7019EAE191415BD">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF36150C33A28203A694C4804">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500C1EDEB09481CB32F02852DF">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA05455927CD3E251F21C229E36129A" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB273CBA97207E317D184945A4">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02BCA07DDCE92FC7BFDDD2954" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA881C901675EA99C16571A0F">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D6150F82E716AD8F2F21F3B36E" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF5C729B4929864C773F12F92">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA8B9CE9963632DC394EEEC60" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21FAE348F8EBE9132B64074C3">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16F04055FCD3A66A0654A934F">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F580477F01D2C26BAFADDB233C">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568E33BE485BF579853046C411" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2AC5624A9D9C7D91B6802D03" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB4D09D328CE755E35FAB6E6A" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F8465EC73BDAC6FCFEF247C7BB" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F8465EC73BDAC6FCFEF247C7BB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F8465EC73BDAC6FCFEF247C7BB" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="1393" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">
<subSubSection id="C3466565465EC73DDAC6FCFEF4CDC56D" box="[178,669,770,792]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465EC73DDAC6FCFEF4CDC56D" blockId="74.[178,669,770,792]" box="[178,669,770,792]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">
<heading id="D0AB8182465EC73DDAC6FCFEF4CDC56D" box="[178,669,770,792]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC465EC73DDAC6FCFEF4CDC56D" bold="true" box="[178,669,770,792]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D465EC73DDAC6FCFEF47FC56D" authority="(LINNAEUS)" baseAuthorityName="LINNAEUS" box="[178,559,770,792]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Protichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pisorius">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC465EC73DDAC6FCFEF7FEC562" bold="true" box="[178,430,770,792]" italics="true" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">Protichneumon pisorius</emphasis>
(LINNAEUS)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 20)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3466565465EC73DDAC6FCD6F773C50B" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465EC73DDAC6FCD6F5C4C54B" blockId="74.[178,916,810,856]" box="[178,916,810,835]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D465EC73DDAC6FCD6F7AAC54B" authority="LINNAEUS 1758" authorityName="LINNAEUS" authorityYear="1758" box="[178,506,810,830]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Ichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pisorius">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC465EC73DDAC6FCD6F732C54B" box="[178,354,810,830]" italics="true" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">Ichneumon pisorius</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F465EC73DDB1CFCD6F7AAC54B" author="LINNAEUS C" box="[360,506,810,830]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" pagination="1 - 824" refId="ref143105" refString="LINNAEUS C. von. (1758): Systema naturae per regna tria naturae, secundum classes, ordines, genera, species cum characteribus, differentiis, synonymis locis. Tomus I. Editio decima, reformata. - Laurnetii Salvii, Holmiae, 1 - 824." type="book chapter" year="1758">LINNAEUS 1758</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Systema Naturae..., edition 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC465EC73DD97EFCD6F571C54B" bold="true" box="[778,801,810,830]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">10</emphasis>
(1): 561, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD67465EC73DD90EFCD2F5D6C536" box="[890,902,814,835]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465EC73DDAC6FCB8F480C52D" blockId="74.[178,916,810,856]" box="[178,720,836,856]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D465EC73DDAC6FCB8F45FC52D" authority=": ROMAN 1932" authorityName="ROMAN" authorityYear="1932" box="[178,527,836,856]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Protichneumon" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pisorius">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC465EC73DDAC6FCB8F7D9C52D" box="[178,393,836,856]" italics="true" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">Protichneumon pisorius</emphasis>
: 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F465EC73DDBE0FCB8F45FC52D" author="ROMAN A" box="[404,527,836,856]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" pagination="1 - 16" refId="ref143437" refString="ROMAN A. (1932): The Linnean types of Ichneumon-flies. - Entomologisk Tidskrift. 53: 1 - 16." type="journal article" year="1932">ROMAN 1932</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ent. Tidskr. 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC465EC73DD8E5FCB8F4F7C52D" bold="true" box="[657,679,836,856]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">53</emphasis>
: 10.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465EC73DDAC6FC95F773C50B" blockId="74.[178,291,873,895]" box="[178,291,873,895]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">F e m a l e</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3466565465EC73BDAC6FC73F247C7BB" lastPageId="76" lastPageNumber="1393" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465EC73DDAC6FC73F427C26C" blockId="74.[178,1085,910,1049]" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">F l a g e l l u m: Stout, bristle-shaped, with 50 segments, with white annulus on segments 6-14(15), beyond middle strongly widened and flattened ventrally; first segment short, only 1,4 times longer than width at apex, already segment 6 square; segments of flagellum clearly separated (differentiated). Flagellum 1,8 times shorter than the front wing and 2,6 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465EC73CDAC6FBD5F46CC77B" blockId="74.[178,1086,1064,1584]" lastBlockId="75.[178,1085,219,270]" lastPageId="75" lastPageNumber="1392" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">
H e a d: Head contour from front slightly narrowed downwards, slightly transversal, 1,2 times wider than height, genae short, 5,2 times shorter than height of eye; head massive, from above 1,5 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral gradually slanting down to occipital carina; temples long, 1,2 times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, not narrowed downwards, from above roundly, almost straightly narrowed behind eyes; occipital carina sharp, from above strongly and roundly impressed, but far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral, meeting with occipital carina before mandible base; malar space 1,5 times shorter than the mandible base width; mandibles strong, long, parallel sided at most part, teeth large, lower two times shorter than upper, situated in the same plane, gape between teeth narrow; clypeus scarcely convex, distinctly separated from face by impression, approximately 2,1 times wider than height, front margin not sharpened, with slight projection at the middle; clypeal foveae sharp, deep; labrum protrude from under clypeus, roundish, narrower than front margin of clypeus; middle field of face slightly elevated, middle field of face in middle narrower than lateral fields; antennal cavities deeply impressed, almost reach borders of eyes and far not reach front ocellus level, laterally with very deep hollow (concavity), characteristic also to species of 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC465EC73DD8FFFA01F554C066" box="[651,772,1533,1555]" italics="true" pageId="74" pageNumber="1391">Amblyjoppa</emphasis>
genus; interantennal tubercle sharp; ocelli small, slightly convex, diameter of lateral ocellus 2,4 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle not elevated. Surface of head slightly wrinkly-punctured, shining, without microsculpture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465FC73CDAC6FEE2F53AC515" blockId="75.[178,1086,285,864]" pageId="75" pageNumber="1392">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum moderately long with straight front margin (from above); transverse furrow of pronotum moderately deep, not interrupted by keel; pronotal ridge not thickened; epomiae sharp; pronotal base gradually curved, almost straight. Mesonotum slightly convex, 1,2 times longer than width; notauli developed in front third; surface of mesonotum densely sculpturated by superficial punctures, interspaces between punctures shagreen in front part, shining; axillary tongue developed; subalarum moderately elevated, moderately thick, not sharpened; prepectus behind front coxae not impressed; prepectal carina sharp; speculum shining, only dorsally with big punctures, polished; area of mesopleural fovea deeply impressed; mesopleural suture straight, interrupted by transversal ribs; border between vertical and horizontal parts of mesopleurae rather sharp; sternauli not developed; apical margin of mesosternum elevated; scutellum almost flat, not carinated laterally, horizontal part smooth, shining, slightly sculpturated by small superficial punctures. Hind margin of metanotum with sharp triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral abruptly sloping from base to apex; external carina of area dentipara parallel to metapleural carina at hind half; area superomedia long, narrow, narrowed backwards (of changeable form) and swollen in different degree; costulae behind middle, distinct, only just marked or absent; lateral carinae of basal area expressed; basal area short and deep, other carinae distinct, coxal carina weak; spiracles long, slit-shaped. Surface of propodeum roughly wrinkly-punctured, including more smoothly sculpturated metapleurae, without microsculpture, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465FC73CDAC6FC8CF7FDC5CA" blockId="75.[178,1086,879,959]" pageId="75" pageNumber="1392">L e g s: Strong; hind coxae without scopa. Segments of tarsi of front legs widened. Claws, smooth, sharply curved at upper third, or almost at middle (front tarsi) and slightly widened at base.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465FC73CDAC6FC33F4D3C249" blockId="75.[178,1085,975,1084]" pageId="75" pageNumber="1392">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, symmetrical; stigma narrow, dark; radial cell narrow and very long, radius sinuous at base and at apex; nervulus postfurcal; ramulus developed; all veins of hind wing pigmented; membrane of wing hyaline, slightly yellowish. Length of front wing 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465FC73CDAC6FBB0F5CDC3D1" blockId="75.[178,1085,1100,1444]" pageId="75" pageNumber="1392">A b d o m e n: Abdomen from above long, lanceolate (fusiform); second tergite from above 1,2 times longer than width at apex; abdomen sharply oxypygous; sheath of ovipositor slightly protrude behind apex. First tergite from lateral with gradual passage to postpetiolus, from lateral carinated and sculpturated by sharp transversal ribs; from above petiolus sharply broadened to postpetiolus; distance between spiracles only just more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; middle field of postpetiolus slightly elevated and not carinated; its surface slightly irregularly wrinkly-punctured; central part impressed. Gastrocoeli deep; thyridia only just expressed, slightly oblique, narrower than interval between them; lunulae in a form of slight impressions; surface of second tergite of abdomen in middle slightly longitudinally wrinkly-punctured other part of tergite and tergites 3-4 with very delicate dense superficial punctures, with microsculpture between punctures, tergites 6-7 shagreen, slightly shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE465FC73CDAC6FA4FF49DC04B" blockId="75.[178,1085,1459,1598]" pageId="75" pageNumber="1392">C o l o r a t i o n: Head and thorax black with yellow pattern; yellow: fronto-vertical orbits, collar, upper margin of pronotum, subalarum, scutellum. Abdomen ferruginous, first tergite darkened in different degree. Coxae and femora of all legs mainly black, middle coxae with yellow spots, apex of trochanters I yellow; tibiae and tarsi of basic color with yellow pattern, front tibiae mainly yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4658C73BDAC6FF27F512C685" blockId="76.[178,834,219,241]" box="[178,834,219,241]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1393">
S i z e: Body length: 22,6; flagellum: 8,8; front wing: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B4658C73BD895FF27F56EC685" box="[737,830,219,241]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.6199999999999999" pageId="76" pageNumber="1393" unit="mm" value="16.2">16,2 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4658C73BDAC6FEFDF6ADC763" blockId="76.[178,253,256,278]" box="[178,253,256,278]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1393">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4658C73BDAC6FED9F247C7BB" blockId="76.[178,1085,293,462]" pageId="76" pageNumber="1393">Flagellum of male long, bristle-shaped, scarcely widened and not flattened beyond middle, with 49 segments, with rather narrow oval tyloides on segments 5-18(19); segments quite closely connected, slightly ribbed, without white annulus; axillary tongue more developed; area superomedia of propodeum more short; coloration similar to female, yellow pattern more extended: face completely, genae and external orbits, axillary tongue, spots on prepectus and mesopleurae, legs more broadly; apical tergites of abdomen often darkened.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>