<document id="0A206D4A124A5173CE013571A79A69C2" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84636C753DAC6FB55F512C57A" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Compsophorus (Epijoppa) verecundus subsp. angolae" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="36" lastPageNumber="1353" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E13C695C563AD19E05BF3C6E9" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB77A0D759C552A4939591C142">
<mods:title id="F639024955F35354C983C0A042882658">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D107532181837129FE387A65" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766415C253E6E45E81AA40683">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB62D800589731010670E41483">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A77D184DECC8E0C2D47F01C1">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95EFDDFA250FDEE849CDCFA0D">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44DDA90C3F547AC3E212E7744" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB5CEDD22903B9EB7E6CE4583">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B0D553CEC70199051E41177C">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF30950AB3A2827916E194AC5">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500C76DED89481CC99F77D501E">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA054559214D38A51F21B899963105B" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB2754BAFF207E36D61F1C4765">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02BA207B5CE92FBD0FA882B95" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA8E9C969675EAE37110218CE">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D61567828F16AD888426A6B1AF" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF5AF29DC9298636C74A42D53">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA8D1CEF163632A6893BBEEA1" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21FC634E78EBE9699B1157602">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16F6C0537CD3A610B621F918E">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F5802F7F69D2C26C04AA8E21FD">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568E5BBE205BF57E2E3713C6D0" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2AAD62229D9C7A3AB1D52FC2" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB4B89D5A8CE7524858FE6CAB" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F84636C753DAC6FB55F512C57A" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84636C753DAC6FB55F512C57A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84636C753DAC6FB55F512C57A" lastPageId="36" lastPageNumber="1353" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">
<subSubSection id="C34665654636C755DAC6FB55F750C288" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4636C755DAC6FB55F52FC2B5" blockId="34.[178,895,1193,1216]" box="[178,895,1193,1216]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">
<heading id="D0AB81824636C755DAC6FB55F52FC2B5" box="[178,895,1193,1216]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755DAC6FB55F52FC2B5" bold="true" box="[178,895,1193,1216]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4636C755DAC6FB55F54DC2B5" authority="(HEINRICH)" baseAuthorityName="HEINRICH" box="[178,797,1193,1216]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Compsophorus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="verecundus" subGenus="Epijoppa" subSpecies="angolae">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755DAC6FB55F71FC2CA" bold="true" box="[178,335,1193,1215]" italics="true" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">Compsophorus</emphasis>
(
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755DB2AFB56F7ECC2CA" bold="true" box="[350,444,1194,1215]" italics="true" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">Epijoppa</emphasis>
) 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755DBBFFB55F4CBC2CA" bold="true" box="[459,667,1193,1215]" italics="true" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">verecundus angolae</emphasis>
(HEINRICH)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 7)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4636C755DAC6FB2DF750C288" blockId="34.[178,1084,1233,1327]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755DAC6FB2DF7EAC290" box="[178,442,1233,1253]" italics="true" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">Epijoppa verecunda angolae</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F4636C755DBB5FB2DF400C290" author="HEINRICH G" box="[449,592,1233,1253]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" pagination="1 - 1258" refId="ref142685" refString="HEINRICH G. H. (1967 - 1968): Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of the Sahara. - Monograph. Farmington State College Press 1 - 5: 1 - 1258." type="book chapter" year="1967">HEINRICH 1967</bibRefCitation>
- Ichn. Stenop. of Africa 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755D937FB2DF51EC290" bold="true" box="[835,846,1233,1253]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">2</emphasis>
: 350, 375, 376, 394, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD674636C755DE50FB29F260C29F" box="[1060,1072,1237,1258]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C34665654636C753DAC6FAFFF512C57A" lastPageId="36" lastPageNumber="1353" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4636C755DAC6FAFFF75FC35A" blockId="34.[178,1084,1233,1327]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755DAC6FAFFF7A8C362" box="[178,504,1283,1303]" italics="true" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4636C755DAC6FAFFF7F8C362" baseAuthorityName="Tosquinet" baseAuthorityYear="1896" box="[178,424,1283,1303]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Compsophorus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="verecundus">Compsophorus verecundus</taxonomicName>
angolae
</emphasis>
: TOWNES H. &amp; M. 
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F4636C755D8C5FAFFF564C362" author="TOWNES H" box="[689,820,1283,1303]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351" pagination="1 - 416" refId="ref144390" refString="TOWNES H. K. &amp; M. TOWNES (1973): A catalogue and reclassification of the Ethiopian Ichneumonidae. - Mem. American Ent. Inst. 19: 1 - 416." type="journal article" year="1973">TOWNES 1973</bibRefCitation>
- Mem. Amer. Ent. Inst. 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4636C755DE55FAFFF267C362" bold="true" box="[1057,1079,1283,1303]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">19</emphasis>
: 253.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4636C755DAC6FABCF773C320" blockId="34.[178,291,1344,1366]" box="[178,291,1344,1366]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4636C755DAC6FA9AF272C3C3" blockId="34.[178,1086,1381,1462]" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">F l a g e l l u m: Slender, bristle-shaped, with 39 segments, without white annulus, ventrally flattened beyond middle; first segment three times longer than width at apex. Flagellum 1,2 times shorter than the front wing and 1,7 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4636C754DAC6FA3AF428C418" blockId="34.[178,1086,1477,1587]" lastBlockId="35.[178,1087,219,621]" lastPageId="35" lastPageNumber="1352" pageId="34" pageNumber="1351">H e a d: Head contour from front roundly narrowed downwards, slightly transversal, 1,2 times wider than height; genae from front very long, 0,6-0,8 height of eye; sutures and elevations on face surface fully absent; head from above 1,5 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral gradually slanting down to occipital carina; temples long, almost two times longer than longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, from above very slightly roundly narrowed behind eyes, from side broadened toward mandible base; occipital carina from above strongly roundly impressed, occipital carina sharp all round, meeting with hypostomal carina on mandible base; malar space 1,3 times longer than the mandible base width; mandibles very broad with large practically equal teeth situated in the same plane and divided by broad gape, bent at the middle almost at right angle; clypeus confluent with face, with slightly rounded front margin; clypeal foveae presented by only just visible pore; labrum only just visible protrude from under clypeus, small and triangular; antennal cavities deeply impressed, almost reach borders of eyes but not reach level of front ocellus, without lateral tubercles and interantennal tubercle, margins of antennal fossae slightly elevated above face surface; ocelli small, diameter of lateral ocellus 3,5 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle practically not elevated. Surface of head smooth, shining, without microsculpture, with sparse very small, only just visible superficial punctures.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4637C754DAC6FD81F508C28C" blockId="35.[178,1085,637,1273]" pageId="35" pageNumber="1352">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long, at front margin with long, directed backwards lamellae, divided by slight incision; lower angle of pronotum very sharp, pronotal base almost straight, epomiae sharp; pronotal ridge not swollen. Mesonotum almost flat, some longer than width; middle lobe of mesonotum medially slightly impressed; notauli in a form of broad crenulated impression, developed all round of mesonotum; lateral fields laterally carinated by distinct keel, forming thus strongly crenulated impression between keel and lateral margin of mesonotum; surface of mesonotum roughly wrinkled, shining, without microsculpture; subalarum thin, sharp; speculum smooth, shining; area of mesopleural fovea broadly, but slightly impressed; sternauli absent; lower part of mesopleurae with angulate bend to ventral part; surface of mesopleurae, with exception of area of speculum roughly longitudinally-wrinkled, shining, without microsculpture; scutellum from lateral conical, vertically abrupt from apex to postscutellum, carinated laterally, its surface longitudinally cellular-wrinkled. Hind margin of metanotum without sharp triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae, only with weak prominences. Propodeum short, transversal, from lateral gradually slanting backwards (without break); horizontal part equal only 0,6 of area posteromedia length in middle; almost all carinae of propodeum developed, with exception of apical transverse carina, thus area dentipara and area posteroexterna merged and area superomedia merged with area posteromedia; basal area absent; area superomedia only just wider than length, laterally rounded, costulae behind middle; spiracles slit-shaped. Surface of propodeum roughly wrinkly-punctured, with exception of entirely smooth area superomedia and slightly wrinkled first lateral field (area superoexterna), without traces of microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4637C754DAC6FAF5F57DC349" blockId="35.[178,1085,1289,1340]" pageId="35" pageNumber="1352">L e g s: Slender, but rather strong, strongly darkened; hind tibiae with distinct longitudinal impression; claws of tarsi small, smooth, slightly curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4637C754DAC6FAB0F7E0C381" blockId="35.[178,1085,1355,1524]" pageId="35" pageNumber="1352">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular, asymmetrical, external vein of base longer than internal, аn external vein of apex shorter than internal; stigma long and narrow, strongly darkened; radius sinuous, radial cell long and narrow; nervulus postfurcal; ramulus distinct; membrane of wing strongly darkened with violet tint, veins very dark. All veins of hind wing distinct throughout and strongly darkened. Length of front wing more than 1,4 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4637C753DAC6F9FFF4A7C418" blockId="35.[178,1085,1539,1590]" lastBlockId="36.[178,1086,219,621]" lastPageId="36" lastPageNumber="1353" pageId="35" pageNumber="1352">A b d o m e n: Form of abdomen longish-oval, strongly pointed backwards with only just visible projected apices of ovipositor sheath, semiamblypygous; tergites of abdomen strongly sclerotized with sharp constrictions between segments; sternites strongly sclerotized, but sternites 2-3 with unsclerotized longitudinal fold. Petiolus of first tergite thin, at base not flattened, from lateral almost straight, smooth, without lateral carinae, from above sharply broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus gradually and distinctly elevated, but not carinated, wider than lateral fields, longitudinally striated by sharp carinae; spiracles slit-shaped, distance between them 1,7 times more than from spiracles to apex of tergite. Gastrocoeli very deep, short, with distinct thyridia approached to base of second tergite; interval between thyridia slightly narrower than breadth of thyridia, with sharp longitudinal carinae (wrinkles) extend almost to apex of tergite and roughly punctured at interspaces; lunulae absent; surface of second tergite sharply striated by high longitudinal carinae with exception of densely and roughly punctured apex and lateral parts; third tergite with similar but less sharply expressed sculpture, 4-5th tergites densely superficially punctured, other smooth. Hypopygium triangle with rounded apex and without longitudinal fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4630C753DAC6FD81F5AFC49F" blockId="36.[178,1085,637,746]" pageId="36" pageNumber="1353">C o l o r a t i o n: Predominate colors in coloration of body ferruginous and metallic violet. Ferruginous: head, thorax and front legs; abdomen and lower part of propodeum metallic violet; middle and hind legs blackened, membrane of front and hind wings strongly darkened with violet tint; light anal spots and annulus on flagellum absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4630C753DAC6FD06F512C57A" blockId="36.[178,834,762,784]" box="[178,834,762,784]" pageId="36" pageNumber="1353">
S i z e: Body length: 14,5; flagellum: 8,6; front wing: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B4630C753D896FD06F56EC57A" box="[738,830,762,784]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.05" pageId="36" pageNumber="1353" unit="mm" value="10.5">10,5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>