<document id="82A635FD66D5216437E2FAC6B591C88E" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F84606C763DAC6FDC6F7F7C27F" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Clypeodromus thyridialis TERESHKIN" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="20" lastPageNumber="1337" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E13F695F563AD1F735916C1EC" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB7790D769C552A2009774C647">
<mods:title id="F639024955C35364C983C633406D215D">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D1375311818377BAFCDD7D60" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766715C153E6E437B18410186">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB62E800689731079572011386">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A74D187DECC8E651D69A06C4">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95ECDDF9250FDE8179E39FD08">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44DEA90F3F547AAAD23CB7041" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB5FEDD12903B9824E42B4286">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B0E553FEC7019F961CA41079">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF339509B3A2821026CFC4DC0">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500C46DEE89481CA0AF598571B">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA054559224D3BA51F21D1A9B86175E" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB2764BACF207E30451DF94060">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02B920785CE92FD43F86D2C90" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA8D9C959675EA8A413E71FCB">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D6155782BF16AD8E172443B6AA" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF59F29EC929865FF76412A56">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA8E1CEC163632CFB915EE9A4" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21FF634D78EBE900AB3F07107">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16F5C0507CD3A679860FA968B">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F5801F7F59D2C26A97A86B26F8">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568E6BBE105BF578BD35F6C1D5" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2A9D62129D9C7CA9B33028C7" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB4889D6A8CE754DB5A1B6BAE" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F84606C763DAC6FDC6F7F7C27F" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F84606C763DAC6FDC6F7F7C27F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F84606C763DAC6FDC6F7F7C27F" lastPageId="20" lastPageNumber="1337" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">
<subSubSection id="C34665654606C765DAC6FDC6F4C8C424" box="[178,664,570,593]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FDC6F4C8C424" blockId="18.[178,664,570,593]" box="[178,664,570,593]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">
<heading id="D0AB81824606C765DAC6FDC6F4C8C424" box="[178,664,570,593]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4606C765DAC6FDC6F4C8C424" bold="true" box="[178,664,570,593]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4606C765DAC6FDC6F467C43A" authority="TERESHKIN" authorityName="TERESHKIN" box="[178,567,570,593]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Clypeodromus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thyridialis">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4606C765DAC6FDC6F7E7C425" bold="true" box="[178,439,570,592]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Clypeodromus thyridialis</emphasis>
TERESHKIN
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 2)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C34665654606C765DAC6FD9EF6ACC4A1" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FD9EF5FCC403" blockId="18.[178,954,609,656]" box="[178,940,609,635]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4606C765DAC6FD9EF46BC403" authority="TERESHKIN 1992" authorityName="TERESHKIN" authorityYear="1992" box="[178,571,610,630]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Clypeodromus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thyridialis">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4606C765DAC6FD9EF7C9C403" box="[178,409,610,630]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Clypeodromus thyridialis</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F4606C765DBEBFD9EF46BC403" author="TERESHKIN A" box="[415,571,610,630]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" pagination="93 - 98" refId="ref143635" refString="TERESHKIN A. (1992): A new tribe, a new genus and a new species of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae from Europe and Siberia (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae). - Entomofauna 13 (10): 93 - 98." type="journal article" year="1992">TERESHKIN 1992</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Entomofauna (
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4606C765D8A2FD9EF4BDC403" bold="true" box="[726,749,610,630]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">13</emphasis>
) 10: 193-204, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD674606C765D900FD9AF5D0C40E" box="[884,896,614,635]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FD80F5EAC4E5" blockId="18.[178,954,609,656]" box="[178,954,636,656]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4606C765DAC6FD80F46BC4E5" authority="TERESHKIN 2000" authorityName="TERESHKIN" authorityYear="2000" box="[178,571,636,656]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Clypeodromus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="thyridialis">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4606C765DAC6FD80F7C9C4E5" box="[178,409,636,656]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Clypeodromus thyridialis</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F4606C765DBEBFD80F46BC4E5" author="TERESHKIN A" box="[415,571,636,656]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" pagination="229 - 236" refId="ref143789" refString="TERESHKIN A. M. (2000): Description of the males of Ulesta nigroscutella TERESHKIN 1993, Rhadinodonta rufidens (WESMAEL 1844) and new name for genus Heinrichia TERESHKIN 1996 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae). - Entomofauna 21 (18): 229 - 236." type="journal article" year="2000">TERESHKIN 2000</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Entomofauna (
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4606C765D8A2FD80F4BDC4E5" bold="true" box="[726,749,636,656]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">21</emphasis>
) 18: 232, distribution.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FD5EF6ACC4A1" blockId="18.[178,1085,673,724]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">
D i s t r i b u t i o n: 
<collectingCountry id="F34B767E4606C765DBD4FD5DF44AC4C2" box="[416,538,673,695]" name="Belarus" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Byelorussia</collectingCountry>
, South Ural, 
<collectingRegion id="4998F80C4606C765D8C1FD5DF512C4C2" box="[693,834,673,695]" country="Russia" name="Altay" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Altai Region</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion id="4998F80C4606C765D927FD5DF5E1C4C2" box="[851,945,673,695]" country="Russia" name="Primorskiy" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Maritime</collectingRegion>
Territory of 
<collectingCountry id="F34B767E4606C765DAC6FD42F6A8C4A1" box="[178,248,702,724]" name="Russia" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Russia</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C34665654606C763DAC6FD1FF7F7C27F" lastPageId="20" lastPageNumber="1337" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FD1FF700C562" blockId="18.[178,1085,739,791]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">Small ichneumon flies with strongly polished, shining body, with absolutely absence of microsculpture.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FCDBF773C549" blockId="18.[178,291,806,828]" box="[178,291,806,828]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">F e m a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FCB7F7BDC5A5" blockId="18.[178,1085,842,976]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">F l a g e l l u m: Of females semi bristle-shaped, with 29 segments, first segment 2,7 times longer than width at apex, black, with white annulus on segments 7-11, ventrally beyond white annulus slightly flattened, but not widened, segment 12 square laterally, last but one segment almost square. Flagellum equal by length to front wing and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4606C765DAC6FC23F4D3C035" blockId="18.[178,1087,990,1600]" pageId="18" pageNumber="1335">H e a d: Head contour from the front roundly narrowed downwards, transversal, 1,3 times wider than height; genae from front 3,5 times shorter than height of an eye; head from above strongly transversal, 2 times wider than length. Vertex from lateral abrupt just after the ocelli, behind ocelli with median impression; temples short, two times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye at the middle, from above sharply roundly narrowed behind eyes, from side strongly broadened toward mandible base; occipital carina from above absent, occiput roundly angularly impressed to level of eyes, occipital carina sharp from upper third of eye, high elevated, meeting with hypostomal carina far before base of mandible; abscissula 1,6 times less than the mandible base width; genae on the borders with mandible base and clypeus with strong matt impression; malar space equal to mandible base width; mandibles almost parallel sided with two teeth situated in the same plane, lover tooth 1,5 times shorter than upper; clypeus transverse, almost 4 times wider than length, strongly convex at the base with thinned front margin and leaf-like broadened and elevated above malar space lateral margins, distinctly separated from face by sharp impression; clypeal fovea sharp, deep; labrum not protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face narrow, distinctly limited, strongly elevated above lateral fields, in middle equal by width to lateral fields; antennal cavities only just impressed, without lateral tubercles, but with distinct tubercle between antennal fossae; front margins of antennal fossae high elevated above face surface; ocelli normal, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,6 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle elevated, but slightly. Surface of head polished, shining, without microsculpture, with sparse superficial punctures on border of face, clypeus and on malar space.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4607C764DAC6FF27F5B1C59F" blockId="19.[178,1085,219,1002]" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336">
T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum rather short with rounded front margin, transverse furrow of pronotum rather deep and broad, interrupted in middle by distinct keel; epomiae strong, lower branch sharp, reach to pronotal base, forming slight angular fracture above front coxae, like fracture of pronotum of genus 
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4607C764D8C7FECEF51DC73D" authorityName=": HEINRICH" authorityYear="1974" box="[691,845,306,328]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Notoplatylabus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4607C764D8C7FECEF51DC73D" box="[691,845,306,328]" italics="true" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336">Notoplatylabus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4607C764D92BFECEF583C73D" box="[863,979,306,328]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="tribe" tribe="Platylabini">Platylabini</taxonomicName>
); pronotal ridge very strongly thickened and separated from spiracles by impression; on border of pronotum and mesonotum with weak, but distinct hollow (see 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC4607C764D916FE91F5FFC7F6" box="[866,943,365,387]" italics="true" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336">Alomya</emphasis>
[
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D4607C764D9B6FE91F27CC7F6" box="[962,1068,365,387]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Alomyini">Alomyini</taxonomicName>
]). Mesonotum strongly convex, equal length and breadth; notauli deep in front third; laterally mesonotum bordered by deep furrow, scuto-scutellar groove very deep and broad; axillary tongue not expressed; surface of mesonotum not sculptured, polished; subalarum thick, not sharpened; surface of speculum not sculptured, polished; area of mesopleural fovea broadly and deeply impressed; lower part of mesopleurae not separated angularly; sternauli developed to middle of mesopleurae, in front third deeply impressed; prepectal carina sharp, high elevated, furrow behind carina interrupted by sharp ribs; mesopleural suture deeply impressed, interrupted by sharp ribs; upper part of mesopleurae under subalarum with sparse superficial punctures, lower, longitudinally wrinkly-punctured; surface of mesopleurae polished; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, convex, not carinated laterally, vertical surface of scutellum with wrinkled impression; postscutellum between lateral foveae with sharp longitudinal wrinkles and impressions (with cellular sculpture). Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral angular, horizontal part 1,8 times shorter than area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum sharp, with exception of lateral carinae, limited basal area; basal area short and deep with distinct tooth; area superomedia hexagonal, from costulae narrowed in front and backwards and sometimes rounded in front, approximately equal by length to breadth between costulae, costulae before middle; apex of area dentipara with denticle; spiracles small, roundish, approximately 1,5 times longer than width. Surface of propodeum from smooth to wrinkled, polished, without microsculpture, metapleurae with sparse superficial punctures.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4607C764DAC6FC06F4FCC23F" blockId="19.[178,1085,1017,1098]" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336">L e g s: Strong; all legs with two trochanters; hind coxae of female without traces of scopa, ventrally, on its place often with distinct impression; hind tibiae at apex with flattened area; claws of all females tarsi pectinate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4607C764DAC6FBA6F523C291" blockId="19.[178,1085,1113,1252]" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336">W i n g s: Radius short, practically straight, radial cell broad; stigma broad; areolet pentagonal with wide base, slightly asymmetrical, external vein of base shorter than internal, and of apex longer than internal; ramulus only just marked; nervulus interstitial, strongly inclival. Cubital vein of hind wing not expressed. Veins of both wings brown; membrane of wings hyaline. Front wing 1,5 shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4607C763DAC6FB0FF750C7CB" blockId="19.[178,1086,1267,1582]" lastBlockId="20.[178,1085,219,446]" lastPageId="20" lastPageNumber="1337" pageId="19" pageNumber="1336">A b d o m e n Of female amblypygous, from above from longish-oval to conically narrowed backwards from apex of second tergite, sheath of ovipositor from above only just visible, second tergite from above transversal, in middle 1,3 times shorter than breadth at apex. First tergite from lateral with distinct bend at place of transition of petiolus to postpetiolus; petiolus at base not flattened; dorsomedian and dorsolateral carinae independently reach base of tergite; surface of petiolus between lateral carinae not sculptured, shining; petiolus rather broad, from above gradually, but distinctly transform to short and broad postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus slightly elevated, not carinated; distance between spiracles 2,9 times more than distance from spiracles to hind margin of tergite; postpetiolus with indistinct wrinkles and punctures, smooth, shining. Gastrocoeli large, long; thyridia very distinct, long, perpendicular to longitudinal axis of a body, three times wider than interval, interspace between them with five sharp longitudinal wrinkles, reaching to apical third of second tergite; second tergite wrinkled in most part, laterally and at apical third with big punctures; lunulae distinct; third tergite with sharp longitudinal wrinkles to middle, with delicate superficial punctures at apical part, other tergites smooth, polished with sparse shallow punctures; all abdomen polished, shining without microsculpture. Sternites 2-3 unsclerotized in most part; hypopygium compressed from side, from lateral, triangle with acute apex and membranous hind margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4600C763DAC6FE31F40EC49F" blockId="20.[178,1086,461,746]" pageId="20" pageNumber="1337">C o l o r a t i o n: Main color of head black; white or yellow: spots on vertex, frontal orbits, sometimes partially external orbits, spots at lateral corners of clypeus, mandibles, excepting darkened teeth. Flagellum black with white annulus. Thorax black; white: subalarum, scutellum, with exception of black middle, sometimes white spots at lower hind corners of mesopleurae and metapleurae. Abdomen black; white: spots at corners of tergites 3-5, apical margin of tergite 5, most part of tergite 6 and 7. Unsclerotized parts of sternites brightly-white. Front and middle coxae mainly white, hind coxae black with white spot dorsally. Trochanters of front and middle legs completely white; trochanters of hind legs with white spots. Femora, tibiae and tarsi of front and middle legs rusty-red with darkened apices; hind tarsi darkened.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4600C763DAC6FD06F529C57A" blockId="20.[178,889,762,784]" box="[178,889,762,784]" pageId="20" pageNumber="1337">
S i z e: Body length: 6,6-6,7; front wing: 4,5-4,8; flagellum: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B4600C763D951FD06F525C57A" box="[805,885,762,784]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.7" pageId="20" pageNumber="1337" unit="mm" value="4.7">4,7 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4600C763DAC6FCDCF6ADC540" blockId="20.[178,253,799,821]" box="[178,253,799,821]" pageId="20" pageNumber="1337">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE4600C763DAC6FCB8F7F7C27F" blockId="20.[178,1085,836,1034]" pageId="20" pageNumber="1337">Males similar in appearance with females. Flagellum of male bristle-shaped, with 28 segments, without white annulus with elongate black tyloides on segments 9-15. Clypeus more convex. Claws of tarsi not pectinate. Impression on hind coxae ventrally situated closer to middle. Hypopygium of male short with cut apex and medial fold. White coloration more expanded: internal orbits distributed on face, middle field of face, clypeus in middle, with exception of apex, front margin of pronotum, small spot on metapleurae and spots on paramerae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>