<document id="7332EFBC377ADDED4ED3189ED6B04010" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5277083" _generate="added" approvalRequired="249" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="33" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="199" approvalRequired_for_treatments="17" checkinTime="1630022602320" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="A. M" docDate="2009" docId="03F587F846A0C7C1DAC6FB08F262C221" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2009.41.2.1317-1608.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 41 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Poecilostictus cothurnatus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="182" lastPageNumber="1499" masterDocId="FFCCFF804614C777DA74FFFCF650C675" masterDocTitle="Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)" masterLastPageNumber="1608" masterPageNumber="1317" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" updateTime="1630025500068" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="6FF3D59E1350955763AD19BD5C83C1B2" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2DA383FB7736D7CBC552A4CE92E1C619">
<mods:title id="F6390249556553C6C983C0FD45F82103">Illustrated key to the tribes of subfamilia Ichneumoninae and genera of the tribe Platylabini of world fauna (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="601C3AB6D19153B381837174F9487D3E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3FF69FC766D75CB73E6E45B51DD401D8">
<mods:roleTerm id="897935DB624E00CA9731015B779413D8">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="362748E7A7EB18DFECC8E09FD30F069A">A. M</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7D4FD3A95E6BDF3050FDEED99BACFD56">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="97D777D44D4C9051F547AC63265E701F" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C28D42EB558DDB0903B9EEAE1BE42D8">
<mods:title id="E38FB239B043535CC701995819311027">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="54B852EBF39F50393A2827CC69694D9E">
<mods:date id="4D94DB500CE0DE4A9481CCC4F00D5745">2009</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3DA054559282D31851F21BD49E131700" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="EBB1C6CB27C2BA6D207E368B186C403E">2009-12-18</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="8FCEC0D02B340727CE92FB8DFDF82CCE" type="volume">
<mods:number id="032A476DA87FC9FB675EAE6A16721F95">41</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F6B259D615F1821D16AD88D921D6B6F4" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11DC549AF539294E9298633173D42A08">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="602CE26FA847CE6363632A3594CBE9FA" unit="page">
<mods:start id="713C11B21F5034758EBE96C4B6657159">1317</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B78DB7E16FFA05A5CD3A6156656F96D5">1608</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="88FCB1F580B97FFBD2C26C59ADFE26A6">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DE1994568ECDBEB25BF57E733063C18B" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5277083</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="71A7746F2A3B62B09D9C7A67B6A52899" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DAD564DB42E9DC88CE752155F8E6BF0" type="Zenodo-Dep">5277083</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="03F587F846A0C7C1DAC6FB08F262C221" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F587F846A0C7C1DAC6FB08F262C221" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F587F846A0C7C1DAC6FB08F262C221" lastPageId="182" lastPageNumber="1499" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">
<subSubSection id="C346656546A0C7C3DAC6FB08F4BBC37F" box="[178,747,1268,1290]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A0C7C3DAC6FB08F4BBC37F" blockId="180.[178,747,1268,1290]" box="[178,747,1268,1290]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">
<heading id="D0AB818246A0C7C3DAC6FB08F4BBC37F" box="[178,747,1268,1290]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" reason="2">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46A0C7C3DAC6FB08F4BBC37F" bold="true" box="[178,747,1268,1290]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D46A0C7C3DAC6FB08F42DC37F" authority="(GRAVENHORST)" baseAuthorityName="GRAVENHORST" box="[178,637,1268,1290]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Poecilostictus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cothurnatus">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46A0C7C3DAC6FB08F795C37F" bold="true" box="[178,453,1268,1290]" italics="true" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">Poecilostictus cothurnatus</emphasis>
(GRAVENHORST)
</taxonomicName>
(Plate 45)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C346656546A0C7C3DAC6FAE0F761C384" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A0C7C3DAC6FAE0F773C323" blockId="180.[178,970,1307,1331]" lastBlockId="180.[178,291,1345,1366]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">
<taxonomicName id="4C5C4D6D46A0C7C3DAC6FAE0F430C345" authority="GRAVENHORST 1829" authorityName="GRAVENHORST" authorityYear="1829" box="[178,608,1308,1328]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Hoplismenus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cothurnatus">
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46A0C7C3DAC6FAE0F7CAC345" box="[178,410,1308,1328]" italics="true" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">Hoplismenus cothurnatus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="EFCD4B1F46A0C7C3DBD4FAE0F430C345" author="GRAVENHORST I" box="[416,608,1308,1328]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" pagination="1 - 827" refId="ref142250" refString="GRAVENHORST I. L. C. (1829): Ichneumonologia Europea. - Vratislaviae, Sum. Auct. 1: 1 - 827." type="journal article" year="1829">GRAVENHORST 1829</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
- Ichneum. Europea 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46A0C7C3D954FAE0F57BC345" bold="true" box="[800,811,1308,1328]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">2</emphasis>
: 426, 428, 
<specimenCount id="9D5AFD6746A0C7C3D9E7FAE3F5CFC341" box="[915,927,1311,1332]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" type="female">♀</specimenCount>
, Ƌ. F e m a l e
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A0C7C3DAC6FA9AF761C384" blockId="180.[178,1085,1382,1521]" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">F l a g e l l u m: Long, slender, with 37 segments, slightly widened and flattened ventrally beyond middle, strongly attenuated toward apex, with white annulus on segments (7)8-12; basal segments moderately long, first segment three times longer than width at apex laterally. Flagellum 1,3 times longer than the front wing and 2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C346656546A0C7C1DAC6F9FDF262C221" lastPageId="182" lastPageNumber="1499" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497" type="description">
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A0C7C2DAC6F9FDF476C497" blockId="180.[178,1085,1536,1587]" lastBlockId="181.[178,1085,219,738]" lastPageId="181" lastPageNumber="1498" pageId="180" pageNumber="1497">H e a d: Head contour from front roundish, slightly narrowed downwards, 1,2 times wider than height; genae convex, slightly narrowed to mandibles, malar space 3,8 times shorter than height of eye; from above head contour transversal, 1,7 times wider than length. Vertex behind hind ocelli from lateral, roundly curved to sharp, low occipital carina; temples behind eyes from above only just narrowed backwards, long, almost equal to longitudinal diameter of eye in middle, from lateral only just narrowed downwards, almost parallel to hind margin of eye; occipital carina from above gradually impressed to hind ocelli, meeting with hypostomal carina almost on mandible base; malar space equal to mandible base width; mandibles strong, slightly evenly narrowed behind base, teeth almost in the same plane; malar space almost equal to mandible base width; clypeus almost flat, transversal, matt (shagreen), not punctured by distinct punctures, in front almost smoothly arcuate rounded, sharply separated from face by suture, 2 times wider than length; clypeal foveae large, deep; labrum rounded, almost not protrude from under clypeus; middle field of face sharply limited and elevated above lateral fields, rather narrow, in middle equal to lateral field breadth; antennal cavities deep, but short, far not reach front ocellus level, without lateral tubercles and with distinct tooth between antennal fossae; ocelli of normal size, rather small, diameter of lateral ocellus almost 1,5 times less than distance from ocellus to eye; ocellar triangle only just expressed. Surface of head and clypeus densely and finely punctured with developed microsculpture, only lateral fields of face slightly shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A1C7C2DAC6FD0EF56DC341" blockId="181.[178,1085,754,1332]" pageId="181" pageNumber="1498">T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long, from above with straight front margin; transverse furrow of pronotum narrow and rather deep. Mesonotum strongly convex, only just longer than width, notauli marked only at base; axillary tongue expressed, but weak; surface of mesonotum densely punctured, matt, with developed microsculpture; subalarum very high, slightly bent upwards, forming deep cavity between subalarum and subalar tubercle; prepectal carina straight, without curve forward; speculum only just expressed, with big, almost merged punctures; area of mesopleural fovea sharply and broadly impressed; mesopleural suture deep, straight, interrupted by only just visible ribs; sternauli only just marked at base, not sculptured; lower part of mesopleurae without sharp bend; surface of mesopleurae very densely punctured to wrinkled, with developed microsculpture, slightly shining; scutellum strongly elevated, carinated laterally up to apex, horizontal part convex with big punctures; declivous surface with very dense punctures, almost matt. Hind margin of metanotum with very thin, almost bacilliform projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum short, from lateral gradually slanted; horizontal part two times shorter than length of area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum distinct, area basalis sharply abrupt, deep; area superomedia sharply transversal, costulae before its middle; areae dentiparae without teeth; coxal carina expressed, but weak; spiracles large, elongated, two times longer than width and equal 0,6 breadth of area at place of spiracle. Surface of propodeum densely wrinklypunctured; metapleurae very densely punctured slightly shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A1C7C2DAC6FAB8F5BDC302" blockId="181.[178,1085,1347,1399]" pageId="181" pageNumber="1498">L e g s: Strong and long. Segments of front and middle tarsi with flattened area ventrally, surface of which some different by structure. Claws thin, gradually curved.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A1C7C2DAC6FA7BF4CFC064" blockId="181.[178,1085,1414,1553]" pageId="181" pageNumber="1498">W i n g s: Areolet quadrangular (rarely almost pentagonal with very narrow base), asymmetrical, external vein of apex longer than internal; stigma narrow, dark; radius almost straight (slightly sinuous), long; radial cell long; nervulus interstitial; ramulus not developed, or in form of slight projection; membrane of wing hyaline, veins dark. Length of front wing 1,2 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A1C7C1DAC6F9DCF70CC425" blockId="181.[178,1085,1568,1590]" lastBlockId="182.[178,1086,219,592]" lastPageId="182" lastPageNumber="1499" pageId="181" pageNumber="1498">A b d o m e n Fromabove rather short, oval, almost parallel sided; second tergite 1,2 times longer than width at apex; tergite 7 cut out along hind margin, ovipositor slightly protrude behind apex of abdomen. Petiolus of first tergite very long, slightly flattened at base from lateral very gradually transform to postpetiolus; lateral carinae of petiolus sharp, interspace between them with ribs; from above petiolus rather sharply broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus distinct, high elevated, not carinated by carinae, with delicate coriaceous sculpture; lateral fields narrow, 4,5 times narrower than middle field. Gastrocoeli slightly impressed, long, thyridia strongly removed from base of tergite, many narrower than interval between them, slightly expressed; lunulae distinct, of moderate size; interval irregularly wrinkled, second tergite in middle coriaceous, at apical third distinctly punctured with developed microsculpture, slightly shining; third tergite very delicate punctured; 5-7th tergites with membranous apex. Hypopygium from lateral triangle with slightly sharpened apex, compressed from sides, but without fold.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A2C7C1DAC6FDA3F7DEC4B8" blockId="182.[178,1085,607,717]" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499">C o l o r a t i o n: Mainly black-brown with yellowish-white pattern: genae broadly, corners of clypeus, internal orbits up to hind ocelli, hind corners of pronotum, membranous strip at apex of tergites 5-7, hind tibiae partially, front tarsi ventrally and hind tarsi completely.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A2C7C1DAC6FD20F579C487" blockId="182.[178,809,732,754]" box="[178,809,732,754]" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499">
S i z e: Body length: 9,2; front wing: 7,9; flagellum: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B46A2C7C1D8A1FD20F575C487" box="[725,805,732,754]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="9.5" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499" unit="mm" value="9.5">9,5 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A2C7C1DAC6FCFEF75CC562" blockId="182.[178,268,770,792]" box="[178,268,770,792]" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499">M a l e:</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A2C7C1DAC6FCDBF77EC27F" blockId="182.[178,1085,807,1034]" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499">Flagellum of males beyond middle not flattened ventrally, with distinct long narrow dark tyloides on segments 8-15, arranged at the place of white annulus disposition. Surface of mesopleurae shining, without microsculpture; apex of abdomen slightly compressed from sides; most part of second tergite, with exception of apex roughly wrinkled; yellow coloration more extensive: internal orbits, genae and face entirely, hind margin and lower corners of pronotum, subalarum, big spot on scutellum, spots on front and middle coxae and trochanters 1 of front and middle legs, tarsi of all legs; main color of all legs ferruginous.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A2C7C1DAC6FBE5F579C25A" blockId="182.[178,809,1049,1071]" box="[178,809,1049,1071]" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499">
S i z e: Body length: 8,2; flagellum: 9,0; front wing: 
<quantity id="4CA49B0B46A2C7C1D8A1FBE5F575C25A" box="[725,805,1049,1071]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="7.2" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499" unit="mm" value="7.2">7,2 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE336EE46A2C7C1DAC6FBC3F262C221" blockId="182.[178,1074,1086,1108]" box="[178,1074,1086,1108]" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499">
B i o l o g y: It is reared by us from pupae of 
<emphasis id="B928EAFC46A2C7C1D8FAFBC2F512C221" box="[654,834,1086,1108]" italics="true" pageId="182" pageNumber="1499">Bupalus piniarius</emphasis>
(L) (TERESHKIN 1997).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>