<document id="DE14B22A68C378192FE342E8291FFA17" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280245" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120183" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280245" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="063B841FA4AC92C4A69EB7E9BA6B8A4F" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys inatos Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="685" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="684" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="896A3BFECA074987CA7DC512CCB5E5AC" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="8C8622A0D7F7A08383C89332EB3BCC7C">
<mods:title id="07D62D3BB58054C8BF9EA21F4770F4AC">The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="E3C749C67C19822111C5E7605C6D07CB" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F424DF30A4C7855DBA61616BF951FA6D">
<mods:roleTerm id="B7C2175E24D7ED8B6FFE7D4C85EB0EDA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3176B30000C20600F260E9A06EE1438D">Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7FFF659824B285346A6C74097784A2EF">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="37DB86E1B1778841F47BC42236BDDA4E" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="587A6E76876D703F047031C52B11CF3B">
<mods:title id="8EED4A66DA0603C28C78765F399186F5">Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="4994B98D3D83A160D78BF35EC85A24E0">
<mods:date id="AD4F36F3F10A8EF204F9ED22861EFDD8">2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="EDF0D52F2EB6EF87E4E390E90DE8F661" type="volume">
<mods:number id="6E246FA1090F5C0A84DAF0B26795D9B4">65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="77A61D415A3697BC556FCC13325EF4E1" unit="page">
<mods:start id="2F628008B526F607AB1C1EBD3F4893D1">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="7DDE0F41845E0AF38BB1F5AF218BEBED">1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="AFE492FB02B458F3FBC3F4024A837691">
<mods:url id="7517ADB41F353015CE95C56A3C9DA50F">http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="36D4DA2B2EC0E1170521C427AD0C618C">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="EE4271FF2E2AC82FE0EB0F44F028A1F4" type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="A1950AF814FA5F64738B5318D0169EFA" type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="063B841FA4AC92C4A69EB7E9BA6B8A4F" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280245" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120183" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280245" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:063B841FA4AC92C4A69EB7E9BA6B8A4F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/063B841FA4AC92C4A69EB7E9BA6B8A4F" lastPageNumber="685" pageNumber="684">
<subSubSection id="2FB0EFD6E9F12FCEA8D0F740C9D80978" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="FAFC3AF9CB5B89E2DAB48A697C99DBEB" pageNumber="684">
<taxonomicName id="55FD93BC579AE242B754AD05A27F9D7F" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155863" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys inatos Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys inatos Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="684" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="inatos">Strumigenys inatos Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="0B0DF2768F1EC985AC916A308B850055" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="42B24F5ABDCD5A2F5A289F5BD8668B9E" type="description">
<paragraph id="AF0CB1533B7AAD67889F17FB4C412AE3" pageNumber="684">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 2.3, HL 0.55, HW 0.43, CI 79, ML 0.28, MI 52, SL 0.37, SI 85, PW 0.26, AL 0.60. Characters of scotti-complex. Mandibles in full-face view with outer margins very shallowly and evenly convex, the width of the basal half approximately constant except near the base. Upper scrobe margin evenly and shallowly convex in fullface view, not bordered by a rim or flange, the eyes visible, the apices of the upper scrobe margins confluent with the sides of the occipital lobes through an even curve, without an angle separating the two. Maximum diameter of eye slightly greater than maximum width of scape, 4 - 5 ommatidia in longest row. Scape narrow and subcylindrical, curved near the base; hairs on leading edge slender, slightly flattened or narrowly spatulate apically. Cephalic dorsum clothed with curved narrow spatulate to spoon-shaped ground-pilosity, the upper scrobe margin fringed with hairs which are similar in shape and size as those on the dorsum. Cephalic dorsum with 6 standing narrow filiform hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. In addition a short erect apicoscrobal hair is present in the holotype and in some of the paratypes. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate. Anterior margin of mesonotum with a pair of standing remiform to clavate hairs. Propodeum with one pair of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Dorsal alitrunk with sparse ground-pilosity that is similar in size and shape as on cephalic dorsum. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and posteriorly gently sloping to the declivity. Metanotal groove shallowly impressed. Anterior mesonotum with a thin carina above the mesothoracic spiracle; mesopleural gland set in a small circular notch. Propodeal tooth triangular, pointed apically and subtended by an inconspicuous, very narrow lamella. Pronotal dorsum longitudinally feebly striolate-rugulose and punctate with a longitudinal carina along dorsal midline. Remainder of dorsal alitrunk reticulate-punctate. Sides of pronotum longitudinally feebly striolate. Pleurae and sides of propodeum smooth, punctate peripherally. Postpetiole disc longitudinally striolate and feebly punctate on lateral margins. In profile ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle an irregular, narrow strip along the base of the peduncle, at deepest less than maximum width of eye. Ventral spongiform tissue of postpetiole moderately developed. Basigastral costulae sharply defined, radiating on each side of a broad central clear area. Dorsal surface of petiole, postpetiole and gaster with standing filiform to remiform hairs. Colour light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="135D350370AEACE174E120B4AB13A2E5" pageNumber="684">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 2.2 - 2.5, HL 0.53 - 0.62, HW 0.40 - 0.45, CI 70 - 78, ML 0.27 - 0.30, MI 44 - 51, SL 0.34 - 0.38, SI 78 - 89, PW 0.26 - 0.29, AL 0.58 - 0.64 (8 measured). Most of the paratype material did not have a standing hair located near the apex of the upper scrobe margin, otherwise the paratype material matched the holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="573A473CDE4D907E1EE957595DDADE5A" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="3EF60233A472D86BEE48DDE33A1C70DB" pageNumber="684">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 9.2 km. WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 14 Â° 45 ' S, 49 Â° 28 ' E, 1200 m., 9. xi. l 994, sifted litter (leaf mold rotten wood), montane rainforest # 1192 (36) - 8 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="80D1DD090F43BFFFA24E1901B97F7F8F" pageNumber="684">Paratypes. 8 workers and 1 queen (dealate) with same data as holotype but coded (2) - 7, (10) - 10, (13) - 6, (29) - 6, (9) - 9, (25) - 5, (40) - 6, (41) - 6 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="823C5332B3E39414A379F6EA3E5C062B" pageNumber="684">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: Mont. d'Ambre 1000 - 1100 m. (W. L. &amp; DE. Brown); R. S. Manongarivo, 12.8 km. 228 Â° SW Antanambao, 780 m. (B. L. Fisher); R. S. Manongarivo, 14.5 km. 220 Â° SW Antanambao, 1175 m. (B. L. Fisher); R. S. Manongarivo, 17.3 km. 218 Â° SW Antanambao, 1580 m. (B. L. Fisher); R. S. Manongarivo, 20.4 km. 219 Â° SW Antanambao, 1860 m. (B. L. Fisher); 9.2 km. WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud 1200 m. (B. L. Fisher); 9.2 km. WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud 1280 m. (B. L. Fisher); 11.0 km. WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud 1565 m. (B. L. Fisher); Bemanevika (A. Peyrieras); 6.9 km. NE Ambanizana, 825 m. (B. L. Fisher); 6.3 km. S Ambanizana, Andranobe, 25 m. (B. L. Fisher); 5.3 km. SSE Ambanizana, Andranobe, 425 m. (B. L. Fisher); 1 km. W Andampibe, Cap Masoala 125 m. (Alperl el al.); 25 km. NNE Ankazobe 1500 m. (P. S. Ward); Perinet &amp; vie. (W. L. Brown); 8 km. E Ivohibe, R. S. Ivohibe 1200 m. (S. Razafimandimby); 6.5 km. ESE Ivohibe, R. S. Ivohibe, 1575 m. (S. Razafimandimby); 8.0 km. NE Ivohibe, 1200 m. (S. Razafimandimby); 40 km. S Ambalavao, Res. Andringitra, 1275 m. (B. L. Fisher); Vohibasia, 780 m. (S. Razafimandimby).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1779A1E2DED96A5250FAEF47DDEBBCC1" type="description">
<paragraph id="D2FFD482B6BFB26F67FE1E7D412576E2" lastPageNumber="685" pageNumber="684">Measurements of this material extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.55 - 0.70, HW 0.40 - 0.53, ML 0.27 - 0.35, MI 48 - 52, SL 0.36 - 0.45 SI 79 - 95 (25 measured). As with many of the paratype specimens, these samples lacked a stiff erect apicoscrobal hair. These samples differ in two aspects from the type material. The specimens from Andronobe and Cap Masoala have erect hairs on mesonotum, petiole, postpetiole and gaster that are distinctly remiform to clavate. In contrast, type-material and other nonparatypic workers had filiform to narrowly clavate hairs. Workers and queens from Ivohibe, were slightly larger than other workers and queens from other localities examined. Perhaps new collections will eventually demonstrate that this widespread species includes distinct localized species, but for the present, 1 consider it best to regard them as a single species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="20FA7E48980502FAA5AEBF56E3F90180" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="461CFAE2F23DE8CBFEB6272173B56BC5" pageNumber="685">
Of the scotti-complex species having the dorsum of petiole node reticulate-punctate 
<taxonomicName id="91EB21245F72D48D3AABBDA2B3BC54A1" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155863" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys inatos Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys inatos Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="685" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="inatos">inatos</taxonomicName>
is distinguished by having:
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9188BD6F31B5D0F013252682B31FE143" pageNumber="685">1 Mesonotum with only a single pair of erect hairs, located at anterior margin.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3201AA6B791BEC5E994625850B5F7698" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="5B5B64BABC504FD99FBA4DD1C936EB77" pageNumber="685">2 Ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle in profile an irregular, narrow strip along the base of the peduncle, its deepest point less than maximum width of eye.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AE83B16C9681DCCF1096F9770B224A8C" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph id="D5D9EEE367ABE16D411BF71C6A77FF1D" pageNumber="685">3 Postpetiole disc not entirely smooth and shiny; disc longitudinally striolate and usually feebly punctate on lateral margins.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="89AAF26351E6BCD7DDB3EB8541EF7007" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="287A88B547874938F66F67A870F23F91" pageNumber="685">4 Anterior half of fist gastral sternite without hairs.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E0F254E5B953F9F314B703FF7F6A6CF0" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="25F89BBB7A6E2828CEA6C74ED43451C1" pageNumber="685">
See under 
<taxonomicName id="AC73AD70A33C51B2E9BF3595CC03A377" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155862" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys glycon Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys glycon Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="685" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="glycon">glycon</taxonomicName>
for further discussion.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>