<document id="5D852D065B281D458771B484758DD7EE" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914" ID-GBIF-Dataset="0e37f739-024b-4e12-a7e0-1aaaaf571dfc" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031411" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-136-47" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-136-47" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 136" ModsDocTitle="Larvae and a new species of Ancyronyx Erichson, 1847 (Insecta, Coleoptera, Elmidae) from Palawan, Philippines, using DNA sequences for the assignment of the developmental stages" checkinTime="1451249787770" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Freitag, Hendrik &amp; Balke, Michael" docDate="2011" docId="083FDD230D5976ABDB6BDB5E79732098" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 136: 47-82" docOrigin="ZooKeys 136" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914" docTitle="Ancyronyx procerus Jaech 1994" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="72" masterDocId="FF89FF98C22CFFB4FFFBFFDEF932FFB9" masterDocTitle="Larvae and a new species of Ancyronyx Erichson, 1847 (Insecta, Coleoptera, Elmidae) from Palawan, Philippines, using DNA sequences for the assignment of the developmental stages" masterLastPageNumber="82" masterPageNumber="47" pageId="22" pageNumber="69" updateTime="1643556418155" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="3B34E0BE2161626B7CF662353EF70524" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="10C7219576892BB199B93E27E0FE1012">
<mods:title id="A4E12640CBC4FFBE6D28AB091EB51C4B">Larvae and a new species of Ancyronyx Erichson, 1847 (Insecta, Coleoptera, Elmidae) from Palawan, Philippines, using DNA sequences for the assignment of the developmental stages</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="814B09D355A162F80B9B85861CD6FF49" type="personal">
<mods:role id="561EB33AE13592617EF1944007E00920">
<mods:roleTerm id="C8490D64ED520BF7C469EBC3BFFD2F02">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="E6611C7E0C8EC33585EF7AB6CB04B0B4">Freitag, Hendrik</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="01B140B1F9150519C654DBA692919CFB" type="personal">
<mods:role id="061C841ABBC3A9CB8E2985897A050BA1">
<mods:roleTerm id="6F4E65A6744DF16936E928B2A57C6697">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="874866B5BF8F8985DBEDBD0B912269EF">Balke, Michael</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="9E47284B6D91F5954067F4A34222ECC7">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="C197D9567C0417B3A6746D34850A3D77" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="F8C87137AE9E9EFFA63FE9347C91F01C">
<mods:title id="CD5AC0D181229F80705981482AC5763E">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="5A5C061109199A63E98500BC0B2F8C78">
<mods:date id="E60AE8270F7FE6748961C6FB31F08957">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="5E6C01E6C955C75FBAEB8599083F937B" type="volume">
<mods:number id="4E03F92039E82F4ECC178A48A3526A0C">136</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="987559C9BC30CC017CB3ACB606712788" unit="page">
<mods:start id="516716D7A1BFA1F48CB4FA22962B5600">47</mods:start>
<mods:end id="91591ECE22E7A954B46C418EC5F957BE">82</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="64B448BBEFC5D8DCF0F1893A6B81AD9E">
<mods:url id="18F1F9B02C1933455CF121D6FD97DEF5">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="AEFC4E1F9DE5D9F5FC54BB1C079440CE">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="E43A6297DBCE665B64894CB88A1186B8" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.136.1914</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="27D2217154E61100782A8FBFF2489334" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-136-47</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="BC33A32C642AABC23B3E653C6938C891" type="ZooBank">39E11554-5C45-4B0A-97EC-3387391E9027</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="083FDD230D5976ABDB6BDB5E79732098" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152031411" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:083FDD230D5976ABDB6BDB5E79732098" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/083FDD230D5976ABDB6BDB5E79732098" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="72" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">
<subSubSection id="47A600BAA22F38BFC7D09FA6917374F2" pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="D8AFCA942DEA9AC55ECCC90B6A2D4F8D" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">
<taxonomicName id="E516B9E8B671FB057FB2617066335B11" LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Ancyronyx_procerus" authority="Jaech, 1994" authorityName="Jaech" authorityYear="1994" class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx procerus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="22" pageNumber="69" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="procerus">
Ancyronyx procerus 
<normalizedToken id="3BDCB2CB57E05D697FFFAA790BD899E3" originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
, 1994
</taxonomicName>
Figs 918
<normalizedToken id="00A547A04269DAEC2C3CEFE66F8D5F1C" originalValue="A–J">A-J</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AA9BFE3B45FD8C47C48C691F4AC06582" pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="B7055636A4548D2F7DEA74DE7D8FFD8E" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">
<taxonomicName id="41FBA258F3CD614E88B985A4ED379464" class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx procerus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="22" pageNumber="69" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="procerus">Ancyronyx procerus</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken id="77F55C323FEEB65F1DBCC094A620CC94" originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
, 1994: 611-613 (adult description); 
<normalizedToken id="92B71EC8D050D21965F0BFFE2F1064B0" originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
, 2003: 259 (new records).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B83EE207820139D830E8CD302F312935" pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="D207DB3C90AD6F6679F7A0188FAD8023" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F5539AF3C9C4FE44DC20BDB274213294" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">
1 L (0.61) (ZSM [FR014]) &quot;PHIL.: Busuanga, Coron; Guadelupe, Balolo R./Brdg. Nat.Rd. km 14; lowld. creek; sec.veget.; run, gravel, CPOM, c.10m asl, 
<geoCoordinate id="BCF9BF0E71DAAB274628BF0240A2F8B4" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="12.028611">12°01'43&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="CF6459126EF9A54712DC1EED2AEC123E" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="120.113335">120°06'48&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
03.2.1995, leg. Freitag (169)M&quot;; 1L (0.63) (NMW) &quot;MALAYSIA, Sarawak, Mulu NP, Long Iman 4.3.1993 leg. M. 
<normalizedToken id="6769682FC43BC9AEB97145525B5E3BFE" originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
(20)&quot;.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="88E7F36F390ACD77F287EC5AE277718B" lastPageId="24" lastPageNumber="71" pageId="22" pageNumber="69" type="larval description (based on 6th instar)">
<paragraph id="3E4558B81DD8FBE4B7C12ED72C8F4D95" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">Larval description (based on 6th instar).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="999EB20A6EE618A70992A7B6DE194299" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">Colour (Fig. 9) predominantly brown; head distinctly darker to almost black dorsally; lateral head, antennal scape, anterior pronotal collar and legs whitish or yellowish pale. Entire ventral side (except for parts of genae), antennal pedicel, anterior margin of pronotum, claws, lateral abdominal projections, small medioposterior areas or entire posterior margin of thoracic and abdominal segments and a median middle portion of abdominal segment IX pale brown to yellowish.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3AF7166A08A97A193F423D90E4FCDBFC" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">
HW c. 0.62 mm, entirely c. 3.7 mm long. Body flattened dorsoventrally, moderately vaulted dorsally, almost flat ventrally, with sagittal line (longitudinal groove from prothorax at least up to 5th abdominal segment). Dorsal side moderately densely covered with setiferous tubercles (Fig. 18A). Ventral side smoother, with scattered setae and few setiferous tubercles (Fig. 18B). Retractable portions of body segments and pronotal collar without setae and tubercles (Fig. 18A). Lateral margins of abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken id="E1DB97E7F609716B5FB2FD8D2EBFE674" originalValue="I–VIII">I-VIII</normalizedToken>
produced laterad forming posterolateral-directed conical projections (Fig. 18C). Projections increasing in size caudad, those of segment VIII c. 3.5 times as long as such on segment I. Rather inconspicuous spiracles present laterally on mesothorax and abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken id="222856A246D85EDE60CFD282E7ABAF2A" originalValue="I–VIII">I-VIII</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CF04096385982CD1416044301989BDB5" lastPageId="24" lastPageNumber="71" pageId="22" pageNumber="69">
Head (Figs 18A, 
<normalizedToken id="27C4E8C15A6C5B225D2B5BF7A8D0339E" originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
) subquadrate, partly retractable, distinctly prognathous, with three anterior-dorsad directed, pointed projections, one each side between antenna and clypeus and one at median frons (Fig. 18A). Frons rather glabrous, only with small and scattered setiferous tubercles. Stemmata arranged as single lateral spot in a glabrous area, slightly exposed. One irregular rim of moderately long setae at ventrolateral head margin (not visible in dorsal view). Frontal suture broadly V-shaped. Frontoclypeal suture uneven, but somewhat straight. Clypeus distally microreticulate, with protuberant anterior seam; without subbasal fringe of setae or tubercles. Ventral side (Fig. 18D) with few scattered setae and an obvious longitudinal crest each side lateral of gula and maxillae. Genae rugose, with asperities and scattered tubercles. Gula with rather inconspicuous asperities. Maxilla (Figs 18D, E) moderately broad; cardo stout, undivided; lateral portion with one median acuminate seta; stipes subrectangular, glabrous, with few short and one long latero-subapical trichoid setae; maxillary palpus (Fig. 18E) four-segmented, approx. as long as stipes broad, distal segment smallest, cylindrical with several apical sensilla of various 
<pageBreakToken id="FB2B2B0CAAAC8C33DA11D98ABAFC8E5D" pageId="23" pageNumber="70" start="start">shape</pageBreakToken>
; predistal segment with lateroapical trichoid seta; galea and lacinia subequal in length and shape, approx. as long as palpus, apically with sensilla. Labium (Figs 18D, E) with broad (about 1.7 times of stipes) mentum (postmentum), broadest at basal half, with median groove most depressed posteriorly, with one pair of moderately long trichoid setae sublaterally at anterior 0.25, one subbasal pair each of spinose and trichoid setae and one pair of short apical lateral teeth. Submentum (prementum) short, transverse, apically convex, with sagittal ridge and one laterobasal pair of setae; ligula inconspicuous with various setae and pegs; labial palpi short, with short and stout palpifer; apical segment similar to that of maxillary palpi, preapical segment with lateral tuft (Fig. 18E). Mandibles not examined. Labrum c. 3 times as wide as long, anterior margin distinctly convex, with a subapical fringe of ramose setae and scattered trichoid and truncate (sensory) setae, proximal portion glabrous. Antenna (Fig. 18F) three-segmented, c. 1/2 as long as head. Peduncle short, about as long as broad, without (visible) dorsolateral fringe of branched trichoid setae; scape cylindrical, longer than pedicel and c. twice as long as broad, with few apical trichoid setae; pedicel cylindrically elongate, comparably short, only slightly longer 
<pageBreakToken id="83743522391A655A09E49E3E43A9E229" pageId="24" pageNumber="71" start="start">than</pageBreakToken>
scape; flagellum and sensorium (broken off in figured specimen) subequal in length, slender, cylindrically elongate, c. five times as long as broad; apex of flagellum with inconspicuous elongate sensillum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0F6DB238DA3AE151660BD6AEE9E103AC" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">Prothorax subquadrate, almost as long as broad, with round signa (glabrous areas) in posterior half and near depressed sagittal line. Meso- and metathorax subtrapezoidal, distinctly broader than long, distinctly shorter than prothorax (Fig. 9); medial longitudinal groove and lateral rims distinctly produced posterolaterad. Venter of prothorax (Fig. 18G) with five sclerites: two oblique anterior, two lateral, and one posteromedial sclerite. Anterior sclerites subtriangular; procoxal cavity closed posteriorly; lateral sclerites posteriorly extend mesad, anteriorly appearing divided by an oblique incomplete suture. Entire anterior and lateral prothoracic venter glabrous, few setiferous tubercles in posterior portions. Venter of meso- and metathorax (Fig. 18G) with six sclerites: two oblique anterior, two subquadrate sclerites anterolateral, two elongate meso-posterolateral sclerites; coxal cavities open posteriad; setiferous tubercles sparse on lateral portion; medial portions almost glabrous. Membrane connecting pro- and mesothoracic venter largely extended medially, appearing almost as a separate sclerite (like a prosternal process in adults). Posterior margin of anterior sclerites with fringe of setiferous tubercles.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="33061BF61AA9B3A2C51141A7628AB76D" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">Legs (Figs 18G, H) stout (compared to larvae of the previous species and adults), similar in shape and length, with scattered trichoid sensilla mainly at femora and tibiae. Coxae large, subtrapezoidal; trochanter shorter, elongately subtrapezoidal, rather slender; femora subtrapezoidal, short; tibiae subcylindrical, broadest basal, distinctly narrower than femur, longer than other segments. Claws elongate, moderately bent, with one subbasal presumably trichoid tooth (broken or invisible in specimen examined).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A05C4D6EA9964A3BBF0131AABA6E5758" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">
Abdomen (Figs 9; 18B, I, J). Segments 
<normalizedToken id="88A7B7B18FB886D350BA78AA4C70C7D5" originalValue="I–VIII">I-VIII</normalizedToken>
similar in shape, broadly subrectangular in dorsal view; terga with depressed sagittal line at least from 1st up to 5th segment. Retractable anterior portion with squamose asperities; posterior terga margins with a rim of squamose setae. Remaining median portions of terga more or less equally covered with setiferous tubercles. Ventral sclerites of segments 
<normalizedToken id="753A33641450CB1009419AB075C7D6E9" originalValue="I–VIII">I-VIII</normalizedToken>
subrectangular, extendingly fused with pleural sclerites from 1st to 8th segment; posterior venter margins with a rim of squamous setae. Segment IX (Figs 18I, J) elongate, subconical (broadest subbasally), subtriangular in cross-section; apex broadly rounded, not emarginate; dorsal and lateral portions densely covered with setiferous tubercles; ventral side with scattered short trichoid setae and some long filiform setae sublaterally (most broken off in specimen figured in Fig. 18J). Operculum (Fig. 18I) subtrapezoidal to subtriangular, less than double as long as broad, medially depressed, rugose. Basal half with small longitudinal ridges and scattered sensilla; apical half with squamose asperities and a lateral rim of trichoid setae; the internally inserted pair of hooks rather small. Gill chamber with long, ramose gill tufts overreaching the opercular margin.
</paragraph>
<caption id="A779768B514FFBA2C600B5B45B36E2FC" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">
<paragraph id="690FFD885DF47081DC5FDEB09124E1A3" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">
Figure 18. 
<taxonomicName id="611AFB87676CC5852D1D6E6D26773336" class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx procerus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="24" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="procerus">Ancyronyx procerus</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken id="D23C3CD9F911D0D1FD172B671633C068" originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
, 1994, larva (SEM photographs): A pronotum and head, dorsal, B detail of abdominal segment III, ventral, C abdominal posterolateral projections, ventral, D head, ventral, E apical portions of labium and maxilla, ventral, F antenna, ventral, G thoracic segments, ventral, H hindleg, ventral, I operculum, ventral, J abdominal segment IX, ventral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2E844135B38322910BDC7D30E9892CFD" pageId="24" pageNumber="71" type="variation between larval instars">
<paragraph id="BCB11084A542C4432151E2D632A19F31" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">Variation between larval instars.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3407F876EE7AB4D2C91E708EBE74A05E" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">The two final instar specimens available do not allow to draw conclusions about variations between the instars.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="56678005787EB139E629482372603B9C" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="72" pageId="24" pageNumber="71" type="larval differential diagnosis">
<paragraph id="2C9C8D14391EF7BEB264DDDEDF565E9E" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">Larval differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="29B7B47868C2FCC44F0571F8987EA491" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="72" pageId="24" pageNumber="71">
The species resembles the previous ones only in very general characters, such as the presence of posterolateral appendages and the distribution 
<pageBreakToken id="296BE01BCECF42FC1A380EA1B286DAD2" pageId="25" pageNumber="72" start="start">of</pageBreakToken>
spiracles. This larva is, however, not torpedo-like elongate and subsemicircular in cross section, but dorsoventrally somewhat depressed, only slightly vaulted dorsally. By this it rather resembles the species 
<taxonomicName id="EE50F82A192ED3DD0F3E579F00AF5C76" class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx variegatus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="72" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="variegatus">Ancyronyx variegatus</taxonomicName>
from North-America than those of the 
<taxonomicName id="05277C587412157AB60DB87AE487A1A5" class="Insecta" family="Elmidae" genus="Ancyronyx" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ancyronyx patrolus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="72" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="patrolus">Ancyronyx patrolus</taxonomicName>
group (Freitag &amp; 
<normalizedToken id="CD9386BCFCF8BB9287511401BB030F89" originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
, 2007, p. 58).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="32053A41D6EBFAAD6751BE43C55A9FCF" pageId="25" pageNumber="72" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="CC7C8DCEBB97CA89E9F2A9EB8457D7AF" pageId="25" pageNumber="72">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AFB3D8BC34B7FC2FAF08882D82652E21" pageId="25" pageNumber="72">
Known from Busuanga, Philippines (recent study; Fig. 20), Malaysia, Brunei and Vietnam (
<bibRefCitation id="A3741E319848E3F1313B5C0F0CB4ECD4" author="Jaech, MA" journalOrPublisher="Revue suisse de Zoologie" pageId="30" pageNumber="77" pagination="601 - 622" title="A taxonomic review of the Oriental species of the genus Ancyronyx Erichson, 1847 (Coleoptera, Elmidae)." volume="101" year="1994">
<normalizedToken id="9318991803362454CE66B79C39032935" originalValue="Jäch">Jaech</normalizedToken>
1994
</bibRefCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>