<document id="9343EF8B2C40DA172C3EFFC1F462BC43" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6232508" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9d63130f-d7a3-4cbf-b2fa-c079654d64c1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119382782" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6232508" _generate="added" checkinTime="1460049246236" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Brailovsky, Harry" docDate="2008" docId="095F87ABCF35FFDA8DE3FE68097BF381" docLanguage="en" docName="zt01936p065.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1936" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@56794250" docStyleName="zootaxa.2007.monograph" docTitle="Diariptus Stal" docType="treatment" docVersion="8" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="61" masterDocId="F566FFD3CF34FFD88D74FFCD0B28F633" masterDocTitle="Revision of the genus Diariptus Stål (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Coreidae: Meropachydinae: Spathophorini)" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="59" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" updateTime="1645574515480" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="A2392EAF248219C03E931BEC33EBE12D" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="9E12C16006BEAA9BFDD2950470F39C36">
<mods:title id="A8DA59C42E13277020B32D7BA5A720A1">Revision of the genus Diariptus Stål (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Coreidae: Meropachydinae: Spathophorini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="7E8BBACD1C5440CB9368442C08717CAB" type="personal">
<mods:role id="5A3D819C774F5AF8F0DA8A56212CBE4C">
<mods:roleTerm id="C1B76223F10893C299BB806678B4362A">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C48E1E78463447D24AF0EE65D2C04AC2">Brailovsky, Harry</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="B2B5E1AD5EEE096DBC83AE13E675D65E">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="020FFF6C3BBD9CF599418E05A41C1C81" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="F9FB2CBBD0D9EAAC5186D7E596CA91E8">
<mods:title id="02913DF66B0D0ED6247D560C16025478">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D09C4C1F26CDCFF670EC124340F17C71">
<mods:date id="A34511833A8DA332464DF43CAD18CAE3">2008</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="662C8B0434CC3B480FD56F3C60EB4A5E" type="volume">
<mods:number id="D6B647CDBEA52AC0B2A1853F8471B522">1936</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="0841FA3C3BFFA08AD870408C1B60AD50" unit="page">
<mods:start id="60D050862CE193F377836EC3F011EE00">59</mods:start>
<mods:end id="3E0FEAF87A7BD1A4503928831155DA37">65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="F30F3ADEFF3E623EC3A1DA5F7DCC42FA">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="9F9EB541A0698D48FDCF32FD51CC8F31" type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.184961</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="7B028741F65D72AB8500B3762F7098DE" type="GBIF-Dataset">9d63130f-d7a3-4cbf-b2fa-c079654d64c1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="1CDE800D4242AD14DC1AB5DA17995116" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="CE2D2036B700DE94C2971701B7EBB193" type="Zenodo-Dep">184961</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="095F87ABCF35FFDA8DE3FE68097BF381" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6232508" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119382782" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6232508" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:095F87ABCF35FFDA8DE3FE68097BF381" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/095F87ABCF35FFDA8DE3FE68097BF381" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">
<subSubSection id="C9EC6536CF35FFD98DE3FE680A16F78C" box="[151,318,421,447]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="814936BDCF35FFD98DE3FE680A16F78C" blockId="1.[151,318,421,447]" box="[151,318,421,447]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">
<heading id="DA0181D1CF35FFD98DE3FE680A16F78C" bold="true" box="[151,318,421,447]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" reason="1">
<taxonomicName id="46F64D3ECF35FFD98DE3FE680A16F78C" authority="Stal" authorityName="Stal" box="[151,318,421,447]" class="Insecta" family="Coreidae" genus="Diariptus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF35FFD98DE3FE680A16F78C" bold="true" box="[151,318,421,447]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF35FFD98DE3FE680A21F78C" bold="true" box="[151,265,421,447]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">Diariptus</emphasis>
Stål
</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C9EC6536CF35FFD98DE3FE3D0A85F434" box="[151,429,496,519]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="814936BDCF35FFD98DE3FE3D0A85F434" blockId="1.[151,429,496,519]" box="[151,429,496,519]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">
<treatmentCitationGroup id="A1E61193CF35FFD98DE3FE3D0A85F434" box="[151,429,496,519]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">
<taxonomicName id="46F64D3ECF35FFD98DE3FE3D0A80F434" authority="Stal, 1859: 452" authorityName="Stal" authorityPageNumber="452" authorityYear="1859" box="[151,424,496,519]" class="Insecta" family="Coreidae" genus="Diariptus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF35FFD98DE3FE3D0BD5F434" box="[151,253,496,519]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">Diariptus</emphasis>
<treatmentCitation id="005710ACCF35FFD98C77FE3D0A80F434" author="Stal" box="[259,424,496,519]" page="452" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" year="1859">
<bibRefCitation id="E5674B4CCF35FFD98C77FE3D0A5BF434" author="Stal" box="[259,371,496,519]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" refString="Stal, C. (1859) Till kannedomen om Coreida. O fversigt af Kongliga Vetenskaps Akademiens Forhandlingar, Stockholm 16, 449 - 476." type="journal article" year="1859">
Stål, 
<number id="373E249ACF35FFD98C4EFE3D0A5BF434" box="[314,371,496,519]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" value="1859.0">1859</number>
</bibRefCitation>
: 
<number id="373E249ACF35FFD98C09FE3D0A80F434" box="[381,424,496,519]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" value="452.0">452</number>
</treatmentCitation>
</taxonomicName>
.
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C9EC6536CF35FFDA8DE3FDFA0BEFF5C9" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" type="description">
<paragraph id="814936BDCF35FFDA8DE3FDFA0BEFF5C9" blockId="1.[151,1437,567,2034]" lastBlockId="2.[151,1437,152,1458]" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="61" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF35FFD98DE3FDFA0A64F462" bold="true" box="[151,332,567,593]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">Redescription.</emphasis>
Body elongate, parallel-side. Head. Wider than long, pentagonal, nondeclivent, dorsally flat; tylus unarmed, apically globose, raised, extending anterior to and higher laterally than juga; juga unarmed; space between antenniferous tubercles filled by tylus, and space between them almost equal to width of one tubercle; antenniferous tubercles unarmed, border entire, continuous, almost semicircular, prominent; side of head anterior to eye unarmed; antennal segment I robust, cylindrical, thickest, slightly curved outward, longer than head; segments II and III cylindrical, slender, and IV fusiform; antennal segment III shortest, II shorter than I, and I longer or shorter than IV; ocelli close to eyes; preocellar pit obliquely deep; eyes hemispheric, protuberant, upper margin located at same level or above vertex and frontal area; postocular tubercle indistinct; mandibular plate absent; buccula squarish, raised, short, entire, not projecting beyond antenniferous tubercles, meeting posteriorly; rostrum reaching posterior margin of prosternum; rostral segment III shortest, I longest, and II subequal or shorter than IV; ventral surface below, and behind buccula without tubercle. Thorax. Pronotum. Wider than long, trapeziform, slightly declivent, with posterior border subequal to base of scutellum in width; collar wide; anterior margin smooth, curved; frontal angles produced forward as a short or bifid tubercle; humeral angles slightly exposed, obtuse; anterolateral margins obliquely straight, uniformly nodulose; posterolateral margin sinuate, smooth; triangular process broad, subtriangular; posterior border straight, smooth; pronotal disk abruptly punctuate, transversely striate. Prosternum deeply concave, posterior third in front of the area between fore legs produced into narrow, acute projection; mesosternum flat, anterior third in front of the area between fore legs, raised into broad and blunt keel, posterior third between middle legs raised into squarish plate, laterally projected into two short and robust arms; metasternum wide, rectangular, anterior border bifid, each tubercle small, broad, blunt, close to mesocoxae; mesosternal arms facing oneto-one to metasternal anterior tubercles; posterior border of metasternum straight, entire; propleura and mesopleura punctate, anterior margin raised into short tuberculate plate; metapleura punctate, flat; metathorax laterally expanded, in dorsal view with metapleura, including meta-acetabulae visible; metathoracic peritreme located near lower margin of metapleuron, bifid, anterior and posterior lobe earlike, and almost same size; evaporative area well developed. Legs. 
<collectingCountry id="F9E1762DCF35FFD98F28FA3509B2F021" box="[604,666,1528,1554]" name="India" pageId="1" pageNumber="60">Hind</collectingCountry>
coxae separated, distance between them 
<number id="373E249ACF35FFD9890EFA350FC0F021" box="[1146,1256,1528,1554]" pageId="1" pageNumber="60" value="1.6" valueMax="1.8" valueMin="1.4">1.4 to 1.8</number>
times diameter of one coxa, and apically with broad and blunt tubercle, located on external surface; fore and middle femora relatively slender, ventrally armed with two rows of short and acute spines, or blunt tubercles; hind femur remarkably incrassate (less in females), attaining posterior third of abdominal sternite V; dorsal surface with three rows of blunt tubercles, and one row of strong and acute spines, running from base to apex, and ventrally armed with two rows of strong spines running from base to apex; fore and middle tibiae unarmed, sulcate, widened distally; male hind tibia flattened, almost same size as length of hind femur, basal portion conspicuously curved (in females weakly curved), outer margin sulcate, not expanded, inner margin not expanded, armed with one row of acute spines, running from middle third to apex, including a broad and large spine near middle third, and one acute spine at distal third. Scutellum.- Longer than wide or wider than long, triangular, shorter than clavus, with wide transversal depression near middle third; disk without triradiate ridge; apex rounded to subacute, raised; lateral margins emarginated. Hemelytra.- Macropterous, reaching posterior margin or apex of last abdominal segment; clavus and claval suture not covered by scutellum; costal margin emarginated; apical margin obliquely straight, with apical angle narrowly, very long, extending beyond middle third of hemelytral membrane. Abdomen.- Parallel-side, gradually narrowing; connexivum scarcely higher than tergum; male connexival segments sulcate, with outer margin of segments II, III and VII unarmed, and IV to VI unarmed or uniformly nodulose, and inner margins of segments II, III and VII unarmed, and IV to VI uniformly nodulose; male posterior angle of outer connexival segments II and III unarmed, and IV to VII unarmed or with short and broad tubercle; inner connexival segments II and III projected into short and broad spine, segment VII entire, without spine or tubercle, segments IV and V with large and acute spine directed outward and slightly backward, and segment VI with medium size and acute spine directed outward and slightly backward; female connexival segments sulcate, outer and inner margins II to VII unarmed; female posterior angle of outer connexival segments II to VII unarmed, and inner connexival segments II to VI projected into short and broad tubercle, and VII unarmed; abdominal sterna without medial furrow; abdominal spiracle III to VII subelliptical and closer to anterior border; abdominal sternite II visible. Integument.- Body surface rather dull, and including antennal segments and legs sparsely clothed with short decumbent to suberect setae; head, pro-, meso-, and metasternum, connexival segments, and abdominal sterna impunctate; acetabulae, pro-, meso-, and metapleura, clavus, and corium densely to finely punctate; pronotal disk densely punctate and striate; scutellum smooth to finely punctate, with apex yellowish cream. Male genital capsule.- Posteroventral edge with deep and wide U-shaped excavation, delimited by a pair of raised sinuate arms, one on each side; midpoint protruding as a large squarish plate, with lateral angles tuberculate (
<figureCitation id="19CD2A38CF36FFDA8997FC8D0E04F569" box="[1251,1324,832,858]" captionStart="FIGURE 1 – 10" captionStartId="3.[151,255,1885,1909]" captionTargetBox="[416,1166,854,1851]" captionTargetId="figure@3.[408,1178,847,1859]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURE 1 – 10. Diariptus spp. 1 – 2. Scutellum. 1. Diariptus hexacanthus Stål. 2. Diariptus napoanus n. sp. 3. Caudal view of male genital capsule of Diariptus napoanus n. sp. 4 – 6. Abdomen. 4. Diariptus napoanus n. sp. (male). 5. Diariptus hexacanthus Stål (male). 6. Diariptus napoanus n. sp. (female). 7 – 10. Paramere. 7 – 8. Diariptus napoanus n. sp. 9 – 10. Diariptus haxacanthus Stål." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/184962/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">
Fig. 
<number id="373E249ACF36FFDA8868FC8D0E04F569" box="[1308,1324,832,858]" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" value="3.0">3</number>
</figureCitation>
). Female genital plates.- Abdominal sternite VII with plica and fissure; plica narrowed, hard to see; gonocoxae I enlarged dorsoventrally, inner and upper margin rounded, in caudal view closed; paratergite VIII triangular, spiracle visible; paratergite IX squarish, longer than paratergite VIII, in caudal view with inner third contiguous.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C9EC6536CF36FFDA8DB2FBCA097BF381" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="814936BDCF36FFDA8DB2FBCA097BF381" blockId="2.[151,1437,152,1458]" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF36FFDA8DB2FBCA0A7DF212" bold="true" box="[198,341,1031,1057]" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Comments.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="46F64D3ECF36FFDA8C14FBC50970F211" authority="Stal, 1859" authorityName="Stal" authorityYear="1859" box="[352,600,1032,1058]" class="Insecta" family="Coreidae" genus="Diariptus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF36FFDA8C14FBC50AF8F212" box="[352,464,1032,1057]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Diariptus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="E5674B4CCF36FFDA8CA8FBC50970F211" author="Stal" box="[476,600,1032,1058]" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" refString="Stal, C. (1859) Till kannedomen om Coreida. O fversigt af Kongliga Vetenskaps Akademiens Forhandlingar, Stockholm 16, 449 - 476." type="journal article" year="1859">
Stål, 
<number id="373E249ACF36FFDA8F6FFBC50970F211" box="[539,600,1032,1058]" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" value="1859.0">1859</number>
</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
, resembles 
<taxonomicName id="46F64D3ECF36FFDA8F9DFBC50F38F211" authority="Bergroth, 1912" authorityName="Bergroth" authorityYear="1912" box="[745,1040,1032,1058]" class="Insecta" family="Coreidae" genus="Allopeza" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF36FFDA8F9DFBC50878F212" box="[745,848,1032,1057]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Allopeza</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="E5674B4CCF36FFDA8E2FFBC50F38F211" author="Bergroth" box="[859,1040,1032,1058]" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" refString="Bergroth, E. (1912) Notes on Coreidae and Neididae. Annales de la Societe Entomologique de Belgique 66, 76 - 93." type="journal article" year="1912">
Bergroth, 
<quantity id="460E9B58CF36FFDA8EA1FBC50F38F211" box="[981,1040,1032,1058]" metricMagnitude="1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.85648" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" unit="in" value="1912.0">1912</quantity>
</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
in general aspects; these genera have the antennal segments II and III cylindrical, not apically dilated; body length shorter than 
<quantity id="460E9B58CF36FFDA8986FBFD0E60F279" box="[1266,1352,1072,1098]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.7" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" unit="mm" value="27.0">27 mm</quantity>
; posterior border of pronotum with triangular process; space between antenniferous tubercles filled by tylus; and humeral angles slightly exposed, obtuse, and never produced laterally into winglike expansions. 
<taxonomicName id="46F64D3ECF36FFDA8864FB4D0EA8F2AA" box="[1296,1408,1152,1177]" class="Insecta" family="Coreidae" genus="Diariptus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF36FFDA8864FB4D0EA8F2AA" box="[1296,1408,1152,1177]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Diariptus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is distinguished by having the posterior angle of the inner connexival segments IV to VI of males projected into large and acute spine, directed outward and slightly backward, and in females projected into short and broad tubercle; the hind femur gradually incrassate from base toward apex; the fore and middle femora dorsally smooth; and the buccula quadrate, and conspicuously raised. In 
<taxonomicName id="46F64D3ECF36FFDA8EFCFAED08C7F30A" box="[904,1007,1312,1337]" class="Insecta" family="Coreidae" genus="Allopeza" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="B382EAAFCF36FFDA8EFCFAED08C7F30A" box="[904,1007,1312,1337]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Allopeza</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
the posterior angle of inner connexival segments IV to VI of both sexes are unarmed; the hind femur strongly clavate, swollen distally, with proximal half slender; the fore and middle femora dorsally granulate from base to apex; and buccula enlarged anteroposteriorly, and scarcely raised.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>