<document id="DE0D6720CA2A36B925076289280E29C9" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047632" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9D754777-E030-44AA-927F-60E971B43DD7" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="11EAE3BAD0243A3EFB7872145565C6D7" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio obturationis Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="9D754777-E030-44AA-927F-60E971B43DD7" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="153" lastPageNumber="154" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="150" pageNumber="151" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="88C5143E5AA4649EA0FD8DA4A23DD75D" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="31C3EC10B695E02837DC59137EA74259">
<mods:title id="949D76239F56E224A3C644C4C826A458">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="F85FBD9D6D7FEE530FC0D0E5B99AEEF3" type="personal">
<mods:role id="8EF634426A99F63FBB222FDDBFE46A2D">
<mods:roleTerm id="C86EC0BDE1B080A65362E989DD6533AE">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1076E87AF55DB89C03038F0A55A74C80">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="A137A2EA5301EBF10C57A4E0CFB4F968" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D2EF76F0D87AAF0ACA357474CFE2DCCC">
<mods:roleTerm id="E8CFF376584062240A181371C6FECC41">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="706FD210AA634289C054090215DB5700">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="070453CC9F954C4B452954F63A8C357E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="E0C325FE5C2787AA1745921B0B954CA4">
<mods:roleTerm id="7E46E43324FA06113A6C8EA94D9A331E">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="6F3C6C34AE5F8739A10F2C04566295B8">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="A6C68594177D46ABD12B53799F28A844" type="personal">
<mods:role id="4C9E5C4CC00B9778945DC2F300C713F1">
<mods:roleTerm id="A85B156F4E159DDE651801227B8EC958">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="43A23C538F266F4B63AC37FD4D630DC0">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="263F9297A6D6C25B2F34ACBA76506508">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="C4619C44CB7BE06FDBBA58DFE1FF99F9" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="B8E45C7C6C74B738A999B422120B15BD">
<mods:title id="CDC4EDFDD98B669013C9DFF2FB9EA9C2">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="E8186AF4018E73CE4BE5115085E18A58">
<mods:date id="CE3E3C7FDF0158936D46A2CCD5C2C25E">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="8AC02DC0107CA2AA00EE108916BA3B8D" type="volume">
<mods:number id="0BE95CBA96FF7E858BE69C867A510F79">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="67F0EE2AF3F965D7D5234E605E2083EC" unit="page">
<mods:start id="3669737E0C612D6A8EA347D57C4344B9">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="8DAB7F2E61FAF7D12DBE7B7758BD8E9F">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="991F3C4777DCF0B39701AAB7632F1501">
<mods:url id="D7A9C8A62AD1F145A8C4A746EE450A2B">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="A44A82781BE342670DE36123DDDC24AA">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="E6587F799177097EB595C32F60558BA9" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="A48121C21B0A20A710EC1ACF6E3D5630" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="CD6F4EFC52191F21AC0576CFD3BCE3B0" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="11EAE3BAD0243A3EFB7872145565C6D7" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047632" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9D754777-E030-44AA-927F-60E971B43DD7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/11EAE3BAD0243A3EFB7872145565C6D7" lastPageId="153" lastPageNumber="154" pageId="150" pageNumber="151">
<subSubSection id="B574891867819E272E574C8C6FE65C55" pageId="150" pageNumber="151" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="7F38C43B2DF0D6C3027E4D370D1C27E8" pageId="150" pageNumber="151">
<taxonomicName id="0D36EF9D2DB4100E15A95DAE20B57507" LSID="http://zoobank.org/9D754777-E030-44AA-927F-60E971B43DD7" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio obturationis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="150" pageNumber="151" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="obturationis">Oxyscelio obturationis Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="2BA85FD1F2B0504C9DE4192F6202158C" pageId="150" pageNumber="151">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 235-240; Morphbank73
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9CCC7E554BB4F92143AFA56238B4F30A" lastPageId="153" lastPageNumber="154" pageId="150" pageNumber="151" type="description">
<paragraph id="9261335194268CF9E8EBA1F9C837F296" pageId="150" pageNumber="151">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BC12A2634F134C1C500BB2C9CFDA5648" pageId="150" pageNumber="151">Female. Body length 2.8-3.8 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E5E6D0EAB2CECFDB0F79EA74131C6220" pageId="150" pageNumber="151">Radicle color and shade: same as scape, both yellowish or reddish. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: shorter than pedicel; as long as pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CCCC4EB797E91F38AD62EDE4898F8E1E" pageId="151" pageNumber="152">
<pageBreakToken id="6ED7A38A6B3381A679AC23137C23A4E9" pageId="151" pageNumber="152" start="start">Ventral</pageBreakToken>
clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: present as multiple regular elevations. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: uniformly rounded dorsally. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2C395E6BC79CBCDC1B28682AD4EC1C0B" pageId="151" pageNumber="152">Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a ruga. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T6. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, but parallel for a short distance anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4DE6E3D09D14AAB604F10FF7265732BF" lastPageId="152" lastPageNumber="153" pageId="151" pageNumber="152">
T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: densely foveolate, longitudinal sculpture irregular. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 
<pageBreakToken id="C6F15799095D5434490320B02ED7A458" pageId="152" pageNumber="153" start="start">sculpture</pageBreakToken>
: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="45A03FE447CEFE847D08120EDE04FB36" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">
<pageBreakToken id="E92ABDB05D10D727A65387BF202DD151" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Body length 3.3 mm (n=1). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching apex of T5. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: weakly emarginate.
</paragraph>
<caption id="3137785563C82C246214C525F5608B5F" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">
<paragraph id="FC0598D29F395D54BEBED77198E95B81" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">
Figures 235-240. 
<taxonomicName id="A84D71EDB8DAF3BF7BA0B309BE39988B" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio obturationis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="obturationis">Oxyscelio obturationis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 439017) 235 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 236 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 237 Head, anterior view 238 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 442295) 239 Antenna 240 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank73
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AFD7B22BCDE18C0CA3B7C14B2852B6E7" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="4FBF3C9331BB810BB8AC9B9C20986FFB" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1374054F0A838349E30CF0D49222E536" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">
Both sexes: Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum black. Frontal depression shallow, transverse carinae absent or interrupted; submedian carina indicated by a set of irregular elevations or weak carinae. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by sharp carina. Occipital carina complete, convex medially. Mesoscutal midlobe with many fine longitudinal rugae posteriorly. Metascutellum deeply concave, broad and short, projecting dorsally. Coxa darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4, A5 broader than long. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. T6 without metasomal flanges. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T6 or exceed metasomal apex. Male: A4, A11 longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach metasomal apex. T7 much broader than long, slightly concave apically, without posterior projections. 
<taxonomicName id="576A8F1D2C668AC4DCB3D1F3CE74CBA0" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio obturationis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="obturationis">Oxyscelio obturationis</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName id="187AE690D8F8CFA98A6CE33340B4ED0C" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio scutorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="scutorum">Oxyscelio scutorum</taxonomicName>
, and in some specimens can have raised mesoscutellar sculpture similar to that species. However, the strong rows of longitudinal rugae and overall stouter body shape can help distinguish these species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A4FC382F4788B72B79BD2E6B94538BD3" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="04955E5A1B5CE16CB7F593C61427762B" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2BB704132CE9C57BB76115CB46FBD60F" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">Latin noun, genitive case, meaning &quot;a plug.&quot; Refers to the compact, stout body shape.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4FD3398D4AFC886737BB7DBE0E900AB7" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="F1429795D8D6FC6566D01554CE1718AC" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6FE44ED46E3FF506AE5372B75D1D7D6A" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307094]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3F6EBFDADE8A5D8AE3E693E3CBE67398" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="106C79054B8FBE3ED05CC6543E44F4D3" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="82FFB73C29981DF5432A180861DF0611" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, via Samford, open forest, Stony Creek, 
<geoCoordinate id="129A1DA35EEC09FDF01AC157ACC4CDC8" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-27.333334">27°20'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="7EEFF75E130A4187F73B607649D011F1" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="152.8">152°48'E</geoCoordinate>
, 2.
<normalizedToken id="422162C69B74FBC3DCC55054777BF322" originalValue="II–">II-</normalizedToken>
8.IV.1995, interception trap, H. Janetzki &amp; G. Monteith, OSUC 439017 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 26 females, 1 male, ANIC DB 32-020096, 32-020114, 32-020115, 32-020116, 32-020117, OSUC 439004, OSUC 439005, OSUC 439006, OSUC 439007, OSUC 439008, OSUC 439009, OSUC 439010, OSUC 439011, OSUC 439012, OSUC 439013, OSUC 439014, OSUC 439015, OSUC 439016, OSUC 439018, OSUC 439019, OSUC 439022 (ANIC); OSUC 451324 (QDPC); OSUC 439020, QM Reg. No. T35153 (QMBA); OSUC 439021, 439023, 451323 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>