<document id="61CD767EEB657B0413BD9313BEC47CAF" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6289167" ID-GBIF-Dataset="da733677-6530-4a1b-b657-6c8861e011c4" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134856" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6289167" ModsDocAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." ModsDocID="20597" checkinTime="1243372031551" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." docDate="1922" docId="1358D1E8EA0739935EAAD74E2663F6C3" docLanguage="en" docName="20597_3" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 45" docSource="http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097" docTitle="Camponotus (Myrmoturba) maguassa Wheeler, 1922, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="238" masterDocId="A3DBBB852C51D8D8BF05CD746529E30A" masterDocTitle="The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition." masterLastPageNumber="269" masterPageNumber="39" pageNumber="237" updateTime="1645827484690" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="97925E0B6A694C82E1B594D3DBF2D617" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2A399DE266D49F76911EBD51056BA3AF">
<mods:title id="7907431FD7E9386024C6DF654A597A4F">The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="E0B3DD12F3A5FCFFF679CA97C769DC03" type="personal">
<mods:role id="C9A5FB88421424DFE283D09DA6845D70">
<mods:roleTerm id="A8F2AF0347BF4BF49FD36F1D80A82787">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="42651322EF0595D7223C15533F419459">Wheeler, W. M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="2557A05D6A858AB142C7011DA27C0875">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="1F6362E549CB25602C303B40B01250A0" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="68C421CA2493EDB46988B0467F307F52">
<mods:title id="C79291E140C58A106614EFAD801FA2A8">Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="A0B34B7FA16FBF120783F1F8E934467A">
<mods:date id="A2C2478385EFA05D82FBC5B584E806B3">1922</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="186B81C421B1326DBEFDBD5EDBA428A0" type="volume">
<mods:number id="3C172ABBE272631095664297252C7444">45</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="556F56C09F6102E440327C7DFDA2C98B" unit="page">
<mods:start id="32C96537166F894007C98D1A8068FB05">39</mods:start>
<mods:end id="6AF62432E8025F88C0295E0EFEF631D5">269</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="1154BA73A133EC0F186D32A8C66BAE01">
<mods:url id="B978BD330AE35F2CBD38FCEF1F208DF2">http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="413CD43BC47D8A89518D196EBB3DF601">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="4A6ED25DAFBE5DA2A5B4EEBF31B3EA67" type="HNS-PUB">20597</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="1358D1E8EA0739935EAAD74E2663F6C3" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6289167" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134856" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6289167" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1358D1E8EA0739935EAAD74E2663F6C3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1358D1E8EA0739935EAAD74E2663F6C3" lastPageNumber="238" pageNumber="237">
<subSubSection id="35B2EC8F0A5E83273ACCD88A51E2BD46" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="9A020164F35B71D9C0D5EEE304626C58" pageNumber="237">
<taxonomicName id="EEBC1E85BF0B4C07FBB53574F6287614" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:135700" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Camponotus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Camponotus (Myrmoturba) maguassa Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="237" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maguassa" subGenus="Myrmoturba">Camponotus (Myrmoturba) marguassa</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="F57D534D014B8B6D95B508FABF56F309" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="79BDB8FE62ECB0DAB3FC238ACBF851F6" type="description">
<paragraph id="D959B0BA396933DE5D9CB01C9BDCB760" pageNumber="237">Major worker.- Length 9 to 10 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="416D7B6C69A34CA8F950B3675F728395" pageNumber="237">Head rather small, subreetangular, as long (1.3 mm. without the mandibles) as broad, a little narrower in front than behind, with straight posterior and very feebly convex lateral borders. Eyes rather large and convex, situated about their length from the posterior border when the head is seen from the front. Mandibles moderately convex, coarsely 6-toothed. Clypeus sharply carjnate behind, rather deeply emarginate on each side of the median lobe, which is short, with straight border, distinctly dentate at the corners. Frontal area subtriangular, indistinct behind; frontal groove pronounced; frontal carina; approximated anteriorly. Antenna; slender, the scapes straight, terete, not enlarged at the tape, reaching about twofifths their length beyond the posterior border of the head. Pronotum flattened above, its sides distinctly marginatc anteriorly; mesonotum evenly arched in profile; metanotum indistinct; epinotum with subequal base and declivity, both surfaces straight and sloping, meeting at a rounded obtuse angle. Petiole rather high, oval when seen from behind, in profile with flattened anterior and posterior surfaces, its superior border rather charp and entire. Gaster and legs as usual, hind tibia; nearly cylindrical, only very slightly compressed, without a row of bristles along their flexor surfaces.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1DACDF6B6CC04F67157369C934D13300" pageNumber="238">Body subopaque, the petiole, gaster and legs more shining. Mandibles coarsely and sparsely punctate, their tips striated, their bases sharply shagreened. Head very densely, evenly and finely punctate, so that it appears granular; the clypeus, cheeks, front, and vertex also with large, scattered, irregular, piligerous punctures. Sculpture of the thorax like that of the head but finer, especially on the pleurae; the dorsal surface with coarse, sparse, piligerous punctures. Gaster finely, sharply and transversely shagreened, with coarse, sparse, transverse piligerous punctures. These have minutely papillate anterior borders so that the coarse hairs seem to rise from small projections. Legs finely shagreened or coriaceous.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2472B57796461C1193EEA98A5539F386" pageNumber="238">Hairs fulvous red, coarse, erect, rather abundant, long on the dorsal surface of the head, thorax, and gaster, somewhat shorter on the gula and petiolar border, still shorter but suberect on the cheeks, scapes and legs. Pleurae, anterior and posterior surfaces of petiole hairless. Pubescence rather coarse, very sparse, visible on the cheeks and gaster.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CC0282F73CE3117A7298EE33F13358FA" pageNumber="238">Brownish black; funiculi, tips of scapes, legs, including the coxae, petiole, and gaster rich castaneous, the legs and funiculi slightly paler. Worker minor.- Length 5 to 7.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DD4AA27A1DC8B7A413C620744E4EEA5D" pageNumber="238">Differing from the major worker in the shape of the head, which is longer than broad, with straight, parallel sides and broadly convex posterior border. The eyes are more convex, the antennal scapes longer, extending somewhat more than half their length beyond the posterior corners of the head. The clypeal lobe has more rounded corners.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A1DDD3342932004A893EDAD78CC4F729" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="9742A21A677062C0413877B112A0DEF7" pageNumber="238">
Described from numerous specimens from two colonies taken at Avakubi (Lang and Chapin). According to a note accompanying one lot, &quot;these ants are said to be common in the forest in the decayed wood of large trees. Native name ' 
<taxonomicName id="DE789FB521F286DF2D6C64EC545DE85B" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:26919" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Camponotus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Camponotus maguassa Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="238" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maguassa">maguassa</taxonomicName>
.'&quot;
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="6C2E1103A7E138194C26812D283E5805" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="1A1987B6F1ABB2439C9F75875E537ACC" pageNumber="238">
This species bears a striking resemblance to 
<taxonomicName id="F5D6B3BF60748A2BC67F3E3B3D78BDF3" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:26481" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Camponotus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Camponotus festai Emery" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="238" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="festai">C. festai</taxonomicName>
Emery from Asia Minor. The single worker major cotype of this insect in my collection lacks the head, so that in making comparisons of this part of the body I have to rely entirely on Emery's description. The head of the worker major of 
<taxonomicName id="C81151F9F01DD03C2F7FFE507EB8A05C" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:26481" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Camponotus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Camponotus festai Emery" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="238" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="festai">festai</taxonomicName>
is evidently larger (3.5X3.5 mm.), more narrowed in front, with the posterior border slightly concave; the mandibles are 7-toothed, the scape is somewhat flattened, the declivity of the epinotum much shorter than the base, the petiole much broader above, with sharper border; the hind tibiae are prismatic, with dorsal groove and their flexor border has a row of bristles; the hairs and pubescence are yellow, the latter much longer and more conspicuous on the gaster than in 
<taxonomicName id="21A3A781B776A91BAAB9703F12B019A0" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:26919" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Camponotus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Camponotus maguassa Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="238" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maguassa">maguassa</taxonomicName>
, and the hairs on the legs are distinctly longer; the head and gaster are black, the thorax, legs, and petiole deep brownish red.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>