<document id="0E161F7520B121688D5AA237DEC8B158" ID-DOI="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4624.4.3" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8c295c37-8139-475d-978e-ea626e787d3c" ID-GBIF-Taxon="158491456" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3265554" ID-ZooBank="2BE27FEB-2F55-4853-825C-27C817036BFE" _generate="added" approvalRequired="34" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="34" checkinTime="1562042286815" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Monné, Miguel A., Nascimento, Francisco E. De L., Monné, Marcela L. &amp; Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2019" docId="1602879F4361FFABFF56FA5AFDB8FB13" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4624.4.3.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4624 (4)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Leptocometes antonkozlovi Monné &amp; Nascimento &amp; Monné &amp; Santos-Silva 2019, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="503" masterDocId="EA3BFFE7436BFFA7FFC1FFABFFAEFFD4" masterDocTitle="New records, new genera, and new species in Acanthocinini (Lamiinae) from the Neotropical region, and new synonym in Cerambycinae (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae)" masterLastPageNumber="506" masterPageNumber="491" pageId="10" pageNumber="501" updateTime="1643459501353" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="0699CC4DBDD2CC6A24BFF33C92FD2AED" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="109F4A55B4A7BFA4B511CE8585DC8D36">
<mods:title id="F2D26F698C6DF652AB2901A09B933CA2">New records, new genera, and new species in Acanthocinini (Lamiinae) from the Neotropical region, and new synonym in Cerambycinae (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A73B8A1BD5D803A76B762A753CF2FD3B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="63C9369F734568287B47526BE0500D16">
<mods:roleTerm id="D1AB1E627B22E8E7D82899C1A012A9FA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="4619EC14041BEB2857AD4A7AED2D60CD">Monné, Miguel A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="6A55B524F9313F66076037733DDE829C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3B9D705DE5AC43B5DB918455F9E8B8A1">
<mods:roleTerm id="2958BC18DB171B664BA66C02A88B233E">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="EB1D5E09685C3DA4803034F9410EF088">Nascimento, Francisco E. De L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="38EB7A41E0AEAD866030067C5E5E832A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="23DC3B3C7178E8BF0DE1ADA3C582AE6B">
<mods:roleTerm id="C65BE50FE397CAB4CE30C4DAE5A5B488">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="96394650972DA68FE81148EDC7DDF723">Monné, Marcela L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="2C951F08DE451B9AB8CC066EB3E9DE40" type="personal">
<mods:role id="EA4F2B075A0C732E740C104CDE4311EB">
<mods:roleTerm id="0D2BD9BB4818C30D34475A16FAF7DDA2">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="B98BC28410168505526FAD89A7B888A5">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="28B56744B801F48FEDDBDFBEDEB2810E">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="F46A045457442BA93E944B7D411E7A6F" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="9013EDDBBA7DC2118BCE4D2ABE67A76E">
<mods:title id="6112DC422F8A8EF0DF6A93C612AF5F18">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="66C2CAEC2A1823993C0F142306896D30">
<mods:date id="9409BEF829FCADC6C3392AB48C964A66">2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="B0164D7B32FFFC6B547842925DCAAF4B" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="BBF10FA6BED0CA5C57556A9731B0C1DE">2019-07-02</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="33B95818FF699D55D25AD255CE304F6A" type="volume">
<mods:number id="252F5FC0834D177B9B4895C6AF3C2BFD">4624</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="1EDFB39DE8C50CE852F64AA7162676B2" type="issue">
<mods:number id="7AA7F2FC0951576AE31D877FCB19BD46">4</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="EAB726B68D7013EFAD606492AEE9BEE7" unit="page">
<mods:start id="448E02A5454DC793DCF6F4620906A01E">491</mods:start>
<mods:end id="C9B47938DD61D0B85B313A6BEEF33B60">506</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="721E8476F6D58062B27AD616A87E84A0">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="3C33B743A5A05AC14AD668A8318D4B75" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4624.4.3</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="DF63B7415499252707F0A45D748D679A" type="GBIF-Dataset">8c295c37-8139-475d-978e-ea626e787d3c</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="1D782D6C1A8AADFEC5EB88F05CA02471" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="A003C565218895EC13311798E5B7F2B7" type="Zenodo-Dep">3265554</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="72995DBC6B4EEE8BA46C6A6FAEA7C9C6" type="ZooBank">2BE27FEB-2F55-4853-825C-27C817036BFE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="1602879F4361FFABFF56FA5AFDB8FB13" ID-GBIF-Taxon="158491456" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1602879F4361FFABFF56FA5AFDB8FB13" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1602879F4361FFABFF56FA5AFDB8FB13" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="503" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">
<subSubSection id="D6B165024361FFADFF56FA5AFDEDF9DF" box="[151,579,1521,1548]" pageId="10" pageNumber="501" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="9E1436894361FFADFF56FA5AFDEDF9DF" blockId="10.[151,579,1521,1583]" box="[151,579,1521,1548]" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">
<heading id="C55C81E54361FFADFF56FA5AFDEDF9DF" bold="true" box="[151,579,1521,1548]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="501" reason="1">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4361FFADFF56FA5AFDEDF9DF" bold="true" box="[151,579,1521,1548]" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4361FFADFF56FA5AFE70F9D8" authority="Monné &amp; Nascimento &amp; Monné &amp; Santos-Silva, 2019" authorityName="Monné &amp; Nascimento &amp; Monné &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2019" box="[151,478,1521,1548]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="501" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4361FFADFF56FA5AFE70F9D8" bold="true" box="[151,478,1521,1548]" italics="true" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">Leptocometes antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="B7EC57E04361FFADFE24FA5AFDEDF9DF" box="[485,579,1521,1547]" pageId="10" pageNumber="501" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D6B165024361FFABFF56F9BEFCA7FDB7" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="503" pageId="10" pageNumber="501" type="description">
<paragraph id="9E1436894361FFADFF56F9BEFEE5F9FB" blockId="10.[151,579,1521,1583]" box="[151,331,1556,1583]" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">
(
<figureCitation id="06902A0C4361FFADFF5EF9BEFEEDF9FB" box="[159,323,1556,1583]" captionStart="FIGURES 18–25. 18–21" captionStartId="13.[151,264,1933,1958]" captionTargetBox="[180,1410,167,1913]" captionTargetId="figure@13.[176,1410,166,1913]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURES 18–25. 18–21, Onalcidion antonkozlovi, holotype female: 18, Dorsal habitus; 19, Ventral habitus; 20, Lateral habitus; 21, Head, frontal view. 22–25, Leptocometes antonkozlovi, holotype male: 22, Head, frontal view; 23, Dorsal habitus; 24, Ventral habitus; 25, Lateral habitus." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3265560/files/figure.png" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">Figures 22–25</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9E1436894361FFACFF56F9F7FAB7FF2F" blockId="10.[151,1437,1628,2015]" lastBlockId="11.[151,1437,153,2015]" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="502" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4361FFADFF56F9F7FE8FF9A3" bold="true" box="[151,289,1628,1655]" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">Description</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4361FFADFEEEF9F6FEC2F9A3" bold="true" box="[303,364,1629,1655]" pageId="10" pageNumber="501">Male</emphasis>
. Head dark brown, almost black, except dark reddish-brown posterior area of gulamentum; labial palpomeres I–II mostly yellowish-brown, and palpomere III blackish; maxillary palpomeres I–II mostly yellowish-brown, palpomere III dark brown, and IV blackish; remaining surface of mouthparts partially reddish-brown; scape and pedicel dark brown; antennomere III brown on anterior 2/3, reddish-brown on posterior third, except dark-brown apex; prothorax dark brown except prosternal process mostly dark reddish brown; ventral surface of mesothorax dark brown except mesoventral process mostly dark reddish brown; ventral surface of metathorax dark brown laterally, lighter toward central area (more dark reddish brown depending on light intensity); elytra dark brown, with irregular dark reddish-brown areas near apex; pro- and mesocoxae yellowish-brown interspersed with brown areas; metacoxae dark brown; trochanters yellowish-brown; pro- and mesofemora with peduncle, anterior 2/3 of ventral surface and part of sides yellowish-brown, and remaining surface dark brown; metafemora mostly yellowish-brown with distal half of dorsal surface, part of lateral surfaces of distal half, and entire posterior area brown (darker toward apex); protarsi dark brown; about basal 2/3 of meso- and metatarsomere I yellowish-brown, and distal third dark brown; meso- and metatarsomeres II–IV dark brown; basal 2/3 of meso- and metatarsomere V dark reddish-brown, and distal third dark-brown; abdominal ventrites reddish-brown with brown areas.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9E1436894360FFACFF06FEAEFED0FC3B" blockId="11.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="11" pageNumber="502">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4360FFACFF06FEAEFEA9FECB" bold="true" box="[199,263,261,287]" pageId="11" pageNumber="502">Head</emphasis>
. Frons transverse, with a few fine punctures laterally; with greenish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, more yellowish close to eyes and clypeus, interspersed laterally with short, erect, sparse yellow setae, and one long, erect dark setae. Area between antennal tubercles with yellowish pubescence centrally, greenishbrown laterally, partially obscuring integument, except glabrous diamond central area close to upper eye lobes; area between upper eye lobes with yellowish-brown pubescence (more brownish depending on angle of light source), yellower close to eyes; remaining surface of vertex with minute, slightly conspicuous greenish-brown pubescence, except glabrous area close to prothoracic margin. Antennal tubercles with greenish-brown pubescence (more yellowish-brown on some areas, especially depending on angle of light source), except yellowish pubescence on apex. Area behind eyes with yellowish-brown pubescent band close to eye, more bristly toward ventral surface of lower eye lobe, glabrous on remaining surface. Genae smooth, with sparse yellowish-brown pubescence. Postclypeus with yellowish-brown pubescence on wide central area, glabrous laterally; with one long, erect brownish seta on each side of wide central area. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior 2/3, inclined at anterior third; with sparse yellowish pubescence interspersed with long, brownish and golden setae directed forward. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous on wide posterior area, depressed, with short yellowish pubescence interspersed with long, erect brownish setae anteriorly. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.15 times length of scape; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.46 times length of scape. Antennae (missing antennomeres IV–XI in both antennae); present antenomeres 0.67 times elytral length, with apex of antennomere III reaching apex of anterior third of elytra; scape with posterior half of ventral surface nearly flattened, moderately abruptly widened at apex; scape, pedicel and antennomere III with yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument; ventral surface of pedicel and antennomere III with short, erect, sparse, thick setae ventrally. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.95; pedicel = 0.10.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9E1436894360FFABFF06FC52FD5EFE5F" blockId="11.[151,1437,153,2015]" lastBlockId="12.[151,1437,153,1223]" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="503" pageId="11" pageNumber="502">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4360FFACFF06FC52FE8EFBC7" bold="true" box="[199,288,1017,1043]" pageId="11" pageNumber="502">Thorax</emphasis>
. Prothorax with large, conical tubercle at posterior third, with apex obliquely projected backward (anterior area as a gradual continuation of margin); anterior area with narrow, distinct constriction; sides gradually divergent from anterior margin to apex of lateral tubercle, then abruptly, strongly concave. Pronotum with five distinct tubercles, one on each side, oblique, place on anterior half, one on each side of posterior half, slighter distinct, nearly fused with anterolateral ones, another subelliptical, placed centrally from about midlength to posterior quarter; with row of coarse, deep punctures near posterior margin, moderately coarse, sparse punctures on sides of central tubercle and anterocentral area, nearly impunctate laterally, impunctate on tubercles; mostly with greenish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, except: moderately wide yellowish pubescent band on each side of central area, together diamond-shaped, following sparsely toward anterior margin; oblique, elongate yellow macula on each side of anterior half; oblique yellow macula on lateral tubercles of prothorax; and yellowish pubescence near anterolateral angles. Sides of prothorax with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument (more greenishbrown depending on light source or intensity). Ventral surface of thorax with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument (more grayish-white depending on light intensity); prosternal process distinctly narrowed centrally, with its narrowest area about as wide as 1/5 of procoxal cavity; mesoventral process gradually narrowed toward its posterior third, then widened, with its narrowest area about 0.4 times as wide as mesocoxal cavity. Scutellum sulcate at posterocentral area; with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument (less distinctly depending on light angle source). 
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4360FFACFDE7F992FDDCF987" bold="true" box="[550,626,1593,1619]" pageId="11" pageNumber="502">Elytra</emphasis>
. Sides gradually narrowed from humerus to apex; centro basal crests elevate, with dark, moderately thick setae directed backward; coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate on anterior half, gradually sparsely punctate on posterior half; with oblique yellowish pubescent band on sides of anterior sixth; with wide, transverse yellowish pubescent band from anterior fifth to about middle, with triangular projections in its anterior and posterior margins, and triangularly fused along suture with posterior yellowish area, interspersed with moderately small, subcircular greenish-brown pubescent spots; with yellowish pubescence covering mostly of posterior half, interspersed with moderately small, subcircular greenish-brown pubescent spots, except moderately large, irregular lateral area with greenish-brown pubescence; remaining surface with greenish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument; with erect, dark setae throughout; apex with long spine at outer angle, and short projection at sutural angle. 
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4360FFACFE45F8D6FE12F843" bold="true" box="[388,444,1917,1943]" pageId="11" pageNumber="502">Legs</emphasis>
. Pro- and mesofemora pedunculate-clavate (club noticeably large); mesofemora slightly curved from apex of peduncle. Metafemora slightly, gradually widened from anterior quarter to near apex, then slightly narrowed; slightly curved from anterior quarter. Femora with yellowish pubescence not obscuring integu- ment. Protibiae with tab-shaped projection ventrally, slightly from midlength; with yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument, more conspicuous on light area, bristly, reddish-brown on posterior third of ventral surface; with long, erect, sparse dark setae (apex of some setae yellowish). Mesotibiae with sparse yellowish pubescence on basal 2/3, denser, bristly, reddish-brown on posterior third; with long, erect, moderately sparse dark setae, especially dorsally, gradually shorter, thicker toward apex. Metatibiae with sparse yellowish-brown pubescence, more reddishbrown on ventral surface of posterior third, interspersed with long, erect dark setae, gradually shorter toward apex. Metatarsomere I about twice length of II–III together.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9E1436894367FFABFF06FE3FFE48FE23" blockId="12.[151,1437,153,1223]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF06FE3FFE92FE7B" bold="true" box="[199,316,404,431]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Abdomen</emphasis>
. Ventrites with yellowish pubescence partially obscuring integument (more grayish-white depending on light intensity); ventrite V with long, erect sparse dark setae; apex of ventrite V deeply emarginate, with sides forming spiniform projection.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9E1436894367FFABFF06FDABFCA7FDB7" blockId="12.[151,1437,153,1223]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF06FDABFE37FDCF" bold="true" box="[199,409,512,539]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Dimensions (mm)</emphasis>
. Total length, 10.85; prothoracic length, 1.75; anterior prothoracic width, 1.80 (2.30, slightly after anterior margin); posterior prothoracic width, 2.25; maximum prothoracic width (between apex of lateral tubercles), 2.95; humeral width, 3.70; elytral length, 8.05.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D6B165024367FFABFF06FDC6FBECFD7F" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="9E1436894367FFABFF06FDC6FBECFD7F" blockId="12.[151,1437,153,1223]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF06FDC6FEDAFD53" bold="true" box="[199,372,620,647]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Type material</emphasis>
. 
<materialsCitation id="2EC33CD44367FFABFE48FDC6FBECFD7F" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2273363935" collectingDate="2017-04-13" collectingDateMax="2017-04-15" collectingDateMin="2017-04-13" collectionCode="MZSP" collectorName="NE Bucaramanga &amp; Sinyaev &amp; Pinilla" country="Colombia" elevation="2250" latitude="7.1452775" location="Santander" longLatPrecision="21" longitude="-73.03111" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Santander" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="4110882B4367FFABFE48FDC6FE5FFD53" box="[393,497,621,647]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry id="E6BC76194367FFABFD46FDC6FCB1FD53" box="[647,799,621,647]" name="Colombia" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">COLOMBIA</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="5C6FF86B4367FFABFCF0FDC6FC0AFD53" box="[817,932,621,647]" country="Colombia" name="Santander" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFCF0FDC6FC0AFD53" box="[817,932,621,647]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Santander</emphasis>
</collectingRegion>
: 
<collectorName id="335E535F4367FFABFC78FDC6FB28FD53" box="[953,1158,621,647]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">NE Bucaramanga</collectorName>
(near Morro Ventanas; 
<geoCoordinate id="FB9F504E4367FFABFF56FD3AFEBEFD7F" box="[151,272,657,683]" degrees="7" direction="north" minutes="08" orientation="latitude" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" precision="15" seconds="43" value="7.1452775">7º08’43”N</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate id="FB9F504E4367FFABFEE7FD3BFE1BFD7F" box="[294,437,656,683]" degrees="73" direction="west" minutes="01" orientation="longitude" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" precision="15" seconds="52" value="-73.03111">73º01’52”W</geoCoordinate>
; 
<elevation id="1586D1BA4367FFABFE01FD3BFDB6FD7F" box="[448,536,656,683]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.25" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" unit="m" value="2250.0">
<quantity id="59539B6C4367FFABFE01FD3BFDB6FD7F" box="[448,536,656,683]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.25" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" unit="m" value="2250.0">2250 m</quantity>
</elevation>
), 
<collectingDate id="FA51E9A14367FFABFDEDFD3BFD7BFD7F" box="[556,725,656,683]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" value="2017-04-13" valueMax="2017-04-15" valueMin="2017-04-13">
<date id="EA1510494367FFABFDEDFD3BFD7BFD7F" box="[556,725,656,683]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" value="2017-04-13" valueMax="2017-04-15" valueMin="2017-04-13">13–15.IV.2017</date>
</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName id="335E535F4367FFABFD21FD3AFC94FD7F" box="[736,826,657,683]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Sinyaev</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName id="335E535F4367FFABFC9FFD3AFC09FD7F" box="[862,935,657,683]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Pinilla</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode id="F8BAAE4C4367FFABFC26FD3AFB98FD7F" box="[999,1078,657,683]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D6B165024367FFABFF06FD1EFD58FBAB" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="9E1436894367FFABFF06FD1EFD41FBE3" blockId="12.[151,1437,153,1223]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF06FD1EFE9AFD1B" bold="true" box="[199,308,693,719]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Remarks</emphasis>
. This new species is provisionally described in 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFCACFD1DFB33FD1B" authority="Bates, 1881" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[877,1181,693,719]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFCACFD1DFBA9FD1B" box="[877,1031,694,719]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Leptocometes</emphasis>
Bates, 1881
</taxonomicName>
. According to 
<bibRefCitation id="FA3A4B784367FFABFA8CFD1EFF4BFD27" author="Monne, M. A." pageId="12" pageNumber="503" pagination="249 - 278" refId="ref10781" refString="Monne, M. A. (1990) Sinopse dos generos de Acanthocinini neotropicais. I. Generos com setas e crista centro-basal nos elitros (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae). Revista Brasileira de Biologia, 50 (1), 249 - 278." type="journal article" year="1990">Monné (1990)</bibRefCitation>
: “ 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFF3CFD72FEF3FD27" authority="Thomson, 1864" authorityName="Thomson" authorityYear="1864" box="[253,349,729,755]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Tithonus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF3CFD72FEF3FD27" box="[253,349,729,755]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Tithonus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
[currently = 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFE2EFD71FD27FD27" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[495,649,730,755]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFE2EFD71FD27FD27" box="[495,649,730,755]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Leptocometes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
] differs from 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFCE5FD72FBBBFD27" authority="Thomson" authorityName="Thomson" authorityYear="1864" box="[804,1045,729,755]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Onalcidion" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFCE5FD72FC0CFD27" box="[804,930,729,755]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Onalcidion</emphasis>
Thomson
</taxonomicName>
, for the central or only post-medial position of the lateral tubercles of the prothorax. In 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFD27FD56FCCAFCC3" authorityName="Thomson" authorityYear="1864" box="[742,868,765,791]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Onalcidion" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFD27FD56FCCAFCC3" box="[742,868,765,791]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Onalcidion</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, the tubercles, in addition to being slightly developed, are placed at the beginning of the posterior third.” Actually, 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFCB9FC89FBBCFCEF" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[888,1042,802,827]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFCB9FC89FBBCFCEF" box="[888,1042,802,827]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Leptocometes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
appears to be formed by more than one genus. It includes species with different forms of the lateral tubercles of the prothorax (although always placed around middle of the prothorax), different forms of the metafemora (from pedunculate-clavate as mesofemora to distinctly slender and elongated), and with or without humeral carina (when present, not reaching the elytral apex). However, the presence of 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFE7AFC19FD6FFC1F" authority="(Melzer, 1934)" authorityName="Melzer" authorityYear="1934" baseAuthorityName="Melzer" baseAuthorityYear="1934" box="[443,705,945,971]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sptizi">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFE7AFC19FDBDFC1F" box="[443,531,946,971]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">L. sptizi</emphasis>
(Melzer, 1934)
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFD36FC19FB80FC18" authority="(Bates, 1863)" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1863" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1863" box="[759,1070,945,972]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="acutispinis">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFD36FC19FC20FC1F" box="[759,910,946,971]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">L. acutispinis</emphasis>
(Bates, 1863)
</taxonomicName>
, which agree somewhat with the new species, especially regarding the shape of the metafemora and lack of humeral carina, allows for its inclusion, although provisionally, in 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFE7FFC51FDF6FBC7" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[446,600,1018,1043]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFE7FFC51FDF6FBC7" box="[446,600,1018,1043]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Leptocometes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. Only a comprehensive review of the tribe may provide a better definition of 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFF77FBB5FEFEFBE3" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[182,336,1054,1079]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF77FBB5FEFEFBE3" box="[182,336,1054,1079]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Leptocometes</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, especially in relation to 
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFDABFBB6FD46FBE3" authorityName="Thomson" authorityYear="1864" box="[618,744,1053,1079]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Onalcidion" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFDABFBB6FD46FBE3" box="[618,744,1053,1079]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Onalcidion</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9E1436894367FFABFF06FBE9FD58FBAB" blockId="12.[151,1437,153,1223]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">
<taxonomicName id="59AB4D0A4367FFABFF06FBE9FE59FB8F" authority="Monné &amp; Nascimento &amp; Monné &amp; Santos-Silva, 2019" authorityName="Monné &amp; Nascimento &amp; Monné &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2019" box="[199,503,1089,1115]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Leptocometes" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF06FBE9FE59FB8F" box="[199,503,1089,1115]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Leptocometes antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="B7EC57E04367FFABFE3FFBEAFDF6FB8F" box="[510,600,1089,1115]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" rank="species">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFE3FFBEAFDF6FB8F" bold="true" box="[510,600,1089,1115]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">sp. nov.</emphasis>
</taxonomicNameLabel>
differs from all other species currently included in the genus by the lateral tubercles of the prothorax distinctly curved backward.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D6B165024367FFABFF06FB22FDB8FB13" pageId="12" pageNumber="503" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="9E1436894367FFABFF06FB22FDB8FB13" blockId="12.[151,1437,153,1223]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">
<emphasis id="ACDFEA9B4367FFABFF06FB22FEE6FB77" bold="true" box="[199,328,1161,1187]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">Etymology</emphasis>
. The species is named in honor of Anton O. Kozlov, who sent the specimen for study and donated the 
<typeStatus id="4110882B4367FFABFF01FB06FE8CFB13" box="[192,290,1197,1223]" pageId="12" pageNumber="503">holotype</typeStatus>
for MZSP collection.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>