<document id="AAE2B7027E09434F3C0E4239D2483262" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2f6b7408-685c-4ad6-aac4-7e42b84abbc7" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152036084" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-202-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-202-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 202" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the Afrotropical Oberthuerellinae (Cynipoidea, Liopteridae)" checkinTime="1451248949478" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Buffington, Matthew L. &amp; Noort, Simon van" docDate="2012" docId="1699A527214FC106A06067FB02B51AC5" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 202: 1-154" docOrigin="ZooKeys 202" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136" docTitle="Tessmannella spinosa Hedicke" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="108" lastPageNumber="109" masterDocId="FFA0FFA1FFCFFF87602FB655FF993C24" masterDocTitle="Revision of the Afrotropical Oberthuerellinae (Cynipoidea, Liopteridae)" masterLastPageNumber="154" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" updateTime="1643539830100" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="F370D589774957E26567CFC4185191E5" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="EAA090D03197A8F0C060013E452F69D3">
<mods:title id="38009B50E61A6D9E40C004A8E6FF065C">Revision of the Afrotropical Oberthuerellinae (Cynipoidea, Liopteridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="19C13AF16E96E4FE83F1E15F946E99AA" type="personal">
<mods:role id="126CF47742E3385BDA518F7AC8FA32FD">
<mods:roleTerm id="56BF56706B961BDDEE2C0EE8B2BB133B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0CA1A60AF08F4D643817947ED1F1C430">Buffington, Matthew L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="F9306F031199555BC0E7C326C1F8376B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="7A9A659C5375A03394B7D9C5333A14F7">
<mods:roleTerm id="13F2E8EECD409664023959F55C821224">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="01F06742B8F758E19CD05050D401A43F">Noort, Simon van</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="B34B96665822766512ADE262555BDDE0">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="4745FD84B784090961DC598E1F3A74B5" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="62494B673700324834D30F000460C64B">
<mods:title id="B24581AD49AE04BCE6E4A00EC2786A91">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="377E306AE897FBB9659D5D1296401D77">
<mods:date id="DF1570866C671E3FF38B7B3D9038567D">2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="2CE78AB72FED3DA48ED459FA8A931595" type="volume">
<mods:number id="D797E0D1A72B8FC964AEF42BA8883317">202</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="6915C05480B9A13E541F1D82D0697655" unit="page">
<mods:start id="1023A8A725FB8A57D4D11318FF138830">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="2D0E69DA9C268886DFDEC02600014834">154</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="EFBF4099F31BEB9F9EE88C3498873768">
<mods:url id="4090EFDE1EB94B029F5C543E6318DC12">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="C19DD3BE4B0099EFD8F252F9F1D53738">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="3648E4F3AAC6DE0D5712C96C1DAFA97E" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.202.2136</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="FA56C0AB7F50E728FA240B5CF9D88000" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-202-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0BFE22753AB05F2B0A3E40B0D7FD29C6" type="ZooBank">4E2F5872-37BF-4ECB-8518-29E40735F4B3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="1699A527214FC106A06067FB02B51AC5" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152036084" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1699A527214FC106A06067FB02B51AC5" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1699A527214FC106A06067FB02B51AC5" lastPageId="108" lastPageNumber="109" pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
<subSubSection id="690B7686E9837C1127030FCC0A0CC760" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="A75285422D008E2975102EC47999C1FD" pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
<taxonomicName id="E86F72F16F4C3B4783FC5802190B4D53" LSID="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:181551" authority="Hedicke" authorityName="Hedicke" class="Hexapoda" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella spinosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosa">Tessmannella spinosa Hedicke</taxonomicName>
Figures 50-51
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0A551ABBD2FF0529C442C0A72D5D5EFB" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="088E5919AAF9C9A744278174A028BEC5" pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
<taxonomicName id="F13A79BE48945E0074CAD87E46ADDA1D" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella spinosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosa">Tessmannella spinosa</taxonomicName>
Hedicke, 1912: 303.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="86A6A925E377FDEDC3A3B012835DF9D0" lastPageId="108" lastPageNumber="109" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" type="description">
<paragraph id="5D4B34650BB863955567BD17E426F3DA" pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="570EA417D5EB15450A263F644AF8CB2A" pageId="103" pageNumber="104">Coloration of head and mesosoma black to dark brown; metasoma and legs reddish brown. Sculpture on vertex, lateral surface of pronotum and mesoscutum present, deeply striate on head, costate with foveae on pronotum, mesoscutum.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B179A5585554CE80FED8BEAA76F60137" lastPageId="106" lastPageNumber="107" pageId="103" pageNumber="104">
Head. Broadly triangular, in anterior view. Pubescence on head present, dense setae covering head. Sculpture along lateral margin of occiput absent. Gena (meas 
<pageBreakToken id="4BDF6DD6595B8155D15F10EC8361B665" pageId="104" pageNumber="105" start="start">ured</pageBreakToken>
from compound eye to posterolateral margin of head) short, ratio of length of gena to length of compound eye in dorsal view &lt;0.3. Sculpture of gena smooth with remnants of costulae along posterior margin. Lateral margin of occiput defined by distinctly angled, raised, sharp carina. Occiput (except extreme lateral margin) smooth. Ocelli small, ratio of maximum diameter of a lateral ocellus to shortest distance between lateral ocelli 0.2-0.4. Anterior ocellus close to posterior ocelli, post 
<pageBreakToken id="0A7D87F9A32DAD1B2C03378F3131F648" pageId="105" pageNumber="106" start="start">erior</pageBreakToken>
margin of anterior ocellus behind or subcontiguous with a transverse line running through anterior margins of posterior ocelli. Relative position of toruli close to ocelli, ratio of vertical distance between inner margin of torulus and ventral margin of clypeus to vertical distance between anterior ocellus and torulus &lt;2.0. Median keel of face present, short, not extending beyond toruli. Vertical carina adjacent to ventral margin of torulus absent. Facial sculpture present, punctate-rugose, transversely striate; striations meeting at midline of face. Facial impression absent, face flat. Antennal scrobe absent. Anterior tentorial pits small. Vertical delineations on lower face absent. Ventral clypeal margin laterally, close to anterior mandibular articulation, distinctly angled. Ventral clypeal margin medially emarginate. Clypeus circumscribed by clypeal carina; surface striate, converging ventro-medially. Malar space adjacent to anterior articulation of mandible evenly rounded, striate-foveate. Malar sulcus absent. Compound eye close to posterior ocellus, ratio of distance between compound eye and posterior mandibular articulation to distance between posterior ocellus and compound eye&gt; 1.2. Compound eye, in dorsal view, distinctly protruding from the surface of the head, particularly laterally. Pubescence on compound eye absent. Orbital furrows absent. Lateral frontal carina of face absent. Dorsal aspect of vertex 
<pageBreakToken id="7B89341A089007715D58E002106BCCAD" pageId="106" pageNumber="107" start="start">deeply</pageBreakToken>
foveate. Posterior aspect of vertex foveate. Hair punctures on lateral aspect of vertex present, indistinct. Posterior surface of head almost flat, not deeply impressed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="233BCBD538EFB49A01A194F1DE1D0087" pageId="106" pageNumber="107">Labial-maxillary complex. Apical segment of maxillary palp with pubescence, consisting only of erect setae. First segment of labial palp shorter than apical segment. Labial palp composed of three segments. Apical seta on apical segment of maxillary palp shorter than twice length of second longest apical seta. Erect setae medially on apical segment of maxillary palp present. Maxillary palp composed of four segments. Last two segments of maxillary palp (in normal repose) straight. Distal margin of subapical segment of maxillary palp straight, apical segment bending outwards. Apical segment of maxillary palp more than 1.5 times as long as preceding segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="13C1D467199B8C3102A1ED14AC1F91A3" pageId="106" pageNumber="107">Antenna. Articulation between flagellomeres in antenna connate with articles broadly joined. Female antenna composed of 11 flagellomeres. Female F1 as long as F2. Flagellomeres of female antenna cylindrical, not widened towards apex, non-clavate. Placoidal sensilla absent. Distal flagellomeres of female antenna not conspicuously enlarged compared to proximal flagellomeres.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B632AD27EE36272372E5448EA7785633" pageId="106" pageNumber="107">Pronotum. Macrosculpture on lateral surface of pronotum present, dorsomedially foveate, laterally foveate-costate. Pubescence on lateral surface of pronotum present, sparse, consisting of few short hairs. Anterior flange of pronotal plate distinctly protruding anteriorly, transversely striate. Carinae extending posteriorly from lateral margin of pronotal plate absent. Lateral pronotal carina present. Pronotal crest present, raised into a distinct process projecting above anterior margin of mesoscutum. Submedian pronotal depressions absent, represented by shallow depression. Lateral margin of pronotal plate defined all the way to the dorsal margin of the pronotum. Pronotal plate wide, almost as wide as head.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E96A070BC263B40E097BCDDE92845535" pageId="106" pageNumber="107">Mesoscutum. Mesoscutal surface convex, evenly curved. Sculpture on mesoscutum present, transversely costate with dorsally projected serrations. Notaulus present, wide, transversely striate, distinctly wider posteriorly. Median mesoscutal carina absent. Anterior admedial lines present, with adjacent cuticular surface wrinkled. Median mesoscutal impression present, short, indicated by notch. Parascutal carina nearly straight anteriorly, posteriorly curved mesally.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DBE3924BC998CEE74326076C47C6BAA2" pageId="106" pageNumber="107">Mesopleuron. Dorsally with strigae running dorsoventrally; ventrally smooth, medially sparsely setose. Subpleuron anteriorly strigate, posteriorly smooth; medially with sparse, long setae. Lower mesopleuron medially smooth, glabrous; costate laterally, ventrally. Epicnemial carina absent. Lateroventral mesopleural carina present, marking abrupt change of slope of mesopectus. Mesopleural triangle present, distinctly impressed into longitudinal trough ventrally; dorsally striate, glabrous. Subalar pit large and well defined, lying in posterior end of mesopleural triangle. Speculum present, striate. Mesopleural carina absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="457D8F11AA30D8FC6DFFE2A1DA6E827B" lastPageId="107" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="106" pageNumber="107">
Scutellum. Dorsal surface of scutellum foveate-areolate. Circumscutellar carina absent. Posterior margin of axillula marked by distinct ledge, axillula distinctly impressed adjacent to ledge. Lateroventral margin of scutellum posterior to auricula smooth ventrally, obliquely longtidinally striate dorsally, entirely striate posteriorly. Dorsoposterior part of scutellum produced posteriorly into sharp spine, less than 1.0
<normalizedToken id="3434F83DCB70A1F29C8442366EAE1D60" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of 
<pageBreakToken id="E63B2E3DE8AE8E42248D2998299937A3" pageId="107" pageNumber="108" start="start">petiole</pageBreakToken>
. Dorsal part of scutellum entirely rugose. Scutellar plate absent. Scutellar foveae present, three. Longitudinal scutellar carinae absent. Single longitudinal carina separating scutellar foveae absent. Posterolateral margin of scutellum drawn out into distinct protuberance. Lateral Lateral bar narrow, with strong strigate, foveate sculpture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6EF6EF41E831D502FD4EF061FB406391" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">Metapectal-propodeal complex. Metapectal cavity anterodorsal to metacoxal base absent. Anterior margin of metapectal-propodeal complex seperated from mesopleuron by distinct dorso-ventral ledge. Posteroventral corner of metapleuron (in lateral view) extended posteriorly. Anterior impression of metepimeron present, triangular, with broadest part ventrally. Posterior margin of metepimeron distinct, separating metepimeron from propodeum. Subalar area slightly broadened anteriorly, without longitudinal division indicated. Calyptra present, blunt, lobe-like, polished posteriorly, strigate anteriorly with setiferous punctures. Dorsellum present, horizontally striate. Anterior impression of metepisternum, immediately beneath anterior end of metapleural carina, large and wide. Pubescence consisting of few scattered hairs on posterior part of metapleuron and lateral part of propodeum. Propodeal spurs present, striate. Lateral propodeal carinae present, not reaching scutellum. Ventral end of lateral propodeal carina reaching nucha, carinae separated from each other. Inter propodeal carinae space lightly setose, smooth. Petiolar foramen removed from metacoxae, directed posteriorly. Horizontal carina running anteriorly from lateral propodeal carina present. Lateral propodeal carina straight, sub-parallel. Calyptra, in lateral view, elongate. Propodeum 'neck-like', drawn out posteriorly. Calyptra, in posterior view, dorsoventrally elongate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3900680F352004CE73BA1EDAF3DC8BD4" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">Legs. Pubescence posterolaterally on metacoxa sparse to moderately dense, confined dense hair patch absent. Microsculpture on hind coxa absent. Longitudinal carina on the posterior surface of metatibia absent. Metafemoral spine present, elongate, with adjacent serrate ridge posteriorly. Distal mesotibial spurs shorter than medial spurs. Distal metatibial spurs shorter than medial spurs. Ratio of first metatibial segment to remaining 4 segments equal to 1.0. Pubescence on outer surface of metatarsal claw sparse, consisting of few setae. Outer surface of metatarsal claw almost entirely smooth. Apical seta of metatarsal claw positioned on outer surface below dorsal margin. Base of metatarsal claw weakly expanded, apex slightly bent, ratio width of base to length of apex &lt;0.6.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="71BD24190F0721D54FB3601BFFBEDA6C" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">Forewing. Pubescence of forewing absent on basal half of wing, sparse distally. Apical margin of female forewing rounded. Rs+M of forewing tubular. Mesal end of Rs+M vein situated closer to posterior margin of forewing, directed towards posterior end of basalis. Vein R1 tubular along at least basal part of anterior margin of marginal cell. Basal abscissa of R1 (the abscissa between 2r and the forewing margin) of forewing as broad as adjacent wing veins. Coloration of forewing hyaline with slight infuscation covering marginal cell, area posterior to marginal cell. Marginal cell of forewing membranous, similar to other wing cells. Areolet absent. Hair fringe along apical margin of forewing absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F35876666ACC98210710475031BCDFA" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">
Petiole. Distinctly elongate,&gt; 5
<normalizedToken id="9233BA119DC7CC94F5A3EAEF882463CB" originalValue="–6×">-6x</normalizedToken>
longer than broad. Surface of petiole longitudinally costate, ventral keel absent, ventral costulae ribbed. Posterior part of female petiole not abruptly widened. Ventral flange of annulus of female petiole absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A290E2C2C552CD741FD5A306E5D08EBB" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
<pageBreakToken id="9D8C25F3D235B9C9D34387DE4FD1C562" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" start="start">Metasoma</pageBreakToken>
. Setal band (hairy ring) at base of tergum 3 absent, base of metasoma glabrous. Tergum 3 distinctly smaller than tergum 4. Posterior margin of tergum 3 smoothly rounded. Posterior margin of tergum 4 straight. Sternum 3 exposed, ventral border of T2-T7 visible. Sculpture on metasomal terga present, dorsally smooth, posteroventrally micropunctate. Syntergum absent, all postpetiolar terga free. Annulus absent. Peg-like setae on T6-T7 absent. Posteroventral cavities of female metasoma T7 present, glabrous save for few, long setae. Female posteroventral margin of T6-T7 straight, parallel, with medial carina. Terebrum and hypopygium (in lateral view) straight, pointing posteriorly.
</paragraph>
<caption id="5FEBDD116B38C3BD7EDB3BC3AB5310BC" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
<paragraph id="41C965EB85C7DD9C2038B27641AC7732" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
FIgure 50. 
<taxonomicName id="8FF58A7E4CF0ED0B6598EC9F87DE7117" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella spinosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosa">Tessmannella spinosa</taxonomicName>
Hedicke, holotype A lateral habitus B dorsal habitus C head and mesosoma, lateral view D head and mesosoma, dorsal view E head and pronotum, dorsolateral view F scutellum, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="EF2FED8531A760A0167A1A42EFDE68CB" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
<paragraph id="5B67F61BE24BA1D222B68ACBD38DCDB9" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
Figure 51. 
<taxonomicName id="A7E927715E57203CDCFEF7AC4E61171E" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella spinosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosa">Tessmannella spinosa</taxonomicName>
Hedicke, holotype A meso- and metapleurae, lateral view B metasoma, lateral view C head, anterior view D labels.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A57C11949B42F33225DFF6941ACB53AF" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="537748526FA44EB18C2DA034C8442308" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C0D10D24B97A4898A7E8B89EDF1D35FC" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
Closely resembles 
<taxonomicName id="8214993AF4B0AB3D3491E631C6F6B2AC" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella expansa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="expansa">Tessmannella expansa</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="E1593491B6D2D253AFF8C42084EE1979" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella nigra" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigra">Tessmannella nigra</taxonomicName>
by having the entire forewing uniformly infuscate (medially hyaline in 
<taxonomicName id="2D228723C4FACF29827BDD88A68C87CB" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella copelandi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="copelandi">Tessmannella copelandi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="CB40D127B8EB5132F5B7DE1BEE5275A8" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella kiplingi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kiplingi">Tessmannella kiplingi</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="F494F7686A680FEC7EB28564970E4B21" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella roberti" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="roberti">Tessmannella roberti</taxonomicName>
); distinguished from 
<taxonomicName id="3EDA90AE91B5B3192074299642D76A94" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella expansa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="expansa">Tessmannella expansa</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="5957613F58557644EC18D6F6EAC38CBE" authority="Hedicke, 1912" authorityName="Hedicke" authorityYear="1912" class="Insecta" family="Liopteridae" genus="Tessmannella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tessmannella nigra" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigra">Tessmannella nigra</taxonomicName>
by the possession of a circum clypeal carina (lacking in these latter species).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A189F16BCCF504A3E35058D6644D8BA7" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="74BE2C366F944A4AC258B9285175F95E" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="63AA33124AD237B27667039B908D1F87" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=181551]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ACE9D3AA4F81B493458B595C80C044C5" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="A37C4CC6E75E3F12ECFDA258B04854EE" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E6324F40F407F4453AE96925C95C4919" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Holotype, female: EQUATORIAL GUINEA: Uelleburg, VI-1908 - VIII-1908, von Tessman, USNM ENT 00764791 (deposited in ZMHU). Paralectotype: EQUATORIAL GUINEA: Uelleburg, VI-1908 - VIII-1908, von Tessman (1 female, USNM ENT 00764792 (ZMHU)).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>