<document id="A2BDA72A6D72AE586F41A2D0D3C89455" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5995394" ID-GBIF-Dataset="f8e70840-628c-4491-b274-433f53396d8c" ID-GBIF-Taxon="141263795" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5995394" ID-ZooBank="506A875B-5B7A-425A-953C-E1C747D89D03" _generate="added" checkinTime="1520058523292" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio, Galileo, Maria Helena M., Joly, Luis J. &amp; Tavakilian, Gérard L." docDate="2018" docId="173987E4FFFA465B3EFDFC4DFD87FBCD" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4387.2.1.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4387 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@43c67247" docStyleName="zootaxa.2013.journal_article" docTitle="Rosalba skillmani Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo &amp; Joly &amp; Tavakilian 2018, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="208" masterDocId="EB00FF9CFFFF465C3E6AFFE2FFC0FF9A" masterDocTitle="The genus Rosalba Thomson, 1864 (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Apomecynini)" masterLastPageNumber="258" masterPageNumber="201" pageId="5" pageNumber="206" updateTime="1644235542015" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="7414BED36F2154B92F1334FBD0DD7A12" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="311F23300243EEB223536FCD35ED953E">
<mods:title id="A62E3A0C6CC249FB3F2FB330D2EA37F3">The genus Rosalba Thomson, 1864 (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Apomecynini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="03E2E9095489F76D0EC7B8DC685F13A5" type="personal">
<mods:role id="2F77F3ADE1A6FADFBDBA04E3A169CA6D">
<mods:roleTerm id="BAFA898EE1C76710C9EAD2A9CDB89E42">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="287B026BEF012DC561AC2D03B9784E37">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="AF0B708EB4142D9409C9AAE523CDD320" type="personal">
<mods:role id="E41E85EC4D860312D32B3FDF4B17475D">
<mods:roleTerm id="6DC0A541A62CD24AA2396283092B0434">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="094D8DBE818393B7D582F3441CE11855">Galileo, Maria Helena M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="B91A3A2CB5A96F30C08A23A455E286D9" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AB1D97DDDB4A841F8A70A736F049A077">
<mods:roleTerm id="8AC06A2C78A9619F1CC8400FD59B2802">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="37F9747361AC29171343873F2660A3AE">Joly, Luis J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="4F698FC1B5436C4F529E1A6EF0226F4E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A51F86DB863DECEBDAD7CFC8C6268E2F">
<mods:roleTerm id="EA286FC3DA5ADA571C5A3117852B3F88">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7020900F4259E68413CF670373C8C9A6">Tavakilian, Gérard L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="9C32C2E3D87D919015CC14A89EFDF5E9">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="90AFFF2EFBB1EBFD719B115A5F6A2D16" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="D53CA9F1999E1AFD4F75ED96FF6AF10F">
<mods:title id="71DD8F9F4F3A923CC38A257B807E9792">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="E427962D176ACA53672258CABF0120F0">
<mods:date id="074F829BA212AA8792D54E64E3846028">2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="CF66732ACE5CDF3AD515A0F950216FBE" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="37BFFEF316C19721B2B6FA1450496FAA">2018-02-27</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="DB9F39E50CC3DC74A0D6DE79AB61CC41" type="volume">
<mods:number id="564F604646305A000F4B80DB28A3AECB">4387</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="EBF83BBA5D88A54DD417C6DD7310CF26" type="issue">
<mods:number id="11C38286DB4C79980EB5F406E4C10C30">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="7DE64C0F0C625956298368BA84EC4DAD" unit="page">
<mods:start id="3739F324F005416109143613838520AE">201</mods:start>
<mods:end id="CA0F396983898BF8E9C6D91625B0D676">258</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="0F58551ACB3F886D466ECF8025E93F0A">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="07C06A320163530B8C227F8F6C621F7C" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4387.2.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="34691FBF5E27BF0269A0C2B879C4A757" type="GBIF-Dataset">f8e70840-628c-4491-b274-433f53396d8c</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="DDBE9D2CE56750BF6386B8822DFA70C3" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B0AD1750A02F3910837628DA916365BF" type="Zenodo-Dep">1187360</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8CD1876E92E5695961143C373FD8FB8D" type="ZooBank">506A875B-5B7A-425A-953C-E1C747D89D03</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="173987E4FFFA465B3EFDFC4DFD87FBCD" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5995394" ID-GBIF-Taxon="141263795" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5995394" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:173987E4FFFA465B3EFDFC4DFD87FBCD" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/173987E4FFFA465B3EFDFC4DFD87FBCD" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="208" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">
<subSubSection id="D78A6579FFFA46593EFDFC4DFEE0FC71" pageId="5" pageNumber="206" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFFA46593EFDFC4DFD3FFC50" blockId="5.[151,767,943,1003]" box="[151,767,943,970]" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">
<heading id="C467819EFFFA46593EFDFC4DFD3FFC50" bold="true" box="[151,767,943,970]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="5" pageNumber="206" reason="1">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFFA46593EFDFC4DFD3FFC50" bold="true" box="[151,767,943,970]" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">
<taxonomicName id="58904D71FFFA46593EFDFC4DFD54FC50" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo &amp; Joly &amp; Tavakilian" authorityYear="2018" box="[151,660,943,970]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Rosalba" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="206" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="skillmani" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFFA46593EFDFC4DFEB0FC53" bold="true" box="[151,368,943,969]" italics="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">Rosalba skillmani</emphasis>
Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="B6D7579BFFFA46593CCBFC52FD3FFC50" box="[673,767,944,970]" pageId="5" pageNumber="206" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFFA46593EFDFC30FEE0FC71" blockId="5.[151,767,943,1003]" box="[151,288,978,1003]" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">
(
<figureCitation id="07AB2A77FFFA46593EF5FC30FED8FC71" box="[159,280,978,1003]" captionStart="FIGURES 8–14. 8" captionStartId="43.[151,264,1942,1965]" captionTargetBox="[249,1339,198,1917]" captionTargetId="figure@43.[244,1344,193,1921]" captionTargetPageId="43" captionText="FIGURES 8–14. 8, Rosalba giesberti sp. nov., holotype male, lateral habitus. 9–12, Rosalba skillmani sp. nov., holotype female: 9, dorsal habitus; 10, lateral habitus; 11, ventral habitus; 12, head, frontal view. 13–14, Rosalba senecauxi sp. nov., paratype female:13, dorsal habitus; 14, head, frontalview." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/1187364/files/figure.png" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">Figs. 9–12</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D78A6579FFFA465B3EFDFBF8FD20FE12" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="208" pageId="5" pageNumber="206" type="description">
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFFA46593EFDFBF8FD62FBE1" blockId="5.[151,1436,1050,2011]" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFFA46593EFDFBF8FE4BFBA9" bold="true" box="[151,395,1050,1075]" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">Description. Female</emphasis>
.Integument dark brown, black on some regions, mainly head and pronotum; mouthparts reddish brown, with last palpomeres mostly brown; base of antennomeres reddish brown; gula reddish brown; basal third of tibiae reddish brown; tarsi black.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFFA465A3EADFB64FF0FFF62" blockId="5.[151,1436,1050,2011]" lastBlockId="6.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="207" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFFA46593EADFB64FEC7FB05" bold="true" box="[199,263,1158,1183]" pageId="5" pageNumber="206">Head</emphasis>
. Frons finely, abundantly punctate; with pale yellow pubescence obscuring part of integument, glabrous on narrow area along median longitudinal groove; with some long, erect, brown setae close to eyes. Area between antennal tubercles finely, abundantly punctate on each side of carina-shaped median longitudinal groove; pubescence as on frons. Area between upper eye lobes with yellow pubescence obscuring integument, except on glabrous along median longitudinal groove, connected to narrow band also with yellow pubescence behind and close to upper eye lobes. Remaining surface of vertex finely, abundantly punctate (punctures coarser than on frons), except on narrow area close to median longitudinal groove; with yellow pubescence obscuring integument, except on inverted V-shaped area with pubescence more brownish and exposing integument, and on glabrous narrow area along median longitudinal groove. Antennal tubercles finely, abundantly punctate, gradually finer toward apex; with pale yellow pubescence, gradually more yellow toward upper eye lobes. Area between antennal socket and eyes with yellow pubescence obscuring integument; with some long, erect, brown setae. Area behind eyes finely, moderately sparsely punctate, with yellow pubescence obscuring integument, interspersed with some long, erect, brown setae. Area on each side of gula, finely, abundantly punctate. Submentum narrow, depressed, with short, yellowish white pubescence, not obscuring integument, with some long, erect, brown setae close to elevated region. Postclypeus minutely punctate; with pale yellow pubescence partially obscuring integument, interspersed with long, erect, brown setae. Labrum convex and coplanar with anteclypeus on basal half, inclined on distal half; pubescence almost absent on base of coplanar area, pale yellow, moderately abundant on remaining surface of coplanar area, more abundant, form yellow to golden on inclined area; with long, erect, thick, brown setae on distal margin of coplanar area. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.15 times length of scape; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.65 times length of scape. Antennae 1.9 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at distal fifth of antennomere VIII; scape with yellow pubescence not obscuring integument; antennomere III with yellow pubescence on basal 2/3, more brownish on remaining surface; antennomere IV with yellow pubescence on basal third, gradually brownish toward apex; antennomeres V–X with narrow ring with yellow pubescence on base, with brownish pubescence on remaining surface; ventral side of scape, pedicel and antennomeres III–X with long, erect, dark setae, gradually sparser toward antennomere X; antennal formula (ratio) based on antennomere III: scape = 1.10; pedicel = 0.22; IV = 1.30; V = 1.10; VI = 1.04; VII = 0.92; VIII = 0.90; IX = 0.84; X = 0.78; XI = 0.82.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF9465A3EADFEE6FE38F89F" blockId="6.[151,1437,151,2013]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF9465A3EADFEE6FEE0FE87" bold="true" box="[199,288,260,285]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">Thorax</emphasis>
. Prothorax 1.15 times wider than long; sides rounded about middle. Pronotum coarsely, densely punctate except on narrow, smooth, transverse band close to basal and distal margin; with three wide, longitudinal bands with dense, yellow pubescence obscuring integument (one centrally, slightly widened at base; one on each side); remaining surface with yellowish brown pubescence, interspersed with white pubescence on basal half, distinctly not obscuring integument. Sides of prothorax with sculpture as on pronotum; with wide longitudinal band with dense, yellow pubescence obscuring integument, placed at about middle, anteriorly and posteriorly fused with that on sides of pronotum by transverse band with same pubescence; remaining surface with yellowish white pubescence, short, decumbent pubescence not obscuring integument; with some long, erect, brown setae. Prosternum moderately coarsely, abundantly punctate; with yellowish white pubescence not obscuring integument. Prosternal process moderately coarsely, abundantly punctate; with sub-erect, abundant, yellowish white setae not obscuring integument, distally distinctly more erect, intersperse with brownish setae. Mesoventrite notably transversely depressed, finely striate-punctate, close to apex of prosternal process; laterally with yellowish white pubescence obscuring integument; with slightly conspicuous, yellowish white pubescence on depressed area. Mesanepisternum with yellow pubescence obscuring integument (slightly whitish on superior inner side). Mesepimeron with yellow pubescence obscuring integument. Metanepisternum with yellow pubescence obscuring integument. Metaventrite moderately coarsely, sparsely punctate on inclined area; inclined area with wide band with yellow pubescence, distinctly narrowed, curved toward margin of metanepisternum distally; between the former and metanepisternum with narrow band with whitish pubescence; remaining surface with yellowish white pubescence, partially obscuring integument, except longitudinal, wide band with white pubescence on area between inclined and flat area. Scutellum with dense, yellow pubescence. 
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF9465A3DA5FC4DFBDBFC52" bold="true" box="[975,1051,943,968]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">Elytra</emphasis>
. Coarsely, abundantly punctate on basal third, gradually finer, sparser toward apex. With dense pubescence as follows: with longitudinal yellow band on vertical area, wide from humerus to after middle, then narrowed and following toward apex, on about apex of basal third interspersed with sub-elliptical macula with yellowish brown pubescence exposing integument; with wide, longitudinal band on center of dorsal surface, almost reaching middle of elytron, connected basally with lateral band of dorsal surface, interrupted on center of basal sixth of elytron by elliptical macula with yellowish brown pubescence exposing integument (inner side of longitudinal band not entirely closed), distally deeply emarginate, connected with distal macula by narrow band near to suture; with moderately narrow, longitudinal band with yellow pubescence, placed laterally on dorsal surface, from base to near middle, narrowed toward apex and connected with oblique band of distal half by narrow; with longitudinal, narrow band with white pubescence between longitudinal yellow band of vertical area and laterally on dorsal surface, and another dorsally between lateral and central yellow bands; with narrow band with white pubescence along suture, from scutellum to apex; with narrow band with yellow pubescence on each side of sutural white pubescence, connected about middle with projection of central projection; with oblique, wide band of pubescence starting laterally about middle (this band formed laterally by white pubescence, connected to yellow lateral band, followed by wide area with yellow pubescence, then by wide band with white pubescence, and finally, another area with yellow pubescence connected to longitudinal yellow band near suture); distal quarter with longitudinal yellow band near suture distinct widened, forming an elongate sub-triangular macula; with elongate band with yellow pubescence between apical subtriangular macula and lateral yellow band, notably narrowed anteriorly and posteriorly, surrounded on its distal half with white pubescence (connected to yellow lateral band through white pubescence). Remaining elytral surface with yellowish brown pubescence distinctly not obscuring integument; with sparse, erect, long, brown setae on distal quarter. Elytral apex slightly obliquely truncate. 
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF9465A3D66F946FC84F927" bold="true" box="[780,836,1700,1725]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">Legs</emphasis>
. Femora with yellow pubescence, gradually whitish toward ventral surface. Metatarsomere I as long as 0.9 times II–III together; metatarsomere V (without claws) as long as 0.8 times I–III together.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF9465A3EADF8EDFD7DF80F" blockId="6.[151,1437,151,2013]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF9465A3EADF8EDFEFCF8B2" bold="true" box="[199,316,1807,1832]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">Abdomen</emphasis>
. Ventrites I–IV with yellow pubescence partially obscuring integument except on moderately narrow band on each side with sparser pubescence, distinctly exposing integument, and along central area; ventrite V with yellow pubescence partially obscuring integument; distal region of ventrite V with long, erect, sparse, brown setae; apex of ventrite V slightly rounded.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF9465A3EADF842FA86F823" blockId="6.[151,1437,151,2013]" box="[199,1350,1952,1977]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF9465A3EADF842FEC4F823" bold="true" box="[199,260,1952,1977]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">Male</emphasis>
. It differs from female mainly by the body slightly slender and by the abdominal ventrites flatter.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF9465B3EADF826FC3CFF62" blockId="6.[151,1437,151,2013]" lastBlockId="7.[151,1437,151,1112]" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="208" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF9465A3EADF826FEF5F847" bold="true" box="[199,309,1988,2013]" pageId="6" pageNumber="207">Variation</emphasis>
. Integument mostly black; base of antennomeres dark reddish brown; inverted V-shaped area on frons absent or slightly distinct; inner side of center-basal longitudinal yellow band of elytron entirely closed; oblique band of pubescence on elytra not connected with longitudinal band near suture; sub-triangular macula of yellow pubescence on distal quarter narrow and deeply emarginate anteriorly.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF8465B3EADFEE6FD20FE12" blockId="7.[151,1437,151,1112]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3EADFEE6FB82FE87" bold="true" box="[199,1090,260,285]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
Dimensions in mm (
<typeStatus id="402B8850FFF8465B3FD1FEE6FDE3FE87" box="[443,547,260,285]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">holotype</typeStatus>
female / 
<typeStatus id="402B8850FFF8465B3CFCFEE6FCC1FE87" box="[662,769,260,285]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">paratype</typeStatus>
males / 
<typeStatus id="402B8850FFF8465B3D00FEE6FC16FE87" box="[874,982,260,285]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">paratype</typeStatus>
females)
</emphasis>
. Total length, 8.90/7.75–8.45/ 7.85–9.90; prothorax: length, 1.45/1.35–1.40/1.40–1.60; anterior width, 1.65/1.40–1.60/1.55–1.80; posterior width, 1.70/1.45–1.60/1.60–1.85; widest prothoracic width, 1.80/1.55–1.65/1.75–1.95; humeral width, 2.65/2.25–2.50/ 2.35–2.80; elytral length, 6.30/5.65–6.20/5.65–7.25.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D78A6579FFF8465B3EADFE76FD44FD56" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF8465B3EADFE76FD44FD56" blockId="7.[151,1437,151,1112]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
<materialsCitation id="2FF83CAFFFF8465B3EADFE76FBE4FE4A" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1828872761" collectingDate="2012-09-16" collectingDateMax="2012-09-20" collectingDateMin="2012-09-16" collectionCode="MNKM" collectorName="Wappes &amp; Skillman &amp; Bonaso &amp; Hamel" country="Bolivia" elevation="3800" latitude="-18.1" location="Volcanes" longLatPrecision="1276" longitude="-63.6" municipality="Refugio" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" specimenCount="2" stateProvince="Santa Cruz" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3EADFE76FEAEFE37" bold="true" box="[199,366,404,429]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
<typeStatus id="402B8850FFF8465B3EADFE76FEC2FE37" box="[199,258,404,429]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Type</typeStatus>
material
</emphasis>
. 
<typeStatus id="402B8850FFF8465B3F17FE76FE25FE37" box="[381,485,404,429]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Holotype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry id="E7877662FFF8465B3C14FE76FD34FE36" box="[638,756,404,428]" name="Bolivia" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">BOLIVIA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3D6AFE76FCBDFE31" box="[768,893,404,427]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
<collectingRegion id="5D54F810FFF8465B3D6AFE76FCBDFE31" box="[768,893,404,427]" country="Bolivia" name="Santa Cruz" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Santa Cruz</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<collectingMunicipality id="7F4BAC88FFF8465B3DE7FE76FC27FE37" box="[909,999,404,429]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Refugio</collectingMunicipality>
los 
<location id="9A4F6029FFF8465B3A7DFE76FBBCFE37" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:173987E4FFFA465B3EFDFC4DFD87FBCD:9A4F6029FFF8465B3A7DFE76FBBCFE37" box="[1047,1148,404,429]" country="Bolivia" latitude="-18.1" longLatPrecision="1276" longitude="-63.6" municipality="Refugio" name="Volcanes" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" stateProvince="Santa Cruz">Volcanes</location>
(
<quantity id="58689B17FFF8465B3AE1FE76FAE7FE36" box="[1163,1319,404,428]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="3.8" metricValueMax="4.2" metricValueMin="3.4" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" unit="m" value="3800.0" valueMax="4200.0" valueMin="3400.0">
<elevation id="14BDD1C1FFF8465B3AE1FE76FAE7FE36" box="[1163,1319,404,428]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="3.8" metricValueMax="4.2" metricValueMin="3.4" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" unit="m" value="3800.0" valueMax="4200.0" valueMin="3400.0">3400-4200 m</elevation>
</quantity>
; 
<geoCoordinate id="FAA45035FFF8465B3B59FE76FA4CFE37" box="[1331,1420,404,429]" direction="south" orientation="latitude" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" precision="925" value="-18.1">18°06’S</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate id="FAA45035FFF8465B3EFDFE55FF3EFE4A" box="[151,254,439,464]" direction="west" orientation="longitude" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" precision="925" value="-63.6">63°36’W</geoCoordinate>
), 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3F7CFE55FE7DFE4A" box="[278,445,439,464]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2012-09-16" valueMax="2012-09-20" valueMin="2012-09-16">
<collectingDate id="FB6AE9DAFFF8465B3F7CFE55FE7DFE4A" box="[278,445,439,464]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2012-09-16" valueMax="2012-09-20" valueMin="2012-09-16">16-20.IX.2012</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3FA6FE5AFDE7FE55" box="[460,551,440,463]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Wappes</collectorName>
, 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3C5FFE55FD5DFE4A" box="[565,669,439,464]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Skillman</collectorName>
, 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3CC6FE5AFCC0FE55" box="[684,768,440,463]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Bonaso</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3D41FE55FCB6FE4A" box="[811,886,439,464]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Hamel</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode id="F981AE37FFF8465B3DD1FE5AFBDCFE4A" box="[955,1052,440,464]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">MNKM</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation id="2FF83CAFFFF8465B3A58FE5AFBDCFE6E" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1828872812" collectingDate="2012-09-16" collectingDateMax="2012-09-20" collectingDateMin="2012-09-16" collectionCode="ACMT, MZSP" collectorName="Wappes &amp; Skillman &amp; Bonaso &amp; Hamel" country="Bolivia" elevation="3800" latitude="-18.1" location="Volcanes" longLatPrecision="1276" longitude="-63.6" municipality="Refugio" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" specimenCount="10" specimenCount-female="4" specimenCount-male="6" stateProvince="Santa Cruz" typeStatus="holotype">
Paratypes— 
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3AD7FE5AFAD7FE4A" box="[1213,1303,439,464]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="male">3 males</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3B4CFE5AFA58FE4A" box="[1318,1432,439,464]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="female">2 females</specimenCount>
, same data as holotype (
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3FC1FE3EFDC9FE6F" box="[427,521,476,501]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="male">2 males</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3C7DFE3EFDBFFE6F" box="[535,639,476,501]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="female">1 female</specimenCount>
, 
<collectionCode id="F981AE37FFF8465B3CE4FE3EFD21FE6E" box="[654,737,476,500]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">ACMT</collectionCode>
; 
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3C85FE3EFC81FE6F" box="[751,833,476,501]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="male">1 male</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3D3AFE3EFC78FE6F" box="[848,952,476,501]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="female">1 female</specimenCount>
, 
<collectionCode id="F981AE37FFF8465B3DACFE3EFBD4FE6E" box="[966,1044,476,500]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">MZSP</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="2FF83CAFFFF8465B3A41FE3EFEEDFDA6" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1828872822" collectingDate="2013-12-04" collectingDateMax="2013-12-09" collectingDateMin="2013-12-04" collectionCode="FWSC" collectorName="Wappes &amp; Skillman" country="Bolivia" county="Bermejo" elevation="1198" latitude="-18.1" location="Volcanes" longLatPrecision="1276" longitude="-63.6" municipality="Refugio" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-female="1" stateProvince="Santa Cruz" typeStatus="holotype">
<collectingCountry id="E7877662FFF8465B3A41FE3EFB61FE6E" box="[1067,1185,476,500]" name="Bolivia" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">BOLIVIA</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="5D54F810FFF8465B3ADAFE3EFAF3FE6E" box="[1200,1331,476,500]" country="Bolivia" name="Santa Cruz" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Santa Cruz</collectingRegion>
: 
<quantity id="58689B17FFF8465B3B2BFE3EFABEFE6F" box="[1345,1406,476,501]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.0" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" unit="km" value="4.0">4 km</quantity>
N 
<collectingCounty id="764E4E7EFFF8465B3EFDFE1DFF38FD82" box="[151,248,511,536]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Bermejo</collectingCounty>
(
<collectingMunicipality id="7F4BAC88FFF8465B3F6DFE1DFEA3FD82" box="[263,355,511,536]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Refugio</collectingMunicipality>
los 
<location id="9A4F6029FFF8465B3FFFFE1DFE3DFD82" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:173987E4FFFA465B3EFDFC4DFD87FBCD:9A4F6029FFF8465B3FFFFE1DFE3DFD82" box="[405,509,511,536]" country="Bolivia" county="Bermejo" latitude="-18.1" longLatPrecision="1276" longitude="-63.6" municipality="Refugio" name="Volcanes" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" stateProvince="Santa Cruz">Volcanes</location>
; 
<quantity id="58689B17FFF8465B3C61FE1DFD66FD8D" box="[523,678,511,536]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.1975" metricValueMax="1.35" metricValueMin="1.045" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" unit="m" value="1197.5" valueMax="1350.0" valueMin="1045.0">
<elevation id="14BDD1C1FFF8465B3C61FE1DFD66FD8D" box="[523,678,511,536]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.1975" metricValueMax="1.35" metricValueMin="1.045" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" unit="m" value="1197.5" valueMax="1350.0" valueMin="1045.0">1045-1350 m</elevation>
</quantity>
; 
<geoCoordinate id="FAA45035FFF8465B3CD9FE1DFCCCFD82" box="[691,780,511,536]" direction="south" orientation="latitude" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" precision="925" value="-18.1">18°06’S</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate id="FAA45035FFF8465B3D4CFE1DFC4DFD82" box="[806,909,511,536]" direction="west" orientation="longitude" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" precision="925" value="-63.6">63°36’W</geoCoordinate>
), 
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3DC9FDE2FBC9FD82" box="[931,1033,511,536]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="female">1 female</specimenCount>
, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3A7CFDE2FB6AFD82" box="[1046,1194,512,536]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2013-12-04" valueMax="2013-12-09" valueMin="2013-12-04">
<collectingDate id="FB6AE9DAFFF8465B3A7CFDE2FB6AFD82" box="[1046,1194,512,536]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2013-12-04" valueMax="2013-12-09" valueMin="2013-12-04">4-9.XII.2013</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3AD2FDE2FAD0FD8D" box="[1208,1296,512,535]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Wappes</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3B5DFE1DFA5CFD82" box="[1335,1436,511,536]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Skillman</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode id="F981AE37FFF8465B3EB9FDC6FEE5FDA6" box="[211,293,548,572]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">FWSC</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 1 female, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3FDEFDC6FD92FDA6" box="[436,594,548,572]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2014-10-17" valueMax="2014-10-24" valueMin="2014-10-17">17-24.X.2014</date>
, Wappes &amp; Morris col. (ACMT); 1 female, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3A35FDC6FAD4FDA6" box="[1119,1300,548,572]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2013-10-31" valueMax="2013-11-03" valueMin="2013-10-31">31.X-3.XI.2013</date>
, Wappes &amp; Kuckartz col. (ACMT); (
<quantity id="58689B17FFF8465B3FC5FDAAFD89FDFA" box="[431,585,584,608]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.1" metricValueMax="1.2" metricValueMin="1.0" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" unit="m" value="1100.0" valueMax="1200.0" valueMin="1000.0">1000-1200 m</quantity>
), 1 male, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3CDDFDA5FCEEFDFA" box="[695,814,583,608]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2011-10-25">25.X.2011</date>
, Skillman &amp; Wappes col. (FWSC); (
<quantity id="58689B17FFF8465B3AADFDAAFAE0FDFA" box="[1223,1312,584,608]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.0" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" unit="m" value="1000.0">1000 m</quantity>
), 1 female, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3EFDFD8EFED9FD1E" box="[151,281,620,644]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2007-10-04" valueMax="2007-10-08" valueMin="2007-10-04">4-8.X.2007</date>
, Wappes &amp; Morris col. (RFMC); (3363’), 2 males, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3DE8FD8EFBD2FD1E" box="[898,1042,620,644]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2008-10-01" valueMax="2008-10-10" valueMin="2008-10-01">1-10.X.2008</date>
, Morris &amp; Wappes col. (RFMC); 
<materialsCitation id="2FF83CAFFFF8465B3EFDFD6DFAE2FD32" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="1828872764" box="[151,1314,655,680]" collectingDate="2004-10-09" collectingDateMax="2004-10-11" collectingDateMin="2004-10-09" collectionCode="ACMT" collectorName="Morris &amp; Wappes" country="Bolivia" location="Achira Campo" municipality="Amboro" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" stateProvince="Santa Cruz" typeStatus="holotype">
<collectingMunicipality id="7F4BAC88FFF8465B3EFDFD6DFF34FD32" box="[151,244,655,680]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Amboro</collectingMunicipality>
road above 
<location id="9A4F6029FFF8465B3F17FD6DFDE0FD32" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:173987E4FFFA465B3EFDFC4DFD87FBCD:9A4F6029FFF8465B3F17FD6DFDE0FD32" box="[381,544,655,680]" country="Bolivia" municipality="Amboro" name="Achira Campo" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" stateProvince="Santa Cruz">Achira Campo</location>
(5000-5800’), 
<specimenCount id="8996FD7BFFF8465B3CA0FD72FCD8FD32" box="[714,792,655,680]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="male">1 male</specimenCount>
, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3D48FD72FC71FD32" box="[802,945,656,680]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2004-10-09" valueMax="2004-10-11" valueMin="2004-10-09">
<collectingDate id="FB6AE9DAFFF8465B3D48FD72FC71FD32" box="[802,945,656,680]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2004-10-09" valueMax="2004-10-11" valueMin="2004-10-09">9-11.X.2004</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3DD7FD6DFBC9FD32" box="[957,1033,655,680]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Morris</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName id="32655324FFF8465B3A46FD72FB44FD3D" box="[1068,1156,656,679]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Wappes</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode id="F981AE37FFF8465B3AA8FD72FAD9FD32" box="[1218,1305,656,680]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">ACMT</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 1 male, 
<date id="EB2E1032FFF8465B3BEFFD72FECFFD56" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" value="2004-10-09" valueMax="2004-10-11" valueMin="2004-10-09">9- 11.X.2004</date>
, Wappes &amp; Morris col. (ACMT).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D78A6579FFF8465B3EADFD35FE17FC8F" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF8465B3EADFD35FE17FC8F" blockId="7.[151,1437,151,1112]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3EADFD35FE86FD6A" bold="true" box="[199,326,727,752]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Etymology</emphasis>
. This new species is named to recognize Fred W. Skillman, one of the primary collectors of specimens in the 
<typeStatus id="402B8850FFF8465B3F32FD1FFE48FC8F" box="[344,392,765,789]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">type</typeStatus>
series.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D78A6579FFF8465B3EADFCFDFD87FBCD" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="9F2F36F2FFF8465B3EADFCFDFD87FBCD" blockId="7.[151,1437,151,1112]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3EADFCFDFEF4FCA2" bold="true" box="[199,308,799,824]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">Remarks</emphasis>
. 
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3F2BFCC2FDCBFCA2" box="[321,523,800,824]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
RΟsalba 
<taxonomicName id="58904D71FFF8465B3FCEFCC2FDCBFCA2" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo &amp; Joly &amp; Tavakilian, 2018" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo &amp; Joly &amp; Tavakilian" authorityYear="2018" box="[420,523,800,824]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Rosalba" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="skillmani" status="sp. nov.">skillmani</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3C7BFCFDFDAAFCA2" bold="true" box="[529,618,799,824]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="B6D7579BFFF8465B3C7BFCFDFDAAFCA2" box="[529,618,799,824]" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
differs from all other known species in the genus by the elytral pattern of pubescence, including a bicolorous oblique band, on distal half of the elytra. 
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3A40FCA6FB46FCC6" box="[1066,1158,836,860]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">RΟsalba</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="58904D71FFF8465B3AFBFCA6FEF4FC1A" authority="Galileo &amp; Martins, 2006" authorityName="Galileo &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2006" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Rosalba" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incrustabilis">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3AFBFCA6FADDFCC6" box="[1169,1309,836,860]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">incrustabilis</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="FB014B03FFF8465B3B42FCA6FEF4FC1A" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" refId="ref48061" refString="Galileo, M. H. M. &amp; Martins, U. R. (2006) Inventario descritivo. In: Galileo, M. H. M. &amp; Martins, U. R. (Orgs.), Cerambycidae (Coleoptera, Insecta) do Parque Copesul de Protecao Ambiental, Triunfo, Rio Grande do Sul, Brasil. Museu de Ciencias Naturais da Fundacao Zoobotanica do RS, Porto Alegre, pp. 65 - 309." type="book chapter">Galileo &amp; Martins, 2006</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
has somewhat similar pubescence on distal half of the elytra, but 
<taxonomicName id="58904D71FFF8465B3A7FFC8BFB5BFC1A" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo &amp; Joly &amp; Tavakilian" authorityYear="2018" box="[1045,1179,872,896]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Rosalba" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="skillmani">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3A7FFC8BFB5BFC1A" box="[1045,1179,872,896]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">R. skillmani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
differs from it in other ways, as follows: antennae surpassing elytral apex at antennomere VIII; basal ring of antennomeres with light pubescence small, mainly after V; oblique elytral band narrower, better delimited, not surrounded with white pubescence; elytral apex slightly oblique truncate. In 
<taxonomicName id="58904D71FFF8465B3D4CFC37FC19FC76" authorityName="Galileo &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2006" box="[806,985,980,1004]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Rosalba" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incrustabilis">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3D4CFC37FC19FC76" box="[806,985,980,1004]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">R. incrustabilis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
the antennae surpass elytral apex at antennomere IX, the basal ring of the antennomeres is distinctly larger, including on antennomeres V–XI, the oblique elytral band is wider and surrounded with whitish pubescence, and the elytral apex is strongly obliquely truncate. Vide remarks on 
<taxonomicName id="58904D71FFF8465B3FD5FBA3FD80FBC2" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Galileo &amp; Joly &amp; Tavakilian" authorityYear="2018" box="[447,576,1088,1112]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Rosalba" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="208" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="giesberti">
<emphasis id="ADE4EAE0FFF8465B3FD5FBA3FD80FBC2" box="[447,576,1088,1112]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="208">R. giesberti</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>