<document id="31DAA24D61C7263C7B20C3B9B4961DC9" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6292980" ID-GBIF-Dataset="620aac46-b4c8-42a1-a0a0-409792b70c2b" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100130619" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6292980" ModsDocID="3948" checkinTime="1243374478140" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Forel, A." docDate="1893" docId="1C346E0FE45FD3F6BFB458643E5831DF" docLanguage="en" docName="3948" docOrigin="Transactions of the Entomological Society of London 1893" docSource="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/social_insects/ants/publications/3948/3948.pdf" docTitle="Pheidole guilelmi muelleri subsp. antillana Forel, 1893, n. st." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="404" masterDocId="3C86B8CE88F3E20382761CE3CF3BA529" masterDocTitle="Formicides de l'Antille St. Vincent. Récoltées par Mons. H. H. Smith." masterLastPageNumber="418" masterPageNumber="333" pageNumber="401" updateTime="1645845610579" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="D68FBDC03077AFB927FCD03F2064AA06" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="F785B1534E9C9CA7F54EDFE23F14696D">
<mods:title id="09746BA93B4739BF701499D13C59D51B">Formicides de l'Antille St. Vincent. Récoltées par Mons. H. H. Smith.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A089FE437A2DE633612C390EF57691B3" type="personal">
<mods:role id="FDADE81ECA55F46C259A317FC48DBFFC">
<mods:roleTerm id="F2F930214B2C0322518333507864395A">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="CCA50030EB8F27CDAFCF3ADE6EC40544">Forel, A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="2F76F8605D9FA5198435D0372FA6D6D0">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="CF95AFCE031D2B351BCAADDD3B7B02D5" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="FFE7849DFA52F5B583C73FAFAACE100D">
<mods:title id="D7EC1BC992523150BC7F2DB056601357">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="EB798F3D2358EFE429497ADD7BB0A85C">
<mods:date id="E98F9A3D5BC4EB1F9E429B700F78A6F6">1893</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="F1FEB576D14122F9A8D289E268C1178F" type="volume">
<mods:number id="5B25B5AF5555C1965F9C28D72406E35D">1893</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="656BE1E6B9B0304B89ED50DC7184CF7A" unit="page">
<mods:start id="3F84934C1F63C587B95EFC7F0295552C">333</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F40C759C8867EA243C1E360CB74390E7">418</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="1218B7A02FA4A2AC3890A5719948C764">
<mods:url id="891A64BD493CF2573578813EAE36AA82">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/social_insects/ants/publications/3948/3948.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="25A4738EB775770188FA406BD009801C">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="FFFA97A7DDF46F74B9B6F2DBDCBEF548" type="HNS-PUB">3948</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="3CC1B0FDA54F8CE03E6323EB8B0634E6" type="ZooBank">5E6A481F-664E-428C-A636-08D4BD5A1EF0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="1C346E0FE45FD3F6BFB458643E5831DF" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6292980" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100130619" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6292980" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:1C346E0FE45FD3F6BFB458643E5831DF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1C346E0FE45FD3F6BFB458643E5831DF" lastPageNumber="404" pageNumber="401">
<subSubSection id="54DD6E5F00DC6230389BC3ED4C9A5638" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="DD9942FF2AF9F0E0CFA32840560B044F" pageNumber="401">
2. 
<taxonomicName id="11BF6B1ABB14E1B0063AE7CD4866C244" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:230986" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Pheidole" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Pheidole guilelmi muelleri subsp. antillana" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="401" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="guilelmi muelleri" subSpecies="antillana">Pheidole guilelmi muelleri, Forel, r. antillana</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A964411B37A9769C973F684EB297AD48" rank="subSpecies">n. st.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F3AD0813676249AE76F83761BA3FA1E0" type="description">
<paragraph id="299EBCAC5EA88954D0EBB4517B6096FC" pageNumber="401">[[ worker ]] [[ soldier ]] [[ queen ]] [[ male ]]. (No. 23 a a 23 s).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="898D5C53FA3CAE97BC197E48DE16EC95" pageNumber="401">Plus petite que l'espece typique du Bresil meridional, dont le soldat et l'ouvriere sont seuls connus.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="897ED34CC793FB16EEFCF66100783882" pageNumber="401">[[ soldier ]]. (soldat). L. 4, 2 a 5 mill. Differe de la forme typique par les caracteres suivants. Tete plus longue, tres sensiblement plus longue que large, a cotes presque droits et paralleles (distinctement convexes chez l'espece typique). Les scapes n'atteignent que les | de la distance de leur articulation a l'angle occipital (presque la moitie chez l'espece typique). Le bourrelet transversal du mesonotum est plus proeminent et a des angles lateraux tres nets. L'incisure meso-metanotale est bien moins profonde; les epines sont plus fortes et un peu plus longues. Le second n oe ud du pedicule est plus court et plus large; sa longueur n'a guere que les f de sa largeur (les 1 / 5 ou les 3 / 5 chez l'espece typique). La tete est ridee jusque vers les angles occipitaux qui ont de gros points enfonces, comme chez la P. Risii. Pilosite un peu plus courte et un peu plus fine que chez l'espece typique, du reste identique, ainsi que la couleur.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1C1A4CF39B8DBEF7B04E060AB8E9A450" pageNumber="401">[[ worker ]]. L. 2, 0 a 2, 3 mill. (3 a 3, 3 chez l'espece typique). La tete est moins circulairement arrondie que chez l'espece typique, sans avoir le bord posterieur distinct de la P. Risii. Le thorax a la forme de l'espece typique et non celle de la P. Risii, mais les tubercules du mesonotum sont un peu moins apparents et le meta- notum n'a que deux dents triangulaires. Le 2 me n oe ud du pedicule est a peine plus long que large. La tete est luisante et assez lisse ¡ elle n'a que quelques rides transversales derriere et les rides arquees des fossettes antennaires (chez l'espece typique et chez la P. Risii elle est fortement ridee et reticulee). Le thorax est aussi bien plus luisant et plus lisse. Les mandibules sont plus petites et le bord anterieur de l'epistome est crenele, comme chez l'espece typique. Pilosite comme chez le [[ soldier ]]. Le reste comme chez l'espece typique,</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CC5A10F958CE4EABA19F74A6897D859D" lastPageNumber="402" pageNumber="401">[[ queen ]]. L. 5 a 5, 5 mill. Comme le [[ soldier ]] Tete aussi large que longue, aussi large devant que derriere, plus large et aussi grande que le thorax. Ce dernier court, aplati dessus. Les deux faces du meta notum subegales, bordees d'aretes qui sont la continuation ante- rieure et posterieure des epines. Ces dernieres triangulaires, larges. Premier article du pedicule avec une convexite longitudinale dessous; second article trois fois plus large que long, avec un bourrelet transversal dessous. Abdomen petit, tronque devant.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6FF4C0B22693FC98B0AD6A1CD2E56F1F" pageNumber="402">Tete entierement et grossierement ridee-reticulee et subopaque; seul le derriere de l'occiput est finement coriace et assez luisant. Dos du mesonotum lisse et luisant au milieu, ride en long sur les cotes. Metanotum en partie ride; sa face declive lisse et luisante. N oe uds du pedicule et devant de l'abdomen subopaques et tres finement coriaces. Pilosite comme chez le [[ soldier ]], mais plus abondante, plus reguliere et plus oblique sur le corps.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="83E9C52A4FEF0BC6535FF6ADD83CD733" pageNumber="402">Roussatre avec les pattes et les antennes d'un roux jaunatre. Ailes teintees d'un jaune un peu brunatre; nervures et pterostigma d'un brun roussatre.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="042FA6F8AC6DE488FF6E790B94BBBCF0" pageNumber="402">[[ male ]]. L. 2, 8 a 3, 2 mill. Mandibules etroites, bidentees, avec le bord interne parallele au bord externe. Ocelles situes sur une eminence de la tete. Metanotum arrondi, sans tubercules; ses deux faces subegales. ' Pedicule et abdomen etroits et allonges.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CF8948DDB31714390EA3FBB8A450F4BA" pageNumber="402">D'un jaune pale et sale; une tache brune autour des ocelles. Luisant et assez lisse. Pilosite dressee fine, oblique, plus courte et moins abondante que chez les autres sexes; ailes bien plus transparentes que chez la [[ queen ]].</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E8823E1F98DBE0EA80C8E2A4C01A055E" pageNumber="402">La taille de la [[ queen ]] et du [[ male ]] est extraordinairement petite relativement a celle du soldat.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="31AB1AC92BA61B1F60C618594DAFD28F" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph id="1A0FB306D91C0FA92DF377C4D0D7F2A1" pageNumber="402">(23). A common species in forest and shady places. The colonies are generally composed of one or two hundred individuals at most, but may have as many as six or seven hundred. The formicarium is generally under bark of very rotten logs, or under a log or stick; rarely under a stone or under turf on a rock. It is an irregular chamber, with short radiating passages, the whole commonly occupying only two or three inches of space. The workers major are few in number, sometimes only one or two in the colony. Both workers major and workers minor are sluggish, especially the former. I have never found these ants except in the nests.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D1C55D86BA34CCBFD8FE12E3947884E8" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="6920F1A51BD74A2D3127BB2B9707ED81" lastPageNumber="403" pageNumber="402">(23 a). Richmond Estate (leeward); valley near sealevel. Oct. 31 st. Shady place. Formicarium under a stone; an irregular chamber, about 2 x 1 in., with branches extending 2 in. deep. Workers major few, minors numerous. A single male and several winged females found.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9D91D5886B8324AB8F3229F3EC17BC88" pageNumber="403">(23 b). Petit Bordelle Valley (leeward), 1000 ft. Nov. 3 rd. Shady place, near a stream. Formicarium under turf on a rock. The colony was pretty large (several hundreds).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="67EC2699A9F7EE082AA3434F8A2A8A47" pageNumber="403">(23 c). Fitz-Hugh Valley (leeward), Nov. 4 th, 500 ft. Shady place. A small colony under bark of very rotten log.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="62091C735FB914D7AE9FB3186CF5FA7C" pageNumber="403">(23 d). Leeward side, near sea-level. April. A single male referred to this species. It was taken flying over a cane-field, at nightfall.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E25771BB588FE6AF1EAA6D2C554756AD" pageNumber="403">(23 e). July. Locality not noted. (Female).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8016F963756CED098053126F6584B4DD" pageNumber="403">(23 f). Leeward; forest hill-side, 500 ft.; under rotting leaves. November.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5EB649B213BD78228C89E0181C0E88D5" pageNumber="403">(23 g). Forest, Morne a Garou, Oct. 27 th and Nov. 1 st, 1500 ft. Collected from several colonies, generally under bark or on the lower sides of logs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="515D760B2B24E0DD998F4239EC8748E7" pageNumber="403">(23 h). Near Palmyra Estate (leeward), 1000 ft. From a pretty large colony; under a log, shady place.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="278E1080828C4AA92E986293F8FF0F38" pageNumber="403">(23 i). Forest, Morne a Garou, 1500 ft. Oct. 27 th. A small colony in rotten wood.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B3F6EC239DA7EE6EF2014CA9AC00608B" pageNumber="403">(23 j). Same locality as No. 23 i. Another colony.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5E5A591B43D2377EE339801A34858196" pageNumber="403">(23 k). Wallilobo Valley (leeward), 250 ft. Nov. 8 th. Open place near a stream. Formicarium in turf and rubbish on a rock. A large colony.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="51AED380C1573B8411420A3C24CF03D8" pageNumber="403">(23 l). Wallilobo Valley, 500 ft.; forest. At the roots of Lycopodia growing on a rock. A small colony. Nov. 8 th.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="974A5DF9441856823EDE7FFBB51F72EE" pageNumber="403">(23 m). Wallilobo Valley, 500 ft.; forest. In rotten wood. The formicarium was in a small cavity near the surface of the log, and there were less than a dozen ants. Many seeds were stored in the cavity, and specimens of these are in the bottle with ants. Nov. 8 th.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B0490120F49BF3C6255C71036B584B75" pageNumber="403">(23 n). Petit Bordelle Valley, 1200 ft. Nov. 18 th. Shady bank of stream; under sod on a rock. The formicarium occupied a space six or eight inches long, with a smoothly worked chamber about two inches long, the remainder being passages on two sides, following a depression of the rock. The males were rather numerous; workers major about one-tenth as many as workers minor. Several hundred ants in the nest.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7E0628A6AC79CCEF470A2D23287DA469" pageNumber="403">(23 o). Petit Bordelle Valley, 1200 ft. Nov. 13 th. Another nest similar to No. 28 n.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8AC3D7416B3827EE824AF4FCDD1F340D" pageNumber="403">(23 p). Petit Bordelle Valley, 1300 ft. Nov. 13 th.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="036FEA55EA82DD0CD651EEF265A39951" pageNumber="404">Shady bank of stream; under sod on a rock. The nest was a pretty large one, with three chambers each, about three inches long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F394E66EF2BE2DF80A7C795F4F7112C3" pageNumber="404">(23 q) Upper Richmond Valley, 1500 ft. Nov. 27 th. Under sod on rocks; forest by the river. From two nests. Common in this locality, which is in the midst of the forest region.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="946305705118B6D8295BB30E880C0C00" pageNumber="404">(23 r). Hermitage Estate, Cumberland Valley, 1000 ft.; open hill-side. Nest in a small cavity of a rotten log. (23 s). Forest by stream; above Chateaubeiais (leeward), 250 ft. Jan. 26 th. Nest in rotten wood. A small community.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>