<document id="09A98863634838599B8A0A0E2959425D" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bdfb4b8e-4c36-4386-a7d0-7437b44fcba1" ModsDocID="21061" checkinTime="1252706925963" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Heterick, B. E." docDate="2006" docId="21617108E22066F650AF52067F5D5279" docLanguage="en" docName="21061.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 57" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf" docTitle="Monomorium platynodis Heterick, 2006, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="137" masterDocId="3A2C4F9A5833769B5007E7556E53E380" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="202" masterPageNumber="69" pageNumber="135" updateTime="1569525778780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="085BD20D6665F67BEE7EC8A546635E8E" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="BFC8D12455113D37887BD1B8169DE6B0">
<mods:title id="04E15A345B58238743BF15828D953F16">A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="89E679AFC2C83A33CD68B441141FB039" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B7541F843BAA3C5A1225FE406A976E9D">
<mods:roleTerm id="AB5D88CCBC01C096F8855E0549C81151">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="9EAE66511DBCCD969BFA67CADA528653">Heterick, B. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="E637D7769E4E9F5E99E77C80B296EABF">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="E8C224344BF857CACD92D83DD103D509" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3896F15AB85D6CA04C290AE86D643D86">
<mods:title id="D6395C291CCA853900DC14AC03F17271">Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="04667B8F57F7476718D93BE1C6CEC6BC">
<mods:date id="507B350B416D2BE8F29FEFAD7C3BC9C0">2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="76F729958CDC3C7D00E59D0275FEA5FB" type="volume">
<mods:number id="8E156444594BCA8ECCE7E5C4908FC8F2">57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="971A39EFA2EA1721AA6B488A11CE7FF6" unit="page">
<mods:start id="FE87B4D615B3A66F5C1C24BA7220765B">69</mods:start>
<mods:end id="A040BD358A1F067D430F869A5C9FA7D2">202</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="F65075B424E0F4F262A22EEE9598FFE8">
<mods:url id="C7E9BAD41BA85AE95CCD7ABFE067BB0D">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="472EDB51EF1AB05A92A98B319530DAC7">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="1E1A0F6D3D4B72E0910702B816E99692" type="HNS-PUB">21061</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="21617108E22066F650AF52067F5D5279" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:21617108E22066F650AF52067F5D5279" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/21617108E22066F650AF52067F5D5279">
<subSubSection id="8152E97B5048BA57B8B63FA8FA427647" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="E5ED9153B4AFD394F8E8574B87B38ED8" pageNumber="135">
<taxonomicName id="7A1C94E78351443079AC36D2102BE40D" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196252" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium platynodis Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium platynodis Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="135" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="platynodis">Monomorium platynodis Heterick</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A775E13C4D2A9338166A998463778B55" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="EC71A9A7139AB540E24DD5642E6051D9" type="description">
<paragraph id="1A24EE61A2754A020E981BBAAB5F9D4A" pageNumber="135">Figs. 22, 63-64.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C8119E12F59CFA21ED8DB5D8113CD237" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="3FEFB7A5494B9A229AA5D724431DCC5A" pageNumber="135">Etymology.- Greek &quot;platys&quot; (flat) + pl. of masc. &quot;nodus&quot;</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="DE524D8745AA31A835DFDB20CC759012" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="2FFE7D7F6939EFFB7BEE68C8E54C0F0C" pageNumber="136">Material examined.- Holotype: [[worker]], Prov. Toamasina, Mont Anjanaharibe, 18.0 km 21 NNE Ambinanitelo 470 m 15°11'3&quot;S, 49°36'9&quot;E, 8-12.iii.2003 Fisher et al. BLF 8002/sifted litter tropical dry forest /CASENT 0026538 8002(24) (CAS). Paratypes: Prov. Toamasina (all specimens with same collection data as holotype): 13 [[worker]] (ANIC); 13 [[worker]] (BMNH); 13 [[male]] + 13 [[worker]] (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="399F9790BE2AE869CBF74C78330CD570" pageNumber="136">Other material examined: Prov. Antsiranana: Ampasindava, Ambilanivy, 3.9 km 181 S Ambaliha 4-9.iii.2001 Fisher et al. (1 [[worker]], 1[[male]]). Prov. Mahajanga: P.N. Namoroka, 17.8 km 329 WNW Vilanandro, 8-12.xi.2002 Fisher et al. (2[[worker]]). Prov. Toamasina: FC. Didy, 16-23.xii.1998 H.J. Ratsirarson (1 [[worker]]). Prov. Toliara: 6 km SSW Eminiminy, Res. Andohahela 4.ii.1993 (3 [[worker]], 3 [[male]]) (MCZ); 11 km NW Enakara, Res. Andohahela 17.xi.1992 B.L. Fisher (3 [[worker]]).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="584EA15866B60AB9B0D5036B5524AA1A" type="description">
<paragraph id="F17EBCBA5B7F08AD15504601C4F48DE2" pageNumber="136">Worker description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex weakly concave; frons shining and smooth except for piliferous pits; pilosity of frons a mixture of well-spaced, distinctly longer erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with shorter decumbent setae or setulae. Eye large, eye width 1.5x greater than greatest width of antennal scape; (in full-face view) eyes set above midpoint of head capsule to set below midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set around midline of head capsule; eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin, or, elongate, eye narrowed to point anteriad; Antennal segments 12; antennal club threesegmented. Clypeal carinae indistinct; anteromedian clypeal margin straight; paraclypeal setae moderately long and fine, curved; posteromedian clypeal margin approximately level with antennal fossae. Anterior tentorial pits situated nearer antennal fossae than mandibular insertions. Frontal lobes sinuate, divergent posteriad. Psammophore absent. Mandibular with three evenly sized teeth; mandibles with sub-parallel inner and outer margins, smooth (except for piliferous pits); masticatory margin of mandibles approximately vertical or weakly oblique; basal tooth approximately same size as t2 (three teeth present).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2F73ADEB1E77188554000A9BBFB006D0" pageNumber="136">Mesosoma: Promesonotum shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to lower anterior mesopleuron; (viewed in profile) promesonotum broadly convex; promesonotal setae seven to greater than twelve; standing promesonotal setae consisting of well-spaced, incurved, erect and semi-erect setae only; appressed promesonotal setulae few, mainly on sides of promesonotum. Metanotal groove strongly impressed, with distinct transverse costulae. Propodeum shining and smooth, with a few weak striolae on metapleuron; propodeal dorsum convex; propodeum always smoothly rounded; standing propodeal setae consisting of two or more prominent pairs anteriad, often with another pair of prominent setae posteriad, and other smaller setae on/around dorsal and declivitous surfaces of propodeum; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle equidistant from metanotal groove and declivitous face of propodeum. Vestibule of propodeal spiracle distinct in some specimens. Propodeal lobes present as rounded flanges.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="061F1AA736CF814779376BEA78D2AFB2" pageNumber="136">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle laterodorsal and situated slightly anteriad of petiolar node, or, lateral and situated within anterior sector of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) cuneate, vertex tapered; appearance of node shining and smooth throughout; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) between 1:1 and 3:4; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; ventral petiolar lobe present; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole about 4:3; height-length ratio of postpetiole about 3:2; postpetiole shining and smooth; postpetiolar sternite without anterior lip or carina, or this structure vestigial.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6397260FA230E624CD737CFE4DCAAE47" pageNumber="136">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with a few appressed setulae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0F437189946A1772C2DB30FD1B37C64C" pageNumber="136">General characters: Color bright yellow-orange. Worker caste monomorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C2C1167833CBD30273A60B29F4E7A344" pageNumber="136">Holotype measurements: HML 1.15 HL 0.42 HW 0.34 CeI 81 SL 0.29 SI 85 PW 0.24.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7C05C4D85EF793A2BE3F2C5913CE71EF" pageNumber="136">Other worker measurements: HML 1.18-1.33 HL 0.44-0.50 HW 0.36-0.39 CeI 75-84 SL 0.31-0.35 SI 84-91 PW 0.25-0.27 (n=18).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D737BB9622938D0599E32B1D3995CD43" pageNumber="137">Male description.- Head: Head width-mesosoma width ratio between 1:1 and 3:4; frons finely micropunctate. Compound eyes protuberant and elliptical; margin of compound eye clearly separated from posterior margin of clypeus. Ocelli not turreted. Ratio of length of first funicular segment of antenna to second funicular segment about 1:1. Maximum number of mandibular teeth and denticles three.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="203C5CF2B9E598AC668A739A2CA3AC90" pageNumber="137">Mesosoma: Mesoscutum broadly convex; pronotum and mesoscutum shining, with dorsum of mesoscutum faintly striolate. Parapsidal furrows vestigial or absent; notauli absent. Axillae separated by width of at least one axilla.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FB47C988E5CCAE6A1DCC025D84820351" pageNumber="137">Wing: Wing veins predominantly depigmented, with distal segments reduced to vestigial lines; vein m-cu absent; vein cu-a absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C111668E6B7F7D681BD73025DE2D0E05" pageNumber="137">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated within anterior sector of petiolar node. Node (viewed in profile) conical, vertex rounded; appearance of node shining and smooth; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) about 4:3. Anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial. Height ratio of petiole to postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; height-length ratio of postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; postpetiole shining and smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="87C1E173CB1E0198513F38E0F0C82897" pageNumber="137">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, semi-erect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C249D72EF5BFB6E2225437D741D9917C" pageNumber="137">General characters: Color brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9DFA2D73E1FD3878093BAE2D8475797D" pageNumber="137">Male measurements: HML 1.31-1.44; HL 0.40-0.41; HW 0.35-0.38; CeI 88-93; SL 0.14-0.17; SI 39-46; PW 0.42-0.44 (n=3).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="368E01D234F1B3A3BF6775C5BBE7E11B" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="FF663A870E6822B8963B3A9DFEC584AD" pageNumber="137">
Remarks.- 
<taxonomicName id="E9B7D9ADAFC3F6262B72F06AA78117F5" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196252" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium platynodis Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium platynodis Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="platynodis">Monomorium platynodis</taxonomicName>
is a rather rare species, which, nonetheless, ranges throughout the entire island of Madagascar. Recorded material comes from Antsiranana, Mahajanga, Toamasina and Toliara provinces. The uniformly orange workers are immediately identifiable through their truncated clypeus, three-toothed mandibles and high nodes. The very small males (the queen is not known) resemble those of 
<taxonomicName id="3D6AC9AF23D92F0E5C48C2BE9F58D291" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31564" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium exiguum Forel" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium exiguum Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exiguum">M. exiguum</taxonomicName>
. The mandible of the male also has three strong teeth, and the entire anterior clypeal margin is straight and well-separated from the basal margin of the mandible. The male node seen in full-face view is bimodal. Specimens of 
<taxonomicName id="20EBAE17D37B49EEC668837B68C5EDEA" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196252" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium platynodis Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium platynodis Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="137" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="platynodis">M. platynodis</taxonomicName>
have been collected from sifted litter and by hand from a rotten log in tropical dry forest and rainforest.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>