<document id="58276F800176F36788E27B68087E1ADB" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.23000" ID-GBIF-Dataset="703b08f5-93d0-4fe7-9828-e2f3d90d554b" ID-GBIF-Taxon="140417926" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-0743-1-73" ID-ZBK="9C28FEF8BA694BCDA91BFA910956E2DD" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2C36E902-F854-409D-9FEA-98C41EB299F8" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1860-0743-1-73" ModsDocOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 94 (1)" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Eisothistos (Isopoda, Cymothoida) and first molecular data on six species of Anthuroidea from the Peninsular Malaysia" checkinTime="1516918307713" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Chew, Melvin, Rahim, Azman bin Abdul &amp; binti Mohd Yusof, Nurul Yuziana" docDate="2018" docId="27380EF4962C540EC90CCB622E906582" docLanguage="en" docName="ZoosystEvol 94(1): 73-81" docOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 94 (1)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.23000" docTitle="Eisothistos tiomanensis Chew, Rahim &amp; Yusof, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="2C36E902-F854-409D-9FEA-98C41EB299F8" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="78" masterDocId="E77BFF898D57F643073CFF92FF9CFFC7" masterDocTitle="A new species of Eisothistos (Isopoda, Cymothoida) and first molecular data on six species of Anthuroidea from the Peninsular Malaysia" masterLastPageNumber="81" masterPageNumber="73" pageId="2" pageNumber="75" updateTime="1643515866645" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="252C24795D7ABF48E7BA16D2ED42D655" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="893AFF018A70E43CE16FA4DC8A907935">
<mods:title id="617A9397E572A65CC3E90C23D59D0161">A new species of Eisothistos (Isopoda, Cymothoida) and first molecular data on six species of Anthuroidea from the Peninsular Malaysia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="B4E33805E131D53A443A382316FC9261" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AE10568F4BAAC985FCFB02163F207F15">
<mods:roleTerm id="97AA98CA1296EC2700A7BAB1E790FC7C">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="57B72ADE06D74D7C160B45DF65AE3433">Chew, Melvin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="CA881842E2DF0F571CBB96FB9960D1E2" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F3CE26B1DADF5644086F335072A3A338">
<mods:roleTerm id="E69B32983737BFB85EE5385567D4AE23">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="647DFC4CE3B4EF0CDE0E39F358FB5310">Rahim, Azman bin Abdul</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="E68474421D77BC12ABC1BBE7E3D83216" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B9658DAC40DCC10C9D062BB3B844FFA1">
<mods:roleTerm id="DDB79EFDE85D8DE500D7465A50377B68">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5A4F3B08B4859DEDD178CE4DE7AD8BB6">binti Mohd Yusof, Nurul Yuziana</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="6CACCA6544F2581D120F75FB47D89AFA">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="0360AD2D5BC6DC0FCDB55AAB79FCBDDD" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="64144A6688A51976C0C9C459C05DF1A3">
<mods:title id="1566DBD1A220C6F6979682D636CEDFAD">Zoosystematics and Evolution</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="10CA017245FA0BCD91E958DA93460CE7">
<mods:date id="426F5502B5626D0A7BF610FA7A2C66DD">2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="BB5B3BFC831FA79F46A00E0D7E7DD413" type="volume">
<mods:number id="2A0E3F86AE55CA4A28C695BBDB17B1C3">94</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="EEED568A543A07084EB3872A64BDCC17" type="issue">
<mods:number id="2AA060C1385BCAEE88005750DF6824C2">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="98F4BA71945C4FC2299CCB1E6E0B7A01" unit="page">
<mods:start id="AD2239F210CA9D1A0AE5C18A1F1CAD17">73</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B3AD19D043B8FD646C5AE603FABEAE24">81</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="BDBE783CA6BF64109BD0601379C1AE8E">
<mods:url id="B37E8133FFB945067BA4955A330308CB">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.23000</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="84EF304386D94D1B08E7E3C905CE7C80">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="6DC7C907D63F9B9D21ACF561E032B998" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.94.23000</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="1433EB1403BE9693D8F323EFB91081F5" type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-0743-1-73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="D0AA313EF351DF47BF95983AB6131AB5" type="ZBK">9C28FEF8BA694BCDA91BFA910956E2DD</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="51F64E1124729C8F234B3E03428ECCCC" type="ZooBank">9C28FEF8BA694BCDA91BFA910956E2DD</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="27380EF4962C540EC90CCB622E906582" ID-GBIF-Taxon="140417926" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2C36E902-F854-409D-9FEA-98C41EB299F8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/27380EF4962C540EC90CCB622E906582" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="78" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">
<subSubSection id="89852A57587351251DB0A8EF81D92659" pageId="2" pageNumber="75" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="55D73CEF60CDEC8F1287CBA86179F36B" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">
<taxonomicName id="9DA15F39FC75D39F4F28B69A40D1D973" LSID="http://zoobank.org/2C36E902-F854-409D-9FEA-98C41EB299F8" class="Malacostraca" family="Anthuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos tiomanensis" order="Isopoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="75" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tiomanensis">Eisothistos tiomanensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="8F4EBF6CB6E47CC92148DC3C00252A6B" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figure 3, 5
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4777BF5BB2B50412A1D4AE9CA2585275" pageId="2" pageNumber="75" type="holotype">
<paragraph id="3891240B87671E9B120727B4A03F51C4" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D5DB347DF2D110258B0B2FE3F44747A" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">
Adult male, UKMMZ-1559, Labas, Pulau Tioman, Pahang, Malaysia, 
<geoCoordinate id="758A11C87627F0BB18B24D1727A10269" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="2.8871415">2°53'13.71&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
; 
<geoCoordinate id="A505B44F39CA97AABE357602625AE014" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="104.065186">104°3'54.65&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
(DMS), C. Melvin, 18 April 2014, coral rubble, ~15 m.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="5C3A3EE8366B7F7E0C5CAF7EA5C0713D" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="2" pageNumber="75" type="description">
<paragraph id="69C40047173CB646DEE8D7B278082874" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F9BCF1BDD0D8D4B46ADF1BE0D168C73A" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">Holotype, adult male.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B6428F3D6D7DC9FF309EE4ED4259E613" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">Total body length 2.2 mm (tip of rostrum to base of telson), approximately 9.9 times as long as greatest width. Cephalon with minute rostrum; eyes grossly enlarged, containing many ommatidia laterally. Pereonites 1-7 progressively shorter, pereonites 2-3 longest, each 1.3 times as long as pereonite 1, pereonites 4-5 each the same length as pereonite 1, pereonite 6 about 0.7 times length of pereonite 5, pereonite 7 half as long as pereonite 5, pereonites 4-6 anteriorly narrow, subdistally widest, pereonite 7 anteriorly narrow, widest posteriorly. Pleonites 1-5 progressively shorter with pleonites 1-2 of similar length, pleonite 3 about 0.8 times as long as pleonite 2, pleonites 4 about 0.7 times as long as pleonite 3, pleonite 5 shortest half as long as pleonite 4, posterior margin of pleonite 6 with a medial cleft.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3652B3ACA0D63F92C182E134A5B55336" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">Antenna 1 peduncle article 1 subquadrate, articles 2-3 progressively shorter; flagellum of 9 articles with short proximal article bearing numerous aesthetascs, articles 2-9 progressively narrower, articles 2-6 each bearing 2 aesthetascs and 1 seta, articles 7-8 each bearing 1 aesthetasc distally, terminal article with 3 apical setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A698D506BEC4B3F0C778058158E925E7" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">Antenna 2 peduncle articles equal, articles 1-2 each bearing 2 setae, article 3 with 1 seta, article 4 elongate, 2.4 times as long as wide, article 5 longest, twice as long as article 4; flagellum of 6 articles, progressively smaller, articles 1-4 each with 1 distal aesthetasc, article 5 with 2 distal setae, terminal article with 4 apical setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7F0BCB6F383D5BD05FEC037F28BDAA8D" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">Mouthparts reduced.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2266C83F4B3FBE6A47057A9D3FB0BC7E" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="76" pageId="2" pageNumber="75">
Pereopod 1 basis 3.3 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 medial seta, posterior margin with 1 subdistal seta and fine setae; ischium 3.2 times as long 
<pageBreakToken id="846E61FDD2D141FB903B6864A2E86277" pageId="3" pageNumber="76" start="start">as</pageBreakToken>
greatest width, posterior margin subdistally with 1 seta and fine setae; merus anterior margin convex distally, bearing 2 setae, posterior margin with fine setae; carpus anterior margin half the length of posterior margin, posterior margin with 1 seta, with 4 submarginal spinules; propodus 4.4 times as long as greatest width, palm weakly concave with 21 submarginal spinules, anterior margin with 1 distal seta, palmar margin with 1 posterodistal robust seta; unguis half as long as propodus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3411DA5364261D78E9399D450AB7C2CD" pageId="3" pageNumber="76">Pereopod 2 basis 3.7 times as long as greatest width, posterior margin with 1 subdistal seta and fine setae; ischium 3.1 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 2 setae, posterior margin with 2 setae and fine setae; merus anterior margin convex, bearing 1 seta, posterior margin with fine setae; carpus anterior margin half the length of posterior margin, posterior margin with 1 seta and fine setae; propodus 3.9 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 2 setae, palmar margin with 1 medial robust seta and 1 posterodistal robust seta, fine setae and subdistal palmar comb; unguis half the length of propodus.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="665602F325BF647CA41D3AD223AFC454" pageId="3" pageNumber="76">Pereopod 3 basis 3.3 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 2 setae and fine setae, posterior margin with 1 seta and fine setae; ischium 3.2 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 2 setae and fine setae, posterior margin with 1 seta and fine setae; merus anterior distal margin convex bearing 2 setae, posterior margin with 1 seta, carpus anterior margin one third length of posterior margin, posterior margin with 1 seta; propodus 3.6 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 2 setae, palmar margin with fine setae, 2 setae, subdistal palmar comb, 1 medial robust seta and 1 posterodistal robust seta; unguis half as long as propodus.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DF1F666C0DB722660603807A8552F0F5" pageId="3" pageNumber="76">Pereopod 4 basis 3.9 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 2 setae and fine setae, posterior margin with 1 seta and fine setae; ischium 3 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta, posterior margin with 2 setae; merus anterior margin convex, bearing 1 seta, posterior margin with 1 seta, carpus linear twice as long as wide anterior margin with 2 setae, posterior margin with setae comb, 1 seta and 1 robust seta; propodus 4.5 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 3 setae, palmar margin bordered with setae comb, 1 medial robust seta and 1 posterodistal robust seta; unguis 0.8 times as long as propodus.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D4C899FD7414B9A796EC6BA9EB506EF9" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="3" pageNumber="76">
Pereopod 5 basis 4.1 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta, posterior margin with 1 seta and fine setae; ischium 4.1 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta, posterior margin with 
<pageBreakToken id="2B8FDD552631FC4E6FEEF0667E5A260E" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" start="start">3</pageBreakToken>
setae and fine setae; merus anterior margin subdistally convex, bearing 2 setae, posterior margin with fine setae; carpus linear 2.4 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta, posterior margin with setae comb, 1 distal seta and 1 distal robust seta; propodus 4.6 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 distal seta, palmar margin bordered with setae comb, 1 medial robust seta and 1 posterodistal robust seta; unguis 0.8 times the length of propodus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A5D36D46683BB2BEC4C7CF65398D64F6" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pereopod 6 basis 4 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 3 setae and fine setae, posterior margin with 1 subdistal seta; ischium 3.8 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with fine setae, posterior margin with 3 setae and fine setae; merus anterior margin convex, bearing 1 seta, posterior margin with 1 seta; carpus linear 2.6 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta, posterior margin bordered with setae comb, distally with 1 seta and 1 robust seta; propodus 5.3 times as long as greatest width, palmar margin bordered with setae comb, proximally with 1 robust seta, medially with 1 robust seta and posterodistally with 1 robust seta; unguis 0.7 times the length of propodus.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E6312E6E91C785A025B54E86B96A9CF3" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pereopod 7 basis 4.1 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta, posterior margin with 1 seta; ischium 3.2 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta and fine setae, posterior margin with 3 setae and fine setae; merus slender 3.6 times as long as greatest width with anterior margin slightly convex, bearing 1 seta, posterior margin with 1 seta; carpus linear 3.2 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 1 seta, posterior margin with setae comb and 1 robust seta; propodus 7.5 times as long as greatest width, anterior margin with 3 setae, palmar margin bordered with setae comb, 1 medial robust seta and 1 posterodistal robust seta; unguis half as long as propodus.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="606594D93274800236AC58CD016607E1" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pleopod 1 with elongated rami, sympod rectangular; exopod slender 4.3 times as long as greatest width, apex truncated bearing 6 plumose setae; endopod shorter than exopod 0.75 times the length of exopod, apex truncated bearing 5 plumose setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9607ED8DEBA49EAFD8DECAD105134E08" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pleopod 2 sympod subrectangular; exopod 3 times as long as wide, apex truncated bearing 7 plumose setae; endopod slender 4.8 times as long as greatest width, apex truncated bearing 5 plumose setae; appendix masculina almost as long as endopod, ending in a somewhat hook-like with a rounded end.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3C246F136C4E21B80392F09701CF80A1" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pleopod 3 not available.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2698B5EE3BDC9536C95779E7F61AFE0A" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pleopod 4 sympod subrectangular, inner margin with 1 seta; exopod broadened 1.8 times as long as greatest width, apex truncated bearing 8 plumose setae, medial lateral margin with 1 seta; endopod as long as exopod 1.3 times as long as exopod with apical margin truncated bearing 6 plumose setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="164F92094123C63746846A13C36E14B7" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pleopod 5 shorter than others with sympod subquadrate; exopod much smaller than endopod half as long as endopod bearing 3 plumose setae; endopod broadend 1.8 times as long as greatest width bearing 2 plumose setae, apical margin medially with two small protuberances.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C74C4A19326B18E8760EC835C7B479D2" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Uropod sympod with serrated inner margin, inner distal margin raised with an acute apex, outer distal margin raised with 2 acute serrations apically; endopod elongate with serrated margin bearing 13 setae, apically with 1 short robust plumose sensory spine; exopod bipartite with 5 setae proximally, medially with a central elongated spike having 3 subdistal setae and apical margin concave bearing 1 short plumose sensory spike, outer margin with a short slender spike bearing 1 seta apically, inner margin obsolete.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DB90B9F25B90F4EF29B714D9FB50E88A" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Pleotelson 2.2 times as long as greatest width, narrowest anteriorly, widest near posterior end, dorsal surface with 4 pairs of setae and a middorsal row of 7 obscure denticles, subdistal margin with 2 obscure teeth on each side, posterior margin strongly dentate with 10 teeth and 5 pairs of setae.</paragraph>
<caption id="7FC8F0CF672F3CF6A28ACA25E0BA7F24" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
<paragraph id="E6DC349117F1067286AB6B6ED2ABAEAE" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName id="F9478EF11EE006983186E9437DE7D277" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos tiomanensis" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tiomanensis">Eisothistos tiomanensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. All scales represent 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="4EEC203F728C351D53CEBFC33AAA39DE" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
<paragraph id="273B2228CB088BE9908E68F2656B543D" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="44ADA150CE7B8779AA4643356DF54A94" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos tiomanensis" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tiomanensis">Eisothistos tiomanensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. All scales represent 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="2904E12DD5D896D7F6F1D1BA7953F7DF" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
<paragraph id="7A7E48D4EF8832F02A386CD3EB0ABB84" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName id="8E047846173461B49BA8757539F159FD" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos tiomanensis" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tiomanensis">Eisothistos tiomanensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. All scales represent 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="A82B89F1350E7D694312E30AEFBF98D2" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
<paragraph id="2829B3E45596118D2CA89C005F9656D1" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
Figure 6. 
<normalizedToken id="AA14A981D6CD8D0CA86DCEF1C06896F0" originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
. 
<taxonomicName id="9D29F26ED81E17D486A2D229ECEEE182" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Expanathura" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Expanathura collaris" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="collaris">Expanathura collaris</taxonomicName>
. A. female. B. male. C. pleotelson. D. uropodal exopod. 
<normalizedToken id="3EB998A186FE8642C9F71F9F695E7B40" originalValue="E–H">E-H</normalizedToken>
. 
<taxonomicName id="293DBB880922AC9514C6C8A343BBF615" class="Malacostraca" family="Leptanthuridae" genus="Accalathura" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Accalathura borradailei" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="borradailei">Accalathura borradailei</taxonomicName>
. E. female. F. male. G. uropodal exopod. H. pleotelson. All scales represent 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D79FF918A32FBFBC39CD3E1A25470175" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="AFCD4EBA762250F440270F7CB73474FB" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C15F86424931AC4AC3F423B2EA712C34" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">This species is named after the type locality, Pulau Tioman, Malaysia.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="72AA1775A1176FA2C77DE6341B11D1F6" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" type="molecular data">
<paragraph id="24D0AB81B31918B3FBBFCD1237345DD5" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Molecular data.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A99F67F9E26E444420136BC9B8CD7ED2" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">n/a.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3C4A2AC499AE799CEB39218DEA0A64D1" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="78" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="59FCDBFBAD61F72C7AA827FE413FFDB1" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="17323ABFB49A3565853C075DE177FB25" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="78" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
Only one male specimen is available. The male 
<taxonomicName id="CEF1CA0404A914CACE34B52E8C87363C" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos" order="Isopoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eisothistos</taxonomicName>
in general, differs from the female by its grossly enlarged eyes, antenna 1 with short basal article bearing numerous aesthetascs, reduced mouthparts, pleonites 1-3 elongate and pleopods 1-3 with elongated peduncles and rami (
<bibRefCitation id="B2E02D648F7EEC3702853D7A94465B74" author="Knight-Jones, EW" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Natural History" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" pagination="1397 - 1419" title="Four new species of Eisothistos (Anthuridae: Isopoda) from tubes of Spirbidae (Serpuloidea: Polychaeta)." url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00222930110052454" volume="36" year="2002">Knight-Jones and Knight-Jones 2002</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="0C4090EC34708CEFC5D9AF5C0BBBC01D" author="Poore, GCB" editor="Kensley, B" journalOrPublisher="Crustacean Issues" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" pagination="63 - 173" title="Families and genera of IsopodaAnthuridea." volume="13" volumeTitle="Isopod systematics and evolution. Balkema, Rotterdam." year="2001">
<pageBreakToken id="DDBDCD12B387FABD6FD4D4F012D87E75" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" start="start">Poore</pageBreakToken>
2001
</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="5D23140CF26EB76A380F3D71CA5916EB" author="Poore, GCB" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" pagination="1 - 60" title="Expanathuridae (Crustacea: Isopoda) from the Australian region." url="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.82.1.1" volume="82" year="2002">Poore and Lew Ton 2002</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="58641F9E33DEE467336530B7478F4E41" author="Waegele, JW" journalOrPublisher="Mitteilungen aus dem Zoologischen Museum der Universitaet Kiel" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" pagination="1 - 19" title="Morphologische Studien an Eisothistos mit Beschreibung von drei neuen Arten (Crustacea, Isopoda, Anthuridea)." volume="1" year="1979">
<normalizedToken id="311569A9C753E15E53371307D58350C7" originalValue="Wägele">Waegele</normalizedToken>
1979
</bibRefCitation>
). Though they appear distinctive, their tail-fan shape are more conserved within a species. Hence, it is possible to determine the identity of 
<taxonomicName id="85A0099074DBEB4C353A03000D906CFB" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos" order="Isopoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eisothistos</taxonomicName>
species based on a male specimen. Moreover in this study, the good condition of preserved material and the unique characteristic of its tail-fan, justify a description.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A12AAF2FF6FC042C71BA10B0FBFF8F35" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">
The uropodal exopod form in the 
<taxonomicName id="DC2DA7F385DF4933DA1E054805D77F8B" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos" order="Isopoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eisothistos</taxonomicName>
can be divided into two types. While most possess the tripartite uropodal exopod shape, several others are described with the uncommon bipartite uropodal exopod shape. 
<taxonomicName id="EFC292008DAF40F1705E945392E088AF" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos tiomanensis" order="Isopoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tiomanensis">Eisothistos tiomanensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. belongs to the latter group with 
<taxonomicName id="843A36EE47563C4BDAB6AE609124D685" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos anomala" order="Isopoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="anomala">Eisothistos anomala</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="B9A88656F65E68FCEA6F7FC2AE875B42" genus="E." lsidName="E. corinellae" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="corinellae">E. corinellae</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="3211AFEBC2CEB93F441F0F4EE6B7C947" genus="E." lsidName="E. macquariensis" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="macquariensis">E. macquariensis</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="08FAC0613ABE3E3A7D186FE012F0AB84" genus="E." lsidName="E. minutus" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="minutus">E. minutus</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation id="0BB495E98FCEBF752970CBC5DB0AD4C3" author="Kensley, B" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington" pageId="6" pageNumber="79" pagination="725 - 742" title="Records of anthurids from Florida, Central America, and South America (Crustacea: Isopoda: Anthuridae)." url="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/34599608" volume="93" year="1980">Kensley 1980</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="90097E8E16604B06478BC9C25D9B2AF8" author="Poore, GCB" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" pagination="1 - 60" title="Expanathuridae (Crustacea: Isopoda) from the Australian region." url="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.82.1.1" volume="82" year="2002">Poore and Lew Ton 2002</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="5DBBB085D345105FC666D18734403047" author="Sivertsen, E" journalOrPublisher="Gunneria" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" pagination="1 - 128" title="The Marine Isopod Crustacea of the Tristan da Cunha archipelago." url="https://www.ntnu.no/c/document_library/get_file?uuid=a84d7dcc-ce88-47f7-9d44-9c2fc3b7181c&amp;groupId=10476" volume="35" year="1980">Sivertsen and Holthuis 1980</bibRefCitation>
). It differs in having a unique two slender spine-like structure in the uropodal exopod rather than one central slender spike-like structure along with a proximal lobe as in 
<taxonomicName id="36570A8B30839174913A0C7F0CF85C89" genus="E." lsidName="E. anomala" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="anomala">E. anomala</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="F4756B462CA832536BF815D8A9C6908A" genus="E." lsidName="E. corinellae" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="corinellae">E. corinellae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="E480930E1391738A413FCB4B36FA81B0" genus="E." lsidName="E. macquariensis" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="macquariensis">E. macquariensis</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName id="1CE3409B3B6437B54D8B56C0237B13B8" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos minutus" order="Isopoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="minutus">Eisothistos minutus</taxonomicName>
on the other hand, possesses a form similar to the present species. 
<bibRefCitation id="31CE7E0BA0490B740A4E67A04EDCB65F" author="Sivertsen, E" journalOrPublisher="Gunneria" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" pagination="1 - 128" title="The Marine Isopod Crustacea of the Tristan da Cunha archipelago." url="https://www.ntnu.no/c/document_library/get_file?uuid=a84d7dcc-ce88-47f7-9d44-9c2fc3b7181c&amp;groupId=10476" volume="35" year="1980">Sivertsen and Holthuis (1980)</bibRefCitation>
described it as &quot;a narrow elongate process on the protopod, it ends in two teeth; the protopod seems to have a second similar process laterally, the nature of this process is not clear&quot;. Nevertheless, there is no strong robust seta on the apex of the central spike and a seta on the lateral spike. Additionally, there are no teeth present on the dorsal surface of the pleotelson in 
<taxonomicName id="B6914EE98C56BD64D5BA8373C12FD983" genus="E." lsidName="E. minutus" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="minutus">E. minutus</taxonomicName>
while there are 7 obscure denticles present in the new Malaysian species.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="41D069A978133AA1CAF5714AF22CD15D" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">
<taxonomicName id="94E5D3F9CD2D10B2BFD516E5A753B8B1" class="Malacostraca" family="Expanathuridae" genus="Eisothistos" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eisothistos" order="Isopoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eisothistos</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is readily distinguishable from the other Malaysian species, 
<taxonomicName id="25A8CA109CFA0C79B495C4EAF759D0F0" genus="E." lsidName="E. besar" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="besar">E. besar</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken id="56EA371C2CD221437001F6D48767DF92" originalValue="Müller">Mueller</normalizedToken>
, 1992 by its bipartite uropodal exopod (tripartite in 
<taxonomicName id="48778E6C1E84A345B023F139E160D1D6" genus="E." lsidName="E. besar" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="besar">E. besar</taxonomicName>
) and the surface of pleotelson with 7 obsure middorsal teeth (4 distinct middorsal teeth in 
<taxonomicName id="A25229513F87545BC46ECBB3A77639F2" genus="E." lsidName="E. besar" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" rank="species" species="besar">E. besar</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>