<document id="8F460EE4CEE64602EABB68A3558AD9F3" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047625" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F30ABCD6-76FB-49CF-A574-E84DBD3ED93F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="2AD178F1D655B67A1289AD431322ED1D" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio conjuncti Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="F30ABCD6-76FB-49CF-A574-E84DBD3ED93F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="55" lastPageNumber="56" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="52" pageNumber="53" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="B3FE8F755CD5E8DA490C52F3E47AFC97" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="0AF8775BB0E46C6CDE2D864438E06993">
<mods:title id="AFA6ED6899276E604A379B938E618F92">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="C36426D66B0E6217E6310FB2FFDDC539" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B5CDAF096CE87A7B52D3F08AF9A341E7">
<mods:roleTerm id="F3555BF6E7C10CE2BA9336DE9B221864">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2B4D7331F32C34D8EAF2505D13E0674A">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="9A0C39A1557067B5E5A67BB789F3D2A2" type="personal">
<mods:role id="E9D4EDBBDE0B234E23C4AB2389A5F706">
<mods:roleTerm id="D3F4683D5E31EE60E3E9CC2680B9E78B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="4B54495BAC12CECD29A5D655539C7CCA">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="3C3FC88799E4C00FACD88BA17CCB1EB4" type="personal">
<mods:role id="DBF8BEB55A560BEEFEB44D4C4DD2676E">
<mods:roleTerm id="457D7F78228B8A55D39D51FE0BDD18D4">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5407F77FA82E0B7D48FEF3531025BE72">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="9DFD1EDF110CCAEF38DA8C2ED96F838E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="77A5C707C67A1B3C7DAC1DA44680383B">
<mods:roleTerm id="93608E244864119A8CE9DE753DC9E292">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7899A7188957E30F8A5DE8AA0B24260A">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="1D0409DCA0A74E1FC6C573ED30174EC2">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="FF5A070FCD0A6C2B324B8788A7B8B233" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="83DFC7376A053B7C40686B75544C3E77">
<mods:title id="F6FF76B6DFFAEAD4FA3800A5BDD98208">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D323F1BF07FFFF8AA214CE07C3A6A192">
<mods:date id="F505A734D970D4D784B77D9B9385E994">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="B1FBB68B160D2EEEE91FCFDE50FD1047" type="volume">
<mods:number id="30D2C7F1908EF2C1621743D13C1624B3">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="5CCB7561F588E9933CD291371867A826" unit="page">
<mods:start id="0D52E8350A10A12E675298823A046F73">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="B690E465678B7B95C44FA4201EFAA555">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="A224A70C71AD7CF77EF075E025683ECB">
<mods:url id="EC9253ED2CA07D0141357811A80221E1">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="9F7119331D92CE23E412BE749B9B0F60">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DD63E4329706853A5C641C782612A063" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="9FBABA891D7BACE3F91DC598287A7DFA" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="F654D5B75468936545F4A99895FBC87A" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="2AD178F1D655B67A1289AD431322ED1D" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047625" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F30ABCD6-76FB-49CF-A574-E84DBD3ED93F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2AD178F1D655B67A1289AD431322ED1D" lastPageId="55" lastPageNumber="56" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">
<subSubSection id="37CB92941746D45EDCB50DA0979C52C8" pageId="52" pageNumber="53" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="10E18BCC9FC43372903661705BC9293D" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">
<taxonomicName id="F1A5AE4C43293EAC2BA55B27D77F9B6E" LSID="http://zoobank.org/F30ABCD6-76FB-49CF-A574-E84DBD3ED93F" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio conjuncti" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="52" pageNumber="53" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="conjuncti">Oxyscelio conjuncti Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="B31C6ACE335360628B4F37941A0599CB" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 57-62; Morphbank38
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="00AA7A12E3E5685AC34FAC8D44E9CF1B" lastPageId="54" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="52" pageNumber="53" type="description">
<paragraph id="843FD561F0C6DBF77398B8868DBC15D2" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7478D028243ACBD6ABC4BBB87B5350C8" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">Female. Body length 3.35-4.85 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AE6CA5F4251AD2AADAE9DBE879688C2D" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: longer than broad; as long as broad. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="59006FDB609782A1D2234C9D9B3AE05C" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: granulate. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="33E18EC126EC40E4B54A52A87B9BF13E" lastPageId="54" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculp 
<pageBreakToken id="E739676AA00D3C2BCEE380057F71574C" pageId="53" pageNumber="54" start="start">ture</pageBreakToken>
. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent; granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, 
<pageBreakToken id="E91C8D637D3E6B617C40E510FFB07F1E" pageId="54" pageNumber="55" start="start">smooth</pageBreakToken>
ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T5. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD9FB9C18CA8C15BA6DA34051FC4CC89" pageId="54" pageNumber="55">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="16A92AAF93E002AD7FD613E355710E60" pageId="54" pageNumber="55">Male. Body length 3.55-4.05 mm (n=6).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D87B48D5165AEA8472CA1F96E7268FB6" pageId="54" pageNumber="55">A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T5. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: broadly and deeply emarginate, with rounded posterolateral margins.</paragraph>
<caption id="C7E6AF8FECDC8BA084A74E7AE5C553C5" pageId="54" pageNumber="55">
<paragraph id="8737F4FCD2DF1A5E93E9C33366DC4961" pageId="54" pageNumber="55">
Figures 57-62. 
<taxonomicName id="46D5CEDC4EE08CD42EE93DD8045882FB" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio conjuncti" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="54" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="conjuncti">Oxyscelio conjuncti</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype female (OSUC 429810) 57 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 58 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 59 Head, anterior view 60 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 429872) 61 Antenna 62 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank38
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0E9B71479AADBE04F56EAE71E6A3C042" lastPageId="55" lastPageNumber="56" pageId="54" pageNumber="55" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="44DC443670A20121BA72A4C9DE43D651" pageId="54" pageNumber="55">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="48224CDEE2DB51EADB169A9851DEC373" lastPageId="55" lastPageNumber="56" pageId="54" pageNumber="55">
Both sexes: Frontal depression deep and broad but nearly parallel-sided, many interrupted transverse carinae present, including some above dorsal separator; submedian carina weakly indicated or absent medially. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by weak rugae. Occipital carina complete, sinuate medially. Metascutellum deeply concave, weakly emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein absent. Coxa darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 much longer than pedicel. A4 about as long as broad. Mesoscutellum without granulate sculpture. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. T6 without metasomal flanges, main body of tergum raised but not always clearly separated from apical rim. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T4 or middle of T5. Male: A4 as broad or broader than long, A11 longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 
<pageBreakToken id="309AE7E1A1548F177FCC54F905BC7B78" pageId="55" pageNumber="56" start="start">4</pageBreakToken>
longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T5. T7 medially emarginate, with rounded lobes laterally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0E3DB157540B6BDABCB4DA3E01BCB9A6" pageId="55" pageNumber="56">
Etymology. Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="2F1D04CD5B3231E035820BDBE53F623B" originalValue="“connection.”">&quot;connection.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="38A7B79EEE060578C633B90F1AB96536" pageId="55" pageNumber="56" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="85A156121E5749EDAEB59DE3E4665566" pageId="55" pageNumber="56">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7B64548344139CB162A973C9109F8225" pageId="55" pageNumber="56">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307069]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D38E28938A376684D7AF8D878127EE4B" pageId="55" pageNumber="56" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="E3C575D8108A7D56A3FA941090E8D86B" pageId="55" pageNumber="56">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C11B29DD466C914372E837475996FF36" pageId="55" pageNumber="56">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, 5729 
<normalizedToken id="EA79BE36DE1B78C0246EA06C5843F709" originalValue="‘amphitheatre’">'amphitheatre'</normalizedToken>
yards, open forest, Expedition National Park, 
<geoCoordinate id="BB8F2B15ECEF245B283B2B6CAB6A96E1" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-25.216667">25°13'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="93608B45B0AE1F4162C73FEF15FE5D1F" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="149.01666">149°01'E</geoCoordinate>
, 440m, 19.XII-4.III.1998, interception trap, Cook &amp; Monteith, OSUC 429869 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 71 females, 6 males, ANIC DB 32-020081, 32-020083, 32-020084, 32-020085, OSUC 429809, OSUC 429810, OSUC 429812, OSUC 429813, OSUC 429814, OSUC 429815, OSUC 429816, OSUC 429818, OSUC 429819, OSUC 429820, OSUC 429821, OSUC 429822, OSUC 429823, OSUC 429824, OSUC 429825, OSUC 429826, OSUC 429827, OSUC 429828, OSUC 429829, OSUC 429830, OSUC 429831, OSUC 429832, OSUC 429833, OSUC 429834, OSUC 429835, OSUC 429836, OSUC 429837, OSUC 429838, OSUC 429839, OSUC 429840, OSUC 429841, OSUC 429842, OSUC 429843, OSUC 429844, OSUC 429845, OSUC 429846, OSUC 429847, OSUC 429848, OSUC 429849, OSUC 429850, OSUC 429855, OSUC 429856, OSUC 429857, OSUC 429858, OSUC 429859, OSUC 429860, OSUC 429861, OSUC 429862, OSUC 429863, OSUC 429864, OSUC 429865, OSUC 429866, OSUC 429867, OSUC 429870, OSUC 429871, OSUC 429872, OSUC 429873, OSUC 429874, OSUC 429875, OSUC 448633 (ANIC); OSUC 451354 (BMNH); OSUC 462753 (CNCI); OSUC 429851-429854, 429868, 449023-449025, 456183-456185 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>