<document id="C729707F803E2F8A2D132208AD8D49F7" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5321858" ID-ISSN="1175­5334" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5321858" _generate="added" approvalRequired="48" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="4" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="36" approvalRequired_for_treatments="8" checkinTime="1629674756648" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Oláh, János &amp; Johanson, Kjell Arne" docDate="2010" docId="2B7E87E4FF84FFBCF5A6FF6AFC28FBA3" docLanguage="en" docName="zt02457p128.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2457 (1)" docSource="https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.2457.1.1" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1.1:Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleId="D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Anisocentropus (Anisocentropus) vitiensis Oláh &amp; Johanson 2010, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" masterDocId="D747FF9CFFADFF97F531FFFDFFD9FFE9" masterDocTitle="Description of 33 new species of Calamoceratidae, Molannidae, Odontoceridae and Philorheithridae (Trichoptera), with detailed presentation of their cephalic setal warts and grooves 2457" masterLastPageNumber="128" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" updateTime="1630239817089" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="6D6AEE0576976585419DD77D555E6E35" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="98EF06A4DC101DDC8FD16664DDE6CF48">
<mods:title id="5017ADAB2D30FF37DE907638253AE63C">Description of 33 new species of Calamoceratidae, Molannidae, Odontoceridae and Philorheithridae (Trichoptera), with detailed presentation of their cephalic setal warts and grooves 2457</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="CECE76B65971D9C3346651465F69E086" type="personal">
<mods:role id="7F34BD66ED745D67ADF64B9FB6E60669">
<mods:roleTerm id="884B929D1F8B4769CEFD758A70AC49F3">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="45BB98515E7BAF1CA18746B2FA524937">Oláh, János</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="989CC6DBB4E28171B3F7FBCB0147EA1B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="CCDF19218E5574E86C023FDAC6DD8F3F">
<mods:roleTerm id="1F9FF3581D812C9D5863F706B24A2609">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2CD028BE9E9B66FBF6403BACD540AA88">Johanson, Kjell Arne</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="44E17C9925A360816B6D460894920616">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="00103B283C84DA7622EECDD3641239CB" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="4A024A4EC96235C0FDF04E84955558A9">
<mods:title id="0972AA2FE064707716FC0928DE99038C">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="FA2F4B913448BFE8E79EEF0E7F1B0BAA">
<mods:date id="ABCEEC358B73B87AFFE340900665B929">2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="24B7B52C66E1F1DC6D9BC75BA8282A48" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="8C5E64B788B521974F6D734212E7B573">2010-05-14</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="94F554D85839A4F223E88FEED8CB2632" type="volume">
<mods:number id="59CD325261035CA4DC7D4CE12E2AD3C6">2457</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="693F7BAB3C58C80D471036E83B10BBDB" type="issue">
<mods:number id="F7DF91EB0154073CAD1CF05D7000D580">1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="8C1A9C003AA17607A6C80F90F976ED77" unit="page">
<mods:start id="2BDF0E7ECC87480AC11D07098A0B96C2">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="1290FCE4C0386B641E2320CB27B74C6B">128</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="63A902E52075B4E5A832D223327EE800">
<mods:url id="22AE2D3437502195183C78A1126D3369">https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.2457.1.1</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="975F98806CEFA11FAA9B1B6DA1191C4E">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="2538FC17CE719150E5CC11D80DCDD287" type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.2457.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="80CE53C4FB6DBC9E99CD6B15625F0714" type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="96851EE19FB74A0327D4A65306F0FD3D" type="Zenodo-Dep">5313709</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="2B7E87E4FF84FFBCF5A6FF6AFC28FBA3" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5321858" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5321858" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2B7E87E4FF84FFBCF5A6FF6AFC28FBA3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2B7E87E4FF84FFBCF5A6FF6AFC28FBA3" lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<subSubSection id="EBCD6579FF84FFBEF5A6FF6AFCEAFF58" box="[151,819,151,177]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF84FFBEF5A6FF6AFCEAFF58" blockId="41.[151,819,151,212]" box="[151,819,151,177]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<heading id="F820819EFF84FFBEF5A6FF6AFCEAFF58" bold="true" box="[151,819,151,177]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" reason="1">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF5A6FF6AFCEAFF58" bold="true" box="[151,819,151,177]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<taxonomicName id="64D74D71FF84FFBEF5A6FF6AFD4FFF58" authority="Oláh &amp; Johanson, 2010" authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[151,662,151,177]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitiensis" status="new species" subGenus="Anisocentropus">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF5A6FF6AFE8DFF58" bold="true" box="[151,340,151,177]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Anisocentropus</emphasis>
(
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF454FF6AFDFBFF58" bold="true" box="[357,546,151,177]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Anisocentropus</emphasis>
) 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF702FF6AFD4FFF58" bold="true" box="[563,662,151,177]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">vitiensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF7A7FF6AFD45FF58" bold="true" box="[662,668,151,177]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">,</emphasis>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="8A90579BFF84FFBEF792FF6AFCEAFF58" box="[675,819,151,177]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="EBCD6579FF84FFBCF5A6FF47FD04FC43" lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" type="description">
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF84FFBEF5A6FF47FEC3FF3D" blockId="41.[151,819,151,212]" box="[151,282,186,212]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<figureCitation id="3BEC2A77FF84FFBEF5A6FF47FEC3FF3D" box="[151,282,186,212]" captionStart="FIGURES 83–88" captionStartId="41.[151,269,1822,1846]" captionTargetBox="[173,1410,557,1783]" captionTargetId="figure-195@41.[167,1419,551,1795]" captionTargetPageId="41" captionText="FIGURES 83–88. Anisocentropus vitiensis, new species, holotype. 83 — right forewing; 84 — genitalia, lateral; 85 — genitalia, dorsal; 86 — genitalia, ventral; 87 — phallus, lateral; 88 — phallus, ventral." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5313759" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5313759/files/figure.png" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Figs 83–88</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF84FFBEF5A6FEF7FDC4FE05" blockId="41.[151,1436,266,492]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
This species is medium-sized, bright chestnut brown, with wide transverse band on each of the forewings. It belongs to diagnostic species-group having short gonocoxites. It is most similar to 
<taxonomicName id="64D74D71FF84FFBEF155FECFFA4CFEA2" authority="Oláh &amp; Johanson, 2010" authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[1124,1429,306,331]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vanuensis" status="new species">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF155FECFFA4CFEA2" box="[1124,1429,306,331]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Anisocentropus vanuensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="8A90579BFF84FFBEF5A6FEA7FEFDFE9D" box="[151,292,346,372]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
described above. 
<taxonomicName id="64D74D71FF84FFBEF4C6FEA7FCCAFE9A" authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[503,787,346,371]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitiensis">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF4C6FEA7FCCAFE9A" box="[503,787,346,371]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Anisocentropus vitiensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is separated from 
<taxonomicName id="64D74D71FF84FFBEF6DDFEA7FB59FE9A" authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[1004,1152,346,371]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vanuensis">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF6DDFEA7FB59FE9A" box="[1004,1152,346,371]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">A. vanuensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by having a broad, dark brown, transverse band on both forewings; and in the genitalia by its gonocoxites being clearly triangular, not sigmoid in ventral view. The cephalic, cervical, thoracic and proepisternal structural units, grooves, and setal warts are similar in the 2 species.
</paragraph>
<caption id="F7A8667AFF84FFBEF5A6F8E3FBE9F8B1" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5313759" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5313759" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5313759/files/figure.png" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" startId="41.[151,269,1822,1846]" targetBox="[173,1410,557,1783]" targetPageId="41">
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF84FFBEF5A6F8E3FBE9F8B1" blockId="41.[151,1436,1822,1880]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF5A6F8E3FE87F8DF" bold="true" box="[151,350,1822,1846]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">FIGURES 83–88.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="64D74D71FF84FFBEF454F8E2FDB0F8DF" authority="Oláh &amp; Johanson, 2010" authorityName="Oláh &amp; Johanson" authorityYear="2010" box="[357,617,1823,1846]" class="Insecta" family="Calamoceratidae" genus="Anisocentropus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Trichoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitiensis" status="new species">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF84FFBEF454F8E2FDB0F8DF" box="[357,617,1823,1846]" italics="true" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">Anisocentropus vitiensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="8A90579BFF84FFBEF746F8E2FD22F8DF" box="[631,763,1823,1846]" pageId="41" pageNumber="42" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
, holotype. 83 — right forewing; 84 — genitalia, lateral; 85 — genitalia, dorsal; 86 — genitalia, ventral; 87 — phallus, lateral; 88 — phallus, ventral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF84FFBDF5F6F87AFCC2F80B" blockId="41.[151,1436,1927,2033]" lastBlockId="42.[151,1437,152,2018]" lastPageId="42" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="41" pageNumber="42">
Male (in alcohol). Medium-sized, eyes small, body brown, legs, antennae and palps light brown; membrane of each forewing brown, with broad, dark brown transverse band on central part; with pale patch on each pterostigma. Head rectangular in dorsal view, almost as long as broad. Ocelli absent. Tentorium slender, without dorsal arm; each posterior arms short, robust, ends in pair of large posterior tentorial pit; tentorial bridge strong, without anteromesal or posteromesal protuberances; anterior tentorial arms robust posteriorly, slender anteriorly, without median lamellate processes; broad posterior half ending in median keel in dorsal view and ventral corner in lateral view. Facial groove pattern forming plate-like flange or rim connecting anterior tentorial pits; theoretical lines separating frons and clypeus (frontogenal vertical groove) forming oblique, dorsad continuation from anterior tentorial pits, almost horizontally merging with broad antennal grooves. Clypeogenal vertical grooves located ventrally of anterior tentorial pits, short, running slightly mesoventrad; well-visible pattern of plate-like flanges, frontogenal and clypeogenal sutures, forming complex of anterior tentorial arms (frontogenal septum). Subantennal grooves small, sinuous, running almost horizontally between frontogenal compact setal wart and palpifers, forming proximal articulation of palpi on stipes. Subocular grooves invisible. Frontal groove pronoumced, short, present between antennae, joining vertexal medioantennal compact setose warts. Vertexal groove pattern reduced. Large, anterad directed, rounded elevation dominating anterior half of vertex, reaching interantennal area, delineated laterally by large, membranous antennal sockets, with corrugated or granulous surface near frontogenal compact setose wart. Stem of epicranial groove (coronal groove) vestigial. Antennal and ocular grooves accompanied by occipito-postgenal grooves, partly merging anterad; tangential to large occipital compact setal warts. Labrum long, quadrangular, with rounded apex, freely hanging, sparsely setose. Mandibles long, slightly pigmented, orienting laterad along each labrum; laciniae narrow, elongating, bearing few setae. Frontal setal warts absent on face, frontal interantennal warts absent due to forward directed vertexal elevation. Pair of large, nearly triangular frontogenal compact setal warts present on posterior pregenae, obliquely or almost horizontally from frontogenal grooves, alone representing only warts visible on face. Triangular elevation on vertex with fused vertexal medioantennal compact setose warts located anteriorly on head. Vertexal lateroantennal compact setal warts absent. Antennal sockets large. Pair of small, rounded vertexal ocellar compact setose warts, and pair of very small vertexal medioocellar diffuse setose warts present, each with 1 or 2 setae in middle of vertex; obliquely located pair of large, ovoid occipital compact setose warts dominating on posterior half of vertex; pair of small postgenal compact setose warts visible between posterior section of ocular grooves and occipital compact setose warts. Maxillary palps filiform; maxillary palp formula II-IV-V-VI-III. Scapes rounded, long, about half as long as head; pedicels 2/5ths as long as scapes. Two pairs pronotal warts present: pair of large dorsal transverse ovoid warts forming elevated humps, almost tangential mesally; pair of rounded, small warts located deep laterally, visible in lateral view. Mesoscutum with 1 pair diffused warts, arranged in longitudinal line along entire mesoscutum, composed mostly of single, double and triple setae in groups, visible as weakly pigmented alveoli. Pair of mesoscutellar warts forming small, weakly pigmented, rounded areas with 7 to 9 setal alveoli. Each proepisternum with minute, rounded setose wart located proximally above articulation of each cervical sclerite. Large, compact setal warts present mainly on membranous part of cervix, touching anterior arm of cervical sclerites. Lateral cervical sclerites forming narrow anterior arms articulating anteriorly with back of head, with occipital condyle above posterior tentorial pits; fusing with posterior cervical sclerites. Posterior cervical sclerites forming narrow, elongated plates, reaching prothoracic episternum, articulating with weakly sclerotized anteromedian band of prothoracic eusternum by thin, ventral intercervical sclerites. Legs with symmetrical claws; spur formula 2, 4, 3; foreleg posteroapical spur 2 times longer than anteroapical spur; midleg anterior spurs 1/4th as long as posterior spurs; hind leg anteroapical spur 1/4th as long as posterior spur. Forewings: length 8.8 mm; membrane brown with dark brown transverse band on middle, pale area at pterostigma; narrow, hyaline, horizontal lines present around crossvein 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF87FFBDF191F8FDFB72F8F0" box="[1184,1195,1792,1817]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">s</emphasis>
, on R4+5 fork base, above short apical section of M, and along stem of M1+2; crossvein 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF87FFBDF68EF8D5FC34F8A8" box="[959,1005,1832,1857]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">sc-r</emphasis>
with subcostal-radial crossvein connecting Sc and R hypertrophied at confluence of Sc; R1 free to C; crossvein 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF87FFBDF173F8ADFB94F880" box="[1090,1101,1872,1897]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">r</emphasis>
located at apical margin of radial cell; base of discoidal cell ending at wing middle; forks I, II, III, IV, V present; crossveins 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF87FFBDF030F885FEC1F850" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">h, sc-r, r, s, rm, m, m-cu</emphasis>
and 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF87FFBDF461F85DFEA2F850" box="[336,379,1952,1977]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">cu2</emphasis>
present; crossveins 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF87FFBDF757F85DFD49F850" box="[614,656,1952,1977]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">cu1</emphasis>
and 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF87FFBDF7F9F85DFD25F850" box="[712,764,1952,1977]" italics="true" pageId="42" pageNumber="43">cu-a</emphasis>
absent; postanal vein absent. Hind wings: R1 fusing with R2; forks I, II, III, V present; fork I longer than fork II.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF86FFBCF5F6FF65FD04FC43" blockId="43.[151,1437,152,1098]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Male genitalia. Abdominal segment IX fused annularly, without longitudinal grooves separating dorsal and ventral parts; tergum longer than venter; dorsum and venter narrowly protruding into quadrangular in lateral view; anterior margin of segment IX convex triangular, directed ventrad; posterior margin straight vertical at ventral half; with well developed, long additional lateral flank below preanal appendages and above gonocoxites. Antecosta forming weak, narrow, marginal rim being equally thin along margin, without conspicuous external groove of antecostal suture. Tergum IX with small triangular mesal elevation in dorsal view; spine row absent on posterior margins of segment IX; entire segment smoothly glabrous, covered only by acanthae, except smaller dorsopleural and larger ventropleural setal areas. Intersegmental depression between segment IX and segment X gently sloping. Segment X longer than gonocoxites, slightly longer than preanal appendage, forming broad hood with ventrad directed apical rim characterised by sinuous excavations visible in lateral and ventral view; excavations forming tooth-like pattern on ventrad curving margin, with 2 blunt teeth. Apicoventral setose lobes reduced to setose, subapical surfaces or shallow protuberances. Apicodorsal setose lobes with few tiny setae above middle of segment X. Dorsal interlobular gap forming narrow, deep cleft. Preanal appendages depressed in lateral view, broad at mid-length, slightly narrowing apically. Gonocoxites without harpago; short, triangular in lateral view, with visible subapical sinus; triangular in ventral view, with long, stout spines on mesal surfaces. Phallic apparatus curving, basal margins convex, ventral margin concave with elongated, sclerotized ventral apical part forming slightly tapering lobe; part of phallicata visible in retracted state above ventral lobe. Phallotremal sclerite looks forming rounded, complex unit in membranous phallicata in lateral view; in ventral view, phallotremal sclerite complex V-shaped. Ejaculatory duct thin, reaching phallotremal sclerite complex.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="EBCD6579FF86FFBCF5F6FC4AFEE0FC13" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF86FFBCF5F6FC4AFEE0FC13" blockId="43.[151,1437,152,1098]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
<materialsCitation id="13BF3CAFFF86FFBCF5F6FC4AFEE0FC13" collectingDate="1974-09-03" collectingDateMax="1974-09-05" collectingDateMin="1974-09-03" collectionCode="NHML" collectorName="G. S. Robinson" country="Fiji" location="Levu" municipality="Nandarivatu" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" specimenCount="1" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF86FFBCF5F6FC4AFEA6FC38" bold="true" box="[199,383,951,977]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
<typeStatus id="7C6C8850FF86FFBCF5F6FC4AFEE0FC38" box="[199,313,951,977]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Holotype</typeStatus>
male
</emphasis>
: 
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF86FFBCF4A0FC4AFD3CFC38" bold="true" box="[401,741,951,977]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
<collectingCountry id="DBC07662FF86FFBCF4A0FC4AFD8CFC38" box="[401,597,951,977]" name="Fiji" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">FIJI ISLANDS</collectingCountry>
: Viti 
<location id="A6086029FF86FFBCF7ADFC4AFD39FC38" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2B7E87E4FF84FFBCF5A6FF6AFC28FBA3:A6086029FF86FFBCF7ADFC4AFD39FC38" box="[668,736,951,977]" country="Fiji" municipality="Nandarivatu" name="Levu" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Levu</location>
:
</emphasis>
<collectingMunicipality id="430CAC88FF86FFBCF7DEFC45FC5AFC3B" box="[751,899,952,978]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Nandarivatu</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<date id="D7691032FF86FFBCF6A0FC45FBC4FC3B" box="[913,1053,952,978]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" value="1974-09-03" valueMax="1974-09-05" valueMin="1974-09-03">
<collectingDate id="C72DE9DAFF86FFBCF6A0FC45FBC4FC3B" box="[913,1053,952,978]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" value="1974-09-03" valueMax="1974-09-05" valueMin="1974-09-03">3–5.ix.1974</collectingDate>
</date>
[
<collectorName id="0E225324FF86FFBCF11EFC45FB07FC3B" box="[1071,1246,952,978]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">G.S. Robinson</collectorName>
] – (B.M. 1974- 462, 
<collectionCode id="C5C6AE37FF86FFBCF5E0FC1DFEF4FC13" box="[209,301,992,1018]" country="Libya" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/49nc-28y0" name="Natural History Museum, Tripoli" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">NHML</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="EBCD6579FF86FFBCF5F6FBFAFE25FBCB" box="[199,508,1031,1058]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF86FFBCF5F6FBFAFE25FBCB" blockId="43.[151,1437,152,1098]" box="[199,508,1031,1058]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF86FFBCF5F6FBFAFEB0FBC8" bold="true" box="[199,361,1031,1057]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Distribution:</emphasis>
<collectingCountry id="DBC07662FF86FFBCF440FBF5FE21FBCB" box="[369,504,1032,1058]" name="Fiji" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Fiji Islands</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="EBCD6579FF86FFBCF5F6FBD2FC28FBA3" box="[199,1009,1071,1098]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="A36836F2FF86FFBCF5F6FBD2FC28FBA3" blockId="43.[151,1437,152,1098]" box="[199,1009,1071,1098]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">
<emphasis id="91A3EAE0FF86FFBCF5F6FBD2FE8EFBA0" bold="true" box="[199,343,1071,1097]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Etymology:</emphasis>
vitiensis, named after the 
<typeStatus id="7C6C8850FF86FFBCF7BCFBCDFD66FBA3" box="[653,703,1072,1098]" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">type</typeStatus>
locality, 
<collectingCountry id="DBC07662FF86FFBCF61AFBCDFC8EFBA3" box="[811,855,1072,1098]" name="Fiji" pageId="43" pageNumber="44">Viti</collectingCountry>
Levu Island.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>