<document id="507E9DA0A0076743089DECBAA7234C88" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282588" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4d306393-ac5c-43b1-ab3a-19d9894998f0" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127266" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282588" ModsDocID="6438" checkinTime="1243377138618" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="1981" docId="2CA0F0C71FAA2B74DBFE1813C3A892EB" docLanguage="en" docName="6438" docOrigin="Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology 43" docSource="http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6438" docTitle="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi Andre" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="252" masterDocId="BC898CD1404B6DE3B19A96923068ACC3" masterDocTitle="A revision of six minor genera of Myrmicinae (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in the Ethiopian zoogeographical region." masterLastPageNumber="307" masterPageNumber="245" pageNumber="251" updateTime="1645805167815" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="03DB72B57270B3C99F831E9ECC046585" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="DD4FB4F47C98E4E0315EEBA32404D0AC">
<mods:title id="65FF0750B4A9C34D5A7EAA2345B18EEE">A revision of six minor genera of Myrmicinae (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in the Ethiopian zoogeographical region.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="9E16A57B3AD53DB45C2418CBE426D060" type="personal">
<mods:role id="0B9C540441C700CC9D5B1D3C0E112974">
<mods:roleTerm id="2C86FA0D72D66E498CEC611693B8D1F2">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5C10A78613A7375911FBFB409C9E102B">Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="62D0C2D6C68DDBEBE2A207FAC6C04ACA">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="46669AEC7E0BA656D189BFA99C237612" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="5F361FA49806BF170B22D9A0A01DF416">
<mods:title id="00192D074DEB7A48D5031A6748E44EF3">Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="FA6612511D8DA621519D5F4FE3BADA8C">
<mods:date id="EF88DEDB9824ADB3DC28BFA97F15997D">1981</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="4403E68807D3D20850C0B502895C8189" type="volume">
<mods:number id="EA197A91AADA7E4EFDB099D8AA6873BB">43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="A52D8773C09E8EF023BDB3D1734B5B11" unit="page">
<mods:start id="079BBDC782C44FBB9BC04E61753B1E92">245</mods:start>
<mods:end id="6E6E273F243C5BC790F83EC5D52F7252">307</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="608E27C9D124B2654FC3093539C07130">
<mods:url id="5B6A481CB534FB2F71B7B7150EABCB0E">http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6438</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="576CDEDD7171FC0098723AC8116606B3">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="D8BA94392F8770A2A161B3459802FF6D" type="HNS-PUB">6438</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="2CA0F0C71FAA2B74DBFE1813C3A892EB" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282588" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127266" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282588" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2CA0F0C71FAA2B74DBFE1813C3A892EB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2CA0F0C71FAA2B74DBFE1813C3A892EB" lastPageNumber="252" pageNumber="251">
<subSubSection id="934D37E83C2F3D712C9F03760B9D12EE" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="18C86E9FF9F984E887F74FF099E16A18" pageNumber="251">
<taxonomicName id="127C208F5DB59D2ADCF72E20CE89F3CF" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:25933" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi André" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mocquerysi">Atopomyrmex mocquerysi Andre</taxonomicName>
(Figs 3 - 8,10)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3587AC3AA1FF20B87DD227B9AF8B488B" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="669DD84672B9D5693940C7C440CB93B4" pageNumber="251">
<taxonomicName id="7EFE4CF413C8AD22DD826E1ABAFB52BA" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:232200" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquersyi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mocquersyi">Atopomyrmex mocquersyi Andre</taxonomicName>
, 1889: 227. Syntype workers, Senegal: Dakar (A. Mocquerys) (MNHN,
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="066C83660FE3C225CC49D4CFE2A1965D" pageNumber="251">
Paris) [examined]. 
<taxonomicName id="F15A2C00AC0062760C5AC563A38260A6" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:134280" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. australis Santschi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="mocquerysi" variety="australis">Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. australis Santschi</taxonomicName>
, 1914 a: 16. Syntype workers, South Africa: Natal, Zulu-land (/. Traegardh) (NM, Basle) [examined]. [Synonymy by Wheeler, 1922: 885.] 
<taxonomicName id="65D69BA382105405BECD6139EC2A57B8" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:134282" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. obscura Santschi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="mocquerysi" variety="obscura">Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. obscura Santschi</taxonomicName>
, 1923: 283. Syntype workers, Ivory Coast: Jacqueville (Lohier); and Benin: Cotonou (Silvestri) (MRAC, Tervuren; NM, Basle) [examined]. Syn. n. 
<taxonomicName id="87A29BCB38CB3A6F2C9A3D7C0C463173" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:134279" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. arnoldi Santschi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="mocquerysi" variety="arnoldi">Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. arnoldi Santschi</taxonomicName>
, 1923: 283. Syntype workers, Zaire: Eala (R. Mayne) (NM, Basle; MRAC, Tervuren) [examined]. Syn. n. 
<taxonomicName id="C374C87808E022B893CB8149A8EA8190" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:134283" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi st. opaca Santschi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="mocquerysi" subSpecies="opaca">Atopomyrmex mocquerysi st. opaca Santschi</taxonomicName>
, 1923: 283. Syntype workers, Angola: ' Riviere Cubia, entre Combo et Cubra' (Rohan-Chabot) (MRAC, Tervuren; NM, Basle) [examined]. Syn. n. 
<taxonomicName id="AA5A74D8308EBE12E5511F1687B69347" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:134281" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. erigens Santschi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="mocquerysi" variety="erigens">Atopomyrmex mocquerysi var. erigens Santschi</taxonomicName>
, 1924: 205. Syntype workers, Zaire: Yambata (Di Giorgi) (NM, Basle; MRAC, Tervuren) [examined]. Syn. n. 
<taxonomicName id="AE464FB5B69814A5E482826AB1E4377D" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:224546" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex mocquerysi st. opacus var. nigellus Santschi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="mocquerysi" subSpecies="opacus" variety="nigellus">Atopomyrmex mocquerysi st. opacus var. nigellus Santschi</taxonomicName>
, 1930: 72. Syntype workers, Angola: Rio Mbale and Chimporo (A. Monard) (NM, Basle) [examined]. [Name not available.]
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9B3B8342DA287C0826DB539BA089B135" type="description">
<paragraph id="94793713E900C7A44577ECFCE0C723DC" pageNumber="251">Worker. Standard measurements are obviously not of great value where continuously polymorphic species are involved, as one size grades into another without any break. However, when graphs of the relationships of various dimensions are plotted a number of allometric relationships become apparent. Most easily noticeable of these are the following. The CI increases with increase in HW; the relative lengths of the scapes (SI) decrease as HW increases; the frontal carinae increase in length and strength as HW increases. The size of the eye has little or no dependence on the size of the head, the eyes of the largest workers being relatively only slightly increased in size over those of the smallest (as expressed by the ratio of ocular diameter to HW). Overall size range in the species is TL 4.0 - 8.7, HL 0.96 - 2.24, HW 0.88 - 2.30, CI 92 - 104, SL 0.70 - 1.22, SI 49 - 80, PW 0.68 - 1.40, AL 1.34 - 2.50 (85 measured).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="960A96A1720A8C75EAB1ACD5399FFF33" lastPageNumber="252" pageNumber="251">
Basic characters as given under generic diagnosis, differentiation from 
<taxonomicName id="DB2996C5DB4B3AAAD474D7277C07E5BB" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:25932" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Atopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Atopomyrmex cryptoceroides Emery" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="251" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cryptoceroides">cryptoceroides</taxonomicName>
as tabulated above. Mandibles pitted, the surface between the pits finely and densely shagreened to finely striate. Frontal carinae increasing in length and strength with increasing worker size (Figs 5 - 7). In smallest workers short, ending in front of the level of the anterior margins of the eyes, forming a short and narrow laterally projecting flange on each side and only very slightly divergent. In larger workers the frontal carinae lengthening and becoming more obviously divergent, the laterally projecting flange broadening. In largest workers the carinae reaching back beyond the level of the eyes, divergent to eye level then becoming almost parallel, the laterally projecting flange very prominent throughout most or all of the length of the carinae. Antennal scrobes absent in small workers, becoming better defined with increased size; in large workers the scrobe conspicuous, narrow but quite deep and capable of accommodating the scape. Change in head shape with increased size as in Figs 5 - 7. Maximum diameter of eye 0.18 - 0.36, about 0.14 - 0.20 x HW, the relative size of the eyes not radically increased in larger workers. Outline shape of alitrunk as in Figs 3, 4. Propodeal spines very variable in length, thickness and degree of curvature. In dorsal view the spines not projecting outwards in their basal portions, the propodeal spiracle or at least its annulus visible from above. In profile the propodeal spiracle some distance away from the margin of the declivity below the spine, the diameter of the spiracle less than the distance separating it from the margin of the declivity. Petiolar teeth conspicuous, varying in length and thickness. Sculpture in general increasing in intensity and frequently also in density from smaller to larger workers. Dorsum of head with scattered shallow pits, the surface between them varying from smooth or almost smooth to densely reticulate-punctate. This ground-sculpture is overlaid between the frontal carinae by fine dense longitudinal striation. As the frontal carinae increase in length so the area of striate sculpture becomes stronger and extends further back on the head. In larger specimens the space between the frontal carinae becomes strongly rugose or costate and this sculpture may reach back almost to the occipital margin. Sides of head densely reticulate-punctate everywhere. With increasing size there is a tendency for the progressive encroachment of rugulose sculpture across the reticulate-punctate surface from the front to the back of the sides. Small workers have only the punctate sculpture but as size increases rugulae appear anteriorly which gradually strengthen and spread further back on the head. Pronotal dorsum longitudinally rugose at least centrally, the rugae varying in intensity and sometimes divergent posteriorly. Ground-sculpture reticulate-punctate and usually distinct, sometimes faint and frequently with larger superimposed punctures present. Pronotal sculpture continuing onto mesonotum in smaller workers, but in larger individuals (and also in some smaller ones) the sculpture becomes reduced on the mesonotum so that only the punctate ground-sculpture is present or rugae occur but are restricted to the anterior part of the sclerite. In large workers there is usually a striking reduction in mesonotal sculpture so that most or all of the dorsum is feebly punctulate or even smooth and shining. Propodeal dorsum densely reticulate-punctate, usually without trace of rugulose sculpture but sometimes with one or two weak rugulae present. Petiole, postpetiole and first gastral tergite finely and very densely reticulate-punctate to densely shagreened. Dorsal surfaces of body without standing hairs of any description. Colour very variable, ranging from dull yellowish brown to blackish brown but most commonly bicoloured, with head and alitrunk reddish, gaster dark brown to black. In some the head alone reddish and the rest of the body darker, in others the head and gaster dark and the alitrunk lighter.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="732B192F579EADA9B925B69A57F8825E" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="89D5579325EA2C4579A14AF1E0B906C2" pageNumber="252">Material examined</paragraph>
<paragraph id="64263FB070EA1F34DA17281E6C1927CB" pageNumber="252">Ghana: Tafo (B. Bolton); Mampong (P. Room); Bunso (D. Leston); Wiawso (D. Leston); Legon (D. Leston); Mepom (D. Leston); Okumaning (D. Leston). Nigeria: Gambari (B. Bolton); Mokwa (C. Longhurst). Cameroun: Nkoemvon (D. Jackson). Zaire: Yangambi (TV. L. H. Krauss); Lukolela to Basoko (H. O. Lang). Sudan: Keilak (R. C. H. Sweeny). Kenya: Kibwesi (S. A. Neave). Uganda: Masindi (R. Lucius). Tanzania: Kilossa (S. A. Neave); Morogoro (A. Loveridge); Zanzibar (W. M. Aders); Zanzibar (L. F. Brown); Duthumi (A. Loveridge); Kigoma Reg., Mahale Mts. (S. Uehara). Zambia: N'Changa (C. T. Macnamara); Mwengwa (Dollman). Malawi: Port Herald (J. E. S. Old). Zimbabwe: Umgusa Riv., Sipopoma (G. Arnold); Victoria Falls (G. Arnold).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>