<document id="B2D0892BB8DE628C3607ACB4BC2506DE" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302" ID-GBIF-Dataset="758f5696-6157-4383-8c42-21466df0f3bb" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030279" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-117-29" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-117-29" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 117" ModsDocTitle="Five new species of the genus Cryptopimpla Taschenberg (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) with a key to species known from China" checkinTime="1451250191811" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Sheng, Mao-Ling" docDate="2011" docId="2CCE8DFDB81B8137B435953A012FBC70" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 117: 29-49" docOrigin="ZooKeys 117" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302" docTitle="Cryptopimpla carinifacialis Sheng, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="35" masterDocId="B014FF916931FFFEFF8AEA382515FFBC" masterDocTitle="Five new species of the genus Cryptopimpla Taschenberg (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) with a key to species known from China" masterLastPageNumber="49" masterPageNumber="29" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" updateTime="1643551466442" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="D4ECD39462C9BF47F25A9CFE4D874E91" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="C40B960A338C3492F78A591088392914">
<mods:title id="C8D8AFFCA9C5B9E9AE23537CB73F9EF9">Five new species of the genus Cryptopimpla Taschenberg (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) with a key to species known from China</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="13CE2E71A897E56902FD5907FBDDBD36" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D8B0D3A84422367163D432C4A7DD3EF2">
<mods:roleTerm id="B4865710A51BE6E6558A3643F16AC858">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="890676120DD3778A230BCDC7EB3E7092">Sheng, Mao-Ling</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="3594149445BF43709E7E90DA3FBBA8AE">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="078B38347B20426AE38ABAC2DB2EC2F0" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="F83FFC145D7D10D752E1DFBDF8FACB95">
<mods:title id="AE80C805FF71461545AFBEAB029560E0">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="DEA0A095326B56C9651B1BF71F1768C5">
<mods:date id="FF74E9D919230B1ED18C0292C5E26197">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3592865AFE07BB970361D53C7932D344" type="volume">
<mods:number id="4C640339CEC5C46E2E5D708B3B4D9490">117</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="D20A6ED3E4C481A6A30F2189BE663A22" unit="page">
<mods:start id="5B6855E1CBAB695165B8143E14F22A97">29</mods:start>
<mods:end id="1D99F477EB3D48BE26832B061B6FE4CE">49</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="03C1A203854E7572D1423D792D1852D7">
<mods:url id="ADA8212CCC33421FDC42C9167FCDACBE">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="CD246EA9DD6A8BCE2D71018AD43A79A9">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="8D77CA9057B1DAEAEB206CCFA41B140C" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8739C79AE4D8D4FF3DE2EDA26FA807B1" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-117-29</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="F2FC1ADB8BAC35907B1B750B8073AAE3" type="ZooBank">BB38479A-4AB2-4A61-A748-B0E716EEAC1C</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="2CCE8DFDB81B8137B435953A012FBC70" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030279" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2CCE8DFDB81B8137B435953A012FBC70" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2CCE8DFDB81B8137B435953A012FBC70" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">
<subSubSection id="25C5271A28B61D254BDD7264DD9B97F8" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="D902938B064AEAEF962845E31B5729A5" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">
<taxonomicName id="7EA0216EA8B1A032103BC40767BF6998" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A953FD9F-994C-4541-8B5F-8E0A4F57037C" authority="Sheng, sp. n." class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cryptopimpla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cryptopimpla carinifacialis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="carinifacialis">
<pageBreakToken id="43182D0AFEAD73D3592DE2BBC1BC4A78" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" start="start">Cryptopimpla</pageBreakToken>
carinifacialis Sheng, sp. n.
</taxonomicName>
Figs 1-5
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B79AC41AB4C36A2068D9A9894B2D1E9B" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="88F330B097CCAD8C3DC8DF90B49F1B08" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FC2B33187BE8A34216B06C359F262AE6" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">The name of the new species is based on the median longitudinal carina of the face.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B1132528CBB6500FCE107027C795B278" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="40DEA572780A82BF86B6D46D7358C9D7" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F011005F15A023020C84EEE910A3D3E7" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Holotype: female, CHINA: Wuyishan Natural Reserve, 1200m, Qianshan County, Jiangxi Province, 11 July 2009, leg. Zhi-Ping Zhong.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FF68535B150A47AA3EB18F6F835AF318" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="40AD171909CD913AC87DC271B3A37901" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D48BFDE735B085C5AD56D6403336ADCD" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Median portion of face strongly convex, with distinct median longitudinal carina. Areolet petiolate. Scutellum and postscutellum with dense punctures. Claws pectinate. Hind wing vein 1/cu approximately 3.8 times as long as cu-a. First tergum approximately 2.5 times as long as apical width, slightly narrowed towards base. Ovipositor almost straight. Face black with latero-median yellowish white spots.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="36495318CD4BEB286D796FDE0E618C7A" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="34" pageId="3" pageNumber="32" type="description">
<paragraph id="FA864885AAB65C94C7FABC681DB350EF" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E5DADF196382986C5F4C0C106D6EF4E5" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Female. Body length about 10.0 mm. Fore wing length about 8.0 mm. Ovipositor sheath length about 2.0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="407C577DF6D2437AC53663AD8F9CF8A4" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">Head. Inner margins of eyes parallel. Face and clypeus with fine leathery texture. Face (Fig. 2) approximately 1.38 times as wide as long, median portion strongly convex longitudinally, with distinct median longitudinal carina; upper-lateral portion longitudinally concave; medially with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.1 to 0.2 times diameter of puncture; laterally with relatively sparse punctures, distance between punctures 0.5 to 1.0 times diameter of puncture. Clypeus approximately 2.2 times as wide as long, almost smooth, strongly convex, basal portion with sparse punctures, apical median portion slightly concave; apical margin thick and convex, with brown hairs. Mandible strong, subapical portion with sparse and shallow punctures. Teeth sharp, upper tooth distinctly longer than lower tooth. Malar space, gena, vertex and frons with fine leathery texture. Malar space approximately 0.55 times as long as basal width of mandible, with indistinct and fine punctures. Gena directly convergent posteriorly, with fine punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 2.0 times diameter of puncture, but gradually more densely punctate towards lower portion. Vertex (Fig. 3) with punctures slightly larger than that of gena, distance between punctures 0.5 to 2.5 times diameter of puncture. Interocellar area weakly convex. Postocellar line approximately as long as ocular-ocellar line. Frons almost flat, sublateral portion with dense and unclear punctures, distance between punctures 0.1 to 0.5 times diameter of puncture, almost contacting each other transversely. Lower-median portion with longitudinal wrinkles. Antenna with 47 flagellomeres, each segment longer than wide. Inner profile of basal half of flagella with a distinctive structure, a strong longitudinal carina (Fig. 3a). Ratio of length from first to fifth flagellomeres: 8.8:6.3:5.7:5.3:5.0. Occipital carina complete, lower end joining hypostomal carina slightly above base of mandible.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BCD57CB88B91E74B342D1DFEDE51491" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="34" pageId="3" pageNumber="32">
Mesosoma. Anterior margin of pronotum almost smooth, with indistinct punctures. Laterally concave with short transverse wrinkles. Upper-posterior portion with even and dense punctures, distance between punctures approximately 0.2 times diameter of puncture. Mesoscutum evenly convex, rough, with punctures denser than 
<pageBreakToken id="FEE03362DFBFEAD5749894C8700FB099" pageId="4" pageNumber="33" start="start">on</pageBreakToken>
upper-posterior portion of pronotum. Without notaulus. Scutellum evenly convex, with punctures as mesoscutum. Postscutellum more convex, with dense and large punctures, larger than on scutellum, latero-anterior portion concave. Mesopleuron (Fig. 4) with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.1 to 0.6 times diameter of puncture. Upper end of epicnemial carina reaching about lower 0.2 level of front margin of mesopleuron, distant from front margin of mesopleuron. Mesopleural fovea 
<pageBreakToken id="6EF201C799A37C12C6525D570C383E61" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" start="start">round</pageBreakToken>
, deep. Without speculum. Metapleuron with denser and finer punctures than mesopleuron. Submetapleural carina complete, triangularly convex anteriorly. Without juxtacoxal carina. Wings brownish hyaline. Vein 1cu-a distal of 1/M, distance between them approximately 0.26 times length of 1cu-a. Areolet quadrate, petiolate, vein 3rs-m distinctly longer than 2rs-m, receiving vein 2m-cu approximately 0.8 distance from vein 2rs-m to 3rs-m. Vein 2-Cu slightly longer than 2cu-a. Hind wing vein 1/cu about 3.8 times as long as cu-a. Legs comparatively long. Ratio of length of hind tarsomeres 10.0:4.3:3.1:1.5:2.3. Claws densely pectinate. Propodeum (Fig. 5) evenly convex, rough, with dense and indistinct punctures. Median point and lateral portion at the place of apophysis of posterior transverse carina and apical section of pleural carina present. Propodeal spiracle elongate, approximately 2 times as long as maximum width.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="88DB71974C4AB216B3463D2515C3D35C" pageId="5" pageNumber="34">Metasoma. First tergum approximately 2.5 times as long as apical width, slightly narrowed towards base, with distinct and dense punctures. Without median dorsal carina. Basal portion of dorsolateral carina, basal of spiracle, present. Spiracle very small, round, evidently before middle of tergum. Second tergum about 1.1 times as long as apical width, with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.1 to 0.3 times diameter of puncture, but gradually finer and more sparsely punctate towards apical margin, basal margin with semicircular thyridium. Third tergum with finer punctures than second tergum, lateral and apical portion weakly, sparsely punctate. Fourth tergum slightly rough, indistinctly punctate. Following terga smooth, with more or less clear transverse lines. Ovipositor sheath approximately 0.55 times as long as hind tibia, approximately as long as first tergum. Ovipositor strongly compressed, almost straight.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8069849207E85A1B30400BEF5FF79FA6" pageId="5" pageNumber="34">Color. (Fig. 1). Black, except the following. White or yellowish white portions: ventral-apical portions of scape and pedicel, apical portion of flagellomere 9, flagellomeres 10 to 16, basal portion of 17, latero-median spots of face, main portion of clypeus, mandible except teeth, maxillary palpus, labial palpus except apical segment grayish brown, front margin and upper-posterior corner of pronotum, elongate spots on latero-anterior portion of mesoscutum, subalar ridge, scutellum except anterior-median portion, spots of posterior portions of mesopleuron and metapleuron, apical part of basitarsus 1, and 2 to 4 entirely, basal, lateral and apical portions of first tergum, posterior margins of terga 2 and 3 widely, 7 and 8 mainly. A small spot near front median portion of mesopleuron vaguely reddish brown. Front and middle coxae and trochanters, ventral profiles of hind coxae, yellowish brown. Front and middle femora, hind coxae, trochanters and base of femora reddish brown. Front and middle tibiae and basitarsus, about basal 0.7 of hind tibiae darkish brown. Stigma blackish brown. Veins brownish black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9ABBA1BCEF5832D97DAE519989541EBA" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="5" pageNumber="34" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="3888AA8DDBAE90FC93C901CA049C1EFA" pageId="5" pageNumber="34">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="455B00353FF461021E2A961EB48DFD10" pageId="5" pageNumber="34">This new species can be easily distinguished from other species of this genus as the face has a distinct median longitudinal carina, the areolet is clearly petiolate, the first tergum is slightly narrowed towards the base and the inner profile of the basal half of the flagella has a particular structure, a strong longitudinal carina.</paragraph>
<caption id="30C6A5F7C2258357CBD353E82F54B01A" pageId="6" pageNumber="35">
<paragraph id="D68AED993E54BFD7F8B0CA8CFEAF83B1" pageId="6" pageNumber="35">
<pageBreakToken id="FAA95AE2290FCD9AF58DD76771C99CBF" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" start="start">Figures</pageBreakToken>
1-5. 
<taxonomicName id="3E7AAB3485E92C187378BC53D5C1A633" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cryptopimpla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cryptopimpla carinifacialis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="carinifacialis">Cryptopimpla carinifacialis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype. Female 1 Body, lateral view 2 Face 3 Vertex 3a Basal portion of flagellum 4 Mesopleuron 5 Propodeum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>