<document id="7BB8C249C73C0D1BB5F57278C88D84D1" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.337.5903" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e34e4613-4d96-4531-a3f0-4e22fa0104d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152048505" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-337-35" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34385B01-7446-45DA-863D-A22C97B1B808" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-337-35" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 337" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Numbakullidae Guţu &amp; Heard, 2002 (Tanaidacea, Peracarida, Crustacea) from the Great Barrier Reef, Australia" checkinTime="1451246861478" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Stepien, Anna" docDate="2013" docId="2F2B821D6CBBB12B929ACCDAF2CDE34E" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 337: 35-47" docOrigin="ZooKeys 337" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.337.5903" docTitle="Numbakulla pii Stepien, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="34385B01-7446-45DA-863D-A22C97B1B808" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="43" masterDocId="FF84FFF5E43FFFFEFFB7FFDAAB58FF8D" masterDocTitle="A new species of Numbakullidae Gutu &amp; Heard, 2002 (Tanaidacea, Peracarida, Crustacea) from the Great Barrier Reef, Australia" masterLastPageNumber="47" masterPageNumber="35" pageId="2" pageNumber="37" updateTime="1643534656000" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="6EF70BD5F35C125357CD516342F1CC61" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="D0984146D10DEBA366480DE909AA19C5">
<mods:title id="44D18A185DC87EBD2EEB0D0F23517459">A new species of Numbakullidae Gutu &amp; Heard, 2002 (Tanaidacea, Peracarida, Crustacea) from the Great Barrier Reef, Australia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="E886C1905B9F354CD93ECEACBE03F580" type="personal">
<mods:role id="2741E0B55ED488B4F72AD6E9ABC43B2A">
<mods:roleTerm id="3F725F8908F33F2BE981756013BCD27E">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C7878CDD5D080DFB8DAB34E4852CB619">Stepien, Anna</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="8A2887CDD6C6B022D914E755087B9891">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="6867FD92DE95C46BFA6A67DA115C918A" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="BA22E9BEA4C41361934AADD14BD47673">
<mods:title id="7F2873091EA7E002CAF3172A67C6BFF1">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="82E7B0E4E13A2F9D45A56D6B3DD07033">
<mods:date id="1599ACC65F8F7338EAD624EE56B0662A">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="A2C46C829708C1CC5EC7BA87D0338992" type="volume">
<mods:number id="7919720F4470FFCBD3D393AF44F84D89">337</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="61C496450785D1293190B2E986DD7CC6" unit="page">
<mods:start id="B0C523F91C5EB6E90A76DDF65F707242">35</mods:start>
<mods:end id="2D3A61A56E0909DC9FD25249AA19976C">47</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="EA773B0C51F8AC3B91159DA16EE58ED4">
<mods:url id="52B77ADC3557921BCF029BCBD876E6A3">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.337.5903</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="836C61CEFDE4AB2DE4FE9258EC5AC335">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="18448155B0D200B1D7708EAB4666E4D8" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.337.5903</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="F1CC371DD6E03571641DC39853246392" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-337-35</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="06CCDE06DCAC203CE0B8C1794BE4E8E5" type="ZooBank">FB76AC3B-D8F6-4D4E-B738-C43DA62199B1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="2F2B821D6CBBB12B929ACCDAF2CDE34E" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152048505" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34385B01-7446-45DA-863D-A22C97B1B808" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2F2B821D6CBBB12B929ACCDAF2CDE34E" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="2" pageNumber="37">
<subSubSection id="A1A00F2829540AA20901F7493F2580B6" pageId="2" pageNumber="37" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="3E3F6D7451DF20D912F05C30AF4CE29E" pageId="2" pageNumber="37">
<taxonomicName id="88B742C5CEA58870EB28A124D193CD46" LSID="http://zoobank.org/34385B01-7446-45DA-863D-A22C97B1B808" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="2" pageNumber="37" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="78A56394AC868482691F005A5A73318E" pageId="2" pageNumber="37">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-4, Photo 1
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="5D362141A83E47E63960EB4EC7A6C944" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="38" pageId="2" pageNumber="37" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="74B5C76CB6DCDB8BC3E904009D9A03F4" pageId="2" pageNumber="37">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B2D24B4677987492F8E19CD4133D6622" pageId="2" pageNumber="37">
Holotype: female (MTQ W34252), Stn HI 10-009E, 
<geoCoordinate id="A83C4F586C26A91C1D915A47C5251221" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-23.431389">23°25'53&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="D00C0CFE00C24B8A69B7FE8F50C3ADDB" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="152.04918">152°2'57&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, Sykes Reef, reef slope, coral rubble on sand, 12m depth, 14 November 2010, coll. C. Buxton.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="94E258A57F2635846D075BCF3A36A378" pageId="3" pageNumber="38">
<pageBreakToken id="13B7586624AACDACB4371202F9BFA789" pageId="3" pageNumber="38" start="start">Paratypes</pageBreakToken>
: 14 females (MTQ W34253), Stn HI 10-009E, same locality as holotype; eleven females (MTQ W34254), Stn HI 10-009D, 
<geoCoordinate id="B7F9BF9F18C8B86B988EBB84CD56BD71" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-23.431389">23°25'53&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="AD495039CF1F9738FC5B810BBAF2EDE4" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="152.04918">152°2'57&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, Sykes Reef, reef flat, small coral rubble on sand, 12 m depth, 14 November 2010, coll. M. 
<normalizedToken id="9DE6D21415AEE4E0005E46BCABD78029" originalValue="Błażewicz-Paszkowycz">Blazewicz-Paszkowycz</normalizedToken>
, C. Buxton; one female (MTQ W34256) Stn HI 10-009B, 
<geoCoordinate id="D23E89098A0B4A8D117C5BA6E99951AB" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-23.431389">23°25'53&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="9BE6D31863B303FBA7FBE5504F1ED272" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="152.04918">152°2'57&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, Sykes Reef, reef slope, coral rubble at base of the wall, 27 m depth, 14 November 2010, coll. S. Smith, C. Buxton; four females (MTQ W34255) Stn HI 10-013A, 
<geoCoordinate id="A49DB9A8FE97A6E4C444E2A75378C05F" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-23.586668">23°35'12&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="684A5064AAFF67776C1BC97418860BF7" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="152.06223">152°3'44&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, Lamont Reef, reef slope, coral rubble on sand, 21 m depth, 15 November 2010, coll. C. Buxton.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35411F619513DF68DD203EA3A1B1EF6B" pageId="3" pageNumber="38" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="585F83A7FC3249F58B269EA53AC27CA6" pageId="3" pageNumber="38">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E496947AA829FBAC7D9F800C0E4AFBEA" pageId="3" pageNumber="38">Named after Pi Patel, the central character from the novel Life of Pi, written by Yann Martel, one of favourite authors novel.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ADB0750781B9EC8082953B46E66122A2" pageId="3" pageNumber="38" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="28076B8F3858F00192BF2F631F4C693A" pageId="3" pageNumber="38">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B20E871AF6389707024A828D3C4FAA30" pageId="3" pageNumber="38">Body dorsoventrally flattened, 6.7 times longer than wide, blunt rostrum, eyes present, pereonite 4 clearly longer than the rest, mandible palp articles 2 with spines on outer margin, lacina mobilis narrow, one-denticled, antennule outer flagellum with six segments, antenna peduncle article 2 elongated, cheliped carpus with inner row of seven setae, pereopod 1 basis with row of setae, pereopod 6 carpus with row of ventral spines, pleopod endopod with proximal acute denticles, uropod endopod with 13 segments.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="999549F457350F6CAFD12DD2AA05EDBC" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="3" pageNumber="38" type="description of female">
<paragraph id="31BB360247C3AEE2268CD146F31FAF0D" pageId="3" pageNumber="38">Description of female.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8E9557EDB0C815D6E8B30D71EC9C281A" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="40" pageId="3" pageNumber="38">
Body (Figs 1A, B, Photo 1) 1.7 mm long, 6.7 times as long as wide. Cephalothorax 22% of total body length, with blunt rostrum; ocular 
<pageBreakToken id="BB8F2E1D1573176A57125F1C9E737102" pageId="4" pageNumber="39" start="start">lobes</pageBreakToken>
present, with visual elements. Pereon: pereonites 1, 2 and 3 similar in length, 0.3 times as long as wide, pereonite 4 longest, 0.4 times as long as wide; pereonites 5 and 6 shorter, about 0.2 times as long as wide; all pereonites with pair of setae dorsally; 
<pageBreakToken id="8177888A87FBD386EAD9BA64EDB58007" pageId="5" pageNumber="40" start="start">last</pageBreakToken>
pereonite with three setae laterally. Pleon 19% of total body length, first four pleonites similar in length, 0.1 times as long as wide, with three or four long plumose setae laterally and pair of setae dorsally, and with rounded lateral margin; last pleonite 0.2 times as long as wide, with three plumose setae laterally and acute lateral margin. Pleotelson acute posteriorly, 1.6 times as long, with four setae laterally and two pairs of setae dorsally.
</paragraph>
<caption id="11443E629A5AAFF6B69162304D205718" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
<paragraph id="2890D6802FFD1DA16357B8EFF923EBF4" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
Photo 1. 
<taxonomicName id="84BE7FBA556356D31F3F07B2845D97D9" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="5" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype female. Body dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="B9E3F60082B2839B31EC7894B98C1BCF" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
<paragraph id="C2543156EE42F13F2C63C17D17EC8683" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName id="DBF0FB97D41A49BBE9093C2E6F1688B8" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="5" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female. A body dorsal view B body lateral view. Scale line = 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="881DCA12D75FF863D0DD68AF5F420548" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
<paragraph id="C3777801E2BC288B1ADE1706C310E9BE" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName id="CA37BEC62CBB0B4DFAAFB54647B29C83" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="5" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
sp. n., A palp of left mandible B left mandible C right mandible D maxillule E maxilla F maxilliped G palp of maxillule H epignath I maxillipedal endite. Scale line = 0.1mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="FE4889094510515BF3637EF2B89C8D99" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">Antennule (Fig. 3A): peduncle article 1 7.5 times as long as wide, with one penicillate seta on outer margin, and with 13 simple setae on whole surface; article 2 0.2 times as long as article 1, with one simple seta on inner margin and with five simple setae and two penicillate setae on distal margin; article 3 2.4 times as long as wide, with four distal simple setae; article 4 with four distal simple setae; outer flagellum with six segments, segments 1 and 3 with aesthetasc, last segment with four simple setae; inner flagellum with two segments, last segment with four simple setae.</paragraph>
<caption id="C4157DA34FDD05EAC3898AB5C398B6F6" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
<paragraph id="6B095F60D3E737B39F62F36C3A5A1963" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName id="76C31E91C0BD1CFFAE52998516818301" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="5" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
sp. n., A antennule B antenna C left cheliped D pleopod E uropod. Scale line = 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="DE01B97791D99FD3008039AFC5102C52" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">Antenna (Fig. 3B): peduncle article 1 with rounded apophysis bearing distal plumose seta; article 2 elongate, five times as long as wide, with three inner plumose setae; squama narrow, bearing two simple setae; article 3 0.2 times as long as article 2, with two distal simple setae; article 4 0.6 times as long as article 2, with one penicillate seta; article 5 similar in length to article 4, with two mid-length simple setae, and distally with two simple, and three penicillate setae; flagellum with four segments, distal segment with three simple setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="14374882B3AC7F2571B0D5E87E57F8DF" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">Mouthparts: Left mandible (Fig. 2B) bearing denticulate pars incisiva; lacinia mobilis with one blunt tooth; setiferous lobe with two simple and two plumose setae; palp (Fig. 2A) article 1 1.7 times as long as wide, with two inner setae; article 2 2.5 times as long as wide, with five long and five short plumose setae on inner margin, and with denticulate outer margin; article 3 2.2 times as long as wide, with seven inner plumose setae. Right mandible (Fig. 2C) with two teeth on pars incisiva; pars molaris robust, margin with row of simple setae. Maxillule (Fig. 2D) outer endite with eight distal spines and two subdistal setae; inner and outer margin finely setose; inner endite with three distal plumose setae; palp (Fig. 2G) two-articled, with two subdistal and one distal setae. Maxilla (Fig. 2E) outer lobe of moveable endite with plumose setae, two subdistally and four on distal margin; inner lobe with four distal simple setae; outer lobe of fixed endite with some simple setae and three trifurcated setae; inner endite with rostral row of twelve setae, inner margin with two denticles. Maxilliped (Fig. 2F) basis 0.8 times as long as wide, naked; palp article 1 0.4 times as long as wide, with one outer plumose seta and with one long inner plumose setae; palp article 2 1.3 times as long as wide, with one outer plumose seta, and with inner row of seven plumose setae; palp article 3 1.7 times as long as wide, with two inner rows of plumose setae (marginal row of 23 setae, submarginal row of six setae); palp article 4 2.7 times as long as wide, with inner row of 15 plumose setae. Endite (Fig. 2I) with 15 plumose setae along outer and distal margin, and with two coupling hooks. Epignath (Fig. 2H) narrow, with strong distal seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F2E4D35B8FAB722B2E49ADCEAF566872" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="42" pageId="5" pageNumber="40">
Cheliped (Fig. 3C) basis 1.8 times as long as wide, ventrally with two proximal setae, and two distal setae, and dorsally with one seta; exopodite three-articled, last arti 
<pageBreakToken id="D795CBD2E43FFAC0CF964356B98C85DE" pageId="6" pageNumber="41" start="start">cle</pageBreakToken>
with four plumose setae; merus 1.5 times as long as wide, with five ventral plumose setae; carpus 1.7 times as long as wide, with four ventrodistal setae, two dorsodistal setae, and with row of seven inner plumose setae; palm of propodus as long as wide, 
<pageBreakToken id="8B9B4B8D4DBCD3D5443928CD8E406060" pageId="7" pageNumber="42" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
three dorsal plumose setae and with six simple setae along ventral margin of palm and fixed finger; fixed finger as long as palm, cutting edge crenulated, with four simple setae, and two proximal tooth-like apophysis; dactylus with unguis 1.2 times as long as propodus, with two dorsal setae, cutting edge crenulated.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CA7C719D253928FDF9CC952AEA3FDC97" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">Pereopod 1 (Fig. 4A) basis four times as long as wide, dorsally with six plumose setae; exopodite three-articled, distal article with four plumose setae; ischium 0.3 times as long as wide, with one ventrodistal seta; merus 1.8 times as long as wide, with mid-dorsal plumose seta and two dorsodistal plumose setae, ventral margin with two rows of numerous, long plumose setae; carpus 0.7 times as long as merus, dorsally with three plumose setae, one simple setae and one spine, ventral margin with two rows of numerous plumose setae; propodus 1.3 times as long as wide, half as long as carpus, with one penicillate and one plumose setae, and one spine dorsally, ventral margin with three plumose setae and four spines; dactylus together with unguis as long as propodus, with one dorsal, and two ventral setae.</paragraph>
<caption id="7C0E7CDA1A6C040DFCC5FBC03706EA04" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">
<paragraph id="F74F801C2D729DC903782437566A6A2D" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="E2EECD3DED8A7EAE99667FE1DDAE5649" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="7" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
sp. n., A pereopod 1 B pereopod 2 C pereopod 3 D pereopod 4 E pereopod 5 F propodus of pereopod 5 G pereopod 6. Scale line = 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="888273FC21C89CCADFAAB963850EF084" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">Pereopod 2 (Fig. 4B) basis six times as long as wide, with four ventral plumose setae and three dorsal setae, ischium as long as wide, with plumose ventral seta; merus three times as long as wide, ventral margin with one plumose seta and thin spine, dorsal margin with one plumose seta; carpus 0.7 times as long as merus, with two plumose setae and two spines ventrally, and with three dorsodistal plumose setae; propodus 5.3 times as long as wide, 2.1 times as long as carpus, with one dorsal penicillate setae, ventral margin with one plumose seta and three spines, three finely denticulate setae near dactylus insertion; dactylus together with unguis 0.7 times as long as propodus, with seta on dorsal and ventral margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AF8071AD40BAE3AB97A5BBACD0BB0DD8" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">Pereopod 3 (Fig. 4C) similar to pereopod 2, but basis with two ventral penicillate setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="54DE6EBC5C01D35E6CE2AD453856C579" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 4D) basis 5.6 times as long as wide, with three dorsal plumose setae and with two ventral plumose setae; ischium 0.6 times as long as wide, with two ventrodistal plumose setae; merus 1.6 times as long as wide, with dorsal plumose seta and with three dorsodistal and one mid-dorsal plumose setae; carpus 1.1 times as long as merus, with two dorsal plumose setae, and with four spines and two plumose setae on ventrodistal and distal margin; propodus 4.8 times as long as wide, 1.7 times as long as carpus, with dorsal penicillate seta, ventral margin with three thin spines and one simple seta, and three finely denticulated setae near dactylus insertion; dactylus together with unguis 0.8 times as long as propodus, with simple seta on ventral and dorsal margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D467270464E12389B3219CF551CF12D4" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">Pereopod 5 (Fig. 4E) basis 5.5 times as long as wide, with three proximal penicillate setae on dorsal margin and with two ventral plumose setae; ischium 0.9 times as long as wide, with two plumose ventrodistal setae; merus 1.3 times as long as wide, with plumose seta dorso- and ventrodistally; carpus 1.6 times as long as merus, with five spines and two plumose setae on distal margin; propodus (Fig. 4F) three times as long as wide, 1.3 times as long as carpus, with three thin ventral spines, and with eleven finely denticulate plumose setae near dactylus insertion; dactylus together with unguis 0.7 times as long as propodus, with simple setae on dorsal and ventral margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="58D0DA01EEBC97900DA1DCB9C4C83722" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="7" pageNumber="42">
Pereopod 6 (Fig. 4G) basis 6.8 times as long as wide, with ten dorsal plumose setae, and with three ventral plumose setae; ischium 0.6 times as long as wide, with two ventrodistal plumose setae; merus 1.7 times as long as wide, with six dorsal plumose 
<pageBreakToken id="A76E5FCDD48E70D8B49B480A0B5CE791" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" start="start">setae</pageBreakToken>
, ventral margin with four plumose setae, and one short, simple seta; carpus 1.7 times as long as merus, with six plumose setae and one spine on dorsal margin, and with four plumose setae and four spines on ventral margin; propodus 3.3 times as long as wide, similar in length to carpus, dorsally with one simple and one penicillate seta, and with row of numerous simple setae along ventral and distal margin; dactylus together with unguis 0.7 times as long as propodus, with one dorsal setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9CB2BFF766542C144DEDF27F456B9501" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">Pleopods (Fig. 3D) in four pairs, basis with two inner marginal plumose setae; exopod with 13 marginal plumose setae; endopod with 15 marginal plumose setae and proximal acute denticles on inner margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EE4E6728036776AE8E00FBC3A34A5A51" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">Uropod (Fig. 3E) basis 6.5 times as long as wide, with six distal and one marginal setae; exopod of four-segments; segment 2 with two distal setae; last segment with four distal setae; endopod of 13 segments, most with simple setae, last segment with four distal setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="081458A646D1894015DD85D32CF35E43" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="1880F89D2A8F542243740AA4EAA3B5F9" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A2054C4DC6CD2B0AE9228E07B3EB14F9" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">
The new species differs from the two previously described species by the length/width ratio of the body, which is 6.7 in 
<taxonomicName id="2600CCFA9211DCC3215B68F42A3BD7D2" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 8.0 in 
<taxonomicName id="BE622ABE476063FAB394AB1CA3DB364F" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla srilankensis" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="srilankensis">Numbakulla srilankensis</taxonomicName>
and 4.5 in 
<taxonomicName id="BB189C29D74D9E16BF604FD70C5CAA3E" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pygmaeus" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pygmaeus">Numbakulla pygmaeus</taxonomicName>
. 
<taxonomicName id="981997B60909B52DA2B9C35EFF79D7CB" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
also differs in lacking &quot;glandular formations&quot; on the pereopods, present in the other species, having ventral spines on pereopod 6 carpus and acute proximal denticles on endopod of pleopod. 
<taxonomicName id="E1301410B05D2A0B50867566A3708472" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished by the appearance of the mandible with a narrow, one-denticled lacina mobilis and palp article 2 with denticles.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D878AC369D9BAB498C4F75FE07CC6982" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">
The new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName id="F48E4466AC85267DC02B59CE0DA8EF34" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla srilankensis" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="srilankensis">Numbakulla srilankensis</taxonomicName>
in having a flat rostrum, well-developed eyes and pereonite 4 clearly longer than the rest, while in 
<taxonomicName id="8B740CE39723C07A61D9E2A81E5C1D56" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pygmaeus" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pygmaeus">Numbakulla pygmaeus</taxonomicName>
rostrum is rounded, eyes are absent and all pereonites are similar in length. 
<taxonomicName id="3F2AFF8E7195A1A61C17296635AA4E8F" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
resembles 
<taxonomicName id="00F83556F3D3C368312546240457732D" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla srilankensis" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="srilankensis">Numbakulla srilankensis</taxonomicName>
also in bearing row of inner setae on cheliped carpus, but in first species the row contain seven setae and in the second species 24. Both species have also a row of setae on basis of pereopod 1 (absent in Australian species)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C071B073F65D2B9ECB83B3C93039F092" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">
<taxonomicName id="1B27787FC6ED433631D9EBE9F6BE6A2D" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pii" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pii">Numbakulla pii</taxonomicName>
shares with 
<taxonomicName id="A212255E3A0E34D11323F7F3B6DF010A" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla pygameus" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pygameus">Numbakulla pygameus</taxonomicName>
an elongated peduncle article 2 of the antenna, which is short in 
<taxonomicName id="89AD35FB9EAF807B5FFCF4BB278FD6F7" class="Malacostraca" family="Numbakullidae" genus="Numbakulla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Numbakulla srilankensis" order="Tanaidacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="srilankensis">Numbakulla srilankensis</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D9C8CFD6F8A9317D6632C5563F97E239" pageId="8" pageNumber="43" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="7207C46E27386339237F724613ED5EDB" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7822F975DC680227047CF1FC31776A8F" pageId="8" pageNumber="43">The species is known from Lamont Reef and Sykes Reef, the Capricorn Group, southern Great Barrier Reef, eastern Australia and was recorded from a depth range of 12-27m in coral rubble.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>