<document id="4012C7F2C232869BEEC9CE1280D32344" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.805.28757" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c0cb883f-3c6c-4d0b-a280-04157f2ad247" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154126818" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-805-45" ID-ZBK="5EF6D879D86F49279B12C0BC91DC6FF2" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D8D16E65-0970-49BE-BC6E-DB0A4D1A4805" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-805-45" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 805" ModsDocTitle="A new genus and species of Brontinae from Borneo (Coleoptera, Silvanidae)" checkinTime="1545315517247" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Yoshida, Takahiro &amp; Hirowatari, Toshiya" docDate="2018" docId="33F1DE47AD6FB5F2D035149182787DCF" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 805: 45-57" docOrigin="ZooKeys 805" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.805.28757" docTitle="Borneophanus spinosus Yoshida &amp; Hirowatari, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="D8D16E65-0970-49BE-BC6E-DB0A4D1A4805" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="55" masterDocId="FFA49D22D31FFF9FFFBDEF54FFFCFFEE" masterDocTitle="A new genus and species of Brontinae from Borneo (Coleoptera, Silvanidae)" masterLastPageNumber="57" masterPageNumber="45" pageId="4" pageNumber="49" updateTime="1643554250668" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="76A21C7CA5BFFA4F2598621BA97344AF" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2BFB3AE873AB337600EE8B5C61CA7217">
<mods:title id="F406BAF07145CCC1D8AD45D7BEA79AD9">A new genus and species of Brontinae from Borneo (Coleoptera, Silvanidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="89B8DB826FC0BB31BF2480992E100592" type="personal">
<mods:role id="2D0D0E2F8849AAC3679AB16D59B20D01">
<mods:roleTerm id="7295A6B0E2AD2FD8FEAA38F670A764FD">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="097B0DA70893FF29080B96D48046CD87">Yoshida, Takahiro</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="7F334B42909B269ACB62B67B2BAAE74A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="330EF1F779E2D8F26E581906DD151DED">
<mods:roleTerm id="E420D2A91DF24656DDBB37922A1FAD19">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="32EEA825038972F9A358FD65B2F7F763">Hirowatari, Toshiya</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="250B5DAAD6AA21CC7D9AC8FD658CF270">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="7AE8CCEA5FDF9827D9824F8BBA26F112" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="8C1C92751B900701146ABC6270168C9C">
<mods:title id="0CA252B4F1F0D2AC6C6FC9AB4BB983AA">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="09B0571B4FCDBC94F40B1AC794ECFEE2">
<mods:date id="A9EBB74679A41197165000A598CB723F">2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="4695F18389E6ACFD6A06B18EB4B377D2" type="volume">
<mods:number id="E0ECEB52006A631BCF6B28DFD62D4D4C">805</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="5314473BCC57397841673910C5C8B0B6" unit="page">
<mods:start id="804A7D62FB74537F59FA91ED97417730">45</mods:start>
<mods:end id="77FA745A9B117ABC0767CFAD5121E6DC">57</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="E4DF1B299C62B62F70D916B3D89D5105">
<mods:url id="42366411B1E68931FEAEB51794378919">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.805.28757</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="0C8D1907CC2B2E88027006CE85059B53">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="26091A7B9F0432330AD1936609436530" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.805.28757</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="69B8655F69C71FDAA0A4604BFAC945BF" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-805-45</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="2B0A5724D6778E81455D45E7783DABCA" type="ZBK">5EF6D879D86F49279B12C0BC91DC6FF2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="218988B3DBD1C7369CB9728466ABA45B" type="ZooBank">5EF6D879D86F49279B12C0BC91DC6FF2</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="33F1DE47AD6FB5F2D035149182787DCF" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154126818" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D8D16E65-0970-49BE-BC6E-DB0A4D1A4805" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/33F1DE47AD6FB5F2D035149182787DCF" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="4" pageNumber="49">
<subSubSection id="51BD50EC535329BBB7689E08A2815E06" pageId="4" pageNumber="49" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="2ECA9D4F24706C339100EB6CE9103852" pageId="4" pageNumber="49">
<taxonomicName id="809E9A8F8C4EF725641F44E3B588B535" LSID="http://zoobank.org/D8D16E65-0970-49BE-BC6E-DB0A4D1A4805" authority="Yoshida &amp; Hirowatari, 2018" authorityName="Yoshida &amp; Hirowatari" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Silvanidae" genus="Borneophanus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Borneophanus spinosus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="49" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosus">Borneophanus spinosus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="DB432656EAB7FE2EAD8349F8A807B01E" pageId="4" pageNumber="49">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 7A
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="73D94FAE7DC760734E4C4F7D861A8297" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="50" pageId="4" pageNumber="49" type="type series">
<paragraph id="C6033F5044F9B4FA4BA15A7F0A35C1AB" pageId="4" pageNumber="49">Type series.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D6329750594EBB7655177BD5863BE699" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="50" pageId="4" pageNumber="49">
Holotype: male, Poling near Ranau, Sabah State, Malaysia, 26 Apr 1980, M &amp; A Sakai leg. (EUMJ). Paratypes: [Sabah State] 1 male and 1 female, same data as 
<pageBreakToken id="CA9798F0CD5E25752FFE4F7CEC3B92D1" pageId="5" pageNumber="50" start="start">the</pageBreakToken>
holotype (EUMJ); 1 female, Sandakan Bay (SW), Sapagaya Lumber Camp (2-20 m), 1 Nov 1957, JL Gressitt leg. (ANIC); 1 female, Poring Hot Springs, Mt. Kinabalu National Park (486 m), 8-14 May 1987, DE Bright leg., Beating foliage. (ANIC; Loan from USNMNH 2031682). [Sarawak State] 1 male, Gunong Matang (120 m), 13 Sept 1958, JL Gressitt leg. (ANIC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B77A48BAA7B1CC859B1538A3BBC632AC" pageId="5" pageNumber="50" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="6B8515B4684E08B6BCAAEF462CF5F6F2" pageId="5" pageNumber="50">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="20FCF0A54E7CE46CA034EC5B6E278239" pageId="5" pageNumber="50">
This new species is superficially similar to some 
<taxonomicName id="38F60071D3B92A87885A81990971E714" class="Insecta" family="Silvanidae" genus="Telephanus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Telephanus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="50" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Telephanus</taxonomicName>
species bearing long spines on lateral pronotum and elytra. This new species can be easily distinguished from these species by the distinct pair of longitudinal frontal lines, the asymmetric shaped antennomere X, and the sharply protruding elytral apices.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E7A0965302A35902A88FDECA9FBB0ABA" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="5" pageNumber="50" type="description">
<paragraph id="C697AAF8E1E28D7B1EAC81E49A3C7DEF" pageId="5" pageNumber="50">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="24AC15D505AD292658C5A4069EA6B5BC" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="5" pageNumber="50">
BL: 4.47-5.28 mm (n = 5). Coloration (Fig. 1). Surface yellowish to reddish brown, mostly unicolored; legs and setae lighter colored. Head (Figs 1-3) subquadrate, HL 0.61-0.70 mm; HW 0.87-1.03 mm; HW/HL 1.37-1.46; IE/HL 0.90-1.04 (n = 5). Eye roundly protruding, as long as length of antennomere IX. Punctation strong and distinct, absent laterally to frontal lines; ventral surface with sparser punctation, impunctate medially. Pubescence fine, composed of short to long 
<pageBreakToken id="173EE5540321150AE6063A5A9ECA5480" pageId="6" pageNumber="51" start="start">setae</pageBreakToken>
, setae located on posterior margin of each puncture or on very minute tubercles lateral to frontal lines. Labrum (Fig. 3B) ventrally with many setae along anterior margin, dorsally with somewhat dense pubescence composed of short to medium length setae. Antenna (Fig. 3A) with long and somewhat thick scape, three times as long as antennomere II; very densely covered with fine and medium length to long setae; antennal length and approximate ratios of antennomere lengths of holotype as follows: 3.10 mm; 3.0: 1.0: 1.3: 1.4: 1.4: 1.4: 1.4: 1.4: 1.4: 1.3: 2.2. Mandible (Fig. 3C, D) ventrally with a stout tooth protruding apically, with a wide tooth on 
<pageBreakToken id="A6A6D2BA009D10777E970C86A296DB23" pageId="7" pageNumber="52" start="start">inner</pageBreakToken>
margin near apex, ventrally densely covered with many asperities near the inner tooth, densely, finely pubescent on approx. anterior 1/3 of inner margin, punctation very fine and partly very dense, sparse or absent near apex, lateral and molar regions, 
<pageBreakToken id="DB132E0C71226376B0D2E9788F72090F" pageId="8" pageNumber="53" start="start">dorsally</pageBreakToken>
with one long seta near apex and some setae of medium length on outer lateral region, with some short setae near mycangium; mola widely extended posteriorly, with some teeth and dense cuticular spines on posterior 1/3 of inner margin; mycangium located on middle of posterior area, opening towards outer lateral margin, longitudinally depressed on and around mycangium. Maxilla (Fig. 3E): lacinia with two long apical blunt teeth, dorsally with some setae in a longitudinal row along inner margin, few apically, these setae long, with several long setae along apical 2/5 of lateral margin; galea long and flattened, somewhat membranous; distigalea with short to very long, dense pubescence, dorsally with a short row of several short setae and one long seta on posterior half, connected to basigalea by a membrane; palpifer longitudinally oblong, ventrally with several short setae; palpomere 1 very small, extended at inner distal portion; palpomere 2 approx. twice as long as palpomere 1, strongly widened distally, with some short setae, with one very long seta on inner distal portion; palpomere 3 longer than palpomere 2, widened distally, covered with setae of various length, with one very long seta on inner distal portion; palpomere 4 securiform, strongly expanded, 2.5 times as long as palpomere 3, densely covered with short to medium length setae, densely with very short setae along distal margin; stipes ventrally with some medium length setae. Labium (Fig. 3F) distinctly divided from ligula; prementum gradually widened distally, with several long setae along distal margin, with pair of long setae and few short setae near palps; palpomere 1 very small, with few short setae, with a puncture on inner side; palpomere 2 densely covered 
<pageBreakToken id="FB60CF09ACEC53938AEFEFCEBF4C7504" pageId="9" pageNumber="54" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
many setae of various lengths; palpomere 3 densely covered with many setae of medium length, ventrally with several thick and long to medium length setae near distal margin, distally and densely covered with minute setae; mentum somewhat strongly widening proximally, partly somewhat densely covered with long setae. Thorax and abdomen (Figs 1, 2, 4
<normalizedToken id="751229323234A42191F6412C185A6B5A" originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
). Pronotum wider than long, PL 1.00-1.18 mm; PW 1.14-1.44 mm; PW/PL 1.15-1.24 (n = 6), enlarged around anterior angles and anterior 1/3 of lateral margins, with numerous minute setiferous tubercles densely covering lateral margins and sparser on anterior and posterior margins, with a long spine on each tubercle, somewhat densely covered with fine and long pubescence except on margins; punctation coarse, similar to vertex. Thoracic ventrites with punctation sparser than on dorsum, with pubescence shorter and sparser than on dorsum, densely covered with numerous short setae on anterior margin of proventrite; intercoxal process of procoxae widest at posterior 2/5, strongly narrowed around anterior 1/5 to 2/5, somewhat extended around posterior angles; mesocoxal process narrowed posteriorly, widened around apex. Scutellar shield (Figs 1A, 2) approx. twice as wide as long, wider than eye length, with few short setae. Legs somewhat thin; trochanters small, with sparse setae of various lengths, with one long seta; femora somewhat thin, densely covered with thin and medium length setae; profemora a little expanded; tibiae thin but gradually widening distally, with similar pubescence of femora, with some conical setae around apices; tarsomere 5 long, approx. 3 times as long as 4 (Fig. 4A,B). Abdomen (Fig. 4C) 1.5 times as long as wide; intercoxal process somewhat wide and moderately rounded anteriorly; 1st and 2nd abdominal ventrites with strong lateral protuberances; punctation sparse, weaker toward posterior; setae similar to those on thoracic ventrites. Elytra (Figs 1A, 2) long, sub-parallel for approximately the anterior 2/3, EL 2.84-3.40 mm (n = 6); EW 1.46-1.76 mm at approximately 1/3 length (n = 6); EW/EL 0.51-0.52 (n = 6); EW/BL 0.32-0.34 (n = 5); apices sharply protruding and triangular, with rows of punctures almost as wide as interstices, with short and thin setae on anterior margins of the punctures, with very minute setiferous tubercles on the spaces between rows, with long and thin setae on the tubercles, these setae near lateral margins thick, densely with many spines of long and medium lengths on lateral margins. Male genitalia (Fig. 4
<normalizedToken id="38EC10413809EE83A56B1EDFE0579B5D" originalValue="D–H">D-H</normalizedToken>
). Tergite VIII (Fig. 4D) square, longer than wide, with rounded posterior margin, with many setae of various lengths around posterior margin; lateral margins protruding inwards near middle and connected with sternite VIII; sternite VIII (Fig. 4D) square, almost as long as wide, with rounded posterior margin, with many setae of various lengths on posterior half, with few long setae along posterior margin near posterior angles; spiculum gastrale (Fig. 4E) Y-shaped, with thin strut, bifurcating at around midlength, with simple branches; branches covered with membrane. Median lobe (Fig. 4H) very long and thin, gradually narrowed toward apex, with internal sac exposed for the apical 1/6, densely punctate around apex. Parameres (Fig. 4F, G) long, flattened, subparallel, dorsally excavated near bases, dorsally without punctures and setae, ventrally densely covered with many setae of various lengths except on bases, with a few long setae along apical margins. Phallobase (Fig. 4F) long and subparallel; tegminal strut connected to basal piece around midlength; basal piece long; posterior margin of upper layer very deeply and sharply 
<pageBreakToken id="62D678361C3A97F54621F6CCBC603BB8" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" start="start">incised</pageBreakToken>
; posterior margin of lower layer widely extended anteriorly, somewhat membranous. Internal sac (Fig. 3H) minutely spinous around midlength; flagellum long, with two coiled sections near posterior 1/3.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="92E35903E94E49D0382C64E7B6AEE156" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Female genitalia (Figs 6, 7A). Gonostyli (Fig. 6B) with a long seta and setae of various length on apical 1/3, shorter than gonocoxite; spermatheca (Fig. 6C, D) bean-shaped and gradually enlarged distally, basally with a small sac connected to spermathecal duct, basis somewhat strongly explanate, with membranous spermathecal gland on basal 1/3, somewhat membranous near midlength.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="65CF9C006E9D0E22906B00E58828C2C7" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="87542E25D63A75D2A54D8A945C90B3D2" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="983B2C2F9F6AD113D741280C5211A714" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Malaysia (Sabah and Sarawak states).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A1E0A317FF78F3284E1CF491A7817CC7" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="BEB3909252B3A37615EF3DFE4D63555E" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1CA650AF12A7B8E760553DCCEE9304F7" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">The specific name means thorny and indicates the characteristic long spines.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="BE95E58206881CAAEF2F5AA7C5AD84A0" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="A19FC5E8A2CC313EEDD73F9DD4257E71" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2B72205BCD015AD9BDCA55DB50115173" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
This new species possesses characteristic long spines covering the lateral margins of pronotum and elytra. In possessing such setation, some 
<taxonomicName id="068DBEDB78D5A6187BC36E025DAE2A6A" class="Insecta" family="Silvanidae" genus="Telephanus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Telephanus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Telephanus</taxonomicName>
species (e.g., 
<taxonomicName id="45DE60BAF12B02AF6EB2D8D8B886F418" genus="T." lsidName="T. paradoxus" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" rank="species" species="paradoxus">T. paradoxus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="3E160AF9A088AEF4C8C033DF75D48593" genus="T." lsidName="T. sellatus" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" rank="species" species="sellatus">T. sellatus</taxonomicName>
Sharp, 1899) are superficially similar to this new species. They can be easily distinguished by the diagnostic character states of these genera. Otherwise, like 
<taxonomicName id="28074FC9804358ACB6896A82DD26A96B" class="Insecta" family="Silvanidae" genus="Telephanus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Telephanus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Telephanus</taxonomicName>
, such setation often occurs as a taxonomic character at the species or species group level; thus, the setal situation is not regarded as a character of this new genus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>