<document id="B5690F354090337236D06C4912302E23" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047621" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B82EF96C-90F3-4C7F-86E8-BAF19435493E" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="350E4F51D782F6C4A0CF0E5D2E3B9F36" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio tenuitatis Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="B82EF96C-90F3-4C7F-86E8-BAF19435493E" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="218" lastPageNumber="219" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="215" pageNumber="216" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="AC21B8D55D02A864FB4AF1EDD9638EBC" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="152740FBB1332CD26C6B255A05F91BB8">
<mods:title id="B079DAC898F02EDEF871388DB378FDB9">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="DCBB11766AD922A95477ACACC2C4B712" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AA1298A96D3F3AC5E0955394C4BA33CC">
<mods:roleTerm id="EC8A6C56E6164C5C08D595C0A63B6A4F">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="34924491F2FB746658B4F3432EF91561">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="85D30E0154A7270B57E0D8A9B4EAA089" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F60BDA1BDFDC63F09182083DB4BC852D">
<mods:roleTerm id="CC2B5F9D5FE6AEDE51AF6F38BDA095A0">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="548B7EFBADC58E739BE3754B6E850EE1">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="23E0FF27983380B11E9E28BF41D26C9F" type="personal">
<mods:role id="C42789155B814B504CF2EE5270CB1545">
<mods:roleTerm id="5AA248D8235CCAEB61DBF2E036C46AFF">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="4BD8C0DFA9F94BC3FAB8504D2D3CCC59">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="8222297F10DB8A518A9C2F30E476F1A5" type="personal">
<mods:role id="687AF0A7C7AD5B82CFEABEBA7B994A10">
<mods:roleTerm id="8CBFB98449B351243EAF7D6B00D090B9">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="674690B88880A3B1381B4BB4363D5421">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="02DB3E7CA1700EA17483D0F30D0E3CE9">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="E08530AFCCDD2C95800D24969AA1C018" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="9C00F0976BD27BC2F22EC86B69554C5C">
<mods:title id="E9204116DE2DAA6A487EA3BB80C0F023">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="CCFCC61F0628BF3410526D19FEBFD3B9">
<mods:date id="EADA9094D8A7946936F1DE85AE9C9BBF">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="AE24812B17DA6E505B596CC06DE4626C" type="volume">
<mods:number id="2F0DF0519159B27FD051E0CF010F5698">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="431442C1F45FA92D8E943229257EDA0D" unit="page">
<mods:start id="128DDF950BC7E190D5143B9C071D1D58">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="A94FD3C5665C3B2B7609073E23E3D77E">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="BDFB90AC707A3C49CCB6D6FE18714CE0">
<mods:url id="F34D644D2D773DBFF373DB0F951B53CA">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="80AE2E931C458E9D56541D6AA6827D4B">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C2BCD39296D1C584EE22BF661B0BD248" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="80658D291CACEC5D4B5B668615630FD1" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E98BE21755BFD3DBF7B20A86A8E2BA51" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="350E4F51D782F6C4A0CF0E5D2E3B9F36" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047621" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B82EF96C-90F3-4C7F-86E8-BAF19435493E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/350E4F51D782F6C4A0CF0E5D2E3B9F36" lastPageId="218" lastPageNumber="219" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">
<subSubSection id="6C636A855E454C498FE9A11C9C6187E4" pageId="215" pageNumber="216" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="87B4B70A8AA6F1B967BEFD5EC18AA7F2" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">
<taxonomicName id="B22FFF58DF9568D950DE26C0F4FFDEDC" LSID="http://zoobank.org/B82EF96C-90F3-4C7F-86E8-BAF19435493E" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio tenuitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="215" pageNumber="216" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenuitatis">Oxyscelio tenuitatis Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="913E38825CF9D4ED120D758B87B5F82C" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 359-364; Morphbank96
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AD26F250CB2D4DB8B0CE939B5C47D7A9" lastPageId="217" lastPageNumber="218" pageId="215" pageNumber="216" type="description">
<paragraph id="12F44E9B1317379E622795492C1C4FE0" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A3635FD8F91403177107498C9050548A" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">Female. Body length 3.3-4 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2E73E891BCB1B0264B2021B5CBB90EC6" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">Radicle color and shade: same as scape, both dark brown. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5F35BA095A5F007562E8D1E2EC7F63A4" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="613A45B5EE28B58ECDC72ABFB91F7546" lastPageId="217" lastPageNumber="218" pageId="215" pageNumber="216">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central prono 
<pageBreakToken id="14C8BE875C4A08241381299B2DEBEB92" pageId="216" pageNumber="217" start="start">tal</pageBreakToken>
area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupt 
<pageBreakToken id="E6B46714A4D1C570E3D17BD68FF4117F" pageId="217" pageNumber="218" start="start">ed</pageBreakToken>
elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T6. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A0FCE983871BBFA5A732F29D5A7513E9" pageId="217" pageNumber="218">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C909D6585A5C7E741FE8A4008BA0EF08" pageId="217" pageNumber="218">Male. Body length 3.25-3.85 mm (n=). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: longer than broad. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate; absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T6. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: weakly emarginate.</paragraph>
<caption id="60B1A71240085CA79032B65515F3D76E" pageId="217" pageNumber="218">
<paragraph id="1EE3E19A15407FCC1AB612F47AF12BA3" pageId="217" pageNumber="218">
Figures 359-364. 
<taxonomicName id="750E3989C82456FC521D7D4AD4593B51" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio tenuitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="217" pageNumber="218" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenuitatis">Oxyscelio tenuitatis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype female (OSUC 438285) 359 Head and mesosoma, lateral view. Holotype female (OSUC 438303) 360 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 361 Head, anterior view 362 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 438340) 363 Antenna 364 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank96
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F639CC41F6268DAA2CEACB35D0CA70FE" lastPageId="218" lastPageNumber="219" pageId="217" pageNumber="218" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="F4CDD4D8F8479F95D27B3BBF68E3AB68" pageId="217" pageNumber="218">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6C1974DAC2507ABDF647292951CCD367" lastPageId="218" lastPageNumber="219" pageId="217" pageNumber="218">
Both sexes: Body entirely dark brown, including antennae and legs. Frontal depression shallow, transverse carinae absent or broadly interrupted ventrally, absent dorsally; submedian carina absent medially. Hyperoccipital carina absent. Occipital carina complete, weakly convex or forming a rounded peak medially. Metascutellum deeply concave, emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein absent. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4 as long or slightly longer than broad, A5 nearly as long as broad. Mesoscutellum without granulate sculpture. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal 
<pageBreakToken id="8A836EE039F8DC7CB64A9347723FFB69" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" start="start">carinae</pageBreakToken>
. T6 without metasomal flanges, main body of tergum not abruptly separated from apical rim. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T6. Male: All flagellomeres longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach to or beyond T7. T7 emarginate apically, with rounded posterior lobes. 
<taxonomicName id="7174EFF4EB0556A831AA3F37DEFD9587" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio tenuitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenuitatis">Oxyscelio tenuitatis</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName id="FFEFC4D33D5A29CE4C8B696223B98D23" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio densitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="densitatis">Oxyscelio densitatis</taxonomicName>
, but differs in having dark brown antennae and legs, and in having weaker, more sparse sculpture on the metasomal sterna.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="BCE697F891FD617F561946DDDD765121" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="363D1587EC11DFB485C8D315EB601BB6" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="698012010AC4444184C7A6CFBB0B04C5" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">
Latin noun, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="4D982983A0B28AE7B2EE2C79076ACBD2" originalValue="“thinness.”">&quot;thinness.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0B5410D51930DD6078A2D5857536ABD3" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="C293C7BD592F0E4F44220E0B0FF4868F" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AC227BF36E23D902F3577B938B5520F0" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307113]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="BC79563F2CB977E887DD23F9DD79DBE0" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="D3E00ACB149534C69A4FC071531DF784" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9A5F71DED8F9E9A485F64D7F699BF614" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: TAS, Collinsvale, 12.II.1983, malaise trap, M. A. Williams, OSUC 438303 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 32 females, 54 males, Australian Museum K245265 (AMSA); ANIC DB 32-020902, 32-020903, OSUC 438282, OSUC 438283, OSUC 438284, OSUC 438285, OSUC 438286, OSUC 438287, OSUC 438288, OSUC 438289, OSUC 438290, OSUC 438291, OSUC 438292, OSUC 438293, OSUC 438294, OSUC 438295, OSUC 438296, OSUC 438297, OSUC 438298, OSUC 438299, OSUC 438300, OSUC 438301, OSUC 438311, OSUC 438312, OSUC 438313, OSUC 438314, OSUC 438315, OSUC 438316, OSUC 438317, OSUC 438318, OSUC 438319, OSUC 438320, OSUC 438321, OSUC 438322, OSUC 438324, OSUC 438325, OSUC 438326, OSUC 438327, OSUC 438328, OSUC 438329, OSUC 438330, OSUC 438331, OSUC 438332, OSUC 438333, OSUC 438334, OSUC 438335, OSUC 438336, OSUC 438337, OSUC 438338, OSUC 438339, OSUC 438340, OSUC 438341, OSUC 438343, OSUC 448574, OSUC 448575, OSUC 448576, OSUC 448577, OSUC 448578, OSUC 448579, OSUC 448580, OSUC 448581, OSUC 448582, OSUC 448583, OSUC 448584, OSUC 448585, OSUC 448586, OSUC 453952, OSUC 453953, OSUC 453954, OSUC 453955, OSUC 453956 (ANIC); OSUC 438345-438346 (MVMA); OSUC 438304-438310, 438323, 448587 (TDAH); OSUC 438302, 438344, 453957 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7861EE579D5ED8CE13A5CF43675CA444" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" type="comments">
<paragraph id="4110BF0ECB04C8EBD8C8072137C05444" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="635C97FAA46D9229BFB017B34F781857" pageId="218" pageNumber="219">
While 
<taxonomicName id="B6BF2039FBDA89746E0A54169E5709F8" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio tenuitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenuitatis">Oxyscelio tenuitatis</taxonomicName>
may be only a melanistic form of 
<taxonomicName id="38B131DCB1AE76CF7E8EB78BD397EA96" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio densitatis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="218" pageNumber="219" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="densitatis">Oxyscelio densitatis</taxonomicName>
, we are recognizing these are separate species because they do differ in minor but consistent ways.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>