<document id="A001601671A655F4121DA0B91022E81F" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.21515" ID-GBIF-Dataset="67f744eb-5776-4655-aef9-e007143a5945" ID-GBIF-Taxon="149667355" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-796-397" ID-ZBK="2942F10D21274D219C2E20CCB4DE5012" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:01387685-0D74-469F-BA86-71B07E377C5B" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-796-397" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 796" ModsDocTitle="Claviplatyshenryi, a new genus and species of Plataspidae from southern India (Hemiptera, Heteroptera)" checkinTime="1542332358273" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="edei, David &amp; indra, Zdenek" docDate="2018" docId="35FE512AFD97F0A879B65806A4F09254" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 796: 397-408" docOrigin="ZooKeys 796" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.21515" docTitle="Claviplatys henryi edei &amp; indra, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="01387685-0D74-469F-BA86-71B07E377C5B" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="397" masterDocId="FFC6FF8FFF86FFA1132CFFEE51183B5A" masterDocTitle="Claviplatyshenryi, a new genus and species of Plataspidae from southern India (Hemiptera, Heteroptera)" masterLastPageNumber="408" masterPageNumber="397" originalUpdateDomain="Boston" originalUpdateTime="1542332358273" originalUpdateUser="pensoft" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" updateTime="1643465133572" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="5BD27DFA8D961956AC3E1F7F9D17632C" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="D32CD639C108D8C697CAF24FFA516FDD">
<mods:title id="10B935ECB36353F69BA31FA9B9FBB135">Claviplatyshenryi, a new genus and species of Plataspidae from southern India (Hemiptera, Heteroptera)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A1A1C3C198AEF1391F2452AEDA3951B3" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B5A9985A163B035D2038061E02BFFA57">
<mods:roleTerm id="D639ED79BB5F53D4F80362DE4BD28823">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="A3C6480080062A7AC99CCD6EE9C8B1CA">edei, David</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="3D737F78A516839DC7596B2422F01BA1" type="personal">
<mods:role id="7A4BC97DAA5DAD8EF85D1A2574F2CDE3">
<mods:roleTerm id="2FABC87D4797A61959E4D254C4CB6151">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="67A9FC5AD7CEF2DC0D38E924CA7BF911">indra, Zdenek</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="A264D7AB698D6B6E79448D15E019A99E">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="40CF89EEFB48052FC67CE1045BD78AB8" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="1B24183C70453AD5EC168AB81F765858">
<mods:title id="7D480DC2A79557FD0D708B97BAA9DA04">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="42AED21E5BF82F0228DFF49D918C84A6">
<mods:date id="4F6F7DC2B7E1E034A468FC2B5E9A3528">2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="B7D72398F82E5C4ADF63949D48E47B07" type="volume">
<mods:number id="2B81A432D33C1FCCF6104814DF1E4B0F">796</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="58BB2A126ECEAA69A7464884F74F91CA" unit="page">
<mods:start id="10D1029AF7B76DFA7D8415A668D2FC10">397</mods:start>
<mods:end id="5586F3AC9BC8BA2086A10681E124C01C">408</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="BFD9C72CBECDAB6FA013D792DEC5C9F4">
<mods:url id="ABB0A2DFA07224AD8F34B86EE55175B0">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.21515</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="3456DEA5FEECC275754B693C64844DCF">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="A4AB51008E756C75F52E31E8C11FC1EC" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.21515</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="1A600EA90D13309CB39BD0810EA66FA5" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-796-397</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="CB10BCD3668476B5B0B197EBA7108DAC" type="ZBK">2942F10D21274D219C2E20CCB4DE5012</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="85756B6CCEA66238D3C49B34B882909E" type="ZooBank">2942F10D21274D219C2E20CCB4DE5012</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="35FE512AFD97F0A879B65806A4F09254" ID-GBIF-Taxon="149667355" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:01387685-0D74-469F-BA86-71B07E377C5B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/35FE512AFD97F0A879B65806A4F09254" lastPageNumber="397" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
<subSubSection id="E20B3ABE82DC9807394BF6E31A804DC9" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="B608D103E759727A1B3333806C9E3295" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
<taxonomicName id="2AC4E17B79E45B980A5A5798898F3BF9" LSID="http://zoobank.org/01387685-0D74-469F-BA86-71B07E377C5B" authority="Rédei &amp; Jindra, 2018" authorityName="Rédei &amp; Jindra" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Plataspidae" genus="Claviplatys" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Claviplatys henryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="henryi">Claviplatys henryi</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="71D753F1D47965D83170CDF63BB71FAB" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-4, 5-15, 16-20, 21-23
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2DFEA503FC997B7B0F90A26F934BA7FA" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" type="type material">
<paragraph id="79843DFB500EFBCD239A2887C2197F9D" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="27653C807F1543E5849448ACBEC24166" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
Holotype (Figs 1-2): ♂, India: Kerala, Pompa [= Pamba], Sabramila [= Sabarimala], 
<geoCoordinate id="DBD95747F36F5AF774B6EE1C85CBB22D" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="92" value="9.415">09°24.9'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="75A4A8B3A4702FB3A9B22656E6B99687" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="92" value="77.065">77°03.9'E</geoCoordinate>
, 3.v.2005, leg. M. Halada; mounted on card, intact, genitalia detached, preserved in plastic microvial with glycerol; deposited in ZJPC. Paratypes: South India: Kerala, Cardamom Hills, 50 km NW of Pathanamthitta, near Pambaiyar River, 
<geoCoordinate id="246FA377AB173549663295EF163E4493" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="9.416667">9°25'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="89C8E24D17B09E29A178AE6DC6A39375" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="77.083336">77°05'E</geoCoordinate>
, 6-9.v.1994, leg. Z. Kejval (1 ♀ ZJPC, 1 ♀ HNHM).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="32218F3816E6DC3C157B318E26508776" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="FF56ACD302FB7E5DDBCD934412BCAF6F" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BA82F8C1CDEC9E1B7CC2F289C3F23739" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
<taxonomicName id="FDE69240C7B648649B5AEBF2CE95240E" authority="Rédei &amp; Jindra, 2018" authorityName="Rédei &amp; Jindra" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Plataspidae" genus="Claviplatys" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Claviplatys henryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="henryi">Claviplatys henryi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., the single known species of the genus, can be recognized by the diagnostic characters provided for the genus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0841CE623B3D38B846B3BCF10158F62F" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" type="description">
<paragraph id="D61537D1937B25D02B0B6F4946AA1FD3" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B89EC9D4551B43BB7F94D1FB6A830263" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Male (Figs 1-2, 5-7, 10-20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C1DDB915C79BA5F5228699A11A8CACC5" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
Color. Dorsum and venter dull black, with ochraceous markings as follows: pair of longitudinal vittae submarginally along mesal margin of mandibular plates (indistinct around middle), and small spot between proximal extremities of above-mentioned vittae; pair of short, obliquely transverse streaks before mesal angles of eyes; proximomesal portion of ventral surface of clypeus; bucculae and surrounding areas between antennal insertions and basal neck-like portion of head ventrally; pair of small submedian spots on callar lobe of pronotum; pair of narrow submarginal vittae along lateral margin of pronotum, terminating slightly anteriad of humeral tubercle; undulating vitta connecting lateral extremities of anterior collar with humeral tubercles, following mesal margin of lateral explanate lobe of pronotum (indistinct around middle); pair of small sublateral spots on scutellum very close to anterior margin; narrow submarginal vitta around scutellum except extreme base; patch on metapleuron immediately anteriad of scent gland ostiole; distal (= lateral) portion of peritreme; small, rounded spot at posterolateral angle of metapleurite; dorsal laterotergites and adjacent lateral margins of ventral laterotergites of abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken id="0730E797C0FA43A27C1565EDC27CA682" originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
; pair of longitudinally elongate spots on each mediosternite of segments 
<normalizedToken id="189364D782160454F51D5126A122D474" originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
marginally (surrounding respective spiracles), and pair of smaller spots posteriad of the above ones on segments 
<normalizedToken id="51CA1C27BB07999B6B1BFA0CBEDEDDE4" originalValue="III–VI">III-VI</normalizedToken>
. Scape ochraceous, irregularly suffused with brown especially in distal half, pedicel, basi- and distiflagellum blackish brown; labrum ochraceous. Legs ochraceous, coxae with large dark brown patch on mesal surfaces; trochanters broadly suffused with dark brown distally, femora with several rounded brown patches on (morphological) anterior and posterior surfaces, with blackish brown longitudinal streak dorsoapically and black patches on anterior and posterior surfaces ventroapically, tibiae with few small, rounded, brown patches and longitudinal streak on nearly entire length of dorsal (furrowed) surface, tarsal segments suffused with brown apically.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="56E17A3789F98617B1DD706598C68245" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Integument and vestiture generally as in generic description. Sternite VI with pair of fringes of long setae arranged along curved line following posterior margin of segment; dorsum of mandibular plates irregularly rugose, pronotum and scutellum with fine, dense, superficial, inconspicuous punctation, abdominal ventrites finely longitudinally wrinkled.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3EB428E678F0D1DED46B89001BFF81A4" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Structure.Head 1.85 times as broad as medial length (from base to imaginary line connecting tips of mandibular plates), 1.5 times as broad as interocular distance; mandibular plates (Fig. 5: mdp) produced anteriad as pair of subtriangular, apically narrowly rounded plates, mesal margins almost straight; distance between ocellus and ipsilateral eye 1.2 times as long as interocellar distance. Antenna (Figs 6-7): distipedicellite approx. four times longer than greatest width, 1.75 and 1.65 times longer than basipedicellite and distipedicellite, respectively. Labium reaching base of abdominal sternite V.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="87D0130CCFEF7B8B25EB36607F94B715" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Thorax and pregenital abdomen as described for genus. Prothorax 2.2 times, scutellum 1.5 times broader than median lengths of respective sclerites.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="ED12B92ABDDAEDB38F17F8F29B6B5A10" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">External male genitalia.Genital capsule (Figs 10-11) broadly oval, posterior margin broadly rounded, slightly protruded posteriorly in mesal third, protruded part with tuft of several long, erect setae; lateral margin with pair of small, compact, brush-like clusters of strong, stiff setae subapically; morphological posterior surface weakly concave, infolding of dorsal rim broad, broadly and deeply impressed medially immediately dorsad of posterior aperture; infolding of ventral rim relatively broad; posterior aperture small, dorsal sinus broadly rounded, completely occupied by tergite X (Figure 11: t10); cuplike sclerite (Figure 11: cs) completely fused with infolding of ventral rim of genital capsule without trace of fusion line, provided with pair of thick suspensory apodemes (Figure 11: sus). Paramere (Figs 12-15) sickle-shaped, with short crown comprising broad stem and elongate, narrow apical process. Phallus (Figs 16-20): basal plates (Figure 17: bp), robust, fused with support bridge complex (Figure 17: sbc) by leaving pair of window-like interspaces open at two sides of median portion of support bridge complex, support bridge complex with broad ponticulus transversalis (Figure 17: pt); phallotheca (Figs 16-17: phth) elongate, greatly membranous, with protruding, diverticulum-like hinge (Figure 16: hi) proximoventrally, with pair of dorsolateral and single ventromedian sclerite distally, each dorsolateral sclerite with blunt, rounded, posteriorly directed tubercle at proximal part; conjunctiva elongate, wall of proximal portion with 4 pairs of sclerites: pair of elongate sclerites submedially, and three pairs of sclerites (derivatives of conjunctival processes?) laterally, apparently forming complex articulation for supporting proximal part of conjunctiva; distal portion with single elongate, membranous, tubular process dorsally (Figs 16, 19, 20: cp) provided with pair of very short, rounded, membranous diverticula subapically on posterior surface; aedeagus (Figs 16, 19, 20: aed) indistinctly demarcated from conjunctiva, weakly sclerotized, somewhat dorsoventrally compressed, produced into pair of flattened, fin-like expansions laterally, abruptly narrowed around middle, gradually tapering towards apex; endophallic reservoir elongate, endophallic duct thin, tubular, rather weakly sclerotized, gradually tapering to distal third, then desclerotized and closely surrounded by fine, transparent outer wall of aedeagus, forming thin, flexible tube.</paragraph>
<caption id="A335D4D2E68B436212C5B293DD3F581B" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
<paragraph id="B7CF36498A1725B65907F21CFC224D64" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
Figures 16-20. 
<taxonomicName id="6AD08A494ADF6FCF814B879EDF4D2C4E" authority="Rédei &amp; Jindra, 2018" authorityName="Rédei &amp; Jindra" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Plataspidae" genus="Claviplatys" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Claviplatys henryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="henryi">Claviplatys henryi</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n., holotype. 16 phallus, lateral view 17 same, dorsal view (conjunctival process omitted, aedeagus not shown) 18 same, ventral view (articulatory apparatus and aedeagus not shown) 19 conjunctival process and aedeagus, morphological dorsal view 20 same, morphological ventral view. Arrows in Fig. 16 show aspect of Figs 19 and 20. Abbreviations: aed = aedeagus; bp = basal plates; cap = capitate process; con = conjunctiva; cp = conjunctival process; dej = ductus ejaculatorius; ds = ductus seminis; end = endophallic duct; erp = erection fluid pump; hi = hinge; phth = phallotheca; pt = ponticulus transversalis; res = endophallic reservoir; sbc = support bridge complex. Scale bars in mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="6F3520C036BD442504767D274B2E0A9F" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Female (Figs 2-3, 21-23). Color, integument, and vestiture as in male. Terminalia brown, with long hairs on laterotergite IX and tergite X forming conspicuous, brush-like tuft around midline.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="881B9D1CF40249257A4CDEAB0389412E" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Structure.Head 2.3 times as broad as medial length, 1.5 times as broad as interocular distance; anterior outline evenly rounded, mandibular plates narrowly overlapping anteriad of apex of clypeus; distance between ocellus and ipsilateral eye subequal to interocellar distance. Antenna (Figs 8-9): distipedicellite 5.5 times longer than greatest width, 1.35-1.5 and 1.2-1.25 times longer than basipedicellite and distipedicellite, respectively. Labium reaching base of abdominal sternite V.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5D5BB8394792538A81D736DD37166212" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Thorax and pregenital abdomen as in male. Prothorax 2.2 times, scutellum 1.4 times broader than median lengths of respective sclerites.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2F94A88EA93581803A8A0760619D62D2" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">External female genitalia (Figs 21-23). Laterotergites VIII (Figure 22: lt8) not separated along midline, forming broad transverse plate posteriad of laterotergites IX; valvifers VIII (Figure 22: vf8) relatively short, subequal in length along midline as laterotergites IX (Figure 22: lt9); valvifers IX (Figure 22: vf9) obliquely elongate, with pair of shorter, finger-like, oblique processes mesally; gynatrium (Figure 23: gy) simple, saccular, lacking distinct pouches, with broad fold immediately proximad of orifice of spermatheca, contralateral ring sclerites fused along midline into single clearly sclerotized and easily traceable U-shaped sclerite (Figure 23: rs); with pair of small, rounded sclerites at two sides of spermathecal orifice; spermathecal duct simple, thin, intermediate part of spermatheca relatively short, apical receptacle globose.</paragraph>
<caption id="3EBB6152EEB5A5D732A0A675CE1118C9" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
<paragraph id="BBBDFD630C09C31BB55FFC559B837BD0" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">
Figures 21-23. 
<taxonomicName id="A5A7EB4F7342B60E7161822A164C20C4" authority="Rédei &amp; Jindra, 2018" authorityName="Rédei &amp; Jindra" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Plataspidae" genus="Claviplatys" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Claviplatys henryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="henryi">Claviplatys henryi</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n., external female genitalia. 21 terminalia, ventral view 22 same, dissected, right valvifer VIII removed (drawn after macerated preparatum) 23 gynatrium and spermatheca, dorsal view after removal of abdominal dorsum. Abbreviations: ga = gonangulum; gy = gynatrium; lt8, lt9 = laterotergites VIII and IX; rs = ring sclerite; t9, t10 = tergites IX and X; va9 = valvula IX; vf8, vf9 = valvifers VIII and IX. Scale bars in mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E59C398CD87B08756913A97F86162D8A" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" type="description">
<paragraph id="C90523077A7C7E2E8F374992102F3E3A" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Measurements</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7897A14E5F7764506453E281F70AB3E7" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">(in mm). Male (n = 1) / female (n = 2): Body length measured along meson from imaginary line connecting tips of mandibular plates to apex of scutellum (♂) 11.6, to apex of genital capsule in dorsal view (♂) 12.2, from apex of head to apex of scutellum (♀) 10.0-10.1; length of head measured along meson from base to imaginary line connecting tips of mandibular plates (♂) 3.00, from base to anterior margin (♀) 2.06-2.08, greatest width across eyes 5.55 / 4.75-4.80, interocular distance 3.75 / 3.20-3.23, interocellar distance 1.05 / 1.00-1.02, distance between mesal margin of eye and ipsilateral ocellus 1.25 / 1.00-1.00; length of scape 1.13 / 0.93-0.95, greatest width 0.50 / 0.26-0.28, length of basipedicellite 0.18 / 0.09-0.10, greatest width 0.27 / 0.15-0.16, length of distipedicellite 2.00 / 1.20-1.20, greatest width 0.50 / 0.20-0.22, length of basiflagellum 1.13 / 0.80-0.90, greatest width 0.21 / 0.15-0.16, length of distiflagellum 1.20 / 0.96-1.00, greatest width 0.20 / 0.16-0.17; length of labiomere I 1.10 / 0.98-1.00, II 2.00 / 1.74-1.85, III 1.48 / 1.32-1.40, IV 1.13 / 1.10-1.15; length of pronotum along meson 3.62 / 3.15-3.17, greatest width 7.94 / 7.06-7.08, length of scutellum along meson 5.73 / 5.36-5.54, greatest width 8.51 / 7.50-7.56.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9F0CD38FCD90CCA4BDB2377A24A196DC" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="77AF94D2D5F8CF67745257620BFFD729" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CBAB151BB70054E40F548CEF288CAA4E" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Patronymic, dedicated to Thomas J. Henry.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0BCD4CBA1EEBB76F1763C96332A7E9C7" pageId="0" pageNumber="397" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="AFD41ABD08841EC55C217AF5E27A7383" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="44421F7E2A79B5D8B4A4FFCF5A19CD38" pageId="0" pageNumber="397">Known only from the Malabar Subregion of southern India. The holotype and the two paratypes were collected at two localities around Pamba station below Sabarimala, a Hindu pilgrimage center, in Pathanamthitta District, Kerala State, separated by a distance of ca. 2 km.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>