<document id="04B4616E8B806ADFA49899F1160879CA" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.90.8059" ID-GBIF-Dataset="398ce969-8cc9-4c63-97d2-f556c96c2236" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154365962" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-0743-2-95" ID-ZBK="F6172163D67C480494B24753B9677E6D" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A76BA32A-4BC1-424E-9359-9696A281342F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1860-0743-2-95" ModsDocOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 90 (2)" ModsDocTitle="Elasmopusyucalpeten sp. n. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Maeridae) from the northern Yucatan coast, with a key for the genus in the Gulf of Mexico and biogeographic comments" checkinTime="1552154808801" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Paz-Rios, Carlos E. &amp; Ardisson, Pedro-Luis" docDate="2014" docId="41760F035A446AA66B3EA9F42D6715AC" docLanguage="en" docName="ZoosystEvol 90(2): 95-104" docOrigin="Zoosystematics and Evolution 90 (2)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.90.8059" docTitle="Elasmopus yucalpeten Paz-Rios &amp; Ardisson, 2014, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="A76BA32A-4BC1-424E-9359-9696A281342F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="96" masterDocId="FF85C506542CB4268151FF862B404039" masterDocTitle="Elasmopusyucalpeten sp. n. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Maeridae) from the northern Yucatan coast, with a key for the genus in the Gulf of Mexico and biogeographic comments" masterLastPageNumber="104" masterPageNumber="95" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" updateTime="1643680876299" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="86CF61F5AFF438F82D164A07EC6719A4" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="945072B92DCA09E0A68C9101760EFD17">
<mods:title id="EB97960DD0D1D1C3C0BDB66C21EB2519">Elasmopusyucalpeten sp. n. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Maeridae) from the northern Yucatan coast, with a key for the genus in the Gulf of Mexico and biogeographic comments</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="384A4A227420867D3F2225B1F808750C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9DA23C520EFDB098C11B0A577A581496">
<mods:roleTerm id="E6A1D1F90A0D7B5922016210874DB448">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="8FDCCEE861662C73B5D4BFDAF82E8E4F">Paz-Rios, Carlos E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="5D599F17C0BCDF289B4E0C23D4F7F410" type="personal">
<mods:role id="904C972B60B02A60F4C8A4BBEA6A4FCE">
<mods:roleTerm id="388C92309191A1C135205B22ED83D98A">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5212346E06D3885593D1189204A53234">Ardisson, Pedro-Luis</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="509D3FC27C9C705A48E1BD9802AF037E">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="BB70A0D721F4F9E8031216B439410475" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="431435928C8A68040CC5E298BABFC8A7">
<mods:title id="E7DC506464AE2D48EAEC02DAC12B576E">Zoosystematics and Evolution</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="682315D579B29E0346564E2DEE871800">
<mods:date id="8095820386D810CAB6D34C04CE10D02E">2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="DD1F2636E7A3CD8CBA08DAD2EEC461A0" type="volume">
<mods:number id="9F118CD6D37D88DF9D462D604869D11F">90</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="DD3767FACF96456169489C1654513151" type="issue">
<mods:number id="48A5FBA3F6DA3A62B16465DD48FA3D14">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="7689F4755C54E94ED2B1103059934D6D" unit="page">
<mods:start id="215F3E6B616E29B8B167CB929390AA3E">95</mods:start>
<mods:end id="548B2E861E4A7C509F3780EAC19CEEA3">104</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="F78937F895F46078FFC28DDC2B3B42EB">
<mods:url id="57C5D22403C1E5E752F00559F02C6FBF">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.90.8059</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="F413CDFD3904F4356D574B2CA4D96665">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="87AC8B52784EA00B5BE3812CB00B88D4" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zse.90.8059</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="AC0DB2A8E5FD0554EA1320494C7E9CF6" type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-0743-2-95</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="94CCDAD053B4C68FAF4E52BD55C87BDD" type="ZBK">F6172163D67C480494B24753B9677E6D</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8DB6E128507FB5ACDE3FC5D6EDB0F1D2" type="ZooBank">F6172163D67C480494B24753B9677E6D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="41760F035A446AA66B3EA9F42D6715AC" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154365962" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A76BA32A-4BC1-424E-9359-9696A281342F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/41760F035A446AA66B3EA9F42D6715AC" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">
<subSubSection id="3106AE54ABC5C2584E6AEEE24781092D" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="2FE6F1EA9CE381731B2E35A3DB2DA7EE" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">
<taxonomicName id="E365DF830E858EC5E0DF28C0A21C6156" LSID="http://zoobank.org/A76BA32A-4BC1-424E-9359-9696A281342F" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus yucalpeten" order="Amphipoda" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yucalpeten">Elasmopus yucalpeten</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="1F347603975DED782D2E0A2AF95E652B" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1, 2, 3, 4
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="50A5210A6CDD2253B10C17E2D33F76F2" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" type="type material">
<paragraph id="F76096709BF42445A610C91531E06AAD" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7A77C67CEAFA32B18E9609DCC06F60FE" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">
Holotype male (dissected and drawn), 6.6 mm, Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico, 
<geoCoordinate id="9459818C393721DD02FC74D98655273E" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="21.277782">21°16.667'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="733C396D659E2F7CA756F78FECAC9F05" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-89.70002">89°42.001'W</geoCoordinate>
, 24 August 2010, on wood dock with algae, coll. C. E. 
<normalizedToken id="2CEF6108D4940C65DBBF4C140C73EF2C" originalValue="Paz-Ríos">Paz-Rios</normalizedToken>
, CYMX-1-EY. Paratypes: one female (dissected and drawn), 6.2 mm, data as for holotype, CYMX-2-EY; four males, four females, data as for holotype, ECOSUR0164; six males, Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico, 
<geoCoordinate id="781EC5428E20D3BA6726917F625AD3D8" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="21.277782">21°16.667'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="B81631443CC987436D3D59385184065A" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-89.70002">89°42.001'W</geoCoordinate>
, 26 June 2012, on rock with algae, intertidal, coll. C. E. 
<normalizedToken id="137EEDB343FFC1D19EDD6CD73D9F2787" originalValue="Paz-Ríos">Paz-Rios</normalizedToken>
, CYMX-3-EY.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0FB565A225F132E019C4530C9AB46847" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" type="other material">
<paragraph id="E83D53D508EC034B33A82306486634E6" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Other material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EEC565DB6DBABDD7F0984F55E8CE355B" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Twenty-six males, 49 females, seven unsexed, data as for holotype, CYMX-4-EY.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D9CA03CCBADDCCF66B01BC9379332A2B" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" type="type locality">
<paragraph id="DAFEC71F7F157E24FCA1BE60C6993A91" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2E2DC82D5D5DA2501C6933F84F61FBA2" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="5D6C93272F7758F8C83E46C81A05C4A5" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="379F89832C151AF917882FF4EDE7059A" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B655B4DB1D8B5A14D396A9CB9B2F94FD" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Body dorsally setose. Antenna 1 long. Accessory flagellum two-articulated. Eyes large, ovate. Group of five long robust setae on basis anterodistal margin of gnathopod 2. Medial concave portion on palm of gnathopod 2 propodus. Long setae on basis posterior margin of pereopods 5-7. One basofacial robust seta on peduncle of uropod 1. Telson entire.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4FF9503FF6214A2632D9F23D3EC529B3" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="0" pageNumber="95" type="description">
<paragraph id="73518CFE4EEDA91413EF8334AF587636" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="295857E19E4B9A6D5586E5EE807F99E9" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">Based on holotype male, 6.6 mm (CYMX-1-EY). Body with groups of one to three setae on head, pereon and pleon. Eyes large, ovate. Lateral cephalic lobe broad, rounded, anteroventral margin with notch/slit. Antenna 1 reaching beyond half of body, longer than antenna 2 (about 2 times the antenna 2 length); peduncular article 1 subequal in length to article 2, without robust setae on posterior margin; article 2 longer than article 3 (about 1.4 times the article 3 length); flagellum with 27 articles; accessory flagellum short, two-articulated, last article minute. Antenna 2 peduncular article 2 gland cone reaching beyond end of peduncular article 3; article 4 subequal in length to article 5, flagellum with nine articles. Lower lip outer lobes with single pair of ducts, mandibular lobes apically acute. Mandible molar well developed, triturative, with plumose seta; accessory setal row with four slender blades; palp three-articulated; article 1 about as long as broad, shorter than article 2; article 2 slightly longer than article 3, with few long slender setae; article 3 longer than article 1, weakly falcate, long (about 3.2 times as long as broad), with comb of short robust setae along anterodistal margin and three slender apical setae. Maxilla 1 inner fig with two apical plumose setae; outer fig with seven serrate robust setae; palp two-articulated, apical part of palp article 2 with seven robust and two slender setae. Maxilla 2 inner fig with five plumose setae and a few slender seate. Maxilliped inner fig with two slender and six plumose setae on apical part; outer fig bearing ten medial/apical robust setae and six apical plumose setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1A6723DA32E3EBB9280D464548E5DDAB" lastPageId="1" lastPageNumber="96" pageId="0" pageNumber="95">
Gnathopod 1 subchelate; coxa anterior margin slightly concave, anteroventral corner produced and rounded, ventral margin with few long setae; basis posterior margin with four long setae; merus with posterodistal tooth; carpus about 1.5 times as long as broad, subequal in length to propodus, heavily setose, with rows of long setae covering the surface and posterior margin; propodus with few rows of long marginal and superficial setae, palm acute, convex, minutely serrate, defined by two posterodistal robust setae; dactylus with one seta on anterior margin. Gnathopod 2 subchelate; coxa subrectangular, longer than broad, ventral margin with some long setae; basis stout, posterior margin with four long setae, anterodistal margin with group of five long robust setae; merus anteroventral corner produced and subquadrate; carpus posteroventral corner produced, rounded and setose; propodus expanded, anterior and posterior margin with rows and clusters respectively of long slender setae; palm about half length of propodus, acute, sculptured, with palm distal shelf subrectangular bearing group of four robust setae, distal subquadrate tooth, medial concave portion for reception of the dactylar tip, defined by 
<pageBreakToken id="73B3FF264044568B7641AAED1896F098" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" start="start">proximal</pageBreakToken>
tooth; dactylus falcate, with one seta on anterior margin. Pereopod 3 similar to pereopod 4, except by the coxa subrectangular. Pereopod 4 coxa longer than broad, posterior margin concave, posteroventral corner produced and rounded, ventral margin with long setae; basis posterior margin with three long setae; propodus with a row of seven robust setae on posterior margin; dactylus short (about 0.5 times the propodus length), dactylar unguis simple. Pereopod 5-6 coxa broader than long, excavate ventrally, anteroventral lobe produced and rounded, with three posteroventral robust setae; basis posterior margin slightly expanded convex, weakly crenulate, with many long stiff slender setae; ischium, merus, carpus and propodus with many long, slender and robust setae along margins; dactylus short (about 0.3 times the propodus length), dactylar unguis simple. Pereopod 7 similar to pereopod 5-6, except by the coxa with ventral lobe produced and rounded, with one posterior robust seta.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6A2277E78A169532C187F7A34C541A00" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">Epimera 1-3 posteroventral corner notched with small subacute tooth; ventral margin with long slender and robust setae. Urosomite 1-3 smooth, without carina. Uropod 1 peduncle with two basofacial robust setae, five robust setae on each of the outer and inner margins, and two long robust setae distally; inner ramus about as long as peduncle. Uropod 2 peduncle with two and three robust setae on outer and inner margin, respectively; inner ramus longer than peduncle (about 1.2 times the peduncle length). Uropod 3 peduncle with two distal robust setae; inner ramus about as long as peduncle; outer ramus slightly longer than inner ramus with three clusters of long setae. Telson entire with posterior margin scalloped, two unequal stout robust setae and two or three plumose setae on each side.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5772152D7ADD5F320F201E562B05158E" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">Female (sexually dimorphic characters); based on paratype female, 6.2 mm (CYMX-2-EY). Gnathopod 1 subchelate; coxa ventral margin with short setae; basis medial surface with two long setae, posterior margin with seven long setae; carpus heavily setose, with long setae covering the surface and posterior margin; propodus with marginal and superficial setae, palm acute, convex, minutely serrate, with ten submarginal robust setae, defined by two posterodistal robust setae, followed by two submarginal robust setae; dactylus not reaching the end of palm, with one seta on anterior margin. Gnathopod 2 subchelate; coxa ventral margin with some long setae; basis posterior margin with five long setae, anterodistal margin with one long robust setae; carpus heavily setose, with long setae covering the posterior margin; propodus anterior and posterior margin with rows and clusters respectively of long slender setae, about twice length of carpus, palm acute, nearly straight, smooth, with 15 submarginal robust setae, defined by three posterodistal robust setae; dactylus falcate, not reaching the end of palm, with one seta on anterior margin. Pereopod 5-7 with few long stiff slender setae. Uropod 1 peduncle with one basofacial robust seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AEB16976B350A265C327243FFA388EAC" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">Variations; based on paratypes (CYMX-2-EY, CYMX-3-EY, ECOSUR0164). A group of six robust setae (instead of five) on the anterodistal margin of the basis of gnathopod 2 was observed in two of the ten male specimens. Male and female specimens were also examined for confirming the presence of two robust setae on peduncle of uropod 1, but there was not consistency; the rule was to present one basofacial robust seta.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="450F03A35F458DD28674DFEA76B6700F" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="ABFDC35CDD31433D943E953EDE327C83" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="99A955EF853D44620CA6D46EF701E5E1" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">The species name is derived from the type locality of the new species. Yucalpeten in the Mayan language means &quot;land of the deer&quot;.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9CC3E09B9CEDF0EF290240E6C2EFD73F" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="98A21D59C459AA296F0E2522CA232755" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C6B26F0C6A0271493FE5F8872B1BA80E" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">So far only known from the type locality, Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3A3AB2341233158B5FD13C21DCB8C854" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" type="habitat">
<paragraph id="237ECF097EF846F753F25363CF617D14" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4F25520D05AB22D2B2B53DCFDA37A667" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
Marine epibenthic, in shallow water (≤1 m) on rocks and wood dock with the brown algae 
<taxonomicName id="9F0190189F140ED1C424569CA16265FF" class="Florideophyceae" family="Gracilariaceae" genus="Gracilaria" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Gracilaria" order="Gigartinales" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Rhodophyta" rank="genus">Gracilaria</taxonomicName>
sp.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="6A528A9241164A23AFC45A1AD3B2FD88" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="78AEE2EBF59A3568965879B683ED7F40" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E3DE16539EF515F807BFAA7766CB0004" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
The presence of one or two basofacial robust setae on uropod 1 peduncle as a characteristic for species category identification may have been overlooked by earlier studies (
<bibRefCitation id="4F6D6E8DE92A13DE0086BADD7B9C7191" author="Hughes, LE" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Natural History" pageId="3" pageNumber="98" pagination="579 - 628" title="The genus Elasmopus (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Maeridae) in Australian waters." url="10.1080/00222933.2010.534825" volume="45" year="2011">Hughes and Lowry 2011</bibRefCitation>
); these same authors also have pointed out that, the presence of two basofacial robust setae on uropod 1 peduncle may be result of a newly-forming moult stage, such as the present case, where only the holotype male bears those spines. 
<taxonomicName id="9484DE5D2A914F62550267E9BB12EEE8" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus yucalpeten" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yucalpeten">Elasmopus yucalpeten</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is distinguished from the rest of the species in the genus by having the antenna 1 accessory flagellum two-articulated, mandibular palp article 3 weakly falcate, gnathopod 2 basis anterodistal margin with group of long robust setae, gnathopod 2 propodus palm with medial concave portion, uropod 1 peduncle with one or rarely two basofacial robust setae, and telson entire. An entire telson is only known in four other species of the genus, 
<taxonomicName id="72514F8B24A57DBB25D03C5728455F20" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus integer" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="integer">Elasmopus integer</taxonomicName>
Myers, 1989, 
<taxonomicName id="D57FB6AD38F9566E4F13CC2C26ACB80D" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus pseudinteger" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pseudinteger">Elasmopus pseudinteger</taxonomicName>
Appadoo &amp; Myers, 2003, 
<taxonomicName id="F351E3288434D21B40FE00D8B103C086" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus takamotus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="takamotus">Elasmopus takamotus</taxonomicName>
Myers, 1986, and 
<taxonomicName id="1D6388E5CEFCF443EDA1821A8D7CB7DF" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus visakhapatnamensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="visakhapatnamensis">Elasmopus visakhapatnamensis</taxonomicName>
Kanakadurga, Rao &amp; Shyamasundari, 1981. Of these species, 
<taxonomicName id="074D86030CEB551C6E8D46D96E8DEFC5" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus yucalpeten" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yucalpeten">Elasmopus yucalpeten</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is closely related to 
<taxonomicName id="068ACFDFC4F5F3EE3735E3DF37B5AD33" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus integer" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="integer">Elasmopus integer</taxonomicName>
from Bora Bora, South Pacific, 
<taxonomicName id="EB843E67F241F91152FFAF5AD537D773" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus pseudinteger" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pseudinteger">Elasmopus pseudinteger</taxonomicName>
from Mauritius, Indian Ocean, and 
<taxonomicName id="52E4ACCD2C794E776E08103B55C23C3D" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus visakhapatnamensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="visakhapatnamensis">Elasmopus visakhapatnamensis</taxonomicName>
from Visakhapatnam, Indian Ocean. It is distinguished from 
<taxonomicName id="8E052686268B35C9A79C906135166FE1" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus integer" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="integer">Elasmopus integer</taxonomicName>
by the eyes ovate; mandibular palp article 3 weakly falcate; gnathopod 2 propodus palm with medial concave portion; pereopod 5-7 basis more setose; and epimera 2-3 posteroventral corner notched with small subacute tooth. It is distinguished from 
<taxonomicName id="81A8179BD2E143216D6B88A00693908D" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus pseudinteger" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pseudinteger">Elasmopus pseudinteger</taxonomicName>
by the two-articulated accessory flagellum; the more setose mandibular palp article 2; the long slender setae along the anterior and posterior margin of the gnathopod 2 propodus; the entire, crenulate and more setose margin of the pereopod 5-6 basis; the margin evenly convex of the epimeron 3 with the posteroventral corner notched and a small subacute tooth; the presence of one basofacial robust setae on the uropod 1 peduncle; and a telson with a scalloped posterior margin. Finally, it is distinguished from 
<taxonomicName id="19D8B759BC0A634CDE5F7D94EEC9739F" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus visakhapatnamensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="visakhapatnamensis">Elasmopus visakhapatnamensis</taxonomicName>
by the following characteristics: mandibular palp article 3 weakly falcate; gnathopod 2 propodus palm with medial concave portion and proximal tooth; epimeron 1-3 margin evenly convex with posteroventral corner notched, having a small subacute tooth; and uropod 3 outer ramus longer than inner ramus.
</paragraph>
<caption id="31FF244860DCD4A9743C844F9AEB0410" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
<paragraph id="E21964CADE2F7E0C73C7F65D4D1F307C" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName id="810DCDB4603DFB9DE60D26A5607E819A" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus yucalpeten" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yucalpeten">Elasmopus yucalpeten</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, 6.6 mm, CYMX-1-EY; Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico. Scale bar for H represents 1 mm; scale bars for G1 and G2 represent 0.3 mm; scale bars for AF and T represent 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="A6FAC8457847905A07CDA9373FD2D642" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
<paragraph id="D2B4DD4896FD2B83DC4F787995AE4B0B" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName id="7E2C08420E19096FE125528A97590A3E" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus yucalpeten" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yucalpeten">Elasmopus yucalpeten</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, 6.6 mm, CYMX-1-EY; Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico. Scale bars represent 0.1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="7E45E99F1FD8E498CBC26391B16283DA" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
<paragraph id="6CE8811016ADC402D55321F87E8742DF" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName id="1EE132E027445D143EE0555AE92EA51A" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus yucalpeten" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yucalpeten">Elasmopus yucalpeten</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, 6.6 mm, CYMX-1-EY; Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico. Scale bars represent 0.3 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="623815A67B81A1DF744DF015F6310823" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
<paragraph id="C976D27EF14F38758EF70EBAB6347433" pageId="1" pageNumber="96">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="624A7B81C984A6BC382B455C07156C01" class="Malacostraca" family="Maeridae" genus="Elasmopus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elasmopus yucalpeten" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="96" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yucalpeten">Elasmopus yucalpeten</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male, 6.6 mm, CYMX-1-EY; paratype female, 6.2 mm, CYMX-2-EY; Yucalpeten harbor, Yucatan, Mexico. Scale bars represent 0.3 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>