<document id="959CC7CBC8B6B24961290A91D644BD20" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="587115f4-9410-4574-9f17-f0c9296f0447" ModsDocID="5959" checkinTime="1243376585186" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1949" docId="41C5D26023A46E81498D547E59B72520" docLanguage="en" docName="5959" docOrigin="Annals and Magazine of Natural History 2" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5959/5959.pdf" docTitle="Camponotus (Tanaemyrmex) gerberti Donisthorpe, 1949, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="272" masterDocId="A3F0C6F750B9C23088FB938E11D20C02" masterDocTitle="A new Camponotus from Madagascar and a small collection of ants from Mauritius." masterLastPageNumber="275" masterPageNumber="271" pageNumber="271" updateTime="1569525771751" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="7282848D3D88CBBE6A96AAF0FCDC10A4" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="592AFED5EA7B6DB85B1C1DC8181AB776">
<mods:title id="8C872953F8AD17FEE34F587E0929F093">A new Camponotus from Madagascar and a small collection of ants from Mauritius.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="66F103966C43C90F3C292BED244764CF" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F76E75FD8F76795A91499170BCE58DB4">
<mods:roleTerm id="FAAFAA1D66130234C1B3CB37EFCB0F51">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="766C4523C3B4474BA23260CEE6657D00">Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="F234050645411277D049AC5E0155498A">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="F13D7D3460660796E1F3211D0A99051D" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="924BBCCF930010921E8D0BDB74B4B803">
<mods:title id="CC34F97123FDB7C0352EBEE4E6E45058">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="292AC67E4862EF6B76557D605D67311A">
<mods:date id="5717A7854FA93B189938B2FB3C0C2DE1">1949</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="692E1CB02938CED90E886590709E929B" type="volume">
<mods:number id="D9F6D6CAFA2743AC073FC93B10035408">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="11AA2010540E7DE0493A57ABA97C8228" unit="page">
<mods:start id="D568ED69BE62ABF16B81D2FF10852185">271</mods:start>
<mods:end id="22E07966918080204CA71A6777FB579A">275</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="B4781866E93F122C3F91DA2322F48DF9">
<mods:url id="5A08B815F6F4A47725B762EC3B8FEDED">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5959/5959.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="311116C879B82BB0F187E2A618B281C1">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="22803AF9C40F91FBCF5217EA87819B6C" type="HNS-PUB">5959</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="41C5D26023A46E81498D547E59B72520" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:41C5D26023A46E81498D547E59B72520" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/41C5D26023A46E81498D547E59B72520">
<subSubSection id="E3C2D210BAA97F7AFAEC82FE87780DBA" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="387281BD89ADD7ABDE1804AA42C1C7DD" pageNumber="271">
No. 123. 
<taxonomicName id="4F6349399BCFD24CEADECAC5B2447341" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:135414" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Camponotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Camponotus (Tanaemyrmex) gerberti Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Camponotus (Tanaemyrmex) gerberti Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="271" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gerberti" subGenus="Tanaemyrmex">Camponotus (Tanaemyrmex) gerberti</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="13CAC2AABEE9A7F5374FBB8DF86A5D96" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="80FEBDD83731F771D2AA5DB9D235A672" type="description">
<paragraph id="528A42616618FAF3D7E49BCB8DCD51AD" pageNumber="271">[[ soldier ]]. Very pale dirty yellow, head reddish yellow, mandibles dark red, teeth, scapes, anterior border of clypeus, and extreme anterior angles of cheeks black, clothed with very sparse outstanding longer and shorter yellow hairs and some fine very short decumbent yellow hairs. Sculpture consisting of very fine reticulations, a little stronger on head.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FF86CD08DEF8B90CC0D6EE090D5FD3CB" lastPageNumber="272" pageNumber="271">Head large, triangular, considerably broader behind than in front, broadest a little before posterior angles, which are rounded and prominent, posterior border excised, slightly sinuate on each side; mandibles massive, strongly punctured and with transverse ridges, masticatory border armed with six large strong teeth, the apical one being the longest, curved and sharp, the next two longer and sharper than the last three; clypeus large, somewhat flat, carinate and slightly convex on disc, anterior border considerably produced in middle where it is somewhat crenulate, and five large punctures are present along the edge, and smaller punctures, rather wide apart, are scattered over the rest of the surface, posterior border excised in middle; frontal area very faintly defined; frontal carinas rather long, raised, with sharp edges, the rims or edges enclosing the antennal sockets are considerably raised and prominent; a very fine narrow longitudinal ridge takes the place of the frontal furrow and extends between the frontal carinae as far back as their extreme edges; eyes large, broad oval, rather flat, are situated rather high up before the middle of the sides of the head; antenna 12 - jointcd, scape long, thickened at apex, extending beyond the posterior border of head funiculus with all the joints elongate, first slightly shorter than the others, last joint long and pointed. Thorax longer than broad, broadest behind centre of sides of pronotum, somewhat slender behind; pronotum ample. convex, with a short neck, sides margined, considerably widened afterneck, posterior border semicircular; sutures between pro- and mesonotum, and meso- and epinotum fine but distinct; mesonotum longer than broad, shorter than pronotum, somewhat flat on disc, sides rather straight, epinotum longer than mesonotum, sides rather straight, angle between dorsal surface and declivity not marked, dorsal surface longer than declivity. Scale of petiole rather thick at base, anterior surface slightly convex, posterior surface slightly concave, upper surface narrow and forming a rather sharp, ridge; gaster oval, not very voluminous, pointed at apex. Legs fairly long; tibiae prismatic. Long. 18 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="75DCF4468CB75EF0179438B9C0810F46" pageNumber="272">[[ worker ]] Of the same pale colour as the [[ soldier ]]. but only the extreme anterior angle of clypens and cheeks blackish; the mandibles are pale yellow with the teeth red. The sculpture and hairs are similar.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CE0A968AC847C22117C3A23B7A711E74" pageNumber="272">Head long, narrow, broader in front than behind, broadest a little in front of sides of head, narrowed, rather sharply behind eyes to base; teeth to mandibles somewhat more slender and sharper, carinae on clypeus a little more pronounced; eyes more prominent. Thorax narrow and slender; pronotum more narrowed to apex. Scale of petiole of similar shape, but a little narrower; gaster and-legs of similar shape. Long. 10 - 12 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="65E48CC513C6856DBD5F363A2ED5AD2A" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="B471F76E7D38F3AB21476E3513DD0B6E" pageNumber="272">Described from eight soldiers and seven workers.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F06CE8F21140146253C68184B470437F" pageNumber="272">
These ants were found by M. Mamet in an old collection of insects at the College of Agriculture, Mauritius. 
<materialsCitation id="B4D269DBE72805A98BE51AFC1038A781" collectingDate="1917" collectorName="S. Geberti" country="Madagascar" location="Sainte Marie Island" specimenImageUri="antbase:CASENT0102309">
They were collected by 
<collectorName id="F4B2B66B037A58685676FCA119319340">S. Geberti</collectorName>
in 
<collectingDate id="4041FB81BCA43E9CEFA843043B4B5176">1917</collectingDate>
, on 
<location id="964EA4EC9A3890A3D6E8A1228B15A850" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:41C5D26023A46E81498D547E59B72520:964EA4EC9A3890A3D6E8A1228B15A850" country="Madagascar" name="Sainte Marie Island">Sainte Marie Island</location>
, which is situated on the East Coast of 
<collectingCountry id="9DAA5DDCB92E362A4B492FA06E599207">Madagascar</collectingCountry>
.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>