<document id="8CF30009E87515D87E626F4F79461928" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.698.14999" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2cd93971-3074-47ec-92f7-769314899c2a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="134310963" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-698-75" ID-ZBK="37FB04B0BD2340EFA39A049147FC4B7F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-698-75" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 698" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Oxyptilus Zeller from the southwestern United States (Lepidoptera, Pterophoridae)" checkinTime="1505750193623" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Matthews, Deborah L." docDate="2017" docId="42DD638E1882EDCF347370CE1F939186" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 698: 75-93" docOrigin="ZooKeys 698" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.698.14999" docTitle="Oxyptilus delawaricus Zeller 1873" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="90" masterDocId="FFF7B406FFDAFF9A9F20EC1187111256" masterDocTitle="A new species of Oxyptilus Zeller from the southwestern United States (Lepidoptera, Pterophoridae)" masterLastPageNumber="93" masterPageNumber="75" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" updateTime="1643484778917" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="87A0B8699E6257CCA64130C46EFFC4B1" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="21D8FC59A755A642ED518844A494B1AE">
<mods:title id="213A79A1CE08E42F4BD8C7D21E2123EB">A new species of Oxyptilus Zeller from the southwestern United States (Lepidoptera, Pterophoridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="250C825F880791BB5601DC1BE06530BC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="22E9CFA30C628218A8DC2A27FE032430">
<mods:roleTerm id="B37D999442F65B85B773BE1E4BBBF41B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C8A6D01C0B13345C03E1E49E4F538191">Matthews, Deborah L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="DF6DE821660D8A2F582442BEF7B48CDE">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="BF20740F423DF53A2E689D4566D1374A" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="2E27181AF91F2E3319D6A53E0390ED5B">
<mods:title id="4DD116C214C7EC605A33AF26A7C4A71A">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D9122DD5850E8C0A1F3CAE3C2BFFE75E">
<mods:date id="9275998A79C0A00DA4BEB3577D9428E1">2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="A37D5777C9FBE36EE89018F4C94E5B31" type="volume">
<mods:number id="2075626EC26200352695FE5DB7B21364">698</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="2B3E2672D1FCFB4406071C370A29ED58" unit="page">
<mods:start id="3B7CF9E167E946935F0A3F499258D80E">75</mods:start>
<mods:end id="55FFC384EFCA6A1976242E630A149C11">93</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="9385273EA41DD3492DF6E1260F1B0142">
<mods:url id="A3F511346CE5DAA31431425D8B9F1229">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.698.14999</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="3832F069D0CAAFCA0C2168C2F041B8CF">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="1D8849341FF067B5CAA2837FC5030E4B" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.698.14999</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="757FE5D580954952F2F9E890A3BB2D18" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-698-75</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="92C15DD8FC59A756C80156BDFB835CFF" type="ZBK">37FB04B0BD2340EFA39A049147FC4B7F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="13E5D757D14A6D45155E1A51093F0961" type="ZooBank">37FB04B0BD2340EFA39A049147FC4B7F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="42DD638E1882EDCF347370CE1F939186" ID-GBIF-Taxon="134310963" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:42DD638E1882EDCF347370CE1F939186" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/42DD638E1882EDCF347370CE1F939186" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<subSubSection id="E1126D369A1DA1A1C90C729D40BE7566" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="BE63CDF63107B6F695CF45E67F6FAB49" pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<taxonomicName id="B41D7D5AE22A962A0449AB0B56AAACB2" authority="Zeller, 1873" authorityName="Zeller" authorityYear="1873" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus delawaricus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="delawaricus">Oxyptilus delawaricus Zeller, 1873</taxonomicName>
Figs 10-12, 15-16, 17-18, 21, 25-26, 27-28
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D1FD3BF01A4CAE6B89448BE5A8456988" pageId="10" pageNumber="85" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="DFE46995A2510E448C207641C4BD3780" pageId="10" pageNumber="85">
<taxonomicName id="C476D5DC55D50325F4DAE260C6DCE7F0" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus delawaricus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="delawaricus">
<pageBreakToken id="4CCF7F861364C809BED8955A076A111D" pageId="10" pageNumber="85" start="start">Oxyptilus</pageBreakToken>
delawaricus
</taxonomicName>
Zeller, Verhandlungen der 
<normalizedToken id="A26E004986E8808308B6775E88FB87A7" originalValue="Kaiserlich-Königlichen">Kaiserlich-Koeniglichen</normalizedToken>
Zoologisch-Botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien Vol. 23, p. 320, 1873.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E002E09196A9BCFC45E5244CF98A63B8" pageId="10" pageNumber="85">
<taxonomicName id="BF7F7729ABB68CC3307C2202F7C97D11" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" form="finitimus" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="f." kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus bernardinus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="form" species="bernardinus">Oxyptilus bernardinus f. finitimus</taxonomicName>
Grinnell, Canadian Entomologist, Vol. 19, p. 315, 1908.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35A4E2687253ADACFB18618AD25B29BC" pageId="10" pageNumber="85" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="BA333A30FE521A67C43054F722ADF4C9" pageId="10" pageNumber="85">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="13F5E52D84E1C8E7DEB66311591A737B" pageId="10" pageNumber="85">
More than 284 specimens were examined from various institutions and label data captured. In the interest of brevity, locality data is given in captions for figured specimens and summarized for all other 
<taxonomicName id="BCAB6B4479549DE5A7F0535BBC05294B" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="10" pageNumber="85" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
specimens examined in the distribution map (Fig. 31). In some cases, where only a state was given on labels and no other state records available, a dot was placed in the center of the state. An exception is Kansas where the dot was centrally placed in Eastern Kansas, reflecting the most likely distribution based on the known distribution of 
<taxonomicName id="96B853D7736549429A11C818C23C7BB8" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Asteraceae" genus="Hieracium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Hieracium" order="Asterales" pageId="10" pageNumber="85" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Hieracium</taxonomicName>
within the state (
<bibRefCitation id="565F3B460C1E588F016D4A0905393E4C" author="Ridgway, R" journalOrPublisher="C., published by the author" pageId="18" pageNumber="93" url="http://plants.usda.gov/" year="2017">USDA 2017</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B20ED0571FBEC1CD1D11A98BB6C0777E" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="11" pageNumber="86" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="DB01869E5A02E975659560D57411B7BA" pageId="11" pageNumber="86">
<pageBreakToken id="1D4A0EC223C975DC79514F862B9EA6D2" pageId="11" pageNumber="86" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E62A6C8D1F1A88824195A627C5567884" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="11" pageNumber="86">
As in 
<taxonomicName id="54BAFBBEFD769BE527A6849850621C0F" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="11" pageNumber="86" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
, the second segment of the labial palpus bears a scale tuft that extends partway alongside the distal segment distinguishing it from related genera. The species is recognized externally by the ochraceous-tawny ground color; the metascutum with three ochraceous-tawny or clay color stripes, as opposed to buff in 
<taxonomicName id="64701523D5F4E5F0108692E5CC15C559" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="11" pageNumber="86" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
(mid-dorsal stripe may be obscure), and flanked by narrow white stripes 
<pageBreakToken id="E93B0292BC074CEB05EAB42C319B55E4" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
the pattern continued on the first abdominal segment; and patterns of the forewing first lobe. Dorsally, the first lobe is traversed by equally narrow white stripes, as opposed to a wider proximal band as in 
<taxonomicName id="B842AEB3A02DD2D5D50C43C413A64BE6" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
. The trajectory of the distal white stripe is also at a smaller angle than in 
<taxonomicName id="1FB104B3D11CD6F155E0F73C91624882" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
. Ventrally, the forewing apex is ochraceous-tawny or clay colored as opposed to white in 
<taxonomicName id="DE700FA09084D1819F7ED61C204024E4" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
. The midventral white band of the abdomen is narrow in 
<taxonomicName id="3A5B9866803A9FAE308175AA71B8B5C9" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
, about half the width of that in 
<taxonomicName id="90845747AFE81DC548704BBBE1FA0431" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
. Genitalia characters also distinguish the two species including the longer tegumen lobes and constricted base of the valvular lobe in 
<taxonomicName id="F3BC75336A2480E759AA3A5437CA4FB4" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
males, and the bilobed ostial margin and smaller signa in females.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="166794103D1641D46B021AB50C542276" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" type="redescription">
<paragraph id="A1FC535E135F85276C695F142ED96BD7" pageId="12" pageNumber="87">Redescription</paragraph>
<paragraph id="239B0CEBA3D8DB4C8B5291A3BD198027" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="89" pageId="12" pageNumber="87">
(male, female). HEAD (Figs 15, 16) with labial palpi slender, length about 1.5
<normalizedToken id="6C4F9F6FC441D549AE589FA91BF2DF3B" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
eye diameter. Second segment with ventral scale tuft reaching 0.3
<normalizedToken id="89E3B2638135792216050966EC7B0C89" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
to.0.75
<normalizedToken id="286853DB88BCA3916694C5E45EC0735B" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
of distal segment. Palpi white and clay colored, with clay colored lateral stripe. Basal segment mostly white, distal segment dorsally with white tip. Frons and vertex ochraceous-tawny or clay colored with transverse single row of white scales anterad of antennae and cluster of white scales laterally at anterior margin or across entire frontal margin. Eye bordered by white scales as in 
<taxonomicName id="4A8FA0DFB9A00BDD9432EACAB60C49BE" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="12" pageNumber="87" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
except sometimes with clay colored scales mixed in. Occipital fringe scales mostly bifid, ochraceous-tawny with some white scales mid-dorsally. Antenna with scape and pedicel with three alternating white and brown 
<pageBreakToken id="A33AF2CBA409630000047FF7D18DC633" pageId="13" pageNumber="88" start="start">stripes</pageBreakToken>
, anterior stripes chestnut-brown; posterior stripe ochraceous-tawny; flagellum dotted with alternating chestnut-brown and white scales dorsally, drab and minutely ciliate ventrally. THORAX with anterior part of tegulae and mesoscutum russet or ochraceous-tawny, grading posteriorly to clay, cream, and white; mesoscutellum mostly cream colored and white; metascutum with three ochraceous-tawny or clay colored stripes flanked by white stripes. Foreleg (Fig. 11), chestnut-brown and white striped, except coxa proximally white, distally ochraceous-tawny; femur evenly striped, tibia chestnut-brown dorsally, white ventrally; first tarsomeres with dorsal dusky-brown stripe, ventrally white, second and third tarsomere white and dusky-brown banded, fourth and fifth tarsomere solid dusky-brown. Mid and hindleg coxa ochraceous-tawny and white or cream striped; femur white and chestnut-brown striped; tibia white with chestnut-brown bands terminating in scale tufts at spurs. Spurs nearly equal, white dorsally with dusky-brown apex, dusky-brown to black ventrally. Tarsomeres white and dusky brown banded, somewhat variable, with distal tarsomere usually dusky-brown. FOREWING (Figs 10, 11) length, males 
<normalizedToken id="B647CE07950D636FA77E38DFA729A7C3" originalValue="xˉ">xˉ</normalizedToken>
= 9.58 mm 
<normalizedToken id="651B5FC1CD45E321B33A23522B7C7011" originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
0.56 (n = 25), females, 
<normalizedToken id="84A5DF34463D5E8DBB013843A79A6D0F" originalValue="xˉ">xˉ</normalizedToken>
= 8.71 mm 
<normalizedToken id="B79BA3119778C3D77CF2C49746EC8174" originalValue="±">+/-</normalizedToken>
0.80 (n = 6). Cleft origin 0.48
<normalizedToken id="43635B44D54037DC8D9932EA236751AF" originalValue="–0.53×">-0.53x</normalizedToken>
wing length from base, lobe apices acute, second lobe with concave termen. Dorsal ground color ochraceous-tawny. Costal margin dotted with white and chestnut-brown. Discal cell with small central chestnut-brown spot with distal trail of white scales. Area between veins 1A and 2A with diffuse elongate patch of russet and chestnut-brown scales. Cleft base with white spot with smaller chestnut-brown spot posterad. First lobe transected in thirds by two oblique narrow white bands of similar width; basal band projecting at more obtuse angle from long axis of wing than distal band. White scaling of bands extending to costa, with some ochraceous-tawny scales mixed in at margin. Forewing apex ochraceous-tawny, between white bands russet, area just basad of basal white band, russet, gradually grading basally to ochraceous-tawny. In some cases, forewing ground color appearing entirely russet with area between white bands not distinctly darker than apex. Second lobe similarly patterned to first except basal white band diffuse and area just basad ochraceous-tawny. Cleft margins of both lobes with scattered spatulate chestnut-brown scales, and elongate clay colored scales overlapping drab linear fringe scales; white spatulate scales likewise overlapping fringe at white bands. Forewing anal margin with terminal and subterminal groups of drab linear fringe scales as in 
<taxonomicName id="978E283C7BE2258F133AD75663CB9298" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="13" pageNumber="88" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
, the subterminal patch larger, flanked by white patches of linear scales, and with dense row of shorter overlapping russet and ochraceous-tawny scales. Fringes at basal third of second lobe with small patch of chestnut-brown and white. Fringes of anal margin basad of cleft mixed drab and white with patch of overlapping elongate white scales basad of cleft. Ventral forewing russet basad of cleft, with mixed ochraceous-tawny, clay, and white scales closer to wing base and trailing along narrow chestnut-brown costal margin. Russet scales grading into lobes to ochraceous-tawny, including lobe apices. White oblique bands as on dorsum except wider and with basal band of second lobe absent. Costal margin of first lobe with short conspicuous dusky-brown or chestnut-brown fringe, contrasting white fringe at basal band and apical third of lobe. Fringes of cleft margin mostly drab. Anal margin fringe alternating white and drab as on dorsum but with spatulate scales mostly hidden by linear fringe scales. HINDWING (Figs 10, 11) first and second lobes 
<pageBreakToken id="9E306E4A9F72317A1B1973C4545F86F4" pageId="14" pageNumber="89" start="start">dorsally</pageBreakToken>
russet, basally grading to drab. Fringes drab, sometimes with trace of white two-thirds from wing base along second lobe anal margin. Third lobe ochraceous-tawny on basal two-thirds, russet on distal third adjacent to scale tooth, occasionally uniformly russet. Scale tooth at distal third of lobe with short spatulate russet and fuscous-black scales extending into fringes along anterior margin; anal margin with russet and fuscous-black in distal third forming triangular patch with basal scales longest. Anal margin also with small apical patch of 2-5 fuscous-black spatulate scales in fringes at apex; fringes drab, mixed with white elongate scales and a few fuscous-black scales basad of scale tooth. Ventrally with basal half of first lobe ochraceous-tawny, banded distally by white, russet, white, and ochraceous-tawny respectively; fringes drab or drab mixed with clay or cream color. Second lobe dull russet; venous scales russet or antique brown; fringes drab. Third lobe ochraceous-tawny or russet, with solid white just basad of scale tooth or mixed white and ochraceous-tawny and trail of white bordering anal margin; fringes as on dorsum. ABDOMEN dorsum mixed ochraceous-tawny and clay with varying amounts of chestnut-brown. A white diverging longitudinal subdorsal band present on A1, on posterior half of A2, reduced to patch of white scales on posterior margin of A3-A7. Segments A2-A7 also with small marginal patches of white scales laterally. Males with distinct, mostly pale chestnut-brown, scale tuft laterally on A8, female with banding contiguous from A7. Abdomen venter clay colored, with narrow white mesal band flanked posteriorly by white scale patches. Males with clay colored and white lateral tuft at A8.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EC3C3B21AA2D61146CF101340CA26C4A" pageId="14" pageNumber="89">
Male genitalia (Figs 17, 18) (n=5). Uncus mesally articulated with tegumen, length less than half that of tegumen, bilobed, weakly sclerotized except for lobes which bear short setae. Tegumen bilobed; lobes distinctly longer than valvular lobes, with widened base, slightly concave medial margin, and distally truncate. Valvae symmetrical, with terminal membranous valvular lobe accounting for about one-third of valve length. Valvular lobe bearing deciduous scale tuft and short setae, basal connection constricted and inserted just anterad of apex of main part of valve. Sacculus mostly parallel to valve margin, not distinctly wider at base. Juxta a short curved sclerotized fulcrum attached to membranous sheath of phallobase. Phallus slightly curved; length similar to valve length. Phallobase width similar or just exceeding valve width. Aedeagus slightly longer than phallobase, with subapical spinous crest-shaped process. Vesica tubular, without cornuti. Inception of bulbus ejaculatorius at 0.5
<normalizedToken id="8F0F2FE4CB98A817FA42A4EAF9AB1D89" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of phallobase. Sternite VIII produced as bilobed structure medially supported by saccus, overall length about one-half that of tegumen, notch between lobes reaching about 0.7
<normalizedToken id="FFCA763A03A4A15D528B85552054190D" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
distance to base. Lobes not distinctly widened basally as in 
<taxonomicName id="1C1A01EC2B25C254F77BB33BCE900110" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="14" pageNumber="89" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C123C81F9897A48FB862425A9836FAC5" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="14" pageNumber="89">
Female genitalia (Figs 21, 25, 26) (n=5). Apophyses posteriores about 3.5
<normalizedToken id="EA3048ED9719B609A920B48F3E888E4B" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of papillae anales, moderately sclerotized. Apophyses anteriores absent. Sternite VII overriding VIII but not extending beyond ostium and forming separate recessed pocket on each side of antrum. Ostium formed from margin of dorsal and ventral antrum plates; dorsal (outer) plate projecting as single rounded medially convex rim; ventral plate weakly bilobed or medially emarginate. Antrum length similar to width, generally appearing funnel-shaped with outer collar where fused with sternite VII. Ductus bursae and corpus bursae similar in length. Width of ductus bursae about 0.2
<normalizedToken id="633935B18015063DE95F6C17650BDEFB" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
ostium diameter. Ductus seminalis similar in width to that of ductus bursae; inception point 
<pageBreakToken id="E1E34C2B6429D6D61AAF2FFD3622EEBF" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
corpus bursae directly adjacent to that of ductus bursae. Corpus bursae ovoid, with paired, small, serrated blade-like signa, length about 0.6
<normalizedToken id="60554FB0B74A4C58D372CA744E92CE1B" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
ostium diameter.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="897C2B79CF0E0E90B40A0552C163CA39" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" type="larval hostplants and habits">
<paragraph id="EFE7EDBDC159C623032733FF37D11637" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">Larval hostplants and habits.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FC1777B96AE3D31C80E560FB2D656DBD" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
Larvae web together leaves and feed within these masses on the developing inflorescences of 
<taxonomicName id="1ABA96392CE4797349E19BA6A3C89D57" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Asteraceae" genus="Hieracium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Hieracium" order="Asterales" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Hieracium</taxonomicName>
(hawkweeds) (
<taxonomicName id="295810B999D8CE4829E19076B8EB2BC2" family="Asteraceae" lsidName="" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="family">Asteraceae</taxonomicName>
). Three species have been recorded as hostplants: 
<taxonomicName id="800935986D4A0CA5120CAF7CC73B09A7" genus="H." lsidName="H. abiflorium" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="abiflorium">H. abiflorium</taxonomicName>
Hook., 
<taxonomicName id="576CD81D6A149C2CA5A7722E0D9B582B" genus="H." lsidName="H. cynoglossoides" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="cynoglossoides">H. cynoglossoides</taxonomicName>
Arv.-Touv. (= 
<taxonomicName id="9A3A5A16DD750788FCF1FF9BEB10D88C" genus="H." lsidName="H. albertinum" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="albertinum">H. albertinum</taxonomicName>
Farr), and 
<taxonomicName id="76BDDF18676789D82CC3D5CA50CEAE37" genus="H." lsidName="H. scouleri" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="scouleri">H. scouleri</taxonomicName>
Hook. (
<bibRefCitation id="8346044F9954A087E3EFC2E9B5D5DA93" author="Clarke, JFG" journalOrPublisher="Canadian Entomologist" pageId="17" pageNumber="92" pagination="171 - 181" title="Notes and new species of Microlepidoptera from Washington State." url="https://doi.org/10.4039/Ent66171-8" volume="66" year="1934">Clarke 1934</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="30F1FE287ACC189C70ADC77C485D2E1D" author="Dyar, HG" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the United States National Museum" pageId="17" pageNumber="92" pagination="779 - 938" title="The Lepidoptera of the Kootenai District of British Columbia." url="https://doi.org/10.5479/si.00963801.27-1376.779" volume="27" year="1904">Dyar 1904</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="0EC5305062B823D54A5BE62523623C8E" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">Landry 1987</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="A37A935BBD6F35E942DF596EE007374E" author="McDunnough, J" journalOrPublisher="Transactions of the Royal Society of Canada" pageId="18" pageNumber="93" pagination="175 - 190" title="Contribution toward a knowledge of our Canadian plume moths (Lepidoptera)." volume="21" year="1927">McDunnough 1927</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D976A600E8B05144FF37D808450EA7C4" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="AB3FA6E81A3C6267F944014845DE456D" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">Distribution and phenology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="12D42606538A6703BCEF0D920F32CC44" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
<taxonomicName id="BCE9D671F3A7D9DF01B6CBE0D2636C60" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus delawaricus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="delawaricus">Oxyptilus delawaricus</taxonomicName>
occurs in both the western and eastern United States and Canada with a large gap in the distribution representing the Great Plains (Fig. 31). Collection records are concentrated in the Northern and Middle Rocky Mountains and Pacific Northwest, extending south along the Pacific Border into Southern California, and north into the middle of British Columbia. Populations may follow the hostplant range further north and across the northern Interior Plains and Canadian Shield, joined by those known from the Appalachian Highlands and southern Interior Plains. Additional study of material from northern Alberta and Saskatchewan is necessary to determine the northern limits and potential for east-west gene flow within the species.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="065B66AC55E48AD3A700D6A5D54242F6" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
Distribution records of 
<taxonomicName id="1E52DB7BB426C6C90B17AACF5D5739D5" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
do not overlap with those of 
<taxonomicName id="DE47CA933EC9AA2F82C0684FAB4E99F2" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
which is restricted to sky islands within the southern part of the Intermountain Basin and Plateau Region. No records of 
<taxonomicName id="D2E6774EF49DABEDACAC95CAB622FC75" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
have been found as yet for Colorado, likewise showing a separation of the two species by the Wyoming Basin and Southern Rocky Mountains. Adults have been collected from the middle of May through the first week of September. The earliest confirmed spring records (mid May) are from Northern Mississippi, and are also the southernmost records with dates included on the labels. Late season records (August, September) are from more northern latitudes but no clear flight patterns are evident.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3299B8A8C4465F1C9D28F8B7E09F85CF" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" type="notes">
<paragraph id="B894FBFA3CD26A0AC787C7127DEC6A29" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">Notes.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="65AC46ED6DDA4AB6C7E0AC089787C174" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
<bibRefCitation id="D3E66317834CD23FC4C64A0738F259DE" author="Zeller, PC" journalOrPublisher="Verhandlungen der Kaiserlich-Koeniglichen Zoologisch-Botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien" pageId="18" pageNumber="93" pagination="201 - 334" title="Beitraege zur Kenntnis der nordamericanischen Nachtfalter, besonders der Mikrolepidopteren." volume="23" year="1873">Zeller (1873)</bibRefCitation>
described 
<taxonomicName id="D32CEC8A52C7D309238307A71B83DA46" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
from a male collected along the Delaware River. 
<bibRefCitation id="596498BC8F8B6110E47C91D715C26F34" author="Barnes, W" journalOrPublisher="Contributions to the Natural History of the Lepidoptera of North America" pageId="17" pageNumber="92" pagination="280 - 483" title="The Pterophoridae of America, north of Mexico." volume="4" year="1921">Barnes and Lindsey (1921)</bibRefCitation>
indicate the holotype should be in the British Museum (Natural History Museum, London). 
<bibRefCitation id="CE8CB0E49F3BB561AD821340EC5D6471" author="Grinnell, F" journalOrPublisher="Canadian Entomologist" pageId="17" pageNumber="92" pagination="313 - 321" title="Notes on the Pterophoridae or plume-moths of Southern California, with descriptions of new species." url="https://doi.org/10.4039/Ent40313-9" volume="19" year="1908">Grinnell (1908)</bibRefCitation>
described 
<taxonomicName id="37F2C66A024B69F22CAFB1FC74C5D279" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus bernardinus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bernardinus">Oxyptilus bernardinus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="C5456F25120454BBAA966FD1DC2DEDD0" authority="." form="finitimus" genus="O." infraspecific-rank="Form" lsidName="O. bernardinus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="form" species="bernardinus">O. bernardinus form finitimus. Form finitimus</taxonomicName>
was named based on one specimen that differed in the white forewing markings from the rest of the series. 
<bibRefCitation id="A534E9296360F2F5073D8C9C0B91B639" author="Barnes, W" journalOrPublisher="Contributions to the Natural History of the Lepidoptera of North America" pageId="17" pageNumber="92" pagination="280 - 483" title="The Pterophoridae of America, north of Mexico." volume="4" year="1921">Barnes and Lindsey (1921)</bibRefCitation>
synonymized 
<taxonomicName id="02C15B9CA89C9C8FC2FCE809F6584623" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus bernardinus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bernardinus">Oxyptilus bernardinus</taxonomicName>
with 
<taxonomicName id="DA861CA002B1A3EAF5E2E7B01CC45914" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Capperia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Capperia ningoris" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ningoris">Capperia ningoris</taxonomicName>
(Walsingham) and 
<taxonomicName id="93B17563AC12E56FBBE1FD8DB22BB6BC" lsidName="bernardinus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="bernardinus">bernardinus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicName id="FB0ED82423F348AB085E84725F36A84D" form="finitimus" infraspecific-rank="form" lsidName="form subsp. finitimus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="form" species="form" subSpecies="finitimus">form finitimus</taxonomicName>
with 
<taxonomicName id="5E68B8B37429E7D7B980437D116A0898" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
. 
<bibRefCitation id="6675A0830D9EAC9929BDCFE3728045CE" author="Barnes, W" journalOrPublisher="Contributions to the Natural History of the Lepidoptera of North America" pageId="17" pageNumber="92" pagination="280 - 483" title="The Pterophoridae of America, north of Mexico." volume="4" year="1921">Barnes and Lindsey (1921)</bibRefCitation>
selected and designated a [lecto]type from five of 
<normalizedToken id="1C1794F75B6849170948E2B94FA2472B" originalValue="Grinnell’s">Grinnell's</normalizedToken>
specimens which is currently in the USNM type collection. They also found an unlabeled specimen with 
<normalizedToken id="85F25EA37F93EC029EA9A6AAD2B12A1D" originalValue="Grinnell’s">Grinnell's</normalizedToken>
<taxonomicName id="97F068DCC644B0D5AA99409A26E1F9B3" lsidName="bernardinus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="bernardinus">bernardinus</taxonomicName>
series which they recognized as the specimen Grinnell referred to as 
<taxonomicName id="33E7D4A2F1252DA205709E84FBEE41E4" form="finitimus" infraspecific-rank="form" lsidName="form subsp. finitimus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="form" species="form" subSpecies="finitimus">form finitimus</taxonomicName>
and labelled this specimen 
<normalizedToken id="E43458957AEA6CFDD227818A1FA11B21" originalValue="“type”">&quot;type&quot;</normalizedToken>
. The later specimen, however, has not been found in USNM holdings. Male valvular lobes are easily broken off during dissection and frequently missing on older specimens.
</paragraph>
<caption id="36FC2EE81AF3BFD2591F874F9638B20B" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
<paragraph id="0D241AE009F10DF76BFA14B550AAAA18" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
Figures 21-26. 
<taxonomicName id="55396383D0A1B8FCFA2B4D9382478D49" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Oxyptilus</taxonomicName>
female genitalia: 21 
<taxonomicName id="CF396BD89AD3254FF0ECA05621019CC9" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
, slide DM 1836, Washington, Chelan County, Wenatchee NF, Swakane Canyon Rd. (FR 7415), 4.2 mi. W of jct w/Hwy 99, 8 Jul 2010, James Adams (DMC) 22 
<taxonomicName id="2FE24AB3F0282009F49CDCB58679D969" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
paratype, slide DM 1831, Arizona: Apache County (see material examined) 23-26 enlargements of ostium/antrum - 23 
<taxonomicName id="C3AF707FE856D7F9EE307C5310AD676B" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
paratype, slide DM 1835, Arizona: Apache County 24 
<taxonomicName id="DFE4034849C5459F37E89CD6CF4E9573" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
paratype, slide DM 1831, Arizona: Apache County 25 
<taxonomicName id="EFF77FEFC5F1594125EC592015EDF91C" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
, slide DM 1811, California, El Dorado County, S. Lake Tahoe, Cold Creek, 1 Aug 1977, D.L. Bauer, MGCL Acc. # 2010-29 26 
<taxonomicName id="EA4C1ED94BF8992A60E5CEC87BBC3456" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
, slide DM 1836, data cited above for same slide.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="AF3EF68C25B8F80EAF5639F7F2615374" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
<paragraph id="FEB4C82E1BBC9C1259E54C52D8F2424F" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
Figures 27-30. 
<taxonomicName id="2D080BE1C09713B0DBA0C085D7B25371" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Oxyptilus</taxonomicName>
abdominal segments I and II: 27 
<taxonomicName id="95BA0D37893450D55EBC96A9E6FCA8A8" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
male, slide DM 1837, California, El Dorado County, S. Lake Tahoe, Cold Creek, 10 Aug 1991, D.L. Bauer, MGCL Acc. # 2010-29 28 
<taxonomicName id="88C8CA81953C0A7608486FAE57728AF0" genus="O." lsidName="O. delawaricus" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="delawaricus">O. delawaricus</taxonomicName>
female, slide DM 1836, Washington, Chelan County, Wenatchee NF, Swakane Canyon Rd. (FR 7415), 4.2 mi. W of jct w/Hwy 99, 8 Jul 2010, James Adams; 29 
<taxonomicName id="693B8228CC48A9D4C303AD67149E2A59" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
male, slide DM 1829, New Mexico: Sandoval County 30 
<taxonomicName id="2CBD649166DC5C29946C4B75B8019CE7" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
female, slide DM 1831, Arizona: Apache County.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="0B12EFCC116FFA337B1CDBB4E3E00C38" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
<paragraph id="8BE6AE12865EEF3B1D56A884086281F4" pageId="15" pageNumber="90">
Figure 31. Distribution of 
<taxonomicName id="3CEAB35F5454107A1FA0F4DBBFD35E5E" class="Insecta" family="Pterophoridae" genus="Oxyptilus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyptilus delawaricus" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="delawaricus">Oxyptilus delawaricus</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="468856979D4EA7DEBE1A4B9479A628C7" genus="O." lsidName="O. eleanerae" pageId="15" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="eleanerae">O. eleanerae</taxonomicName>
. Assembled with simplemappr.net, accessed March 2017.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>