<document id="4D367CF7D7851A01E3BFF2BC726C0AA7" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458922" ID-ISSN="1942-1354" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5458922" ID-ZooBank="4B8831A7-6B5A-4C3C-B1E2-85F22BFC738F" _generate="added" approvalRequired="6" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="4" approvalRequired_for_treatments="2" checkinTime="1630211630327" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio, Heffern, Daniel, Botero, Juan Pablo, de, Francisco Eriberto &amp; Nascimento, L." docDate="2020" docId="4528878FFFC1FF96FF14F98DFD7E802E" docLanguage="en" docName="0785.pdf" docOrigin="Insecta Mundi 2020 (785)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:6D85C66E4B52897F25DA165649BC06DC.1:InsectaMundi.2009-2020.journal_article" docStyleId="6D85C66E4B52897F25DA165649BC06DC" docStyleName="InsectaMundi.2009-2020.journal_article" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Callanga ashaninka Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento. A 2020, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="14" masterDocId="B911FFF7FFCAFF99FFD4FFDBFFD08640" masterDocTitle="Notes, new records, new combinations, a new genus and three new species in Hemilophini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae: Lamiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="25" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="11" pageNumber="10" updateTime="1630870485620" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-NC-3.0">
<mods:mods id="5DDDCBC153EB3BFF1FD4BC9F275F60AC" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="700A43FE90B302DC5C355E4FD61BD98B">
<mods:title id="070475851A750EFBCFFDE03458056E75">Notes, new records, new combinations, a new genus and three new species in Hemilophini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae: Lamiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="8241150AAEAC0993B063814579CF672B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9A243D10210E8CA876AD81774D105618">
<mods:roleTerm id="7F9E3F2E8DA7782DFB09BFF0F83D0BAA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="821C6BCBAB3D1E62508D69B40E251B76">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="90CC021BA3D8AEEE9769918C8EBA7269">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo São Paulo, SP, Brazil</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="05ADAAE4F961DAB040FDB33D8E3DF180" type="personal">
<mods:role id="575514EF5AB1D948961F161EC8E2429A">
<mods:roleTerm id="A5E039CDEFC617AF7A90CA671DF5E3CA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="653542F26A48E0C4A98F6DFAACA9F4D3">Heffern, Daniel</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="3220CD702D6EFA3ED409D5C35D456B9F">10531 Goldfield Lane Houston, TX 77064, USA titanusgiganteus @ hotmail. com</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="7ADE21F82ABEF909431BE4E0D6762B46" type="personal">
<mods:role id="68ABB386801071AD739F654815BBF17D">
<mods:roleTerm id="0C5F2657963D8B95B463613344532569">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1060EF6160F6AEA358E4EFE42632676B">Botero, Juan Pablo</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="AC3F50FF9248F32F7C9E1755B1E1208F">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo São Paulo, SP, Brazil</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="C958B4A0D48AF5E310DF72DA3F0B770F" type="personal">
<mods:role id="2F600366BB6549601192650ADF83BFB8">
<mods:roleTerm id="752C0A6AE4B2641881FF740522CAF493">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="58AFC53CBB5C3DCEE46F5834AA5DC65F">de, Francisco Eriberto</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="0FAC60BC8A6D0B5D9056B94C8D588C56">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade São Paulo, SP,</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="EEB316CEF9F3B5504DF80856085DC75C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3523EF01BFAA6CA52BB2152D2C94E193">
<mods:roleTerm id="A3C0F4112337A55CB8F70B47C6479164">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7C0DA552120347E2E378A2200F829294">Nascimento, L.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="AEDD93DDD3B16DCB394A2ED8ADAB7567">de São Paulo Brazil</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="08123CEAE7093E5D2DFA8D028FE9D667">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="E738362E6BCCA8B35F321BD801E8BA68" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="6882F11D5187BD49F0FA43C7E362A920">
<mods:title id="A83BC99ED50A2CBEE61326D4DF28D11A">Insecta Mundi</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="77AB3A1F2666361AF5F059184F03BEE2">
<mods:date id="647C65D9BC6AB965AC7AA465EF4D205F">2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="2CF7FC3CB0EF9032673A18C8F656ACC8" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="CF988A098C288BAE017C85DF0CDF7AEB">2020-07-31</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="0FC1773233AB60316F0BC641DA08030C" type="volume">
<mods:number id="52EC07102C39DA4C391FB6943A009738">2020</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="28AA537D183A4EFC9FEF9E4B52D647A3" type="issue">
<mods:number id="3F6A25E24BFDE5E5182EC866095B1DFE">785</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="F2A06C737648BC25B3DB2A281F240A8A" unit="page">
<mods:start id="0847AF36C15329DF78C276B8E3F0212C">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F5E2E43F5CD08846EB2411EBEEFD8885">25</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="56E924404250DE2C4B5A12CB2213141F">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="ABBD1C19FBA78B83F1CB4AECD8868D1D" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458922</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="598DBED27D5AC688DC80B98E4E2A98F9" type="ISSN">1942-1354</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="82C2B5DA9DC52DCD0C440EA655118DF7" type="Zenodo-Dep">5458922</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E64E8C145C640C83DD600FB701A5B4B1" type="ZooBank">4B8831A7-6B5A-4C3C-B1E2-85F22BFC738F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="4528878FFFC1FF96FF14F98DFD7E802E" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:4528878FFFC1FF96FF14F98DFD7E802E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4528878FFFC1FF96FF14F98DFD7E802E" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC1FF92FF14F98DFADC802E" box="[192,1292,1622,1647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC1FF92FF14F98DFADC802E" blockId="11.[192,1292,1622,1679]" box="[192,1292,1622,1647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
<heading id="967681F5FFC1FF92FF14F98DFADC802E" bold="true" box="[192,1292,1622,1647]" fontSize="10" level="2" pageId="11" pageNumber="10" reason="3">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC1FF92FF14F98DFADC802E" bold="true" box="[192,1292,1622,1647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC1FF92FF14F98DFB8B802E" authority="Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento" authorityName="Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento. A" authorityYear="2020" box="[192,1115,1622,1647]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="10" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ashaninka" status="new species">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC1FF92FF14F98DFE0C802E" bold="true" box="[192,476,1622,1646]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">Callanga ashaninka</emphasis>
Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E4C657F0FFC1FF92FBBCF98CFADC802E" box="[1128,1292,1622,1647]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC1FF94FF14F9ACFC27824A" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="11" pageNumber="10" type="description">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC1FF92FF14F9ACFE8280CF" blockId="11.[192,1292,1622,1679]" box="[192,338,1655,1679]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC1FF92FF1DF9ACFE9B80CF" box="[201,331,1655,1679]" captionStart="Figures 45–52" captionStartId="25.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[229,1402,213,1814]" captionTargetId="figure-59@25.[229,1403,213,1814]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="Figures 45–52. Callanga ashaninka. 45–48) Holotype male. 45) Dorsal habitus. 46) Ventral habitus. 47) Lateral habitus. 48) Head, frontal view. 49–52) Paratype female. 49) Dorsal habitus. 50) Ventral habitus. 51) Lateral habitus. 52) Distal antennomeres." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458936" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458936/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">Fig. 45–52</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC1FF95FF14F97CFAD88710" blockId="11.[190,1443,1703,1922]" lastBlockId="12.[192,1441,215,336]" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC1FF92FF14F97CFE658080" bold="true" box="[192,437,1703,1728]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">Description. Male</emphasis>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC1FF92FE1CF973FD9F80FF" box="[456,591,1703,1728]" captionStart="Figures 45–52" captionStartId="25.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[229,1402,213,1814]" captionTargetId="figure-59@25.[229,1403,213,1814]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="Figures 45–52. Callanga ashaninka. 45–48) Holotype male. 45) Dorsal habitus. 46) Ventral habitus. 47) Lateral habitus. 48) Head, frontal view. 49–52) Paratype female. 49) Dorsal habitus. 50) Ventral habitus. 51) Lateral habitus. 52) Distal antennomeres." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458936" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458936/files/figure.png" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">Fig. 45–48</figureCitation>
). Head mostly dark brown, almost black; mouthparts light yellowish brown; mandibles black; antennae dark brown, almost black. Prothorax mostly yellowish brown; pronotum with large T-shaped dark-brown macula anteriorly, transverse “arm” wider, close to anterior margin, longitudinal “arm” narrower, slightly surpassing middle of pronotum; prosternum both reddish and brownish anteriorly. Ventral surface of mesothorax yellowish brown, slightly lighter in some areas. Metanepisternum mostly dark brown in anterior 3/4, gradually reddish brown toward metaventrite, and mostly yellowish brown in posterior quarter. Metaventrite mostly yellowish brown, with L-shaped brownish macula on each side of posterior half. Basal 3/4 of elytra dark brown laterally, dark reddish brown centrally except dark brown sutural area; posterior quarter mostly light reddish brown, with sutural area and sides dark brown. Coxae and trochanters yellowish brown; femora yellowish brown with apex blackish; tibiae and tarsi dark brown, almost black. Ventrites yellowish brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC6FF95FF14FEB2FDD5834D" blockId="12.[190,1443,361,1293]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC6FF95FF14FEB2FEC087C1" bold="true" box="[192,272,361,385]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Head.</emphasis>
Frons minutely, abundantly punctate; with grayish-white pubescence nearly obscuring integument, except glabrous median groove and narrow area close to eyes; with both long and moderately short, erect, sparse setae of same color interspersed. Vertex minutely, abundantly punctate, with a few fine punctures interspersed; with grayish-white pubescence centrally, sparser than on frons, especially after area between antennal tubercles, nearly glabrous laterally; with long, erect, sparse setae of same color interspersed. Area behind eyes almost glabrous close to vertex, with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument on remaining surface, except glabrous narrow area close to eye; with long, erect, sparse setae of same color behind upper eye lobe. Genae with grayish-white pubescence partially obscuring integument, bristly, slightly more yellowish close to postclypeus, except glabrous narrow area close to eye and apex. Wide central area of postclypeus with sculpturing and pubescence as on frons, and sides smooth and glabrous; with long, erect brownish setae interspersed in wide central area. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior half, inclined at anterior half; posterior quarter close to anteclypeus finely, sparsely punctate, with minute, sparse, decumbent grayish-white setae; anterior quarter of coplanar area depressed, rugose-punctate, with long, erect, moderately abundantly reddish-brown setae directed forward; posterior region of inclined area with long, erect reddish-brown setae directed forward, except nearly glabrous central area, and remaining surface glabrous. Antennal tubercles with sculpturing, pubescence, and erect setae as on frons. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.28 times length of scape (0.22 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.78 times length of scape (0.61 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 1.9 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at base of antennomere VII. Scape with grayishwhite pubescence not obscuring integument, denser dorsally; with moderately long, erect grayish-white setae ventrally. Pedicel with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, denser dorsally; with moderately long, grayish-white erect setae ventrally, and at apex of dorsal surface. Antennomeres with grayish-white pubescent ring basally, less conspicuous ventrally, and remaining surface with short brownish pubescence; apex of antennomeres III–IV with short, slightly distinct grayish-white pubescent ring at apex; antennomeres with long, erect grayish-white setae ventrally, gradually shorter toward XI (setae more yellowish-brown depending on light intensity). Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.59; pedicel = 0.10; IV = 0.70; V = 0.41; VI = 0.38; VII = 0.35; VIII = 0.30; IX = 0.27; X = 0.22; XI = 0.27.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC6FF94FF14FAFDFB8C8770" blockId="12.[191,1442,1318,1926]" lastBlockId="13.[190,1441,215,304]" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC6FF95FF14FAFDFEFC837E" bold="true" box="[192,300,1318,1342]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax transverse; sides sinuous. Pronotum gibbose on each side of central area and with elongated, subelliptical gibbosity centrally; dark area coarsely, sparsely punctate, with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument anterocentrally and around central gibbosity, remaining surface with minute grayish-white pubescence (top of central gibbosity glabrous) and with long, erect sparse grayish-white setae interspersed; lighter area with dense yellowish-brown pubescence and long, erect, sparse grayish-white setae interspersed. Sides of prothorax with dense yellowish-brown pubescence except margins with sparse pubescence. Ventral surface of thorax with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, sparser on prosternum, prosternal process, mesoventrite, mesoventral process and anterocentral area of metaventrite. Narrowest area of prosternal process slightly wider than 0.2 times width of procoxal cavity. Sides of mesoventral process moderately tab-shaped near apex. Scutellum with sparse grayish-white pubescence. 
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC6FF95FD04F9B1FCFF80C2" bold="true" box="[720,815,1642,1666]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Elytra.</emphasis>
Coarsely abundantly punctate basally and on sides of basal 3/4, finely, moderately sparsely punctate in remaining basal 3/4, almost indistinctly punctate in posterior quarter and posterior 3/4 of inclined sides; with grayish-white pubescence appearing to be denser in posterior quarter depending on angle source, with short, erect, sparse setae of same color interspersed; humeral carina well-marked from humerus to near apex; carina in inclined area placed very near to humeral carina, slightly less distinct than humeral carina, especially depending on angle source. 
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC6FF95FEC9F8F6FEB58105" bold="true" box="[285,357,1837,1861]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, bristly ventrally on meso- and metafemora. Protibiae with yellowish-white pubescence dorsally and laterally, with long, erect, sparse setae of same color interspersed, and bristly, dense yellowish-brown pubescence ventrally (gradually longer toward apex); meso- and metatibiae with sparse yellowish-white pubescence except yellowish-brown, denser, bristly pubescence in central area of posterior 3/4 of dorsal surface and posterior third of ventral surface, and long, erect yellowish-brown setae interspersed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14FE93FA4E87C1" blockId="13.[190,1440,328,385]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14FE93FE988720" bold="true" box="[192,328,328,352]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with short yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, slightly longer at apex, with long, erect, sparse setae of same color interspersed. Apex of ventrite V emarginated centrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF6CFE42FB8185D9" blockId="13.[184,1442,409,921]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF6CFE42FECD87F1" bold="true" box="[184,285,409,433]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Female</emphasis>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FEE0FE42FE6887F1" box="[308,440,409,433]" captionStart="Figures 45–52" captionStartId="25.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[229,1402,213,1814]" captionTargetId="figure-59@25.[229,1403,213,1814]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="Figures 45–52. Callanga ashaninka. 45–48) Holotype male. 45) Dorsal habitus. 46) Ventral habitus. 47) Lateral habitus. 48) Head, frontal view. 49–52) Paratype female. 49) Dorsal habitus. 50) Ventral habitus. 51) Lateral habitus. 52) Distal antennomeres." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458936" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458936/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 49–52</figureCitation>
). Pronotum with posterocentral brownish macula; wide central area of prosternum mostly brown; prosternal process brown basally, gradually reddish brown toward apex; mesoventrite and mesoventral process dark brown except narrow reddish-brown anterocentral macula on mesoventrite; mesanepisternum and mesepimeron dark brown toward elytra, gradually yellowish brown toward ventral surface; metanepisternum dark brown, almost black; metaventrite mostly dark brown, almost black, with anterocentral area yellowish brown (central area of this region brownish); elytra entirely dark brown; coxae and trochanters mostly dark brown; femora on base and apex yellowish brown centrally (more reddish brown depending on light intensity); ventrites I–IV dark brown, almost black; abdominal ventrite V dark brown, almost black in anterior 3/4, yellowish brown in posterior quarter. Vertex and area behind upper eye lobes nearly glabrous, except grayish-white pubescent band in posterocentral area of vertex; area behind eye with moderately coarse, sparse punctures interspersed; area behind lower eye lobes with moderately long, erect, sparse grayish-white setae interspersed; antennae 1.4 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at base of antennomere XI; scape slimmer than in male; antennomeres III–IV as in male; antennomeres V–XI with dense yellowish-white pubescence, distinctly longer, bristly ventrally; antennomeres V–XI with long, moderately abundant, erect yellowish setae ventrally; abdominal pubescence distinctly more conspicuous in posterocentral area of ventrites.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14FC6AFC27824A" blockId="13.[190,1440,945,1034]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14FC6AFE178589" bold="true" box="[192,455,945,969]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Dimensions in mm</emphasis>
(
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FE0FFC6AFD948589" box="[475,580,945,969]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">holotype</typeStatus>
male/ 
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FD40FC6AFCD08589" box="[660,768,945,969]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">paratype</typeStatus>
female). Total length 13.35/13.75; prothoracic length 2.50/2.60; anterior prothoracic width 2.90/3.15; posterior prothoracic width 3.15/3.25; widest prothoracic width 3.25/3.45; humeral width 4.85/4.95; elytral length 9.85/10.15.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC7FF94FF14FBF8FC24821B" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14FBF8FC24821B" blockId="13.[190,1440,1058,1116]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14FBF8FE56827A" bold="true" box="[192,390,1058,1083]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation id="7DE93CC4FFC7FF94FE5DFBF8FE5E821B" collectingDate="2012-09" collectionCode="MZSP, DHCO" country="Peru" location="Rio Venado" municipality="Satipo" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Junin" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FE5DFBF8FE27827B" box="[393,503,1059,1083]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry id="B5967609FFC7FF94FDA8FBF8FD1C827A" box="[636,716,1059,1082]" name="Peru" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">PERU</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="0F45F87BFFC7FF94FD02FBF9FCE0827D" box="[726,816,1058,1085]" country="Peru" name="Junin" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">JUNÍN</collectingRegion>
: 
<collectingMunicipality id="2D5AACE3FFC7FF94FCEBFBF8FC40827B" box="[831,912,1059,1083]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Satipo</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location id="C85E6042FFC7FF94FC4EFBF8FBF7827B" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:4528878FFFC1FF96FF14F98DFD7E802E:C85E6042FFC7FF94FC4EFBF8FBF7827B" box="[922,1063,1059,1083]" country="Peru" municipality="Satipo" name="Rio Venado" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" stateProvince="Junin">Rio Venado</location>
, 
<date id="B93F1059FFC7FF94FBE4FBF8FB42827B" box="[1072,1170,1059,1083]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" value="2012-09">
<collectingDate id="A97BE9B1FFC7FF94FBE4FBF8FB42827B" box="[1072,1170,1059,1083]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" value="2012-09">IX.2012</collectingDate>
</date>
, local collector (
<collectionCode id="AB90AE5CFFC7FF94FA98FBF8FA4B827B" box="[1356,1435,1059,1083]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
, formerly 
<collectionCode id="AB90AE5CFFC7FF94FEFAFB98FE55821B" box="[302,389,1091,1115]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">DHCO</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FE4CFB9FFDD8821C" box="[408,520,1092,1116]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Paratype</typeStatus>
female, same data as 
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FCCCFB98FC50821B" box="[792,896,1091,1115]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">holotype</typeStatus>
(
<collectionCode id="AB90AE5CFFC7FF94FC44FB98FC38821B" box="[912,1000,1091,1115]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">DHCO</collectionCode>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC7FF94FF14FBAFFAD082EC" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14FBAFFAD082EC" blockId="13.[190,1440,1140,1196]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14FBAFFE8B82CC" bold="true" box="[192,347,1140,1164]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Etymology.</emphasis>
The epithet of this new species refers to the Asháninka indigenous people living in the area where the 
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FE94FB4FFE7882EC" box="[320,424,1172,1196]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">holotype</typeStatus>
was collected. The name “ 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FD38FB4FFCBE82EC" authorityName="Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento. A" authorityYear="2020" box="[748,878,1172,1196]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ashaninka">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FD38FB4FFCBE82EC" box="[748,878,1172,1196]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">ashaninka</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
” is used as a noun in apposition.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC7FF94FF14FB1EFE8280B4" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14FB1EFD6782BD" blockId="13.[190,1440,1221,1667]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14FB1EFE93829D" bold="true" box="[192,323,1221,1245]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Remarks.</emphasis>
As the color in the 
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FDEDFB1EFD71829D" box="[569,673,1221,1245]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">holotype</typeStatus>
and 
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC7FF94FD35FB1EFC9F829D" box="[737,847,1221,1245]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">paratype</typeStatus>
are considerably different, it is expected to find more chromatic variations in the species.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF3CFADEFA708022" blockId="13.[190,1440,1221,1667]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
The male of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FEA3FADEFDBD835D" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento" authorityYear="2020" box="[375,621,1285,1309]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ashaninka" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FEA3FADEFDBD835D" box="[375,621,1285,1309]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Callanga ashaninka</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E4C657F0FFC7FF94FDA1FADDFD00835D" box="[629,720,1286,1309]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FD09FADEFC8C835D" box="[733,860,1285,1309]" captionStart="Figures 45–52" captionStartId="25.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[229,1402,213,1814]" captionTargetId="figure-59@25.[229,1403,213,1814]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="Figures 45–52. Callanga ashaninka. 45–48) Holotype male. 45) Dorsal habitus. 46) Ventral habitus. 47) Lateral habitus. 48) Head, frontal view. 49–52) Paratype female. 49) Dorsal habitus. 50) Ventral habitus. 51) Lateral habitus. 52) Distal antennomeres." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458936" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458936/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 45–48</figureCitation>
) differs from that of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FB99FADDFB36835D" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[1101,1254,1285,1309]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FB99FADDFB36835D" box="[1101,1254,1285,1309]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FB22FADEFA99835E" box="[1270,1353,1285,1310]" captionStart="Figures 34–44" captionStartId="24.[192,287,1789,1811]" captionTargetBox="[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetId="figure-90@24.[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetPageId="24" captionText="Figures 34–44. Callanga and Lapazina spp. 34–36) Callanga tenebrosa, paratype female. 34) Dorsal habitus. 35) Lateral habitus. 36) Distal antennomeres. 37–39) Callanga trichocera, paratype female. 37) Dorsal habitus. 38) Lateral habitus.39) Distal antennomeres.40) Callanga trichocera, paratype male, dorsal habitus. 41–43)Lapazina fuscipennis, female. 41) Dorsal habitus. 42) Lateral habitus. 43) Distal antennomeres. 44) Lapazina fuscipennis, male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458934" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458934/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 40</figureCitation>
) by the shorter antennae, reaching elytral apex at base of antennomere VII (longer, reaching elytral apex before apex of antennomere V in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FE27FA9CFD5A831E" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[499,650,1350,1374]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FE27FA9CFD5A831E" box="[499,650,1350,1374]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), antennomeres dark brown (antennomeres V–XI orangish-brown in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FF0BFABCFEA9833F" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[223,377,1383,1407]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF0BFABCFEA9833F" box="[223,377,1383,1407]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), and pronotum with T-shaped dark brown area anteriorly (with transverse dark brown macula in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FEEBFA53FE0A83DF" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[319,474,1415,1439]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FEEBFA53FE0A83DF" box="[319,474,1415,1439]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
). The female of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FD48FA5CFC4683DF" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento" authorityYear="2020" box="[668,918,1415,1439]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ashaninka" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FD48FA5CFC4683DF" box="[668,918,1415,1439]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Callanga ashaninka</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E4C657F0FFC7FF94FC49FA53FC2A83DF" box="[925,1018,1416,1439]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FBDDFA5CFB5A83DF" box="[1033,1162,1415,1439]" captionStart="Figures 45–52" captionStartId="25.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[229,1402,213,1814]" captionTargetId="figure-59@25.[229,1403,213,1814]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="Figures 45–52. Callanga ashaninka. 45–48) Holotype male. 45) Dorsal habitus. 46) Ventral habitus. 47) Lateral habitus. 48) Head, frontal view. 49–52) Paratype female. 49) Dorsal habitus. 50) Ventral habitus. 51) Lateral habitus. 52) Distal antennomeres." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458936" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458936/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 49–52</figureCitation>
) differs from that of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FA51FA53FEEA8380" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FA51FA53FEEA8380" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FE9DFA73FE1A8380" box="[329,458,1448,1472]" captionStart="Figures 34–44" captionStartId="24.[192,287,1789,1811]" captionTargetBox="[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetId="figure-90@24.[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetPageId="24" captionText="Figures 34–44. Callanga and Lapazina spp. 34–36) Callanga tenebrosa, paratype female. 34) Dorsal habitus. 35) Lateral habitus. 36) Distal antennomeres. 37–39) Callanga trichocera, paratype female. 37) Dorsal habitus. 38) Lateral habitus.39) Distal antennomeres.40) Callanga trichocera, paratype male, dorsal habitus. 41–43)Lapazina fuscipennis, female. 41) Dorsal habitus. 42) Lateral habitus. 43) Distal antennomeres. 44) Lapazina fuscipennis, male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458934" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458934/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 37–39</figureCitation>
) by the pubescence and erect setae shorter (
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FC31FA73FBEA8380" box="[997,1082,1448,1472]" captionStart="Figures 45–52" captionStartId="25.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[229,1402,213,1814]" captionTargetId="figure-59@25.[229,1403,213,1814]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="Figures 45–52. Callanga ashaninka. 45–48) Holotype male. 45) Dorsal habitus. 46) Ventral habitus. 47) Lateral habitus. 48) Head, frontal view. 49–52) Paratype female. 49) Dorsal habitus. 50) Ventral habitus. 51) Lateral habitus. 52) Distal antennomeres." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458936" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458936/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 52</figureCitation>
) (longer in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FB11FA73FAB18380" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[1221,1377,1448,1472]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FB11FA73FAB18380" box="[1221,1377,1448,1472]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FAA4FA73FF0E83A1" captionStart="Figures 34–44" captionStartId="24.[192,287,1789,1811]" captionTargetBox="[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetId="figure-90@24.[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetPageId="24" captionText="Figures 34–44. Callanga and Lapazina spp. 34–36) Callanga tenebrosa, paratype female. 34) Dorsal habitus. 35) Lateral habitus. 36) Distal antennomeres. 37–39) Callanga trichocera, paratype female. 37) Dorsal habitus. 38) Lateral habitus.39) Distal antennomeres.40) Callanga trichocera, paratype male, dorsal habitus. 41–43)Lapazina fuscipennis, female. 41) Dorsal habitus. 42) Lateral habitus. 43) Distal antennomeres. 44) Lapazina fuscipennis, male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458934" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458934/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 39</figureCitation>
)), and pronotum with T-shaped dark brown area anteriorly (with transverse dark brown macula in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FA57FA12FEEA8041" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FA57FA12FEEA8041" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
). The female of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FE28FA32FD268041" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento" authorityYear="2020" box="[508,758,1513,1537]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ashaninka" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FE28FA32FD268041" box="[508,758,1513,1537]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Callanga ashaninka</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E4C657F0FFC7FF94FD29FA32FC8A8040" box="[765,858,1513,1536]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
differs from that of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FB99FA32FB338041" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[1101,1251,1513,1537]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenebrosa">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FB99FA32FB338041" box="[1101,1251,1513,1537]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. tenebrosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FB27FA32FAA48041" box="[1267,1396,1513,1537]" captionStart="Figures 34–44" captionStartId="24.[192,287,1789,1811]" captionTargetBox="[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetId="figure-90@24.[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetPageId="24" captionText="Figures 34–44. Callanga and Lapazina spp. 34–36) Callanga tenebrosa, paratype female. 34) Dorsal habitus. 35) Lateral habitus. 36) Distal antennomeres. 37–39) Callanga trichocera, paratype female. 37) Dorsal habitus. 38) Lateral habitus.39) Distal antennomeres.40) Callanga trichocera, paratype male, dorsal habitus. 41–43)Lapazina fuscipennis, female. 41) Dorsal habitus. 42) Lateral habitus. 43) Distal antennomeres. 44) Lapazina fuscipennis, male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458934" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458934/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 34–36</figureCitation>
) by the pubescence and erect setae shorter (longer in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FCCDF9D1FC7E8061" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[793,942,1545,1569]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenebrosa">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FCCDF9D1FC7E8061" box="[793,942,1545,1569]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. tenebrosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FC6AF9D2FBC28061" box="[958,1042,1545,1569]" captionStart="Figures 34–44" captionStartId="24.[192,287,1789,1811]" captionTargetBox="[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetId="figure-90@24.[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetPageId="24" captionText="Figures 34–44. Callanga and Lapazina spp. 34–36) Callanga tenebrosa, paratype female. 34) Dorsal habitus. 35) Lateral habitus. 36) Distal antennomeres. 37–39) Callanga trichocera, paratype female. 37) Dorsal habitus. 38) Lateral habitus.39) Distal antennomeres.40) Callanga trichocera, paratype male, dorsal habitus. 41–43)Lapazina fuscipennis, female. 41) Dorsal habitus. 42) Lateral habitus. 43) Distal antennomeres. 44) Lapazina fuscipennis, male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458934" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458934/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 36</figureCitation>
)), pronotum with T-shaped dark brown anterior area (entirely dark on wide central area in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FC55F9F1FBC68002" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[897,1046,1578,1602]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenebrosa">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FC55F9F1FBC68002" box="[897,1046,1578,1602]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. tenebrosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), and sides of prothorax entirely yellowish-brown (
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FE45F991FE328022" box="[401,482,1610,1634]" captionStart="Figures 45–52" captionStartId="25.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[229,1402,213,1814]" captionTargetId="figure-59@25.[229,1403,213,1814]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="Figures 45–52. Callanga ashaninka. 45–48) Holotype male. 45) Dorsal habitus. 46) Ventral habitus. 47) Lateral habitus. 48) Head, frontal view. 49–52) Paratype female. 49) Dorsal habitus. 50) Ventral habitus. 51) Lateral habitus. 52) Distal antennomeres." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458936" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458936/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 51</figureCitation>
) (brown with large, transverse yellowish-brown macula in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FB42F990FAF78022" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[1174,1319,1610,1634]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenebrosa">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FB42F990FAF78022" box="[1174,1319,1610,1634]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. tenebrosa</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FAE3F991FA598022" box="[1335,1417,1610,1634]" captionStart="Figures 34–44" captionStartId="24.[192,287,1789,1811]" captionTargetBox="[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetId="figure-90@24.[272,1361,213,1761]" captionTargetPageId="24" captionText="Figures 34–44. Callanga and Lapazina spp. 34–36) Callanga tenebrosa, paratype female. 34) Dorsal habitus. 35) Lateral habitus. 36) Distal antennomeres. 37–39) Callanga trichocera, paratype female. 37) Dorsal habitus. 38) Lateral habitus.39) Distal antennomeres.40) Callanga trichocera, paratype male, dorsal habitus. 41–43)Lapazina fuscipennis, female. 41) Dorsal habitus. 42) Lateral habitus. 43) Distal antennomeres. 44) Lapazina fuscipennis, male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458934" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458934/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 35</figureCitation>
)).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF3CF9B0FA8980C3" blockId="13.[190,1440,1221,1667]" box="[232,1369,1643,1667]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
The three species of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FE36F9B0FD8380C3" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[482,595,1643,1667]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FE36F9B0FD8380C3" box="[482,595,1643,1667]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Callanga</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
were described from 
<collectingCountry id="B5967609FFC7FF94FC8CF9B0FC4380C2" box="[856,915,1643,1666]" name="Peru" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Peru</collectingCountry>
(
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FC77F9B0FBEF80C3" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1973" box="[931,1087,1643,1667]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Callanga" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trichocera">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FC77F9B0FBEF80C3" box="[931,1087,1643,1667]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">C. trichocera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
also occurs in 
<collectingCountry id="B5967609FFC7FF94FB26F9B0FA9D80C3" box="[1266,1357,1643,1667]" name="Bolivia" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Bolivia</collectingCountry>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14F960FB2A8093" blockId="13.[192,1274,1723,1780]" box="[192,1274,1723,1748]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14F960FB2A8093" bold="true" box="[192,1274,1723,1748]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC7FF94FF14F960FB998093" authority="Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento" authorityName="Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento" authorityYear="2020" box="[192,1097,1723,1748]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lazulina" status="new species">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14F960FE1A8093" bold="true" box="[192,458,1723,1747]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fredlanea lazulina</emphasis>
Santos-Silva, Heffern, Botero and Nascimento
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E4C657F0FFC7FF94FB82F967FB2A8093" box="[1110,1274,1723,1748]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14F907FE8280B4" blockId="13.[192,1274,1723,1780]" box="[192,338,1756,1780]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
(
<figureCitation id="55BA2A1CFFC7FF94FF1DF907FE9A80B4" box="[201,330,1756,1780]" captionStart="Figures 53–60" captionStartId="26.[192,287,1846,1868]" captionTargetBox="[257,1375,214,1813]" captionTargetId="figure-67@26.[257,1375,213,1813]" captionTargetPageId="26" captionText="Figures 53–60. Fredlanea spp. 53–56) Fredlanea lazulina, holotype male.53) Dorsal habitus.54) Ventral habitus. 55) Lateral habitus. 56) Head, frontal view. 57–60) Fredlanea consobrina, female. 57) Dorsal habitus. 58) Lateral habitus. 59) Lateral habitus, holotype. 60) Dorsal habitus, holotype." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5458938" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5458938/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Fig. 53–56</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC7FF96FF14F8D7FA4F8503" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="13" pageNumber="12" type="description">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC7FF94FF14F8D7FE6081C5" blockId="13.[190,1442,1804,1926]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC7FF94FF14F8D7FE318164" bold="true" box="[192,481,1804,1828]" pageId="13" pageNumber="12">Description. Female.</emphasis>
Integument mostly blackish-blue; mouthparts reddish brown except mostly brownish maxillary palpomere IV and labial palpomere III; anterior third of labrum reddish brown; elytra orangish except blackish-blue apex, and reddish-brown epipleural margin and inclined area close to dark apical apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC4FF97FF14FF0CFDFA8314" blockId="14.[190,1442,215,1364]" pageId="14" pageNumber="13">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC4FF97FF14FF0CFEC186AF" bold="true" box="[192,273,215,239]" pageId="14" pageNumber="13">Head.</emphasis>
Frons abundantly micropunctate, with fine punctures interspersed (fine punctures sparser toward clypeus); with minute, almost inconspicuous yellowish-white pubescence absent close to clypeus, denser and longer close to eyes; with a few long, erect black setae close to eyes. Area between antennal tubercles and sides of area between upper eye lobes with dense yellowish-white pubescence, continuing along vertex to prothoracic margin as two slightly divergent bands; central area between upper eye lobes with somewhat dense brown pubescence; remaining central area of vertex with short, very sparse brownish setae; central area of vertex coarsely sparsely punctate, except row of coarse punctures close to each dense pubescent band, and with long, erect, sparse black setae interspersed (absent in area close to prothorax). Area behind eyes coarsely, sparsely punctate (punctures denser, somewhat finer close to eye); with moderately dense brown pubescence close to eye, nearly glabrous on remaining surface; area of connection between eye lobes with longitudinal, dense yellowish-white pubescent band from eye to prothoracic margin. Genae abundantly micropunctate except smooth apex; with dense, large yellowishwhite pubescent macula laterally close to inferior margin of eye; with somewhat sparse yellowish-white pubescence frontally close to eye, continuing toward smooth area close to frons, nearly glabrous on remaining surface, and glabrous in smooth area. Antennal tubercles with somewhat abundant brown pubescence not obscuring integument (appearing to be dark due to integument color), with long, erect black setae interspersed. Wide central area of postclypeus densely micropunctate, punctures slightly coarser toward smooth apex; glabrous. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior 2/3, oblique at anterior third; posterior 2/3 with slightly depressed large area close to oblique anterior third, separated by area close to anteclypeus by abrupt slope; posterior 2/3 densely micropunctate (punctures slightly coarser than on postclypeus); oblique area densely micropunctate (punctures finer than in central area of postclypeus); posterior 2/3 with minute yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument, with a few long, erect golden setae close to anteclypeus; anterior third glabrous. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous except for a few long, erect dark setae in strongly oblique anterior area. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.35 times length of scape (0.26 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.82 times length of scape (0.61 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 1.9 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at apex of antennomere VII. Scape very finely, abundantly punctate except smooth apex; with dark pubescence not obscuring integument, somewhat bristly ventrally, with a few long, erect brownish setae interspersed. Pedicel with somewhat dense and bristly pubescence, with long, erect dark setae interspersed ventrally. Antennomere III with dense, bristly dark pubescence, absent in part of dorsal surface, with long, erect, abundant black setae ventrally and inferior inner area. Antennomeres IV–X with abundant, somewhat bristly (more so ventrally) dark pubescence throughout; with long, abundant, erect dark setae ventrally, gradually shorter and sparser toward X (distinctly sparser on IX and X). Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.57; pedicel = 0.09; IV = 0.63; V = 0.51; VI = 0.48; VII = 0.42; VIII = 0.37; IX = 0.33; X = 0.28; XI = 0.29.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC4FF96FF14FAB7FC6484DE" blockId="14.[190,1442,1388,1926]" lastBlockId="15.[190,1441,215,670]" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="14" pageNumber="13">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC4FF97FF14FAB7FEFC83C4" bold="true" box="[192,300,1388,1412]" pageId="14" pageNumber="13">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax slightly narrower posteriorly than anteriorly. Pronotum distinctly widely convex about anterior third to posterior quarter; with distinct, rounded tubercle on each side of center of convex area, placed slightly before middle, and longitudinal, slightly distinct central gibbosity placed in convex area, and another comma-shaped tubercle on each side; coarsely, sparsely punctate (punctures absent on tubercles and gibbosity); with dense yellowish-white pubescence laterally, except glabrous commashaped tubercles, glabrous in most of central area, with yellowish-brown pubescence in anterior third, not obscuring integument and not reaching anterior margin, and yellowish-brown pubescence posteriorly (in both areas appearing to be darker due to the integument color); with long, erect, sparse brownish setae in area with dense pubescence. Sides of prothorax coarsely, somewhat sparsely punctate; with dense yellowish-white pubescence close to pronotum (continuing that on sides of pronotum), and wide pubescent yellowish-white pubescent band close to prosternum; with a few long, erect brownish setae. Prosternum finely, sparsely punctate; with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, sparser centrally. Prosternal process with yellowish-white pubescence denser than in central area of prosternum; narrowest area about 0.2 times width of procoxal cavity. Mesoventral process distinctly widened laterally in posterior half; narrowest area about 0.5 times width of mesocoxal cavity. Ventral surface of meso- and metathorax with abundant, short yellowish-white pubescence, but not entirely obscuring integument, except glabrous metathoracic discrimen; metaventrite with erect, sparse yellowish-white setae interspersed. Scutellum transverse, almost truncate posteriorly, with minute yellowish-white pubescence distinctly not obscuring integument. 
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FCCCFF23FCA68750" bold="true" box="[792,886,248,272]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Elytra.</emphasis>
Coarsely, abundantly punctate in basal half, punctures finer, sparser toward apex (nearly indistinct in posterior seventh); humeral carina distinct from base to near apex; with two dorsal carinae from base to about posterior quarter; with longitudinal carina between humeral carina and epipleural margin, from base to about middle; apex concave, with outer and sutural angles triangularly projected; with minute yellowish-white pubescence, indistinct depending on viewing angle; with a few somewhat short, erect yellowish-white setae dorsally in posterior quarter, and long, erect, brownish setae on epipleural margin (setae slightly longer and more abundant toward apex). 
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FEBCFE3BFE7F87B8" bold="true" box="[360,431,480,504]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, slightly denser ventrally, especially on meso- and metafemora, with long, erect setae of same color ventrally, slightly more abundant in basal third. Tibiae with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, yellower and denser ventrally and in area of dorsal sulcus of mesotibiae; with long, erect dark brown setae interspersed (yellowish on anterior third). Tarsi with grayish-white pubescence dorsally, sparser on tarsomere III and part of V (pubescence denser on metatarsi).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC5FF96FF14FD6CFAB184B0" blockId="15.[192,1440,695,752]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FF14FD6CFE9A848F" bold="true" box="[192,330,695,719]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, shorter centrally (almost indistinct depending on viewing angle); apex of ventrite V strongly emarginate centrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC5FF96FF14FCD2FA4F8503" blockId="15.[192,1440,777,835]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FF14FCD2FE178562" bold="true" box="[192,455,777,802]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Dimensions in mm.</emphasis>
Total length 14.70; prothoracic length 2.60; anterior prothoracic width 2.90; posterior prothoracic width 2.70; widest prothoracic width 3.00; humeral width 3.60; elytral length 10.15.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC5FF96FF14FC87FE2F85D5" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC5FF96FF14FC87FE2F85D5" blockId="15.[192,1440,859,917]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FF14FC87FE5F8534" bold="true" box="[192,399,860,884]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation id="7DE93CC4FFC5FF96FE4EFC87FE2F85D5" collectingDate="2018-05-05" collectionCode="TAMU, DHCO" country="Colombia" location="Otanche" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Boyaca" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC5FF96FE4EFC87FDD98534" box="[410,521,860,884]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Holotype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry id="B5967609FFC5FF96FD63FC87FC848534" box="[695,852,860,884]" name="Colombia" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">COLOMBIA</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="0F45F87BFFC5FF96FCB0FC80FC098536" box="[868,985,859,886]" country="Colombia" name="Boyaca" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">BOYACÁ</collectingRegion>
: 
<location id="C85E6042FFC5FF96FC3FFC87FB868534" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:4528878FFFC1FF96FF14F98DFD7E802E:C85E6042FFC5FF96FC3FFC87FB868534" box="[1003,1110,860,884]" country="Colombia" name="Otanche" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" stateProvince="Boyaca">Otanche</location>
, 
<date id="B93F1059FFC5FF96FBB2FC87FB358534" box="[1126,1253,860,884]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" value="2018-05-05">
<collectingDate id="A97BE9B1FFC5FF96FBB2FC87FB358534" box="[1126,1253,860,884]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" value="2018-05-05">05.V.2018</collectingDate>
</date>
, local collector (
<collectionCode id="AB90AE5CFFC5FF96FF1CFCA6FEF085D5" box="[200,288,893,917]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">TAMU</collectionCode>
, formerly 
<collectionCode id="AB90AE5CFFC5FF96FE4FFCA6FE2285D5" box="[411,498,893,917]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">DHCO</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC5FF96FF14FC75FDB785A7" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC5FF96FF14FC75FDB785A7" blockId="15.[190,1441,942,999]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FF14FC75FE888586" bold="true" box="[192,344,942,966]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Etymology.</emphasis>
The epithet “ 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FE21FC75FD888586" box="[501,600,942,966]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lazulina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FE21FC75FD888586" box="[501,600,942,966]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">lazulina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
” refers to lapis lazuli, a deep-blue mineral, alluding to the predominant blackish-blue color of the 
<typeStatus id="123A883BFFC5FF96FE23FC14FDB385A7" box="[503,611,975,999]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="859B6512FFC5FF96FF14FBDAFD7E802E" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC5FF96FF14FBDAFCCF8341" blockId="15.[190,1441,1025,1646]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FF14FBDAFE938259" bold="true" box="[192,323,1025,1049]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Remarks.</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="A9104B68FFC5FF96FE9FFBDAFD018259" author="Galileo, M. H. M. &amp; A. Santos-Silva" box="[331,721,1025,1049]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" pagination="589 - 593" refId="ref14303" refString="Galileo, M. H. M., and A. Santos-Silva. 2016. Notes on the differences between Fredlanea and Eulachnesia, and description of a new species (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Hemilophini). Zootaxa 4097 (4): 589 - 593." type="journal article" year="2016">Galileo and Santos-Silva (2016)</bibRefCitation>
discussed the differences between 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FB57FBDAFEB5827A" authority="Martins and Galileo, 1996" authorityName="Martins and Galileo" authorityYear="1996" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FB57FBDAFAD08259" box="[1155,1280,1025,1049]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Fredlanea</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="A9104B68FFC5FF96FAD3FBDAFEB5827A" author="Martins, U. R. &amp; M. H. M. Galileo" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" pagination="189 - 196" refId="ref14969" refString="Martins, U. R., and M. H. M. Galileo. 1996. Divisao de Eulachnesia Bates, 1872 e descricao de novos taxons (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Hemilophini). Revista Brasileira de Entomologia 40 (2): 189 - 196." type="journal article" year="1996">Martins and Galileo, 1996</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FE73FBF9FD0F827A" authority="Bates, 1872" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1872" box="[423,735,1058,1082]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FE73FBF9FDEE827A" box="[423,574,1058,1082]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Eulachnesia</emphasis>
Bates, 1872
</taxonomicName>
. Even so, the differences between these genera are still very problematic and, depending on the feature considered, 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FC4BFB98FBCC821B" authorityName="Martins and Galileo" authorityYear="1996" box="[927,1052,1091,1115]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FC4BFB98FBCC821B" box="[927,1052,1091,1115]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Fredlanea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
may in the future prove to be a synonym of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FE82FBBFFE3C823C" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1872" box="[342,492,1124,1148]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FE82FBBFFE3C823C" box="[342,492,1124,1148]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Eulachnesia</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. This is particularly true if the humeral carina was considered because both the type-species of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FE7AFB5EFD9582DD" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1872" box="[430,581,1157,1181]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FE7AFB5EFD9582DD" box="[430,581,1157,1181]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Eulachnesia</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FD81FB5EFBDE82DD" authority="Bates, 1866" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1866" box="[597,1038,1157,1181]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Amphionycha" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sapphira">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FD81FB5EFCA582DD" box="[597,885,1157,1181]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Amphionycha sapphira</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="A9104B68FFC5FF96FCA9FB5DFBDE82DD" author="Bates, H. W." box="[893,1038,1157,1181]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" pagination="425 - 435" refId="ref13594" refString="Bates, H. W. 1866. Contributions to an insect fauna of the Amazon Valley. Coleoptera: Longicornes. The Annals and Magazine of Natural History (3) 17: 425 - 435." type="journal article" year="1866">Bates, 1866</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
= 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FBE5FB5EFF2C82FF" authority="Fabricius, 1801" authorityName="Fabricius" authorityYear="1801" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Saperda" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="humeralis">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FBE5FB5EFACD82DD" box="[1073,1309,1157,1181]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Saperda humeralis</emphasis>
Fabricius, 1801
</taxonomicName>
) and 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FEEFFB7DFE6882FE" authorityName="Martins and Galileo" authorityYear="1996" box="[315,440,1190,1214]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FEEFFB7DFE6882FE" box="[315,440,1190,1214]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Fredlanea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FE1CFB7DFC8582FE" authority="Lane, 1966" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1966" box="[456,853,1190,1214]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="velutina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FE1CFB7DFD1982FE" box="[456,713,1190,1214]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Eulachnesia velutina</emphasis>
Lane, 1966
</taxonomicName>
) have very distinct humeral carina. On the other hand, there are species in both genera lacking humeral carina. The new species is allocated in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FAF6FB13FA4E82A0" authorityName="Martins and Galileo" authorityYear="1996" box="[1314,1438,1224,1248]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FAF6FB13FA4E82A0" box="[1314,1438,1224,1248]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Fredlanea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
because it has no squamiform setae on the elytra.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC5FF96FF3CFAD1FCCB8324" blockId="15.[190,1441,1025,1646]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FF3CFAD1FE028362" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento" authorityYear="2020" box="[232,466,1290,1314]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lazulina" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FF3CFAD1FE028362" box="[232,466,1290,1314]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Fredlanea lazulina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E4C657F0FFC5FF96FE0DFAD1FDE78361" box="[473,567,1290,1313]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
differs from 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FD02FAD0FBF58362" authority="(Bates, 1881)" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1881" box="[726,1061,1290,1314]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aequatoria">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FD02FAD0FCAA8362" box="[726,890,1291,1314]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">F. aequatoria</emphasis>
(Bates, 1881)
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FBE6FAD0FAAB8362" authority="(Lane, 1970)" baseAuthorityName="Lane" baseAuthorityYear="1970" box="[1074,1403,1290,1314]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="consobrina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FBE6FAD0FB078362" box="[1074,1239,1290,1314]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">F. consobrina</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation id="A9104B68FFC5FF96FB33FAD1FAA28362" author="Lane, F." box="[1255,1394,1290,1314]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" pagination="369 - 428" refId="ref14490" refString="Lane, F. 1970. Cerambycoidea Neotropica nova VII (Coleoptera). Studia Entomologica 13 (1 - 4): 369 - 428." type="journal article" year="1970">Lane, 1970</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FA53FAD0FE3A8303" authority="(Lane, 1966)" baseAuthorityName="Lane" baseAuthorityYear="1966" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavipennis">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FA53FAD0FE968303" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">F. flavipennis</emphasis>
(Lane, 1966)
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FDFAFAF7FC978303" authority="(Fuchs, 1970)" baseAuthorityName="Fuchs" baseAuthorityYear="1970" box="[558,839,1323,1347]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hiekei">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FDFAFAF7FD488303" box="[558,664,1323,1347]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">F. hiekei</emphasis>
(Fuchs, 1970)
</taxonomicName>
by the setae on the antennomeres much denser (distinctly sparser in both sexes of these species).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CD3E3699FFC5FF96FF3CFAB5FD7E802E" blockId="15.[190,1441,1025,1646]" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">
As the separation between 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FDF3FAB6FD7283C5" authorityName="Martins and Galileo" authorityYear="1996" box="[551,674,1389,1413]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FDF3FAB6FD7283C5" box="[551,674,1389,1413]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Fredlanea</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FD0EFAB6FCA083C5" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1872" box="[730,880,1389,1413]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FD0EFAB6FCA083C5" box="[730,880,1389,1413]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Eulachnesia</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is still problematic, we think better to compare the new species with some species of the latter. The general appearance of the new species resembles that of 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FEC6FA6BFCFF8388" authority="Monne and Monne, 2015" authorityName="Monne and Monne" authorityYear="2015" box="[274,815,1456,1480]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boteroi">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FEC6FA6BFE2F8388" box="[274,511,1456,1480]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Eulachnesia boteroi</emphasis>
Monné and Monné, 2015
</taxonomicName>
, but the presence of a distinct humeral carina allows the separation of them (absent in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FDB4FA09FD0583A9" authorityName="Monne and Monne" authorityYear="2015" box="[608,725,1489,1513]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="boteroi">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FDB4FA09FD0583A9" box="[608,725,1489,1513]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">E. boteroi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
). 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FD39FA0AFC0783A9" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Heffern &amp; Botero &amp; de &amp; Nascimento" authorityYear="2020" box="[749,983,1489,1513]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Fredlanea" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lazulina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FD39FA0AFC0783A9" box="[749,983,1489,1513]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">Fredlanea lazulina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FBA1FA09FA7083A9" authority="Bates, 1881" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[1141,1440,1489,1513]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cobaltina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FBA1FA09FAD883A9" box="[1141,1288,1489,1513]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">E. cobaltina</emphasis>
Bates, 1881
</taxonomicName>
by the humeral carina well-marked (slightly marked in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FCB5FA28FC23804A" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[865,1011,1522,1546]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cobaltina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FCB5FA28FC23804A" box="[865,1011,1522,1546]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">E. cobaltina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
) and erect setae dense ventrally on antennomeres (sparser in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FDD7F9CFFD46806B" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[515,662,1555,1579]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cobaltina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FDD7F9CFFD46806B" box="[515,662,1555,1579]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">E. cobaltina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
). It differs from 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FCB6F9CFFC33806B" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1881" box="[866,995,1555,1579]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Lamacoscylus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="humilis">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FCB6F9CFFC33806B" box="[866,995,1555,1579]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">E. humilis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the punctures on pronotum finer (coarser in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FE9DF9EEFE0C800C" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[329,476,1588,1612]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cobaltina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FE9DF9EEFE0C800C" box="[329,476,1588,1612]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">E. cobaltina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
) and absence of longitudinal pubescent band in center of pronotum (present in 
<taxonomicName id="0A814D1AFFC5FF96FF14F98DFE83802E" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1881" box="[192,339,1622,1646]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Eulachnesia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cobaltina">
<emphasis id="FFF5EA8BFFC5FF96FF14F98DFE83802E" box="[192,339,1622,1646]" italics="true" pageId="15" pageNumber="14">E. cobaltina</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, but often absent centrally).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>