<document id="6A98D09E4C8C73B8F3871433C7E5286A" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.635.10604" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bff72997-9a13-47a8-88d4-f7ecdf478720" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127870915" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-635-53" ID-ZBK="8F2DB24A9E8D43D282471D65B995E86F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D0556EA9-F25D-458F-9FDD-EEAFACAEA53F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-635-53" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 635" ModsDocTitle="Two new species of pontogeneiid amphipods (Crustacea, Senticaudata, Calliopioidea) from Korean waters" checkinTime="1480088961796" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Jung, Tae Won, Kim, Jong Guk &amp; Yoon, Seong Myeong" docDate="2016" docId="4750ECC45F1C90892103CF6DB07B786F" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 635: 53-79" docOrigin="ZooKeys 635" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.635.10604" docTitle="Paramoera dentipleurae Jung, Kim &amp; Yoon, 2016, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="D0556EA9-F25D-458F-9FDD-EEAFACAEA53F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="67" masterDocId="FFCB7576FF92C00EFFC7F675FF8FBB6B" masterDocTitle="Two new species of pontogeneiid amphipods (Crustacea, Senticaudata, Calliopioidea) from Korean waters" masterLastPageNumber="79" masterPageNumber="53" pageId="6" pageNumber="59" updateTime="1643596765071" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="36660162B594711F6B761D4B531CDEC1" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="A20A82C2B63EBDCEC408283305F5A12A">
<mods:title id="97E7BACD04739EA6546B2A9AA45A9278">Two new species of pontogeneiid amphipods (Crustacea, Senticaudata, Calliopioidea) from Korean waters</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A16655E8B7BAA5FB2AB190036242C6CC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D3BCB1A54A3854ACBFCFA328E7BB4EC9">
<mods:roleTerm id="168D755BAE348266361C3D7915CDFAB5">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2D9B3B3C72274AE532AA24BCCDAC0BEF">Jung, Tae Won</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="B0C77A9AFE24D43AA7081779D6DF28E5" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A759D04813E7EDDB4777AF0E137816E7">
<mods:roleTerm id="534C2C6E83275A1C0DB52CBFAB7044C8">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="425C336F9E0B88864EDE01E811D4810D">Kim, Jong Guk</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="629B4DBF54218F002B1041A1492AECAC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="FEF410B964C79A7A43A64890C707F02B">
<mods:roleTerm id="C773422D27BBEE7A2D8355299E34EDC0">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="9ADF3CC9F5ADEB949A707A9FA03217CF">Yoon, Seong Myeong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="B0DBC24F18C6F2848E01B74A29EB3F03">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="9AE5A73B9F12584734B332A4979B65CB" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="791D450296B3F2EBB6F83E4EE0CA031C">
<mods:title id="1065C97C4DD8E9C00F6A9AD9833794E9">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="8CB8B5D171C77ED0837673834A995222">
<mods:date id="8E7BABC4ACAB31C7BF33929432B712C2">2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="20C6C7FB862FEC53DBE3CEABE5E8D5E8" type="volume">
<mods:number id="C96F09DC05EA8DAF32011C87BD164DC9">635</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="E84FA14D93C7BD8819623F4BC347EA9F" unit="page">
<mods:start id="D1AB2FFED22BB3B6323A3CE32731BC9B">53</mods:start>
<mods:end id="75BEB5155D4C6E62BA9920C535367E5D">79</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="DA8E895F05A56EECB37712689310B9C0">
<mods:url id="473A636EC57E8207FD00DD4CF23E75D3">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.635.10604</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="8966D51C47906C0FC0939DF75235BF95">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="F4DE519B6A1F093A0DB40E9F8892606C" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.635.10604</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="5193151EEA284F86E39EABE0BE69D725" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-635-53</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="2F805133B316F97D40D72FE811E5EE7E" type="ZBK">8F2DB24A9E8D43D282471D65B995E86F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E64622EED6A5C95488DA10E3D53BCEE9" type="ZooBank">8F2DB24A9E8D43D282471D65B995E86F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="4750ECC45F1C90892103CF6DB07B786F" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127870915" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D0556EA9-F25D-458F-9FDD-EEAFACAEA53F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4750ECC45F1C90892103CF6DB07B786F" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
<subSubSection id="ED90F4161F7B3B9070801BE57DE59DA6" pageId="6" pageNumber="59" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="80A91DE83ABECBC026AEBC96BDCEBD19" pageId="6" pageNumber="59">
<taxonomicName id="B073FB87E5E1E56D1B614EC02D169CB5" LSID="http://zoobank.org/D0556EA9-F25D-458F-9FDD-EEAFACAEA53F" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="B9E258A272E6844833775519CBAE91FE" pageId="6" pageNumber="59">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 7, 8, 9, 10, 11
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="DDB883C8C943F1D1A0F5A2A4C29B7694" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" type="type locality">
<paragraph id="BB598070A536FECD48598D52395C4CCF" pageId="7" pageNumber="60">
<pageBreakToken id="7C6689AE03C8B5B5A5877371E71C4253" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
locality.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9EEDD17ED8B290226A9C23DF15AD9BA5" pageId="7" pageNumber="60">
Jeju Island, South Korea, 
<geoCoordinate id="61ADE413346E62BEF300D2915B88B7AA" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="33.239723">33°14'23&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate id="BC86A7132A4173429E0771C628C9DD63" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="126.58305">126°34'59&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, sublittoral (average depth 24 m).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="56791DCD20C3B73D312A0866EDF2E562" pageId="7" pageNumber="60" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="35C6058C180E9F7E54EE5A69106F2D14" pageId="7" pageNumber="60">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D3B0FB282826E762D0980C50FB8F7850" pageId="7" pageNumber="60">Holotype: NIBRIV0000328602, adult female, 7.6 mm, collected from the type locality on 30 Nov 2012 by Prof. H.-Y. Soh.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="302A344A2A02C9C5308C24689B0FF75A" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="61519FE8A3CC278AA1A2CED25817ECD4" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<pageBreakToken id="143ED99F34E5B26DAE17A21719FDC372" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" start="start">Etymology</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2167ECC53AAFAECA6CA375F546662512" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
The composite epithet of the species name of 
<taxonomicName id="41983C2B8B37F153CE96C15E3DB25853" genus="Calliopioidea" lsidName="Calliopioidea dentipleurae" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
is a combination of Latin dens, Gen. dentis (meaning 
<normalizedToken id="83F7E859772867AA3B65D06B056E0726" originalValue="‘teeth’">'teeth'</normalizedToken>
or 
<normalizedToken id="5F1F154F9C0CEB0473C3A86807672A60" originalValue="‘serration’">'serration'</normalizedToken>
) and pleurae (indicating 'pleonal 
<normalizedToken id="7296F1FC66232EDAA4AEDD5B7F5E112C" originalValue="epimera’">epimera'</normalizedToken>
). Noun in apposition.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C9CC27F6E0AB6B73DD4A84ED6CFBE491" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="EDE4CB2FB262F50267F49DB8FBDA2312" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3B2958C1C680D7CF17A4ADC0B28B768C" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Head with short rostrum; lateral cephalic lobes not mammilliform, with sinusoid upper part; inferior antennal sinus forming deep notch, lower margin produced forward; eyes large, reniform. Antenna 1 with stout peduncular articles; accessory flagellum uni-articulate, short, scale-like. Antenna 2 slightly shorter than antenna 1. Lower lip outer lobe with 5 bifid setae mediodistally. Right mandible with 6-dentate incisor and bifid lacinia mobilis. Left mandible with 6-dentate incisor and 5-dentate lacinia mobilis. Maxilla 1 outer plate with 10 dentate robust setae apically; palp bi-articulate, apex beyond apical setae of outer plate. Maxilla 2 inner plate shorter than outer plate. Maxilliped outer plate as long as inner plate, with long serrate setae along apex and medial margins submarginally; palp articles 2 and 3 slender. Gnathopods 1 and 2 moderately subchelate. Gnathopod 1 palm oblique, with robust defining setae of 1, 1, 3 laterally and 2, 3, 1 medially in formulae. Gnathopod 2 palm more oblique than in gnathopod 1, with robust defining setae laterally in formula 1, 2, 1. Pereopods 3-7 dactylus short, with blunt protrusion bearing 1 seta on inner margin, apex curved and claw-like. Pereopods 5-7 elongate and slender. Pereopod 7 basis expanded posteriorly, angulate proximally and diminished distally. Pereonite 7 and pleonites 1-3 carinate dorsally. Pleonal epimeron 1 with 2 naked serrations and 1 weak notch posteriorly; epimeron 2 with 2 serrations bearing 1 minute seta and 1 naked notch posteriorly; epimeron 3 largest, weakly upturned posterodistally, with 5 serrations and 1 distal small notch bearing 1 minute seta posteriorly. Uropod 1 slender; peduncle longer than rami. Uropod 2 shortest. Uropod 3 rami lanceolate, longer than peduncle. Telson deeply cleft (approximately 3/4 length).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E8D7400C2805687BC463C3F3CF0FB0DD" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="66" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="description">
<paragraph id="5072D1475CD8015DDA3FF1AD7F9DD198" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Description of holotype male.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F2CC7238E53EAFE26CFE271E7160DCC9" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Head (Fig. 7A): rostrum short; lateral cephalic lobes not mammilliform, with sinusoid upper part; inferior antennal sinus forming deep notch, lower margin produced forward; eyes large, reniform.</paragraph>
<caption id="059A9F8FB91845EDD2DC3EEEC3862026" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<paragraph id="D6A15008E002B41DB3646E081BA06BB7" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName id="91798E30813CD214B7598CA8D85802F1" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype. A Head B Antenna 1 C Posterodistal part of peduncular article 1 on antenna 1 D Posterodistal part of peduncular article 2 on antenna 1 E Accessory flagellum F Calceoli of flagellum on antenna 1 G Antenna 2 H Calceoli of flagellum on antenna 2 I Upper lip J Lower lip K Right mandible L Left mandible M Maxilla 1 N Dentate apical setae of outer plate on maxilla 1 O Maxilla 2. Scale bars 0.05 mm (
<normalizedToken id="331E25EBA6BAAE12A91878B6539A35B7" originalValue="C–F">C-F</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken id="1C93E207A2899160325015DE2C74EA02" originalValue="H–M">H-M</normalizedToken>
, O), 0.1 mm (N), 0.2 mm (A, B, G).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="04DDFB2A63992814E1FAFCB343BADC79" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Antenna 1 (Fig. 7
<normalizedToken id="EFB9CECF2F71F88881F4F07D77733C5E" originalValue="B–F">B-F</normalizedToken>
): peduncular articles stout, with length ratio of 1.0:0.8:0.5 in peduncular articles 1-3, each article with 4-6 groups of elongate setae along posterior margin; peduncular article 1 with 1 robust seta posterodistally and with small triangular lobe on surface posterodistally; peduncular article 2 also with 1 robust seta posterodistally; peduncular article 3 without posterodistal setae; accessory flagellum uni-articulate, short, scale-like, with 5 simple setae on apex and 1 simple seta anteroproximally; flagellum 33-articulate, 2.0 times as long as peduncular articles 1-3 combined, proximal article longest, with aesthetasc present on every alternate article and calceoli present from 3rd to 24th articles posterodistally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4CAE4874D73F0FDC30E7F0FE51253D8B" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Antenna 2 (Fig. 7G, H): slightly shorter than antenna 1; gland cone produced with 2 simple setae; peduncular articles stout, with length ratio of 1.0:1.7:1.8 in peduncular articles 3-5; flagellum 29-articulate, 1.6 times as long as peduncular articles 3-5 combined, proximal article longest, with calceoli present from 1st to 20th articles.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3B22D3C49B7E8E4ABFBE1592B517DB67" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Upper lip (Fig. 7I): triangular, apical margin convex, covered with fine setae distally.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5DCB89BEE04395C00F1B2D607640C4B0" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
<pageBreakToken id="147CFF2683C8241B526943818C9963E3" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" start="start">Lower</pageBreakToken>
lip (Fig. 7J): with well-developed mandibular processes bearing round apices; outer lobe apically round with 5 bifid setae mediodistally; inner lobe weak.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3FA4B441F526AE947C6931DE9ABAE815" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Right mandible (Fig. 7K): with 6-dentate incisor and bifid lacinia mobilis; accessory setal row lined with 1 simple, 5 serrate and 2 simple setae in turn; molar triturative, columnar, with 1 long plumose seta; palp enlarged, 3-articulate; palp article 1 shortest; palp article 2 lined with plumose setae on surface and medial margin; palp article 3 brush-like, with many simple, plumose and serrate setae along apex and medial margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="86474BFF13AF8896C1CD5E0BEA8C9323" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Left mandible (Fig. 7L): with 6-dentate incisor and 5-dentate lacinia mobilis; accessory setal row with 1 simple, 7 serrate setae and 1 simple seta in turn.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="40820BC8E82BEA833EEFA1542A403252" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Maxilla 1 (Fig. 7M, N): outer plate with 10 dentate setae apically; palp long, beyond apical setae of outer plate, article 2 with 1 row of 9 setae on surface and 8 robust setae along apical and mediodistal margins, with 1 plumose and 1 simple seta at centre of lateral margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="53A8390854D77D78AD959100A6A5466C" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Maxilla 2 (Fig. 7O): inner plate with 1 oblique row of 5 plumose setae on medial margin, with apical and subapical setae; outer plate with 2 serrate and 2 forked setae on mediodistal margin, with apical and subapical setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8CF3296A194A90F757C89BC8FFD2A045" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Maxilliped (Fig. 8A): inner plate subrectangular, swollen laterodistally, with 3 robust setae apically, with plumose setae on apex and mediodistal margin; outer plate as long as inner plate, convex laterally and wider than inner plate, with elongate plumose setae along apex and medial margin submarginally; palp elongate, slender, 4-articulate; article 2 subrectangular, longest, lined with long forked and simple setae on medial margin; article 3 thumb-shaped, with forked, serrate and simple setae on distal surface and margin; article 4 falcate, 0.8 times as long as article 3, lined with setae on medial margin, with 1 elongate seta apically.</paragraph>
<caption id="47C51ACBC7235F93B4C7B17F951B76BF" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
<paragraph id="6C8327D9848C07855D0369F225633B3A" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
Figure 8. 
<taxonomicName id="14FFEE71B9961C3B423ADFFC60BDB17D" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype. A Maxilliped B Gnathopod 1 C Setae of posterodistal margin of propodus on gnathopod 1 D Gnathopod 2 E Coxal gill of gnathopod 2. Scale bars 0.05 mm (A, C), 0.1 mm (B, D, E).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="B986BE984F02A69FAC7FD008437D0376" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 8B, C): subchelate; coxa subrectangular, ventral margin round with 5 minute setae and with 1 small notch bearing 1 minute seta posteroventrally; basis anterior margin straight with 8 minute setae, with 1 pair of elongate setae on medial surface anteroproximally, posterior margin with 1 elongate seta proximally, lined with 1 group of 4 elongate setae and with 3 minute setae, with 1 group of 3 simple setae subdistally; ischium with moderate anterior lobe, posterior margin convex with 1 simple seta and 1 group of 9 elongate setae; merus rectangular, as long as ischium, forming groove anterodistally, with medial and lateral protrusions distally, with 1 pair of short setae medially, with elongate setae in formula 1, 2, 3, 2 on posterior margin, lined with 14 long setae on distal margin; carpus longer than merus, with 1 lateral row of 5 setae anterodistally and 1 medial row of 5 setae on distal margin, posterior margin broadly lobed and weakly crenulate, with 4 groups of serrate and simple setae; propodus ovoid, as long as basis, with 4 setae on anterior margin, with 1 group of 6 simple setae at anterodistal corner, with 5 groups of serrate setae on weakly crenulate posterior margin, with setae of various combinations on medial surface, palm oblique with medial and lateral rows of simple setae, with robust defining setae of in formulae 1, 1, 3 laterally and 2, 3, 1 medially; dactylus falcate, stout, slightly shorter than palm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="46D356DE2EA0D881443748C09B6E00B1" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="63" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 8D, E): also moderately subchelate, similar to gnathopod 1 in size; coxa subrectangular, with 3 minute setae on round ventral margin anteriorly, with 
<pageBreakToken id="E59498DF19BD256C7B7082BD9CF802F7" pageId="10" pageNumber="63" start="start">2</pageBreakToken>
small notches posteroventrally, with 7 minute setae on anterodistal surface, coxal gill ovoid and large, slightly shorter than basis; basis anterior margin slightly convex lined with 10 minute setae, posterior margin with 1 elongate setae proximally and 1 group of 3 simple setae (2 elongate and 1 short) at proximal 1/3, lined with 7 simple setae and 1 group of 3 simple setae subdistally at distal half; ischium with moderate anterior lobe, posterior margin convex with 4 setae; merus as long as ischium, forming groove anterodistally, with medial and lateral protrusions distally, with 2 pairs of simple setae on anterior margin medially, with 1 seta and 2 pairs of setae on posterior margin distally, with 6 elongate setae on distal margin; carpus longer than merus, with 1 lateral row of 6 setae anterodistally, posterior margin broadly lobed and weakly crenulate with 5 groups of serrate and simple setae; propodus ovoid, as long as basis, with 4 simple setae on anterior margin, with 1 group of 6 simple setae at anterodistal corner, weakly crenulate posteriorly with 7 groups of serrate setae, palm more oblique than in gnathopod 1, with medial and lateral rows of simple setae, with robust defining setae laterally in formula 1, 2, 1; dactylus falcate, stout, slightly shorter than palm.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="73631022E073FC037FD125046210E9D5" pageId="10" pageNumber="63">Pereopod 3 (Fig. 9A, B): coxa subrectangular, convex anteriorly, with 4 minute setae on anterior surface, ventral margin round with 3 marginal and 5 submarginal setae, with 2 small notches bearing 1 minute seta at posteroventral corner, posterior margin short, coxal gill ovoid and large, as long as coxa; basis anterior margin straight with 4 pairs and 6 minute setae, posterior margin setose; ischium short, with moderate anterior lobe, with 1 minute seta on posterior margin and 1 pair of simple setae at posterodistal corner; merus 0.7 times as long as basis, anterior margin weakly spinose and slightly expanded distally, with 1 group of 3 simple setae at anterodistal corner, posterior margin weakly setose; carpus not expanded and slightly curved, with 2 groups of simple setae on anterior margin and 1 pair of simple setae at anterodistal corner, with 1 minute and 3 pairs of simple setae on posterior margin, with several minute setae at posterodistal corner, distal margin round; propodus slender, 1.1 times as long as carpus, with 3 groups of simple setae on anterior margin and 1 row of 4 setae at anterodistal corner, with 1 small seta and 2 pair of setae on posterior margin, with 1 elongate, 1 robust and 2 moderate setae at posterodistal corner; dactylus short, with blunt protrusion bearing 1 seta on inner margin, apex curved and claw-like.</paragraph>
<caption id="5E692B73055E99A91717F0D2DA84133E" pageId="10" pageNumber="63">
<paragraph id="4A6E64DDD59797B14BC4B2567C374317" pageId="10" pageNumber="63">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName id="50719856B0815E7CF2F10293C9BEBB32" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="63" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype. A Pereopod 3 B Dactylus of pereopod 3 C Pereopod 4 D Coxal gill of pereopod 4. Scale bars 0.05 mm (B), 0.2 mm (A, C, D).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="0B4CCF59C06AA9BC14B8C3C9E0C90072" pageId="10" pageNumber="63">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 9C, D): coxa subquadrate, with acutely produced posterior margin; dactylus with blunt protrusion on inner margin but weaker than that of pereopod 3; other articles similar to those of pereopod 3 except for additional 1 robust seta at posterodistal corner of basis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="633B1DFFB8EF03B13740F38541FA8704" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="10" pageNumber="63">
Pereopod 5 (Fig. 10
<normalizedToken id="4896C3152222C016D552910AEB8BFA85" originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
): elongate and slender; coxa bilobed, anterior lobe expanded downwards with 4 minute setae on ventral margin, posterior lobe not expanded with 1 small notch bearing 1 minute seta at posteroventral corner, coxal gill ovoid and small; basis subovoid, anterior margin convex with 1 group of 5 elongate setae proximally and lined with 7 robust setae, anterodistal corner weakly lobed downwards with 1 pair of robust setae, posterior margin moderately expanded with 13 weak serrations bearing 1 minute seta; ischium short, anterodistal corner weakly lobed downwards with 1 pair of setae, posterior lobe moderate; merus as long as 
<pageBreakToken id="0DFF6414D648A696206A7C37A1ADFCE4" pageId="11" pageNumber="64" start="start">basis</pageBreakToken>
, with short robust setae on anterior margin and with 1 pair of robust and simple setae at anterodistal corner, posterior margin weakly expanded and setose with robust setae, posterodistal corner slightly produced with 1 pair of unequal setae; carpus linear and slender, as long as merus, margins weakly setose, anterodistal and posterodistal corners with robust and simple setae; propodus also linear, 0.9 times as long as carpus, with 4 pairs of robust setae on anterior margin and with 1 group of 4 setae (1 simple elongate and 3 robust) at anterodistal corner, with 4 groups of robust and simple setae on posterior margin and with 10 setae (1 robust and 9 simple) at 
<pageBreakToken id="527DF29505B5CA4D00AC0524414E1E6D" pageId="12" pageNumber="65" start="start">posterodistal</pageBreakToken>
corner; dactylus short, with blunt protrusion bearing 1 seta on inner margin, with curved and claw-like apex.
</paragraph>
<caption id="56615AD07C8C66637DC8156212433E77" pageId="12" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="06642EB092A308CC552CD35E832A95F1" pageId="12" pageNumber="65">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName id="CE1BACBF518D1F9FAC7BF2994861F0EE" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="12" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype. A Pereopod 5 B Coxal gill on pereopod 5 C Distal part of carpus on pereopod 5 D Dactylus on pereopod 5 E Pereopod 6. Scale bars 0.1 mm (B), 0.05 mm (C, D), 0.2 mm (A, E).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="32E4CA6828CF9FEB7D6F20B978520E01" pageId="12" pageNumber="65">Pereopod 6 (Fig. 10E): elongate and slender, longer than pereopod 5; coxa bilobed, smaller than that of pereopod 5, anterior lobe expanded downwards with 2 minute setae anteriorly, posterior lobe not expanded with notch bearing 1 minute seta at posteroventral corner, coxal gill ovoid and slightly smaller than that of pereopod 5; basis as long as that of pereopod 5, anterior margin convex with 1 elongate seta proximally and irregular spaced 7 robust and simple setae, anterodistal corner weakly lobed downwards with 1 robust seta, posterior margin expanded proximally and diminished distally, with 13 weak serrations bearing 1 minute seta and 2 minute setae distally; ischium short, anterodistal corner weakly lobed downwards with 1 group of 3 setae, posterior lobe moderate; merus as long as basis, setose with robust and simple setae on anterior margin, with 1 pair of setae at anterodistal corner, posterior margin weakly expanded and setose with elongate and short robust setae irregularly, posterodistal corner slightly produced with 1 group of 5 setae; carpus linear and slender, 1.1 times as long as merus, margins weakly setose, anterodistal and posterodistal corners with robust and simple setae; propodus also linear, as long as carpus, with 5 groups of robust and simple setae on anterior margin, and with 1 group of 4 setae (1 simple elongate and 3 robust) at anterodistal corner, posterior margin armed with setae of various combinations, with 9 setae (8 simple elongate and 1 robust) at posterodistal corner; dactylus short, with blunt protrusion bearing 1 seta on inner margin, with curved and claw-like apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="44F2D65E7611B4F849F0CD2176C0AD58" pageId="12" pageNumber="65">Pereopod 7 (Fig. 11A, B): shorter but stouter than pereopod 6; coxa unilobed, with 1 simple seta at anterior corner, with 2 notches bearing 1 minute seta and 2 small naked notches on posterior margin; basis larger than that of pereopod 6, anterior margin widened with irregular spaced 8 minute setae, anterodistal corner a little lobed distally with 1 group of 3 robust setae, posterior margin expanded, angulate proximally and diminished distally, with 12 weak serrations bearing 1 minute seta and 2 naked serrations distally; ischium short, anterodistal corner weakly lobed downwards with 1 group of 5 robust setae, posterior lobe moderate; merus short, 0.7 times as long as basis, anterior margin straight and setose with single or paired setae, anterodistal corner weakly produced with 1 subapical simple seta and 1 pair of robust apical setae, posterior margin slightly expanded and setose with irregular elongate and short robust setae, posterodistal corner slightly produced with 1 group of 6 robust setae (1 elongate and 5 moderate); carpus linear, as long as basis, with 5 groups of robust setae on anterior margin and with 1 group of 7 robust setae at anterodistal corner, with 1 single and 5 groups of robust setae on posterior margin and with 1 group of 6 robust setae at posterodistal corner; propodus also linear, as long as carpus, with 5 groups of 3 robust setae on anterior margin and 1 group of 4 setae (1 simple elongate and 3 robust) at anterodistal corner, posterior margin armed with setae of various combinations, with 13 setae (2 robust and 11 simple) at posterodistal corner; dactylus short, with blunt protrusion bearing 1 seta on inner margin, with curved and claw-like apex.</paragraph>
<caption id="420FAFBAD4223F462DEF58FF0F8018AC" pageId="12" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="F1C6A2230BC8D4ED14DB77E40D32A899" pageId="12" pageNumber="65">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName id="1977858E4D7F26C9D3F1DC3FFD326100" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="12" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype. A Pereopod 7 B Dactylus on pereopod 7 C Pleonal epimera D Uropod 1 E Uropod 2 F Uropod 3 G Telson. Scale bars 0.05 mm (B), 0.1 mm (G), 0.2 mm (A, 
<normalizedToken id="3C3C6862C4F951101B5737940D6EDB78" originalValue="C–F">C-F</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="D4853E34C8BC648427D9AADD4F600521" pageId="12" pageNumber="65">Pereonite 7 and pleonites 1-3 (Fig. 11C): each carinate dorsally.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="89E0622F54DA53F97F0749E8A18EE1BB" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">
<pageBreakToken id="0AE55E31D3D1378D4B9A5FBF0927D5D4" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" start="start">Pleonal</pageBreakToken>
epimera (Fig. 11C): epimeron 1 with 2 naked serrations and 1 weak notch on posterior margin; epimeron 2 round ventrally, with 3 setae on anterior half of ventral margin, with 2 serrations bearing 1 minute seta and 1 naked notch on posterior margin; epimeron 3 largest, weakly upturned posterodistally, with 3 setae on ventral margin, with 5 serrations and 1 distal small notch bearing 1 minute seta on posterior margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E8C591D4D2CB6E1CEBDE356E6CED5011" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">Uropod 1 (Fig. 11D): slender; peduncle longer than rami, with 14 lateral and 9 medial robust setae dorsally; outer ramus with 6 lateral robust setae dorsally, apex blunt with 2 subapical and 2 apical robust setae; inner ramus shorter than outer ramus, with 6 lateral and 5 medial robust setae dorsally, apex blunt with 2 subapical and 2 apical robust setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D4DA0E270133549E6366849876690DAB" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">Uropod 2 (Fig. 11E): shortest; peduncle 0.7 times as long as that of uropod 1, with 9 lateral and 7 medial robust setae dorsally; outer ramus shorter than peduncle, with 4 lateral robust setae dorsally, apex blunt with 2 subapical and 2 apical robust setae; inner ramus subequal to outer ramus, with 4 lateral and 3 medial robust setae dorsally, apex blunt with 2 subapical and 2 apical robust setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9A25E93FF05FA42AF6B3F23CAC6B9944" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">Uropod 3 (Fig. 11F): peduncle 0.7 times as long as that of uropod 2, with 4 medial and 4 lateral robust setae dorsally; rami lanceolate; outer ramus 2.0 times as long as peduncle, with 4 pairs and 2 single robust setae along lateral margin, with 2 single robust setae, 7 pairs of robust and plumose setae, and 1 minute subapical seta along medial margin; inner ramus slightly longer than outer ramus, with 2 proximal single setae, 7 plumose setae and 1 minute subapical seta on lateral margin, with 1 proximal simple seta, 10 robust and 5 plumose setae on medial margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B661CD6F581392EF44EF07B158CC773B" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">Telson (Fig. 11G): deeply cleft (about 3/4 length), each lobe with notch bearing 1 pair of 1 plumose and 1 long simple seta on apex, with 1 pair of plumose setae on dorsal surface.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9FAD1947BCD45D188CC89ED0B694446D" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" type="female">
<paragraph id="03C4253295131AAF094BF65B25674C6D" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">Female.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8DD483DA4A27076893E4E3945F4F5C30" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FFD85233B21FA16BF86ED601EDD7D62C" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="AC99EC45DF69440DA84CA2715B7A4CEA" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9F349B9E63482379B9A84A2BDE61290F" pageId="13" pageNumber="66">
<taxonomicName id="FD3D14826022CE585FB9335479811FD7" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is very similar to 
<taxonomicName id="2952980F950A30493241140B7592ADEF" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera tridentata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tridentata">Paramoera tridentata</taxonomicName>
Bulycheva, 1952 and 
<taxonomicName id="85D85EE7BB4ACE08D9E08EFC1F2279B6" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
Hirayama, 1990 in the following characteristics: (1) the anterior cephalic lobe is sinusoid; (2) pereopods 5-7 are more slender than those of other congeners; (3) the posterior lobe of basis on pereopods 6-7 is largely expanded proximally and diminished distally; (4) epimera 1-3 are carinate dorsally; and (5) epimeron 3 is prominently expanded backward with very similar serration pattern on the posterior margin (
<bibRefCitation id="C9F7E8C978700E5037B2BE1F8AF5B7A8" author="Bulycheva, AI" journalOrPublisher="Trudy Zoologicheskogo Instituta AN SSSR" pageId="15" pageNumber="68" pagination="195 - 250" title="A new species of side-swimmers (Amphipoda, Gammaridea) from the Japan Sea." volume="12" year="1952">Bulycheva 1952</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="FB3416FDEA2D0F98422E16BFD7C81092" author="Hirayama, A" journalOrPublisher="Zoological Science" pageId="15" pageNumber="68" pagination="955 - 959" title="A new species of the genus Paramoera (Crustacea: Amphipoda) from the intertidal zone of Hokkaido, northern Japan." volume="7" year="1990">Hirayama 1990</bibRefCitation>
). However, 
<taxonomicName id="B2C1FCBDBEFBF16442B733889DFA66DA" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. can be readily distinguished from 
<taxonomicName id="E725FE05734EE0B3E814F8F5A5F4CB2A" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera tridentata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tridentata">Paramoera tridentata</taxonomicName>
by the following features: (1) the inferior antennal sinus is deeply cleft and its lower part is produced forward in 
<taxonomicName id="CB4E57B0C58F579244469D3CB34AAD04" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., whereas it is concaved quadrately in 
<taxonomicName id="3CD56A46E4073F2C033A42EBAD2DF2F6" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera tridentata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tridentata">Paramoera tridentata</taxonomicName>
; (2) the formulae of robust defining setae at the palmar corners on gnathopods 1 and 2 are complex in 
<taxonomicName id="3B94A21ADF099DB7F485A63525B49F10" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (1, 1, 3 for lateral and 2, 3, 1 for medial setae on gnathopod 1 and 1, 2, 1 for lateral setae on gnathopod 2), whereas 
<taxonomicName id="8C03C060BCC80F63D11D939AA8F2003F" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera tridentata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tridentata">Paramoera tridentata</taxonomicName>
has only two lateral setae on gnathopods 1 and 2, respectively; (3) the serrations of each posterior margin of the basis on pereopods 5-7 are weaker in 
<taxonomicName id="9C0EEDE302E38E139E0E46A8043BB8FA" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera tridentata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tridentata">Paramoera tridentata</taxonomicName>
; and (4) the dorsal carina on pereon 7 is absent in 
<taxonomicName id="F956FE45F49D5EF9DB1AF7CBA4A45242" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera tridentata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="13" pageNumber="66" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tridentata">Paramoera tridentata</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation id="E7F08ADA04D53CF4EC5420346BAB51F8" author="Bulycheva, AI" journalOrPublisher="Trudy Zoologicheskogo Instituta AN SSSR" pageId="15" pageNumber="68" pagination="195 - 250" title="A new species of side-swimmers (Amphipoda, Gammaridea) from the Japan Sea." volume="12" year="1952">Bulycheva 1952</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="D08E58C107AD9734EEA493D3966FF18A" author="Labay, VS" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="15" pageNumber="68" pagination="69 - 85" title="Paramoeraanivae a new species of Eusiridae Stebbing, 1888 (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea) from the Okhotsk Sea." volume="3475" year="2012">Labay 2012</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FE6F0F621906A9477632E89C985FB441" pageId="14" pageNumber="67">
<taxonomicName id="E893CC103AA616CF6DAC3AD199200B84" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">
<pageBreakToken id="C8120A97710DBDFA40AABB8BF7D633F0" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" start="start">Paramoera</pageBreakToken>
dentipleurae
</taxonomicName>
sp. n. can be discriminated from 
<taxonomicName id="046937104CF034DEFAAE2BDC33C51453" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
by the following features: (1) upper and lower parts of the inferior antennal sinus do not overlap in 
<taxonomicName id="47AF39775164370D7C175ADDAF2873AB" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n.; (2) antenna 1 is longer than antenna 2 in 
<taxonomicName id="30F40E875CB95E07AD911A53228EA2C6" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., but antenna 2 is longer than antenna 1 in 
<taxonomicName id="D0027CF4E50CBB0EC4D5DB0DB820005B" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
; (3) setations of the peduncular articles on antennae 1 and 2 of 
<taxonomicName id="157403088EB79E164C45E1AEF4F1770E" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. are weaker; (4) accessory flagellum has five apical setae in 
<taxonomicName id="F7119B5B5E662094272D897B2ADD992E" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., but it has only two apical setae in 
<taxonomicName id="31AC9E2A6BEA821DEDFB223A4D8D74C6" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
; (5) formulae of the robust defining setae at the palmar corners on gnathopods 1 and 2 are different from each other (1, 1, 3 for lateral setae and 2, 3, 1 for medial setae on gnathopod 1, and 1, 2, 1 for lateral setae in gnathopod 2 in 
<taxonomicName id="3765664094B66DE0115FF02D89BE16FF" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., whereas there are three rows of three setae on the medial surface of gnathopod 1 and without setae on gnathopod 2 in 
<taxonomicName id="196EA071ED167FF2737215173DACF5DD" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
); (6) posterior margin of basis on pereopod 5 is more expanded distally and the length of the merus is shorter in 
<taxonomicName id="7C396CAAEF19A16A65BC695D31C1B74A" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
; (7) serration patterns are weaker and the posterodistal lobes are indistinct for basis on pereopods 5-7 in 
<taxonomicName id="E523B793A62E12563B418C36306C0C74" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. compared to 
<taxonomicName id="F08B73CC5674387FDD74B1F35C329889" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
; (8) each dorsal margin from pereon 7 to pleon 3 has a distal carina in 
<taxonomicName id="3F6099B25EC28A0A1327F757E2F019B9" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., whereas the distal carina is absent in 
<taxonomicName id="2B2714C554602ADF68684106ED564B96" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
; and (9) serration patterns of the posterior margins on the pleonal epimera are simpler in 
<taxonomicName id="8F6E0598977013F3E657EE08E98F39C5" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera hanamurai" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hanamurai">Paramoera hanamurai</taxonomicName>
compared to those in 
<taxonomicName id="37B8FF5DDF18DB5A09F1E45B901FFA04" class="Malacostraca" family="Pontogeneiidae" genus="Paramoera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paramoera dentipleurae" order="Amphipoda" pageId="14" pageNumber="67" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dentipleurae">Paramoera dentipleurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (
<bibRefCitation id="C0DC27FD7C4F7435A8C8BEA141FD047F" author="Hirayama, A" journalOrPublisher="Zoological Science" pageId="15" pageNumber="68" pagination="955 - 959" title="A new species of the genus Paramoera (Crustacea: Amphipoda) from the intertidal zone of Hokkaido, northern Japan." volume="7" year="1990">Hirayama 1990</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>