<document id="66018123C084A69E4C4C323960C106C3" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bdfb4b8e-4c36-4386-a7d0-7437b44fcba1" ModsDocID="21061" checkinTime="1252706925963" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Heterick, B. E." docDate="2006" docId="48A64A2FD809CF59050074C0C1426570" docLanguage="en" docName="21061.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 57" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf" docTitle="Monomorium clarinodis Heterick, 2006, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="90" masterDocId="3A2C4F9A5833769B5007E7556E53E380" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="202" masterPageNumber="69" pageNumber="89" updateTime="1569525778780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="619CE92A5C4C5FD4BBD1EE63F87C6987" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="D60FEA036F389498DDD4F77EA882D1B9">
<mods:title id="6D26611361718A2816103344338A081F">A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="E0214288F8E1939C98C79287AA008730" type="personal">
<mods:role id="DE9324A3018395F5478AD886D4885994">
<mods:roleTerm id="C29AB3EB86286939AD2A78C3F7D72658">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="F7695D7627956439CE55410C644DB15A">Heterick, B. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="8FF0EC51A46736F1CC485A460C89DDB6">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="81051F1371D1FE65983DFEFB6F1CE200" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="5151CA7D8274C50F19862C2ED37B0A8F">
<mods:title id="BFFE670E26E32C965573326ABDEE4578">Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="6DA140A86DDEEEC84D761D2778D1F1B5">
<mods:date id="39BC0E2C7B448247A730C96BC224FEC9">2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="1F3012B2B6F595D2554ABBC4CBE192F2" type="volume">
<mods:number id="E7D25F63636263219948C3022E90FFFB">57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="FEDD02C898C3BE8EFFC46E4CAFD148FF" unit="page">
<mods:start id="97408FF12F9A0FC009B3027CCC3F4152">69</mods:start>
<mods:end id="C9878612B036AFD216A0A05CE28090DB">202</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="9F974E931EC95D5D370D08282B87C8E1">
<mods:url id="AE2E81F32181F34609625C795E788C04">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="2EE9E076D53319F5C706ADF72B2FEDCE">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="77DD344A0762DB4FC4A8247EA8F6A19B" type="HNS-PUB">21061</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="48A64A2FD809CF59050074C0C1426570" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:48A64A2FD809CF59050074C0C1426570" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/48A64A2FD809CF59050074C0C1426570">
<subSubSection id="7DCEDBBF63AB149B7D860AA0E0D9DD85" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="849F5B013A83474782BB86AB32E146CF" pageNumber="89">
<taxonomicName id="9EE6176D12C3C3A31F7C13B0D51D5358" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196242" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium clarinodis Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium clarinodis Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="clarinodis">Monomorium clarinodis Heterick</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="29137DE3B81D92E3AD835199829149A1" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FDDDD0D795E19851FE770639BD5ACE95" type="description">
<paragraph id="1F2F84DD3EB15E3882C9CAA0F1AD181D" pageNumber="89">Figs. 14, 35-36.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9D3031BF3B2E15B840705851BAE2425F" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="E010EB93FE70A89323C8FDFE7D4C28DF" pageNumber="89">Etymology.- Latin &quot;clarus&quot; (&quot;shiny&quot;) + pl. of &quot;nodus&quot; (masc. &quot;knot&quot;)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8831DEEA644045C1C3F370793F5B10D8" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="25E9316DF66B9851B6F088688ACBF0C6" pageNumber="89">Material examined.- Holotype: [[worker]], Prov. Toliara, 6.1 km 182 s Marovato 25°35's, 45°18'e, 20 m. 14.ii.2002, Fisher et al. blf#5528 /under stone spiny forest/thicket/ casent 0453886 (cas). Paratypes: Prov. Toliara (all specimens with same collection data as holotype): 1 [[worker]] (anic); 21 [[worker]] (bmnh); 21 [[worker]] (cas); 31 [[worker]] (mcz).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A006347159772DA4FB79501345BCB89B" pageNumber="89">Other material examined: Prov. Toliara: Beza-Mahafaly [&quot;Mahafely&quot;], 27 km e Betioky 23.iv.1997 b.l. Fisher (3 [[worker]], 1 [[queen]]); Cap Sainte Marie, 12.3 km 262 w Marovato 11-15.ii.2002 Fisher et al. (6 [[queen]]); Ehazoara Canyon, 26 km e Betioky 27.iv.1997 b.l. Fisher (1 [[worker]]); Foret Beroboka, 5.9 km 131 se Ankidranoka 12-16.iii.2002 Fisher et al. (2[[worker]]); Foret Mahavelo, Isantoria Riv., 5.2 km 44 ne Ifotaka 28i.-1.ii 2001 bl. Fisher (16 [[worker]]); Foret Tsinjoriaka [&quot;Tsinjoriaky&quot;], 6.2 km 84 e Tsifota 6-10.iii.2002 Fisher et al. (16 [[worker]]); Mahafaly [&quot;Mahafely&quot;] Plateau 6.2 km 74 ene Itampolo, 21-25ii.2002, Fisher et al. (7 [[worker]]); Mandarano [&quot;Manderano&quot;], 10.iv.2002, Frontier Project mg030 (1 [[worker]]); 6.1 km 182 Marovato 14.ii.2002 Fisher et al. (1 [[worker]]); p. n. Ambovo Springs, 29.3 km 4 n Ranohira, 9-14.ii.2003, bl. Fisher (2 [[worker]]); p. n. Kirindy Mite, 16.3 km 127 se Belo sur Mer 6-10.xii.2001 Fisher et al. (1[[worker]]); pn. Andohahela, 1.7 km 61 ene Tsimelahy 16-20.i.2002 Fisher et al. (6 [[worker]]); p.n. Andohahela, 7.6 km 99 e Hazofotsy 12-16.i.2002 Fisher et al. (4 [[worker]]); Tsimanampetsotsa, 6.7 km 130 se Efoetse, 18-22.iii.2002 bl. Fisher (8 [[worker]]); Tsimanampetsotsa, Bemanateza, 23.0 km 131 se Beheloka, 22-26.iii.2002 bl. Fisher (1 [[worker]]).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="6B2EC90ED4019EA47D0B21352C1E7404" type="description">
<paragraph id="2DCDAB0CDA4A49B0BDF60AF692E9EBB7" pageNumber="89">Worker description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex planar or weakly concave; frons ranging from shining, smooth with almost effaced reticulation to shining and finely punctate-reticulate; pilosity of frons consisting of a few short, thick, erect setae interspersed with short, appressed setulae. Eye moderate, eye width 1-1.5x greatest width of antennal scape; (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set around midline of head capsule; eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin. Antennal segments 12; antennal club three-segmented. Clypeal carinae indicated by multiple weak ridges; anteromedian clypeal margin broadly convex; paraclypeal setae short and thickened, not reaching basal margin of closed mandibles; posteromedian clypeal margin approximately level with antennal fossae. Anterior tentorial pits situated nearer antennal fossae than mandibular insertions. Frontal lobes straight, parallel. Psammophore absent. Palp formula 5,3. Mandibular teeth five; mandibles triangular and mainly smooth (weakly striate basally); masticatory margin of mandibles approximately vertical or weakly oblique; basal tooth approximately same size as t4 (five teeth present).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="909E8CDE6A6DB7325AD5F6DB0868A8E8" pageNumber="89">Mesosoma: Promesonotum shining and microreticulate, microreticulation reduced on humeri, or, shining and smooth on dorsum, lower mesopleuron strongly punctate; (viewed in profile) promesonotum broadly convex, or, anterior promesonotum smoothly rounded, thereafter more-orless flattened, promesonotum on same plane as propodeum; promesonotal setae very variable, from one or two to up to a dozen; standing promesonotal setae consisting of short, erect or semi-erect bristles; appressed promesonotal setulae well-spaced over entire promesonotum. Metanotal groove vestigial. Propodeum with reduced sculpture, generally smooth dorsally, metapleuron punctate; propodeal dorsum flat throughout most of its length; propodeum smoothly rounded or with indistinct angle, but dorsal and declivitous faces separated when seen in profile; standing propodeal setae absent; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle nearer declivitous face of propodeum than metanotal groove. Vestibule of propodeal spiracle absent or not visible. Propodeal lobes present as vestigial flanges or small strips of cuticle only.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="460EFCC5637C0C72EB22D79407E2FC83" lastPageNumber="90" pageNumber="89">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle laterodorsal and situated well anteriad of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) cuneate, vertex rounded; appearance of node shining and faintly microreticulate; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) between 4:3 and1:1; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; ventral petiolar lobe absent; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; height -length ratio of postpetiole about 1:1; postpetiole shining, with vestigial sculpture; postpetiolar sternite not depressed at midpoint, its anterior end an inconspicuous lip or small carina.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9A95CD19A410992FC0B4B7051DEE2300" pageNumber="90">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, short, thick, erect setae interspersed with minute, appressed setulae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0797CD0FB645CAFE66051AA2B3C3144B" pageNumber="90">General characters: Color from orange or yellowish with gaster light brown, through to uniform chocolate. Worker caste monomorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="49C51DC99DE892122F09039A4EBD3D98" pageNumber="90">Holotype worker measurements: HML 1.55 HL 0.53 HW 0.44 CeI 83 SL 0.40 SI 91 PW 0.32.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="20E5958160B8FFCA7A17DC0C3334DAE7" pageNumber="90">Other worker measurements: HML 1.22-1.57 HL 0.45-0.55 HW 0.35-0.47 CeI 78-87 SL 0.32-0.43 SI 90-97 PW 0.26-0.35 (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="15BCAE23DC2A3761BFB49DBCC232752D" pageNumber="90">Queen description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex always planar; frons shining and smooth except for piliferous pits; pilosity of frons a mixture of well-spaced, distinctly longer erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with shorter setae or setulae, which are decumbent or appressed, longer setae thickest on vertex. Eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin; (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set posteriad of midline of head capsule.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1CDAF58945E109067356C521D6111B64" pageNumber="90">Mesosoma: Mesoscutum broadly convex anteriad, convexity reduced posteriad; pronotum, mesoscutum and mesopleuron shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to anterior katepisternum; length -width ratio of mesoscutum and scutellum combined between 2:1 and 3:2; axillae narrowly separated (i.e., less than width of one axilla); standing pronotal/mesoscutal setae consisting of well-spaced, incurved, erect and semi-erect setae only; appressed pronotal, mescoscutal and mesopleural setulae few, mainly on dorsum of pronotum and mesoscutum. Propodeum shining and microreticulate; propodeum distinctly angulate, propodeal angles produced as short denticles; propodeal dorsum sloping posteriad, and depressed between raised propodeal angles; standing propodeal setae absent; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle equidistant from metanotal groove and declivitous face of propodeum. Propodeal lobes present as vestigial flanges only, or absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B39C4BA006B3D527E2F16AD8C6234442" pageNumber="90">Wing: Wing not seen (queen dealated).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="907D2F6C993008D64E46E485DA51C993" pageNumber="90">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated well anteriad of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) cuneate, vertex tapered; appearance of node shining and microreticulate; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) about 4:3; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole about 1:1; height -length ratio of postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; postpetiole shining and microreticulate; postpetiolar sternite not depressed, in form of narrow, rectangular projection.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3FA39BF754A7C454AEF48E0637D0AE37" pageNumber="90">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, short, thick, erect setae interspersed with minute, appressed setulae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="44B7361B4DB77CC2EA4E9C1C8FCC9FC2" pageNumber="90">General characters: Color brownish-yellow, gaster darker. Brachypterous alates not seen. Ergatoid or worker-female intercastes not seen.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9AFBCC3CB561A9F865F7196D191A64C7" pageNumber="90">Queen measurements: HML 2.29 HL 0.66 HW 0.61 CeI 92 SL 0.52 SI 85 PW 0.52 (n=1).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="BB6CB59723A178D46C959037DBDF0B53" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="CE6FDBD9C6DD0121527E317FBD159CD4" lastPageNumber="91" pageNumber="90">
Remarks.- This species appears to have a wider distribution than other members of the 
<taxonomicName id="ECF6C7D2BE82FF8D1A0567F90A7EF2CE" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31715" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium shuckardi Forel" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium shuckardi Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="shuckardi">M. shuckardi</taxonomicName>
group, with most specimens being obtained from sifted litter in spiny forest in Toliara Province. The species has also been collected, however, in pitfall traps, from under a stone and from within a rotten log in tropical dry forest. Workers are very variable in appearance, and range from shining with largely effaced sculpture on the frons and most of the promesonotum to uniformly granulose-reticulate on the mesosoma with a striolate-reticulate frons, the latter form resembling members of the 
<taxonomicName id="B27F3A9B5D740073FBC3F4CB8DF1DAEB" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31703" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium salomonis (Linnaeus)" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium salomonis (Linnaeus)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="salomonis">M. salomonis</taxonomicName>
species group. Color is similarly variable, and ranges from uniformly pale yellowish or bicolored orange-and-brown to dark chocolate, some of the latter workers exhibiting a rather mottled appearance (not unlike blended white and dark chocolate confectionery). One of the dark workers possesses numerous differences from similarly dark specimens taken in the same pitfall trap. The propodeum is more elongate and positioned relatively lower to the promesonotum so that there is no metanotal groove, the eye is slightly larger, the appendages are longer, and there is more extensive sculpture and erect pilosity. In other, respects, however, it conforms to the habitus of the other dark workers. This specimen does not appear to be an ergatoid, and the reason for the aberrant appearance is not known.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>