<document id="A0622B23FBFDE8348890088AAB607187" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047614" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BAD32776-3ECD-4EB9-9139-1C5C902909B7" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="4C97A7B10C098160841E572CD61BDF1F" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio nitoris Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="BAD32776-3ECD-4EB9-9139-1C5C902909B7" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="145" lastPageNumber="146" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="142" pageNumber="143" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="D5B850358689DFC0DF9BA89C2143CE95" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6CBEA81B6AB85B7648BA7C2BFDD95B91">
<mods:title id="C9E03228437B597ADCA061FC4B58BD90">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A522F996B152550D70A6F5DD3AE4F73B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D38B7049B6B44D61C4440AE53C9A73E5">
<mods:roleTerm id="951384B63D9D3BF82C04CCB15E1B2A66">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="4D0BAC71297003C27C65AA32D6D95548">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="FC4AE6E18F2C50AF733181D84CCAE0A0" type="personal">
<mods:role id="8F9232FB04571454B553514C4C9CC504">
<mods:roleTerm id="B5B2B77D846DD97A757E36494580D589">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2D12961B764EF9D7BF322C3A96A54EC8">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="5A7917C743B8F7153A4F71CEB9F22CB6" type="personal">
<mods:role id="BDBE61F5800A3CF46823B72388EB556C">
<mods:roleTerm id="233BA038F8D7BD4F450AAB91CEE42AD6">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3241283F72723C67DE69093CD51C8C70">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="FBBBC19FCB50FDF5AE4D76411C56B18C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="11E318471C262C26EB3BE7CB83B90A39">
<mods:roleTerm id="F5265164923826801A7E241AF8F0D090">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1EDF7858530BD4151CCA12C5CE1D1408">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7B42D69C7AFB790550528982F52E7CC0">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="991CD84F17565B31A4DC7DE762818031" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="E5991877B0590C66D6FF911A91750C75">
<mods:title id="90B9A9F605A6DDCE6CAFFACA78E0B00A">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="B5652EFFDDA3C89034833468069F9390">
<mods:date id="93437874032CE3CD122087F456BCDB96">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D7BD69CBCC5119F47F8835B195C42245" type="volume">
<mods:number id="569418B14AD2C5DBF480B9BEF92F16B1">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="3A8DAA212FD4DE89AA456B58DD5E9A24" unit="page">
<mods:start id="6B143775D04C9634F1C562EDFF3D5D71">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="D0D63B25BDD74C8F52D85E4FDBC39757">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="C462784CABF14BEDE8678F8FE0510CC9">
<mods:url id="8AD48CADF6FC4A1BD7A2827E6D3B13E3">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="F937C673C7CEF9397285441B5EA23D62">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="BB253B724D5AB220CAF3E617E32B9261" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="F9FC65C9C7279BF96F8A3FF7ED434FF8" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="90120AF78E34A47FD36353F750C2FA78" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="4C97A7B10C098160841E572CD61BDF1F" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047614" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BAD32776-3ECD-4EB9-9139-1C5C902909B7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4C97A7B10C098160841E572CD61BDF1F" lastPageId="145" lastPageNumber="146" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">
<subSubSection id="AEC78700CE314442140BE25F6576B3C5" pageId="142" pageNumber="143" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="6D6F4212E660A4FAA06C4CB3E06C6ACD" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">
<taxonomicName id="07F23B368B27C547B1E0E0421A17FA17" LSID="http://zoobank.org/BAD32776-3ECD-4EB9-9139-1C5C902909B7" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nitoris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="142" pageNumber="143" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nitoris">Oxyscelio nitoris Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="0AB039E0B9F6EAEB44944FD4571F59BD" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 219-224; Morphbank70
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E70C36D12F67D7DC1692F366BC9A2BD6" lastPageId="144" lastPageNumber="145" pageId="142" pageNumber="143" type="description">
<paragraph id="B62B828490C722D2B00247AB9D525872" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="32BBB98B008C65B545E7818956B856DA" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">Female. Body length 2.9-3.55 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="570CB3AD7EB18D7248191DDDDD89E12F" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: at least partially darker than scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1748EE7D6FE1E70E6FBA1BD462D1C3EE" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by a set of irregular elevations. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: omicron-shaped, with sharp corners where median portion meets lateral portions. Occiput sculpture: transversely rugose. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; absent. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="515A06C18194D4C885D0CCA88063C3F8" lastPageId="144" lastPageNumber="145" pageId="142" pageNumber="143">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe poste 
<pageBreakToken id="C7899DAF1020585A5723359EB1C6683A" pageId="143" pageNumber="144" start="start">riorly</pageBreakToken>
: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: deeply emarginate, with the resulting 
<pageBreakToken id="3ACA470073BFDF408A4341651E91B3E5" pageId="144" pageNumber="145" start="start">pair</pageBreakToken>
of posterior processes subtriangular and directed dorsally. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, but parallel for a short distance anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: with median areole or pair of pits. Median propodeal carina: present.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F9C35CD1D987FE1D4CC63DC4FB411E38" pageId="144" pageNumber="145">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: slightly emarginate, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7984D6608D5808300CBD629D057E54E0" pageId="144" pageNumber="145">Male. Body length 2.7-3.55 mm (n=20).A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent; punctate. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: with a pair of sharply defined spine-like posterolateral projections.</paragraph>
<caption id="CCF57E94D9BFAFDEB35A5F44E0DA95EE" pageId="144" pageNumber="145">
<paragraph id="0FF22764E2C91D5015C62B2858FBAE5C" pageId="144" pageNumber="145">
Figures 219-224. 
<taxonomicName id="1B23B70520CD2826913596D5CE44EA2B" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nitoris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="144" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nitoris">Oxyscelio nitoris</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female (OSUC 359541) 219 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 220 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 221 Head, anterior view 222 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (QM Reg. No. T35136) 223 Antenna 224 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank70
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="15852BF86028A13907265A4451E88311" pageId="144" pageNumber="145" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="B8A1F4E56AF3D979AED99D8436775ABF" pageId="144" pageNumber="145">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5C83394CC1A2D2DA70F738B119DE0DB6" pageId="144" pageNumber="145">
Both sexes: Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum black. Frontal depression shallow, transverse carinae absent or interrupted; submedian carina absent. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by rugae. Occipital carina complete, sinuate medially. Metascutellum deeply concave, emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Coxa same color as rest of leg. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Female: A3 not shorter than pedicel. A4, A5 broader than long. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. T6 without metasomal flanges. Fore wing long enough to reach middle of T6 or beyond metasomal apex. Main body of T6 not abruptly separated from apical rim. Male: A3 longer than pedicel. A4, A11 longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to exceed metasomal apex. T7 with elongate spine-like posterior projections. 
<taxonomicName id="2059F00807A3C852C276284AADD8ABB5" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio nitoris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="144" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nitoris">Oxyscelio nitoris</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName id="C4CFE0AB08E5F9F433A7F2CAC3D9A2B9" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio livens" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="144" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="livens">Oxyscelio livens</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="0D19ECA87D61EA17287EFCA96166A98E" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio palati" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="144" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="palati">Oxyscelio palati</taxonomicName>
, but has a moderate-length antenna in combination with a lack of T6 metasomal flanges.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="BBB43D56EF8978946F0A079FE1E4B6FB" pageId="145" pageNumber="146" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="7FDB33C46AB48918A9265A466ADF527A" pageId="145" pageNumber="146">
<pageBreakToken id="68AD3761D67B218CBE5C4D0D37BECB8A" pageId="145" pageNumber="146" start="start">Etymology</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B30EC07A240A2D8BCAF7398081F02492" pageId="145" pageNumber="146">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="529133A6BEF3096BA752FE70B5212A9F" originalValue="“brightness.”">&quot;brightness.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="07323B8AB26653F0415108DE0A8BBE59" pageId="145" pageNumber="146" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="7AE5A25E8EA78B7E3252DF0E8A5C1112" pageId="145" pageNumber="146">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="ED80E81075215B8CF21E9EDC8D76FFFC" pageId="145" pageNumber="146">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307091]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="929994D4B88AF5D88E0044957F259495" pageId="145" pageNumber="146" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="C0622E9674109660C88053EFEB632E62" pageId="145" pageNumber="146">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="56BC4B6FAD5DD65390B6D6473AB8744B" pageId="145" pageNumber="146">Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, Maroochy Horticultural Research Station, Nambour, 8.III-15.III.1985, malaise trap, OSUC 359530 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 55 females, 24 males, ANIC DB 32-020089, 32-020091, 32-020092, 32-020093, 32-020101, 32-020102, 32-020143, OSUC 359540, OSUC 359541, OSUC 359543, OSUC 359544, OSUC 359545, OSUC 359547, OSUC 359548, OSUC 359552, OSUC 359553, OSUC 359555, OSUC 359558, OSUC 359559, OSUC 359561 (ANIC); OSUC 449087 (BMNH); OSUC 227550, 227632-227633 (CNCI); OSUC 359549-359550, QDPC 0-165631, QDPC 0-165677 (QDPC); OSUC 148382, 359551, 435937, QM Reg. No. T35135, QM Reg. No. T35137, QM Reg. No. T35138, QM Reg. No. T35141, QM Reg. No. T35143, QM Reg. No. T35144, QM Reg. No. T35146 (QMBA); OSUC 359527-359529, 359531-359539, 359542, 359546, 359554, 359556-359557, 359560, 359562-359574, 436937-436938, 449081-449086, 449088-449089 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>