<document id="F428C155069ECE7736590332998FC011" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047611" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:00FC118E-552B-4F38-ACDC-410AB49F05EB" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="4EF2F1BF47F950C56F7A30E9F3BDCBDA" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio scutorum Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="00FC118E-552B-4F38-ACDC-410AB49F05EB" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="193" lastPageNumber="194" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="190" pageNumber="191" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="D7DD063BCD790E6534FFCF5904E5DA50" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6EDBFE1521488AD3A3DE1BEED87F4F54">
<mods:title id="CB856426088B88DF37C406396EFEA955">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A747AF98FAA284A89BC292181F42E3FE" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D1EE2647FD449CC42F206D20193C6720">
<mods:roleTerm id="9776D2B8766DEA5DC760AB747BBD3EA3">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="4F6EFA7F6280D2679701CDF7F37F418D">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="FE2FB0EFC4DC810A9855E61D696CF465" type="personal">
<mods:role id="8DF764F54FA7C5F15E373689693AD1C1">
<mods:roleTerm id="B7D7E173CF9D08DF9E1A518C6026C14C">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2F77C0153DBE287254564BFFB3035A0D">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="581C41C9084826B0D12B160B9C543873" type="personal">
<mods:role id="BFDB37FBCBFAED518347D0E6AD4D41A9">
<mods:roleTerm id="215EF636B3276CEAAE6ECC54EB423E13">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="30247E313982EDC2350D6EF9F0BA98B5">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="F9DE979180A02C504529118439F0A549" type="personal">
<mods:role id="13864E4957D6FD83005F800EA61F1EFC">
<mods:roleTerm id="F743076AD9C8F725F11A43DFDD56C455">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1CBA2E5618FB05B0F7AE7500EBBB00CD">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="79278092310BA8A0BB36EE47D0886805">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="9B798E415CA68A944FB81A22472794F4" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="E7FC4E79FBA9DDC33D9BF6DFB4D318B0">
<mods:title id="92DCFFF84E560C6B87CB9D0F5D46A4CF">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="B70078F196531935DFE753AD23398755">
<mods:date id="91262E7A48DC3268F944E031731ACF53">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D5D83FC587A1C85194EC5274B0623680" type="volume">
<mods:number id="54F14EBF0122147E1FE4DE7BDC890274">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="38E8FC2F64240F2C41210C9DF8F88EE1" unit="page">
<mods:start id="6971617B9BBC47911AA10528DA9B49B4">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="D2B36D2BF6279D2AB9BC398AFE658392">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="C6072E42E0019A480303E84AC5F7180C">
<mods:url id="88B1DAA3BD0C9BBE3CC6E5BB489D0726">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="FB52907D8C3E289C99E123DE7B0429A7">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="B9406D7C06AA6385219781D2C68D86A4" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="FB9933C78CD74A5C84EE5832C8E55B3D" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="92775CF9C5C475DA380734327564EEBD" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="4EF2F1BF47F950C56F7A30E9F3BDCBDA" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047611" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:00FC118E-552B-4F38-ACDC-410AB49F05EB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4EF2F1BF47F950C56F7A30E9F3BDCBDA" lastPageId="193" lastPageNumber="194" pageId="190" pageNumber="191">
<subSubSection id="F1155ABBF103E3FD41034A24B15BA8A4" pageId="190" pageNumber="191" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="F6260B40C9EBA77C87A76013E6363CA2" pageId="190" pageNumber="191">
<taxonomicName id="AE571AC4DC9D0E6700A8083EBC7B8D9F" LSID="http://zoobank.org/00FC118E-552B-4F38-ACDC-410AB49F05EB" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio scutorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="190" pageNumber="191" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="scutorum">Oxyscelio scutorum Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="296A9CC2F7621B32814B3020E975F1A6" pageId="190" pageNumber="191">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 313-318; Morphbank87
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ED4A44CB3AF114B59AB56738C8909AC6" lastPageId="193" lastPageNumber="194" pageId="190" pageNumber="191" type="description">
<paragraph id="349E3CD1494AB18AF2D36FC4D1254AFF" pageId="190" pageNumber="191">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="09892B861CEE7E1571097B4588CE6805" pageId="190" pageNumber="191">Female. Body length 2.45-3.4 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DBD8ED0426E440793932D51A2645A018" pageId="190" pageNumber="191">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: shorter than pedicel; as long as pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="50E36F4C9E12AE18DCB6E3C4DB9506E8" lastPageId="191" lastPageNumber="192" pageId="190" pageNumber="191">
Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression 
<pageBreakToken id="031EE793857DB31A3DCF498441B7730E" pageId="191" pageNumber="192" start="start">dorsally</pageBreakToken>
: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: present as a single carina. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: present laterally, absent medially. Occiput sculpture: transversely rugose. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="865A3D6B0E82F9171A10A1452AA76916" pageId="192" pageNumber="193">
<pageBreakToken id="45BFC8B83C0999C3710E94E45EEA211E" pageId="192" pageNumber="193" start="start">Lateral</pageBreakToken>
pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a ruga. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate; obliquely rugose. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate; obliquely rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: deeply emarginate, with the resulting pair of posterior processes subtriangular and directed dorsally. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="107ABF81EB9F2AC13C4F49C50B897410" pageId="192" pageNumber="193">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6A19F08DA9918F7C2D5D60BCE581BD60" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
<pageBreakToken id="F3A4A7D9F4F23E19671B064F47A8FE71" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Body length 2.35-3.35 mm (n=13). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: weakly emarginate.
</paragraph>
<caption id="8262D9E3D89AE47E6740D045CFFFD07F" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
<paragraph id="B956F2C3FE169A6A951465904185F225" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
Figures 313-318. 
<taxonomicName id="3A73E6209F8F0DA62A562D87AF707D75" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio scutorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="scutorum">Oxyscelio scutorum</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 359721) 313 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 314 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 315 Head, anterior view 316 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 359730) 317 Antenna 318 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank87
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C47A5CEFFDA255446B5D837436E213A2" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="D2961E133E2D58F663692B77CC128B43" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="92A80EC5D911F9779A2705BEDFE6EE25" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
Both sexes: Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum black. Frontal depression shallow, transverse carinae absent; submedian carina indicated by a set of irregular elevations or weak carinae. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by sharp carina. Occipital carina with a faintly indicated convex medial portion. Metascutellum concave, broad and short, projecting dorsally. Coxa not darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 shorter than pedicel. A4, A5 much broader than long. Mesoscutellum with obliquely raised sculpture. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. T6 without metasomal flanges. Fore wing long enough to reach or exceed metasomal apex. Male: A4 broader than long, A11 longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 4 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to exceed metasomal apex. T7 much broader than long, blunt apically, without posterior projections. 
<taxonomicName id="474867D5F7EA670977723D0EE302D3B0" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio scutorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="scutorum">Oxyscelio scutorum</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName id="6A78FCC26DB2530A4A3A6DA4EB4C64E9" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio brevitas" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="brevitas">Oxyscelio brevitas</taxonomicName>
in having a roughly sculptured occiput and strong hyperoccipital carina. It differs having a stronger hyperoccipital carina and an indicated submedian carina. The raised oblique mesoscutellar sculpture is also distinctive, but it may be difficult to distinguish in some specimens. It sometimes accompanies a flat, broad median mesoscutellar carina.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="260BB19E2B63E99427A9816500E396FC" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="F6C67CD15688C03A177C3E67D78B6963" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8F2B91A266C126D7428AC4CDF98A349D" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="4AA72F2279C94A8DA453605AE7DFBB63" originalValue="“shields.”">&quot;shields.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4F0090A3EF3E876E188278F0A900567A" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="E488DAE6F929C21FA1E116EBFCA7C8FC" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EC6E650C140AB2347314EC67FD1870C6" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307107]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A564A722811F493CF5D475D0C76F302A" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="0C7C865B1E9DED3DFDB8DBCDFA7A0BC2" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F72A5593F7F606FBDCEF0E15F346ED9E" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, 3.5km SSW Mount Baird, 
<geoCoordinate id="16BDCA302194E8CF05868A316244E4B2" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-15.166667">15°10'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="185146DBB18B8453D8DF8BACB63991AD" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="145.11667">145°07'E</geoCoordinate>
, 3.
<normalizedToken id="7EABC5BA017B48D9CD95749C9AD15561" originalValue="V–">V-</normalizedToken>
5.V.1981, malaise trap, I. D. Naumann, OSUC 359721 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 22 females, 13 males, ANIC DB 32-020146, OSUC 359716, OSUC 359717, OSUC 359718, OSUC 359719, OSUC 359722, OSUC 359724, OSUC 359730, OSUC 359732, OSUC 359733, OSUC 359734, OSUC 359739, OSUC 359743 (ANIC); OSUC 451368 (BMNH); OSUC 227634, 462754 (CNCI); OSUC 359725 (MVMA); OSUC 451320, QDPC 0-165674 (QDPC); OSUC 359720 (QMBA); OSUC 359713-359715, 359723, 359726, 359728-359729, 359731, 359735, 445346, 448925-448927, 451321-451322 (WINC). Other material: AUSTRALIA: 1 female, OSUC 359727 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>