<document id="E55F9E2566AA6C1155877DA3CFE56CE0" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.662.12124" ID-GBIF-Dataset="85e41c76-28ec-4f0d-86cc-6a6ffd5f3784" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127879723" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-662-101" ID-ZBK="0250ADB4740A4DB283FA92E3BA0363D2" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-662-101" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 662" ModsDocTitle="The ground beetle genus Bembidion Latreille in Baltic amber: Review of preserved specimens and first 3D reconstruction of endophallic structures using X-ray microscopy (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Bembidiini)" checkinTime="1490252562655" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Schmidt, Joachim &amp; Michalik, Peter" docDate="2017" docId="556993CE3B5B353924EFFE0A1D3BAC68" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 662: 101-126" docOrigin="ZooKeys 662" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.662.12124" docTitle="Bembidion alekseevi" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="107" masterDocId="4035B67CBA16C000FFD2B459FFD5FF83" masterDocTitle="The ground beetle genus Bembidion Latreille in Baltic amber: Review of preserved specimens and first 3 D reconstruction of endophallic structures using X-ray microscopy (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Bembidiini)" masterLastPageNumber="126" masterPageNumber="101" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" updateTime="1643482675434" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="1D4A10DD8F2938D1676CD41F32AA262F" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="CF134226E6190E186A09BF43F2DBF47C">
<mods:title id="6012FD3E784CDF972DF2B24E4C2E52A9">The ground beetle genus Bembidion Latreille in Baltic amber: Review of preserved specimens and first 3 D reconstruction of endophallic structures using X-ray microscopy (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Bembidiini)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="378E6A0C898C74A0F7E2977DC32F66F5" type="personal">
<mods:role id="BDD49A0D39F9585C0CE43C9CDB5E0339">
<mods:roleTerm id="5E27B8CDFAB1A9250F80F778F86C29D6">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0B1D349C8E6D83A9DB42B0E5A06E9C81">Schmidt, Joachim</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="52248368EEE55D4C3EB3DEC6538BAA3B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="60BBD8EF8643380D36290638B807F953">
<mods:roleTerm id="195E159066C27E939E0A765B29B3A3FB">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0A9ABD1B9361B307881C977283A9CAD7">Michalik, Peter</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="2BA3F2B67250F2D6FD0B0C62500B093A">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3D224713C8D6B76A2B6E30D447A40204" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="6FE5EF5DEBD876A0FA09F98DBCD7FE07">
<mods:title id="B242F7B94456B220E24242E86919B449">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="76ADF0E3F844D0C3211335B546479C17">
<mods:date id="BA1FDFC950C50DCB2CAB115194C4A6A3">2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="E048A9C809939A03CF834452100EC9CD" type="volume">
<mods:number id="DD1DF50C60FA4F13184612F6B9C2655B">662</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="AC94529AACD545268EA4BA8E3AB5A1C9" unit="page">
<mods:start id="D1A1B1647403C1A237D42279AC585CE2">101</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F3211E06F81CB3F02A1C5E2F667A6F67">126</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="12E6F02BAD5FA7FFE7CAE61D08E645CD">
<mods:url id="687F46BF052DB05EBA87EDACE8DF918C">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.662.12124</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="1DF4B1ACB79598657D7FB33AAD23CD84">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="63BBFEA6DC2B12E05777D5E21C37107B" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.662.12124</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="3D8A6D1A1F2AC70412DBCDCCDDA88D68" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-662-101</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0D7A4697D7940872176F774231C88503" type="ZBK">0250ADB4740A4DB283FA92E3BA0363D2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="3290D8305DF27CC933BAD21D93527C7B" type="ZooBank">0250ADB4740A4DB283FA92E3BA0363D2</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="556993CE3B5B353924EFFE0A1D3BAC68" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127879723" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:556993CE3B5B353924EFFE0A1D3BAC68" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/556993CE3B5B353924EFFE0A1D3BAC68" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="107" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
<subSubSection id="0721DE600D015C2A8806BDBF894A80B6" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="236230C13CDDA23FF0CD4112B151191B" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
<taxonomicName id="A5CDDF124342E2954D1A5B26385FFC0E" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion alekseevi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alekseevi">Bembidion alekseevi</taxonomicName>
http://zoobank.org/A58EB208-0710-496E-85ED-3D6D9E4AF9F9Figs 28, 29-31, 32-34, 35-36
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35B33A8FC48EE4C14308F7F383D46F5F" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" type="holotype">
<paragraph id="C25C30FBABC4B338567534BDD438EADA" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A45EAD1191267B6CB12100CD1BEA3B8D" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
Female in Baltic amber; size of amber piece approximately 14 
<normalizedToken id="738B402C2767A819D7A0529C802C5D6B" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
12 
<normalizedToken id="5CA399A0419FA26427FB6C66831449B2" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
4 mm (irregularly cut, Fig. 31), with collection label data &quot;AWI 130&quot;, in Vitalii I. Alekseev Collection, Kaliningrad. This amber piece was found in the surf zone of the Baltic Sea coast of the Sambian peninsula, in winter 2014-2015.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E45284C6A27EA2F7119EB6154FE00385" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="107" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" type="preservation status">
<paragraph id="3FD6C67679439E7A801659AA7BD82339" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">Preservation status.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0C117130BF40E6BC0EA629CC00FFED7D" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
The amber piece is permeated by broad light-reflecting flow lines particularly at level of the 
<taxonomicName id="EE2D1CA8857AB3ADAC41EC050B5979D5" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Bembidion</taxonomicName>
inclusion. The anterior portion of the ventral side of the beetle body is covered by milky coating. Thus, mouth parts, ventral side of prothorax, and some portions of the dorsal surface of the fossil cannot by investigated by light microscopy (Figs 29-30). The specimen is markedly shrunken with its exoskeleton which is disintegrated, shattered, and dissociated from the inclusion wall (Fig. 35). However, the negative imprint of the beetle body (= inclusion wall) could be recovered in detail using micro-CT (Figs 32-36). The left elytron is somewhat impressed behind the middle which is probably the result of the embedding of an immature and thus teneral specimen (Fig. 32). The hindwings are inflated caudal of the elytra (Fig. 30).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CDE21501CC2E8A7C1B7DDF339DD518F8" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">Syninclusions. Few dirt particles, numerous air bubbles.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4A9A22FFF4C1F99D7C5894F5C7B614B2" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">Description. Body length: 3.9 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="368E21528B6B27364215B3A93477ADC3" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">Colour: Head and pronotum blackish brown with marked metallic lustre. Elytra middle brown with yellowish side margin (eighth and part of the seventh intervals), a small yellowish pre-apical spot between sixth and eighth interval at the beginning of the apical elytral third, and additionally with small yellowish spots in the third (4 spots) and fifth intervals (3 spots) as shown in Fig. 28.</paragraph>
<caption id="4F05A383F247D05FC517A45DFA6753C6" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
<paragraph id="FA9BA5DF93B1C72128B82737313D5F3C" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
Figures 27-28. Fossil 
<taxonomicName id="D7E01EEAD50C32B32BBFBE9622E5D499" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Bembidion</taxonomicName>
Latreille, 1802, reconstruction of the external shape in dorsal view. 27 
<taxonomicName id="6C2A1120D5BE12C519E9CC2AAE5D6AB9" genus="B." lsidName="B. bukejsi" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" rank="species" species="bukejsi">B. bukejsi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 28 
<taxonomicName id="54DC7ED0BBFE08297E5EF4A6992B2CCA" genus="B." lsidName="B. alekseevi" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" rank="species" species="alekseevi">B. alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="A6F8C2B46F6A801BD18384F1C5FAE961" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
Microsculpture: Surfaces of head including labrum and pronotum with deeply engraved isodiametric sculpticells. Elytral intervals with very finely engraved, small and irregularly formed meshes which are not clearly visible below magnification of 
<normalizedToken id="07E1943E9A6C2D91515C4D51FE07C2B8" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
100.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2A14212D9836D6012CAAB19AD19416FD" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
Head: Moderately large and transverse; length 0.84 mm, width 0.91 mm. Mandibles moderately stout. Labrum with apical margin slightly concave, dorsally with three pairs of setae near apical margin. Clypeus with one pair of setae in normal position. Apical segment of maxillary palpus subulate, approx. 2/5 of length of penultimate segment; penultimate segment rather long and slender, moderately dilated anteriorly. Antennae moderately slender, with pedicellus almost two times longer than broad, and with four antennomeres extending beyond the pronotal base. Mentum and submentum distinct (shape and setation of medio-apical tooth could not be recovered); pits absent. Eyes large, hemispherical protruded; tempora very small, approx. 1/16 of eyes diameter. Disk slightly convex, smooth apart from the prominent microsculpture. Frontal furrows very shallow, very short, absent on disk. Supraorbital furrows very shallow, without punctures; two supraorbital setae present and in usual position for 
<taxonomicName id="3735D11A11327EE799E8879B4B354F57" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Bembidion</taxonomicName>
. The pore of the anterior supraorbital seta is semicirculary surrounded by a prominent ridge on its internal side (Fig. 36).
</paragraph>
<caption id="A00AC7EA000EFC1F6C1A61606EDB85AB" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
<paragraph id="48F14C2F7DB6887DE1D6C2B1E1D0AD8A" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
Figures 29-31. 
<taxonomicName id="4EE836D326D3787EC922F381B5E94F9D" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion alekseevi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alekseevi">Bembidion alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., light microscopic images of the holotype. 29 left dorso-lateral aspect 30 right ventro-lateral aspect 31 general view of the amber piece; the position of the fossil is marked by an arrow.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="43982CC9FD12875DC9800C3E3487831A" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">Prothorax: Pronotum rather small, length 0.77 mm, width 1.02 mm, transverse (width/length = 1.32), 1.1 times broader than head, subcordate, broadest in middle, with sides distinctly concave in posterior third. Laterobasal angles large, slightly obtuse, not protruded laterally. Basal margin 1.05 times broader than apical margin. Disk moderately convex, smooth apart from the prominent microsculpture. Anterior margin slightly convex in middle, lateroapical angles small and rounded, slightly protruded. Posterior margin not beaded, distinctly convex in middle and concave near laterobasal angles. Median longitudinal impression moderately deep in middle, absent near pronotal apex and base; anterior and posterior transverse impressions very shallow, smooth; laterobasal foveae large and rounded, moderately deep, smooth. Lateral gutter narrow and flat, faintly widened in middle, smooth. Laterobasal carina long and straight, approx. 1/3 of length of pronotum. Both lateral and laterobasal setae present, with the lateral seta located slightly before middle of pronotum. Surface structures on ventral side of the prothorax could not be imaged.</paragraph>
<caption id="E7B14FAB43C4CAA23FC77050994806F3" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
<paragraph id="A5E0D61ED44E340C404C22C54747B042" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
Figures 32-34. 
<taxonomicName id="323EE88431F1A8C6C2BBAE38455C1B13" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion alekseevi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alekseevi">Bembidion alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., volume rendering of the holotype. 32 dorsal aspect 33 right lateral aspect 34 ventral aspect.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="45F87E3E1B8241ABD278EB29013B7646" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">Pterothorax: Elytra in lateral view moderately convex, slightly flattened on disc, in dorsal very slender ovate, length 2.34 mm, width 1.52 mm, length/width = 1.54, widest slightly behind the middle, distinctly wider than pronotum (width of elytra/width of pronotum = 1.49). Surface and lateral border glabrous and smooth apart from the primary elytral setation. Shoulders moderately broad, humeral margin rounded, sides with preapical sinuation indistinct. Presence or absence of crista clavicularis as well as subapical plica could not be imaged. Parascutellar stria long, parascutellar seta present. All striae complete, slightly impressed but markedly punctate, intervals flat or slightly convex; apical stria deeply impressed from the apical cross of 5th and 6th stria towards apex; recurrent stria lacking. Ninth interval very narrow in front, slightly broadened from beginning of apical third towards apex (the left elytron of the specimen is artificially flattened in anterior third and therefore, the external intervals appearing distinctly broader caudally than on the right elytron, see Figs 19, 31). Each elytron with two discal setae in third interval, with relevant pores distinctly separated from third stria. Preapical seta located in the deepened apical portion of the seventh stria; the fine apical seta located at apical margin. Subapical setae of umbilicate series could not be imaged; the humeral series consist of four setae, with distance between first and second setae slightly larger than between second and third setae, and with distance between third and fourth setae distinctly larger than between first and second setae; the fourth seta located slightly caudad of the level of the anterior discal seta; two apical setae of the umbilicate series situated anterior of the junction of the eighth stria and lateral gutter. Metepisternum markedly long, glabrous and smooth, with outer margin 2.3 times longer than anterior margin. The surface of the metasternal process could not be imaged. Hindwings fully developed.</paragraph>
<caption id="28CB2744190271F7D4D9CF8C59E8BAA6" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
<paragraph id="F84EF575A1BD42E23CA851809AF656AA" pageId="5" pageNumber="106">
Figures 35-36. 
<taxonomicName id="F715C02A96811588727C25BB1EE99C9D" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion alekseevi" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="alekseevi">Bembidion alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., volume rendering of the head capsule of the holotype using different grayscale thresholds, dorsal aspect. The arrow in Fig. 36 point to the prominent ridge on internal side of the anterior supraorbital pore, which is characteristic for representatives of the 
<taxonomicName id="8CE25B10BD05455AE806D62029B2AF7A" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" infraspecific-rank="subgenus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion (Eupetedromus)" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subGenus" subGenus="Eupetedromus">Bembidion subgenus Eupetedromus</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="7EC951D172998860E22415891574F56E" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">
<pageBreakToken id="8C9C4350787B5ECFBB44FD30E4EFCB89" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" start="start">Abdomen</pageBreakToken>
: Abdominal sternites 
<normalizedToken id="2200B871360D5792C448F1B094F743E2" originalValue="V–VI">V-VI</normalizedToken>
with one, VII with two (female) pairs of setae near apical margin; surfaces smooth, without hairs or micropunctures.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DD215F75337E90247CFA07AE59092711" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">Legs: Moderately short, unmodified, femora moderately robust, protibiae straight and moderately dilated towards apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1867D3AAF135B686DD6801FEE13A4375" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">Female genitalia: Could not be recovered using micro-CT.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7BE3CBCD655F2387B4C305D3DC19DA2C" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="14AA54FD69C12F375467090D2041F79A" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">Derivatio nominis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2DA3BE01AE4DBB210E737B57B9EE1C62" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">
The new species is dedicated to Vitalii I. Alekseev, Kaliningrad, for his important contributions to the systematics and biogeography of Cenozoic 
<taxonomicName id="FAC72655F27FAA2816E4C2E896638C16" genus="Bembidiina" lsidName="Bembidiina" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="order">Coleoptera</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4543EF3BE6C70D528D9B09E6BEB1870F" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" type="relationships and recognition">
<paragraph id="872CCACC9DDEBD49907C512D8597FBCF" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">Relationships and recognition.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="17F69040A6417A014FCFA0E96C88F98F" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">
This fossil 
<taxonomicName id="0EF31AE08462F45A8CB7A73268C86993" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Bembidion</taxonomicName>
is considered to be a representative of the subgenus 
<taxonomicName id="DC152ED1B65847F02D820F84B699AB53" genus="Bembidiina" lsidName="Bembidiina (Eupetedromus)" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="subGenus" subGenus="Eupetedromus">Eupetedromus</taxonomicName>
Netolitzky, 1911 based on combination of the following characters: (i) micro-meshes on surface of head and pronotum deeply engraved and thus contrasting with the elytra which appearing polished when viewed by magnification below x80; (ii) penultimate segment of maxillary palpus rather slender; (iii) anterior supraorbital pore on internal side semicirculary surrounded by a prominent ridge; (iv) supraorbital furrows very shallow; (v) pronotal median longitudinal impression not deepened near base; (vi) pronotal posterior transverse impressions very shallow; (vii) elytral discal setiferous pores distinctly separated from third stria; (viii) distance between third and fourth setae of the umbilical humeral series much larger than between first and second and between second and third setae. Similar patterns of elytral chaetotaxy are also observed in other species groups of 
<taxonomicName id="53278DFDEB7B89C252772301B8896F45" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Bembidion" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Bembidion" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Bembidion</taxonomicName>
, e.g., 
<taxonomicName id="1EA0C571565056F609287D9E37C0CA7C" authority="Motschulsky, 1850" authorityName="Motschulsky" authorityYear="1850" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Emphanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Emphanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Emphanes</taxonomicName>
Motschulsky, 1850, 
<taxonomicName id="4B8D20E199FA1F40CE0FD5A19B1E424C" authority="Netolitzky, 1920" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1920" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Notaphemphanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Notaphemphanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Notaphemphanes</taxonomicName>
Netolitzky, 1920, 
<taxonomicName id="A73F0CB3110C65062E83DBEB76502EA9" authority="Netolitzky, 1914" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1914" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Notaphocampa" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Notaphocampa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Notaphocampa</taxonomicName>
Netolitzky, 1914, 
<taxonomicName id="DE02A0FDE557B67D4BA7653309DFF58A" authority="Dejean, 1821" authorityName="Dejean" authorityYear="1821" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Notaphus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Notaphus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Notaphus</taxonomicName>
Dejean, 1821, 
<taxonomicName id="DACDD58678C2DFD3BE5E5C4C34469F4C" authority="Netolitzky, 1914" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1914" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Omotaphus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Omotaphus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Omotaphus</taxonomicName>
Netolitzky, 1914, 
<taxonomicName id="E7F2DECB9F17D6495C3BFD6553FE4413" authority="Motschulsky, 1864" authorityName="Motschulsky" authorityYear="1864" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Talanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Talanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Talanes</taxonomicName>
Motschulsky, 1864, 
<taxonomicName id="10D333FD28D8DC5B5D77DA4D9A96D22A" authority="Netolitzky, 1918" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1918" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Trepanedoris" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Trepanedoris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Trepanedoris</taxonomicName>
Netolitzky, 1918, 
<taxonomicName id="4492BE093F105EDF63DD27B350C3AD6B" authority="Motschulsky, 1864" authorityName="Motschulsky" authorityYear="1864" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Trepanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Trepanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Trepanes</taxonomicName>
Motschulsky, 1864, and the 
<taxonomicName id="B9C6AF9310250B28E2C1D3698B6FA799" authority="Bedel, 1896" authorityName="Bedel" authorityYear="1896" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Diplocampa" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Diplocampa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Diplocampa</taxonomicName>
complex sensu 
<bibRefCitation id="132685FD4DAA9E2767F0E3A7D1D0D1CA" author="Maddison, DR" journalOrPublisher="Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution," pageId="9" pageNumber="110" pagination="533 - 576" title="Phylogeny of Bembidion and related ground beetles (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Trechinae: Bembidiini: Bembidiina)." url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2012.01.015" volume="63" year="2012">Maddison (2012)</bibRefCitation>
. Species of the latter complex differ from this fossil and other species of 
<taxonomicName id="D7F6ABF3745F5FC0C1F6FCCFFCB12813" authority="Netolitzky, 1911" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1911" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Eupetedromus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eupetedromus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eupetedromus</taxonomicName>
by presence of long and deep frontal and suborbital furrows. The same feature applies for species of the subgenera 
<taxonomicName id="616B2119D03A6829E55940461899C5DE" authority="Motschulsky, 1850" authorityName="Motschulsky" authorityYear="1850" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Emphanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Emphanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Emphanes</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="A4D73D9E0B70B01E03D387DFDE396301" authority="Netolitzky, 1920" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1920" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Notaphemphanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Notaphemphanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Notaphemphanes</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="E5DCE7586DF8C457E9BE26492B0326F9" authority="Motschulsky, 1864" authorityName="Motschulsky" authorityYear="1864" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Talanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Talanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Talanes</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="D5C6F6C1BB87DEA3CE89E2A46866EC2A" authority="Netolitzky, 1918" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1918" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Trepanedoris" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Trepanedoris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Trepanedoris</taxonomicName>
, and 
<taxonomicName id="CDB6097B9EE01E8DE333D93D4F5D2AC4" authority="Motschulsky, 1864" authorityName="Motschulsky" authorityYear="1864" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Trepanes" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Trepanes" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Trepanes</taxonomicName>
which additionally differ by much more convex discs of head and pronotum, weakly engraved microsculpture on head and pronotum and, in most cases, by stouter penultimate maxillary palpomeres and deeper median longitudinal and posterior transverse impressions of pronotum. Species of 
<taxonomicName id="09D8BDD0262ABAFA01B8E553DD01FCA3" authority="Dejean, 1821" authorityName="Dejean" authorityYear="1821" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Notaphus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Notaphus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Notaphus</taxonomicName>
are very similar to the fossil 
<taxonomicName id="6594D737D03FACCBFD8413DAF81EBA30" genus="B." lsidName="B. alekseevi" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="species" species="alekseevi">B. alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. last but not least due to the characteristic colour patterns of the body. However, species of 
<taxonomicName id="466F2170546D492B5B0D061AEAB2D092" authority="Dejean, 1821" authorityName="Dejean" authorityYear="1821" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Notaphus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Notaphus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Notaphus</taxonomicName>
lack the prominent ridge on internal side of the anterior supraorbital pore which is observed in 
<taxonomicName id="BE4E05170B13A95E2454BF88EFF33CE5" genus="B." lsidName="B. alekseevi" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="species" species="alekseevi">B. alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Most species of 
<taxonomicName id="78B4FA27A41BC8D99D3703713217E049" authority="Netolitzky, 1914" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1914" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Notaphocampa" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Notaphocampa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Notaphocampa</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="06583F54D5F9B6E7A6433B17ED6F27A3" authority="Netolitzky, 1914" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1914" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Omotaphus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Omotaphus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Omotaphus</taxonomicName>
differ strikingly by very different patterns of its elytral microsculpture; in the Ethiopian species 
<taxonomicName id="90DA3558AA749AE9CE457F1620662E3D" genus="B." lsidName="B. scotti" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="species" species="scotti">B. scotti</taxonomicName>
Netolitzky, 1931 the micro-meshes on the elytra are extremely fine engraved similar to what is observed in 
<taxonomicName id="57E52D9847A1797CFB1E8128CB069E81" genus="B." lsidName="B. alekseevi" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="species" species="alekseevi">B. alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (see 
<bibRefCitation id="55CF96CCF9A76AF3DA20389D92B0B9AF" author="Bonavita, P" journalOrPublisher="Entomologische Blaetter und Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" pagination="67 - 106" title="Bembidiina of the Afrotropical region: BembidionsubgenusOmotaphus Netolitzky, 1914 (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Bembidiini)." volume="112" year="2016">Bonavita et al. 2016</bibRefCitation>
), however, in 
<taxonomicName id="95B4EC6034B3BC936A3BFF3F879A4A3F" genus="B." lsidName="B. scotti" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="species" species="scotti">B. scotti</taxonomicName>
the microsculpture on pronotal surface is likewise weak and thus very different from what is developed in 
<taxonomicName id="21157B3B88184D4C57C4770C33C858BF" genus="B." lsidName="B. alekseevi" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="species" species="alekseevi">B. alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2C73609747E12F6436B7BF625B521A22" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="D825512D4542B975163E9C179F3C09F0" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">Remarks on biogeography and ecology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="642814E34F2696A96FDCB7FE5BFD95F3" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">
The subgenus 
<taxonomicName id="574F0CA73615D8BDE4BFD1D0933D0247" genus="Bembidiina" lsidName="Bembidiina (Eupetedromus)" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="subGenus" subGenus="Eupetedromus">Eupetedromus</taxonomicName>
contains ten species which are distributed in the temperate and boreal zones of the Holarctic region (
<bibRefCitation id="4DF71ACA22AF63E9034F9FE3A51AF36A" pageId="6" pageNumber="107">Marggi et al. 2003</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="16F08FC21D4B6C25BAF79E05A0352DB9" author="Lorenz, W" journalOrPublisher="Published by the author, Tutzing" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" title="Systematic list of extant ground beetles of the world. Second edition." year="2005">Lorenz 2005</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="B5D0A6D2D8B9C9C4C8EED5917C3526B6" author="Bousquet, Y" journalOrPublisher="Zookeys" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" pagination="1 - 1722" title="Catalogue of Geadephaga (Coleoptera, Adephaga) of America, north of Mexico." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.245.3416" volume="245" year="2012">Bousquet 2012</bibRefCitation>
). The occurrence of 
<taxonomicName id="66B7122ED91342DE8949AAE57A2BABDE" genus="B." lsidName="B. alekseevi" pageId="6" pageNumber="107" rank="species" species="alekseevi">B. alekseevi</taxonomicName>
sp. n. in the Baltic amber forest is therefore in accordance with the expected distribution 
<pageBreakToken id="A3DE8A0E03DB1420F9DAC178A6305CE8" pageId="7" pageNumber="108" start="start">of</pageBreakToken>
<taxonomicName id="7C356B9CD1BE5A6755C3DCE5690C372C" authority="Netolitzky, 1911" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1911" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Eupetedromus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eupetedromus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="108" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eupetedromus</taxonomicName>
group during the Early Cenozoic if one would accept presence of extra-tropical habitat conditions at least locally in the area of this forest. Based on comparative studies, 
<bibRefCitation id="FBDF7713971A2AC375C2804A10DC03F1" author="Wolfe, JA" journalOrPublisher="Annals of the Missouri Botanical Garden" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" pagination="264 - 279" title="Some aspects of the plant geography of the Northern Hemisphere during the Late Cretaceous and Tertiary." url="https://doi.org/10.2307/2395198" volume="62" year="1975">Wolfe (1975)</bibRefCitation>
found close relationships of the flora of the Eocene northern Europe to the modern flora of Indo-Malaya. This flora represents a mixture of tropical/subtropical and temperate elements with occurrences of the latter along slopes of the many high elevated areas of this region. Based on evidences from insect fossils, 
<bibRefCitation id="4CAE5C6E428BBB95CAB7A3ECA736DDE2" author="Ander, K" journalOrPublisher="Lunds Universitets Arsskrift N. F. 2" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" pagination="1 - 83" title="Die Insektenfauna des Baltischen Bernsteins nebst damit verknuepften zoogeographischen Problemen" volume="38" year="1942">Ander (1942)</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="4E56F19AE5D3B206C1C311F9ED3A75A7" author="Schmidt, J" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" pagination="539 - 550" title="Confirmation of occurrence of Trechus Clairville, 1806 in the Baltic amber forests, with description of a flightless edaphic species, and remarks on Trechoides Motschulsky, 1856 (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Trechini)." url="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4028.4.5" volume="4028" year="2015">Schmidt and Faille (2015)</bibRefCitation>
, and 
<bibRefCitation id="EA40395EFB301B3E358F5F8425BCCFF2" author="Schmidt, J" journalOrPublisher="Zookeys" pageId="9" pageNumber="110" pagination="113 - 127" title="X-Ray microscopy reveals endophallic structures in a new species of the ground beetle genus Trechus Clairville, 1806 from Baltic amber (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Trechini)." url="https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.614.9283" volume="614" year="2016 b">Schmidt et al. (2016b)</bibRefCitation>
suggested the presence of higher elevated areas in the Baltic amber forests which may represent suitable habitats for insects adapted to the temperate climate, e.g., 
<taxonomicName id="7FF46D4FD66ABFE06984FFBC4745C9E0" authority="Netolitzky, 1911" authorityName="Netolitzky" authorityYear="1911" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Eupetedromus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Eupetedromus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="108" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Eupetedromus</taxonomicName>
ground beetles.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>