<document id="EC2C19113D1DC131B7142DD6961E7ABB" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047607" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4BC03313-37D8-4322-9FED-245C696C8607" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="577DDF24BC57E3944CE0A31E9260A160" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio oculi Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="4BC03313-37D8-4322-9FED-245C696C8607" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="156" lastPageNumber="157" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="CE5228A036D7BD3417655CAE6538B0EA" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="7754D08EDAE6398280448819B9A225EE">
<mods:title id="D20A4ABDF3253B8E145E95CE0F23C3EF">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="BEC88103010C37F9B85801EF7E9F8944" type="personal">
<mods:role id="C86108DC06EA2F950CBAFED778E10D9A">
<mods:roleTerm id="8EF9FC238DC3590CE4FA38831A605419">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="56E1D4E4992E6136B49B5E0092A22B37">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="E7A09E743F72325BBBCF75EA08B19EDF" type="personal">
<mods:role id="94784A6EB40976A07DADA57E08E7BB7B">
<mods:roleTerm id="AE58CFE83433BB8EBD80C27B01FBABF6">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="36F8EE8EC6109B2377CCD808D2DE30B7">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="41936F52F3E695E1F2B185FCFD8952C9" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A654196030545E00A0DD4311CC902B13">
<mods:roleTerm id="38D1D8AD4889DFBB8DF45FA38A9F54A9">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="29AB50AAC22C5E931697FD0E9167F20F">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="E051B90A7B0E9F0166B38273582DCFF3" type="personal">
<mods:role id="0A0960D2AC784ED223C513F9C7C27446">
<mods:roleTerm id="EECC29F122664474D280D028BC8BAEEF">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="053500CDE355B6E1D434E6F78A666A77">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="60A8AE09CAA51BF198AC7DB0B15502BF">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="82F6A0DAA70839C56C2289D526FAFE4E" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="FE7360E200076E921E016528D50E720A">
<mods:title id="8B53D163B5F8BF3AA4510EF83C9BCE75">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="AE8F566A6DFDAA64FC7DC05A42E4EDEF">
<mods:date id="88A900E1B3728139DADE73C612C7A5E9">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="CC57115E7C0F7B00B776C183D1BF5C3A" type="volume">
<mods:number id="4D7E6024FA8CA72F3C7E4D8CBD5468CE">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="2167D2B49F8ABC7D62BB9F6A9925E45B" unit="page">
<mods:start id="70FE4FE06012F4C0393B96DFBB46230E">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="CB3C43B00D892E7B9A26AA7D9FB8E928">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="DF8800D91BAF291920997BBDA42A72B6">
<mods:url id="913EF43846A228EF1F5C764C29406D9C">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="E2DDBEE677909BCDBA7BB0291AD9431D">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="A0CF43E7FD04D0D4020D1225A750EC1E" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E2161D5C7779F90DA774CBC5A9383187" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8BF872623E6AC68B1B9DA7C514B98407" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="577DDF24BC57E3944CE0A31E9260A160" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047607" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4BC03313-37D8-4322-9FED-245C696C8607" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/577DDF24BC57E3944CE0A31E9260A160" lastPageId="156" lastPageNumber="157" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">
<subSubSection id="DBD45D5AEA8D09F2E1B6BABD7894F582" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="3FF56EE3EB4B47B4C50FA16ABF586092" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">
<taxonomicName id="8C8157308BA532DE648367FE6CC08FF6" LSID="http://zoobank.org/4BC03313-37D8-4322-9FED-245C696C8607" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio oculi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oculi">Oxyscelio oculi Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="0F5445E23F95D29D9AFA20AA110CA271" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 241-246; Morphbank74
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="357962DDCAD1AA998205CBDC2D9654BE" lastPageId="156" lastPageNumber="157" pageId="153" pageNumber="154" type="description">
<paragraph id="93F32DF4DBE57585371C1B941D81A8A1" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BED1F1209AB377BCB90C973C40124BC1" pageId="153" pageNumber="154">Female. Body length 2.7-3.2 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="130C3A9D5E59DD34138AFFC5253EF595" pageId="154" pageNumber="155">
<pageBreakToken id="0E1A6A40CB76D90CDA87C83B11489CD8" pageId="154" pageNumber="155" start="start">Radicle</pageBreakToken>
color and shade: same as scape, both yellowish or reddish. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: shorter than pedicel; as long as pedicel. A4: longer than broad. A5: longer than broad.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EA2E74964E6204304CA42AB9E6D33A9E" pageId="154" pageNumber="155">Ventral clypeal margin: concave. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: granulate. Hyperoccipital carina: present as a single carina. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: present laterally, absent medially. Occiput sculpture: smooth. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, complete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: rugose; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: rugose; umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: granulate. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: granulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1431F8E3D65BE80A51E996A9FC70A7EA" pageId="154" pageNumber="155">Lateral pronotal area sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate punctate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent; granulate. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: slightly emarginate posteriorly, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T6. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: meeting near propodeal midlength. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: with series of longitudinal carinae extending to lateral propodeal carinae. Median propodeal carina: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="507006E9F6ACE254CBAD755CA28F62EB" lastPageId="155" lastPageNumber="156" pageId="154" pageNumber="155">
T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: straight. T2 sculpture: densely foveolate, longitudinal sculpture irregular. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: 
<pageBreakToken id="A2FC318ED2B8CEECEAAC81F45EFA48BC" pageId="155" pageNumber="156" start="start">absent</pageBreakToken>
. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: densely setose, setal pits between very weak longitudinal rugae. S5 sculpture: densely setose, setal pits between very weak longitudinal rugae. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="50BFCB4D7A0D24CD805831A322AC90C3" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">
<pageBreakToken id="8E406980995C7314805EE93FFF3496A4" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Body length 2.65-3.15 mm (n=20). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: longer than broad. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 3. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: truncate.
</paragraph>
<caption id="B1260B7EA56C6B152754FD2720783FBE" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">
<paragraph id="F963828AE4FFE48D7BACB87F0FF70948" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">
Figures 241-246. 
<taxonomicName id="471AF798FEAB88E61DCEE8BF867E0BFD" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio oculi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oculi">Oxyscelio oculi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 442277) 241 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 242 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 243 Head, anterior view 244 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 442295) 245 Antenna 246 Mesosoma, dorsal view. Morphbank74
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="5238ABE7EFA912859C6BAA95514E8258" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="38C0516F90944D3CC204751C0FB49E69" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="78CA981D0D1E44C390A2A067CE20BC42" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">Both sexes: Frontal depression nearly parallel-sided, transverse carinae absent; submedian carina sharp. Hyperoccipital carina sharp and strong. Occipital carina incomplete, lateral portions almost reaching hyperoccipital carina; occiput smooth, with only a few setiferous puncta and fine rugae. Metascutellum with a small concave postero-medial area, laterally with broad longitudinally striate area, weakly emarginate, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein present. Coxa not darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina not expanded laterally. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4 longer than broad, A5 nearly as long as broad. Mesoscutellum nearly smooth, with a few setiferous puncta. T1 midlobe with 5 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach or exceed T6. Male: All flagellomeres longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 3 longitudinal carinae, hardly raised above sidelobes. Mesoscutellum with strong longitudinal rugae and no granulate sculpture. Fore wing long enough to reach to or beyond T7. T7 truncate, steeply sloping.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AB3ACCECF3BE4E4CE0C7E45FC3A03DEB" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="9426A7CEC245DA27D8928CF8B6DD9DF5" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5DF2A566147A3A7CB00E60B6CF8485A1" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="8A914FCF39E8E978686B2FADF22E3DF6" originalValue="“eye.”">&quot;eye.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1424899BD995CC1D77C47687D926F394" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="B2E2E7FB35BF2E62D67677F43C8AC022" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6031CEF6F47D7720F3110CA334770C32" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307095]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A3DCF2E9B1108FB6FFD46C2D02EB67AD" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="B31AF60119CD28291BAA534B2BD0BC8C" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="24DBA9EDF367ED557EBAD950FA1A4B6D" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, Mount Glorious, 1977, malaise trap, OSUC 442277 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 35 females, 36 males, Australian Museum K245262, K245267, K245268, K245270, K245274 (AMSA); ANIC DB 32-020075, 32-020076 (ANIC); OSUC 227548, 227608, 462563-462566, 462727-462728 (CNCI); OSUC 442273, 442278, 442301-442302, 451276-451277, QDPC 0-165656, QDPC 0-165658 (QDPC); OSUC 442298 (QMBA); OSUC 359782-359787, 442271-442272, 442274-442276, 442279-442297, 442299-442300, 442303, 442305-442310, 451274-451275, 451278-451283 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A3D66868C126EF342727E303D46246C6" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" type="comments">
<paragraph id="7343DF96372164367B062FBF25EFD9AB" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DB4EEF36DB5C36B1948B3DF2E137A720" pageId="156" pageNumber="157">
<taxonomicName id="D23573A57AE609632D6683E9E0D00F0C" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio oculi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oculi">Oxyscelio oculi</taxonomicName>
is part of a species complex characterized by a weakly developed T1 midlobe in males but vaulted T1 in females, a very smooth occiput, a short and convex mesoscutellum, and large eyes. Distinction between 
<taxonomicName id="77291BB657E5A0045E53B9F7ABDAC5B3" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio oculi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oculi">Oxyscelio oculi</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="33D3A6633595D8F6A7E532E762DA8ACC" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio croci" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="156" pageNumber="157" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="croci">Oxyscelio croci</taxonomicName>
is chiefly based on mesoscutellar surface sculpture. Males in this complex but not fitting the above diagnosis occur, and are not currently assigned to species. These imply that undetected sibling species in this complex may exist.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>