<document id="7A9CC1633C0E57E76B620AB3C1618F6E" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.73.836" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6ad4de08-67ef-4cec-9513-58c1aefd033c" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159360943" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-73-61" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1F3772D3-2D07-45A3-985B-B547E618578C" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-73-61" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 73" ModsDocTitle="A new genus and two new species of Phygadeuontini (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) from China" checkinTime="1451250852223" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Sheng, Mao-Ling &amp; Sun, Shu-Ping" docDate="2010" docId="587CA30D818EB2462B8E2CB5C9165FE8" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 73: 61-71" docOrigin="ZooKeys 73" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.73.836" docTitle="Carinityla pilosa Sheng &amp; Sun, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="1F3772D3-2D07-45A3-985B-B547E618578C" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="67" masterDocId="BA53FFA51757D057FFA30C7FFFB0FFAB" masterDocTitle="A new genus and two new species of Phygadeuontini (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) from China" masterLastPageNumber="71" masterPageNumber="61" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" updateTime="1643725879403" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="BA371EE0B3B9FF451C0783077A11C35E" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2E93F753AA38E4D1C3AC56388F881641">
<mods:title id="80515B55647D0F189759CF0098478A4D">A new genus and two new species of Phygadeuontini (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae) from China</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="88721A16E557BAD54F0A0FBA0E8CB26C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="4C4EFCBD9E40844EF04F16FE29096D06">
<mods:roleTerm id="6A4E5FCC0B5601417605A539AD10BD80">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1341EAABD29C02584B219FD905FA5E45">Sheng, Mao-Ling</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="0CB11C9043D34DE481E68D2C0EF96ED7" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9B1145601ED6A4B34A4991FFA39AB7B7">
<mods:roleTerm id="03972108298C48B0316D95F94A588919">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3E1157CAF7126A5F287FB1C03C6E3B36">Sun, Shu-Ping</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="FE38C19EB82774B8923F3119352994EF">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="10007DB2A89174E4E05D84554E38520E" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="2A0B96998DA3F72A8EC02A2457DA69BA">
<mods:title id="615D130CF5AD18F87430E7642CBEDECB">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="C800259D0BEA80FB2FCA46691E59BD7F">
<mods:date id="6AE735D7F1FCA4CFF4030E1E92F17954">2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="CC30F7F1BBFAD956F26CB2A96D7273D7" type="volume">
<mods:number id="E48343DAFC49EB6E1CF28816C1876C8C">73</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="66CB3E01C70FE3FBEBFEF43A0466A0E0" unit="page">
<mods:start id="C277070386771B5B397C0DEC8688CE07">61</mods:start>
<mods:end id="49065EA2442426FFE640263AC3D6F929">71</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="16CF2504C2816CB47FB33EFA9530C299">
<mods:url id="1B07AFAA03D576F00C01B0E9652322E9">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.73.836</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="0725F243BA9DEB501DCA2DFE16258B3A">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="D23C8AC7BB79C94E200AD7FB429DE302" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.73.836</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="0BBCE9945546504E56A5A82CB1A5AF10" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-73-61</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="35E741651840B4177A3739DE9E265A04" type="ZooBank">869064F2-F69C-49B9-BBC3-8275FFCB76AF</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="587CA30D818EB2462B8E2CB5C9165FE8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159360943" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1F3772D3-2D07-45A3-985B-B547E618578C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/587CA30D818EB2462B8E2CB5C9165FE8" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">
<subSubSection id="AD07F1F54D96BB4DEA4678CC028FD11F" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="57C84507C29EEAA48E3D761460CBCE1E" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">
<taxonomicName id="D55F4B7441C165DE3BB14AB2D83639E1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1F3772D3-2D07-45A3-985B-B547E618578C" authority="Sheng &amp; Sun" authorityName="Sheng &amp; Sun" authorityYear="2010" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Carinityla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Carinityla pilosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pilosa">Carinityla pilosa Sheng &amp; Sun</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="81D9A19327416DF0401BFE46D4D6CA31" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 10-16
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3805A8CA490AA4B6BE5F9E01A5FD959B" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="1E2CED84A11AFF33E493043C84CADDB7" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="687811C0ECA8B5D28B249CF866284425" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">The specific name is derived from the long and dense hairs on the body.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="32ABB1B19718F914A9FDCE33AA6E9D84" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" type="types">
<paragraph id="E5C6DCF58B31B654A88B140AE4945DBD" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Types.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A3AD88E1F57E52DFFE3AA46C050FF125" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Holotype, female, CHINA: Quannan County, 650m, Jiangxi Province, 29 June 2010, leg. Shi-Chang Li. Paratypes: 7 males, CHINA: Quannan County, 530 to 628m, Jiangxi Province, 12 May to 10 June 2008, leg. Shi-Chang Li. 3 males, CHINA: Quannan County, 628 to 700m, Jiangxi Province, 31 May to 18 June 2010, leg. Shi-Chang Li.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1DBC68DAACED9A5A2865A75F3D64DF72" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="7B51D9CC369C5D873AB750E13175D581" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3546CDAC99D87E558F0369524B79F2F6" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Second tergum, hind femur and tibia black. Notaulus of male reaching beyond center of mesoscutum. Lateral sides of scutellum raised and median portion weakly concave in male. Scutellum with lateral carina extending 0.2 to 0.3 of its length.</paragraph>
<caption id="0B66E414795B66465991117C47ADF8AD" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="78D21CF126AD242B26DDCF2B4CBA34FC" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">
Figures 10-16. 
<taxonomicName id="4C59D243A4C9AE3287C72F5525CE4ACF" authority="Sheng &amp; Sun, 2010" authorityName="Sheng &amp; Sun" authorityYear="2010" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Carinityla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Carinityla pilosa" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pilosa">Carinityla pilosa</taxonomicName>
Sheng &amp; Sun, sp. n. 10-13: Female. 10 Body, lateral view 11 Face 12 Mesopleuron 13 Propodeum 14-16: male 14 Body, lateral view 15 Median portion of flagellomeres and tyloids 16 Propodeum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="49C5E5F3CEEC054B713F8ADD73643091" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" type="description">
<paragraph id="F91C50BE189E36DB145DBAE5E7CA03F2" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="08D87F349BEA79C933F3C9BAE44F8F75" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Female. Body length about 9.0 mm. Fore wing length about 7.2 mm. Ovipositor length about 2.8 mm. Head and mesosoma with long and dense yellowish brown hairs.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E80F29C56ACCE3E03C8CED490C329EE0" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" type="head">
<paragraph id="7D8E94EE58D6747BA3EA5834A2387F75" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Head.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="20EE666BB204719054E9AE74C6034901" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">
Face (Figure 11) strongly convex medially, approximately 1.9 times as wide as long, with dense and irregular punctures. Clypeal suture vestigial between clypeal foveae. Clypeus slightly convex, basal portion with sparse and irregular punctures, distance between punctures 1.0 to 3.0 times diameter of puncture; subapical portion with shallow, transverse concavity; apical 0.2 smooth and impunctate, median section of apical margin distinctly raised. Mandible with indistinct longitudinal wrinkles and fine punctures; upper tooth longer than lower tooth. Cheek with elongate punctures. Subocular sulcus indistinct. Malar space approximately 0.5 times as long as basal width of mandible. Gena with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 1.0 times diameter of puncture; in dorsal view approximately 0.6 times as long as width of eye. Vertex with irregular punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 1.5 times diameter of puncture. Postero-ocellar line about 0.6 times as long as ocular-ocellar line. Frons approximately flat, with regular and dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 1.0 times diameter of puncture. Antenna distinctly shorter than body in length, with 27 flagellomeres, ratio of length of flagellomeres 1:2:3:4:5 is 3.7:4.7:4.5:4.3:4.1. Flagellomeres 10 to 11 (12) of male with tyloids (Figure 15) similar to those of 
<taxonomicName id="3A967C8A93C6540B2CE52A90E60FCCC6" authority="Sheng &amp; Sun, 2010" authorityName="Sheng &amp; Sun" authorityYear="2010" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Carinityla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Carinityla punctulata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="punctulata">Carinityla punctulata</taxonomicName>
. Tyloid on flagellomere 11 0.7 to 0.9 times as long as flagellomere. Occipital carina complete and strong, joining oral carina above base of mandible.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2FB7748EDD42C07CCF8CC06DFB70472F" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="4" pageNumber="65" type="mesosoma">
<paragraph id="7F38CD1DEBC0491B5622CAA6643C315F" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">Mesosoma.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3497D1D49857F61A9F400F8971ACCF92" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="67" pageId="4" pageNumber="65">
Anterior portion of pronotum with fine punctures, laterally concave and lower portion with dense, oblique transverse wrinkles; upper posterior portion with fine punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 1.0 times diameter of puncture; upper posterior margin slightly and narrowly raised. Mesoscutum with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 0.5 times diameter of puncture; posterior median portion with irregular longitudinal wrinkles. Notaulus present anteriorly. Scutoscutellar groove with fine longitudinal wrinkles. Scutellum almost flat, with irregular punctures. Postscutellum smooth and shining, lateral portion strongly convex, anterior-lateral portion deeply concave. Subalar prominence strongly co 
<pageBreakToken id="15C0BCDD2BC3D15644022A97FEEE5952" pageId="5" pageNumber="66" start="start">nvex</pageBreakToken>
. Upper portion of mesopleuron (Figure 12) with dense punctures; lower portion, above sternaulus, with irregular punctures; lower posterior portion with transverse wrinkles. Speculum with dense punctures. Epicnemial carina strongly curved backward above sternaulus, upper end reaching to subalar prominence. Metapleuron with dense and irregular punctures. Juxtacoxal carina complete. Anterior section of submetapleural carina strongly projecting. Wings brownish hyaline. Fore wing with vein 1cu-a almost opposite 1-M. Vein 2-Cu approximately 2.0 times as long 
<pageBreakToken id="30D3BBA53D74F25477ABA7A4A5B1D87E" pageId="6" pageNumber="67" start="start">as</pageBreakToken>
2cu-a. Hind wing vein 1-cu about 3.0 times as long as cu-a. Legs robust, with long and dense brown hairs. Hind coxae and femora with distinct fine punctures. Spurs of hind tibia approximately half length of first tarsomere. Ratio of length of hind tarsomere 1:2:3:4:5 is 10.0:4.7:3.4:1.6:3.7. Propodeum (Figure 13) with long, brown hairs. Area superomedia hexagonal, approximately 1.15 times as wide as long, costula connecting slightly in front of its middle. Area basalis and area superomedia smooth and shining. Area externa with fine punctures. Area dentipara with indistinct wrinkles. Area spiracularis almost smooth. Area lateralis with oblique transverse wrinkles. Area petiolaris and area posteroexterna with transverse wrinkles. Propodeal apophysis short and compressed. Propodeal spiracle approximately 3.0 times as long as wide, distance to pleural carina approximately 1.3 times as long as distance to lateral longitudinal carina.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AEE5C39FB2D3C79256B85C88655F1C28" pageId="6" pageNumber="67" type="metasoma">
<paragraph id="10AF642253B39A2E6A74CE5CD20F5C46" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">Metasoma.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3A350250A90188E365EEAF5C20266B37" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">First to third terga smooth and shining. First tergum approximately 2.3 times as long as apical width. Hind section of dorsolateral carina, behind spiracle, indistinct. Lateral margins of petiole almost parallel, only posterior portion slightly broadened. Postpetiole weakly and evenly convex, anterior half with sparse and fine punctures. Spiracle circular, very small, located at about apical 0.3 of first tergum. Second tergum approximately 0.65 times as long as apical width. Remaining terga with short brown hairs and indistinct punctures. Ovipositor sheath approximately as long as hind tibia. Ovipositor compressed, with weak nodus.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F25D2C211A9E77566173C24AA1B2921B" pageId="6" pageNumber="67" type="color">
<paragraph id="BB80EF6F8176AEB91972B0718A787500" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">Color</paragraph>
<paragraph id="29E66227A2C12CC3F5D89F3B0FAF9BE5" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">(Figure 10). Black, except the following. Ventral profiles of scape and pedicel dark brown. Flat portion of flagellomeres more or less brown. Dorsal profiles of eighth to fourteenth flagellomeres white. Maxillary and labial palpi buff except dark bases. Median portion of mandible crimson. All coxae and trochanters, inner profiles of front and mid femora yellowish brown. Remaining portion of fore legs and mid femora brown. Apices of mid femora, mid tibiae and tarsi puce. Apical portion of first tarsomere of hind tarsi, second to fourth tarsomeres, posterior median portions of sixth and seventh terga, main portion of eighth tergum white. Petiole of first tergum yellowish brown; postpetiole reddish brown. Stigma yellowish brown. veins brownish black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1D3FC885497FDDFADEDF9255387A7D89" pageId="6" pageNumber="67" type="male">
<paragraph id="820E0664F32A40502453E76DF40B291B" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">Male</paragraph>
<paragraph id="800248A444922B19FC4778824A85EBB3" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">(Figure 14). Body length 9.5 to 12.0 mm. Fore wing length 7.5 to 8.8 mm. Face 1.7 to 1.8 times as wide as long. Malar space 0.2 to 0.3 times as long as basal width of mandible. Antenna with 27 to 29 flagellomeres. Upper posterior portion of pronotum, in front of tegula, weakly convex. Notaulus long, reaching beyond center of mesoscutum. Lateral sides of scutellum raised, median portion weakly concave; basal 0.2 to 0.3 with lateral carina. Median portion of mesopleuron smooth and shining, impunctate. Area superomedia 1.5 to 1.6 times as wide as long, costula connecting at its anterior 0.3 (Figure 16). Propodeal spiracle 3.0 to 3.5 times as long as wide. First tergum 2.3 to 2.5 times as long as apical width. Dorsal profile of basal flagellomeres brownish black, ventral profile reddish brown; dorsal profiles of seventh to thirteen flagellomeres white; apical flagellomeres brownish black. Stigma and veins brownish black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3A4913A7BBFAB9525E4331C6BD878EA2" pageId="6" pageNumber="67" type="host">
<paragraph id="86D523DB555D93363FDE28192D730B98" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">Host.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4198CD5E15EF143477DA7D11D868D39F" pageId="6" pageNumber="67">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>