<document id="B10AB63B0EAC3CD8922A35423B473495" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047604" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D798D4E2-4822-4F23-8735-ABA7EA088346" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="5B36FEDCBA379AA2C9288FF5E16978ED" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio sepisessor Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="D798D4E2-4822-4F23-8735-ABA7EA088346" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="196" lastPageNumber="197" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="C219095830B7C40292AD704516316967" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="7B1FF176DC8640B4058CA4F2CAABFC63">
<mods:title id="DE416B45F54542B89196B9257C2A1A62">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="B283A0FB076C4ECF3D902D040D9650C9" type="personal">
<mods:role id="C42A2924008A56A38972D23C0BE8D417">
<mods:roleTerm id="82B2DDDB8BA3203A6132146869698D94">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5AAAF51C9F4E1800315372EBE1ABF2BA">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="EBEBBF8C39124B6D3E0759017BB84752" type="personal">
<mods:role id="98336B96B2690F96F86589957BEE62F6">
<mods:roleTerm id="A213EE103253C2B83848EE9072F2727B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3AB3CF76C070E215F204F4E3A1D7E93A">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="4DD84EAAF586ECD77779A9178E808B44" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AA1F38983634273625156FFABF99F29E">
<mods:roleTerm id="349AF9554EE9A68D083C7348F9968D24">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="25E07152C44C27A5935FD1E5E26E2B82">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="EC1A98F27D6EE637E37BAE982B24167E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="0642412AAA1837E4A60D3F12B4CBADCB">
<mods:roleTerm id="E287080924063D425748FCC3CF827762">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="097E2135E535CFD751FCCA1CF96FB3FA">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="6CE38FF1CCC562C71D64515BC25CDB32">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="8EBD8122A16840F3E9EAA53E55F327C3" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="F238411A066717A49BC949C3A607AB87">
<mods:title id="8718F09BB398C60C219922134F9217F8">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="A2C477926B9DD35279B5ECB131ED3462">
<mods:date id="84E22119B512F80F5F165F2D61CE7C64">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="C01C30A67A6F023632BEED68A2B685B7" type="volume">
<mods:number id="413541DCFCECDE19B9B66167CE5DB143">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="2D2CF34C99EAC54BE773B381EA2C3DD6" unit="page">
<mods:start id="7CB56E1866728DF6BCF3BA34C84FFA83">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="C77762480BE9574D1FEE8696ECB130A5">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="D3C321211DCF502FA5515756D723AB3B">
<mods:url id="9D75D5C040C251D99A945AA75A49B411">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="EE969F1E71F0E2FB3FB39CC269D09A90">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="AC84621FFB64A9E287C53ECED4593593" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="EE5D3CA47119803B22BCE72EDA31E80A" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="87B3539A380ABFBD9E558B2E67B05D8A" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="5B36FEDCBA379AA2C9288FF5E16978ED" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047604" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D798D4E2-4822-4F23-8735-ABA7EA088346" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5B36FEDCBA379AA2C9288FF5E16978ED" lastPageId="196" lastPageNumber="197" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
<subSubSection id="E79DEB6C57A0D953954AB24DE5D9BE9F" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="11A5DDD90D0CD46831F11963C3996F82" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
<taxonomicName id="0D498970873A50716C09AEF13648575F" LSID="http://zoobank.org/D798D4E2-4822-4F23-8735-ABA7EA088346" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio sepisessor" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sepisessor">Oxyscelio sepisessor Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="265B3741E0DC964F589BDE832638C6E2" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 319-324; Morphbank88
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D7FB71265BC508CFDAE1FCB32DA1551E" lastPageId="196" lastPageNumber="197" pageId="193" pageNumber="194" type="description">
<paragraph id="F4737BC3A2C535869474BA2F0C7A4064" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="996F0E29669B0CD0FD06FC1BA30AF865" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">Female. Body length 3.75-4.3 mm (n=21).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1168FC607E1A0D6BDE3CA33AC4C1B555" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: shorter than pedicel. A4: longer than broad. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EA855C9068BEA8DD2850C65E5A31BC30" lastPageId="195" lastPageNumber="196" pageId="193" pageNumber="194">
Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: with transverse ledge, face sharply receding below it. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression 
<pageBreakToken id="C63075EDE132BADD61D99D201D6C8496" pageId="194" pageNumber="195" start="start">to</pageBreakToken>
eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: smooth. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present only as a weak shift in elevation. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: present as a single carina. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: present laterally, absent medially. Occiput sculpture: transversely ru 
<pageBreakToken id="765B968664D000DDE7D1D7F775DC4D3D" pageId="195" pageNumber="196" start="start">gose</pageBreakToken>
. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, medially incomplete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate punctate; absent. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; absent. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3D822CE1D512BEA472CB629E3891EBF5" pageId="195" pageNumber="196">Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent; granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: absent; present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T6. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4654C26997F7FCFB965ACDCF51FBE63D" pageId="195" pageNumber="196">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1 lateral carina: straight. T2 sculpture: densely foveolate, longitudinal sculpture irregular. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: longitudinally striate; umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A81DB3B6DC5D0F6F2FB4DD529E231F71" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">
<pageBreakToken id="8CDDC3A4E74B4E25F882F75D744FA988" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
. Body length 3.6-4 mm (n=5). A3: shorter than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: expanded, ovate or sinuate. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 3. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: truncate.
</paragraph>
<caption id="4E12E63F8F3930C9B2E57250AB1F856A" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">
<paragraph id="9D3DE0864A3E3786A3B3FDBB1A195FD6" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">
Figures 319-324. 
<taxonomicName id="0D109A00743E4F194FE3A3BFDDB197E0" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio sepisessor" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sepisessor">Oxyscelio sepisessor</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 438936) 319 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 320 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 321 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype female (OSUC 227542) 322 Head, anterior view. Paratype male (OSUC 438946) 323 Antenna 324 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank88
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="905C3D23B2079CFBB2321FC2E2BD1BFE" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="C3AA838F965EE0975DF787737E64EAAF" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="168DCB25EE0BD696442C8326177643AD" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Both sexes: Frontal depression shallow, transverse carinae absent; submedian carina indicated by a set of weak rugae. Hyperoccipital carina sharp and strong. Occipital carina incomplete (difficult to discern due to rough sculpture). Metascutellum broad and concave, truncate or slightly emarginate apically, projecting dorsally. Postmarginal vein present. Coxa not darker than rest of leg. T1 lateral carina not expanded laterally. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 much longer than pedicel. A4 about as long as broad, A5 broader than long. Mesoscutellum without granulate sculpture. T1 midlobe carinae obscured by raised smooth area. T6 without metasomal flanges, main body of tergum sloping down to apical rim. Fore wing long enough to reach base of T6. Male: Flagellomeres beyond A3 broader than long or only slightly longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 3 longitudinal carinae. Fore wing long enough to reach to or beyond T7. T7 truncate or very weakly emarginate.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="29A5D0E657CD4B470FB292842648D6C2" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="F6592EAE0D49C90F4DBC1A8C0FF57D20" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9541F8C101ED0FF7D77B39EBA21D4A56" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Latin noun in apposition, meaning &quot;the fence-sitter.&quot;</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B848182CBCC2C34431F7A0A7341301DD" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="2D813EF99239FA32D91AE81CB27F3E2D" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FFAC933822E4A0B0AAF728511A77D670" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307108]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="09766DDC442CD540E83DC79E290B4FC8" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="1069CA6CB7F3B0E47EE4C1A644426723" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BC8D4488582E261E9407E2A7E29000A8" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, Brisbane, DPI Indooroopilly site, 8.II.1971, malaise trap, OSUC 438936 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 20 females, 5 males, OSUC 438930, 438946 (ANIC); OSUC 227542, 462561 (CNCI); QDPC 0-165646 (QDPC); OSUC 438931-438935, 438937-438945, 438947-438949, 438951, 451325-451326 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="01C2C03F9B74E40781FDB41CF5B909B8" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" type="comments">
<paragraph id="CFD11A42977C6A78BF9717B31E321A81" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1E227CDEE697BC4865A3CD9DABEBE424" pageId="196" pageNumber="197">
<taxonomicName id="A83C36D615145CA047936323B198B875" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio sepisessor" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="196" pageNumber="197" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sepisessor">Oxyscelio sepisessor</taxonomicName>
is provisionally placed in the flavipes-group because of its incomplete occipital carina and simple T1 lateral carina that is not expanded. It resembles some atricoxa-group species in having a roughly-sculptured occiput and relatively broad metasoma.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>