<document id="4D59585D0DA63F8149137D5509BC9344" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bdfb4b8e-4c36-4386-a7d0-7437b44fcba1" ModsDocID="21061" checkinTime="1252706925963" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Heterick, B. E." docDate="2006" docId="5B929F1FFE0F33FA7B00647F31089825" docLanguage="en" docName="21061.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 57" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf" docTitle="Monomorium micrommaton Heterick, 2006, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="133" masterDocId="3A2C4F9A5833769B5007E7556E53E380" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="202" masterPageNumber="69" pageNumber="132" updateTime="1569525778780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="72A83C1A7A4AA377C5D1FEDC083694D2" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="C53B3F33493E683BA3D4E7C158C82CEC">
<mods:title id="7E12B4234777768B681023FBC3C0F54A">A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="F31597B8DEE76F3FE6C782385A4A7A65" type="personal">
<mods:role id="CDA7F19327856956398AC83924C2A4C1">
<mods:roleTerm id="D1AE66DBA02E959AD32A687C079DDB0D">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="E45D88460193989AB05551B394074C0F">Heterick, B. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="9CC439618261CA52B2484AF9FCC320E3">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="9231CA2357D702C6E63DEE449F561F55" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="42651F4DA47239AC67863C912331F7DA">
<mods:title id="ACCAB23E00E5D0352B7322D54DA4B82D">Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="7E9595984BD8126B33760D98889B0CE0">
<mods:date id="2A88DB1C5D427EE4D930D9D4326E039C">2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="0C04C78290F369712B4AAB7B3BAB6FA7" type="volume">
<mods:number id="F4E68A5345649F82E748D3BDDEDA02AE">57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="EDE9D7F8BEC5422D81C47EF35F9BB5AA" unit="page">
<mods:start id="84745AC1099CF36377B312C33C75BC07">69</mods:start>
<mods:end id="DAB353229630537168A0B0E312CA6D8E">202</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="8CA39BA338CFA1FE490D1897DBCD35B4">
<mods:url id="BD1A54C307870FE577624CC6AE327151">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="3DDD3546F335E556B906BD48DB65109B">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="64E9E17A216427ECBAA834C158BC5CCE" type="HNS-PUB">21061</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="5B929F1FFE0F33FA7B00647F31089825" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:5B929F1FFE0F33FA7B00647F31089825" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5B929F1FFE0F33FA7B00647F31089825">
<subSubSection id="39B6DAE007C9688AAF39CA420917CEA8" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="E3FF4E8A17D9BA0C2DDFDEFD2B425604" pageNumber="132">
<taxonomicName id="33DDE118DF7048163488EB470624D41C" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196250" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium micrommaton Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium micrommaton Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="132" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="micrommaton">Monomorium micrommaton Heterick</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E9114D4E1C286E15B3424310FC307893" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B21D4DA0C99E64D9EF1341A5165F4BF5" type="description">
<paragraph id="0653518391185D0A67D2B18BF356A747" pageNumber="132">Figs. 22, 61-62.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="37AB400B02510C99B9AABB949A59319D" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="21EACA968137C852618B0F5792724CC2" pageNumber="132">Etymology.- Greek &quot;mikrommatos&quot; (&quot;small-eyed&quot;)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="65B4AC4D7AD6EFD2B094716C9CA33C0C" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="C6B271FB3FDBFEE26FBD1C9A15F084EE" pageNumber="132">Material examined.- Holotype: [[worker]], Prov. Toamasina, P.N. Mantadia 895 m, 18°47'5&quot;S, 48°25'6'E, 28.xi -1.xii.1998 H.J. Ratsirarson 112/sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood) rainforest/112(32)-51 (CAS). Paratypes: Prov. Toamasina (all specimens with same collection data as holotype): 32 [[queen]] + 1 [[queen]] (ANIC); 42 [[worker]] + 1 [[queen]] (BMNH); 32 5+ 1 (CAS); 42 [[worker]] + 1 [[queen]] (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5CEE51A034BE333A4B1050EAB6C9D3CE" pageNumber="132">Other material examined: Prov. Antsiranana: 12.2 km WSW Befingotra, Res. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 19.x.1994 B.L. Fisher (19 [[worker]]). Prov. Fianarantsoa: 45 km S Ambalavao 25ix.1992 B.L. Fisher (24 [[worker]]); 43 km S Ambalavao, Res. Andringitra 10.x.1993 B.L. Fisher (120[[worker]]); Parc Nat. de Ranomafana, 11.v.1991 L. Bartolozzi, S. Tiati &amp; C. Raharimina (1 [[worker]]); P.N. Ranomafana, Vatoharanana 4.1 km 231 SW Ranomafana 27-31.iii.2003 Fisher et al. (25 [[worker]]); Ranomafana N.P 1.i.1992 E. Rajeriarison (3 [[worker]]) (MCZ); W.E. Steiner (1 [[queen]]) (MCZ); Ranomafana N.P. 7 km (sic!) 8.x.1988 W.E. Steiner (1 [[queen]]) (MCZ); 3 km W Ranomafana, nr. Ifanadiana 27.iv. 1989 P.S. Ward (4 [[worker]]) (MCZ); 7 km W Ranomafana, 10.ix.1993 W. E. Steiner et al. (2 [[worker]]) (MCZ); 7 km W Ranomafana, 23 ix.1993 M. Stebbins, W. E. Steiner et al. (2 [[queen]]) (MCZ); 7 km W Ranomafana, 14.x.1993 W.E. Steiner et al. (1 [[queen]]); (MCZ) R.S. Ivohibe, 7.5 km ENE Ivohibe, 7-12.xi.1997 BL. Fisher (24[[worker]]); R. S. Ivohibe, 9.0 km NE Ivohibe, 12-17.xi.1997 BL. Fisher (3 [[worker]]). Prov. Toamasina: 6.9 km NE Ambanizana 2.xii.1993 BL. Fisher (20[[worker]]); 6 km ESE Andasibe (- Perinet) 17. xi. 1990 P.S. Ward (4[[worker]]) (MCZ); FC Andriantantely 4-7.xii.1998 H.J. Ratsirarson (11 [[worker]]); FC. Didy, 16-23.xii.1998 H.J. Ratsirarson (10[[worker]]); P.N. Mantadia, 28.xi -1.xii.1998 H.J. Ratsirarson (2[[worker]]).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="399F1F64C2B8159EE810EA1B2CDB98DB" type="description">
<paragraph id="9ADDC6A61EB00F9CA5F68E4A6F106B1A" pageNumber="132">Worker description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex planar or weakly concave; frons shining and smooth except for piliferous pits; pilosity of frons a mixture of incurved, semi-erect setae and slightly shorter decumbent setae; Eye small, eye width less than 1x greatest width of antennal scape; (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set posteriad of midline of head capsule; eye more-or-less circular, or, elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin. Antennal segments 12; antennal club three-segmented. Clypeal carinae indistinct; anteromedian clypeal margin emarginate, clypeal carinae indistinct; paraclypeal setae moderately long and fine, curved; posteromedian clypeal margin extending slightly beyond level of posterior margin of antennal fossae. Anterior tentorial pits equidistant from antennal fossae and mandibular insertions. Frontal lobes sinuate, divergent posteriad. Psammophore absent. Palp formula 2,2. Mandibular teeth four; mandibles linear-triangular and smooth (except for piliferous pits); masticatory margin of mandibles strongly oblique; basal tooth approximately same size as t3 (four teeth present).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9BB0CF4A3C402A06AFE26A3F832ADF57" lastPageNumber="133" pageNumber="132">Mesosoma: Promesonotum shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to lower anterior mesopleuron; (viewed in profile) promesonotum broadly convex; promesonotal setae greater than twelve; standing promesonotal setae a mixture of well-spaced, distinctly longer, erect and semi-erect setae which are curved distally and often paired, interspersed with much shorter, incurved, decumbent setae; appressed promesonotal setulae few, mainly on sides of promesonotum. Metanotal groove strongly impressed, with distinct transverse costulae. Propodeum shining and smooth, with a few weak striolae on metapleuron; propodeal dorsum convex; propodeum always smoothly rounded; standing propodeal setae consisting of two or more prominent pairs anteriad, often with another pair of prominent setae posteriad, and other smaller setae on/around dorsal and declivitous surfaces of propodeum; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle equidistant from metanotal groove and declivitous face of propodeum. Vestibule of propodeal spiracle distinct. Propodeal lobes present as vestigial flanges or small strips of cuticle only.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="885759C23826512C947CE253D0820DD1" pageNumber="133">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated within anterior sector of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) cuneate, vertex tapered; appearance of node shining and smooth throughout; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) about 1:1; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; ventral petiolar lobe present; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole about 3:2; height -length ratio of postpetiole between 1:1 and 3:4; postpetiole shining and smooth; postpetiolar sternite without anterior lip or carina, or this structure vestigial.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B91C7F11D01114F8E04A5B3BC4359BC8" pageNumber="133">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of a mixture of incurved, semi-erect setae and slightly shorter decumbent setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DA83CDBF8ACEFB42A3BABB916AD5712D" pageNumber="133">General characters: Color yellow. Worker caste monomorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="14251EF2705FC0FAE535313FE7812A5F" pageNumber="133">Holotype measurements: HML 1.02 HL 0.39 HW 0.32 CeI 82 SL 0.27 SI 84 PW 0.22.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EB3707300DC6619E2472C9A7961FF3CE" pageNumber="133">Other worker measurements: HML 0.92-1.11 HL 0.36-0.43 HW 0.30-0.35 CeI 78-84 SL 0.24-0.28 SI 78-87 PW 0.20-0.26 (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C6DE176B6791C79CC5C0867F1300394A" pageNumber="133">Queen description.- Head: Head square; vertex always planar; frons shining and smooth except for piliferous pits; frons a mixture of incurved, semi-erect setae and slightly shorter decumbent setae. Eye elliptical, outer margin may be shallowly concave; (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set posteriad of midline of head capsule.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="60BAADE7D8DCA6E72E219B09BB8D200D" pageNumber="133">Mesosoma: Mesoscutum broadly convex; pronotum,mesoscutum and mesopleuron shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to anterior katepisternum; length-width ratio of mesoscutum and scutellum combined between 2:1 and 3:2. Axillae narrowly separated (i.e., less than width of one axilla). Standing pronotal/mesoscutal setae consisting of a mixture of incurved, semi-erect setae and slightly shorter decumbent setae; appressed pronotal, mescoscutal and mesopleural setulae few, mainly on sides of pronotum and mesopleuron. Propodeum shining and smooth, metapleuron with a few distinct striolae; propodeum smoothly rounded or with indistinct angle; propodeal dorsum convex; standing propodeal setae consisting of up to a dozen or more longer erect and shorter sub-erect setae; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle nearer metanotal groove than declivitous face of propodeum; propodeal lobes present as vestigial flanges only, or absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BABB180907E4529F491AB2B9F0F5BC51" pageNumber="133">Wing: Wing not seen (queens dealated).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="733F061059159EEB714F6238A5E533A0" pageNumber="133">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated within anterior sector of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) cuneate, vertex tapered, to cuneate, vertex rounded; appearance of node shining, with vestigial sculpture; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) between 4:3 and 1:1. Anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; height -length ratio of postpetiole between 2:1 and 4:3; postpetiole shining and smooth to shining, with vestigial sculpture; postpetiolar sternite without anterior lip or carina, or this structure vestigial.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="906691A589A51FEBF4E323CC003A3CB8" pageNumber="133">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of a mixture of incurved, erect and semi-erect setae and slightly shorter decumbent setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1BBA585C5AA556DCAE9C802717C1AE1D" pageNumber="133">General characters: Color bright orange-yellow. Brachypterous, alates not seen. Ergatoid or worker-female intercastes not seen.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="27106B0D75A69E506CC444971AF30C47" pageNumber="133">Queen measurements: HML 2.87-2.98 HL 0.67-0.70 HW 0.68-0.71 CeI 99-104 SL 0.53-0.58 SI 76-82 PW 0.74-0.96 (n=5).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C05ABC379705A24009BA560A18666850" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="560E68FEFE0DD6A2967CC5609E809FBD" lastPageNumber="134" pageNumber="133">
Remarks.- 
<taxonomicName id="26082468D1100AE54C13D9907FA1D595" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196250" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium micrommaton Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium micrommaton Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="133" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="micrommaton">Monomorium micrommaton</taxonomicName>
workers are similar to the yellow, typical form of 
<taxonomicName id="6FBBB0F327F4C9B7F9E5CA2C12E31B80" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:31741" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium termitobium Forel" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium termitobium Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="133" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="termitobium">M. termitobium</taxonomicName>
, but, unlike the latter, appear to be restricted to cryptic environments. The queens are also clearly separable from those of the latter species. All collections have been made in rainforest on the east coast of Madagascar in the provinces of Antsiranana, Fianarantsoa and Toamasina, usually in sifted leaf litter, mould or rotten wood. The very reduced eyes and depigmented coloration suggest this species is strongly adapted to a cryptic lifeway.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>