<document id="E5F55515A24AE6815F523F2AEC323D50" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.244.3979" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b96e3846-e9b9-4126-9b28-a47ea520cec6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152038003" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-244-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-244-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 244" ModsDocTitle="The melectine bee genera Brachymelecta and Sinomelecta (Hymenoptera, Apidae)" checkinTime="1451248534040" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Engel, Michael S. &amp; Michener, Charles D." docDate="2012" docId="5E0B59608998FA36EA79F76F9C891708" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 244: 1-19" docOrigin="ZooKeys 244" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.244.3979" docTitle="Sinomelecta oreina Baker" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" masterDocId="FFA8FFFCFF85112A3F55FFB3FF92FF99" masterDocTitle="The melectine bee genera Brachymelecta and Sinomelecta (Hymenoptera, Apidae)" masterLastPageNumber="19" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" updateTime="1643546726362" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="520D813CA6B775996A918011FD7B6C70" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="E2DEE13B16BD2CE694B88FBD3D720655">
<mods:title id="5F24023D5CC267731FEC97E33C9DA876">The melectine bee genera Brachymelecta and Sinomelecta (Hymenoptera, Apidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="B3DF40FCBF748FC212CBABAF71C1FECD" type="personal">
<mods:role id="8A31CE2EAC3C5C7A1A6240815D4E1910">
<mods:roleTerm id="9CE94A0CCDA7454CD7F0CA8ABBB8BE35">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="CF9F193EEDBF0D8016A4335C47523FC5">Engel, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="B5E06B880E16FF06347B62FF4220F4F0" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A3BE32819F97F4BBF108CC96A6B2DC23">
<mods:roleTerm id="201718EFB4C8E52817A0DE1F69F0ABC9">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="8996ACD5F3B59521D8D9FCE39A47245D">Michener, Charles D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="4A3BCCC8FBE640B09241DD3A5A1D477C">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="583C0096131E29D622F8F87E380D0BAF" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="BE1FC21D15E1630ADCCE236E4FAE2328">
<mods:title id="5377C293924E8F86C1E41D58AF2BEA83">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="F4D7092BB0F9585E6D95219797D1E1CB">
<mods:date id="36724A04B99D97619049910968B08E64">2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="5E1BF160F4731F9B68E0E2209B32C0BF" type="volume">
<mods:number id="FB2E6188D9168A51DE03F71DE75C20C6">244</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="5F424FD9DC050B98281A8CE854F135BD" unit="page">
<mods:start id="010F93A72C7893F8AD5C79B36FD60683">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="C12EEE65B314E536E15A090853A2F582">19</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="2BA0BB93C933556050B9DEE94EBAD239">
<mods:url id="6A859C8A201B4A4E75B5F1B334F8CC6C">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.244.3979</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="42008E3503B12F3C9F304C9257E7F48F">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="9F5A34D0BE3C13D4B3A623B1A6A7EAC1" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.244.3979</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="C392A43519CDA54150AC1C567EEFF23D" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-244-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="5E0B59608998FA36EA79F76F9C891708" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152038003" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:5E0B59608998FA36EA79F76F9C891708" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5E0B59608998FA36EA79F76F9C891708" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
<subSubSection id="F6512FD90DD5526CA8EEF6BB781CFC85" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="C0F1BE3E3C77EC9C015910536874A9A2" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
<taxonomicName id="A3F98B6B16436CD19025F15B5DF83655" LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Sinomelecta_oreina" authority="Baker" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina Baker</taxonomicName>
Figs 11-23
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="CF065E55A8E26724A72917F18E4A497D" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="E1BA8873B2545418E2A445ED3AAD9AEB" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
<taxonomicName id="1214FBCD612545B5F99DD4A83F4E5F11" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina</taxonomicName>
Baker, 1997: 246 [♂♀].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="696A922C86F62BC2CEE273B43D83785D" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="holotype">
<paragraph id="E96CE1348776349835370D7830A584EA" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B73667F9E4F52C4A50BCC3AFFC9BD12B" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
♂ (Figs 11-12), labeled &quot;China: Szechuan, 
<normalizedToken id="23026BD4EA4A93567AF31E5F9D1B23A6" originalValue="Ta-hsuëh">Ta-hsueh</normalizedToken>
Shan or Chiunghsia Shan&quot; // &quot;Holotype ♂, Sinomelecta oreina, D.B. Baker 1993 [actual publication date was 1997] [red label]&quot;; deposited in the Division of Entomology, University of Kansas Natural History Museum, Lawrence, Kansas, USA.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="64518DAD562E2A1760CA4B79F81C8F6D" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="paratype">
<paragraph id="BAA6DE561A3DC938F741B605C7A13127" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Paratype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B06932A77FD069FFE24DF2CD1E11FF2C" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">1♀ (Figs 22-23), with same labels as holotype except second label blue and reading &quot;Paratype ♀, Sinomelecta oreina, D.B. Baker 1993 [actual publication date was 1997] [blue label]&quot;; deposited in the Division of Entomology, University of Kansas Natural History Museum, Lawrence, Kansas, USA.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="68F5AFE1D48638454D9B986738194D9D" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="67A0CCD1318CF438E004C0E4273FE8C5" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="597EC8DADA60BA71DAB006CE41A697B3" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">As for the genus (vide supra).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1B19421922D248637EA7EFAF4B85D1BB" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="description">
<paragraph id="DF23D79A11377A203DD751322F5603BF" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9B1304A331D2FE6E7C907DDB59B20250" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
Male (holotype): Body length 11.5 mm (apex of metasoma damaged, as noted by 
<bibRefCitation id="1EBCA20F50667E32E87646470DEB85A3" author="Baker, DB" journalOrPublisher="Entomologist's Gazette" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="245 - 256" title="New Melectini from western China (Hymenoptera: Apoidea, Anthophoridae)." volume="48" year="1997">Baker 1997</bibRefCitation>
, and dissected, so that body length measurement is not exact), forewing length 10 mm. Head narrower than thorax, head width 3.15 mm, head length (lower margin of clypeus to vertex in facial view) 2.75 mm. Intertegular distance 3.0 mm, distance between outer margins of tegulae 4.0 mm.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7BD5BAC20D0EB431A9E21C10484FCC5C" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="10" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
Clypeus strongly protuberant, in lateral view extending anteriorly more than compound eye width on front of compound eye margin; lower margin of clypeus straight, mandibles closed and difficult to see, but distal half narrow, tapering to narrowly rounded apex, no teeth visible. Malar space very short, base of mandible separated 
<pageBreakToken id="A27AA03181383220F4B8E3340327C227" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" start="start">from</pageBreakToken>
compound eye by about one-fourth of distal diameter of F1. Labrum broader than long. Inner orbits weakly concave, slightly converging below (Fig. 20), vertex strongly convex as seen in facial view (Fig. 20); gena broadest near lower end, broader than compound eye in lateral view; preoccipital ridge rounded; ocelli about equal in diameter; ocellocular distance more than twice interocellar distance which is less than ocellar diameter; ocelloccipital distance about three ocellar diameters but indefinite because of rounding onto occiput. Distance between lateral and middle ocelli about two-thirds of ocellar diameter. Antenna with 12 antennomeres; scape (without basal bulb) nearly three times as long as its maximum width which is slightly less than apical width of F1; pedicel small, exposed part about three times as wide a long; F1 nearly twice as long as apical width and about twice as long as F2; F2 to F9 broader than long, F10 scarcely longer than F9, scarcely longer than broad, apex broadly rounded; flagellum on left hand side and as shown by Baker (1997: fig. 14) tapering slightly from F2 to F10 so that F2 maximum width is about 1.24 times F10 width, but on right hand side tapering less evident. Mesoscutellum with subhorizontal dorsal surface about twice as long as subvertical surface, both surfaces divided by weak longitudinal median depression so that mesoscutellum is weakly biconvex, each convexity emphasized by small posteriorly directed sublateral projection that almost overhangs metanotum. Metatibia 
<pageBreakToken id="57986BF869E0D00BBDB53F23F368472D" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
outer surface nodulose posteriorly; apex of protibia with two sharp spines, one anterior, the other posterior; other tibiae without evident apical spines although apical outer margin, especially of metatibia, protuberant; spurs of meso- and metatibiae about as long as tibial diameters, those of metatibia subequal in length; arolia small, much less than half as long as pretarsal claws; pretarsal claws cleft, inner ramus shaped more or less like outer ramus but somewhat shorter than outer ranus. Metasomal T1 with midlength of horizontal surface about half as long as declivitous anterior surface and about half as long as midlength of exposed part of T2, but since dorsal surface of T1 curves gradually onto anterior surface, these measurements are arbitrary; apical terga fragmented but apparent apex of T7 slightly less produced medially than S7 but notched like S7; surface of S7 with longitudinal median depression; posterior margins of S2 to S5 straight, transverse; S6 somewhat produced medially so that posterior margin is strongly convex; S7, S8, and genitalia shown in figures 15-19.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EA575B868BF80312992D684F12137553" pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Setae mostly sparse enough that details of surface sculpturing visible (unlike in 
<taxonomicName id="4D70B2E748069876083FD7598755005A" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Brachymelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Brachymelecta mucida" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mucida">Brachymelecta mucida</taxonomicName>
). Head including labrum coarsely and closely punctate, upper part of head somewhat more coarsely so than lower part; area in front of ocelli, extending down medially as frontal carina, smooth and impunctate; area around base of mandible, including malar space, smooth and shining; scape and basal half of mandible more finely punctate except for anterior apical smooth shining swelling of scape and smooth mandibular area near articulation. Mesosoma mostly coarsely and closely punctate, punctation similar to that of clypeus except somewhat coarser (like upper frons and vertex) in much of mesoscutum; median part of mesoscutum, except anteriorly, with many punctures separated from one another by smooth ground often one-third as wide as nearby punctures; lateral margin of mesoscutum (about as wide as nearby tegula), lateral extremity of mesoscutellum, and axilla much more finely punctate, these punctures as dense as they can be, variable but most about one-third as wide as those on disc of mesoscutum; posterior propodeal areas with sculpturing grading toward granular. Metasomal terga and sterna with coarse, dense, shallow punctures about size of punctures of frons; posterior margins of T1 to T3 narrowly impunctate, T4 more broadly impunctate, T5 with impunctate zone much broader than exposed punctate zone; S1 to S5 with narrow apical smooth margins.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="797C139191F791FDB97B52D5CC4C0DC6" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Setae of head and mesosoma mostly four to five ocellar diameters in length, those of clypeus shorter than elsewhere; setae largely absent on posterior three-fourths of mesoscutum, mostly not branched, dull whitish or cinereous but dusky brownish on genal and hypostomal areas, grading to brownish cinereous on labrum and clypeus (although whitish on upper margin of clypeus medially) and black on lateral margin of clypeus, on lower paraocular area below level of antennal base, and on posterior lateral angle of mesoscutum, on upper part of axilla, and perhaps on extreme basolateral margin of mesoscutellum. Setae of antennal scape and basal parts of legs including upper surfaces of femora similar to cinereous setae of mesosoma but shorter; posterior margins of pro- and mesofemora with fringes of long, pale setae, slightly darkened apically on mesofemur; setae of flagellum and pedicel extremely short; under surfaces of femora with areas of brownish dusky setae, grading to dusky on outer surfaces of 
<pageBreakToken id="3D377453C22820A681FE2C99188921A3" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" start="start">meso-</pageBreakToken>
and metatibiae; posterior outer surface of metatibia with large area of extremely dense, appressed setae that hide surface, these setae brown medially and whitish marginally; under surfaces of tarsi with short, yellowish brown setae. Metasomal T1 with long cinereous setae similar to those of mesosoma; T2 to T5 with similar setae, some of them brownish, at extreme sides; T2 to T4 with subapical bands of white setae (broken medially on T2); anterior to these bands setae inconspicuous, short (about one ocellar diameter in length), dusky; T5 largely hidden by T4, thus setal characters not clear but 
<pageBreakToken id="E0B02752F49CFAB91403BBA77048FD17" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" start="start">band</pageBreakToken>
of pale setae absent; S2 to S6 with long whitish setae, up to five ocellar diameters in length, sparse on S2 and S3, denser and forming preapical bands on S4 and S5.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="40779B18EB6A8A20B7E25FAAE8548BC9" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Integumental coloration black throughout. Wings transparent, with brownish dusky stain in distal halves, darker distal to marginal cell, clear near and for short distance distal to 1rs-m and 2m-cu and along anterior margins of both submarginal cells; veins and pterostigma black.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="45BAC3BFA964B01F8C8E9B02F4A73D25" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Female (paratype): As described for holotype male except as follows: Apex of metasoma intact. Forewing length 9.5 mm. Head width 3.3 mm; head length 2.8 mm; distance between outer margins of tegulae 4.25 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E054592539EB1B561478106DD6B66666" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="13" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
Malar space a depressed groove, base of mandible separated from compound eye by about one-third of distal diameter of F1. Labrum broader than long, apical margin concave. Inner orbits more distinctly converging below than in male; ocellocular distance about 1.5 times interocellar distance, nearly three ocellar diameters; distance between lateral and median ocellus nearly one ocellar diameter. Apical width of F1 approximately equal to apical width of scape; pedicel fully exposed, broader than long; F1 about 2.5 times as long as its apical width, F2 about as long as broad, subsequent flagellomeres similar but progressively very slightly longer so that F7 is slightly longer than broad, F10 only slightly longer than F9 with apex broadly rounded; flagellum not tapering so that F1 and F10 approximately equal in width. Distitarsi broken off and lost except for one front leg that is difficult to see, although pretarsal claws smaller than in male; apical tibial spines represented by outer apical anterior and posterior protuberances except posterior spine of protibial apex present and that of mesotibia a large, long, blunt process; thickened spinelike setae also present on meso- and metatibial apices and on outer surface of metatibia; tibial spurs 
<pageBreakToken id="E7D3573F5AF76D2013F6713980798A7C" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" start="start">slightly</pageBreakToken>
longer than maximum tibial diameters. Metasomal T6 with well-defined pygidial plate, pointed at apex; T6 apparently produced as slender apical process above comparable slender apical process of S6 which has strongly notched apex exceeding tergal apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="88746D76FE5AAB400613A9158121A4C9" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Area in front of ocelli not entirely smooth, with somewhat irregular punctures; scape without smooth, shining apical swelling. Metasomal terga and sterna with punctures slightly better spaced than in male, middorsally separated by shining ground one-third puncture width to full puncture width; apical impunctate margins of T1 to T3 slightly wider than in male, not contrasting with that of T4.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="210D4A21D72CBAE1ACD3D46ED086D3A7" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<pageBreakToken id="B6EEEF0D6877E1F481F5CE648E47FFD0" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" start="start">Most</pageBreakToken>
setae of legs from coxae to upper surfaces of tarsi whitish; area of dense setae on outer surface of mesotibia absent. Discal area of mesoscutum, upper inner extremity of axilla, and anterior margin of mesoscutellum with setae blackish (setae largely absent from discal area of mesoscutum in male). Metasomal T2 to T4 with discal setae largely palid and longer than in male so that subapical white setal bands contrast with their background less than in male; T5 and T6 without subapical bands of white setae; S2 to S5 with abundant long whitish setae, those of S2 and S3 not contrastingly sparse, as in male.
</paragraph>
<caption id="64BA7C194A118BD30D1D6350099E5D8C" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph id="692D1CED98A5CE45647B74E3A6E6E4C0" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figures 11-12. Lateral (11) and dorsal (12) habitus images of holotype male of 
<taxonomicName id="BADA06B9C5FB6BCE5CDF9CD177DC1CC7" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina</taxonomicName>
Baker (SEMC Type No. 9280).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="45DFB3153E6C50582E481B1B9B8CD924" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph id="3886C4EA988CC52C91DD1CE0BAF6C405" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figures 13-14. Forewing (13) and hind wing (14) of holotype male of 
<taxonomicName id="03E044774409D9429E6AA8D13766D3A0" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina</taxonomicName>
Baker (SEMC Type No. 9280).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="F5531F66ECBEBAE2E83DBE28DF83075C" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph id="8E1E19F506F6FF9EA9897341400A09D1" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figures 15-19. Male terminalia of holotype of 
<taxonomicName id="FDC69E3539ED1799F83120C1E54794A3" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina</taxonomicName>
Baker (SEMC Type No. 9280). 15 Seventh metasomal sternum 16 Eighth metasomal sternum 17 Genital capsule, lateral view 18 Genital capsule, dorsal view 19 Genital capsule, ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="6489165A9D74692A4E0FE654223CB323" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph id="C2B4BF23FFE0D1CBE8A615F5327D40D2" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figures 20-21. Male holotype (20) and female paratype (21) facial views of 
<taxonomicName id="B9FA1F53A9158962C55352DDCBBF40AD" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina</taxonomicName>
Baker (SEMC Type No. 9280).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="85B4913E4FD6A4D93EE770F0741FEA57" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph id="CF1E8B6B3643B51391C061D232198A0C" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figures 22-23. Lateral (22) and dorsal (23) habitus images of paratype female of 
<taxonomicName id="4284954BA28C3F29CB4BBC816B339072" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina</taxonomicName>
Baker (SEMC Type No. 9280).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0A60150328D20B00EA04AC8906606F39" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="comments">
<paragraph id="957563467B4A853B32DF55CF27121F8E" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4CD2D24CB582B1720134F9EB16046F67" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Although peculiar, the 12 antennomeres in the male of 
<taxonomicName id="1ED594D557EB69CA960F6C182CB5729D" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Sinomelecta oreina</taxonomicName>
is not unheard of among bees and this condition is found in various genera. For example, this same reduced antennomere count is well known and fixed across species in the augochlorine genus 
<taxonomicName id="0418B243688CE8D8ABFDA0B6D899B4DD" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Chlerogas" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chlerogas" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Chlerogas</taxonomicName>
Vachal (
<bibRefCitation id="E35974C96DEADAE0D44E65650AFC096E" author="Brooks, RW" journalOrPublisher="Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="463 - 486" title="A revision of the augochlorine bee genus Chlerogas Vachal (Hymenoptera: Halictidae)." url="10.1111/j.1096-3642.1999.tb00601.x" volume="125" year="1999">Brooks and Engel 1999</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="7952FEAB392C735FE2C68EB1AA9E15CB" author="Engel, MS" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="1 - 89" title="Classification of the bee tribe Augochlorini (Hymenoptera: Halictidae)." url="10.1206/0003-0090(2000)250&lt;0001:COTBTA&gt;2.0.CO;2" volume="250" year="2000">Engel 2000</bibRefCitation>
), the ammobatine genus 
<taxonomicName id="2986F394B46843F1ECC5284CDBFBF40D" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Chiasmognathus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chiasmognathus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Chiasmognathus</taxonomicName>
Engel (
<bibRefCitation id="DD0463022A2CD18AA0E274E9354D8A2C" author="Engel, MS" journalOrPublisher="Acta Entomologica Slovenica" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="113 - 121" title="A new genus of minute ammobatine bees (Hymenoptera: Apidae)." volume="14" year="2006">Engel 2006</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="541B60C3BB3724FAFBFACAA033417316" author="Engel, MS" journalOrPublisher="Fauna of Arabia" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="237 - 247" title="The bee genus Chiasmognathus in the Arabian Peninsula (Hymenoptera: Apidae)." volume="24" year="2009">2009</bibRefCitation>
), the biastine genus 
<taxonomicName id="9004F883F76BD3D1A0B498EB835E9697" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Neopasites" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neopasites" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Neopasites</taxonomicName>
Ashmead (
<bibRefCitation id="397E6979CEE93E9156792535F923CD15" author="Linsley, EG" journalOrPublisher="Transactions of the American Entomological Society" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="141 - 149" title="A revision of the genus Gnathopasites (Hymenoptera: Nomadidae)." volume="69" year="1943">Linsley 1943</bibRefCitation>
), and the ammobatoidine genus 
<taxonomicName id="2961D71A506C013674DCCAFD42D72C21" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Holcopasites" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Holcopasites" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Holcopasites</taxonomicName>
Ashmead (
<bibRefCitation id="7822DBEBE9D2D30C407FCC91B30AD8DD" author="Hurd PD, Jr" journalOrPublisher="Smithsonian Contributions to Zoology" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="1 - 41" title="Parasitic bees of the genus Holcopasites Ashmead (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)." url="10.5479/si.00810282.114" volume="114" year="1972">Hurd and Linsley 1972</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="B94EAB601FDA52E27E600158B3D27D32" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Michener 2007</bibRefCitation>
). Accordingly we do not consider this to merely represent an isolated teratology.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="47F4AFD4F2177C8EC2A5EEAFB8B4BCE2" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Note that the mention of &quot; 
<taxonomicName id="C90AD1936016C4BF3FD61862C4484762" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Melecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melecta oreina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="oreina">Melecta oreina</taxonomicName>
Baker&quot; in the key to Eastern Hemisphere genera of 
<taxonomicName id="48C1D3F6C4B8182B1B8A95B1D6896394" lsidName="" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" rank="tribe" tribe="Melectini">Melectini</taxonomicName>
by 
<bibRefCitation id="97CD7596FCC13B0E8D8E37EAD8DF124F" author="Rightmyer, MG" journalOrPublisher="American Museum Novitates" pageId="14" pageNumber="15" pagination="1 - 22" title="A new Palearctic genus of melectine bees (Hymenoptera: Apidae)." url="10.1206/0003-0082(2003)-" volume="3392" year="2003">Rightmyer and Engel (2003)</bibRefCitation>
should have read &quot; 
<taxonomicName id="CDA540908D9945FC4E7ACF9DDCDB24BA" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Melecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Melecta emodi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="emodi">Melecta emodi</taxonomicName>
Baker&quot; (oreina is, of course, the type species of 
<taxonomicName id="14B137E241433D081ABD5D5EC2ABE37D" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Sinomelecta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinomelecta" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Sinomelecta</taxonomicName>
which they recognized as a valid genus).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>