<document id="2A24A938E08E5D5698DAEAB2261905B7" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472" ID-GBIF-Dataset="64686cef-cf34-47d6-9cf4-3bd4e0dc9160" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152049027" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-345-73" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C79C62F9-32ED-4F77-8457-4B7D1142975D" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-345-73" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 345" ModsDocTitle="The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)" checkinTime="1451246762417" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Belokobylskij, Sergey A., Tang, Pu &amp; Chen, Xue-xin" docDate="2013" docId="5F352856CA2B72A26F1578C3A3E607EB" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 345: 73-96" docOrigin="ZooKeys 345" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472" docTitle="Ontsira abbreviata Belokobylskij, Tang &amp; Chen, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="C79C62F9-32ED-4F77-8457-4B7D1142975D" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="80" masterDocId="FF94FFF6852CFFA9582EFF9DAB3CFF96" masterDocTitle="The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)" masterLastPageNumber="96" masterPageNumber="73" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" updateTime="1643696211464" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="E7838B0D8C6223271ABE54202F5105DD" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="F94BF6CBE19D0BE104C7D86A8E1EEB97">
<mods:title id="6D471EBC8FD3B644C28A4E489D31E2A5">The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="47E30F18E1F6E3BB55622FCA28AD2A4E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A2E260A89DD39B9A767D0CBD9BF13C77">
<mods:roleTerm id="4F6E58C6B67204F4C742163B56E545F6">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7979DFA17D5F87D7EEFE96A1AEF732B8">Belokobylskij, Sergey A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="04F4F41AEF11EBF3DD26DFD0AEEC3F2F" type="personal">
<mods:role id="1CA9D41550428E7818C406C0869A072D">
<mods:roleTerm id="D7F5A4C81596E9D5EACA62FA277E519E">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="BD3468CF9CB13FE25092F61F0993D844">Tang, Pu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="EB1D058373D60BE5715C1D07B4F32AC0" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AD9E8716FFFC74E022400D25C4F57857">
<mods:roleTerm id="31ABE314DB844D061E5C1C3D1D5C6EDC">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="92476CE014CBAA0BCCD3FD89EF97CF4B">Chen, Xue-xin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="D3925967065CF71027CD92A23B87C402">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="8E5EC50D95353FF3909028EFAE7112E2" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="8E783AF9BE97E2B2B44F6807E808A722">
<mods:title id="836F505DA0BB096911F1038C2B541792">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="BD509C5E57B7FCC2EC6789CF3A673A97">
<mods:date id="A3B99E3F14ADC16792DC9721D9F36E08">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="84759C48711D494315AA84DD18E2B26E" type="volume">
<mods:number id="A765E7C77BF02E10EEC255FCEF44FCA2">345</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="8D21CB3F58DB22185592A95082B75B0D" unit="page">
<mods:start id="180F9FC0E175028C28D9BCC7B5EB6B4D">73</mods:start>
<mods:end id="12CE0428CB1B3464CD784A8B21A0D87C">96</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="60FD0F0DA0AC3A3A220F26DD9A3893D3">
<mods:url id="BD28E6FDD0F5A9F1725E1991DF8DBDDA">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="BF54061AAD6C90E1FC40C7EA7B575510">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="7FCC7D635172B37D4C6555C976E45371" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="6648C090013165C4ADABE29FB3FCDD13" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-345-73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="DDC0F9790477F16FDAC58838F6208453" type="ZooBank">5F4F3D22-2655-4E1B-A9D2-714D9E6F5991</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="5F352856CA2B72A26F1578C3A3E607EB" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152049027" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C79C62F9-32ED-4F77-8457-4B7D1142975D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5F352856CA2B72A26F1578C3A3E607EB" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="80" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">
<subSubSection id="70C9E68518F21959A8EF180E05190937" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="5F2549A484EE4E09DB84029DFBF02710" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">
<taxonomicName id="2990579B509BE325EC66B3BD5CD63752" LSID="http://zoobank.org/C79C62F9-32ED-4F77-8457-4B7D1142975D" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira abbreviata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="abbreviata">Ontsira abbreviata</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="96E019CDFBE3E212D6AA7A15DE786EE0" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Fig. 1
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="6C2B95BC033B77E9E3AC608E9C855529" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" type="type material">
<paragraph id="14B2815A5B2BECF35E0338D6364B7897" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="431D7E3DCC7B57923DE0AA8553D0BDB8" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Holotype: female, China, Shaanxi, Huoditang, 5.VI.1998 (Du Yuzhou), N 982455 (ZJUH).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="66808C52916A5E1F0AF827F5FC59F1B8" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="6E9AB81303229DDDB178BCCD6637CC40" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4EBC0890BD17FB02B82BC2D0870168E7" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">
From Latin 
<normalizedToken id="C264E0A0B9815E3436E8FDD7F97E2B90" originalValue="“abbreviatae”">&quot;abbreviatae&quot;</normalizedToken>
, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="23CAE22DA0A2EF511DF7F0C2223A1DDE" originalValue="“shortened”">&quot;shortened&quot;</normalizedToken>
, after the shortened second radiomedial cell of the fore wing
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="546C4A599B5A46D88CD3BA0E69414540" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="80" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" type="description">
<paragraph id="A6BA942938E4E8EBDBBBC15E8C9B106E" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8347A274D2D5784F27756C34D562D95C" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Female. Body length 3.0 mm; fore wing length 2.7 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0E0166C5B5A371FF15D3F2C9D0A46879" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Head width 1.6 times as long as its median length, 1.2 times as long as width of mesoscutum. Frons without carina, with distinct elongate pit between antennal sockets. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) regularly roundly narrowed; transverse diameter of eye 1.2 times as long as temple. Ocellar triangle situated behind middle of head (dorsal view), its anterior ocellus situated almost on level of anterior margins of eyes. Ocelli small, in almost equilateral triangle. POL 1.2 times as long as Od, 0.3 times as long as OOL. Eye sparsely and shortly setose, without emargination opposite antennal sockets, 1.2 times as high as broad. Face along eyes without carinae, with small shallow depressions above clypeus; width of face 1.4 times height of eye and 1.4 times height of face and clypeus combined. Diameter of antennal socket almost equal to distance between sockets and distance between socket and eye. Malar suture indistinct. Malar space about 0.6 times height of eye and 0.9 times basal width of mandible. Clypeus with distinct lower flange. Clypeal suture distinct and complete. Hypoclypeal depression oval, its width almost equal to distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.4 times width of face. Occipital carina ventrally fused with hypostomal carina at upper base of mandible. Maxillary palpi long, 1.5 times as long as head height.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C89367EA993F79442710F99151AAD216" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Antennae rather slender, filiform, 25-segmented, as long as body. Scape 1.9 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment 5.0 times as long as its apical width, and 1.4 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 2.7 times as long as wide, 0.5 times as long as first flagellar segment, and 0.9 times as long as apical segment; the apical segment distinctly pointed apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="068BCFFF9131CF3DCC2F6D0DADE98E4F" pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Mesosoma. Length 1.8 times its height. Pronotum not convex dorsally (lateral view), with distinct pronotal carina. Median lobe of mesoscutum (dorsal view) weakly protruding forward, with wide median furrow. Notauli deep, narrow, crenulate-rugulose. Prescutellar depression rather deep, with three median carinae, finely rugulose to smooth between carinae, 0.4 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum convex, without lateral carinae. Metanotum (dorsal view) with two strongly convergent and fused posteriorly lateral carinae, without median carinae; with short and obtuse metanotal tooth. Subalar depression rather shallow, wide, sparsely rugose-striate. Sternaulus deep, straight, finely crenulate, connected with prepectal carina anteriorly, running along anterior 0.6 of the lower part of mesopleuron. Metapleural flange long, wide, rounded apically. Propodeum with short, thick lateral tubercles.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F333453F75A2EE6D118D2EEE1C6BA389" pageId="6" pageNumber="79">
<pageBreakToken id="FE1AEAB9EA61776F52A8918BFDACB08B" pageId="6" pageNumber="79" start="start">Wings</pageBreakToken>
. Fore wing 3.1 times as long as maximum width. Radial vein arising weakly behind middle of pterostigma, from its basal 0.55. Radial cell not shortened; metacarp 1.25 times as long as pterostigma. First radial abscissa 0.5 times as long as maximum width of pterostigma. Second radial abscissa 4.5 times as long as first abscissa, 0.5 times as long as the straight third abscissa, and 1.15 times as long as first radiomedial vein. Second radiomedial cell 2.4 times as long as its maximum width, and 1.7 times as long as brachial cell. First medial abscissa weakly sinuate. Mediocubital vein almost straight. Recurrent vein distinctly antefurcal. Distance from nervulus to basal vein about 0.5 times as long as nervulus. Parallel vein arising distinctly behind middle of distal margin of brachial cell. Hind wing 4.5 times as long as maximum width. First costal abscissa 0.7 times as long as second abscissa. First abscissa of mediocubital vein 1.1 times as long as second abscissa. Mediocubital cell large, weakly widened toward apex, 7.0 times as long as wide, and 0.4 times as long as wing. Recurrent vein weakly curved, strongly antefurcal, unsclerotized.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C35525CC68D5DBAAAC18DEAB10E5E321" pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Legs. Fore tibia with rather numerous slender spines arranged in almost single line. Hind coxa without dorsal tooth, 1.6 times as long as wide. Hind femur 4.2 times as long as wide. Hind tarsus 0.9 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.7 times as long as second-fifth segments combined. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.45 times as long as basitarsus, 1.1 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C478057CF1E8732A20BF66A6DBD3285A" pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Metasoma about as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite with distinct dorsope, with small spiracular tubercles in basal 0.3, rather distinctly and almost linearly widened from base to apex. Maximum width of first tergite about twice its minimum width; length 1.15 times as long as its apical width. Second tergite without basomedian area; length of tergite 0.7 times as long as its basal width, almost equal to length of third tergite. Second suture very shallow and straight. Third tergite without additional transverse furrow. Ovipositor sheath 0.8 times as long as metasoma, as long as mesosoma, and 0.4 times as long as fore wing.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8737689C4CE3EA81A729D4D6C9ED2358" pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Sculpture and pubescence. Vertex and temple smooth; frons mostly smooth, finely coriaceous anterolaterally; face mostly smooth, finely rugulose-striate on upper part and on clypeus. Sides of pronotum smooth ventrally, coarsely crenulate medially, rugulose dorsally. Mesoscutum densely and distinctly granulate, rugulose anteriorly. Scutellum entirely finely granulate. Mesopleuron mostly smooth. Propodeum with distinctly areas delineated by carinae; basolateral areas large, smooth, but rugose in posterior 0.3 and along carinae; areola long and narrow, twice as long as wide; dorsal carina rather long, about twice as long as areola fork. Hind coxae coarsely striate in dorsal half, finely rugulose to smooth in ventral half. Hind femur smooth. First tergite with high complete subparallel dorsal carinae, rather distinctly striate, but smooth mediobasally (between dorsal carinae) and lateroapically. Second and the following tergites smooth. Vertex with rather sparse, long and semi-erect setae, glabrous in anterior half. Mesoscutum with dense, rather long and semi-erect pale setae, glabrous in rather wide submedian areas on lateral lobes. Hind tibia dorsally with rather long, sparse semi-erect setae basally and densely apically, length of these setae 0.7-1.0 times as long as maximum width of hind tibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EEC73FCBF84135C59425C65EC810B7B1" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="80" pageId="6" pageNumber="79">
Colour. Body dark reddish brown, metasoma behind first tergite reddish brown, malar area of head yellowish brown. Antennae dark brown, light reddish brown ba 
<pageBreakToken id="E4F088443175759A178EE047619C346C" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" start="start">sally</pageBreakToken>
. Palpi yellow. Legs entirely yellow. Ovipositor sheath black. Forewing membrane faintly infuscate. Pterostigma brown, paler basally and apically.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A7CBDC82B89E7B55C047E1EAA40B6C88" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">Male unknown.</paragraph>
<caption id="5140B7BD353DD9333C7370B94DF44A1D" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">
<paragraph id="6D30C93060CDABA3CAD69A4F0E8CA914" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName id="B355F43F5C6188A2127049E3DA8F8666" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira abbreviata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="abbreviata">Ontsira abbreviata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (female). A habitus, lateral view B head, front view C head, dorsal view D metasoma, dorsal view E mesosoma, lateral view F basal segments of antenna G fore and hind wings H mesosoma, dorsal view. Scale bar 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="39D7DA6CD624422D55512DFE9BA6D102" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="B5960C1BE3E168C73391CB95BF426935" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9D213D35B76BBB177392BB6B69E01BB2" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">China (Shaanxi).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="436E1A959207EF8E84604ECE53CFA526" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="3F369D4B9BC4852EAF5518A7945F0B6B" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B416F8BB83CB88602DEC17DAE08AD93F" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">
The new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName id="525280850E9A78DC98C37FFE020F099E" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira reticulata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="reticulata">Ontsira reticulata</taxonomicName>
Cameron (India), but differs in having the second radiomedial cell and the second radial abscissa short, the nervulus postfurcal, the ovipositor shorter, the hind coxa sculptured dorsally, the legs entirely yellow, the first tergite shorter, and the frons with distinct elongate pit between antennal sockets. It also resembles 
<taxonomicName id="225D2345F741BDA664DA5D688C03AFA7" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira gratia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="80" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gratia">Ontsira gratia</taxonomicName>
Belokobylskij (from Taiwan), but differ in having the parallel vein arising distinctly behind middle of distal margin of brachial cell, the occipital carina fused below with hypostomal carina, the basolateral areas of propodeum without granulation, the radial vein arising weakly behind middle of pterostigma, and the second radial abscissa and the second radiomedial cell shorter.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>