<document id="A653531C0A776018B48AC5C62B4DE659" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047599" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3D711BFF-EFA8-49DE-B27E-5923F2D05BDC" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="6439240F06A52A775A3DAC4700504117" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio leviventris Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="3D711BFF-EFA8-49DE-B27E-5923F2D05BDC" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="108" lastPageNumber="109" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="105" pageNumber="106" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="FD16D38B8C2574D701B853F7F708509D" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="44102BA56014F061969987402B92C599">
<mods:title id="E14EB19649D7F26D02839A979D132398">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="8D8C7A28BBFEFE1AAE850EB6ECAF6933" type="personal">
<mods:role id="FB25F3F7BC18E6761A67F18EEAD1EDED">
<mods:roleTerm id="BDBD0708373190EFF22737DA8850B46E">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="65A52FCF23DCA8D5A24651590092CB40">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="D4E4655F8580FBB8AD127AB39A817EA8" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A73CB1450EFBBF436B70AA279AD75B0C">
<mods:roleTerm id="9D1C34C38EC1726DAB5DCD2293CB4B81">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="05BC15A57CE252C06111D75140EED0C0">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="72D7947949145C02E46C8AA56FB9B2BE" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9510E24B8AA697E3B6004C485EA0CB64">
<mods:roleTerm id="0B952386F27B16589B2950FA18AFB4DE">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1AEFAB8178DE9770004AF25703571278">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="D3154221C1FC56E2706E8D2ACA1D2F84" type="personal">
<mods:role id="394D9BF9168A873135181CA055F29431">
<mods:roleTerm id="DD88D2DA98948D97C45DDF712EBB4E98">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3671FBE659A77F02C2E9E9AE18568A00">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="53EC55227057D2128E7172E92365E2C8">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="B1B25BF11DFAF0267AFF868CB4CA1E39" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="CD379BC9BAF5A77108DC6A71473E927D">
<mods:title id="B8172A480F0A76D9B28C01A1AEAB2E02">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="9DCBAD41D70F6387EAA0CF03D0D40D98">
<mods:date id="BBEDFBCA098048DACC037C9F80F7459E">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="FF13EA75C6FDB2E3A1ABCEDA438FBC4D" type="volume">
<mods:number id="7E3A9B0F407E6ECC2AA342D52F6488B9">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1223299F2578759E746690330B15042C" unit="page">
<mods:start id="43BAB4CBDAE03D232FE699862976C379">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F878B89BB77BE7988CFBA5240D88095F">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="ECCCFBF2A15DE0FA364474E4361A92C1">
<mods:url id="A27A0F13FC50E10C09817915BB708DEB">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="D19945CDCD62522EACA6BF7088E9A36A">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="938BB8CC47F6193714D01D7C35600C69" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="D152E677CD8B30EEB1A9C49C3B08D1F0" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B8BC894984980F680D40A89C86896470" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="6439240F06A52A775A3DAC4700504117" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047599" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3D711BFF-EFA8-49DE-B27E-5923F2D05BDC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6439240F06A52A775A3DAC4700504117" lastPageId="108" lastPageNumber="109" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">
<subSubSection id="49C8DD0757BBD1E84DA358975B428432" pageId="105" pageNumber="106" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="43C2CB4108F177DF6BA0A929209BCAAC" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">
<taxonomicName id="EAD0EEB3DB4F904B49EE06AC79FA7651" LSID="http://zoobank.org/3D711BFF-EFA8-49DE-B27E-5923F2D05BDC" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio leviventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="105" pageNumber="106" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leviventris">Oxyscelio leviventris Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="760ABAFA2AD340DE9EB317BA259E734F" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 153-158; Morphbank57
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E53FBE5D5CC97E70A790C7F6BAF5DB9A" lastPageId="107" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="105" pageNumber="106" type="description">
<paragraph id="13D137C4AFFFC0CCE532A97BF1A6D868" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C57397ABEF0A2FE132007F28B853D5C1" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">Female. Body length 3.5-4.25 mm (n=5).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="12B025841F3974CC277831F500537738" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">Radicle color and shade: same as scape, both dark brown. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: longer than broad. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="117F194DF85EE22F038816D043D32723" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: granulate. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by a set of irregular elevations. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: transversely rugose. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, complete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: rugose; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: rugose; umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="14918D032A939D98C711B2DC24733573" lastPageId="107" lastPageNumber="108" pageId="105" pageNumber="106">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: anteriorly smooth, posterodorsal corner with dense microsculpture, ventral corner with irregular carinae. Posterior border of cen 
<pageBreakToken id="964FE2DCD6EE370042A03AF72756931D" pageId="106" pageNumber="107" start="start">tral</pageBreakToken>
pronotal area: directed posteriorly, epomial carina absent or meeting transverse pronotal carina at arch on lateral surface of pronotum. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate punctate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: obliquely rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: granulate. Median mes 
<pageBreakToken id="24947D60E02D5B5E06614B98D3A4770F" pageId="107" pageNumber="108" start="start">oscutal</pageBreakToken>
carina: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent; granulate. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: smooth. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex; reaching middle of T6. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, but parallel for a short distance anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E210E650F84D8F4D6A3B9605B88379C8" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: more than 6. T1 lateral carina: straight. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 sculpture: mostly smooth, with tiny umbilicate foveae. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 sculpture: mostly smooth, with tiny umbilicate foveae. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of T6: granulate. T6 medially: flat and tapering to a rounded apex, not separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: smooth, with tiny umbilicate foveae. S5 sculpture: smooth, with tiny umbilicate foveae. S5 median carina: absent. S6 peripheral carina: absent. S6 apex in relation to T6: not exposed to dorsal view. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7265C16490211EC4232D7FD91F81F477" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">Male. Body length 3.6-3.95 mm (n=20). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: irregularly rugose; umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate punctate; obliquely rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: granulate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate punctate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent; granulate. Fore wing apex at rest: exceeding metasomal apex. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 3. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: absent. T6 metasomal flanges: absent. T7: weakly emarginate.</paragraph>
<caption id="65F927DC0DD8AEE31AD2F1DD7074B0B4" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">
<paragraph id="7A7C49E3EF6F1ED97E24D3398BCC35CD" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">
Figures 153-158. 
<taxonomicName id="451A72C9BE27A4D5386DEDF5A05D40A2" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio leviventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="107" pageNumber="108" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leviventris">Oxyscelio leviventris</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype female (OSUC 438829) 153 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 154 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 155 Head, anterior view. Holotype female (OSUC 438828) 156 Metasoma, dorsal view 157 Metasoma, ventral view. Paratype male (OSUC 438832) 158 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank57
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1B6ECD10F7E054144F6B39D04197331E" lastPageId="108" lastPageNumber="109" pageId="107" pageNumber="108" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="501F834D537478FCD5AFCA6DC337883C" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="18351ADB04F9784F6826DDD01F6D99A1" lastPageId="108" lastPageNumber="109" pageId="107" pageNumber="108">
Both sexes: Body and limbs entirely dark brown. Frontal depression nearly flat, not crossed by carinae; submedian carina weakly indicated by some rugae. Clypeus not elongate. Hyperoccipital carina indicated by rugae. Occipital carina complete, irregular or weakly convex medially. Notauli absent. Mesoscutellum smooth, with only some scattered setae. Metascutellum broad and short, concave dorsally, rugose. Postmarginal vein present. Metasomal depression sculptured antero-medially. T1 lateral carina not expanded. Metasomal sterna without longitudinal rugae or cari 
<pageBreakToken id="AE202566E7061E6E6BE0C831EC6C43D0" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" start="start">nae</pageBreakToken>
. Metasomal flanges absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A5 broader than long. T1 midlobe with 5 or more longitudinal carinae. T6 broader than long, apical rim not separated from main body of tergum. Male: All flagellomeres longer than broad. T1 midlobe with 3 longitudinal carinae. T7 very broad and short, without posterior lobes.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8777A648ADDF8BBA8102BA20267F35EB" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="B266C8B8899C2AFADFF39E08D37EFA0C" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AFD5C3CDDC425EDF95BC89F5C4CA032F" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="06D4CBF7F7667B76A2FAD24BE5AFCFDE" originalValue="“smooth-abdomen.”">&quot;smooth-abdomen.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="5F3A095FE8D3D39ED49682BBFCB14DB4" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="D1301CA8A04AA194CDB38D6B7C465F73" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="15ABADD0F195AE07C9374C227EB7B461" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307085]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="5AF7D73B417BF6F87169A321670BE4CF" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="F25999B2EF7FB70686112347E55B1237" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0F6FF4640CA78E6D6D1336D2187E67A3" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: TAS, Bathurst Harbour, margin of copse / heathy sedgeland, Melaleuca, 
<geoCoordinate id="45B928CA04D0B60F3ED27425B698DFCC" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-43.416668">43°25'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="472E5ABB8A91524126BA206B533D423C" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="146.16667">146°10'E</geoCoordinate>
, 12.
<normalizedToken id="1DECCEEAD7B845F74BF1C9AC47ACF1A4" originalValue="II–">II-</normalizedToken>
17.II.1990, malaise trap, I. D. Naumann, OSUC 438828 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 4 females, 21 males, OSUC 438809, 438826-438827, 438829-438843, 438845-438849 (ANIC); OSUC 227562 (CNCI); OSUC 438844 (MVMA).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="93FF61DC5ED1C192E02084EF5B7A99D1" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="comments">
<paragraph id="2283CC6AFA4655A788928A7AF4115607" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EE75418A6D19373E39C4B3384D7AD2FB" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
<taxonomicName id="12315C2768A1E8F2CD0487718B252C91" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio leviventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leviventris">Oxyscelio leviventris</taxonomicName>
is similar to some members of the flavipes-group, as indicated by the usual loss of notauli and the smooth mesoscutellum. However, the occiput is roughly sculptured, and the frontal depression is very weak. Some other species in southeast Australia also exhibit dark coloration and reduced sculpture, but at least some of these may be convergent. While the absence of notauli may be striking in some specimens, this feature appears to be variable in this and some other species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>