<document id="94CA5470F7209A05C87D1D158AC68137" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.221.3659" ID-GBIF-Dataset="afbc8702-b004-473a-8096-49c93ec6161e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152037041" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-221-63" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8FC01C8B-6EA5-469D-BAEF-8F258B5EB93B" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-221-63" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 221" ModsDocTitle="Two new species of Euglossa from South America, with notes on their taxonomic affinities (Hymenoptera, Apidae)" checkinTime="1451248744304" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Hinojosa-Diaz, Ismael A., Nemesio, Andre &amp; Engel, Michael S." docDate="2012" docId="66B011CB32B5D6E14592DD5C5736074E" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 221: 63-79" docOrigin="ZooKeys 221" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.221.3659" docTitle="Euglossa (Glossurella) embera Hinojosa-Diaz, Nemesio &amp; Engel, 2012, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="8FC01C8B-6EA5-469D-BAEF-8F258B5EB93B" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="73" masterDocId="D8141563FFD6FFFAD1708141FF9F7C00" masterDocTitle="Two new species of Euglossa from South America, with notes on their taxonomic affinities (Hymenoptera, Apidae)" masterLastPageNumber="79" masterPageNumber="63" pageId="1" pageNumber="64" updateTime="1643703121695" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="D9C65AA4F64D539B5BD9E98CCBA3FD76" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="B6B1536404DECD332F98B70EFE6A6E62">
<mods:title id="96A100E62EAC4AB8B22BCCB03494FD35">Two new species of Euglossa from South America, with notes on their taxonomic affinities (Hymenoptera, Apidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="D4BEB050E3D9217B0D03D5F266326F44" type="personal">
<mods:role id="62CB06A198E6364870CEDBF5152051A2">
<mods:roleTerm id="817D5AC8ACCC9CF3D5FBC14620A24499">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="D1BAC9341F8025B41230FE0ACEA2291B">Hinojosa-Diaz, Ismael A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="3BFA27BE271C893ECD8AF91B49202035" type="personal">
<mods:role id="6C7F9CEA067A4D06B934D7A27545DDC2">
<mods:roleTerm id="77D4B208D25E3455BEB13FA4AB58C98B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1396873E5459493AEE96FCA6223D2E85">Nemesio, Andre</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="5FD0DA1BC628A1839CB0CB569F3CB39B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="2C492B6F3B578622AC21910ACB8F50E2">
<mods:roleTerm id="1032F9CEC4480F05B8B57433D2D87A9F">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="A9863976E5FC11B73253082B83316954">Engel, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="EDD58A9B7A48798B2AA34C797E7E7EC4">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="C49389E8E9636B0BB9EE5FE21AD90D12" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="03F3264FE30070765662D13561EA0F11">
<mods:title id="8F6DE2DD6728FA4615991ADD599FBB66">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="364A47978C2A9B134AE48F9801B751F2">
<mods:date id="8FAB39BBFF2476632416E625B62B80FA">2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="D60EE6EA271B6F4B3A76315428831F4D" type="volume">
<mods:number id="9FA4E033DBD9531ABAF469DFE2E45480">221</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="A13180390482876E3097E974F9082D5E" unit="page">
<mods:start id="7D18B114806C3640420B7988AFBC4BB9">63</mods:start>
<mods:end id="09A1C07C971AB6BD0C7316AB1CDC4D61">79</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="FC03509463B1FEB8864043D8FE6B81CA">
<mods:url id="AB57F461F782EBDC80D12A93EB6143EF">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.221.3659</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="0F28374943DB938732EBC0DA1142658F">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="071C8A527FB2FE7DE3BEF04CE0EF40EF" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.221.3659</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="58B03ECCEFA932D82664245884608C58" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-221-63</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="95C0A27F9816E3D2C4D992C8355B45A1" type="ZooBank">02106488-7B26-4E82-810C-DB1CB075D7B4</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="66B011CB32B5D6E14592DD5C5736074E" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152037041" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8FC01C8B-6EA5-469D-BAEF-8F258B5EB93B" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/66B011CB32B5D6E14592DD5C5736074E" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="73" pageId="1" pageNumber="64">
<subSubSection id="ECDA08231F1AF40BE264413B4AFE3533" pageId="1" pageNumber="64" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="A6A255E609A63269CF98FE07BECEEC18" pageId="1" pageNumber="64">
<taxonomicName id="DE7CB0B37735CABA30E664E24F5D5DA3" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8FC01C8B-6EA5-469D-BAEF-8F258B5EB93B" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa (Glossurella) embera" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="64" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="embera" subGenus="Glossurella">Euglossa (Glossurella) embera</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="73CCB399B084AFE171C0800D697A3E83" pageId="1" pageNumber="64">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 120
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E2496899A46DAE306FE2F3502CE4D259" pageId="1" pageNumber="64" type="holotype">
<paragraph id="D43995A416AE610FE2701B946C93288D" pageId="1" pageNumber="64">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="70858C6AED762AE9065832877B09E304" pageId="1" pageNumber="64">♂, labeled: &quot;COLOMBIA: Prov. Valle; Rio Anchicaya, 400m.; 10 Feb. 1977. M.D.;Breed &amp; C.D.Michener&quot;. The holotype is in SEMC.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="DBFCE0EA74527F0D7C346E79758C4E38" pageId="2" pageNumber="65" type="paratypes">
<paragraph id="5348A438DE2DF87D8DA088FF0D205884" pageId="2" pageNumber="65">
<pageBreakToken id="ECD10A487A79F908A4FA7F31B52B4857" pageId="2" pageNumber="65" start="start">Paratypes</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E7A567D4D2938DC27C9918790CD48E26" pageId="2" pageNumber="65">3♂♂, 1♀: labeled as follows: data as holotype (1♂); data as holotype plus two extra labels &quot;2 // Euglossa; bursigera Moure; det. R.L.Dressler 1977&quot; (1♂); label data as holotype except date and collectors &quot;IX-28-76. Bell,; Breed &amp; Michener&quot; (1♂); label data as holotype except date &quot;11 Feb. 1977&quot; (1♀). Paratypes are deposited in SEMC and UFMG.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AC3DB55B245B95C8CA7B00F898114F46" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="2" pageNumber="65" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="E44D042AEEFD68596D62847D1D6E868D" pageId="2" pageNumber="65">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4E78928186EE774A606837103D84D7C8" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="68" pageId="2" pageNumber="65">
Labiomaxillary complex in repose surpassing tip of metasoma by about one metasomal tergum length in the male (Figs 1-2), slightly shorter than metasoma in the female (Figs 3-4); both sexes with integument coloration light blue-green in the 
<pageBreakToken id="32FC6BC4E620AAC3FA0618131924730E" pageId="3" pageNumber="66" start="start">head</pageBreakToken>
, metasoma and mesosoma green with strong golden-bronzy coloration on dorsal areas as well as on metasomal sterna (Figs 1-4), male paraocular ivory marks narrow, not noticeably widened on lower sections, in most specimens not reaching epistomal sulcus (Figs 2, 5); male mandible tridentate, middle tooth reduced; female mesoscutellar tuft tear-drop shaped, occupying two thirds of mesoscutellar length (Fig. 3); female metabasitarsus trapezoidal with narrower straight distal margin, anterior and posterior margins convex (Fig. 9); metasomal terga in both sexes with dense punctures, becoming slightly shallower towards posterior margin; male mesotibia as follows: michrotrichia (velvety area) with anterior margin noticeably sparser, posterior margin obliquely truncate distally (Fig. 7), anterior mesotibial tuft ellipsoidal, proximal margin concave, and posterior mesotibial tuft elongated antero-posteriorly (Fig. 8); male metatibial shape 
<pageBreakToken id="9E58C1CC2D69735C3B90FCF51B3AA4DC" pageId="4" pageNumber="67" start="start">scalene</pageBreakToken>
obtuse triangular, metatibial organ slit of male metatibia with basal section tear-drop shaped, distal section narrow and noticeably elongated, only separated from tibial ventral margin by less than the 
<normalizedToken id="2BCC7C44A377E9B2D623153A79497832" originalValue="organ’s">organ's</normalizedToken>
distal section maximum width (Fig. 10), 
<pageBreakToken id="C6DD6C3D8C1CCF813625507C3B60F00C" pageId="5" pageNumber="68" start="start">inner</pageBreakToken>
surface with notorious circular depression near metabasitarsal joint (Fig. 11); male second metasomal sternum with two notorious omega-like integumental depressions (Fig. 12); male terminalia features as follows: eighth metasomal sternum with posterior section triangular (Fig. 15); dorsal process of gonocoxite thumb-like, about as long as broad (Fig. 18); lateral area of gonostylar process of gonocoxite projected as a short, broad prong; lateral section of gonostylus large, spoon-like, covered with dense, simple, long setae (Fig. 17). See also Table 1.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="423B3AFF82D6C137CA0F739D4E23CE9C" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="73" pageId="5" pageNumber="68" type="description">
<paragraph id="EFFB08BFB684F12A459F4CEF3808764C" pageId="5" pageNumber="68">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BDF2BA8AC8957C16A874D3AD18323E11" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="70" pageId="5" pageNumber="68">
♂: Structure (all measurements in millimeters and based on 4 individuals). Total body length 11.62 (11.33-12.02); labiomaxillary complex in repose surpassing tip of metasoma by about one metasomal tergum length (Figs 1-2). Head length 2.54 (2.44-2.59), width 4.31 (4.21-4.43); upper interorbital distance 2.08 (2.04-2.15); lower interorbital distance 2.09 (2.07-2.15); upper clypeal width 1.13 
<pageBreakToken id="ABA6997CE96A2785903CA350BFCE8156" pageId="6" pageNumber="69" start="start">(</pageBreakToken>
1.11-1.19); lower clypeal width 1.97 (1.93-2.00); clypeal protuberance 0.87 (0.81-0.93); medial clypeal ridge well developed, wide and blunt, paramedial clypeal ridges diagonal, well developed, sharp along their lower two thirds, obscured by punctation on upper third; labrum wider than long, length 1.09 (1.04-1.15), width 1.19 (1.15-1.22); medial labral ridge sharp; paramedial labral ridges blunt, oblique, running along length of labral windows; labral windows ovoid, occupying proximal two thirds of labrum; interocellar distance 0.34 (0.30-0.37); ocellocular distance 0.61 (0.59-0.65); first flagellomere shorter [0.37 (0.35-0.37)] than second and third flagellomeres combined [0.42 (0.37-0.44)]; length of malar area 0.19 (0.17-0.20). Mandible tridentate, middle tooth reduced, adjacent to inner margin of outer tooth. Pronotal dorso-lateral angle obliquely truncate (truncation appearing subtle, but noticeable), thicker (along the truncate edge) than remainder of posterior pronotal marginal ridge; intertegular distance 3.17 (3.04-3.33); mesoscutal length 2.61 (2.59-2.63); mesoscutellar length 1.19 (1.11-1.26); mesuscutum with no noticeable concavity on mesial area (at most with a thin linear shallow depression on posterior half); posterior margin of mesoscutellum evenly convex, convexity rather blunt on meso-posterior section (Fig. 1); mesotibial length 2.05 (2.00-2.07), mesotibial spur present; mesobasitarsal length 1.85 (1.78-1.93), width 0.71 (0.67-0.74) (as measured at proximal posterior keel), poste 
<pageBreakToken id="B1A8B38019EC7AD513EAE4B80B271E15" pageId="7" pageNumber="70" start="start">rior</pageBreakToken>
keel projected in a slightly obtuse angle; metatibial shape triangular (scalene obtuse triangular), anterior margin noticeably convex on outer view (Figs 10-11), metatibial anterior margin length 3.11 (2.96-3.26), ventral margin length 2.43 (2.30-2.52), postero-dorsal margin length 4.28 (4.15-4.37), maximum metatibial thickness 1.10 (1.04-1.19); metatibial organ slit narrow, basal section teardrop shaped, anteriorly acute, length 0.67 (0.59-0.81), distal section spur shaped, elongated distally, separated from ventral margin by less than its maximum width, maximum width occupying about one-fourth of metatibial outer surface width (Fig. 10), metatibial inner surface with a notorious circular depression adjacent to joint with metabasitarsus (Fig. 11), metabasitarsal length 2.15 (2.07-2.22), mid-width 0.83 (0.81-0.89); metabasitarsal ventral margin oblique (Fig. 10). Forewing length 8.80 (8.67-8.96); jugal comb with 13-14 blades; hind wing with 16-20 hamuli. Maximum metasomal width 4.19 (4.07-4.30); second metasomal sternum with two shallow omega shaped depressions, lined with setae, located on concave areas of sinuate margin (Fig. 12).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="71DF3027516679A5125919EDF175EAC8" pageId="7" pageNumber="70">Coloration. Head light blue-green with golden-bronzy iridescence specially on paraocular areas, antennal depressions and preoccipital area; clypeal medial ridge dark brown; paraocular ivory marks thin but well developed, slightly wider below, in most specimens not reaching epistomal sulcus (separated from it by about their width); lower lateral parts of clypeus, labrum, malar area, and mandibles (except teeth) ivory; labral windows amber-translucent; antennal scape with ivory spot covering all lateral surface and part of anterior surface, scape otherwise dark brown as remainder of antenna (Fig. 5). Pronotum green, blue-purple lights on lower ventral areas, golden-bronzy iridescence all over; mesoscutum, mesoscutellum and tegula green with strong golden-bronzy iridescence, dominant (obscuring green coloration) on mesoscutum and mesoscutellum (Figs 1-2); mesepisternum green with golden-bronzy iridescence specially on lateral areas (not as marked as on mesoscutum), preomaular area with brown-brassy spot on upper lateral area (Fig. 15); metepisternum and propodeum concolor with lateral areas of mesepisternum plus some blue-green coloration on areas close to leg joints; legs mainly bottle green on outer surface (except all tarsomeres beyond basitarsa) with moderate golden-bronzy iridescence, inner surface of all podites and entire tarsomeres beyond basitarsi brown-brassy, blue-purple lights on outer-anterior margins of most podites, specially notorious on mesofemur and mesotibia (Figs 2, 7); wings glossy hyaline with brown veins (Figs 1-2). Metasomal terga green with strong golden-bronzy iridescence in a gradient, strong anteriorly (fully bronzy) to weaker posteriorly (green-golden-bronzy) (Fig. 1); sterna with same colors and pattern as terga.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D5CDC692FC89FC85B9689974605AC126" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="71" pageId="7" pageNumber="70">
Sculpturing. Face densely areolate-punctate, areole-puncture size around one third of median ocellar diameter on clypeal disc, one eighth on frons (frontal fringe), and somewhere in between in other areas, paraocular groove between paraocular marks and torulus smooth (Fig. 5), gena with areole-punctures comparable in size to those of clypeal disc, well marked above, shallow on lower areas. Mesoscutum with round punctures about one fifth of median ocellar diameter, dense (separated by less than a puncture diameter) on most areas, becoming slightly sparser along median mesoscutal line (separated by one to two puncture diameters), where smaller punctures (about one 
<pageBreakToken id="FFC1C16F8AA5E5034A8DC635381CFAB7" pageId="8" pageNumber="71" start="start">fourth</pageBreakToken>
of a regular puncture size) are intermixed sparsely; mesoscutellum with punctation as on mesal areas of mesoscutum (sparse punctures intermixed with smaller punctures), punctures becoming denser (contiguous) and bigger (at least double in size) on posterior area along mesoscutal margin (Fig. 1); mesepisternal lateral-facing surface with dense punctures on upper areas as big as punctures on frons, becoming slightly bigger and sparser towards lower areas (separated by one or more puncture diameters on ventral areas); preomaular area with punctation as a continuation of lateral-facing area of mesepisternum, except for impunctate brown-brassy spot; metatibial outer surface with punctures comparable in size to those on posterior margin of mesoscutellum, relatively dense (separated by less than one puncture diameter) on upper half, sparser (separated by two to three puncture diameters) on lower half, smooth (impunctate) on small depression contiguous to organ slit (Fig. 10). Dorsal surface of posterior half of first metasomal tergum and second through fifth terga with dense punctures, around half the size of regular mesoscutal punctures, becoming slightly shallower towards posterior margin, anterior half of first tergum, lateral sections of second through fifth terga, and entire surface of sixth and seventh terga with similar pattern but punctures as big as those on posterior margin of mesoscutellum (Fig. 1); metasomal sterna with relatively dense punctation (punctures of a varied size, but most comparable to those on mesepisternum), leaving large semicircular smooth areas mesally on every sternum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="34023E0CFE17AA0B61D450F8FD857C42" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="72" pageId="8" pageNumber="71">
Vestiture. Frontal fringe with dense setae of two natures, some brown, very minutely branched, straight, as long as two mid-ocellar diameters, the others, amber-golden, with noticeable but short branches, shorter than the brown setae; remainder of the face (except as noted hereafter) with scattered amber-golden setae (as the ones on frontal fringe), shorter on most areas, and noticeably plumose on antennal depressions; posterior section of vertex and mid-ocellar area with long curved brown setae; gena with dense, light, plumose setae, increasing in size towards lower genal section; antenna with scattered amber golden setae (Fig. 5). Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum densely setose, majority of setae amber-golden with few intermixed brown setae (these last notorious on anterolateral corners of mesoscutum) (Figs 1-2, 13); lateral-facing surface of mesepisternum, metepisternum and propodeum with, dense, pale, plumose setae as long as those on lower gena, some brown setae interspaced on pronotal lobe; preomaular area with setae as those on lateral-facing mesepisternal areas, except bare on preomaular spot and contiguous smooth area (Fig. 2); outer surface of all legs with light yellowish setae, moderately dense and short in most areas except as follows: dense, long (as long as those on lower gena) and plumose on posterior surface of foreleg, dense and erect downwards on anterior surface of mesotibia (Fig. 7), dense and appressed on mesobasitarsus, long (as long as those on vertex) and arranged in a fringe on distal half of postero-dorsal margin of metatibia, other leg setal features as follows: inner surface of all basitarsi with dense, hirsute, brown-amber setae, chemical gathering tufts on second through fourth protarsomeres with dense, brown-amber, moderately long, setae, microtrichia on outer mesotibial surface (velvety area) composed of dense, fulvous, simple, minute setae, anterior margin of velvety area noticeably sparser, distal third of posterior margin diagonally truncate (Fig. 7), anterior mesotibial tuft ellipsoidal with 
<pageBreakToken id="9EED937AB4EDF996445910731688AD03" pageId="9" pageNumber="72" start="start">proximal</pageBreakToken>
margin concave, composed of dense, fulvous, minutely plumose setae, posterior tuft sitting on a deep cavity elongated antero-posteriorly, with a distinctive semicircular setose patch on posterior half, anterior inner margin of the cavity covered with a fringe of setae, all setae fulvous (Fig. 8); metatibial organ slit closed with dark brown setae (Fig. 10); inner metatibial depression devoid of setae (Fig. 11). Anterolateral corners of first tergum, with moderately dense, amber-golden, simple setae as long as those on mesoscutum, lateral areas of all terga and posterior margin of seventh tergum with similar setae but rather pale, dorsum of posterior half of first tergum and second through sixth terga with dense, appressed, grayish, minute setae, intermixed with scattered, sturdy, brown, short setae appressed, similar setae but appearing simple, shorter and appressed, on lateral margins of remainder terga, as well as posterior half of fifth tergum and entire surface of sixth to seventh terga; posterior dorsal half of first tergum through anterior half of fifth tergum with dense, dusky, appressed short setae, intermixed with some scattered, darker, longer setae (Figs 1, 2); metasomal sterna with moderately dense setae on punctate areas; integumental omega-like depressions on second sternum lined with amber, appressed, simple setae (Fig. 12).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1D030ECCDEBD6CB7FB323CF2A68BF6C3" pageId="9" pageNumber="72">Terminalia. Seventh metasomal sternum with posterior disc margin deeply emarginated mesally, bearing a row of scattered setae (Fig. 14). Eighth metasomal sternum with posterior section triangular (lateral margins straight) on dorsal or ventral view, covered with scattered, minute setae (Fig. 15). Dorsal process of gonocoxite thumb-like, about as long as broad, basal incision broadly concave (Fig. 18); lateral area of gonostylar process of gonocoxite projected as a short, broad prong; lateral section of gonostylus large, spoon-like, ventral lobe with scattered, short, simple setae on outer surface, inner concave surface covered with dense, simple, long setae (Fig. 17).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="69F2715D54AC8AEF3FCF1C8A5F70ABB6" pageId="9" pageNumber="72">♀: Structure (all measurements in millimeters). Total body length 9.56; labiomaxillary complex in repose short of metasomal tip by less than one metasomal segment length (Fig. 4). Head length 2.48; head width 4.22; upper interorbital distance 2.11; lower interorbital distance 2.07; upper clypeal width 1.11; lower clypeal width 1.95; clypeal protuberance 0.74; medial clypeal ridge as in male, paramedial ridges weak, almost completely obscured by punctuation, labral ridges as in male, labral windows occupying about four fifths of labral length; labrum rectangular, wider than long, length 1.00, width 1.11; anterior edge of labrum arched outwards; interocellar distance 0.37; ocellocular distance 0.59; length of first flagellomere (0.37) shorter to combined length of second and third flagellomeres (0.41); length of malar area 0.09. Mandible tridentate. Pronotal lateral angle mainly as in male, but not so noticeably thicker than remainder of pronotal posterior ridge; intertegular distance 3.26; mesoscutal length 2.52; mesoscutellar length 1.26; posterior border of mesoscutellum as in male (Fig. 3); mesotibial length 2.00; mesobasitarsal length 1.63, maximum width 0.59; metatibia triangular (scalene right triangular) (Fig. 9), metatibial anterior margin length 2.81; metatibial ventral margin length 1.63; metatibial posterodorsal margin length 3.19; metabasitarsus trapezoidal with narrower straight distal margin, anterior and posterior margins convex (Fig. 9), length 1.70, maximum width 0.89. Forewing length 8.00; hind wing with 18 hamuli. Maximum metasomal width 4.30.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5B8DDE3BC8AF99E07ECC6CE7DC486F38" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<pageBreakToken id="0DB9239780FEF64F763B17AC5AC47E59" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" start="start">Coloration</pageBreakToken>
. As described for male (Figs 3-4). Paraocular marks, antennal scape spot, and preomaular spot absent (Fig. 6).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="244D8D4D14B7F37C345CFE66E855753D" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">Sculpturing. As described for male except no differentiation on preomaular area (preomaular spot absent); mesoscutellum with slightly denser punctation (Fig. 3).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="87EAAD89DEBB7DC97BCFEB1657FB6E51" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">Vestiture. As described for male (some setal features on protarsi, meso- and metatibia exclusive of male) except as follows: Mesoscutellar tuft tear-drop shaped, occupying about two thirds of mid mesoscutellar length, composed of dense, dark, erect, multibranched (branches minute) setae (Fig. 3). Foreleg with slightly shorter setae on posterior surface as compared to male (Fig. 6); mesotibial posterior margin with some scattered, dark, sturdy short setae; metatibial corbicula surrounded for the most part by setae as in other leg areas, except by some scattered, dark, sturdy, curved setae (Fig. 9).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="42C5C8731BBCFDBDD236F24895D49857" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="625FCFF5E87E3853BE4CD3C82D56A03C" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="033C1C99954F29A6FA7126E3173D8BCE" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
The specific epithet is a reference to the 
<normalizedToken id="2E8887E204BBAA40E7A208073AF9C020" originalValue="Emberá">Embera</normalizedToken>
, an indigenous people inhabiting the Pacific lowlands of Colombia.
</paragraph>
<caption id="EB84507303B016E7A0AB5F422433E242" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<paragraph id="59A21123033454AC9516F74E99243F88" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
Figures 1-2. 
<taxonomicName id="EBC985EDE2927E97B3CB4D3BD250AF7A" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa embera" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="embera">Euglossa embera</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. 1 Dorsal habitus 2 Lateral habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="C57EC6E1A9EB1D498742FF9202046DDE" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<paragraph id="5806AA19B346F7AD8C17D65E6017E83A" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
Figures 3-4. 
<taxonomicName id="72D69C0C963C8C99475685E75F0A1E7D" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa embera" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="embera">Euglossa embera</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female paratype. 3 Dorsal habitus 4 Lateral habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="80EA6FF39BDC71C0B42FD801BBEABF79" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<paragraph id="181C55422FC094F7CE2008EF7DDF9E3A" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
Figures 5-13. 
<taxonomicName id="3F625F3603589CD13C9764E03A6C5D24" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa embera" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="embera">Euglossa embera</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 5 Facial aspect of male holotype 6 Facial aspect of female paratype 7 Outer surface of male mesotibia (arrow pointing to oblique truncation of velvety area) 8 Mesotibial tufts of male 9 Outer view of female metatibia and metatarsus 10 Outer view of male metatibia and metatarsus (arrow pointing to distal-most extreme of organ slit) 11Inner view of male metatibia and metatarsus (arrow pointing to circular depression) 12 Section of male second metasomal sternum 13 Dorsal view of pronotal dorso-lateral angle (arrow) of male.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="11114B7AD86AE591650372F1336F6BF1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<paragraph id="9E0374D827C0D765685D3AD823C8B57A" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
Figures 14-20. Male genitalic features of 
<taxonomicName id="36B91F0619129306D122720FCFB99A5A" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa embera" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="embera">Euglossa embera</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 14 Seventh metasomal sternum, ventral aspect 15 Eighth metasomal sternum, ventral aspect (arrow pointing to straight lateral margin) 16 Eighth metasomal sternum, lateral aspect 17 lateral section of gonostylus 18 Genitalic capsule, dorsal aspect 19 Genitalic capsule, ventral aspect 20 Genitalic capsule, lateral aspect.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="F43D6F86DB0015005B8B75833E9426E9" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<paragraph id="7F7588828121319CF6C49DA1ADFF1564" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
Table 1. Summary of useful male features for the species included in 
<taxonomicName id="C1DDF70B719E054F89EF1687E430E3D4" authority="Dressler, 1982" authorityName="Dressler" authorityYear="1982" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Glossurella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Glossurella" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Glossurella</taxonomicName>
as here restricted.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="18D618E62E7518CD3661CFDA5578C5A0" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<table id="5F4611F2C279A326AA8B9922FAE31819" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<tr id="0B0ED3D86E1994B6E8758D169152E53B" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<th id="DF0E2447100C29E41D3A144C6F379497" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonomicName id="CAB3D6603266AB67BF604E20DF514E65" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa prasina" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="prasina">Euglossa prasina</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th id="1537A2A98C505587AEAE2916D285B7F9" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonomicName id="D79F10C839DACD7136B5C21A12D43A71" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa bursigera" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bursigera">Euglossa bursigera</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th id="E73A47A399698560DDBB4E9FE65FC7A1" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonomicName id="B73C3005B5ADDB260AFA760821B6090B" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa embera" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="embera">Euglossa embera</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th id="734F578B61F356BA56D07E0B7BADFB2F" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonomicName id="3BAF520CB672300444BF31C0E5BE2028" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa augaspis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="augaspis">Euglossa augaspis</taxonomicName>
</th>
<th id="2F31DBCE7B0A2B06AE2B79F83900F2AD" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonomicName id="6ED1342025D5535C0E02995679AD63A3" class="Insecta" family="Apidae" genus="Euglossa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Euglossa adiastola" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="adiastola">Euglossa adiastola</taxonomicName>
a
</th>
</tr>
<tr id="47B8BD43805A083B21595F630976196D" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<td id="F1BB4E73D1BF2C237608E05A73E11EC5" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1">Shape of metatibia</td>
</tr>
<tr id="B7FFCA1354652D29C8F3E1FD18D40399" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<td id="98406C5D714E726997110F03DB2E7499" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1">Shape of scape</td>
</tr>
<tr id="6EAD6E478A793573C9AAC2E8D722A235" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<td id="13BC6D7A627BDE181EFEA957A846A06D" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1">Length of labiomaxillary complex</td>
</tr>
<tr id="D0EB0666D6491D7E54653E1794599C77" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<td id="D17E4D5EDE37459256E57AA12FBD0535" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1">Malar length</td>
</tr>
<tr id="742913D30B2A99CDFF353E3B509E0387" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<td id="A2B32699F4FC96471E3D3DAA65D7DF65" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1">Separation of tip of metatibial organ slit from ventral margin of metatibia</td>
</tr>
<tr id="948BF2464F1A6A23DF01878086872EDA" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<td id="A14F3AA698502250C307E9F2CF53EBC8" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1">Mid-mandibular tooth</td>
</tr>
<tr id="0850D2419ACB419ABE2EC749E26BCD88" pageId="10" pageNumber="73">
<td id="D1F97EF13151C30E36F825E89F33835A" colspan="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="73" rowspan="1">Known distribution</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>