<document id="011598046BC60CEFEDB52B803588DA3C" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047593" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4270F536-05E9-4F20-873D-CE8F455BD6D2" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="6AD379AE3E436DD98B63B33372B7C153" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio incisurae Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="4270F536-05E9-4F20-873D-CE8F455BD6D2" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="102" lastPageNumber="103" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="100" pageNumber="101" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="F3FC8E2AB4C33379D0E64C8385EFD0D9" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="4AFA760458F2B7CF47C79834597545DD">
<mods:title id="EFA4EC377131B5C3D3DD85E3EFF4A3DC">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="836627898318B9B47FDB11C29E48E977" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F5CFAE5684FEA1D8CB39EEFA98366DA9">
<mods:roleTerm id="B3575AA90FD7D741237928AEFAB7342A">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="6B4F726E1B3AEF7B73184E2D72754B04">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="DA0E38FEBD66BC167C4C65C7E866FEEC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A9D6ECE4361DF8EDBA2EB553E830DB48">
<mods:roleTerm id="93F66962B62735C37A03D256E12CCBC5">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0B5648044404156EB04FC82532095084">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="7C3DC9D871F21BAC353295D11D5E32FA" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9BFABFEAB240D04D675E533C2C474B20">
<mods:roleTerm id="057F7E27CA9D51F64A774F8E6A48349A">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1405F6204038D0DED114ED2371B0923C">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="DDFF1F80F91A114CA130925EB8FAAFC0" type="personal">
<mods:role id="37A7C6582E6CC09FE44603D427151475">
<mods:roleTerm id="D3628F7BA072CA391503C0055C5CCEDC">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="389BA647614138AC13B7F6DA6AB10A44">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="5D06088348B195BC5F2F6D9D5182628C">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="BF580650251CB788ABA199F8C62D9E7D" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="C3DDC6688213E0DFD982750535D91239">
<mods:title id="B6FD77E937EC317763D21ED5DC4CAE46">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="9321F0E0EFE924293BFED077A2338DDC">
<mods:date id="B507A66B31660F741D5D63EBF210C5DA">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="F1F9B7D4FE1BF54D70F5D1AE31683C09" type="volume">
<mods:number id="70D0C6AE78982962FBFD5DA15D8308FD">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1CC9743E1D9E3230A5388F4779F28468" unit="page">
<mods:start id="4D50E96AE2067A8DFEB886F25B91433D">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F692E53A8F9DA0365DA5BA507F6F891B">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="E226A65399BBA754E71A6B9044FD1285">
<mods:url id="AC9052B2C4B6A6A2D8DF6661C9970DAF">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="DF73186CF58415807DF8A004FA0E232E">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="9D61E56D7F105E99C58E020847878C2D" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="DFB8BBD6F56D774060F7DBE849EF51B4" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B656D4E8BC7E48C6DC1EB7E8F46EE434" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="6AD379AE3E436DD98B63B33372B7C153" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047593" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4270F536-05E9-4F20-873D-CE8F455BD6D2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6AD379AE3E436DD98B63B33372B7C153" lastPageId="102" lastPageNumber="103" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">
<subSubSection id="DD2213D9BB502529E3E9BF834A0D01D8" pageId="100" pageNumber="101" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="6F3B7381EDE521629C19C9CB1B0CAF2C" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">
<taxonomicName id="3CC294B2F50BB0B3F685E96BFE4E85B3" LSID="http://zoobank.org/4270F536-05E9-4F20-873D-CE8F455BD6D2" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio incisurae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="100" pageNumber="101" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incisurae">
<pageBreakToken id="F6D27198D2DCB1460FC18C57CAB62A7E" pageId="100" pageNumber="101" start="start">Oxyscelio</pageBreakToken>
incisurae Burks
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="8F861D410A05B76CD6EDCD2CA6B5F733" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 143-148; Morphbank55
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3F57E587AED2BD0ABADA4156ABF50137" lastPageId="102" lastPageNumber="103" pageId="100" pageNumber="101" type="description">
<paragraph id="5E466047C6EB862E31803D31E94B3B0C" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CBB3623B19E043846C2EA195C7595FC6" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">Female. Body length 3.65-4.4 mm (n=11).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CFF11AD0F7E284043B345E37BF9DECA7" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0D7290C9F318E159BDC86C97C62CA66D" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: with some transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: not hood-like, open dorsally. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: weakly arched dorsally, with rounded lateral corners. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: absent. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4CA4DABFEAF8D1580F1EAD47CFD85236" pageId="100" pageNumber="101">Lateral pronotal area sculpture: irregularly foveate, with smooth area dorsally. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a flattened or rounded elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Mesoscutellar rim: expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: with notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching base of T5. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: narrowly separated, angled anteriorly to become parallel. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="377CB074CE860992A5ADE48A79D1AEF7" lastPageId="102" lastPageNumber="103" pageId="101" pageNumber="102">
<pageBreakToken id="59C131F2BA9021F259B1533D17BCFC8B" pageId="101" pageNumber="102" start="start">T</pageBreakToken>
1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: present. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: present as slightly protruding sharp corners. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: present, blade-like with rounded margins. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: longitudinally striate; umbilicate fove 
<pageBreakToken id="FAFD018758DC637447DEA920AD349D50" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" start="start">ate</pageBreakToken>
. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: with medially truncate emargination, separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: present, very broadly rounded but with sharp apices. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: present, posteriorly complete. S6 apex in relation to T6: exposed to dorsal view by T6 emargination. S6 apex: rounded or acuminate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A7310D93A549EFEF05444D6697CA9F59" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Male. Body length 3.85-3.9 mm (n=2). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: longer than broad. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T5. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: obscured by other raised sculpture. T3 metasomal flanges: present. T4 metasomal flanges: present. T5 metasomal flanges: present, rounded and lobe-like. T6 metasomal flanges: present, rounded and lobe-like. T7: M-shaped, with a triangular median emargination.</paragraph>
<caption id="7B2FA7287DE2AFF4D9693AA8EE753A3B" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
<paragraph id="89B3C27CA2EAB3BEF39BEB1BDB6F8E66" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
Figures 143-148. 
<taxonomicName id="EE277E370BD9F439D06E122975953314" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio incisurae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incisurae">Oxyscelio incisurae</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 435942) 143 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 144 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 145 Head, anterior view 146 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 435949) 147 Antenna 148 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank55
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="62254E8BB64DA11A44752056DE2B5FCE" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="6A9E692753EC6910E12CCE7AA81FBE82" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="71CB4EFC7C456901A9132D50CDBB3333" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
Both sexes: Frontal depression deep, all carinae except dorsal separator interrupted medially, carinae present above dorsal separator; submedian carina distinct but irregular medially. Hyperoccipital carina absent. Occipital carina complete, medially sinuate. Mesoscutal midlobe densely foveate. Mesoscutellar rim not expanded, with median notch. Metascutellum scoop-like, projecting dorsally. Coxa darker than rest of leg. Postmarginal vein absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A4, A5 broader than long. T4 with weak metasomal flanges. T5 with lobe-like metasomal flanges. T6 with broad, wavy lateral metasomal flanges. T6 broadly and deeply emarginate, truncate medially. S6 exposed to dorsal view, rounded apically. Male: A3, A4, A11 longer than broad. Mesoscutellum and mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly with small and densely set foveae, mesoscutellum without smooth area medially. T5 with weak metasomal flanges, T6 with lobe-like metasomal flanges. T7 with broad postero-lateral lobes, deeply emarginate medially, posterior margin broadly M-shaped. 
<taxonomicName id="62BA90D74795AF664808F65CB9CF2635" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio incisurae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incisurae">Oxyscelio incisurae</taxonomicName>
is very similar to 
<taxonomicName id="9B9F2BC8778E80B044C51B1D29471E01" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio funis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="funis">Oxyscelio funis</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="4BD61A6C9308C9C7E09DCF98EA3FB59F" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio bellariorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bellariorum">Oxyscelio bellariorum</taxonomicName>
, but differs in the short antenna and small and close-set mesoscutal midlobe foveae of females. Males may be more difficult to distinguish from similar species, but the long, dark flagellum in the only examined male was distinctive.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9295F7F999B16D9D9A6D8D3EBD863CA1" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="F352D22D34A05AD389BECB14DF928DB1" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F4E7870788F2967207156844FDEEE8B6" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="354679E9B03AC16A259A23DC5FF20146" originalValue="“incision.”">&quot;incision.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="00594B5B1145A8BA568505F09E19DD8E" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="D461373323391904496BCD653AD99456" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="22A8F50B05D8E5B70C5D5F9D9D02004D" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307083]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2BAAF0DCBDFA25519656EB1634B2CA45" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="6E60A400F59C3D876E0BA4FC7800FFAD" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C08CDAE2A3245D75BA7C22A88C20D32D" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: SA, 14km WNW Renmark, Calperum Station, Bookmark Biosphere Reserve, 
<geoCoordinate id="E12EB3A196AC7A654CCB0A31DBDA387A" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-34.116665">34°07'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="3466C48A83443CDE87C8042A0E2B0625" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="140.61667">140°37'E</geoCoordinate>
, 7.
<normalizedToken id="8D4DC03E16763317FA73B8D9CAA46176" originalValue="XI–">XI-</normalizedToken>
13.XII.1995, flight intercept trap/gutter trap, K. R. Pullen, OSUC 435942 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 10 females, 2 males, OSUC 435939-435941, 435943-435949, 453998 (ANIC); OSUC 462737 (CNCI).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>