<document id="61A69D0B6F751A774505464D26070DC0" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5636481" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d1467dc5-42ac-4656-b728-69cbbe44f692" ID-GBIF-Taxon="189796599" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5636481" ID-ZooBank="0E9C6A17-710A-4DF7-A23F-69FAA1113F4D" _generate="added" checkinTime="1635758123376" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto De L. &amp; Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2021" docId="6C7F3F1B6C6FFF83DEC6FC34FBBAF0A8" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.5050.3.3.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 5060 (3)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Oxycoleus mirabilis Nascimento &amp; Santos-Silva 2021, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="362" masterDocId="904647636C69FF8ADE51FF9AFFDAF259" masterDocTitle="The interesting and complex tribe Oxycoleini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae): a new genus, new species, and taxonomic notes" masterLastPageNumber="370" masterPageNumber="353" pageId="6" pageNumber="359" updateTime="1635779129829" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="ED4CB6DB2019F24A6B3A8A8C42ECEE29" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="688E10A81F9F8D08829525DBA82E9A14">
<mods:title id="5447A3CDB8678C8E20D9ADEF9C13488D">The interesting and complex tribe Oxycoleini (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae): a new genus, new species, and taxonomic notes</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="740A02D9F93DCA6055EACB0C06451A4E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="052C81DDE0812F322A59EFC8128E193D">
<mods:roleTerm id="267453B0BD5B4FB3A51F6646D045A709">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0B8D8E9545B9D5CE750A73F41B5987BF">Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto De L.</mods:namePart>
<mods:nameIdentifier id="8F3D54D46126633CC128D7679B09E07F" type="ORCID">0000-0002-5047-8921</mods:nameIdentifier>
<mods:affiliation id="B514C108E9E6624260D99DC6AAB6A9C7">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil &amp; eribnascimentofl @ gmail. com; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0002 - 5047 - 8921</mods:affiliation>
<mods:nameIdentifier id="82203FA5AAE1F0624DF20C5883FD78ED" type="email">eribnascimentofl@gmail.com</mods:nameIdentifier>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="70D9519F1490A284CD37432F4BC6CD1D" type="personal">
<mods:role id="E649C1C4D782479FC0759883EC1314E7">
<mods:roleTerm id="72241D95C4AFF78162C9D8035CB400CF">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7761806AD8FEF64A99DC429B4BFCB022">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
<mods:nameIdentifier id="677D657ACEEAB4BB86F02B4CA17C1800" type="ORCID">0000-0001-7128-1418</mods:nameIdentifier>
<mods:affiliation id="8671E9C7B77E25B2594E8A35DB01905A">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil &amp; toncriss @ uol. com. br; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0001 - 7128 - 1418</mods:affiliation>
<mods:nameIdentifier id="E31F6A8F8877170200B29A168DD69813" type="email">toncriss@uol.com.br</mods:nameIdentifier>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="6EA03B420A3CD096470228FBC01A1C4C">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="F4C9DDCBC8EF71376EA0704DA90B1800" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="0ED1A7F4E559B82CB20A5DBE46F97612">
<mods:title id="A9E4424F1402DAB597A1C8F4116A30B6">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="AB19EDA68E6CDBA7F417D26E82CFA58F">
<mods:date id="940B2A4D46888F13DA5786677E06B42B">2021</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="DD16D6BA8EF2EFE83155A71031EB23EC" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="D0EFDF3E0F29CB6F657021F8C7762096">2021-11-01</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="041DF53086180829CEE5AB2172AA0CE5" type="volume">
<mods:number id="028FF22A9D07C40F9EEBEB7333539885">5060</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="784684F0673A7A86CBC1D2E7E263D8B0" type="issue">
<mods:number id="37D943FBB5431FB1304CCF9FC4F004FB">3</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="57514F0BDDAEA95C19038807A821DDE8" unit="page">
<mods:start id="2C98E92A1A58F4FE00FF162E5D10B069">353</mods:start>
<mods:end id="5A720A42C63A36162A0870BDB75D6D50">370</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="84D0A7253C9B40BDB0C6AA5775BFCB0B">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="07E8714150D1E1251C098EA4AD6BC40F" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.5060.3.3</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="A662BB96118E6634F09879A0F660D53B" type="GBIF-Dataset">d1467dc5-42ac-4656-b728-69cbbe44f692</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="087F980639E8FAD61EA104E95569358C" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8F1BC02BCC770B59B4137DAC274859B8" type="Zenodo-Dep">5635847</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="69E458119BC6363AD78625D94B0BB718" type="ZooBank">0E9C6A17-710A-4DF7-A23F-69FAA1113F4D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="6C7F3F1B6C6FFF83DEC6FC34FBBAF0A8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5636481" ID-GBIF-Taxon="189796599" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5636481" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6C7F3F1B6C6FFF83DEC6FC34FBBAF0A8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6C7F3F1B6C6FFF83DEC6FC34FBBAF0A8" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="362" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">
<subSubSection id="ACCCDD866C6FFF8CDEC6FC34FE36F190" box="[151,492,942,969]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C6FFF8CDEC6FC34FE36F190" blockId="6.[151,492,942,1005]" box="[151,492,942,969]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">
<heading id="BF2139616C6FFF8CDEC6FC34FE36F190" bold="true" box="[151,492,942,969]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="359" reason="1">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6FFF8CDEC6FC34FE36F190" bold="true" box="[151,492,942,969]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">
<taxonomicName id="23D6F58E6C6FFF8CDEC6FC34FE52F190" authority="Nascimento &amp; Santos-Silva, 2021" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2021" box="[151,392,942,969]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oxycoleus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="359" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirabilis" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6FFF8CDEC6FC34FE52F190" bold="true" box="[151,392,942,969]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">Oxycoleus mirabilis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="CD91EF646C6FFF8CDFDEFC35FE36F190" box="[399,492,943,969]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ACCCDD866C6FFF83DEC6FC49FB04F33C" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="362" pageId="6" pageNumber="359" type="description">
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C6FFF8CDEC6FC49FEC3F1B4" blockId="6.[151,492,942,1005]" box="[151,281,979,1005]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">
(
<figureCitation id="7CED92886C6FFF8CDECEFC49FECBF1B4" box="[159,273,979,1005]" captionStart="FIGURES 8–14" captionStartId="8.[151,264,1738,1762]" captionTargetBox="[151,1434,181,1713]" captionTargetId="figure-24@8.[151,1436,181,1714]" captionTargetPageId="8" captionText="FIGURES 8–14. Oxycoleus mirabilis, 8–12) Holotype male: 8) Dorsal habitus; 9) Ventral habitus; 10) Lateral habitus; 11) Head, frontal view; 12) Antennomeres X–XI. 13–14) Paratype male: 13) Dorsal habitus; 14) Ventral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5635859" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5635859/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">Figs 8–14</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C6FFF8CDEC6FB80FF3CF754" blockId="6.[151,1437,1050,2013]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6FFF8CDEC6FB80FE07F66C" bold="true" box="[151,477,1050,1077]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">
Description. 
<typeStatus id="3B6D30AF6C6FFF8CDF61FB81FE47F66C" box="[304,413,1051,1077]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">Holotype</typeStatus>
male
</emphasis>
(
<figureCitation id="7CED92886C6FFF8CDFBDFB81FDBAF66C" box="[492,608,1051,1077]" captionStart="FIGURES 8–14" captionStartId="8.[151,264,1738,1762]" captionTargetBox="[151,1434,181,1713]" captionTargetId="figure-24@8.[151,1436,181,1714]" captionTargetPageId="8" captionText="FIGURES 8–14. Oxycoleus mirabilis, 8–12) Holotype male: 8) Dorsal habitus; 9) Ventral habitus; 10) Lateral habitus; 11) Head, frontal view; 12) Antennomeres X–XI. 13–14) Paratype male: 13) Dorsal habitus; 14) Ventral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5635859" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5635859/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">Figs 8–12</figureCitation>
). Integument mostly black; ventral mouthparts reddish brown, except yellowish-brown palpomeres; pedicel and antennomeres dark brown; anteclypeus and labrum dark brown. Prothorax reddish brown, slightly yellowish-brown anteriorly and posteriorly, except narrow brown area close to anterior margin; prosternal process dark brown. Metaventrite with irregular reddish-brown areas interspersed, more distinctly anterocentrally. Fore- and middle legs light reddish brown, with femoral club slightly darker, and apex of tarsomere V and claws brown; hindlegs light reddish brown, except black femoral club and apex of tarsomere V and claws brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C6FFF8DDE96FA8DFE09F0DC" blockId="6.[151,1437,1050,2013]" lastBlockId="7.[151,1437,150,2042]" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="360" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6FFF8CDE96FA8DFED4F768" bold="true" box="[199,270,1303,1329]" pageId="6" pageNumber="359">Head.</emphasis>
Frons narrow, transverse, finely, sparsely punctate, punctures finer, denser close to eyes; with minute, sparse yellowish-brown setae close to eyes, glabrous on remaining surface. Median groove deep, somewhat wide between clypeus and area between antennal tubercles, gradually narrowed toward its apex. Area between antennal tubercles and upper eye lobes longitudinally striate-punctate centrally, rugose-punctate close to upper eye lobes; with sparse, erect, somewhat long yellowish-brown setae on sides of area between antennal tubercles and central area between upper eye lobes; area close to upper eye lobes with short, sparse yellowish-brown setae; remaining surface of vertex finely, sparsely punctate (punctures sparser close to prothorax), with short, sparse yellowish-brown setae laterally, glabrous centrally. Area behind upper eye lobes rugose-punctate close to eye, finely, somewhat sparsely punctate close to prothorax; with both, short and somewhat long, erect yellowish-brown setae close to eye, almost glabrous close to prothorax. Superior area behind lower eye lobes smooth close to eye, obliquely striate on remaining surface; inferior area behind lower eye lobes finely, somewhat abundant punctate close to eye, slightly longitudinally striate on wide remaining area; superior area almost glabrous; inferior area with somewhat long, erect yellowish-brown setae close to eye, glabrous on remaining surface. Genae with transverse row of minute punctures near eye, smooth on remaining surface; with minute, decumbent yellowish-white setae on punctate area, glabrous on remaining surface. Wide central area of postclypeus smooth close to frons, except finely punctate sides of this region, coarsely, sparsely punctate close to anteclypeus; sides smooth; with a few, both short and long yellowishbrown setae. Sides of postclypeus smooth and glabrous. Labrum with short, somewhat abundant yellowish-brown setae and long, erect setae of same color interspersed posteriorly, especially laterally. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous on posterior 2/3; anterior third finely punctate, striate on center of its posterior region, with short, erect yellowishbrown setae, almost absent centrally. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.29 times distance between outer margins of eyes; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.55 times distance between outer margins of eyes. Antennae 1.8 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at basal third of antennomere X. Scape clavate; almost smooth dorsally, finely, gradually densely punctate from sides toward ventral surface; dorsal surface most glabrous, sides with somewhat long, erect brownish setae; ventral surface with decumbent brownish setae, denser on posterior half. Pedicel with brownish pubescence on basal 3/4, almost glabrous on posterior; with a few short, erect brownish setae interspersed dorsally, and long, erect brownish setae ventrally. Antennomeres III–IV cylindrical, with brownish pubescence, almost absent on narrow apex, and long, erect, thick brownish setae ventrally. Antennomere V gradually widened toward area near apex on its outer surface; pubescence and erect setae as on III and IV. Antennomeres V–XI gradually widened from base (width and circumference), then distinctly narrowed toward apex (narrowest posterior area placed about posterior quarter on V, about posterior third on VI, and about middle on remaining antennomeres); sculpturing on dorsal surface of narrowest posterior area distinctly finer than on remaining surface; with short brownish pubescence, except glabrous dorsal surface of narrowest posterior area. Antennal formula based on length of antennomere III: scape = 1.32; pedicel = 0.32; IV = 1.37; V = 1.64; VI = 1.58; VII = 1.45; VIII = 1.16; IX = 1.13; X = 1.03; XI = 1.29.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C6EFF8DDE96FD15FE13F530" blockId="7.[151,1437,150,2042]" pageId="7" pageNumber="360">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6EFF8DDE96FD15FEFDF0F0" bold="true" box="[199,295,655,681]" pageId="7" pageNumber="360">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax as long as wide; sides rounded between anterolateral angles and anterior constriction, with distinct rounded projection centrally, then almost parallel-sided toward posterolateral angles. Pronotum strongly tumid between anterior margin and sulcus of anterior constriction, especially centrally; anterior sulcus widely Vshaped; with large, elevated gibbosity on each side, between anterior and posterior constrictions, more elevated centrally, and elevated gibbosity centrally, from middle to posterior constriction, more elevated than lateral gibbosities; central gibbosity surrounded laterally and posterior with narrow U-shaped sulcus; area between anterior margin and anterior sulcus smooth and glabrous centrally, somewhat coarsely, shallowly punctate, and a few yellowish setae laterally; central area between anterior and posterior constrictions finely punctate between gibbosities, smooth on central gibbosity, with a few fine punctures on lateral gibbosities, with a few, somewhat long, erect yellowish setae; sides of area between constrictions somewhat coarsely, shallowly punctate anteriorly, punctures finer, denser toward posterior region, with long, erect yellowish setae throughout, and pubescent about posterior 2/3; area between posterior constriction and posterior margin pubescent, with long, erect yellowish setae interspersed (erect setae denser laterally). Sides of prothorax coarsely punctate between constrictions, finely, sparsely punctate before anterior constriction, partially transversely striate near anterior margin, somewhat rugose-punctate from posterior constriction; with short, sparse, decumbent yellowish setae between constrictions, with long, erect yellowish setae before anterior constriction, pubescent, with long, erect yellowish setae interspersed after posterior constriction. Prosternum somewhat rugose-punctate on posterior half, tumid, almost smooth on anterior half; pubescent, with long, erect yellowish setae interspersed on posterior half, with long, erect yellowish setae on anterior half. Prosternal process very narrow on anterior 2/3, strongly widened with truncate apex on posterior third. Ventral surface of mesothorax mostly glabrous centrally, pubescent, with long, erect yellowish-brown setae interspersed laterally. Metanepisternum finely, sparsely punctate, punctures finer and sparser toward apex; with short, sparse, decumbent yellowish setae, and long, erect setae of same color interspersed. Metaventrite somewhat coarsely abundantly punctate laterally, slightly finer and sparser centrally; with long, erect, abundant yellowish setae laterally, sparser toward central area. Scutellum with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, and a few long, erect yellowish-brown setae interspersed. 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6EFF8DDF7CFA7DFE5AF458" bold="true" box="[301,384,1511,1537]" pageId="7" pageNumber="360">Elytra.</emphasis>
Reaching posterior third of abdominal segment II; strongly narrowed toward acute apex, distinctly dehiscent internally from basal third; lateral carina well-marked, especially from anterior quarter; coarsely, abundantly punctate; with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, and somewhat long, sparse yellowish setae interspersed. 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6EFF8DDFC2F9C9FE08F434" bold="true" box="[403,466,1619,1645]" pageId="7" pageNumber="360">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora pedunculate-clavate; femoral club distinctly wider than pro- and mesofemoral clubs; peduncles with long, erect, sparse yellowish setae; femoral clubs with short, bristly yellowish-brown setae not obscuring integument, setae gradually more abundant toward metafemoral club, and long, erect setae of same color interspersed, erect setae more abundant toward metafemoral club. Pro- and mesotibiae with sparse, erect yellowish setae on basal third, and dense, bristly yellowish pubescence on remaining surface; metatibiae with long, erect yellowish setae on basal third and remaining dorsal surface, long, somewhat abundant, erect yellowish setae on remaining ventral surface, and dense, bristly yellowish pubescence on apical quarter. Metatarsomere I slightly shorter than II–III together.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C6EFF8DDE96F8E9FEA2F5A3" blockId="7.[151,1437,150,2042]" pageId="7" pageNumber="360">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C6EFF8DDE96F8E9FE99F5D4" bold="true" box="[199,323,1907,1933]" pageId="7" pageNumber="360">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with long, erect, abundant yellowish-white setae laterally, slightly sparser on 4–5; central area of 1–2 with long, erect, sparse yellowish-white centrally, sparser on posterior half of 2; 3–4 with short, decumbent, sparse yellowish setae centrally; 5 almost glabrous centrally; 6 almost entirely glabrous. Posterior margin of V strongly concave.
</paragraph>
<caption id="B0A9DE856C61FF82DEC6F950FB3DF55F" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5635859" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5635859" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5635859/files/figure.png" pageId="8" pageNumber="361" startId="8.[151,264,1738,1762]" targetBox="[151,1434,181,1713]" targetPageId="8">
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C61FF82DEC6F950FB3DF55F" blockId="8.[151,1436,1738,1799]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DEC6F950FE90F4BB" bold="true" box="[151,330,1738,1762]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">FIGURES 8–14.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="23D6F58E6C61FF82DF03F950FDFBF4BB" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2021" box="[338,545,1738,1762]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oxycoleus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="361" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirabilis">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DF03F950FDFBF4BB" box="[338,545,1738,1762]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">Oxycoleus mirabilis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DC7EF950FDB0F4BB" bold="true" box="[559,618,1738,1762]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">8–12)</emphasis>
Holotype male: 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DD4AF950FCEBF4BB" bold="true" box="[795,817,1738,1762]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">8)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DD8EF950FC2EF4BB" bold="true" box="[991,1012,1738,1762]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">9)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus; 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DAF9F950FB10F4BB" bold="true" box="[1192,1226,1738,1762]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">10)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus; 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DB2DF950FA46F4BB" bold="true" box="[1404,1436,1738,1762]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">11)</emphasis>
Head, frontal view; 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DF33F974FE5EF55F" bold="true" box="[354,388,1774,1798]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">12)</emphasis>
Antennomeres X–XI. 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DC3BF974FD68F55F" bold="true" box="[618,690,1774,1798]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">13–14)</emphasis>
Paratype male: 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DD07F974FCA2F55F" bold="true" box="[854,888,1774,1798]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">13)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DA4FF974FB9BF55F" bold="true" box="[1054,1089,1774,1798]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">14)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C61FF83DE96F8AEFB62F2A0" blockId="8.[151,1436,1844,2015]" lastBlockId="9.[151,1437,151,753]" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="362" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C61FF82DE96F8AEFEE5F517" bold="true" box="[199,319,1844,1870]" pageId="8" pageNumber="361">Variation.</emphasis>
Anteclypeus and labrum yellowish brown; pronotum and sides of prothorax black; ventral surface of prothorax and mesoventrite black laterally, yellowish-brown on wide central area, except reddish brown anterior area of prosternum; central area of metaventrite with inverted V-shaped yellowish-brown macula, starting on metaventral process, reaching apex of ventrite, gradually darkened or not toward posterior third; anterior 2/3 of elytra dark yellowish brown on wide inner dorsal area, brown on remaining surface (slightly darker on posterior third); erect setae on pronotum somewhat abundant; erect setae on scutellum somewhat abundant, especially posteriorly; elytral pubescence somewhat abundant, but not obscuring integument; erect setae on elytra more abundant, especially on dorsal surface of anterior third; elytra almost reaching apex of abdominal segment II.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C60FF83DE96FE98FB04F33C" blockId="9.[151,1437,151,753]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DE96FE98FE78F345" bold="true" box="[199,418,258,284]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Dimensions (mm)</emphasis>
(
<typeStatus id="3B6D30AF6C60FF83DFE8FE99FDF9F344" box="[441,547,259,285]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Holotype</typeStatus>
male/ 
<typeStatus id="3B6D30AF6C60FF83DC20FE99FD06F344" box="[625,732,259,285]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">paratypes</typeStatus>
male). Total length, 10.55/7.25–10.60; prothoracic length, 1.80/1.20–1.75; anterior prothoracic width, 1.20/0.85–1.20; posterior prothoracic width, 1.65/1.10–1.70; maximum prothoracic width, 1.80/1.20–1.90; humeral width, 2.30/1.50–2.30; elytral length, 5.20/3.80–5.30.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ACCCDD866C60FF83DE96FEF5FF21F3AC" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C60FF83DE96FEF5FF21F3AC" blockId="9.[151,1437,151,753]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DE96FEF5FEACF3D1" bold="true" box="[199,374,366,393]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation id="54BE84506C60FF83DF2FFEF5FD9BF3F4" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3395996305" collectingDate="1986-07-06" collectingDateMax="1986-07-08" collectingDateMin="1986-07-06" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="J. E. Wappes" country="Mexico" location="Tuxtla Gutierrez" municipality="Sumidero Canyon" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Chiapas" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="3B6D30AF6C60FF83DF2FFEF5FE3CF3D0" box="[382,486,367,393]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry id="9CC1CE9D6C60FF83DC3DFEF5FD07F3D0" box="[620,733,367,393]" name="Mexico" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">MEXICO</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DCBBFEF5FC9DF3D0" box="[746,839,367,393]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">
<collectingRegion id="261240EF6C60FF83DCBBFEF5FC9DF3D0" box="[746,839,367,393]" country="Mexico" name="Chiapas" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Chiapas</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<collectingMunicipality id="040D14776C60FF83DD06FEF5FBFDF3D0" box="[855,1063,367,393]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Sumidero Canyon</collectingMunicipality>
, near 
<location id="E109D8D66C60FF83DA3AFEF5FAF2F3D0" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6C7F3F1B6C6FFF83DEC6FC34FBBAF0A8:E109D8D66C60FF83DA3AFEF5FAF2F3D0" box="[1131,1320,367,393]" country="Mexico" municipality="Sumidero Canyon" name="Tuxtla Gutierrez" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" stateProvince="Chiapas">Tuxtla Gutierrez</location>
, 4000’, 
<date id="9068A8CD6C60FF83DBD4FEF5FECEF3F4" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" value="1986-07-06" valueMax="1986-07-08" valueMin="1986-07-06">
<collectingDate id="802C51256C60FF83DBD4FEF5FECEF3F4" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" value="1986-07-06" valueMax="1986-07-08" valueMin="1986-07-06">6- 8.VII.1986</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="4923EBDB6C60FF83DF70FE09FE71F3F4" box="[289,427,403,429]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">J.E. Wappes</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode id="82C716C86C60FF83DFBDFE09FDE2F3F4" box="[492,568,403,429]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation id="54BE84506C60FF83DC1DFE09FC61F388" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3395996306" collectingDate="1987-06-14" collectingDateMax="1987-06-26" collectingDateMin="1987-06-14" collectionCode="FSCA, MZSP" collectorName="J. E. Wappes" country="Guatemala" location="San Jeronimo" municipality="Sumidero Canyon" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" specimenCount="2" specimenCount-male="2" stateProvince="Baja Verapaz" typeStatus="paratype">
<typeStatus id="3B6D30AF6C60FF83DC1DFE09FD63F3F4" box="[588,697,403,429]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Paratypes</typeStatus>
– 
<specimenCount id="F2D045846C60FF83DC86FE09FCEBF3F4" box="[727,817,403,429]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="male">2 males</specimenCount>
, same data as holotype, except 
<date id="9068A8CD6C60FF83DAC9FE09FAE7F3F4" box="[1176,1341,403,429]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" value="1987-06-14" valueMax="1987-06-26" valueMin="1987-06-14">
<collectingDate id="802C51256C60FF83DAC9FE09FAE7F3F4" box="[1176,1341,403,429]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" value="1987-06-14" valueMax="1987-06-26" valueMin="1987-06-14">14-26.VI.1987</collectingDate>
</date>
(
<collectionCode id="82C716C86C60FF83DB1CFE09FA42F3F4" box="[1357,1432,403,429]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
; 
<collectionCode id="82C716C86C60FF83DEC6FE2DFF3FF388" box="[151,229,439,465]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
). 
<collectingCountry id="9CC1CE9D6C60FF83DEADFE2DFE77F388" box="[252,429,439,465]" name="Guatemala" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">GUATEMALA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DFEDFE2DFD8CF389" box="[444,598,439,464]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">
<collectingRegion id="261240EF6C60FF83DFEDFE2DFD8CF389" box="[444,598,439,464]" country="Guatemala" name="Baja Verapaz" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Baja Verapaz</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<quantity id="232E23E86C60FF83DC38FE2CFD7DF388" box="[617,679,438,465]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="5.0" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" unit="km" value="5.0">5 km</quantity>
S 
<location id="E109D8D66C60FF83DC9DFE2DFCB6F388" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6C7F3F1B6C6FFF83DEC6FC34FBBAF0A8:E109D8D66C60FF83DC9DFE2DFCB6F388" box="[716,876,439,465]" country="Guatemala" name="San Jeronimo" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" stateProvince="Baja Verapaz">San Jerónimo</location>
, 4500
</materialsCitation>
’, 
<materialsCitation id="54BE84506C60FF83DD9EFE2DFF2DF3AC" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="3395996304" collectingDate="1989-05-24" collectingDateMax="1989-05-31" collectingDateMin="1989-05-24" collectionCode="MZSP" collectorName="J. E. Wappes" country="Guatemala" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" stateProvince="Baja Verapaz" typeStatus="paratype">
<specimenCount id="F2D045846C60FF83DD9EFE2DFBF8F388" box="[975,1058,439,465]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="male">1 male</specimenCount>
, 
<date id="9068A8CD6C60FF83DA60FE2DFB16F388" box="[1073,1228,439,465]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" value="1989-05-24" valueMax="1989-05-31" valueMin="1989-05-24">
<collectingDate id="802C51256C60FF83DA60FE2DFB16F388" box="[1073,1228,439,465]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" value="1989-05-24" valueMax="1989-05-31" valueMin="1989-05-24">24-31.V.1989</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="4923EBDB6C60FF83DA8AFE2DFAB2F388" box="[1243,1384,439,465]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">J.E. Wappes</collectorName>
leg. (
<collectionCode id="82C716C86C60FF83DECEFE41FF34F3AC" box="[159,238,475,501]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ACCCDD866C60FF83DE96FE65FA54F040" box="[199,1422,511,538]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C60FF83DE96FE65FA54F040" blockId="9.[151,1437,151,753]" box="[199,1422,511,538]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DE96FE65FE94F040" bold="true" box="[199,334,511,537]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Etymology.</emphasis>
The specific epithet is from Latin (mirabilis), which means “wonderful,” “remarkable amazing.”
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ACCCDD866C60FF83DE96FDB9FBBAF0A8" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="E4698E0D6C60FF83DE96FDB9FBBAF0A8" blockId="9.[151,1437,151,753]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DE96FDB9FEE1F064" bold="true" box="[199,315,547,573]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="23D6F58E6C60FF83DF13FDB9FDF8F064" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2021" box="[322,546,547,573]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oxycoleus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirabilis">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DF13FDB9FDF8F064" box="[322,546,547,573]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">Oxycoleus mirabilis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName id="23D6F58E6C60FF83DCE3FDB9FC08F064" authority="(Melzer, 1934)" baseAuthorityName="Melzer" baseAuthorityYear="1934" box="[690,978,547,573]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Merionoeda" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolor">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DCE3FDB9FCFFF064" box="[690,805,547,573]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">O. bicolor</emphasis>
(Melzer, 1934)
</taxonomicName>
and has been confused with it. However, it differs as follows: antennomeres V–XI distinctly modified; pro- and mesofemoral club not black; metafemoral club distinctly wider; tarsomeres mostly light. In 
<taxonomicName id="23D6F58E6C60FF83DCEEFDF1FCE9F0DC" baseAuthorityName="Melzer" baseAuthorityYear="1934" box="[703,819,619,645]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Merionoeda" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bicolor">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DCEEFDF1FCE9F0DC" box="[703,819,619,645]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">O. bicolor</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(see photograph of the 
<typeStatus id="3B6D30AF6C60FF83DA6DFDF1FB44F0DC" box="[1084,1182,619,645]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">holotype</typeStatus>
on 
<bibRefCitation id="8047F3FC6C60FF83DA99FDF1FABDF0DC" author="Bezark, L. G." box="[1224,1383,619,645]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" refId="ref11023" refString="Bezark, L. G. (2021 a) A photographic Catalog of the Cerambycidae of the World. New World Cerambycidae Catalog. Available from: http: // bezbycids. com / byciddb / wdefault. asp? w = n / (accessed 4 August 2021)" type="url" year="2021">Bezark 2021a</bibRefCitation>
), the antennomeres are not modified, pro- and mesofemoral club black, metafemoral club distinctly narrower, and the tarsomeres are dark. It is also somewhat similar to 
<taxonomicName id="23D6F58E6C60FF83DC83FD29FC24F094" authority="(Bates, 1885)" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1885" box="[722,1022,690,717]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oxycoleus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gratiosus">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DC83FD29FC87F095" box="[722,861,691,717]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">O. gratiosus</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation id="8047F3FC6C60FF83DD3DFD29FC2FF094" author="Bates, H. W." box="[876,1013,690,717]" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" refId="ref10969" refString="Bates, H. W. (1885) Supplement to Longicornia. In: Godman, F. D. &amp; Salvin, O. (Eds.), Biologia Centrali-Americana, Insecta, Coleoptera. Vol. 5. Taylor and Francis, London, pp. 249 - 436." type="book" year="1885">Bates, 1885</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
, especially by the shape of the metafemoral club, but differs by the antennomeres modified (not modified in 
<taxonomicName id="23D6F58E6C60FF83DD97FD4DFB8AF0A9" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1885" box="[966,1104,727,753]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Oxycoleus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="362" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gratiosus">
<emphasis id="D6A2521F6C60FF83DD97FD4DFB8AF0A9" box="[966,1104,727,753]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="362">O. gratiosus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>