<document id="D1454F4DDEF6AD4BED1018F14F2EF00B" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047590" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7F866CF9-58A6-4972-94FA-81F30B203CDD" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="6F58E5E349AA0B7762823E5A56C57DB8" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio limbi Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="7F866CF9-58A6-4972-94FA-81F30B203CDD" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="111" lastPageNumber="112" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" updateTime="1643687160130" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="F6771267C32A55D73907C1EAA19D6C32" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="4F71EA492F1BD161AE26155D7D07F936">
<mods:title id="EA2F707A06D8D36D3A3C088ACB861F37">Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="86EDBBC4F4F1DF1A963A9CABBA3A559C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F044321BF317C77622D86393BC44D142">
<mods:roleTerm id="B6DCC6E4783EB1EFCA98A5C7DEC588C1">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="6EC4EE236CD389D59AF9C3445607F7EF">Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="DF85A4B3CA8FDAB895ADE8AECC144207" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AC5D70A941F49E4353CF383ACC4267A3">
<mods:roleTerm id="967DF52FC1CE536D93E25F3FC55E772E">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0EDDD44933ED73C059AE454C167BEC6F">Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="79B65595061B7D02DCD318B8392C8E11" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9E7123A7C5A9B6E38EBFDE550835F7CB">
<mods:roleTerm id="00F4E26ABD743758A396C2E74E3A8871">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="118E6A6D37D1B67038F5604A55C22ED7">Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="D87483CD8EF377E248D11F379C88132B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="322C5A155985A6310DA78EBD0367A89E">
<mods:roleTerm id="D6E91336D79BAC97FCE24D6C782E7237">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3D103A0A16A85E02FA567BB34EC3B6AF">Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="588D94CE3F58F312B6CEE0F475F0DE67">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="BAD39A1D52F5D12642401491E25F2296" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="C6565A25F5FA86713063F86C11ABAED2">
<mods:title id="B376EBA4400557D98A3393BCF83E12AD">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="96AA6CAD98004287D21F5D1E86413137">
<mods:date id="B08C3A26468F69DAF4BCEE82D6627931">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="F4722B9989F293E399145CC7151A80E2" type="volume">
<mods:number id="755B5AE30F714FCC121CD0C879F1B416">331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1942E8736A77549E4CD9022E5D803883" unit="page">
<mods:start id="48DB752795EF1C2317590B9B7FE3FFD6">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F3197977F874C698B44437395B1D35F0">266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="E7AD3A1EEE52C1FA0EFBE6F9608FAE6E">
<mods:url id="A91BCEFFB35FC00C313EEB08EDE5B144">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="DAF88421826D732E94192D6DDE7C9FC5">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="98EA792008F938372C6F8F6163F530C6" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="DA33279B828411EE891656816D9DED5F" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B3DD48A5CB972E6835FF3A81D01C58DF" type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="6F58E5E349AA0B7762823E5A56C57DB8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047590" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7F866CF9-58A6-4972-94FA-81F30B203CDD" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6F58E5E349AA0B7762823E5A56C57DB8" lastPageId="111" lastPageNumber="112" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
<subSubSection id="D5175DD838F3961DCA58E72B752C55D7" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="89280340A59E7C6E72B83C837F92A9D2" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
<taxonomicName id="EF19449EE9D37A067F38BA440DA4B100" LSID="http://zoobank.org/7F866CF9-58A6-4972-94FA-81F30B203CDD" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio limbi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limbi">Oxyscelio limbi Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="4C6712A70E9E5C65E6D30CCD5B03CC22" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 159-164; Morphbank58
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="784AD1CA8530A6BC36C0886091138CCD" lastPageId="110" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="108" pageNumber="109" type="description">
<paragraph id="222AF113F355928CAA2F36D458EEFFDB" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5DF1DBF80F9A6222623AE1DD060359FF" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Female. Body length 9.1-11 mm (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E995FACC8DD513F011202EF86532488E" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Radicle color and shade: same as scape, both yellowish or reddish. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="541DDEAD1015F5EF3F8B751835A3C14D" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">Ventral clypeal margin: uniformly convex. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: hood-like, dorsally protruding. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: uniformly rounded dorsally. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, complete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2E5B7033889315129DFD9BAFBD079CD0" lastPageId="110" lastPageNumber="111" pageId="108" pageNumber="109">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: with a series of arched carinae, posterodorsal corner with weak longitudinal rugae. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed ante 
<pageBreakToken id="1A587E063196B5D6D778FFFC3C5AC86B" pageId="109" pageNumber="110" start="start">riorly</pageBreakToken>
, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: present as a vague, occasionally interrupted elevation. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; umbilicate fove 
<pageBreakToken id="CE724837804342D89A589DBD4A0A1CC0" pageId="110" pageNumber="111" start="start">ate</pageBreakToken>
. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent; punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: punctate. Mesoscutellar rim: expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally, smooth ventrally. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Postmarginal vein: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: not reaching base of T5. Coxae color brightness: same color as femora. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6133E57BB76C5E8DCC63F82B56A525D5" pageId="110" pageNumber="111">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: present. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: present and strongly protruding. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: present as strongly protruding acuminate flanges. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate; longitudinally striate; umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: with deep emargination that is V-shaped medially, separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: present, very broadly rounded, with rounded apices. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: present, posteriorly complete. S6 apex in relation to T6: exposed to dorsal view by T6 emargination. S6 apex: truncate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="72D89F31FF4905051F07804DE0E769C4" pageId="110" pageNumber="111">Male. Body length 4.3-4.75 mm (n=14). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: longer than broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate; transversely rugose. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: punctate. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching middle of T5. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 5. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: present as sharp corners that do not protrude. T6 metasomal flanges: present, rounded and lobe-like. T7: M-shaped, with a triangular median emargination.</paragraph>
<caption id="098DA13C2729EAC578D8759E1E4AFB05" pageId="110" pageNumber="111">
<paragraph id="355E9ABB761C85B4E92F7E091D03633D" pageId="110" pageNumber="111">
Figures 159-164. 
<taxonomicName id="D0DC2C862F886D211B15723AA47833B2" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio limbi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="110" pageNumber="111" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limbi">Oxyscelio limbi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype female (OSUC 436019) 159 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 160 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 161 Head, anterior view 162 Metasoma, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 376694) 163 Antenna 164 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank58
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F374428DB0B7FDD37C4C1B3A5926C846" lastPageId="111" lastPageNumber="112" pageId="110" pageNumber="111" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="EA7BB5004C5A6F378D97DE6DE8FA0A0B" pageId="110" pageNumber="111">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CDF0CE5548FDC69B113A94DA45263E6C" lastPageId="111" lastPageNumber="112" pageId="110" pageNumber="111">
Both sexes: Frontal depression deep, all carinae complete medially; no carinae present above dorsal separator, submedian carina sharp. Hyperoccipital carina absent. Occipital carina complete, medially weakly convex. Mesoscutellar rim expanded and strongly sculptured, without median notch. Metascutellum scoop-like, projecting dorsally. Coxa same color as rest of leg. Postmarginal vein absent. Female: A3 longer than pedicel. A5, A6 broader than long. T4, T5, T6 with broad, flat metasomal 
<pageBreakToken id="05EE9317A77155820CA00AC82E5D2FE9" pageId="111" pageNumber="112" start="start">flanges</pageBreakToken>
. T6 apically broadly and deeply emarginate, angularly emarginate medially. S6 exposed to dorsal view, truncate apically. Male: A3 longer than broad. A4 broader than long, A11 as long or longer than broad. Mesoscutellum and mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly with small foveae, mesoscutellum with smooth area medially. T5, T6 with metasomal flanges. T7 with long postero-lateral lobes, deeply emarginate medially, posterior margin M-shaped.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="55D9E8929629B00AD244E4B4988F3D67" pageId="111" pageNumber="112" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="4233F751B689486388C4E697AB171D13" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E634666D99311C5FE42BDA7D62515FD9" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken id="498D598BE1FDBD2CF310486C31768690" originalValue="“rim.”">&quot;rim.&quot;</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8E064CB0163022140671937B17B70271" pageId="111" pageNumber="112" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph id="AAC8F49366366092BC2CC9EB75639900" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F52FD00621B3E1AA8A7ACE079A0CE249" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=307086]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D3EF39118AECE9D043144DD27275CF77" pageId="111" pageNumber="112" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="5AC9DC4FC806230913A2AB578D4F4D78" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="775AEA2DF202A7F3453EA03EEE945CED" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">
Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: NSW, Fowlers Gap Research Station, 
<geoCoordinate id="A313B0DFA4019D120F1B0469DED27497" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="-31.083334">31°05'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="E6AF4352720ECE61E15D588D53ED7ACD" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="141.7">141°42'E</geoCoordinate>
, 29.
<normalizedToken id="DD2E5623DC549D0681D16D03D1A85E13" originalValue="XI–">XI-</normalizedToken>
2.XII.1981, J. C. Cardale, OSUC 436000 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 39 females, 14 males, Australian Museum K256282 (AMSA); OSUC 435995-435999, 436001-436003, 436009, 436011-436022, 436024-436029, 445337 (ANIC); OSUC 376685-376700, 376735 (MCZC); OSUC 436004, 436007 (MVMA); OSUC 448604 (QPIM); OSUC 436005 (UQIC); OSUC 449097-449099 (WINC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9DDE5A3DC38F3CFCAFA6078A36D6F2DE" pageId="111" pageNumber="112" type="comments">
<paragraph id="3B234FA82BB09D9E46402206FA90C4A1" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FE3DF885C27A719019F1D87E31066450" pageId="111" pageNumber="112">
<taxonomicName id="335A98B77B6F9C7C4AC0F0B8558C6854" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio limbi" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="111" pageNumber="112" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="limbi">Oxyscelio limbi</taxonomicName>
exhibits a variably expanded and sculptured mesoscutellar rim. This may be difficult to assess in some specimens, but identification can be verified using other discussed features.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>