<document id="A32283F526E9E40C2797F650EB2C81B9" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.104.763" ID-GBIF-Dataset="49714d8e-3fa4-4927-a6e0-49ca815a45e2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152029617" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-104-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-104-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 104" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the Phyllognathopodidae (Copepoda, Harpacticoida): re-examination of Phyllognathopus viguieri (Maupas, 1892) and Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi Dumont and Maas, 1988, proposal of a new genus for hyllognathopus bassoti Rouch, 1972, and description of a new species of Phyllognathopus" checkinTime="1451250324985" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Galassi, Diana M. P., Laurentiis, Paola De &amp; Fiasca, Barbara" docDate="2011" docId="76948213A95A9CEC09A9E69191E6E0F8" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 104: 1-65" docOrigin="ZooKeys 104" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.104.763" docTitle="Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi Dumont and Maas 1988" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" masterDocId="FFEEFFC87E57C968B742FF93CF11FF92" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the Phyllognathopodidae (Copepoda, Harpacticoida): re-examination of Phyllognathopus viguieri (Maupas, 1892) and Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi Dumont and Maas, 1988, proposal of a new genus for hyllognathopus bassoti Rouch, 1972, and description of a new species of Phyllognathopus" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" updateTime="1643550626762" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="2EBEC5CB831BA58B91399703E59DB1D3" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="B93E7FF9D104A9C6B705AE4D66247465">
<mods:title id="2DDB3522A1C1259DDA3F7FE16030EF53">Systematics of the Phyllognathopodidae (Copepoda, Harpacticoida): re-examination of Phyllognathopus viguieri (Maupas, 1892) and Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi Dumont and Maas, 1988, proposal of a new genus for hyllognathopus bassoti Rouch, 1972, and description of a new species of Phyllognathopus</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="8BFD3275E954EBF50E9A6659E938B1A5" type="personal">
<mods:role id="7C2450E076BB890217D86C80EFA7336E">
<mods:roleTerm id="B83490E89942716C7E9C154A68B3178C">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="AC45737B302BFFB1D7C4E41190BE48BE">Galassi, Diana M. P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="0A6D9C92CDD5A64E9A25B590146F6DE1" type="personal">
<mods:role id="86CAFBF1868C661B4840C0AE30B10FE5">
<mods:roleTerm id="967A36FB19F0EBB0841F0E5F13E5A19B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C9A62EF7D6A8FB87062E295AE3D76443">Laurentiis, Paola De</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="4374A8B2AC576B1E3718D9F676D97849" type="personal">
<mods:role id="BC28970BA4F2AD11DE4E32B7CABA081B">
<mods:roleTerm id="2093CF4BED4A852DCB4BB57FC75F2CBB">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="F223D81629A6EDED5F5666FDD8B5B90F">Fiasca, Barbara</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7DBB42F941B486222DBC26E72FC38D1D">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="F1A0EF9B49C1A42A18573CF06E2CF5D9" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="27C649B28FAFA0D1B72063E8EC3D4034">
<mods:title id="D06CCF0567B8D33077678B9FB075CCE5">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D16D68A5CCC42C5D47B6BD5FD69B986B">
<mods:date id="EDA54DA8E7025B2C4BB44CC7D2A6415E">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="B9164A0497FA8B68D9255EBDB82AAFAF" type="volume">
<mods:number id="41EDBBF37BCEC61E58AFCC0C8C965D70">104</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="F9BEE879CBAD191DA0000FB7EF56C305" unit="page">
<mods:start id="03A10DCF0BC42D880AEEB5F5A23429A2">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="16603A72A280C3FBBF7E1E22219DB164">65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="BFD6622A789F70BA6AA7CB6614064629">
<mods:url id="56F72A5775F1E70837DADCA89AB0D1FE">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.104.763</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="F4637CC3FAB9867A4EFD91858FAF103B">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="6F9036D9F383FF09E1F648899E0D9582" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.104.763</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="47E9EB8B5B41EAF70C71D60E07F07730" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-104-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="6747F223C9EB0B17250A452F6DA6B58E" type="ZooBank">1530C44D-6543-4E0C-A046-F235105E5EEF</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="76948213A95A9CEC09A9E69191E6E0F8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152029617" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:76948213A95A9CEC09A9E69191E6E0F8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/76948213A95A9CEC09A9E69191E6E0F8" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<subSubSection id="7613DB6468F0D187FA6A35596013FF6F" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="8390DFD6B1A97EDF82D546E3D29F9F5E" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<taxonomicName id="8A05CCC835C9B6EDF013DDADDAD721E6" LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Parbatocamptus_jochenmartensi" authority="Dumont and Maas, 1988" authorityName="Dumont and Maas" authorityYear="1988" class="Hexanauplia" family="Phyllognathopodidae" genus="Parbatocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jochenmartensi">Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi Dumont and Maas, 1988</taxonomicName>
Figs 14-16
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="115BEB7039E48D37705E74D63AA06CAF" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="CD634B575B833D548037972230F0D95C" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="29D0F5DAC4AD9BB499ECE64F9B3E62B8" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">♂ holotype, completely dissected and mounted on slide labeled SMF 14657, deposited at the Senckenberg Museum (Germany).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ADA7EB2E39CE64B501F252A08C2569D1" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="emended diagnosis of the genus parbatocamptus dumont and maas, 1988">
<paragraph id="08159607316A1824E5A4B26805D40031" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Emended diagnosis of the genus 
<taxonomicName id="8C8EAF1E367C0107A33CC5F5CBE56CB2" class="Hexanauplia" family="Phyllognathopodidae" genus="Parbatocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parbatocamptus" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Parbatocamptus</taxonomicName>
Dumont and Maas, 1988.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="27DA44C2DF0A0EC7353C4E119BE9D833" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<taxonomicName id="F3121388CBEB7CA186400214E1A5BF0F" family="Phyllognathopodidae" lsidName="" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" rank="family">Phyllognathopodidae</taxonomicName>
. Body flattened. First pedigerous somite free. Hyaline frills of abdominal somites ventrally smooth. Anal operculum prominent, subdistally crenulated. Caudal ramus subquadrate in ventral view, tapering on free distal margin in dorsal view, with 6 setae; anterolateral accessory seta (I) absent; dorsal seta inserted on spinulose protuberance closely located to free distal margin. Male antennule 10-segmented, with geniculation between segments 7 and 8; segment 9 distinct, as usual in the family; tube-pores on segments 1 and 2; aesthetascs on segments 5 and 10. Antenna: exopod 1-segmented, well-defined at base, bearing 3 lateral and 2 apical unipinnate setae; free endopod 2-segmented; both segments robust, of about the same length. Mandibular 
<pageBreakToken id="C99A9D0266C08473B25A728D3C0E047C" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" start="start">palp</pageBreakToken>
biramous; basis with inner long bipinnate seta; exopod with 2 setae; endopod with 2 apical geniculate setae; 1 inner and 1 subapical bipinnate setae. Maxillary syncoxa with 3 endites. Proximal endite quadrilobate, with 6 apical setae; medial and distal endites, each with 3 setae. Allobasis drawn out into a strong claw, accompanied by 1 curved and 2 normal setae; endopod 3-segmented; segment 1 with 1 robust curved seta; segment 2 with 2 robust curved setae; segment 3 with 2 robust curved and 2 slender setae. Maxilliped phyllopodial, lamelliform, 1-segmented. Clear trace of ancestral 2-segmented condition well discernible and marked by outer and inner incisions; armature consisting of 11 elements: 1 strong spine inserted on inner corner of former proximal segment; 4 spines and 6 setae along free distal margin of former second segment, two of which inserted on independent little knob. P1-P2 with 3-segmented exopods and endopods. P3-P4 with 3-segmented exopods and 2-segmented endopods. P1-P4 praecoxa present. P1 exp-1 long, about as long as exp-2 and -3 together. P1-P4 endopods distinctly shorter than exopods, not overreaching distal margin of exp-2. P2 enp-2 transformed: outer margin produced into a comb-like structure; P2 enp-3 with 1 apical strong curved spine and 1 apical seta. P5 with 2-segmented exopod; endopod incorporated to basis, forming a baseoendopod; suture line still observable on posterior surface; rudimentary intercoxal sclerite still discernible. P6 symmetrical, consisting of a well developed, deeply incised lamella, marking original division between left and right legs. Armature consisting of 1 outer seta and 2 inner short spines of different length.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="870AA996532299DC7AC9257E67E8C4A9" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Female unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D2082262C808EAAC713B792B652B42C5" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" type="supplementary description of the holotype">
<paragraph id="991C7035465921AE9F6F1A7EEC0D8FCA" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Supplementary description of the holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A673CC9F61B7A8C1B05D1C0186C9C721" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">The description deals with major morphological details, omitted or overlooked in the original description, and with improvements of observational errors.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EF9C32109081E744DFC0FA64E517FE21" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Integumental pitting not detectable on the dissected holotype; integument well sclerotized.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8632D810380039E135281BA33E5A4354" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">Urosomites 3-5 with smooth hyaline frills ventrally (Fig. 14A); third and fourth urosomites with spinular fringe closely located to hyaline frill; fifth urosomite with surface spinule rows ventrally, anal somite with distal continuous spinule row. Other ornamentation as in Fig. 14A. Urosomites 3-5 with crenulated hyaline frills dorsally. Indented surface rows are observable on third, fourth and fifth urosomites dorsally (Fig. 14B). Anal somite with row of fine spinules on proximal third; spinule row at the insertion of each caudal ramus; paired dorsal sensilla. Anal operculum slightly protruding the insertion line of caudal rami, subdistally crenulated (Fig. 14B).</paragraph>
<caption id="4E7F688769D2A09ACF6B95B9D77D4A9D" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<paragraph id="E1115B1E0781603B459B49E30188A32C" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
Figure 14. 
<taxonomicName id="3C4223AD415214156267A18225EA9445" class="Hexanauplia" family="Phyllognathopodidae" genus="Parbatocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jochenmartensi">Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi</taxonomicName>
Dumont and Maas, 1988 (♂). A abdomen, ventral view B abdomen, dorsal view C antennule D antennule, detail of segments 5-7 (scale bars in 
<normalizedToken id="98BEC7E5EE37FE01D55C9E4EFC11D89E" originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="2AB820C2A54AED13BEF27985B576FDDF" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="13" pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
Caudal rami ventrally subquadrate, parallel, longer than wide (length/width ratio: about 1.4), with incomplete setal pattern (6 setae) (Fig. 14
<normalizedToken id="9ED3255C222989223C8D07D5E8F54F9C" originalValue="A–B">A-B</normalizedToken>
). Anterolateral accessory seta (I) absent, anterolateral seta (II) unipinnate, inserted at second third of caudal ramus; posterolateral seta (III) inserted in subdistal position, transformed in spiniform bifid seta. Outer terminal seta (IV) well developed, unipinnate, with articulation at base; inner terminal seta (V) bipinnate and long; terminal accessory seta (VI) thin and naked, about as long as posterolateral seta; dorsal seta (VII) inserted on a spinulose knob, close to free distal margin of caudal ramus, distinctly longer than caudal ramu 
<pageBreakToken id="83D2773C33601B1F022109720F10DA12" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" start="start">s</pageBreakToken>
. A spinule row on proximal third of each caudal ramus dorsally; three spinule rows inserted ventrolaterally and one spinule row at distal margin of caudal ramus, ventrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AB1447FA2BEB9DE0C956D2FBB3143C60" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Antennule (Fig. 14C): 10-segmented. Segment 1 with spinule row and tube-pore. Segment 2 with tube-pore. Segment 4 represented by small U-shaped sclerite. Segment 5 large, sclerotized (Fig. 14D). Segment 8 very large and transformed, moderately sclerotized, segment 9 short, discrete, segment 10 derived by complete fusion of former segments 10 and 11. Armature formula: 1-[1], 2-[9], 3-[8], 4-[2], 5-[5?+(1 + ae)], 6-[2], 7-[2], 8-[0], 9-[1], 10-[10 + (1 + ae)].</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F379EC988D3EF9C27FA5E72A586EEBC9" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Antenna (Fig. 15A): coxa unarmed; basis with 1 transverse spinule row on surface, a spinule row inserted on apical inner margin; exopod 1-segmented, well-defined at base, bearing 3 lateral and 2 apical unipinnate setae; free endopod 2-segmented; both segments robust, of about the same length; segment 1 naked; segment 2 with one inner spinule row, armature consisting of 2 inner spines and 1 seta, 1 apical unipinnate spine, 4 geniculate setae, 1 apical slender seta and 1 subapical tiny seta; a row of spinules at outer corner.</paragraph>
<caption id="CBC42849757C8E62A87F0E20B863F4BD" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
<paragraph id="D8C479C0DD9C8B3D62C69E6D2618CFD8" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">
Figure 15. 
<taxonomicName id="6284FB2C62A6BFC0296410F246C0FA78" class="Hexanauplia" family="Phyllognathopodidae" genus="Parbatocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jochenmartensi">Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi</taxonomicName>
Dumont and Maas, 1988 (♂). A antenna B mandible C maxilla D maxilliped E P1 (scale bars in 
<normalizedToken id="119462BBD5D5E542C92E0DAE496DFF52" originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="B9757D4C121FC3A316489E617F871E2A" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Mandible (Fig. 15B): coxal gnathobase elongate, cutting edge with 2 large and coarse teeth, three smaller teeth and row of tiny teeth; naked seta at dorsal corner. Mandibular palp biramous, basis with inner long bipinnate seta and spinule row, exopod with 2 bipinnate setae; endopod with 2 apical geniculate setae, 1 inner and 1 subapical bipinnate setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7890CA956EAD349F2CE3734AEE2F23E1" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Maxillule not observable.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C9623F6A21EE0672710E47C3015DD008" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Maxilla (Fig. 15C): syncoxa with 3 endites fully incorporated to syncoxa. Proximal endite quadrilobate, with 6 setae; the first two distal lobes each bearing 2 setae; the proximal ones, each with 1 plumose seta; medial and distal endites, each with 3 bipinnate setae. Allobasis drawn out into a strong claw, distally spinulose, accompanied by 1 robust and curved seta and 2 naked setae, respectively; endopod 3-segmented; segment 1 with 1 robust curved seta; segment 2 with 2 robust curved setae; segment 3 with 2 curved and 2 slender setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0F162469107E223DCF6D679905A3C46D" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">Maxilliped (Fig. 15D): phyllopodial, lamelliform, 1-segmented. Clear trace of ancestral 2-segmented condition marked by the presence of both outer and inner incisions. Armature consisting of 11 elements: 1 strong spine inserted at inner corner of former segment 1; 4 strong unipinnate spines along inner margin, 1 bipinnate seta inserted along inner margin and 5 bipinnate setae in apical position.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9D6977D1C53BD22F1C3F78233C3304EF" pageId="12" pageNumber="13">P1-P2 with 3-segmented exopods and endopods. P3-P4 with 3-segmented exopods and 2-segmented endopods. P1-P4 praecoxa well developed. P1 (Fig. 15E): praecoxa and coxa with outer spinule row on anterior surface; one posterior row of thin spinules inserted on coxo-basis boundary. Basis with 1 outer spiniform seta and 1 inner spine, with spinule rows along outer margin, between exopod and endopod and at the insertion of inner spine, respectively. Endopod distinctly shorter than exopod, reaching about distal third of exp-2; exp-1 long, about as long as exp-2 and -3 together; exp-1 and -2 with 1 outer spine; exp-3 with 2 outer curved, unipinnate spines, and 1 apical and 1 subapical geniculate setae. Endopod: enp-1 unarmed, about as long as enp-2 and enp-3, wider than enp-2 and enp-3. Enp-2 cylindrical, unarmed. Enp-3 with 1 inner long seta, and 2 apical geniculate setae of different length. Ornamentation as in Fig. 15E.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="609C12F368B4B68BADAB889E504D5C14" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<pageBreakToken id="9B5258C1B9CE40FE56733A21405F3C67" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" start="start">P</pageBreakToken>
2 (Fig. 16A): praecoxa unornamented, coxa as in P1 and P2. Basis with 1 outer spiniform seta, with spinule rows along outer margin. Exopod distinctly longer than endopod; endopod reaching about the proximal half of exopodal segment 2; exopodal segments of about the same length; exp-1 and -2 with 1 outer spine; exp-3 with 2 outer unipinnate spines, 1 apical fringed seta and 1 subapical long and slender seta. Endopod: enp-1 unarmed; enp 2 transformed, with outer strong comb-like process; enp-3 with 1 transformed spine and 1 long slender and naked seta in apical position. Ornamentation as in Fig. 16A.
</paragraph>
<caption id="1F6ADA65BCA2F349C62D0C240FDEFBAB" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<paragraph id="A6C19EFA148BDE3F93DD1AA1D6C484E6" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
Figure 16. 
<taxonomicName id="30F6FB4D3E631E1B7812DABB03D8DE3C" class="Hexanauplia" family="Phyllognathopodidae" genus="Parbatocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jochenmartensi">Parbatocamptus jochenmartensi</taxonomicName>
Dumont and Maas, 1988 (♂). A P2 B P3 C P4 D P5 E P6 (scale bars in 
<normalizedToken id="86004FF36D4C80BB0D2B729517041890" originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="8B1726B8200151237B72A30BE6961FA0" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">P3 (Fig. 16B): praecoxa unornamented; ornamentation of coxa as in P1 and P2. Basis with long outer plumose seta and spinule rows along outer margin and at the insertion of the endopod. Exopod distinctly longer than endopod; endopod reaching about half of exp-2. Exp-1 and -2 with 1 outer spine; exp-3 with 2 outer fringed spines, 1 apical unipinnate seta and 1 subapical long and naked seta. Endopod: enp-1 unarmed; enp-2 with 2 apical spinulose setae and 1 subapical thin and naked seta. Ornamentation as in Fig. 16B.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="664BFA10A1DE45A81EB30C70D5D6B75E" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">P4 (Fig. 16C): slightly smaller than the other swimming legs, praecoxa present, unornamented; coxa with outer spinule row, one posterior row of thin spinules inserted on coxo-basis boundary; basis with outer plumose seta, and spinule rows along outer margin and at the insertion of endopod; exopod distinctly longer than endopod. Exp-1 and -2 with 1 outer bipinnate spine; exp-3 with 2 outer unipinnate spines and 2 apical bipinnate setae of different length. Endopod: enp-1 unarmed; enp-2 with 1 spine and 1 seta in apical position, and 1 subapical short unipinnate seta. Ornamentation as in Fig. 16C.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A26585AA47F35C4DC117788088261969" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">P5 (Fig. 16D): free, with clear articulation to P5-bearing somite; right and left legs distinct, trace of intercoxal sclerite present but hardly observable, with coxo-basis protrusions; exopod discrete, 2-segmented, segment 1 with 1 outer spine and 1 inner seta distally fringed; segment 2 with 4 elements: 1 outer slender and naked seta, 1 apical long spine, 1 medial short spine and 1 short seta distally crested; endopod incorporated to basis forming a baseoendopod, trace of original segmentation still recognizable on posterior surface (Fig. 16D); rudimentary endopod 1-segmented, bearing 1 strong spiniform element, crested on its distal margin. Basipodal outer seta slender and naked.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B1776B68FED15BB2CA4B4A8772D33694" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">P6 (Fig. 16E): well developed, symmetrical, right and left legs distinct, deep medial incision marking boundary between legs; armature consisting of 1 outer long, bipinnate seta and two inner short spines, the innermost the shortest.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>