<document id="BE48CBCD0C5356A60D4ED0C36CFCBC9F" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6ecd52bf-ea5e-4a9a-8ab6-baa91b99ea58" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648956" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-685-15" ID-ZBK="DF60153C7D8F448C9274CFF507523092" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:15D6AFA7-B148-4474-B348-C7F011A0D3E7" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-685-15" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 685" ModsDocTitle="Three new species of Heteromysis (Mysida, Mysidae, Heteromysini) from the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, with first documentation of a mysid-cephalopod association" checkinTime="1502744508259" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Wittmann, Karl J. &amp; Griffiths, Charles L." docDate="2017" docId="83714F8F80AE71C7D0CC23C5D1F9BA92" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 685: 15-47" docOrigin="ZooKeys 685" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890" docTitle="Heteromysis (Heteromysis) fosteri Wittmann &amp; Griffiths, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="15D6AFA7-B148-4474-B348-C7F011A0D3E7" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="25" masterDocId="FFC0FFF4EE471008870FFFE18748FFC7" masterDocTitle="Three new species of Heteromysis (Mysida, Mysidae, Heteromysini) from the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, with first documentation of a mysid-cephalopod association" masterLastPageNumber="47" masterPageNumber="15" pageId="6" pageNumber="21" updateTime="1643572060749" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="9F27DA4BBC3CFEBBE17F4D05E0C4301F" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="915A5DDE3C01F939BAA9824F233B6AC9">
<mods:title id="EE1EAEDE8E9455E9005DC0747C62BF07">Three new species of Heteromysis (Mysida, Mysidae, Heteromysini) from the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, with first documentation of a mysid-cephalopod association</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="626E4283D763314C539997BD7BD4D08E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B93C756787D13E721345CE4D8B33A360">
<mods:roleTerm id="5A8AD7B529D23269250B3573F0F26010">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C7B0B727549AF75AF5CDDBA82EF94DF7">Wittmann, Karl J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="F7712FC15DF2BF67A23DFBCE43E9DDDD" type="personal">
<mods:role id="12E8C793EACFDFABA5CD020C19389E93">
<mods:roleTerm id="AF11C8987553287F2542403D2E3FE0C9">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="43BFE0F794A6437D2242446947F4609A">Griffiths, Charles L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="25EB9556137B2DF32CC9C0E443654CD1">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="923B9B572023C81A951499B77B736127" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="5592007C26C00ED0092C20B601998312">
<mods:title id="9E4C9B0D924FDB84888A2A71A8624748">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="60DF298C7C6FE0F64D6C43D223C16A4C">
<mods:date id="1F7D60BFE1FB80AFA78B86B6B89450E3">2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="284C2E036966BC97971721E10FFF60CC" type="volume">
<mods:number id="35BFD6D79C84CCBECFCEAF5162026699">685</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="993CCCA6F2E8324C807590D159BCE3FD" unit="page">
<mods:start id="3F107B0D8F7F6B55D916A2571B06E98D">15</mods:start>
<mods:end id="43A5EAB3386C077F68793A3A12AFC709">47</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="C162B41BB772D562B172DDB83227BCD6">
<mods:url id="D2A0A6AB1C1C0EC2F104FF5F10BFA619">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="7EAB64A01702CEC2E09F42FE417F34DF">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="7845137A414F33757D1D1F3C1CFABAE4" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.685.13890</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="6458E0894D697354BA3FCAC85BC435D5" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-685-15</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="41A78D36F5ADE4354FAFCED2D1F05160" type="ZBK">DF60153C7D8F448C9274CFF507523092</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E82192CBF643A254E7B77D90C290E5C8" type="ZooBank">DF60153C7D8F448C9274CFF507523092</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="83714F8F80AE71C7D0CC23C5D1F9BA92" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648956" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:15D6AFA7-B148-4474-B348-C7F011A0D3E7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/83714F8F80AE71C7D0CC23C5D1F9BA92" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
<subSubSection id="044F375995B8EDC95D88E51FCBFFBE79" pageId="6" pageNumber="21" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="65D83C9FA44BF80760E6A1B718704902" pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
<taxonomicName id="E4ED026992BF15B7966F06EC80DB0DF4" LSID="http://zoobank.org/15D6AFA7-B148-4474-B348-C7F011A0D3E7" authority="Wittmann &amp; Griffiths" class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis (Heteromysis) fosteri" order="Mysida" pageId="6" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fosteri" subGenus="Heteromysis">
<pageBreakToken id="9BEE5C501F578350F01C1831F0C98A51" pageId="6" pageNumber="21" start="start">Heteromysis</pageBreakToken>
(Heteromysis) fosteri Wittmann &amp; Griffiths
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="0EF9E99A9E5065274EF204E45C93042C" pageId="6" pageNumber="21">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 6A, 7, 8
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F54F68BA1C541F6BC374C9FA2FE375DF" pageId="7" pageNumber="22" type="type series">
<paragraph id="29DF505EF7CEF54A2DF08A0A422454C8" pageId="7" pageNumber="22">
<pageBreakToken id="11CB8CFFFCBA66C265CCC192B60FDEAC" pageId="7" pageNumber="22" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
series.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F5254565967CBF05D188929031C6E484" pageId="7" pageNumber="22">
Holotype, adult male with 6.7 mm body length, in vial at NHMW-25905; paratypes adult female 7.0 mm, adult male 6.6 mm, 2 subadult males 3.6, 4.6 mm in vial at SAM-MB-A067551; dissected paratypes on slides at NHMW-25906: adult female 8.0 mm, subadult female 5.9 mm, adult male 6.0 mm; sublittoral marine coastal waters, 
<normalizedToken id="32FCF37B2DFA2A9B62415A0C8596A500" originalValue="Miller’s">Miller's</normalizedToken>
Point, on the False Bay coastline of the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, 
<geoCoordinate id="B767F9A82AE281AE69F1998A757E042F" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-34.229668">34°13.78'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="5711A0734FF1F3297C0AE9EAB3393410" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="18.4745">18°28.47'E</geoCoordinate>
, 5 m depth; extracted from empty urchin and gastropod shells without hermit crabs, 25 Jan. 2017, leg. Craig Foster.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9AF041C710C6A69E3DF773D750AB4C57" pageId="7" pageNumber="22" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="EFDB7A56585A510FF98C5B88DB49267F" pageId="7" pageNumber="22">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D049346ACDBD0FAF838434613755F0A7" pageId="7" pageNumber="22">
Carapace produced into well-projecting, triangular rostrum with narrow rounded apex. Eyes well developed; cornea occupies 35-50% of eye surface; eyestalks with inconspicuous, distally-directed, blunt extension of (obliquely anterior facing) inner margin. Antennular trunk with a number of smooth and barbed setae, but no particularly modified setae; inner distal corner of its terminal segment with anteriorly directed apophysis carrying two large, smooth setae. Antennal scale stout, extending to 0-10% below tip of antennular trunk; outer margin convex. First thoracic sternite with anteriorly-projecting, terminally-rounded median lobe; sternites 2-8 without lobes in both sexes. Carpopropodus of thoracic endopods 1-8 with 2, 2, 2, 3, 6, 6, 6, or 5-6 segments, respectively. Third thoracic endopod weakly dimorphic, without any spines or spine-like setae; carpus not swollen in female, slightly swollen in male (with respect to merus). Carpus of third thoracic endopod with series of three subbasally toothed setae (i.e. with modified barbs) near outer margin. Carpopropodus of fourth thoracic endopod with series of 2-3 subbasally toothed setae near outer margin; no such modified setae in endopods 5-8. Penes long and slender, twice length of merus of eighth thoracic endopod; tip with three rounded lobes, each wider than long. Pleopods reduced to small setose, bilobate plates, without any spines in both sexes. Exopods of uropods extend distinctly beyond endopods. Endopods with only one spine on inner margin, in subbasal position near statocyst. Telson subtriangular, terminally truncate; lateral margins weakly-sigmoid, along their distal 83-93% furnished with slightly discontinuous series of 17-20 spines each. Telson with apical cleft forming proximally poorly rounded 
<normalizedToken id="1D0A942799159ACB00B6139FC74864BA" originalValue="‘V’">'V'</normalizedToken>
. This cleft slightly deeper than wide, its depth 14-18% telson length. Cleft densely furnished with 16-24 acute laminae all along its margins. Two latero-apical lobes of telson show narrow, transverse apical margins, each bearing a large latero-apical spine plus much smaller medio-apical spine.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C9FE659EEF3789EFE087C067F8680F18" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="24" pageId="7" pageNumber="22" type="description">
<paragraph id="9705DBB0C318DFFA1A9DA9C2ADD3CC5F" pageId="7" pageNumber="22">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="462313D9BFE9B2408434F3F1BC8376DA" pageId="7" pageNumber="22">
As described above for 
<taxonomicName id="98A0E02E5C38533AF8FB7795B1052CFE" genus="H." lsidName="H. cancelli" pageId="7" pageNumber="22" rank="species" species="cancelli">H. cancelli</taxonomicName>
sp. n. unless stated otherwise in the following. Cephalothorax comprises 41-44% of body length without telson, pleon 56-59%, and carapace 30-38%, when measured along dorsal median line. First thoracic sternite with median lobe showing a smooth, rounded apex. Terminal margin of sixth pleonite with lateral shields more evenly rounded in females (Fig. 7L) versus males (Fig. 7K).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D42F8940D66A2EA2B5F09F7643871AF2" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
<pageBreakToken id="89051D44FC986D4C62A9D1C177A74F49" pageId="8" pageNumber="23" start="start">Carapace</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 6A, 7A). Non-dimorphic, antero-lateral edges evenly rounded. Anterior pore group with 25-34 pores, in strongly flattened 
<normalizedToken id="1E50B8F99F255A318FDCB6584B51CD53" originalValue="‘U’">'U'</normalizedToken>
-shaped arrangement. Posterior pore group with 12-16 pores.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C87CB7F1B22730ACB96FEEE2910F1ECD" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Eyes (Figs 6A, 7A). Anterior, basal, and posterior margins of eyestalks densely covered by scales. Ocular symphysis with broadly-rounded, smooth, subrostral process (dashed line in Fig. 7A).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A10DB83B83F519D22811EFEB6A3D1382" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Antennulae (Fig. 7A, B). Basal segment 41-48% the length of trunk, middle 14-18% and terminal segment 37-43%, when measured along dorsal midline of trunk. Trunk stouter in males, with basal segment 1.1-1.2 times longer than broad, compared to 1.3 times in females. Basal segment with three barbed and one smooth seta at its dorsal apophysis; four plumose setae at tip of outer ventral lobe (exite). Anterior margin of median segment dorsally with a smooth seta and larger barbed seta; and more laterally another smooth seta together with three barbed setae in both sexes. Two small barbed setae antero-ventrally near outer margin, visualized by dashed lines in Fig. 7B. Anterior margin of terminal segment in about median position with a lobe bearing 3-4 medium-sized barbed setae plus a dense series of short bristles. Only females with additional, large plumose setae on terminal segment of trunk, one inserting ventrally half-way near inner margin, the second, forward directed in Fig. 7A, on the ventral surface proximally from the inner flagellum at about 9-19% segment length from anterior margin of terminal segment. Outer antennular flagellum 1.5-1.7 times as thick as inner flagellum, when measured near basis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8F5F5401D7992BC004C71FC37B596F02" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Antennae (Fig. 7A). Length of antennal scale 2.7-3.0 times its maximum width. Basal segment 24-29% length of peduncle, second 33-39% and third 34-38%.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2B36F18A9C52D35AE234AF0D515A70E1" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Mouth parts (not figured). Pars incisivus of mandibles with 3-4 large teeth, and digitus mobilis with 3-4 large plus 1-3 small teeth. Pars centralis with 4-5 spiny teeth. Distal segment of maxillula terminally with 8-10 strong, inconspicuously serrated spines, subterminally with a transverse row of 5-6 barbed setae. Endite of maxillula with three large, distally-spinose setae, and a total of 15-20 smaller, smooth or barbed setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="32CE200A5C9EFA8F2A54438B56504CE0" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
Thoracopods in general (Figs 7
<normalizedToken id="380D6E31975AC9DCB22E70556F0506B5" originalValue="D–J">D-J</normalizedToken>
, 8
<normalizedToken id="306A14B53179B36DCF2A3102928B5478" originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
). Sizes increase from exopod 1 to 4 and then show no clear trend from 4 to 8. Homologous exopods are not clearly different between sexes. Flagellum of first to eighth exopods with 8, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 8-9 segments. Exopods with basal plate 1.4-2.0 times longer than broad in both sexes. Claw of third endopod more strongly serrated in males (Fig. 7J) versus females (Fig. 7E), to a minor degree also in fourth endopod, not so in remaining endopods.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="558DF82921757FCA813D6C0A7BCF49DE" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Maxillipeds (first and second thoracic endopods; Fig. 7C, D). First endopod with hairs on outer half of sympod. Its epipod large, leaf-like, with comparatively long field of minute scales near insertion with sympod, and subbasally with a large seta densely barbed along its distal 60-75%. Dactylus of second endopod with dense brush of setae, among these 10-15 modified ones.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5F25ED8CD827AAA7B0D921CA987EC28F" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
Gnathopods (Figs 7E, J; 8
<normalizedToken id="DD7FA86723A4159FB4DD4D6855742D16" originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
). Carpopropodus of endopod comparatively slender, four times longer than broad in males, versus five times in females; length is 0.8-0.9 times that of merus and 0.9-1.0 times that of ischium in both sexes. Subbasally toothed setae (Fig. 8C): three on carpus plus two in (sub)apical position near outer margin on merus (Fig. 8A, B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A4155A6A2BDC76EC1E6FC07589CD00F6" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">
<pageBreakToken id="D0894E1A03BDCEC50B221D956ACA2DA2" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" start="start">Pereiopods</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 7
<normalizedToken id="8802ECB11D8C862891A806FF4850B94C" originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
, 8
<normalizedToken id="598DEC9708B4197F90C07052184AA3BC" originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
). Carpus of fourth endopod (Fig. 8D, E) with longer, subbasally toothed setae compared to third endopod (Fig. 8
<normalizedToken id="247CB85C85E4F8BC7E224F41A8462508" originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
). Fourth endopod with moderately small dactylus bearing long, strong, weakly-bent claw, microserrated on two opposite sides of subapical portions (Fig. 7F). Fifth to eighth endopods equipped with again smaller dactylus bearing a much shorter claw that shows slightly stronger, distally-increasing curvature; this claw unilaterally microserrated only in median portions of its inner margin (Fig. 7G, H). Sixth thoracopod of females with rudimentary oostegite representing a small lobe, on its inner margin with 0-2 proximally weakly barbed setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7AAA67AF16B90D422045A8877121CBB5" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">Penes (Fig. 8F) as above in diagnosis. Presence of small, barbed setae: 1-2 subterminally on exterior face plus 4-5 ones scattered anywhere between 3% and 70% penis length from basis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1946C59045FC622308A2BC00413A7AA7" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">Pleopods (Fig. 8G). The seta at inner terminal edge of endopod shows only minor number of barbs, all remaining setae well-barbed or plumose. Total length of pleopod 5 is 177-190% that of pleopod 1 (n = 4). Starting with pleopods 1 versus 2, length increase between subsequent pleopods is 19-32%, 0-13%, 1-18%, and 22-33%, respectively.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3FE3531AAEF8EFD817958A0BCA7BF6D1" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">
Uropods (not figured). The exopods reach with 21-30% of their length beyond endopods and 17-25% beyond telson, the endopods 6-11% of their length beyond telson. Exopod length 4.3-4.4 times maximum width. Statoliths composed of fluorite; diameter 145-181 
<normalizedToken id="54C77038DC4E60E5A7542885F531DDAF" originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
(n = 4); statolith formula is 2 + 3 + 1 + (8-13) + (16-19) = 31-38.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4134FD44A61EBCD13F194B8EFCB691BC" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">Telson (Fig. 8H). Length 1.2 times that of ultimate abdominal somite or 0.7-0.8 times exopod of uropods. Length of telson 1.2-1.5 times its maximum width. Laminae of cleft show 0.6-0.8 times average length of lateral spines. Length of lateral spines distally discontinuously increasing in size by a factor of about 1.6, arming almost all outer margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="98F297420B3CD112D5B19C55E7AE9B34" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">
Colour (Fig. 6A). General appearance of living specimens light red with orange tinge. The stronger orange tinge of the thorax in Fig. 6A is due to yolk in the ovarian tubes. Cornea yellow-golden; eyestalks mainly light red, except for a white ribbon along posterior, dorsal portions of the inner margin of the cornea. Red chromatophore centres scattered over eyestalks, antennae, pleon, uropods, and most densely over carapace, thoracomere 8, and telson. Two transverse series of chromatophores, one in about the middle and the second near posterior margin of pleomeres 1-2, and less regularly arranged also on pleomeres 3-6. Starting with pleomere 3, additional chromatophores are scattered with increasing density up to pleomere 6. Uropods with chromatophores only over proximal 70%. Persistence of colours as in 
<taxonomicName id="BE187836A8761901ED362CA015CC741F" genus="H." lsidName="H. cancelli" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" rank="species" species="cancelli">H. cancelli</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EAB296828A1EB7C041D55EDB57210601" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">
Nauplioid stage (Fig. 7M). One female with body length 8.0 mm carried 13 nauplioid larvae at substage 3, length 1.1-1.3 mm. At that same state of development one finds the same external morphological features as in 
<taxonomicName id="F4C44464A0A7404E9686D7E778B5A5D3" genus="H." lsidName="H. cancelli" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" rank="species" species="cancelli">H. cancelli</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (Fig. 3N shows substage 2). Each cercopod bears 10-14 acute spines with apically increasing size.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="883B9A7DB26555C2490D563589917778" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="C784C1FD299CCD96979B865896F202EA" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AF8CCE6A89817F0A195569F09921FC8F" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">The species name is a noun in genitive singular, named after well-know underwater-photographer and diver Craig Foster, who has accompanied and assisted the second author in many collecting expeditions and who made all in situ photographs and sampled all specimens of both this species and the one following.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="93F9C0672C2B5796E6E723956EB693D0" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" type="type locality">
<paragraph id="D41FE3EC273EF1C2C802A57153C48AF1" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9FE6D81F1893552822D9E2FAB03F9D13" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">
Sublittoral marine coastal waters at 
<normalizedToken id="833D9264AE6A7E780C75CEA2C77109DC" originalValue="Miller’s">Miller's</normalizedToken>
Point, on the False Bay coastline of the Cape Peninsula, South Africa, 
<geoCoordinate id="2E5CB974DBE114A0335644446F5D46B9" direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-34.229668">34°13.78'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="3B2D05E1534CEA3939E6E5F2B5249C2E" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="18.4745">18°28.47'E</geoCoordinate>
. This is only 5.5 
<pageBreakToken id="C1458952711F5873A65562809ACD1FCA" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" start="start">km</pageBreakToken>
to the SSE of the type locality of 
<taxonomicName id="2773E576403DCED587E4DAD48D6F5DF8" genus="H." lsidName="H. cancelli" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" rank="species" species="cancelli">H. cancelli</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (above). Materials were extracted from mixed collection of dead shells mainly belonging to the whelk 
<taxonomicName id="BE8C9230B7280AA35D166A8A5C3FFD06" class="Gastropoda" family="Cymatiidae" genus="Argobuccinum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Argobuccinum pustulosum" order="Littorinimorpha" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Mollusca" rank="species" species="pustulosum">Argobuccinum pustulosum</taxonomicName>
(Lightfood, 1786), the winkle 
<taxonomicName id="646078D789D56F27EC0FADDB99371E25" class="Gastropoda" family="Turbinidae" genus="Turbo" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Turbo cidaris" order="Trochida" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Mollusca" rank="species" species="cidaris">Turbo cidaris</taxonomicName>
Gmelin, 1791, and the urchin 
<taxonomicName id="B16E8CB6EC7F0922E8FA5D42623E23F8" class="Echinoidea" family="Parechinidae" genus="Parechinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parechinus angulosus" order="Camarodonta" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="angulosus">Parechinus angulosus</taxonomicName>
(Leske, 1778).
</paragraph>
<caption id="5BC5C54157196D490E6701DACD82DC85" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
<paragraph id="AF09E7A45D0542A55C9115FC3CBC7494" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
Figure 6. Microphotographs of adult female of 
<taxonomicName id="720892DDE841FDD576ACD2F85C89C512" class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis fosteri" order="Mysida" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fosteri">Heteromysis fosteri</taxonomicName>
sp. n. with 7 mm body length (A) and of adult male of 
<taxonomicName id="549A2DFB2FBEBFF9814EDC88CADA5363" class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis octopodis" order="Mysida" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="octopodis">Heteromysis octopodis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. with 9 mm (B), each from 
<normalizedToken id="781402B93F9C101B13E5B67A7049A625" originalValue="Miller’s">Miller's</normalizedToken>
Point, Cape Peninsula, South Africa. A laboratory photo by C.L. Griffiths B in situ image by Craig Foster, this last with background cleaned with electronic tools.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="14A65D71E8002ED3FC546915301E57D6" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
<paragraph id="F8DB5584DC71F52CDEF40644AA0A5884" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName id="6CCCCCBF83F9265374F4B3F2209B4604" class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis fosteri" order="Mysida" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fosteri">Heteromysis fosteri</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype females with 7.0 mm (A) and 8.0 mm (
<normalizedToken id="EDE0ECDDAEBA84F2BC5AA65D109386E0" originalValue="C–H">C-H</normalizedToken>
, L) body length, paratype male 6.0 mm (B, J, K). A cephalic region plus anterior part of carapace in female, dorsal view B male antennula, dorsal C epipod of first thoracopod, caudal 
<normalizedToken id="B27771BE3E6E360F1A2C086F2219CA09" originalValue="D–H">D-H</normalizedToken>
series of dactylus with claw in thoracic endopods 1, 3-5, 8 of female, caudal J tip of claw of third thoracic endopod in male K, L terminal margin of sixth pleonite, lateral, in male (K) versus female (L) M nauplioid larva at substage 3, lateral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="37995F0336D9ACCF7A5E3ED6843B2A5F" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
<paragraph id="582571EC4846B1502E803CA28C97A393" pageId="10" pageNumber="25">
Figure 8. 
<taxonomicName id="36BE7907D1411AA36DF248ABBEF17D18" class="Malacostraca" family="Mysidae" genus="Heteromysis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteromysis fosteri" order="Mysida" pageId="10" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fosteri">Heteromysis fosteri</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype male (A, 
<normalizedToken id="9785A7FEAC3AAB460B02D645E34E1364" originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
) with 6.0 mm body length and paratype female 8.0 mm (
<normalizedToken id="2338824CEC60A926D00E0015C3DF077B" originalValue="B–E">B-E</normalizedToken>
). A male tarsus with part of merus pertaining to third thoracic endopod, caudal aspect B the same for female, detail (C) shows subbasally toothed seta D tarsus of fourth thoracic endopod, caudal, detail (E) shows subbasally toothed seta F eighth thoracopod with penis, caudal G third male pleopod, rostral H telson, dorsal.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>