<document id="7847C2E24FD4BF5130983F3B7CEAB492" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.116.1473" ID-GBIF-Dataset="88e30de3-4f1b-44b9-b892-c9c770aadd89" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030223" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-116-59" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C11F980C-6446-4311-B71B-6812939BEC49" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-116-59" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 116" ModsDocTitle="Pictorial key for females of Decevania Huben (Hymenoptera, Evaniidae) and description of a new species" checkinTime="1451250198483" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Kawada, Ricardo" docDate="2011" docId="8ACE961B38CAA4FDA60C1ED821A3864C" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 116: 59-84" docOrigin="ZooKeys 116" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.116.1473" docTitle="Decevania feitosai Kawada, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="C11F980C-6446-4311-B71B-6812939BEC49" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="65" masterDocId="986BFFA4FFAA7939FFE5FF92D963B96E" masterDocTitle="Pictorial key for females of Decevania Huben (Hymenoptera, Evaniidae) and description of a new species" masterLastPageNumber="84" masterPageNumber="59" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" updateTime="1643717801961" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="CD5B5D1DB9704F064A7EE183B591FCC7" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="E2EB075FA8E89EE3480DE2B9779CC04A">
<mods:title id="E5DE46B54D45DDD3ECD98694A16C1DBF">Pictorial key for females of Decevania Huben (Hymenoptera, Evaniidae) and description of a new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A9384EAEC0F201D0D264E99DC738762C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="DE0E3882E224C48D42A0F164A117FC36">
<mods:roleTerm id="C48CC81ADB589B6B38418FD37BE85CAC">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="32E1C5F60CC22E006984A222CF823E0D">Kawada, Ricardo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="4102B3A8D99986BB9BD54EC7E17F7397">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="0EF04A07F561CA465DC231FB5164ADA9" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3C4C8EC9F362FD594BCA6F87693DD05D">
<mods:title id="7CF1A4B5C112AF146B60D5BD81D4C6C8">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="46D525862FAC707F092750BFDD5F9E57">
<mods:date id="8387EF37736A576921F2954ACBC32084">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="799080F243BD94B3734C3218244BB71B" type="volume">
<mods:number id="10709629E994AB34F56300F0A44119B6">116</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="67EDFB3AB5DC9F6C02026828F4FA1115" unit="page">
<mods:start id="77C772B9B288826B780C766AA45BEA5E">59</mods:start>
<mods:end id="0CC545F41522E35BE112BEADCE7BE093">84</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="674A37E0ACE6F43D46D8B34C7592259C">
<mods:url id="572AAD98D02E0643A31F2B781C897503">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.116.1473</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="A86ABCCDF62E79B3ADECE8EE03E10196">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="13067A9FA3DA77DF7331C6892FA961FC" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.116.1473</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="6D86CE93C954FE36B855BC4E3E880B9A" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-116-59</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="9F2433BB3DDAC8411A12344462576462" type="ZooBank">C966B837-596B-4D8C-AB2E-670DD93A5C10</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="8ACE961B38CAA4FDA60C1ED821A3864C" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030223" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C11F980C-6446-4311-B71B-6812939BEC49" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8ACE961B38CAA4FDA60C1ED821A3864C" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">
<subSubSection id="99070AF8F41EE357C3871CA7642F5CB2" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="984ED82177CA170E5C42759A5E88A13C" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">
<taxonomicName id="12EC7EF8B2A0B72A1BE6852DC6C6F9FE" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C11F980C-6446-4311-B71B-6812939BEC49" authority="Kawada" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai Kawada</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="8BF4E5001B4AA2CAC2EA1F9CB104C477" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Fig. 112
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B0A23CAE78511139B1C59AF7CD126F8B" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="2" pageNumber="61" type="description">
<paragraph id="0674F627A1A266054D222D7161C7568E" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7A267480D22191065B726533482F616F" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Female body length: 1.6 mm (head to propodeum). Head color: black. Mesosoma color: black. Legs color: fore leg: trochanter, trochantellus, tibia, tarsus light-castaneous; femur dark-castaneous. Wings: fore and hind wing hyaline. Metasoma: petiole light-castaneous; tergites: dark-castaneous.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7B14FDE84E2EE6F31E74954D255A126B" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">Head (Fig. 1-2, 5-7, 9). Head: long and stiff setae present evenly distributed; close to mesosoma. Vertex: slightly convex in lateral view; nitid with some small and sparse punctures. Ocelli: equal in size; arranged in obtuse isosceles triangle; anterior ocellus: separated from posterior ocellus by one ocellar diameter; anterior ocellus: not reaching the imaginary line between the anterior margin of posterior ocelli; posterior ocelli: separated by three ocellar diameters. Upper face: nitid with some sparse punctures. Eye: subovoid (lateral view); detached from dorsal profile of head; height of eye: as high as anterior margin of mesopleuron. Circumocular sulcus: absent. Postorbital carina: present; extending from anterior base of mandible to 3/4 the height of eye; strongly sinuous; narrower than postgenal sulcus. Antennal foramen: positioned at the same level as the top of the eye orbit; separated by one antennal foramen diameter; antennal rim: elevated laterally. Scape: long and stiff setae present evenly distributed; as long as F8. Pedicel + flagellomere 1: longer than wide; pedicel: as long as F1; flagellum: evenly and densely setose with some sparse and long setae. Median process of lower face: very weak in lateral view (difficult to see). Orbital band: strong, narrow and straight striae to the ventral margin of antennal foramen. Malar sulcus: present and conspicuous, differs from orbital band striae. Malar space: 0.64 times the height of eye (greater length). Clypeus: projecting medially; apical margin dilated and convex laterally. Mandible: two visible teeth, apical tooth longer and sharper than basal tooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="337031E9A063A43237C880E67F186268" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="63" pageId="2" pageNumber="61">
Mesosoma (Fig. 1-2, 9, 11-12). Pronotum: long and stiff setae present evenly distributed. Pronotal neck: obscured. Dorsal pronotal area: concealed medially. Dorsolateral area of pronotum: expanded posteriorly into a lobe. Pronotal suprahumeral sulcus: scrobiculate, with a large fovea anterior to the lobe. Transverse pronotal carina: acuminate and extending along the anterior margin of pronotum. Mesothoracic spiracular incision: strongly curved and almost closed into an orifice. Lateral and dorsolateral pronotal area: not clearly separated by a carina (inconspicuous). Lateral pronotal area: narrow, same width between the upper eye orbit and occipital carina (widest point); vertical and covered by a row of fovea (transverse pronotal sulcus). Mesonotum: slightly raised (lateral view: compared with propodeum). Mesoscutum: 2.0 times wider than long; nitid with a few, sparse and regular foveae. Anterior mesoscutal sulcus: present as continuous furrow. Notaulus: present as continuous furrow, slightly curved towards the middle and not reaching the posterior margin. Median lobe of mesoscutum: slightly curved anteriorly (lat 
<pageBreakToken id="8A7ADCC4CB9109FE22007201B86DAE24" pageId="3" pageNumber="62" start="start">eral</pageBreakToken>
view: difficult to see). Parascutal carina: present at posterior half; sulcus: following the parascutal carina and opening posteriorly. Parapsidal line: conspicuous suture, same length of parascutal carina and reaching the posterior margin of mesoscutum. Transscutal articulation: open in the middle and closing to lateral, near the parapsidal line. Mesoscutellum: long and stiff setae present, evenly distributed laterally; 
<pageBreakToken id="559E94E026E452E94319C8D64AB4913E" pageId="4" pageNumber="63" start="start">nitid</pageBreakToken>
in the middle with closed fovea laterally; bulging posteromedially; with a delicate median convexity on the posterior margin, but without overlap on metanotum. Scutoscutellar sulcus: not reaching the transscutal articulation, covered by a large and subcircular fovea. Metanotum: dorsolateral area covered by moderate (cuticle visible) layer of setae. Metanotum and metascutellum: form a continuous structure. Metascutellum: as a flat and nitid structure. Epicnemial carina: without median process (continuous shape). Prespecular sulcus: composed of one fovea. Anterior mesopleural area: covered by a row of rectangular impressions to femoral groove. Speculum: slightly dilated just above the middle of femoral groove. Mesepimeral sulcus: present as a row of irregular and subcircular foveae from posterodorsal mesepimeral area to mesocoxal foramen. Posterodorsal mesepimeral area: scrobiculate (narrow and shallow). Posterior mesepimeral area: curve and elongated posteriorly (closer to metacoxal foramen). Femoral groove: weakly concave; unsculptured medially. Mesopleural pit: absent. Ventral mesopleural area: covered by a subcircular and adjacent fovea; long and stiff setae present evenly distributed. Mesosternum: higher compared to metasternum; mesosternum foveate (irregular) with an open area (punctate) laterally. Mesodiscrimen: present as a flat and inconspicuous sulcus. Mesocoxa: distant 2.5 times (width of mesocoxa) from procoxa; adjacent to metacoxa. Meso- and metacoxa: without a pair of processes between coxae. Metapleuron (metapleural arm to metacoxal foramen): at least 3 times longer than wide. Metapleural carina: straight and parallel with concave lower metapleural area. Upper metapleural area: covered by a row of rectangular foveae. Lower metapleural area: lower region covered by an irregular polygonal fovea; long and stiff setae present, evenly distributed. Metapleural pit: present. Anterior area of metapleural pit: acute isosceles triangle shaped and covered by an irregular fovea. Metapleural epicoxal sulcus: present as a row of large and subrectangular foveae. Metanotum and propodeum: form a continuous structure. Propodeum: irregular foveae (dorsal) to regularly areolate (lateral). Dorsal propodeal area: long and stiff setae present, evenly distributed. Lateral propodeal carina: absent. Lateral propodeal area (upper region): long and stiff setae present evenly distributed. Adpetiolar strip: longer than wide. Nucha: slightly elevated (lateral view). Upper region of propodeal declivity (ventral to nucha): projection present and longer than base. Middle area of propodeal declivity: with long and stiff setae present evenly distributed. Posterior edge of metapectal-complex: curved (lateral view).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5D95CF4CD943FB9FDD7450BCD072CC0A" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="64" pageId="4" pageNumber="63">
Legs (Fig. 4, 10). Protibial spur: apex of calcar longer than apex of velum. Hind leg: long and stiff setae present evenly distributed (longer than outer spur); nitid with sparse punctures (trochanter, trochantellus, femur and tibia). Trochanter: 3.6 times longer (longer point) than wide (widest point). Hind femur: dorsal and ventral margin slightly dilated medially. Hind tibia: longer than hind femur; apical incision of hind tibia: sinuous. Tibial spurs: slightly sinuous; inner tibial spur: extending past the mid length of basitarsus; outer tibial spur: 1.8 times the length of hind basitarsus. Tarsus: minute striae (interspace) and more closer punctures; projections: conspicuous in tarsus 1-3; basitarsus: as long as tarsus 2-4 combined; basitarsus projection: longer than 
<pageBreakToken id="1C6C585328E71D146439E7A6B6EC9143" pageId="5" pageNumber="64" start="start">apex</pageBreakToken>
of basitarsus (widest point). Tarsal claw: hook-shaped, medially with a minute ventral spine.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="598B5D241419D4F5F835453FAB5ED886" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="5" pageNumber="64">
Wings (Fig. 8). Apex of fore wing: bordered by long setae. Costal cell: the same length as head + mesosoma combined (dorsal view). Stigmal vein: as wide as costal 
<pageBreakToken id="08A57396E833F9731229EE8918F692AC" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" start="start">cell</pageBreakToken>
. 1R1 vein: as long as stigmal vein, with slightly dilated apex. M+CU, 1CU and 2CU veins combined: extending past the propodeal declivity. 1CUb and 2CU vein: combined to form an angulated angle (45 degrees). 2CU vein: present with a slight dilatation distally. Hind wing: three hook-shaped hamuli of equal size; fusiform and three times longer than wide. Jugal lobe: present, slender and extending past the propodeal spiracle.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="10A34CF5CBCC95639F8CA31E4C7ADCF0" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">Metasoma (Fig. 11). Petiole: shorter than propodeal declivity; 6-7 times longer than wide; slightly curved distally. Transverse carina on petiole: as a narrow and acuminate rim. Dorsal petiolar area: nitid. Lateral petiolar area: some sparse and elongated punctures; long and stiff setae present, evenly distributed. Ventral petiolar area: fine and delicate longitudinal carina. Metasoma: subovoid (lateral view) with ovipositor concealed; without setae except T6-7 on posterior edge. Tergite 1: longer than petiole.</paragraph>
<caption id="DF8400E9711AE9B116C3D0FE12A08FED" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="F02B1D6E6588F12747CDDBF3E628C76D" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName id="A726E8E7B383A385EE62458A02974010" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype, female. Head and mesosoma in lateral view. For terminology see the list in Material and methods. Scale in the figure.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="2B678339CB7574F54A84029EF0B3A7C3" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="1FF0D307E8F8CEC9448A8B7561B23E10" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName id="63776BF8693E7E93E199737A6E13613A" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype, female. Head and mesosoma in dorsal view. For terminology see the list in Material and methods. Scale in the figure.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="3AF9DB15C7AA58910D96957E8D3CE536" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="8C44063C359E8A6EFF84219BDABA5171" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Figures 3-5. 
<taxonomicName id="0D768BA7027F5B4DBD60199B7E41626F" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype, female. 3 right antenna in dorsal view 4 hind legs in lateral view 5 head in dorsal view. For terminology see the list in Material and methods. Scale in the figures.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="8E694E8348E85639846C09064B5D6C3A" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="C1209D9F961A1BDA1AEC05AFEDD47AA8" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Figures 6-7. 
<taxonomicName id="261BA12E80935886505A45EA37BF4C73" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype, female. 6 head in lateral view 7 head in frontal view. For terminology see the list in Material and methods. Scale in the figures.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="01A4FC9E62E89BA3310FD94566598626" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="7F15D17EAFC30D5DB25C50DE727BB9E0" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Figures 8-9. 
<taxonomicName id="6708908294263FB4DC1C644CC1D320E5" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype, female. 8 left fore wing 9 head and mesosoma in ventral view. For terminology see the list in Material and methods. Scale in the figures.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="0D84458DDCD297D9B4B5E016CDCC2408" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="5D174BDF53EE0CDD74906ACC95290FEA" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Figures 10-11. 
<taxonomicName id="23EC97470BDB38C0C603EDA0ED59920A" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype, female. 10 fore and mid leg in frontal view 11 metasoma in laterodorsal view. For terminology see the list in Material and methods. Scale in the figures.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="07CAFF784C3FF8C416B5ADA70876DBA7" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
<paragraph id="C6153A6516451A213F6A629EC500877C" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Figure 12. 
<taxonomicName id="A4B572BB750BD0030752D84E9C4B9F4B" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Holotype, female. 10 habitus in lateral view. Scale in the figure.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="38F7A7670F4BEFE847BEE77E449C5E40" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="E96A4138AF393141B554D37C5C008D22" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CFA08B8EB588ED7C93AE5936B0D39562" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Eye: 1.8-2.0 times higher than wide. Postorbital carina: present and complete; conspicuously outlined; detached from the margin of lower eye orbit; sinuous (see malar space); reaching the top of eye orbit (some foveae may also be present and are part of carina). Antennal foramen: inserted at the same level as the top of eye orbit; antennal rim: conspicuously elevated laterally (head lateral view). Median lobe of mesoscutum: slightly curved or flat (lateral view). Notaulus: present as continuous furrow. Metanotum: not concealed by mesoscutellum (dorsal view). Sculpture of hind femur: unsculptured (nitid, autapomorphy for 
<taxonomicName id="DEEEFD1FACB71D4CD876FCF0FCFCA7EF" class="Insecta" family="Evaniidae" genus="Decevania" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Decevania feitosai" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="feitosai">Decevania feitosai</taxonomicName>
sp. n.). Posterior edge of metapectal complex: curved (lateral view). Dorsal area of propodeal declivity (ventral to nucha): projection present and longer than base. Petiole: longer than or as long as dorsal margin of tergite 1. 1R1 vein: present and elongate.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="751F7DD5717F905982EE637E28DE94F0" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="BA1716B7A5819C332CEEC4286AFD3143" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="736FB8ED6126BFA81A5DC009D95466D6" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
The specific epithet is a patronymic honoring Rodrigo M. Feitosa, colleague and researcher of 
<taxonomicName id="310008D859ABF7604C122C1A41644CD9" family="Formicidae" lsidName="" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" rank="family">Formicidae</taxonomicName>
from MZSP.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F7635A36F070C0DA5B359ABE5BF3E4B6" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="CD6C4A66E06A08B22208B1EFB17F58EF" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D18BA5B77ED7814477319AF5C469DAC0" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">Decevania Distribution16.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="BC3384CCC41E1E99806D18BB55D17BA1" pageId="6" pageNumber="65" type="material examined">
<paragraph id="F422CF1B91E7B4B461BA11AFDA229F93" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="99AD8F74EB61F52A4DFD9A3A725EE545" pageId="6" pageNumber="65">
Holotype. Female. COLOMBIA: Risaralda, SFF 
<normalizedToken id="3148B9D5DAF1791A702914E7FD20C12E" originalValue="Otún">Otun</normalizedToken>
Quimbaya, El Molinillo, 
<geoCoordinate id="E0E3516D4230D2ADD8C0031EE60D8654" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="4.7166667">4°43'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="6FA3817A70BB223A020ED5327BED4A62" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-75.566666">75°34'W</geoCoordinate>
, 2220 m, Malaise, 17.
<normalizedToken id="AAB0BC24BAB55E3E25737D9120A27A9B" originalValue="ii–">ii-</normalizedToken>
04.iii.2003, G. 
<normalizedToken id="B9C4AB04A6B3907B8B8E7BD4B41E97E5" originalValue="López">Lopez</normalizedToken>
leg., M.3696 (IAVH). Paratypes. 3 females. COLOMBIA: Magdalena, PNN Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta, San Lorenzo, 
<geoCoordinate id="9293E3935DBAA6E2FD88BAAE6FADC9FF" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="10.8">10°48'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="2AAD4E3132D88554BEA911D6C76AB08A" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-73.65">73°39'W</geoCoordinate>
, 2200 m, Malaise, 09-24.vi.2000, J. Cantillo leg. M. 205 (IAVH 65814); 09-24.vi.2000, J. Cantillo leg. M. 205 (IAVH 65815); 24-30.vi.2000, J. Cantillo leg. M. 211 (IAVH 65816). 4 females. Risaralda, SFF 
<normalizedToken id="ADCC4282B303ED0D1C03ECA00D776F48" originalValue="Otún">Otun</normalizedToken>
Quimbaya, El Molinillo, 
<geoCoordinate id="6188C3C2B58D5D8C6AA4062D34A4573C" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="4.7166667">4°43'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="A5A91D26F52C911FEF90425CF0C5DF79" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-75.566666">75°34'W</geoCoordinate>
, 2220 m, 03-17.xii.2002, Malaise, G. Walker leg., M. 2972 (IAVH 65827); 
<geoCoordinate id="9DCC8638EB35E8D4FD0622A81E6CC2F3" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="4.7166667">4°43'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="B81A797502D01694A336B4FE4462F6A4" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-75.566666">75°34'W</geoCoordinate>
, 2220 m, 17.xii.2002-03.i.2003, Malaise, G. Walker leg., M. 2971 (IAVH 65828). Cuchilla Camino, 
<geoCoordinate id="3A5527ADBC7ED0AB1D6B1390B747FD9C" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="4.7166667">4°43'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="F7FE78D1E303835E8D0CE71006F4889F" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-75.583336">75°35'W</geoCoordinate>
, 2050 m, 04-17.ii.2003, Malaise, G. 
<normalizedToken id="56E3FB3082B9EC857F23E506317FFB3A" originalValue="López">Lopez</normalizedToken>
leg., M. 3680 (IAVH). Cuchilla Camino, 
<geoCoordinate id="136812CE067CD5DAAA041D6FC48D7F9D" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="4.7333336">4°44'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="6EBF137E32B37F6FADAE223F364991F6" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-75.583336">75°35'W</geoCoordinate>
, 1960 m, 04-21.iii.2003, Malaise, G. 
<normalizedToken id="AB09BFBD352372288D5AE00FD7A2CE25" originalValue="López">Lopez</normalizedToken>
leg., M. 3669 (IAVH 65826).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>