<document id="BD5F533370F8E3A7010C179079FF018A" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280160" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120138" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280160" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="8C21063262E345176C93800EA3784896" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys actis Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="649" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="648" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="0370B9D30C489E540070F2F5D5A62775" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="069CA08D11B8775049C5A4D5F2280EA5">
<mods:title id="8DCCAF1673CF831B759395F85E633675">The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="69DDCBEBBA5655F2DBC8D087457EC512" type="personal">
<mods:role id="7E3E5D1D6288528E706C568CE04238B4">
<mods:roleTerm id="3DD89573E2983A58A5F34AAB9CF8CC03">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="BB6C312DC68DD1D3386DDE4777F28154">Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="F5E5E7B5E2FD52E7A06143EE6E976036">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="BDC104CC77385F923E76F3C52FAE1897" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="D260EC5B4122A7ECCE7D062232020DE2">
<mods:title id="04F7C84B1C49D411467541B82082442C">Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="C38E3BA0FBCC76B31D86C4B9D149E639">
<mods:date id="2755B4DE37455921CEF4DAC59F0D3F01">2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="67EA5702E8F938542EEEA70E14FB34B8" type="volume">
<mods:number id="E43EED8CCF408BD94ED7C7557E861B6D">65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="FDBC9F6C9C79406F9F62FBF42B4D3638" unit="page">
<mods:start id="A5780225736921D46111295A265B5108">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="F7C48D6C4211DD2041BCC24838982934">1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="25FE10D6C4FB8F2031CEC3E55390B448">
<mods:url id="FF0D2F99D97AE7C60498F28D258E67D6">http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="BCCE5806E88F36C4CF2CF3C0B41FA355">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="6458F3D2E8651FFC2AE638A3E93B632D" type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="2B8F88D5D2B588B7B98664FFC9055C23" type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="8C21063262E345176C93800EA3784896" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280160" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120138" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280160" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:8C21063262E345176C93800EA3784896" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8C21063262E345176C93800EA3784896" lastPageNumber="649" pageNumber="648">
<subSubSection id="722E268E013A3214D5B06C24ED81382C" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="82414EA8F771C6FC429CBA2E40FA113B" pageNumber="648">
<taxonomicName id="EAC5B5FDE8F639214B041194C0E994EC" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155830" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys actis Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys actis Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="648" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="actis">Strumigenys actis Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="DE357461715929BF966CB3C641527F7F" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FBAA75B5A75398226528C6A4CA02DB1F" type="description">
<paragraph id="FC5DEB55340A4D86D79060168EAE1606" pageNumber="648">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 3.4, HL 0.88, HW 0.70, CI 80, ML 0.46, MI 52, SL 0.59, SI 84, PW 0.36, AL 0.85. Characters of chilo-complex. Mandibles almost straight and at full closure parallel. Apical fork of mandible subtended by a third, shorter spiniform tooth, the fork effectively 3 - dentate; without intercalary teeth or denticles. Preapical teeth absent. Upper scrobe margin ends, or at least becomes extremely indistinct, at about the level of the eye; when viewed in profile upper scrobe margin extends posteriorly across dorsal apex of vertical preocular groove of side of head; preocular groove meets and is interrupted by the upper scrobe margin before reaching the cephalic dorsum. Eye large, convex, and plainly visible in full-face view. Scape long and slender, approximately straight, the leading edge with a row of slender hairs which are slightly flattened or spoon-shaped apically. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with curved spoon-shaped ground-pilosity; the upper scrobe margin without a row of hairs. Cephalic dorsum with 4 simple standing hairs arranged in a transverse row close to the occipital margin. Dorsum of head reticulatepunctate. Mesonotum with a single pair of stout standing hairs situated on anterior margin. Propodeum with one pair of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Ground-pilosity on alitrunk as on head but sparser. With the alitrunk in profile the posterior portion of the mesonotum sharply depressed, the metanotal groove represented by a shallow impression. Pronotal humeri rounded. Lateral margin of posterior pronotum bluntly marginate. Anterior mesonotum with a narrow carina above the mesothoracic spiracle. Propodeal tooth long and slender, almost spiniform; propodeal lamella absent. Alitrunk dorsum and sides reticulate-punctate. Petiole node in dorsal view reticulate-punctate and much longer than broad. Postpetiole disc reticulate-punctate. Spongiform appendages of petiole weakly developed. Postpetiole with small but distinct lateral and ventral spongiform lobes. Basigastral costulae fine across base of gaster without a central clear area; gaster smooth and shiny where clean. Dorsal surfaces of petiole often with a pair of short posteriorly projecting hairs; postpetiole with a pair of posteriorly projecting stout hairs; gaster with stout standing hairs which are weakly swollen apically. Colour dull yellow to light medium brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B27516D38689EF9021BDF70F762E4B06" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="536E48047D4E1B0FB2144BFCCFA7A9D2" pageNumber="649">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 43 km. S Ambalavao, Res. Andringitra, 22 Â° 14 ' S, 47 Â° 00 ' E&gt; 825 m., 5. x. 1993, sifted litter (leaf mold rotten wood), rainforest # 747 (14) - 8 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BE09050EF94D1F3219CFF0A186E30A1" pageNumber="649">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: Perinet, 900 m., (J. - M. Belsch); Ranomafana Nat. Park, Vohiparara Forest, 1160 m. (E. Rajeriarison); Pare Nat. de Ranomafana (Bartolozzi el at.); Ranamafana Nat. Park, 1040 m. (WE. Steiner); 7 km. W Ranomafana, 900 m. (WE. Sleiner); 3 km. W Ranomafana, 950 m. (P. S. Wjrd); 7.5 km. ENE Ivohibe, 900 m. (S. Razqfimandimby); 9.0 km. NE Ivohibe, 900 m. (S. Razafimandimby).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2BD2672E237F7D7C9DDA7C1A9A0BAEEE" type="description">
<paragraph id="158E0F946F7642E2CC34D35EEC551938" pageNumber="649">Measurements of this material extend the range shown by the type-series: TL 3.3 - 3.9, HL 0.86 - 1.01, HW 0.65 - 0.86, CI 75 - 92, ML 0.44 - 0.54, MI 49 - 59, SL 0.56 - 0.70, SI 79 - 86, PW 0.34 - 0.41, AL 0.80 - 0.99 (9 measured).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A60498B868C5FB1B33EA1A31DD5B5A1A" pageNumber="649">Among the Malagasy species that have the mandibular apical fork subtended by a shorter third tooth actis is easily isolated by the following characters:</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="EBD6F35C3E66F36A3D3FF8ED095EFD03" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="3CEB2932F7994A0198BA5579D2917B56" pageNumber="649">1 Upper scrobe margin ends, or at least becomes extremely indistinct, at about the level of the eye; when viewed in profile, upper scrobe margin extends posteriorly across dorsal apex of vertical preocular groove of side of head; preocular groove meets and is interrupted by the upper scrobe margin before reaching the cephalic dorsum.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F35BC0C55FA30C8907F4078A079E6CFE" pageNumber="649">2 Mesonotum with 1 pair of erect hairs, on anterior margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="56987386969855E7F376CFFDF32E984F" pageNumber="649">3 Cephalic dorsum with a transverse row of four erect hairs immediately in front of occipital margin.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>