<document id="EDF077A6B2442AD8EBDF835FAAB5FE85" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.749.23165" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bfd2bd34-077c-41ba-85d7-49105d681f94" ID-GBIF-Taxon="143536419" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-749-1" ID-ZBK="F941B98FC5DB4784A676977496D7E472" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6D34788A-7029-4933-9A27-855786E4F731" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-749-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 749" ModsDocTitle="Seven new freshwater species of Gammarus from southern China (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)" checkinTime="1523392991472" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Hou, Zhonge, Zhao, Shuangyan &amp; Li, Shuqiang" docDate="2018" docId="8F414ECE60E07CCCABE8DA0126114C0A" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 749: 1-79" docOrigin="ZooKeys 749" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.749.23165" docTitle="Gammarus vallecula Hou &amp; Li, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="6D34788A-7029-4933-9A27-855786E4F731" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" masterDocId="FFA9FFBB6F2CFFFBC121FFD3FFFDAD60" masterDocTitle="Seven new freshwater species of Gammarus from southern China (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)" masterLastPageNumber="79" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" updateTime="1643515554975" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="28D1C145EB970FCBF06EAE3F30BCD9D0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="DC759C3106BE8D59FB12550322BD435E">
<mods:title id="33C0924C0D3A2F2707D66E8AB5450E0D">Seven new freshwater species of Gammarus from southern China (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="62DEE0B7605B64FE01BF8A9EBA5E4834" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B252A2AF1C511FE033FBBEE8530495A7">
<mods:roleTerm id="B2A844AA597E733D56F2A0B09992B606">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="B36E72DD3AB8121B724890B907462C43">Hou, Zhonge</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="BCED91827F6D8F3EC79D8D6449C0CAD2" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9720BE60F44D83729F8A93BB5A038FD3">
<mods:roleTerm id="967CE1D5A2E8A2262EF467C3D5E3422C">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="B1BEBAE66A9F649EBED095639C4E1E72">Zhao, Shuangyan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="E516A1449E6B5E59F403FED597862A3F" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B2D8AD06D982D8243992321E16A55FAB">
<mods:roleTerm id="60E37417B06405CAA942C75E6377FD79">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="D18D87AA99E2C2917374DDB357CD7A1D">Li, Shuqiang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="73431101A9DB0C2D00300112E834F11F">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="C018969008085CD3FB991784758D4F67" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="6781E739F450E9B95D7E6C46860D39DE">
<mods:title id="07DEE9A6754B0E5BA01A940788034639">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="A2CAB5E6D08D6F74A8761534F3BF0FC0">
<mods:date id="F21DEEC4FA4337CCED4F7009CCD423C7">2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3E07C185D9AAA1FCBFBAE1BC54321270" type="volume">
<mods:number id="4A8AD22325E47D5BAD4A27279E76D6E9">749</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="BFEACDA895C6F579EF35B2AB2DB225FF" unit="page">
<mods:start id="4752A1261D90C3FA80E9362B5E40EB77">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="5889363F9D7505D2F9814D7D177DA223">79</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="1546061A9DE21F9DDEF006761CBA19CC">
<mods:url id="E408A0A7D065891D31817BB525263547">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.749.23165</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="967E78EDF2295F94F2F6C77F7840286F">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="11DB68E9AB2B25F81411B0A688C03273" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.749.23165</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="F9C276F91E5278B60890572A0F72CB86" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-749-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="FC9BFAB2B8540FC90FA372D4EEFC0D54" type="ZBK">F941B98FC5DB4784A676977496D7E472</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="3ECAEE49C613EC1C947E5A60C9812191" type="ZooBank">F941B98FC5DB4784A676977496D7E472</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="8F414ECE60E07CCCABE8DA0126114C0A" ID-GBIF-Taxon="143536419" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6D34788A-7029-4933-9A27-855786E4F731" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F414ECE60E07CCCABE8DA0126114C0A" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<subSubSection id="FCA4AA92245013E70CD2C5C5D74AEDFA" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="3425EAAEA7FCA11AC34653631A2C5F92" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<taxonomicName id="23EDB5A884E824F060711133FCCDF399" LSID="http://zoobank.org/6D34788A-7029-4933-9A27-855786E4F731" authority="Hou &amp; Li" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula Hou &amp; Li</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="6C9B2C66A5AE13A2C0635AA1FA6F4DAC" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A58FA5BB2F2AD9F344F3A4F385B28B43" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="81FEC05430615159717759498575CB5B" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FB133A1F629BCCC20D323A7B1A1051DE" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Holotype: male (IZCAS-I-A1411-1), 8.5 mm, Liuba County (
<geoCoordinate id="4BC0CC17A2C8B55FA12214D6EDA42F96" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="555" value="106.92">106.92°E</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="91E2BFFFE38E2E8C6C2239EC1927B90D" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="555" value="33.61">33.61°N</geoCoordinate>
), altitude 1001 m, Hanzhong City, Shaanxi Province, China, October 23, 2013, collected by Yunchun Li and Jincheng Liu. Paratype: female (IZCAS-I-A1411-2), 7.8 mm, same data as holotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B293FCC8997895067CD1EA5B1C3E470C" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="5594F0BB1C3BFC6C9204087FDA213CE6" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="95B994CB30B76E9E9AC5D831BE947082" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">The specific name alludes to its typical biotope, living in a valley; adjective.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E66BF8624B257A54B848095D8EE07206" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="780058D2E0CA6A54638FBADCADA8CAD0" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="46E7E965078EB5DC93831FBA0E979D35" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Antenna II with setae along peduncle articles and flagellum, calceoli absent; merus to propodus of pereopods III and IV with short straight setae on posterior margins; epimeral plate II with blunt posterodistal corner; epimeral plate III with subacute posterodistal corner; uropod III inner ramus reaching 0.5 times the length of outer ramus, second article of outer ramus subequal to adjacent spines, both rami with a few plumose setae on inner margins.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="84F3FC2E6DFE9A0CDDB659D1AAEC09D9" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="description">
<paragraph id="2DC9449F8CA6255982C462A177F2C377" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Description of holotype male</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D7762CE931DF3DFB97541B6B20527A40" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">(IZCAS-I-A1411-1). 8.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="10267710C8F06C68BACADD8F015107AD" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Head (Fig. 2A): eyes reniform, inferior antennal sinus deep, lateral cephalic lobe rounded.</paragraph>
<caption id="DA02A2DAFD9E72D20C90243A2CEE83E0" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph id="162BD16A9D1EFA9F5106284171E5AD84" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName id="EFE71FB5D569E0F67720875AAA974D35" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n., male holotype. A head B antenna I C flagellar article of antenna I with aesthetasc D antenna II E upper lip F lower lip G left mandible H incisor and lacinia mobilis of right mandible I left maxilla I J distal part of palp article II of right maxilla I K maxilla II L maxilliped M dorsal margins of urosomites 
<normalizedToken id="2ACE8ACB11B4502DCBE1B8A1FE6D3AFE" originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="A8E55797F33BA5E2B2588F13DF5B0979" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Antenna I (Fig. 2B, C): peduncle articles 
<normalizedToken id="D33F107F56BD0075AFBFD8DBE8E10409" originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
in length ratio 1.0: 0.7: 0.4, with distal setae; flagellum with 26 articles, articles 
<normalizedToken id="AB823192AB0B41E140ED899F311D4FCC" originalValue="IV–XX">IV-XX</normalizedToken>
with aesthetascs; accessory 
<normalizedToken id="F216DFB37CD02B0D570D50A49E8E352F" originalValue="ﬂagellum">ﬂagellum</normalizedToken>
with four articles; both primary and accessory 
<normalizedToken id="9D63071647BD1642C1C5F7EF2147D752" originalValue="ﬂagella">ﬂagella</normalizedToken>
with short distal setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B5D0FDB70C4BE75D8307EAA0F70D2DEA" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Antenna II (Fig. 2D): peduncle articles 
<normalizedToken id="629DF758738D6BEB290E9A796F220DEB" originalValue="III–V">III-V</normalizedToken>
in length ratio 1.0: 2.5: 2.3, peduncle article III with setae on lateral margin, articles IV and V of peduncle with clusters of lateral and medial setae; flagellum with ten articles, each article with long setae; calceoli absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1E3DF979857FC036ACD25C549EEE5376" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Upper lip (Fig. 2E): ventral margin rounded, bearing short minute setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FA05423BE745C1A455365A91F00DD889" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Mandible (Fig. 2G, H): left mandible incisor with five teeth; lacinia mobilis with four teeth; spine row with five pairs of plumose setae; articles 
<normalizedToken id="6BBB0A242FF54318DD26631766C22022" originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
of palp in length ratio 1.0: 3.1: 1.9, second article of palp with 12 marginal setae, article III with four A-setae, four B-setae, 16 D-setae, and five E-setae apically; incisor of right mandible with four teeth, lacinia mobilis bifurcate, with small teeth.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B10975847D12A0A79949423DCC5F53B6" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Lower lip (Fig. 2F): inner lobes lacking, outer lobes covered with thin setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CB7DEB882BD9BEA4FC72DC0F88C5973F" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Maxilla I (Fig. 2I, J): asymmetrical, left inner plate with nine plumose setae and two simple setae on medial margin; outer plate with 11 robust serrated apical spines, each spine with small teeth; second article of left palp with seven slender spines apically; second article of right palp with five stout spines, one slender spine and one stiff spine.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9B4B437F0FE1621430BF0E1F66F8E118" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Maxilla II (Fig. 2K): inner plate with three simple setae and 11 plumose facial setae in an oblique row; inner and outer plates with long setae apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4FA3E0B38306A828E9E852B9A05B607A" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Maxilliped (Fig. 2L): inner plate with three stout apical spines and one subapical spine, 21 plumose setae along lateral margin; outer plate bearing a row of 14 blade spines and three plumose setae apically; article IV of palp hooked, with a group of setae at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="43A911546C577881ABEFCD7702A779F2" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Pereon.Gnathopod I (Fig. 3A, B): coxal plate bearing three setae and two setae on anterior and posterior margins, respectively; basis with setae on anterior and posterior margins, and with three serrated spines accompanied by two setae on posterodistal corner; carpus 1.3 times as long as wide, 0.7 times as long as propodus, ventral margin bearing a cluster of simple setae and three clusters of serrated setae; propodus oval, palm with one medial spine and 12 spines on posterior margin and surface; dactylus with one seta on outer margin.</paragraph>
<caption id="9949D81AFA1B03DAC663179E5F8772F8" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph id="712F919C273D96C9ED521CBF50156E06" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName id="50E6EE78AD17C97320CDA09A0D33E03B" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n., male holotype. A gnathopod I B propodus and dactylus of gnathopod I C gnathopod II D propodus and dactylus of gnathopod II.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="4F72B9D94DB419B33860B7FC127260AB" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Gnathopod II (Fig. 3C, D): coxal plate bearing three setae and two setae on anterior and posterior margins, respectively; basis with setae on anterior and posterior margins, and with three serrated spines accompanied by one seta on posterodistal corner; carpus 1.8 times as long as wide, 0.9 times as long as propodus, bearing seven clusters of setae along ventral margin, two clusters of setae on dorsal margin; propodus subrectangular, palm margin with one medial spine and three spines on lateral posterodistal corner; dactylus with one seta on outer margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="08B78C3AED8277B57FC04913316FD49D" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Pereopod III (Fig. 4A, B): coxal plate bearing two setae on anterior margin and three setae on posterior margin; basis elongated, with setae along anterior and posterior margins; merus with long and straight setae on posterior margin and two spines on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with one spine accompanied by setae; carpus with five spines accompanied by setae on posterior margin, anterodistal corner with one spine and one seta; propodus with three spines accompanied by setae on posterior margin and two spines on posterodistal corner; dactylus with one plumose seta on anterior margin, and two setae at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<caption id="C015CFA11DABBF7E0FCA3B445FADDD5B" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph id="2E6FCA7ED7D7FFE2014BB40EE47C4899" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="5C3667A79FA781DB3BE891CCAE86AC67" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n., male holotype. A pereopod III B dactylus of pereopod III C pereopod IV D dactylus of pereopod IV E pereopod V F dactylus of pereopod V G pereopod VI H dactylus of pereopod VI I pereopod VII J dactylus of pereopod VII K epimeral plate I L epimeral plate II M epimeral plate III.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="FF06262B651B6721C27212B9482690BF" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Pereopod IV (Fig. 4C, D): coxal plate concave, bearing three setae on anterior margin and seven setae on posterior margin; basis with two setae on anterior margin, with clusters of setae on posterior margin; merus with clusters of long setae on posterior margin and one spine on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with one spine accompanied by setae; carpus with seven spines accompanied by setae on posterior margin, anterodistal corner with two spines accompanied by setae; propodus with two spines accompanied by setae on posterior margin and two spines on posterodistal corner; dactylus with one plumose seta on anterior margin, and two setae at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9C805E217FFB6837264B289661537FCE" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<pageBreakToken id="85484C817A6C965B6083413EBC804965" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">Pereopod</pageBreakToken>
V (Fig. 4E, F): coxal plate bearing one seta on anterior margin and three setae on posterior margin; basis expanded, with four long setae and three spines accompanied by fine setae on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with two spines accompanied by two setae, posterior margin with a row of 12 setae; merus with one spine accompanied by setae on anterior margin and one spine on posterior margin, anterodistal corner with two spines accompanied by setae and posterodistal corner with three spines; carpus with two groups of spines on anterior and posterior margins each; propodus with three groups of spines on anterior margin; dactylus with one plumose seta on posterior margin, and two setae at hinge of unguis.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8810B4CCEF0DA5E6BE9146F7D6E9D971" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Pereopod VI (Fig. 4G, H): coxal plate bearing two long setae and two fine setae on anterior and posterior margins, respectively; basis elongated, with two long setae and four spines accompanied by setae on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with three spines and one fine seta, posterior margin with a row of 12 fine setae; merus with three groups of spines and one spine on anterior and posterior margins, respectively, anterodistal and posterodistal corners with four spines each; carpus with three or two groups of spines on anterior and posterior margins, respectively; propodus with four groups of spines on anterior margin; dactylus with one plumose seta on posterior margin, and two setae at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8AB4D0D1152709AAF5006B99644C6442" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Pereopod VII (Fig. 4I, J): coxal plate bearing one seta on anterior margin and five setae on posterior margin; basis with four long setae and four spines accompanied by setae on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with two spines and a fine seta, posterior margin with a row of 11 setae, posterodistal corner with one spine; merus with two groups of spines on anterior margin and one spine on posterior margin, anterodistal and posterodistal corners with four and three spines, respectively; carpus with three groups of spines on anterior margin and one spine on posterior margin, anterodistal and posterodistal corners with three and four spines, respectively; propodus with groups of spines on anterior margin; dactylus with one plumose seta on posterior margin, and two setae at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9C70FA498458CDE99A935174D8A532E6" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Coxal gills: coxal gill of gnathopod II and gills of pereopods 
<normalizedToken id="CDA4809D6EFB6103C72816A3797A3AFE" originalValue="III–V">III-V</normalizedToken>
longer than bases; gill of pereopod VI a little shorter than basis; gill of pereopod VII smallest, half the length of basis.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4640393B749D604F02176D6D16CA7904" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Pleon.Epimeral plates (Fig. 4
<normalizedToken id="0F6FD08F5EAF6095EB41C2719D198C48" originalValue="K–M">K-M</normalizedToken>
): plate I ventrally rounded, bearing seven long setae on anteroventral margin and three tiny setae on posterior margin; plate II with two spines on ventral margin and six tiny setae on posterior margin, posterodistal corner blunt; plate III with three spines on ventral margin and six tiny setae on posterior margin, posterodistal corner subacute.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EA5B70225BC38DF363D67B6B44F29D40" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Pleopods 
<normalizedToken id="53D5DA5E03460AF12D94280186992B00" originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
(Fig. 5
<normalizedToken id="F5BFC0C1D29E2A064AB8BEFA2EAF3645" originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
): similar, peduncle with two retinacula accompanied by two setae; outer ramus slightly longer than inner ramus, both inner and outer rami fringed with plumose setae.
</paragraph>
<caption id="43DC1EDA0940405A87A71E05081B9D1E" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<paragraph id="5786F54AA168C27F60B1026DA752756E" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName id="66B3AEDA190A96E04BC121AAD7E6B83A" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n., 
<normalizedToken id="A8F85B3972205E2334E16664E148D3D4" originalValue="A–G">A-G</normalizedToken>
male, holotype; H female, paratype. A pleopod I B pleopod II C pleopod III D uropod I E uropod II F uropod III G telson H uropod I.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="60DF66B697154A3455B95CB9F97BBD15" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Urosome.Urosomites (Fig. 2M): urosomite I with one-one-one-one spines accompanied by setae on dorsal margin; urosomite II with three-one-one-three spines accompanied by setae on dorsal margin; urosomite III with two spines accompanied by two setae on each side and two pairs of setae on dorsal margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E972846536DAC6EC98E8931351F1EEEC" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<pageBreakToken id="EB2CCF0175483B8E8CC40B85D2DEC34E" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" start="start">Uropods</pageBreakToken>
<normalizedToken id="70097C50F80DBF8A46A61E2958DEF6FA" originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
(Fig. 5
<normalizedToken id="F83284A051275511FC7561DCA6BB1919" originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
): uropod I peduncle with one basofacial spine, two spines on inner margin and three spines on outer margin, inner and outer distal corners with one and two spines, respectively; inner and outer rami with two and one spines on inner margins, respectively; both rami with five terminal spines. Uropod II peduncle with one and two spines on inner and outer margins respectively, and with one distal spine on each corner; inner ramus with two spines on inner margin; outer ramus with one spine on inner margin; both rami with five terminal spines. Uropod III peduncle with two spines accompanied by one seta on surface and eight distal spines; inner ramus 1.2 times as long as peduncle, reaching 0.5 times the length of outer ramus, with one spine accompanied by three plumose setae on inner margin and two distal spines accompanied by setae; proximal article of outer ramus with three pairs of spines accompanied by simple setae on outer margin, with four plumose setae and one simple seta on inner margin, terminal article with simple setae, subequal to adjacent spines.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D627C037A1DD2D71D7AC943676CEBAF4" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Telson (Fig. 5G): deeply cleft, 0.8 times as long as wide; each lobe with one spine accompanied by one seta and clusters of setae on surface, bearing two distal spines accompanied by three setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4B7806C99CCE842F9C28F70188CAF3C0" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="description">
<paragraph id="8539AC1CF9C52BD0B06CA8C8DBA2EEC7" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Description of paratype female</paragraph>
<paragraph id="19B903908C03D8F9F177370BB32434E7" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">(IZCAS-I-A1411-2). 7.8 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2AD55C9A7CE2781FE2DA8CCAA03082D8" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Pereon.Gnathopod I (Fig. 6A, B): coxal plate bearing four and two setae on anterior and posterior margins, respectively; basis with long setae on anterior and posterior margins, posterodistal corner with four serrated spines accompanied by setae; propodus oval, palm with six spines on posterior margin, bearing long setae along anterior and posterior margins; dactylus with one seta on outer margin.</paragraph>
<caption id="526AB0A74DC310C20C21679FD0B465C8" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<paragraph id="DCF4C5B5665625A4C4E59627948B717C" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName id="234D7EC5104EDB0A6077D8A9184178E9" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n., female paratype. A gnathopod I B propodus and dactylus of gnathopod I C gnathopod II D propodus and dactylus of gnathopod II.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="F7FDF0A11629EF7BB4DDB50F695756FE" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Gnathopod II (Fig. 6C, D): coxal plate bearing five and two fine setae on anterior and posterior margins, respectively; basis with setae on anterior and posterior margins; propodus subrectangular, palm margin with three spines on posterodistal corner, bearing long setae along anterior and posterior margins; dactylus with one seta on outer margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="46A61059B9F5AF90C0D815778E4F3A14" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Pereopods 
<normalizedToken id="2C8CFB90ABC3A8BE259EFDBCE91B4CA1" originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
(Fig. 7
<normalizedToken id="114A26EA0941036CBE0F77081033539C" originalValue="E–I">E-I</normalizedToken>
): similar to those of male.
</paragraph>
<caption id="EE0905832E540A094E7AD7D983398800" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<paragraph id="9BDA0A565A6C4E5BB6F9212D3AA16F1A" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName id="FA5DDE47342E95A78B17A020580C23C6" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n., female paratype. A oostegite of gnathopod II B oostegite of pereopod III C oostegite of pereopod IV D oostegite of pereopod V E pereopod III F pereopod IV G pereopod V H pereopod VI I pereopod VII J uropod II K uropod III L telson.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="07643338AD8CDE24A09BF18172C16B9A" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Oostegite (Fig. 6
<normalizedToken id="3827DA2156E11872E1AB608B3319A2B7" originalValue="H–K">H-K</normalizedToken>
): oostegite of gnathopod II broad, oostegites of pereopods III and IV elongated, oostegite of pereopod V smallest.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1D092447B8E72BF53ECD8CFBF44BBF10" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Urosome.Uropods 
<normalizedToken id="5EEBF667AF032A518A4A3471359B79CC" originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
(Figs 5H; 7J, K): uropod I peduncle with one basofacial spine, with two and one spines on outer and inner margins, respectively, with two and one spines on outer and inner distal corners, respectively; outer ramus with two spines on inner margin and one spine on outer margin; inner ramus with two spines on inner margin; both rami with five terminal spines. Uropod II short, peduncle bearing two spines on outer and inner margins each, with one spine on outer and inner distal corners each; outer ramus with one spine on outer margin; inner ramus with two spines on inner margin; both rami with five terminal spines. Uropod III peduncle with two spines accompanied by one seta on surface and five distal spines; inner ramus 1.1 times as long as peduncle, reaching 0.6 times the length of outer ramus, with one spine accompanied by three plumose setae and one simple seta on inner margin and two distal spines accompanied by setae; proximal article of outer ramus with five spines accompanied by one plumose seta and simple setae on outer margin, inner margin with three plumose setae and two simple setae, terminal article subequal to adjacent spines.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="959D1A66DCB2C96A81AB15DD8006B386" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<pageBreakToken id="870A99415D69942E65DF90DDBF0467AD" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" start="start">Telson</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 7L): cleft, 0.8 times as long as wide; left lobe with one spine accompanied by one seta and a cluster of two setae on surface, bearing two distal spines accompanied by three setae; right lobe with one spine accompanied by one seta and a cluster of three setae on surface, bearing one distal spine accompanied by five setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F1DE1C84333F0A8CB1CF7B71B8370A67" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="habitat">
<paragraph id="E627CEBBE6A743EDB3ECE67D2B8E711F" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D771FDF7EA4A3F5670A4C33932FA40B2" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">This species was collected from a valley of south part of the Qinling. Individuals inhabit a stream, usually under decomposing leaves.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="30EE473A935710EF70F87B596A5551CD" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="remarks">
<paragraph id="7ABAB1A71140B783A2B72D851F2A39DD" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A149327205D4A314FB5B2709496A2177" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
The new species of 
<taxonomicName id="2FF852979EC33567CE8B73CC4DF8514F" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n. is similar to 
<taxonomicName id="17B1FF356126392DD334F2BE3BCED523" genus="G." lsidName="G. craspedotrichus" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="craspedotrichus">G. craspedotrichus</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, 2002a in antenna II calceoli absent; pereopods III and IV with straight setae on posterior margins; and both rami of uropod III with plumose setae on inner margins. It differs from 
<taxonomicName id="8DB5016CFBA60A7E28268078BEDECA47" genus="G." lsidName="G. craspedotrichus" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="craspedotrichus">G. craspedotrichus</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName id="3AEF7CD0151ABF0A6A402DC0A6D80FFB" genus="G." lsidName="G. craspedotrichus" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="craspedotrichus">G. craspedotrichus</taxonomicName>
in parentheses) by peduncle of antenna II with setae along ventral margin, setae as long as 
<normalizedToken id="091F5484A3C7F15D09588C5EBFE97AF7" originalValue="article’s">article's</normalizedToken>
diameter (antenna II with long setae along ventral margin, setae as long as three times of 
<normalizedToken id="25E2116FB411CD7A6E1ED0D0C9316928" originalValue="article’s">article's</normalizedToken>
diameter); uropod I peduncle with one basofacial spine (without basofacial spine); inner ramus of uropod III 0.5 times the length of outer ramus (as long as first article of outer ramus); terminal article of outer ramus of uropod III subequal to adjacent spines (shorter); and urosomites 
<normalizedToken id="12DE76AE4BF40BCB49ACB8BA361BF742" originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
with four clusters of dorsal spines and setae (with two clusters of dorsal spines and setae).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="69924CCED60289D78136EF945A9BCD1E" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<taxonomicName id="801B8FAD91D5FF5F35921F05DF8E79A8" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n. is also similar to 
<taxonomicName id="2BB29F8CEDB9A31DB0D58395FA814477" genus="G." lsidName="G. emeiensis" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="emeiensis">G. emeiensis</taxonomicName>
Hou, Li &amp; Koenemann, 2002 in antenna II calceoli absent; epimeral plate II with blunt posterodistal corner and plate III with subacute posterodistal corner; peduncle of uropod I with one basofacial spine; and terminal article of outer ramus of uropod III approx. as long as adjacent spines of first article. It can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName id="77F576647D88165B6D56D70009ADD0E1" genus="G." lsidName="G. emeiensis" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="emeiensis">G. emeiensis</taxonomicName>
by the following characters (
<taxonomicName id="FA1BB7A6D2D009E60D8CFC881703A6F0" genus="G." lsidName="G. emeiensis" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="emeiensis">G. emeiensis</taxonomicName>
in parentheses): second article of left palp of maxilla I with seven slender spines apically (seven slender spines and three stiff setae); pereopod III with short setae on posterior margin (with long setae on posterior margin); and inner ramus of uropod III 0.5 times the length of outer ramus (0.74 times the length of first article of outer ramus).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7061D5933494762AF26AB9A177FBDD36" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
The new species of 
<taxonomicName id="7F79BD3E5CB32D141817FE12C8A97D02" class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus vallecula" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vallecula">Gammarus vallecula</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, sp. n. can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName id="B787D8B0421E63D8A80B4E44CD46CC79" genus="G." lsidName="G. martensi" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="martensi">G. martensi</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, 2004a which was collected on the summit of the Qinling by the following characters (
<taxonomicName id="F26DA89D75F3EF039460459CC636AD5F" genus="G." lsidName="G. martensi" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="martensi">G. martensi</taxonomicName>
in parentheses): antenna II flagellum with a few setae, calceoli absent (with flag-like brush of setae, calceoli present); merus and carpus of pereopods 
<normalizedToken id="8D65F776F17F49728163326A4C24D0B4" originalValue="V–VII">V-VII</normalizedToken>
with few marginal setae (with marginal setae); and uropod III inner ramus approx. half of outer ramus, both with a few plumose setae on inner margins (inner ramus 0.75 times as long as outer ramus, both rami densely with plumose setae on inner and outer margins).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>