<document id="E82EEE2DC4CCCD7BC6C249D462297592" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9ff557b9-e220-41a4-84b7-eb1ac4ae2fcb" ModsDocID="21380" checkinTime="1243372374881" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Schatz, G. E., Lowry, P. P. &amp; Wolf, A. - E." docDate="2001" docId="8F8DA8B9AD087E5DB1280C9DCAAE6A56" docLanguage="en" docName="21380" docOrigin="Adansonia 23" docSource="http://www.mnhn.fr/publication/adanson/a01n2a1.pdf" docTitle="Leptolaena pauciflora" docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageNumber="185" masterDocId="2F51780DD7A081814C7B519960B5F62B" masterDocTitle="Endemic families of Madagascar. VII. A synoptic revision of Leptolaena Thouars sensu stricto (Sarcolaenaceaea)." masterLastPageNumber="189" masterPageNumber="171" pageNumber="185" updateTime="1569525776785" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="83533784A7988A5177E3AE9823785624" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="9245C1DED5E6BBB1A45550F47920D312">
<mods:title id="3DCA28397F95A0478CA5620F75D1B1E9">Endemic families of Madagascar. VII. A synoptic revision of Leptolaena Thouars sensu stricto (Sarcolaenaceaea).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="43B9283E455F2BA6DB65BC488702832A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="BE0BAADD773BAF6850C2E738EC85E7A1">
<mods:roleTerm id="925F2AAF46055DA795CD716AE4D76161">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C887D645035C11E4D8A9C8B59A69A8D6">Schatz, G. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="7A389915FFA42CD11F3F9D89C9868ED7" type="personal">
<mods:role id="7FB3C9A751EB43ABE140D1A70B5EBEEF">
<mods:roleTerm id="2F9E3F96ED23379E4246A692F704A5A3">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="A9249A026CAF9E44316EF54018DFD87E">Lowry, P. P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="802B336C53AF0E4D8B08AA7ED1382651" type="personal">
<mods:role id="634584615322923D814BDAE6D174FF4A">
<mods:roleTerm id="E0CD91ECC28245AB6447B31FB505411F">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0E105292F45794D6928B71CA3E879689">Wolf, A. - E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="F301A48DA808292234A7BF8EA04DC493">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="406135D8E92227C418ACD87EAD272633" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="EE82F2802AC9B02A32C20B06E8B67913">
<mods:title id="E1A204B9D2A4AAE2B7D7A46F978DD2D3">Adansonia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="71DF76BE883AFE3730C5B19D87E630E5">
<mods:date id="4BCCE6488F7CCEF39D42A3441EAD04FB">2001</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="6DC940602FDE3134AE1118E157F43027" type="volume">
<mods:number id="A436110AD470D4496C6240FBAFBB7770">23</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="D75803E6791EBAD22D7941F00F253DEC" unit="page">
<mods:start id="9073A19ECCEE003B1E3B0151BD802F84">171</mods:start>
<mods:end id="C0341E7C82515D177F9074181FF1D154">189</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="5D7213B355C0F9B632CF22F8189D6E39">
<mods:url id="8EE0AE6332705A312AADCEF78A9DC934">http://www.mnhn.fr/publication/adanson/a01n2a1.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="343187B41088C84CD76B9EC6B4E45B3E">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="13E88EE60373AFA1CC44DA2DD5F90952" type="HNS-PUB">21380</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="8F8DA8B9AD087E5DB1280C9DCAAE6A56" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:8F8DA8B9AD087E5DB1280C9DCAAE6A56" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F8DA8B9AD087E5DB1280C9DCAAE6A56">
<subSubSection id="E0D0C5628CB84E175C6AAB285154C101" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="14743A71D2B9146921EC9C4F85FE1323" pageNumber="185">
7. 
<taxonomicName id="9731167264E7DF045B8A1B3D1190F06F" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="pauciflora">Leptolaena pauciflora Baker</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E4FEB3A0F9BF8DF7676299C41FB77487" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="70E08C0ED3C5710C0032A2FAB7FC1782" pageNumber="185">J. Linn. Soc. Bot. 20: 96, 97 (1883).Lectotype (here designated): Baron 1390, Madagascar, in forests of the province of Imerina (K!; iso-, MO!, P (3 sheets)!).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5ADFFF103C59C4E53990D17BA5D3C6A6" pageNumber="185">
<taxonomicName id="5FF2BA084BADD21E9FFDED1A4FF4C4ED" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="turbinata">Leptolaena turbinata Baker</taxonomicName>
, J. Linn. Soc. Bot. 20: 97 (1883).
<taxonomicName id="103091B71914095A35BCE8C5141AE75E" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="variety" species="pauciflora" variety="turbinata">Leptolaena pauciflora var. turbinata (Baker)</taxonomicName>
H. Perrier, Bull. Soc. Bot. France 78: 60 (1931).Type: Baron 1560, Madagascar, East coast (holo-, K!; iso-, P!).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8D1E5CF86C4454FBFD57899C75395E6A" pageNumber="185">
<taxonomicName id="C7FFBA01D843601E85828246AB077D04" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="parviflora">Leptolaena parviflora</taxonomicName>
Scott-Elliot, J. Linn. Soc. Bot. 29: 6 (1891).Lectotype (here designated): ScottElliot 2554, Madagascar, woods near Fort Dauphin (K!; iso-, P (2 sheets)!).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="950C6D974F9D466A9373A820149057A0" pageNumber="185">
<taxonomicName id="9087AAEF98C8E9E550569BE5DF07974C" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="rubella">Leptolaena rubella</taxonomicName>
Scott-Elliot, J. Linn. Soc. Bot. 29: 7 (1891).
<taxonomicName id="5E4C1E2DE5B6C83A6F1D6C878E798472" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="variety" species="pauciflora" variety="rubella">Leptolaena pauciflora var. rubella</taxonomicName>
(ScottElliot) H. Perrier, Bull. Soc. Bot. France 78: 60 (1931).Type: Scott-Elliot 2369, Madagascar, woods near Fort Dauphin (holo-, K!; iso-, P (2 sheets)!).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3555955A4586BF1F2E34E48A1DD356BB" type="description">
<paragraph id="C2EBA5936CAAD40868577F1DB03F9EED" pageNumber="185">
<taxonomicName id="4D2A4F6462F0C8B65A4D982E2DDC07FE" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="pauciflora">Leptolaena pauciflora</taxonomicName>
is a small shrub to medium-sized tree occurring from humid littoral forest at sea level to subhumid and montane woodland and thicket up to 2,300 m (Fig. 3). Other than habit, it is remarkably uniform in vegetative and reproductive characters throughout its broad ecological range, and is easily recognized by its small, broadly ovate to circular or rhombic leaves usually not exceeding 2 cm in length.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FDDADD41CCCE1E168B30B74C037BB15A" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="FED5A06DBFD7CEE894BF5DA0495045AE" pageNumber="185">
Of the two syntypes cited in the protologue of 
<taxonomicName id="E76A44469A30E94B52E753A1D8775A85" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="pauciflora">L. pauciflora</taxonomicName>
(Baron 1390 and Meller s. n.), the former is here chosen as the lectotype. Syntypes were also cited for 
<taxonomicName id="A6A997BF1176A37902AD88F38FA590CB" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="parviflora">L. parviflora</taxonomicName>
(Scott-Elliot 2554 and Scott-Elliot 2713), the first of which is here chosen as the lectotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="904BBA487A088589FE22FCCF3A59C933" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="7B278514E5EDBA1C3079651ED8A7235C" pageNumber="185">Vernacular names.Amaninambilahy, Anjananjana, Anjananjanalahy, Fotina, Foto, Fotona, Fotona Madinidravina, Fotondahy, Hazomaritra, Laro, Madiorano, Milaliambomadinika, Taolandaro.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3E336C816048562A9CA768C271427A3B" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph id="EE15629BBDBF5BAAE277327AFB5787DD" pageNumber="185">
Conservation status.With an extent of occurrence far exceeding 20,000 km 2, and c. 33 sub-populations, six of which are present in protected areas, 
<taxonomicName id="5F4E8F84B6A3BCFF57A57C47E13E27E8" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Sarcolaenaceae" genus="Leptolaena" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" order="Huerteales" pageNumber="185" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="pauciflora">L. pauciflora</taxonomicName>
is considered not threatened, and assigned a preliminary status of Lower Risk (LR).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="25C5D46631355B3809CD2490E70740C2" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="54966FC5E59D8C5F8F57D94E525087D3" lastPageNumber="186" pageNumber="185">Material examined.Baron 1390, 1560, 2624, Meller s. n., without precise locality; Andrianjafy 11, Andranofeno-Sud; Barnett 502, Mt. Ibity; Benoist 759, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Boiteau 2568, Mahialambo; Bosser 7944, Tampoketsa d'Ankazobe; Bosser 9969, Sahatsio; Bosser 14138, pic St. Louis; Bosser 15978, Tampoketsa; Bosser 18772, col des Tapias; Cours 2981, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Cours 4646, Didy; Cremers 1624, 2020, Ambohitantely RS; Cremers 2311, Marosiky; Croat 29218, Antsirabe; Croat 29910, Itremo; Decary 4026, 4038, Fort-Dauphin; Decary 6353, 6388, 6502, 6508, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Decary 7302, Ankazobe; Decary 7473, Ambohitantely RS; Decary 10011, pic Saint Louis; Decary 13063, 13226, Ambatofinandrahana; Decary 14023, 14036, Faliarivo; Decary 14927, Tampoketsa d'Ankazobe; Decary 17214, Manankazo STF; Decary 17311, Ambositra; Decary 17333, Ambatofinandrahana; Decary 17403, Ambositra; Descoings 338, Fort-Dauphin; Dorr 3842, col des Tapias; Edmondson 95 - 57, Mandena STF; Geay 7507, 7618, 7707, 7926, 8708 Mananjary; Gentry 11363, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Gentry 11836, Ambohitantely RS; Gereau 3294, Evatra; Gereau 3423, Manafiafy; Gereau 5690, Anjozorobe; Harder 1536, Anjozorobe; Humbert 4640, col des Tapias; Humbert 5864, Enivaha; Humbert 5899, pic St. Louis; Humbert 7111, col des Tapias; Humbert 11090, Ambohitantely RS; Humbert 13835, Andohahela RNI; Humbert 14080, Imonty; Humbert 14477, Faliarivo; Humbert 20623, Ampasimena; Humbert 20702, Vohimavo; Humbert 28059, Ambatofinandrahana; Humbert 29938, Itremo; Jacquemin 934, Ambavarano; Jacquemin 1158, Mandromodromotra; Johnson WII 33, Mandena STF; Jongkind 828, 932, col des Tapias; Keraudren 1062, pic Saint Louis; Keraudren 24894, 24997, Fort Dauphin; Keraudren 25712, IvatoAmbatofinandrahana; Keraudren 26009, Itremo; Labat 3010, col des Tapias; Leeuwenberg 14443, c. 20 km Ivato-Itremo; Leeuwenberg 14589, AmbilaLemaitso STF; Leeuwenberg 14648, Anjozorobe; Lewis 728, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Louvel 33 bis, Analamazaotra-Perinet RS; Lowry 4375, 4397, Anjozorobe, 5215, Mandena STF; McPherson 14164, Ste. Luce; McPherson 14278, Analalava (Manantenina); Messmer 781, Itremo; Miller 8777, Anjozorobe; Morat 3315, Ivato; Morat 4411, Andohahela RNI; Morat 4512, Antsiatsiaka; Peltier 2159, Fiadanana; Peltier 2184, Anjoma; Perrier de la Bdthie 3004, Andringitra RNI; Perrier de la Bdthie 3007, Ambatofinandrahana; Perrier de la Bdthie 3012, Matatana; Perrier de la Bdthie 4488, Vatovavy; Perrier de la Bdthie 5337, Manankazo STF; Perrier de la Bdthie 5341, Ibity; Perrier de la Bdthie 5342, Tamatave; Perrier de la Bdthie 13180, Tsitondroina; Perrier de la Bdthie 13213, Beveromay; Perrier de la Bdthie 13574, Ibity; Phillipson 1850, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Rabenantoandro 62, Itremo; Rabevohitra 3770, Mahabo; Rakotoarisoa 22, 32, Ambatofinandrahana; Rakotoarisoa 59, Faliarivo FC; Rakotozafy 2682, Anjozorobe; Randriamampionona 331, 569, Andohahela RNI; Randriamanantena 119, Andohahela RNI; Randrianaivo 75, Ambohitantely RS; A. Randrianasolo 224, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; A. Randrianasolo 232, Ivato; A. Randrianasolo 283, Manantantely; A. Randrianasolo 347, Manafiafy; Rauh 1445, FortDauphin; Reserves Naturelles 13 - RN-XI, Andohahela RNI; Reserves Naturelles 168, 202, Ambohitantely RS; Reserves Naturelles 706, Andringitra RNI; Reserves Naturelles 1416, 1499, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Reserves Naturelles 6507, Andringitra RNI; Reserves Naturelles 6706, Ambohitantely RS; Reserves Naturelles 7166, Andringitra RNI; Reserves Naturelles 11247, Zahamena RNI; Reserves Naturelles 11691, Andringitra RNI; Schatz 1320, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Schatz 2961, Anjozorobe; Schatz 3955, Ankafobe; Schatz 3964, Itremo; Schedl 133, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Scott-Elliot 2369, 2554, 2713, 2713 bis, 2753, Fort-Dauphin; Service Forestier 3 - R- 3, Ambohitantely RS; Service Forestier 54 - R- 10, Itremo; Service Forestier 232, Manandona; Service Forestier 1078, 1122, 1569, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Service Forestier 2155, Fianarantsoa; Service Forestier 2708, Ampandrambato; Service Forestier 3259, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Service Forestier 3267, Mahanoro; Service Forestier 3811, Anosivelo; Service Forestier 4157, 4707, 4711, AmbilaLemaitso STF; Service Forestier 4829, Mangatsiatra; Service Forestier 4887, 4908, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Service Forestier 5625, Vohipaho; Service Forestier 5631, Marohita; Service Forestier 5737, AmbilaLemaitso STF; Service Forestier 6077, Mandena STF; Service Forestier 7035, Mananjary; Service Forestier 7258, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Service Forestier 7292, Misevo; Service Forestier 7419, Mandena STF; Service Forestier 7598, Fierenana; Service Forestier 7771, Mandromodromotra; Service Forestier 7820, Mandena STF; Service Forestier 8416, Ambohitantely RS; Service Forestier 9506, Ampangalana Atsimo; Service Forestier 9540, Marohita; Service Forestier 9592, Ambohitantely RS; Service Forestier 9647, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Service Forestier 9668, Manantenina; Service Forestier 11542, Faliarivo; Service Forestier 12988, Vatovary (= Vatovory); Service Forestier 13180, Ambila-Lemaitso STF; Service Forestier 13472, Ankijana; Service Forestier 13701, Ampangalana Atsimo; Service Forestier 14047, Antanambao; Service Forestier 14661, Nosy-Varika; Service Forestier 14670, Analalava; Service Forestier 14763, Ankijana; Service Forestier 15156, Anjozorobe; Service Forestier 15806, Sahavoay; Service Forestier 16113, Nosy-Varika; Service Forestier 16119, Ambazato; Service Forestier 16806, Manankazo STF; Service Forestier 18361, Ambohitantely RS; Service Forestier 18771, Manohilahy; Service Forestier 19626, Iamboala; Service Forestier 19695, Ambohimanana; Service Forestier 19874, Ambohitantely RS; Service Forestier 22456, Andohahela RNI; Service Forestier 25366, Ampasimpotsy STF; Service Forestier 32214, AmbilaLemaitso STF; Service Forestier 34202, Ambohitantely RS; Zarucchi 7345, Anjozorobe; Zarucchi 7411, Ambila-Lemaitso STF.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>