<document id="F5DBD0DD5D9FA7F6B3FF9576CE155595" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a503b11a-2446-4eb1-8c52-0be37806a642" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051544" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-387-33" ID-ZBK="462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D8B43827-4941-42D9-8DF4-860ECA76A259" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-387-33" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 387" ModsDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" checkinTime="1451246192135" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan F. &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2014" docId="92496D91087EA3118D7519D35E5F1A16" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 387: 33-49" docOrigin="ZooKeys 387" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827" docTitle="Cymatodera mitae Burke, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="D8B43827-4941-42D9-8DF4-860ECA76A259" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="45" masterDocId="FFBDFF91FFAAFF8DFFBA9E66E77FFFFD" masterDocTitle="Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)" masterLastPageNumber="49" masterPageNumber="33" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" updateTime="1643670665773" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="804C28F435607734FD98E7E9332B0346" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="816CCE200CE4E313C55661DDCA532922">
<mods:title id="BD249BD8A95D04907C8472EB4F417092">Four new species of Cymatodera Gray from Mexico (Coleoptera, Cleridae, Tillinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="C513CC6C348DD49803F0AD9D5A3555CC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F62B95EF7D288ECCBBC48428410C79D7">
<mods:roleTerm id="C4A4EE5C18F06CEFA59A14557770CAD7">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="CD241DC7FA9729DFDCB81C2C1391E75C">Burke, Alan F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="E84B01BDFC37A9566CC867760D48FDEB" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D15B8DAE40AF53CAB82CA2A9E65546E3">
<mods:roleTerm id="A0F413E52004D5599DE988F352FD6D06">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0E6FD0624ABF3D109DD82685D9699672">Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="369168BD5CCA0677CE5BCE18A722835B">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="75AD82D6E081E16D885860C4921B63D9" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="0D223C83EA9EA8C22A4419DBC82ADF2D">
<mods:title id="6CF93235FE7D49C35B8A2A4C6752F655">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="4FA6CCAC9ECC6A8AF678C3B1795757ED">
<mods:date id="6AC7728E368A6539F3C8800DFBDC4E7B">2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="5723C8FA161BB76984AAE25A032257A1" type="volume">
<mods:number id="F206D1A9638BC2DE4C656D8AD3A0B8FF">387</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="809406E391A858797A84CF65D4C0581B" unit="page">
<mods:start id="583AA4AD953C9035BC39317BA9C39705">33</mods:start>
<mods:end id="BD91A5455C95DE1869D96BBF3C5BF99E">49</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="B6F2D3DBD2552BB8CE80A21039F4F34A">
<mods:url id="B002FCE73A278AA72B8E0175C1BC1B04">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="C13AC4906EA89874DB494191856A1634">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="DECE41ED8BD269762455BA8E43D37264" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.387.6827</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="6322375655A11A9A420100AFB5C55402" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-387-33</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E03E35DB43C4664EA4745F527F3B3EDB" type="ZBK">462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="D5E46B5322B5E0714C07055AD3653F1F" type="ZooBank">462836DE651F47528897C8F1A0E41C73</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="92496D91087EA3118D7519D35E5F1A16" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051544" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D8B43827-4941-42D9-8DF4-860ECA76A259" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/92496D91087EA3118D7519D35E5F1A16" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">
<subSubSection id="928E0CF1B34F36C1B42F390853710EA9" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="34E862A925C359D1CD0C8390B5FD5414" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">
<taxonomicName id="3F16872D800E7309563BCB029B11ADA8" LSID="http://zoobank.org/D8B43827-4941-42D9-8DF4-860ECA76A259" authority="Burke" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera mitae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mitae">
<pageBreakToken id="F463F8402F2C4840E8D45B1C55A72F18" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" start="start">Cymatodera</pageBreakToken>
mitae Burke
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="A9BCEAEF757B98E7AE8B9C7FD95C4B30" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 3, 8, 13, 20, 21, 28, 32, 33
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="989B212BDC747843C3C9344CADD952D7" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" type="type material">
<paragraph id="07AD3FEDE786B7DBF026B10FD9D374B8" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6E3B73B1827F1B663EB09E14B748475F" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">Holotype: male, Mexico, Nayarit, 2 km NE Punta de Mita, 26-VII-1990, R. L. Westcott, printed red label, holotype deposited in CSCA. Paratypes: 2 males and 3 females. 2 females and 1 male: Mexico, Nayarit, 2 km E Punta de Mita, 30-VII to 2-VIII-1993, C. L. Bellamy (JNRC); 1 female: Mexico, Jalisco, 2 km N Cuitzamala, 10-IX-1988, on dead wood, F. T. Hovore (CNCI). 1 male: Mexico, Nayarit, Playa Piedra Blanca, vicinity of Punta de Mita, 22-VII-1993, tropical deciduous forest, mercury vapor and black light, Rifkind, Bellamy and Reifshneider (JNRC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E2C923C55F30DB934F0F224510E6CEF2" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph id="631EFA760FEA922FD4C6F31D6D6AF6C4" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7807921004F5C469B4B432F92870D77D" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">
This species can be distinguished from congeners by its small size (Fig. 3), antennomeres 4-10 gradually becoming serrate distally, and the conspicuously robust and elongate eleventh antennomere (Fig. 8). The fifth and sixth abdominal segments (Figs 20-21) and genitalia (Fig. 13) of the male also serve to separate this species from remaining 
<taxonomicName id="89C9A3B311FCB81DB5BCB7B19DB316D7" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Cymatodera</taxonomicName>
species. Together with 
<taxonomicName id="7A4ED4F960658140F9AE7691EBC6EDE8" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera bogcioides" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bogcioides">Cymatodera bogcioides</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="59F9817AF3A97454B35612991342A30F" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera mitae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mitae">Cymatodera mitae</taxonomicName>
is part of a group of species characterized by a broad, rather deep carina that extends transversely across the first visible ventrite of males (Figs 30, 32).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4C401D1524916AFBCECCCA1D775E8465" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="44" pageId="9" pageNumber="42" type="description">
<paragraph id="F0E90C18B877879480F140B1050DAFCA" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E7070E3C796F64F5F31EE26E85793587" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">Holotype. Small, somewhat robust, posterior wings fully developed, TL = 7.75 mm. Color: head, pronotum, prosternum, mesosternum and metasternum ferruginous-brown, remainder of body uniformly brown. Each elytron with a brown macula located on humeral angle and a pair of irregular, obliquely directed fasciae located on median region of elytral length, the first fascia diffuse, yellowish-testaceous, extending from first stria to epipleuron, the second black, posteriorly adjacent to first fascia, extending from second stria to seventh stria (Fig. 3).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3EA1996B746ADF338010DD88E10A6280" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">
Head: HL = 0.7 mm, HW = 1.35 mm. Measured across eyes wider than pronotum; surface moderately rugose; frons bi-impressed; moderately, coarsely punctate; vested with short, recumbent setae and occasional long, semierect setae behind eyes; eyes rather rounded, moderately large, somewhat longer than wide, feebly emarginate in front, bulging laterally. Antennae not reaching posterior margin of pronotum; first antennomere 0.75
<normalizedToken id="F6D486E330B14049CE8D7CA36FB1A2B2" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than second antennomere, third antennomere about equal in length to first antennomere; fourth antennomere slightly shorter than third antennomere; antennomeres 4-10 subequal in length; antennomeres 2-4 subcylindrical; antennomeres 4-10 gradually becoming serrate toward distal end; last antennomere somewhat robust, cylindrical, about the same length as preceding three antennomeres (Fig. 8).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EE19C167424AE27E36FDEF3657CC3EFD" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="9" pageNumber="42">
Thorax: PL = 1.95 mm, PW = 1.25 mm. Pronotum rugose; moderately, finely punctate; less coarsely punctate than head; anterior margin as wide as middle; sides constricted subapically; slightly more constricted behind middle; disc flat, inconspicuously impressed in front of middle; subbasal tumescence moderately produced; surface clothed with moderately long, semierect setae interspersed with long semierect 
<pageBreakToken id="A03C893B00EEED1899E580F5F4598F03" pageId="10" pageNumber="43" start="start">and</pageBreakToken>
erect setae. Prosternum smooth, shiny, feebly, shallowly punctate. Mesosternum smooth, shiny; moderately, shallowly punctate. Metasternum with surface rugulose, shiny, moderately, shallowly puncticulate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7009BB85E12B3154CC16D31ABE2CE148" pageId="11" pageNumber="44">
<pageBreakToken id="6733A6966EC084B6A5DC31B5706F79B4" pageId="11" pageNumber="44" start="start">Legs</pageBreakToken>
: Moderately vested with semirecumbent and semierect setae of three sizes; femora somewhat puncticulate, rugulose; tibia moderately, shallowly punctate, rugulose; fourth pulvillus medially incised, incision not extending beyond apical third.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D44B595BF73E891C627370D2BA382479" pageId="11" pageNumber="44">
Elytra: EL = 5.1 mm, EW = 2.35 mm. Broader than pronotum; humeri indicated, rounded; sides subparallel; widest portion behind middle; disc flattened above; surface shiny, rugulose; apices rounded; somewhat dehiscent; elytral declivity gradual; clothed with short, semierect setae intermixed with long, semierect and erect setae, long setae more abundant on anterior 1/4 of elytral ground; sculpture consisting of coarse punctations arranged in regular striae that gradually become smaller and shallower on posterior 1/4 of elytral gound, punctations not reaching elytral apex; interstices at elytral base about 2
<normalizedToken id="C52A0CF2626B376877E079C652BFA4BF" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
the width of punctuation.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CDA83E2AB4DABD04DD222D024D3F3EC0" pageId="11" pageNumber="44">Abdomen: Ventrites 1-5 rugulose; strongly, finely punctate; clothed with short, fine, recumbent setae. First ventrite rather convex; subquadrate, posterior margin conspicuously elevated with a transverse carina that initiates on posterolateral angles, producing a broad, deep, arcuate emargination (Fig. 32). Second visible ventrite convex; subquadrate; posterior margin feebly elevated with a longitudinal carina producing a moderately broad, rather deep, arcuate emargination. Fifth visible ventrite moderately convex; subquadrate; surface shiny, moderately, shallowly, finely punctate; lateral margins oblique; posterolateral angles rounded; posterior margin truncate with a median, narrow, shallow emargination (Fig. 20). Sixth visible ventrite small; broader than long; surface feebly convex, shiny; moderately, finely and shallowly punctate; lateral margins strongly convex, hind margin reduced, shallowly, broadly emarginate. Fifth tergite subquadrate, rugulose; lateral margin subparallel, posterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate (Fig. 21). Sixth tergite subtriangular, broader than long; surface rugulose; lateral margins strongly oblique. Sixth tergite extending beyond apical margin of sixth visible ventrite; base of sixth visible ventrite extending laterally, slightly farther than sixth tergite. Aedeagus: 0.9 mm long; robust; ratio of length of paramere to whole tegmen 0.39: 1; tegmen partially covering phallus; parameres moderately robust; lateral margins obtuse, pointed distally; phallobase wide; phallic plate armed with a long row of large, sharp denticles along dorsal margin; phallobasic apodeme slender, moderately short; endophallic struts slender throughout their length (Fig. 13).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="76003057A2435FDD928A8D41400281E8" pageId="11" pageNumber="44">Females in the type series have the first visible ventrite posteriorly truncate and slightly longer than males, and lack the transverse carina (Fig. 33) present in males (Fig. 32). The second visible ventrite also lacks the moderately elevated carina observed in males. Fifth visible ventrite rugulose; lateral margins rather arcuate, feebly oblique; posterior margin truncate and medially narrowly, very shallowly emarginate; sixth visible ventrite rugulose, feebly convex; semicircular; lateral and posterior margins broadly rounded (Fig. 28); fifth tergite rugulose, subtriangular; lateral margins moderately oblique; posterior margin shallowly, broadly, triangularly emarginate. Sixth tergite subtriangular; rugulose; broader than long; surface inconspicuously convex; lateral margins rather arcuate, strongly oblique; posterior margin arcuate, rendering a rather continuous and semicircular posterolateral margin. Sixth tergite extending beyond sixth visible ventrite.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D7B169A01C5B5777DB31832D88635E5A" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="11" pageNumber="44" type="variation">
<paragraph id="6BC3E470B6F2837B143DC68E93B7F2F1" pageId="11" pageNumber="44">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A19E0FF3E9702BFFAB5C093A4148EDF5" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="11" pageNumber="44">
Length of males 6.9-8.1 mm, length of females 7.15-8.7 mm; n = 6. Length to width ratio of head: males average 0.59, females average 0.66. Length to 
<pageBreakToken id="FC6FF2FD786C782E42EE2042C44EE4AB" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" start="start">width</pageBreakToken>
ratio of thorax: males average 1.6, females average 1.62. Length to width ratio of elytra: males average 2.18, females average 2.21.Two males and one female show a slightly darker integument on the elytral disc; also, these individuals display the humeral maculae completely black, rather than dark brown, as seen in the holotype. One male in the type series displays a feebly paler coloration on the elytral disc. The black fascia is variably marked among individuals, ranging from strongly marked to rather diffuse.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9B471ACAC14319FD63561F7B3258EE7B" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="40EAF28E4C9B9BFF6E85A45BC32E90A4" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="305460D74CDEFE40CABBCD250722478C" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">The type series was collected primarily in Punta Mita, at the southwestern tip of the state of Nayarit, Mexico. One female specimen was collected in the Cuitzmala region of Jalisco, about 50 km southeast of Punta Mita, Nayarit (Fig. 34).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="72F0C7CAEDA68F417977996D98D93A9A" pageId="12" pageNumber="45" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="5D87C52C991D2DFC8F9FB0EF0F86E7B2" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="68DD4F459856620943D7CDB83698D336" pageId="12" pageNumber="45">The specific epithet refers to Punta Mita, Nayarit, Mexico, the locality where the holotype was collected.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>