<document id="CEE43751544A904F49F9992E9A5C70F4" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bdfb4b8e-4c36-4386-a7d0-7437b44fcba1" ModsDocID="21061" checkinTime="1252706925963" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Heterick, B. E." docDate="2006" docId="93833FD1A2A60D66CB802310D681387D" docLanguage="en" docName="21061.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 57" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf" docTitle="Monomorium notorthotenes Heterick, 2006, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="93" masterDocId="3A2C4F9A5833769B5007E7556E53E380" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="202" masterPageNumber="69" pageNumber="91" updateTime="1569525778780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="BAB99CD426E39DEB7551B9B3EFBF348A" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="0D2A9FFD159756A71354A0AEBF418CB4">
<mods:title id="B60314ED1BDE4817D890649424495512">A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="3B043776824E51A35647C557BDC3DA3D" type="personal">
<mods:role id="05B6515D7B2C57CA890A8F56C34B0499">
<mods:roleTerm id="19BFC615FC87AB0663AA2F13E0147B55">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2C4C28885D3AA60600D516DC738EEC57">Heterick, B. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="54D599AFDEC8F4CE02C80D961B4A80BB">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="5A206AED0B7E3C5A56BDA92B78DFBF0D" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="8A74BF83F8DB0730D7067BFEC4B85782">
<mods:title id="64DB12F05C4CEEA99BF365BAAA2D1875">Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="B684355617712CF783F64AF76F12ACB8">
<mods:date id="E2997BD201EB407869B09EBBD5E7A3C4">2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="C415674CCC5A57ED9BCAEC14DC22CFFF" type="volume">
<mods:number id="3CF72A9D19CDA11E57C894D23953A2F6">57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="25F87736E26C7CB13144399CB81215F2" unit="page">
<mods:start id="4C65FA0F5535CDFFC73355ACDBFC1C5F">69</mods:start>
<mods:end id="12A2F3ECCA996DEDD820F78CF543CDD6">202</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="44B23B6D64669F62F98D5FF83C4495EC">
<mods:url id="750BF40D5B2E3179C7E20BA949BBD109">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="F5CC9588AF9CDBCA0986FA273CECB0C3">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="ACF841B47DCD19700A2873AEBF35FC96" type="HNS-PUB">21061</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="93833FD1A2A60D66CB802310D681387D" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:93833FD1A2A60D66CB802310D681387D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/93833FD1A2A60D66CB802310D681387D">
<subSubSection id="3A930533D7F31F283E0FFC6CA4A790E5" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="E0883DF212462C11C759B9D3F9D3CAB2" pageNumber="91">
<taxonomicName id="76DD1249E764B2BC0E662033E18713EA" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196243" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium notorthotenes Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium notorthotenes Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="notorthotenes">Monomorium notorthotenes Heterick</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="382952C2ED051073369224062FB0D1F0" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D2A8C7ABFE31DC5620EBFA6E6FB93C65" type="description">
<paragraph id="FE9CC0C799D587FB8B330AABEDF1BF9C" pageNumber="91">Figs. 14, 85-89.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="056556A0623DD9410DB15578867C86B5" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="0A6C1B16E24F045B29B4EE8F0E5DE005" pageNumber="91">Etymology.- Greek &quot;noton&quot; (neut. &quot;back&quot;) + &quot;orthotenes&quot; (&quot;stretched out&quot;)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="50D026119B665C38DC0D051254EDA5B2" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="E116B4990CA9CD3F8760D0C43A7FDC70" pageNumber="91">Material examined.- Holotype: [[worker]], Prov. Toliara, Res Cap Sainte Marie 14.9 km 261 W Marovato 25°36'S, 45°09'E, 160 m. 13-19.ii.2002, Fisher et al. BLF# 5740/under stone spiny forest/thicket/ CASENT 0002257 (CAS). Paratypes: Prov. Toliara (all specimens with same collection data as holotype): 1x2 [[worker]] (one with head missing) (ANIC); 1x2 [[worker]] (BMNH); 1 [[queen]]+2[[male]] (5741) (CAS); 2 [[worker]]+1 [[queen]] (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5F7BED3D32E9BB61CE17895D78D45F0E" pageNumber="91">Other material examined: Prov. Toliara: Cap Sainte Marie 14.9 km 261 W Marovato, 13-19.ii.2002, Fisher et al. (23[[worker]], 4[[queen]], 3[[male]]); Foret Tsinjoriaka [&quot;Tsinjoriaky&quot;], 6.2 km 84 E Tsifota 6-10.iii.2002 Fisher et al. (27 [[worker]], 6 [[queen]], 6[[male]]); 4.4 km 148 SSE Lavanono, 17.ii.2002, Fisher et al. (37 [[worker]], 4 [[queen]], 4[[male]]); Mahafaly [&quot;Mahafely&quot;] Plateau 6.2 km 74 ENE Itampolo, 21-25ii.2002, Fisher et al. (48 [[worker]], 4 [[queen]], 3 [[male]]); Tsimanampetsotsa, Bemanateza, 23.0 km 131 SE Beheloka, 22-26.iii.2002 B.L. Fisher (15 [[worker]], 1[[queen]]).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8CEA21FEFA73D12CF7FA80054F268AEC" type="description">
<paragraph id="3FA53E520AE029CE0459FDBBEBB5F3FB" pageNumber="91">Worker description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex planar; frons shining and finely striolate and microreticulate; pilosity of frons consisting mainly of short, appressed setulae with a few stout, erect and semi-erect setae on vertex. Eye large, eye width 1.5x greater than greatest width of antennal scape; (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set around midline of head capsule; eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin. Antennal segments 12; antennal club four-segmented. Clypeal carinae indistinct; anteromedian clypeal margin broadly convex; paraclypeal setae moderately long and fine, curved; posteromedian clypeal margin approximately level with antennal fossae. Anterior tentorial pits situated nearer antennal fossae than mandibular insertions. Frontal lobes sinuate, divergent posteriad. Psammophore absent. Palp formula 5,3. Mandibular teeth five; mandibles triangular and striate; masticatory margin of mandibles approximately vertical or weakly oblique; basal tooth approximately same size as t4 (five teeth present).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BB980BD52D9F5DB606D59F0FB3093126" pageNumber="91">Mesosoma: Promesonotum shining and microreticulate throughout; (viewed in profile) promesonotum broadly convex; promesonotal setae seven to twelve; standing promesonotal setae consisting of short, erect or semi-erect bristles; appressed promesonotal setulae well-spaced over entire promesonotum. Metanotal groove weakly impressed, with faint costulae or costulae lacking. Propodeum shining and microreticulate; propodeal dorsum convex; propodeum smoothly rounded or with indistinct angle, but dorsal and declivitous faces separated when seen in profile; standing propodeal setae absent; appressed propodeal setulae abundant, particularly on dorsum of propodeum; propodeal spiracle equidistant from metanotal groove and declivitous face of propodeum. Vestibule of propodeal spiracle absent or not visible. Propodeal lobes present as rounded flanges.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="875B4F3351770BC1044B725909423C86" lastPageNumber="92" pageNumber="91">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle laterodorsal and situated well anteriad of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) conical, vertex tapered; appearance of node shining and distinctly microreticulate; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) between 1:1 and 3:4; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; ventral petiolar lobe absent; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole between 1:1 and 3:4; height -length ratio of postpetiole between 1:1 and 3:4; postpetiole shining and microreticulate; postpetiolar sternite not depressed at midpoint, its anterior end an inconspicuous lip or small carina.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E717B759C8DB856A5067889E7D59B3EF" pageNumber="92">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, short, thick, erect setae interspersed with minute, appressed setulae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D242C236B1D6C143679AFEBEA2616A86" pageNumber="92">General Characters: Color depigmented ochre. Worker caste monomorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F2D536DB9A77955DC028A2A7DAC6FF8D" pageNumber="92">Holotype measurements: HML 2.77 HL 0.88 HW 0.76 CeI 86 SL 0.86 SI 113 PW 0.49.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B8EE00B92A8E6A3AA6582662C6157C82" pageNumber="92">Other worker measurements: HML 2.39-2.80 HL 0.75-0.90 HW 0.62-0.78 CeI 81-86 SL 0.82-0.96 SI 115-132 PW 0.42-0.50 (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="99E9CF1357D78F8812B8BAF7EE661420" pageNumber="92">Queen description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex always planar; frons shining and smooth except for piliferous pits; pilosity of frons a mixture of well-spaced, distinctly longer erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with shorter setae or setulae, which are decumbent or appressed, longer setae thickest on vertex. Eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin;. (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set posteriad of midline of head capsule.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BE614F346D3448AEC51B1474CAAF83E9" pageNumber="92">Mesosoma: Mesoscutum broadly convex anteriad, convexity reduced posteriad; pronotum, mesoscutum and mesopleuron shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to anterior katepisternum; length -width ratio of mesoscutum and scutellum combined between 2:1 and 3:2; axillae narrowly separated (i.e., less than width of one axilla); standing pronotal/mesoscutal setae consisting of well-spaced, incurved, erect and semi-erect setae only; appressed pronotal, mescoscutal and mesopleural setulae few, mainly on dorsum of pronotum and mesoscutum. Propodeum shining and microreticulate; propodeum distinctly angulate, propodeal angles produced as short denticles; propodeal dorsum sloping posteriad, and depressed between raised propodeal angles; standing propodeal setae absent; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle equidistant from metanotal groove and declivitous face of propodeum; propodeal lobes present as vestigial flanges only, or absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="686DA2888A666F925C5BC26046262C59" pageNumber="92">Wing: Wing veins tubular and strongly sclerotised; vein m -cu present as an entire vein enclosing first discoidal cell; vein cu -a present.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AB26D19FC5497E7523E0BD87159CD0B2" pageNumber="92">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated well anteriad of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) cuneate, vertex tapered; appearance of node shining and microreticulate; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) about 4:3; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole about 1:1; height -length ratio of postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; postpetiole shining and microreticulate; postpetiolar sternite not depressed, in form of narrow, rectangular projection.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4C723D0B559811F48FE94C3163DF2F75" pageNumber="92">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, short, thick, erect setae interspersed with minute, appressed setulae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EA0C4D2C742E3438A19E9DBC9E29E47E" pageNumber="92">General Characters: Color brownish- yellow, gaster darker. Brachypterous alates not seen. Ergatoid or worker-female intercastes not seen.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BAD7E1D8D6D5023AABE0BE97698445BE" pageNumber="92">Queen measurements: HML 3.98-4.39 HL 1.14-1.21 HW 1.11-1.23 CeI 95-103 SL 1.00-1.09 SI 85-98 PW 0.90-1.04 (n=13).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DD2BEF981ABBE7E676D4EC9CE615E103" lastPageNumber="93" pageNumber="92">Male description.- Head: (In full-face view) head width-mesosoma width ratio between 4:3 and 1:1; frons finely micropunctate. Compound eyes protuberant and elliptical; margin of compound eye clearly separated from posterior margin of clypeus. Ocelli turreted. Ratio of length of first funicular segment of antenna to second funicular segment between 2:3 and 1:2. Maximum number of mandibular teeth and denticles three.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2EFE2BEEABBD3CE6CE87CDE50CD1C17D" pageNumber="93">Mesosoma: Mesoscutum broadly convex; pronotum and mesoscutum shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to lower katepisternum; parapsidal furrows vestigial or absent; notauli absent; axillae separated by width of at least one axilla.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="659A441131E29D8CB1FA0DFD1AFF59B0" pageNumber="93">Wing: Wing veins tubular and strongly sclerotised; vein m-cu absent; vein cu-a present.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A8579A3D7F11CFE3D41E738657DC3BF3" pageNumber="93">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated slightly anteriad of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) evenly tumular; appearance of node shining and smooth; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) between 4:3 and 1:1; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole about 1:1; height-length ratio of postpetiole about 3:4; postpetiole shining and smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="00325B28C443802A185FE2131BCCDF64" pageNumber="93">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, semi-erect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9B9453C0BA89941C273F10AD00E75A28" pageNumber="93">General characters: Color a depigmented ochre.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9C57C8423F0737331EE35C49C79D8C25" pageNumber="93">Male measurements: HML 2.01-2.23 HL 0.46-0.53 HW 0.48-0.54 CeI 94-106 SL 0.11-0.14 SI 21-26 PW 0.58-0.71 (n=15).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="6B9A61757A0C2EB334E3D628EE9B1215" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="0AC53ECA8559000F6FC9FF7CF04BAADD" pageNumber="93">
Remarks.- This species appears to be restricted to spiny forest and associated thickets in coastal localities in the extreme south and south-west of Madagascar. Collections have been made from colonies under stones, or of foraging workers. Workers of the species are much more uniform in appearance than those of 
<taxonomicName id="9F7044B0992FCDE82913A234B2D91580" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:24899" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium Mayr" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium Mayr" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="93" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Monomorium</taxonomicName>
detrinodis but, apart from their larger size and longer antennae, closely resemble pale workers of that ant. Superficially, workers of this species may be confused with 
<taxonomicName id="AB696DC760DFDC8FB39FF9D7428E7514" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2351" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Aphaenogaster" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Aphaenogaster Mayr" lsidName-HNS="Aphaenogaster Mayr" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="93" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Aphaenogaster</taxonomicName>
because of their elongate bodies and spindly appendages.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>