<document id="8BC639A54E4A27238739B37F152BC30C" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bdfb4b8e-4c36-4386-a7d0-7437b44fcba1" ModsDocID="21061" checkinTime="1252706925963" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Heterick, B. E." docDate="2006" docId="A1CCAC9CDF3C2FAC32CE2FA3A6F5F796" docLanguage="en" docName="21061.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 57" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf" docTitle="Monomorium flavimembra Heterick, 2006, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="122" masterDocId="3A2C4F9A5833769B5007E7556E53E380" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="202" masterPageNumber="69" pageNumber="120" updateTime="1569525778780" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="88F60F995B79BF218C1FB5009FCBFB61" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="3F650CB0680D746DEA1AAC1DCF35435F">
<mods:title id="844C87A066446ADD21DE6827543D9AF9">A revision of the Malagasy ants belonging to genus Monomorium Mayr, 1855 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="094BA43BFFD47369AF09C9E4CDB715D6" type="personal">
<mods:role id="37F9C21006B67500704483E5B33FCB72">
<mods:roleTerm id="2BF05558811D89CC9AE423A09060B4BE">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1E03BBC520A084CCF99B1A6F03FA23BC">Heterick, B. E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="669A0AE2A352D604FB8601256B3E4F50">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="686FF9A076E41E90AFF3A59808AB70E6" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="B83B2CCE854125FA2E48774DB4CC9869">
<mods:title id="569481BD21D6CC6362BD6909DA59D79E">Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="84CBA61B6AEB0E3D7AB846441F666353">
<mods:date id="D0D6E89F7C7162B290FE9208A5936C2F">2006</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="F65AF401B1C075276284E0A7AC560014" type="volume">
<mods:number id="0EB8B9D0645783D4AE86986149276D1D">57</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="17B7E47B9FF65E7BC80A352FC866DA19" unit="page">
<mods:start id="7E2A694228AFEF353E7D591FAB88D3B4">69</mods:start>
<mods:end id="20ED60A1B7034F27216EFB3F8537023D">202</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="76FDA82019FCBDA800C3534B4C305A07">
<mods:url id="4744674026B413B33EAC071A39CF1EE2">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/21061/21061.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="C78306C5D206F900F0C8F6944C987F28">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="9EB7D2F900573BBAF3667F1DCF41337D" type="HNS-PUB">21061</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="A1CCAC9CDF3C2FAC32CE2FA3A6F5F796" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A1CCAC9CDF3C2FAC32CE2FA3A6F5F796" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A1CCAC9CDF3C2FAC32CE2FA3A6F5F796">
<subSubSection id="4C27BD76312A0130E2F68C1823E1B315" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="D75F05852ADF54F9933A56D6014BD98E" pageNumber="120">
<taxonomicName id="50EB3A232E973155CB5BDAD2672EF885" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196248" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium flavimembra Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium flavimembra Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavimembra">Monomorium flavimembra Heterick</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="40310D314D82E852B7769C57609CF5C1" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0FE0B2A25521941B0D2C3BF95232C229" type="description">
<paragraph id="A1C9F43948220ADB7EAD3771522AB710" pageNumber="120">Figs. 19, 53-54.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2894F130EFA62446FDDB60E23E9C7342" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="5C0BA9B86CA072EE8C463710A43F5B72" pageNumber="120">Etymology.- Latin &quot;flavus&quot; (yellow) + pl. of &quot;membrum&quot; (neut. &quot;member&quot;) Material examined.- Holotype: [[worker]], Prov. Antsiranana, Reserve Speciale Ambre, 3.5 km 235 SW Sakaramy 325m, 12 29&quot;S, 49 15&quot;E, 26-31.i.2001, Fisher et al. BLF# 2676 /ex rotten log tropical dry forest/ CASENT 0401520 (CAS). Paratypes: Prov. Antsiranana (three workers and three queens collection code 2676, seven workers collection code 2679, otherwise data as for the holotype): 12 [[worker]] (ANIC); 1 [[worker]] + 12 [[queen]] + 12 [[worker]] (BMNH); 1 [[worker]] (CAS) 1[[queen]] + 12 [[worker]] + 2[[worker]] (MCZ). Other material examined: Prov. Antsiranana: Montagne Francais, 7.2 km 142 SE Diego Suarez 22-28.ii.2001 Fisher et al. (2 [[worker]]); Reserve Speciale Ambre, 3.5 km 235 SW Sakaramy 26-31.i.2001 Fisher et al. (15 [[worker]], 1 [[queen]]); Res. Spec. Ankarana, 22.9 km 224 SW Anivorano Nord 10-16.ii.2001 Fisher et al. (67 [[worker]]); Res. Spec. Ankarana, 13.6 km 192 SSW Anivorano Nord 16-21.ii.2001 Fisher et al. (2 [[worker]])</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FAE3978F7BF238ACF8F602EC77D0C18F" type="description">
<paragraph id="10F8A0BAB4906A6A1F32E3D662BE3FCE" lastPageNumber="121" pageNumber="120">Worker description.- Head: Head oval; vertex planar or weakly concave; frons shining and smooth except for piliferous pits; pilosity of frons a mixture of well-spaced, distinctly longer erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with shorter decumbent setae or setulae. Eye moderate, eye width 1-1.5x greatest width of antennal scape; (in full-face view) eyes set below midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set around midline of head capsule; eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin. Antennal segments 12; antennal club three-segmented. Clypeal carinae indistinct; anteromedian clypeal margin broadly convex; paraclypeal setae short and thickened, not reaching basal margin of closed mandibles; posteromedian clypeal margin extending slightly beyond level of posterior margin of antennal fossae. Anterior tentorial pits situated nearer antennal fossae than mandibular insertions. Frontal lobes sinuate, divergent posteriad. Psammophore absent. Mandibular teeth three, plus minute, basal denticle or angle; mandibles with sub-parallel inner and outer margins, smooth (except for piliferous pits); masticatory margin of mandibles approximately vertical or weakly oblique; basal tooth a small to minute denticle or angle, much smaller than t3 (four teeth present).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F76F6285FA88176534A642C321F7505C" pageNumber="121">Mesosoma: Promesonotum shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to lower anterior mesopleuron; (viewed in profile) promesonotum broadly convex anteriad, convexity reduced posteriad; promesonotal setae seven to twelve; standing promesonotal setae a mixture of well-spaced, distinctly longer, erect and semi-erect setae which are curved distally and often paired, interspersed with much shorter, incurved, decumbent setae; appressed promesonotal setulae very sparse or absent. Metanotal groove strongly impressed, with distinct transverse costulae. Propodeum shining and smooth, with a few weak striolae on metapleuron; propodeal dorsum flat throughout most of its length; propodeum smoothly rounded or with indistinct angle; standing propodeal setae consisting of one prominent pair anteriad, with other shorter setae very sparse or absent; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle equidistant from metanotal groove and declivitous face of propodeum. Vestibule of propodeal spiracle absent or not visible. Propodeal lobes present as blunt-angled flanges.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5329DC371D09D857D807F4C3896DE012" pageNumber="121">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated within anterior sector of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) conical, vertex tapered to conical, vertex rounded; appearance of node shining and smooth throughout; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) between 4:3 and1:1; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; ventral petiolar lobe present; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole about 4:3; height -length ratio of postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; postpetiole shining and smooth; postpetiolar sternite not depressed at midpoint, its anterior end an inconspicuous lip or small carina, or without anterior lip or carina, or this structure vestigial.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DF35C0A558DA86B9AB7067600A004EF1" pageNumber="121">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with a few appressed setulae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="24E868A1D7E5DECC8F0DBEA51B20E080" pageNumber="121">General characters: Color light to dark reddish brown, gaster darker brown, appendages yellowish. Worker caste monomorphic.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B603EE0C54A30FC894A28D45DE0A3E41" pageNumber="121">Holotype measurements: HML 1.33 HL 0.48 HW 0.43 CeI 89 SL 0.40 SI 94 PW 0.25.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FBFF2FDC079F5F4615DE0C6F80797A03" pageNumber="121">Other worker measurements: HML 1.12-1.31 HL 0.41-0.50 HW 0.37-0.43 CeI 83-89 SL 0.34-0.42 SI 89-101 PW 0.23-0.27 (n=20).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B39D26064184B6CA3B673C0FD8469AE8" pageNumber="121">Queen description.- Head: Head rectangular; vertex weakly concave or planar; frons shining and smooth except for piliferous pits; pilosity of frons a mixture of well-spaced, distinctly longer erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with shorter setae or setulae, which are decumbent or appressed, longer setae thickest on vertex. Eye elliptical, curvature of inner eye margin may be more pronounced than that of its outer margin; (in full-face view) eyes set at about midpoint of head capsule; (viewed in profile) eyes set posteriad of midline of head capsule.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5E21C09811E434F4C088F7A2935E8173" lastPageNumber="122" pageNumber="121">Mesosoma: Mesoscutum broadly convex anteriad, convexity reduced posteriad; pronotum, mesoscutum and mesopleuron shining and mainly smooth, vestigial striolae, if present, confined to anterior katepisternum; length -width ratio of mesoscutum and scutellum combined between 2:1 and 3:2; axillae contiguous, or nearly so; standing pronotal/mesoscutal setae consisting of wellspaced, incurved, erect and semi-erect setae only; appressed pronotal, mescoscutal and mesopleural setulae few, mainly on sides of pronotum and mesopleuron; propodeum shining and smooth, with a few distinct striolae on metapleuron; propodeum smoothly rounded or with indistinct angle; propodeal dorsum flat throughout most of its length; standing propodeal setae consisting of up to a dozen or more longer erect and shorter sub-erect setae; appressed propodeal setulae very sparse or absent; propodeal spiracle nearer metanotal groove than declivitous face of propodeum; propodeal lobes present as well-developed, rounded flanges.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7503D67811C42ECABE17C5FDEC87CDBB" pageNumber="122">Petiole and postpetiole: Petiolar spiracle lateral and situated within anterior sector of petiolar node; node (viewed in profile) conical, vertex tapered; appearance of node shining and weakly striolate posteriad; ratio of greatest node breadth (viewed from front) to greatest node width (viewed in profile) between 4:3 and 1:1; anteroventral petiolar process absent or vestigial; height ratio of petiole to postpetiole between 4:3 and 1:1; height-length ratio of postpetiole between 2:1 and 4:3; postpetiole shining and weakly striolate posteriad; postpetiolar sternite without anterior lip or carina, or this structure vestigial.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0AC4CD4F4CB221F6ACB1B3D46980B7CC" pageNumber="122">Wing: Wing not seen (queens dealated).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4BA7F025974AFD0B938BDBA492D6FE19" pageNumber="122">Gaster: Pilosity of first gastral tergite consisting of well-spaced, erect and semi-erect setae interspersed with a few appressed setulae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FF9361BCFB33897EFA6343E59D09031B" pageNumber="122">General characters: Color foreparts reddish brown, gaster brown, appendages yellow. Brachypterous alates not seen. Ergatoid or worker-female intercastes not seen.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F33E4DD3DE9A569A38901F708FDF26CC" pageNumber="122">Queen measurements: HML 1.55-1.57 HL 0.51 HW 0.47-0.49 CeI 92-96 SL 0.43-0.45 SI 88-95 PW 0.34-0.35 (n=4).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A6609B1E974077B1129BF65A5CABF150" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="398EF49C7C40315F1EBF6954B043891C" pageNumber="122">
Remarks.- 
<taxonomicName id="B17885A7C858521F8C58459598D14F18" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196248" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium flavimembra Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium flavimembra Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="122" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavimembra">Monomorium flavimembra</taxonomicName>
is similar in morphology to 
<taxonomicName id="9890131C71B71473CCE0A751D9DB4C9D" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:196245" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium bifidoclypeatum Heterick" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium bifidoclypeatum Heterick" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="122" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bifidoclypeatum">M. bifidoclypeatum</taxonomicName>
, but the anteromedian clypeal sector is only weakly carinate, and the petiolar node is higher and less sharply conical. The basal tooth is usually present as a small obtuse angle but may be absent altogether. The rich, russet color of the upper part of the frons and mesosoma contrasts with the bright yellow clypeus, mandibles and appendages in most specimens, but the legs may have a brownish tinge. The four known queens, all dealated, are very small and ergatoid-like. Queens of more regular proportions (for a 
<taxonomicName id="68148942644F8E5D51D26EAFE62BE96E" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:24899" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium Mayr" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium Mayr" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="122" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Monomorium</taxonomicName>
whose workers reach about 2 mm TL) may exist among the unclassifiable CAS 
<taxonomicName id="14C3650A5EDCD3E7757F535639633130" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:24899" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Monomorium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Monomorium Mayr" lsidName-HNS="Monomorium Mayr" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="122" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Monomorium</taxonomicName>
queen material that cannot be associated with workers.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="01B317CD2941C182136C3E71C9F9673B" pageNumber="122">This taxon has a localized distribution in Antsiranana Province, in far northern Madagascar. Workers have been collected in tropical dry forest as ground foragers, in sifted litter and from colonies in wood (rotted logs and twigs) and root mats.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>