<document id="3C6E7EEE169B4B6AB4B092D55B072FFA" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b92acfc0-9d67-42c4-9e37-ebd5a53d24b5" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200924" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-719-75" ID-ZBK="36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-719-75" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 719" ModsDocTitle="A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World" checkinTime="1555319501509" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2017" docId="A209A689B712643854A7D0A0C4F4B001" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 719: 75-157" docOrigin="ZooKeys 719" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253" docTitle="Lecontella gnara Wolcott 1927" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="45" lastPageNumber="118" masterDocId="5C2D8118751DD235197A6569FFE59A6E" masterDocTitle="A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World" masterLastPageNumber="157" masterPageNumber="75" pageId="41" pageNumber="116" updateTime="1643480888860" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="A9C05F81562FEB457F61FF14A36D3867" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="D3D585FAEE01085D3660D2E36CE84B46">
<mods:title id="47F696271B0F24F9E775F9ABD8D16639">A taxonomic revision of the subfamily Tillinae Leach sensu lato (Coleoptera, Cleridae) in the New World</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="EDB394353CCDB1793BBFF2C11473243A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9047CE9647C98486B0735A34F7ABC219">
<mods:roleTerm id="D46C70CB457C6F9141700EB08DBA4AE9">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="9653FA031E3CDEF11BC20A4EA9D344BF">Burke, Alan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="051AB2522FD216924C225AFD150D5B62" type="personal">
<mods:role id="0FBE71319115CC5DEDBA1F098F5B3E8C">
<mods:roleTerm id="AAC905DAD8239B80D924477BB24307FE">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="6F2BD0A9C4162DB21FC1BABBF795856B">Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="FC92405D62787576038CF6C84911D11A">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="0254C25100364ED21F8FE5E95CB99BBA" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="53933312B0081A3588F398DEAB54C8A4">
<mods:title id="5BB112DBDCAD5B1B0EFAC14666E925AA">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="9C21958AD47C85727792D3B8B4A39649">
<mods:date id="5824BA7F35D62BD7D020EDC32B73A18E">2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="150B456D7F400E2AFB09879323965158" type="volume">
<mods:number id="133DF40D62252801C3AB51B7A6BC388C">719</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="8C27FECDCD63D5999152317B8E540572" unit="page">
<mods:start id="2122E5DEC5EBFC0DD2D266D8D8511C75">75</mods:start>
<mods:end id="172A61E8E5EC3A76A60D0F6F6CE096C5">157</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="E56046FB1BDFA067B528DDC8DD9267C0">
<mods:url id="A70A9D829B2FF3D2ADEE7118C27FBB14">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="ECFCEDEE46B53444C7D11138C394F4E2">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="620501C772C3F6A9DEA46D58B2B65C82" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.719.21253</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="66E821866F2F3BB921D9FB5C958B61A9" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-719-75</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="BF162DF72EC0D0CD0B5A5DA51E657AE4" type="ZBK">36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="BB4CAE9C5AC5E54E26A78DF7B8A573E9" type="ZooBank">36C4E2C8E07D4CC9A1D696B0FCE92CCF</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="A209A689B712643854A7D0A0C4F4B001" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200924" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A209A689B712643854A7D0A0C4F4B001" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A209A689B712643854A7D0A0C4F4B001" lastPageId="45" lastPageNumber="118" pageId="41" pageNumber="116">
<subSubSection id="11022A51A3CD695797C430DF50036ADF" pageId="41" pageNumber="116" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="07A8C57AFA920A40A73172BB61C040C5" pageId="41" pageNumber="116">
<taxonomicName id="711356AA72804E7AD5425D6A938483AD" authority="Wolcott, 1927" authorityName="Wolcott" authorityYear="1927" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Lecontella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lecontella gnara" order="Coleoptera" pageId="41" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gnara">
<pageBreakToken id="F0D0C8336A750A2AD5F31C7FA7F5EA63" pageId="41" pageNumber="116" start="start">Lecontella</pageBreakToken>
gnara Wolcott, 1927
</taxonomicName>
Figs 3F, 7G, 10A, 12C, F, 19F
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="565A174A4703BA70CCFADA32E4BEBB25" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" type="synonyms">
<paragraph id="CA6BF7DA1C9DAE2B5182D0048E9E05EA" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">
<pageBreakToken id="A9867649050A965F975916ED22ABD9A5" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" start="start">Synonyms</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="474E5B15D3B3F9CC99C73CA820679245" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">
<taxonomicName id="10A3C05610DE4597700E9A9129697637" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera cilindricollis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="cilindricollis">Cymatodera cilindricollis</taxonomicName>
Spinola, 1844, nec. 
<bibRefCitation id="690A99F0FD68B3D369BC91A5B3F7827F" author="Chevrolat, MA" journalOrPublisher="Strasburg" pageId="75" pageNumber="150" pagination="1 - 25" title="Coleopteres du Mexique. Impremiere de G. Silberman." volume="1" year="1833">Chevrolat 1833</bibRefCitation>
, no. 11 (
<taxonomicName id="D13D8455A24355123040CE2AA359CB10" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Cymatodera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cymatodera" order="Coleoptera" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Cymatodera</taxonomicName>
). 
<normalizedToken id="A9CC4ADF258EB963EFE422EEE1235F09" originalValue="“Mexique”">&quot;Mexique&quot;</normalizedToken>
Synonymized by 
<bibRefCitation id="70E0F33582CDD66B8EC520D55E1B4386" author="Ekis, G" journalOrPublisher="Bollettino dell'Museo di Zoologia della Universita di Torino" pageId="75" pageNumber="150" pagination="1 - 80" title="Taxonomic and nomenclatural status of clerid taxa described by Massimiliano Spinola (1780 - 1857) (Coleoptera: Cleridae)." volume="1" year="1975">Ekis (1975)</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="CD969F52BE271A1EEBE057F8C54BFA5A" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" type="paratypes">
<paragraph id="D2A40580433A1FFFE4179ADB2D6E81B2" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Paratypes.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9989B214F723A0A28765E0791D0837FE" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Two females examined.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0A7873A4E8E7C5D25605490CE9D8B936" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" type="type locality">
<paragraph id="56342832DDE2EBE7DEF745A6D200EFBB" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EB765B6B0DF4A27D4687116BF9746D28" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Sabinas Canyon, Tucson, Arizona. Type depository: Field Museum of Natural History (FMNH).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D0DC471A88738D94BDD92D6CE4B3CBFF" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="8C4E06B7FADE080F3475D02F49BD1B38" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="00F70F17D261A898CCE179CD505194BF" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">USA: AZ, CA, NM, NV, TX, UT; Mexico: Baja California, Sonora.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="ECB93B4AF10A09EEDD321DC59A6A1FCA" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph id="EE22FF926FD0778B84AE9363AE09601B" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3BEE938626595FBC1F653DD499385321" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">
<taxonomicName id="77092455F186AC1020D81CDFE95BBBFE" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Lecontella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Lecontella gnara" order="Coleoptera" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gnara">Lecontella gnara</taxonomicName>
is most closely related to 
<taxonomicName id="5EAB932BA8C59B17282E15195C47D02E" genus="L." lsidName="L. brunnea" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" rank="species" species="brunnea">L. brunnea</taxonomicName>
. Characters to distinguish these species are given in the diagnosis section of 
<taxonomicName id="F3278E51174124151F3D50E479886938" genus="L." lsidName="L. brunnea" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" rank="species" species="brunnea">L. brunnea</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F460B4291FC627E4D62D8946C1F398AE" lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="118" pageId="42" pageNumber="117" type="redescription">
<paragraph id="029A540AAD8870BC89F1F83E757CE7E1" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Redescription.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="47189AD4C48BB974CA779817956E2C7F" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Male. Form: Medium-sized to large, somewhat robust. Color: Head, pronotum, thorax, scutellum, legs, antennae and elytra light testaceous to dark brown; mouthparts fuscous, last fourth of mandibles piceous to black; abdominal segments testaceous to piceous; elytral disc devoid of any bands or fasciae (Fig. 3F).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EA1CC1C7EA4831B2B911E55DB254197C" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">
Head: Including eyes wider than pronotum; eyes large, taller than wide, bulging laterally, coarsely faceted, emarginate posteriorly; antennal notch located in front of emargination; frons bi-impressed; integument coarsely, conspicuously, deeply punctate; clothed with fine, pale, recumbent setae interspersed with some erect, pale setae; antennae with 11 antennomeres; antennomeres 2-10 moderately robust, about the same length, gradually increasing in width toward distal end; antennomeres 1-4 cylindrical; serration in antennomeres 5-10 gradually increasing toward distal end; last antennomere of males sexually dimorphic; conspicuously elongate, robust, parallel, cylindrical, 4-6
<normalizedToken id="CFA3853F15C803DA08116FD127E1E537" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than length of tenth antennomere (Fig. 10A).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3418A0FA9D288EDEC63A1BBE7320B5EB" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">Thorax: Pronotum bisinuate, widest at middle, somewhat short in length; sides constricted subapically, more strongly constricted behind middle and feebly constricted in front of middle; surface conspicuously punctate; elytral disc with punctations coarse, deep interspersed with a smooth disc (Fig. 12F); clothed with fine, short, pale, recumbent setae intermingled with some long, erect, fine, pale setae, long setae more abundant on anterior and lateral area of pronotum; anterior transverse depression present; subbasal tumescence absent; posterior margin of pronotum compressed. Prosternum conspicuously wider than long; moderately to strongly punctate, punctation fine, deep; surface vested to glabrous. Mesoventrite surface rugulose, scarcely vested with fine, pale, semi-erect setae; coarsely top very coarsely punctate, punctations wide, deep. Metaventrite surface smooth to rugulose, convex; rather punctate; punctations coarse, shallow to deep; vested with fine, pale, recumbent setae; longitudinal depression and metaventral process present. Scutellum elongate, clothed with pale, fine, semirecumbent setae, compressed medially.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E3E44C972AC2870F5F7518B75B2FC279" lastPageId="43" lastPageNumber="118" pageId="42" pageNumber="117">
Elytra: Broader than pronotum; elongate; humeri indicated, rounded; sides inconspicuously broadening toward distal end, broadest on posterior third, then abruptly narrowing toward apex at posterior fourth; disc flat above; surface rugose to rugulose at interstices; elytral apices subtriangular; inconspicuously dehiscent; elytral declivity moderately steep; surface vested with fine, short, pale, recumbent setae interspersed 
<pageBreakToken id="C680B941DBEA215C0B2A85EB5A95BCD2" pageId="43" pageNumber="118" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
some pale, fine, long, erect setae; conspicuously, coarsely punctate, punctations consisting of coarse, deep, wide punctations arranged in regular striae of the same size that decrease in size at elytral declivity, punctation reach the elytral apex (Fig. 7G); interstices at elytral base as wide as the width of punctation; interstices smooth. Epipleural fold gradually narrowing toward apex, last sixth moderately crenulate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F95378926F71FC957B8B7C1241A7C1E8" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">Legs: Femora rugulose; feebly swollen posteriorly; clothed with some whitish, fine, semirecumbent and semi-erect setae; surface conspicuously punctate; punctations small and shallow. Tibiae rugulose; punctations shallow and small; vestiture consisting of short, recumbent and semirecumbent setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7FF1DEC61CBEED55617C0F9970C8D01D" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">Abdomen: Six visible ventrites. First ventrite coarsely rugose to rugulose. Ventrites 2-4 rugulose; convex; subquadrate; clothed with fine, long, yellowish pale, recumbent setae; not compressed laterally; posterior margins truncate. Posterior margin of first and second visible ventrites elevated with a transverse carina originating next to posterolateral angles, producing a broad, elevated arcuate emargination. Fifth visible ventrite subtriangular; shiny; surface rugulose, convex; punctations shallow, small; vested with fine, pale, recumbent setae; lateral margins oblique, feebly arcuate; posterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate. Sixth visible ventrite small, subtriangular in shape; rugulose to rugose; surface convex, moderately, finely punctate; clothed with short, pale, fine, recumbent setae; broader than long; lateral margins oblique, arcuate; posterior margin short, broadly, shallowly, emarginate. Fifth tergite subquadrate, surface convex, shiny, finely rugulose; punctate; posterior margin truncate. Sixth tergite subquadrate; rugulose to rugose; wider than long; surface convex; clothed with fine, pale, recumbent setae; surface punctate; lateral margins oblique; posterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate. Sixth tergite extending beyond apical margin of sixth visible ventrite, covering sixth ventrite in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1663228697179485087E77DE5D872A56" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">Aedeagus: Phallobasic apodeme present; phallus with copulatory piece swollen at apex; phallic plate unarmed; intraspicular plate present, elongate; phallobasic apodeme long, slightly expanded distally; phallobase subparallel; parameres free; tegmen complete, completely covering phallus; parameres pointed distally; endophallic struts long, slender distally (Fig. 19F).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="68F847D7CAC0CF3C049DC211C5EFDCE7" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">
Sexual dimorphism: Females of 
<taxonomicName id="1A94E7324CD021017B6640BCAB25A571" genus="L." lsidName="L. gnara" pageId="43" pageNumber="118" rank="species" species="gnara">L. gnara</taxonomicName>
can be differentiated from males based on the shape of the last abdominal segment. The sixth visible segment in females is broadly rounded, while males have this segment somewhat subquadrate with the posterior margin broadly, very shallowly emarginate. In addition, females of 
<taxonomicName id="586555665F25833D32282D08600A880F" genus="L." lsidName="L. gnara" pageId="43" pageNumber="118" rank="species" species="gnara">L. gnara</taxonomicName>
have the eleventh antennomere short, somewhat robust and longer than the tenth antennomere; males, on the other side, have the last antennomere cylindrical, not compressed medially and conspicuously longer than the tenth antennomere.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="91F0A8DE4E41F61850D54640F63F6ABA" pageId="43" pageNumber="118" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="73F3F43CC47712A910AFC452D787F8C6" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D8F0D2426D477D8CAEDD5E75DBEB6EE" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">PARATYPE: 1 female: Sabino Canyon, Tucson, Arizona, 15-VII-1915, L. Liebeck; PARATYPE: 1 female: Copper Basin, near Prescott, Arizona, 9-IX-1907, J. A. Krusche.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FB5644C712A722C925FFECEE795B8B2F" lastPageId="45" lastPageNumber="120" pageId="43" pageNumber="118" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="C9FCEF4950BBC53EFD377F2833ABF632" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CE528266A59EF42C24E4B2B82B577CF1" lastPageId="45" lastPageNumber="120" pageId="43" pageNumber="118">
1 female: Arnett Creek, AZ, S. W. Superior, VIII-13-1972, L. J. Bayer; 1 male: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-20-1953, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-22-1957, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 
<pageBreakToken id="A7CADC3580A65CAFB578935C8436013B" pageId="44" pageNumber="119" start="start">1</pageBreakToken>
male: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-17-1957, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 1 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-8-1952, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-26, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 3 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-9-1959, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-14-1957, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males, 1 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-15-1961, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 3 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-22-1961, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 3 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-28-1962, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 males, 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VII-29, J. N. Knull; 2 males: Tucson, AZ, VIII-10, J. N. Knull; 2 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-11, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-12-1952, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 male, 3 females: Tucson, AZ, VIII-27, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-27-1953, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Chisos Mountains, TX, Oak Spring, VIII-15-1962, C. A. Triplehorn; 2 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-2-1952, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-28, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VIII-13; J. N. Knull; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VIII-27, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VII-11, J. N. Knull; 2 males: Tucson, AZ, VII-14, J. N. Knull; 2 males: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-21-1962, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Tumacacori Mountains, AZ, VIII-2-1962; D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 females: Sabino Canyon, AZ, VIII-15-1945, Tucker; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VIII-6, J. N. Knull; 1 male: Wickenburg, AZ, VII-25, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Tucson, AZ, VIII-6-1913, J. N. Knull; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, 26-VII-1920, J. N. Knull; 2 females: Huachuca Mountains, AZ, 25-VII, J. N. Knull; 3 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, IX-4-1962, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 2 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-30-1959, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-7-1959, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 1 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-10-1961, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 4 males, 2 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-10-1961, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VII-18-1961, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, IX-11-1962, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 2 females: Sabino Canyon, AZ, VIII-7-1962, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 male, 2 females: Chiricahua Mountains, AZ, VIII-14-1962, D. J. and J. N. Knull; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VII-1929, J. N. Knull, 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VIII-1910, J. N. Knull; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VIII-1927, J. N. Knull; 1 male: Pecos, TX, 15-VIII-1962, N. M. Downie; 1 female: Globe, AZ, 1-VII-1933, F. H. Parker; 2 males: Santa Cruz Co., AZ, Yanks Spring, 4 m SE Ruby, Pajarito Mountains, 4,000 ft, IX-5-1950, T. Cohn, P. Boone and M. Cazier; 1 male: Pima Co., AZ, El Mirador Ranch, 4 mi NW Sasabe, Baboquivari Mts., 3,900 ft, IX-3-1950, T. Cohn, P. Boone and M. Cazier; 2 females: Pima Co., AZ, Sabino Canyon, Santa Catalina Mts., 5,000 ft, VIII-6-1948, G. E. Ball; 1 male: Pima Co., AZ, 15 mi E Tucson, 2600 ft, VIII-18-1950, T. Cohn, P. Boone and M. Cazier; 1 male, 1 female: Pima Co., AZ, Madrona Canyon, Ranger Station, Rincon Mts, VIII-24-1952, 3,300 ft, G. M. Bradt; 3 males: Pima Co., AZ, Continental, VII-29-1948, G. E. Ball; 2 females: Patagonia, AZ, VII-6-1936, M. Cazier; 2 males: Hidalgo Co., NM, 18 mi N Rodeo, VII-7-1956; 1 male: Pima Co., AZ, Tucson, VII-1953, G. M. Bradt; 1 female: Patagonia, AZ, 
<pageBreakToken id="467E030DC2C66061A6B24145A3558A24" pageId="45" pageNumber="120" start="start">VII-</pageBreakToken>
6-1936, M. Cazier; 1 female: Tucson, AZ, VIII-26-1949, 2,700, G. M. Bradt; 1 female: Globe, AZ, VIII-28-1952, F. H. Parker; 1 female: Huachuca Mountains, AZ, 5,400, on palm, Chass; 1 male: Gila Bend, AZ, [no collecting date and collector data]; 2 females: Baboquivari Mountains, AZ, VII-23-1949; F. H. Parker; 1 male, 1 female: Coyote Mountains, AZ, VII-4-VIII-1916, 
<geoCoordinate id="E975915A1FA20B655CF4F3839BE26FBF" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="31.983334">31°59'N</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate id="900FA56836BD3D5B79911F639194877B" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-111.48333">111°29'W</geoCoordinate>
, 3,500, [no collector data]; 1 female: Patagonia mountains, AZ, VIII-20-1949, F. H. Parker; 1 female: Huachuca Mountains, AZ, VIII-15-1949, F. H. Parker; 1 female: Pima Co., AZ, Lowell Ranger Station, VI-20-VII-1916; 1 female: Globe, AZ, VIII-26-1935, C. Parker; 1 female: Santa Cruz Co., AZ, Pajarito Mts., Pena Blanca, Canyon, VII-27-1978, 1191 m, at light, S. McCleve; 1 male, 1 female: Cochise Co., AZ, Texas Canyon, 5,300', black lite, VIII-12-1974, S. McCleve; 1 female: Cochise Co., AZ, San Bernardino Ranch, VIII-14-1976, S. McCleve; 2 female: Cochise Co., AZ, Leslie Canyon, VIII-17-1978, S. McCleve; 1 male: Cochise Co., AZ, Texas Canyon, 5300', black lite, VIII-12-1974; 1 female: Graham Co., AZ, Aravaipa Canyon, Turkey Creek, VIII-11-1998, MV and blacklight, F. W. Skillman Jr; 1 male, 1 female: Tortilla Mountains, AZ, 12 mi N of Tucson, Pima Co., VII-16-1966; 1 female: Pima Co., AZ, Collsal Cave Park, VIII-25-1970, K. Stephan; 1 female: Cochise Co., AZ, South Western Res. Sta., VII-6-1980, UV light, L. L. Lampert Jr; 2 males: Cochise Co., AZ, Cottonwood Canyon, mercury vapor + black light, VII-16-2000, R. Turnbow; 1 male, 1 female: La Paz Co., AZ, 12-VI-1996, Cibola NWR, D. Anderson. MEXICO: 1 male: Sonora, Mexico, Tastiota, VII-18-1952, C. and P. Vaurie; 1 male: Durango, Mexico, Rodeo, San Juan del Rio, 4,700 ft, VII-29-1947; 2 females: Sonora, Mexico, Obregon, VII-29-1952, C. P. Vaurie; 1 male, 1 female: Sonora, Mexico, Minas Nuevas, 7-VIII-1952, C. and P. Vaurie.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>