<document id="93AC1E45938DCF3DDDABAFAA8ACEDFE0" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280265" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120203" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280265" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="A59BBBC0C7178A5B8320087E6C30A4EC" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys origo Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="693" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="691" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="2ACA0421A9BC5118EFC37A851AEECB0F" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2F261D7FB44CB81CA6762CA53D60E2DF">
<mods:title id="A47612E4D63B4C579A201D88912BDA0F">The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="406776191FA29ABE347B58F78A362968" type="personal">
<mods:role id="5784E0EFC77C9DC29FDFDEFC2F0AD4CE">
<mods:roleTerm id="14622881476CF5144A40C2DB53B02079">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="92D68CDF63791E9FD7DE5637B8BA6D2E">Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="DC5F5A4747099DAB4FD2CB9EA1DF8C4C">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="947BB93ED2CC90DED1C57BB5E0E6F4ED" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="FBDA51A9E4D668A021CE8E52FD4AE198">
<mods:title id="2D4D75B9B9BD1B5DA9C6C9C8EFCAA856">Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="EA3486525E38B9FFF2354CC91E010A43">
<mods:date id="0EEF092C92B1966D214752B55045D37B">2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="4E50EAF04D0DF718C15D2F7EDBB3D8C2" type="volume">
<mods:number id="CD84507E6AB44495A1644F25B1CEF717">65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="D406229E398D8F2370D17384E405DA42" unit="page">
<mods:start id="8CC2BFD7D69DEE988EA2A12AE913BD72">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="DE7E309EE7E5126CAE0F4A38F7D0C54E">1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="0C44AD24610F406CDE7D4B959CD85832">
<mods:url id="D6B7926B7C8E288AEB2B7AFDEAC68BAC">http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="9574E5F44D7BF988209F7BB07B574F2F">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="4DE24E204D91D0B0C555B0D326738F57" type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="02353527774147FB5635EC8F064DB059" type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="A59BBBC0C7178A5B8320087E6C30A4EC" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280265" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120203" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280265" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A59BBBC0C7178A5B8320087E6C30A4EC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A59BBBC0C7178A5B8320087E6C30A4EC" lastPageNumber="693" pageNumber="691">
<subSubSection id="DC223A286FBD8E3444C51EFA8F9D19C7" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="B368472412E797E1CAFBED58269148D3" pageNumber="691">
<taxonomicName id="86554BE2E71A23E1B0AC0F4FA775A903" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155871" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys origo Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys origo Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="691" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="origo">Strumigenys origo Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="4CBB0A71E0AF3EEF46BACEFFA1DD91BA" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Fig. 403)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="59474BC9FD3BF95E56B91C92BB21BE2F" type="description">
<paragraph id="F5C532E854532089317F88A87E4F2A80" lastPageNumber="692" pageNumber="691">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 2.2, HL 0.50, HW 0.39, CI 78, ML 0.25, MI 49, SL 0.30, SI 78, PW 0.26, AL 0.54. Characters of scotti-complex. Mandibles in full-face view short, outer margins shallowly and evenly convex. Upper scrobe margin evenly and shallowly convex in full-face view, not bordered by a rim or flange, the eyes visible. Maximum diameter of eye slightly greater than maximum width of scape, with 4 - 5 ommatidia in longest row. Scape subcylindrical, curved and narrowed near base; hairs on leading edge slender, flattened or spoon-shaped apically. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with erect to suberect filiform ground-pilosity. The upper scrobe margin fringed with sharply curved hairs which are similar in shape and size or slightly larger than those on the leading edge of the scape. Cephalic dorsum with 6 standing filiform hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate, dorsum with a central pair of standing hairs. Mesonotum with three pairs of standing filiform to narrowly remiform hairs: a pair on anterior margin, a pair situated central laterally, and a pair on posterior margin. Propodeum with one pair of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Ground-pilosity on dorsal alitrunk inconspicuous and more or less absent, consisting of short suberect to decumbent fine filiform hairs. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and more or less flat to shallowly convex posteriorly. Metanptal groove without a conspicuous impression. Anterior mesonotum with a narrow carina above the mesothoracic spiracle; mesopleural gland set in a small circular notch. Propodeal tooth triangular, lamellate, pointed apically, and subtended by a narrow lamella. Pronotal dorsum longitudinally striolate; mesonotal and propodeal dorsa reticulate-punctate. Sides of pronotum superficially longitudinally striolate. Pleurae and side of propodeum glassy smooth and peripherally punctulate. Postpetiole disc more or less smooth. In profile ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle a well developed curtain that is continuous along the base of the peduncle and equal or greater in depth than maximum diameter of eye. Basigastral costulae well developed and sharply defined, radiating on each side of a broad central clear area. Dorsal surface of petiole, postpetiole, and gaster with standing filiform hairs which are slightly thickened apically. Colour light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="48B8A6DE4655D3E32BBBCF4B34A5CB33" pageNumber="692">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 2.1, HL 0.49 - 0.51, HW 0.38 - 0.40, CI 74 - 82, ML 0.24 - 0.25, MI 48 - 50, SL 0.29 - 0.30, SI 73 - 79, PW 0.24 - 0.26, AL 0.51 - 0.54 (4 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B516133B86D1A0057E89B0F5E7930BB3" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="D11B96976895C9060BAC3D71C3296574" pageNumber="692">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 10 km. NW Enakara, Ris. Andohahela, 24 Â° 34 ' S, 46 Â° 49 ' E, 430 m., 24. xi. 1992, sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood, rainforest # 522 (17) - 4 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ). Paratypes. 4 workers and 2 queens (dealate) with same data as holotype but coded (2) - 3, (3) - 2, (7) - 2, (9) - 5, (18) - 25 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A02A8A66E84F02701DE22DADCF85C056" pageNumber="692">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: R. S. Manongarivo, 12.8 km. 228 Â° SW Antanambao, 780 m. (B. L. Fisher); Marojejy R. N. I. / C 12, 375 m. (G. D. Alpert); Marojejy, 600 m. (J. - M. Betsch); 6.5 km. SSW Befingotra, Ris. Anjanaharibe-Sud, 875 m. (B. L. Fisher); 19 km. ESE Maroantsetra, 350 m. (P. S. Ward); 6.9 km. NE Ambanizana, Ambohitsitondroina, 825 m. (B. L. Fisher); 5.3 km. SSE Ambanizana, Andranobe, 425 m. (B. L. Fisher); 1 km. W Andampibe, Cap Masoala, 125 m. (Alpert el at.); F. C. Didy, 960 m. (H. J. Ratsirarson); For. d'Ankarongambe, 10 km. E. Ambohidray, 900 m. (J. - M. Betsch); F. C. Andriantantely, 530 m. (H. J. Ratsirarson); 10 km. NE Antananarivo, Sacred Forest, 1360 m. (Alpert et at.); Andasibe, 800 m., 870 m. (Alpert el al.); Perinet &amp; vie. (W. L. Brown); 16 km. S Moramanga (P. S. Vihrd) ;; Col des Tapias, 1550 m. (J. - M. Betsch); Itremo Mts, 1630 m. (A. Peyrieras); Massif de 1 ' Itremo, 1630 m. (J. - M. Betsch); 7 km. W Ranomafana Nat. Park, 900 m. (WE. Steiner); Ranomafana Nat. Park, Miaranony Forest, 700 m. (E. Rajeriarison); 3 km. W Ranomafana, nr Ifandiana, 950 m. (P. S. Ward); 45 km. S Ambalavao, 785 m. (B. L. Fisher); 43 km. S Ambalavao, Ris. Andringitra, 825 m. (B. L. Fisher); Ambalamarovandava, 1550 m. (J. - M. Betsch); 8.0 km. NE Ivohibe, 1200 m. (S. Razaflmandimhy); 9.0 km. NE Ivohibe, 900 m. (S. Razaftmandimby); R. S. Ivohibe, 7.5 km. ENE Ivohibe, 900 m. (S. Razqflmandimby); R. S. Ivohibe, 8.0 km. E Ivohibe, 1200 m. (S. Razqfimandimby); Anosyennes Mts, 600 m. (J. - M. Betsch); 13 km. NW Enakara, Ris. Andohahela, 1250 m. (B. L. Fisher); 10 km. NW Enkara, Ris Andohahela, 420 m. (B. L. Fisher); 6 km. SSW Eminiminy Reserve, Andohahela, 250 m. (G. D. Alpert); Ris. Andohahela, 6 km. SSW Eminiminy, 330 m. (P. S. Vhrd); 6 km. ESE Imonty, Res. Andohahela, 1000 m. (Alpert et al.); 2.7 km. WNW 302 Â° Ste Luce, 20 m. (B. L. Fisher); Mandena, 8.4 km. NNE 30 Â° Tolagnaro, 20 m. (B. L. Fisher).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FA89502250954AF98E0FA37DD1342D50" type="description">
<paragraph id="762FA7FEBBC03FE7E5F9F2886B1C8D07" pageNumber="692">Measurements of these specimens extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.41 - 0.55, HW 0.33 - 0.45, CI 75 - 83, ML 0.20 - 0.28, MI 46 - 53, SL 0.25 - 0.36, SI 74 - 86 (14 measured).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="DF5F8E928F8E5C47E116C2D4F2AEF151" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="8E580916218E92B2C199B61C3255C3CF" pageNumber="692">
<taxonomicName id="0CBB4900C5991C8CE301C394B46405AD" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155871" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys origo Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys origo Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="692" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="origo">S. origo</taxonomicName>
is a widespread and commonly collected species. Among the scom'-complex species which have the dorsum of the petiole node reticulate-punctate, 
<taxonomicName id="EE41CF7409C8A8CCA9612AE9A899FF2C" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155871" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys origo Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys origo Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="692" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="origo">origo</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished by having:
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FF5F0B8588FEE96FCE668A289C19C380" pageNumber="692">1 Mesonotum with 3 pairs of erect hairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D5B445413F155510E46367632A5ED473" pageNumber="693">2 Pronotum with one pair of long erect hairs on central dorsum.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="16642986F4D6EED48C23B99496456DF4" pageNumber="693">3 In profile ventral spongiform curtain of petiolar peduncle well developed, entire depth of curtain more or less greater than maximum diameter of eye.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="50B1271ECF5E20EF11789944010F22C8" pageNumber="693">4 Cephalic ground-pilosity erect or suberect.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E1BB9A3CC7FC76B0837CB60CA4573741" pageNumber="693">
See under 
<taxonomicName id="967E0343117C432F9D836DEBB3F86717" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155862" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys glycon Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys glycon Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="693" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="glycon">glycon</taxonomicName>
for further discussion.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>