<document id="E36D6148DFDAF18CE0F3284AEB7CD0E1" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.101.1182" ID-GBIF-Dataset="27b97ed3-f3cd-4468-af5e-0c3701b28f46" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152029510" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-101-51" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1DA0608B-A874-4338-BDAE-FECE7D9E7FEA" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-101-51" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 101" ModsDocTitle="Alocanthedon, a new subgenus of Chalicodoma from Southeast Asia (Hymenoptera, Megachilidae)" checkinTime="1451250346471" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Engel, Michael S. &amp; Gonzalez, Victor H." docDate="2011" docId="AD2DD9C9DABA704EF24249A560EDD5A3" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 101: 51-80" docOrigin="ZooKeys 101" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.101.1182" docTitle="Chalicodoma ((Alocanthedon)) odontophorum Engel, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="1DA0608B-A874-4338-BDAE-FECE7D9E7FEA" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="59" masterDocId="FFE06A70FFD9FFB6D71F3A05AE130042" masterDocTitle="Alocanthedon, a new subgenus of Chalicodoma from Southeast Asia (Hymenoptera, Megachilidae)" masterLastPageNumber="80" masterPageNumber="51" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" updateTime="1643720448410" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="0B92A11F5A39B70FCBE5CCA1183F3B12" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="D5361D10DC4D723D32187D2C63C702DB">
<mods:title id="B6D0D1472287B11E3DFCED5E71DE6BA3">Alocanthedon, a new subgenus of Chalicodoma from Southeast Asia (Hymenoptera, Megachilidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="C3050FAB6BD65E7DE7BB98417FF1DB37" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AD3A17E3D67A8BFDBC72426D922E5955">
<mods:roleTerm id="34D26793F5F41D2FCA3CB298DDF123FD">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3EFCDC98D6BE119C4707C1101CE5F4DC">Engel, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="78E555B0C530B223F04FD5791F3BADE2" type="personal">
<mods:role id="5A66B4F6DB618D910312CE31040E7EAC">
<mods:roleTerm id="EF1557D7B1034A0E0BACF7B0C7E61FAB">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="FAF89584EDFCCC0FD45CC31D52ED51C8">Gonzalez, Victor H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="7EDC4D0D6EC9E8A2CF5B72F79673FEA1">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3F207C57B9B757810F9C1CF0FA39E3D7" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="8AABD6EA1F3BA3EC16FB1159AE2BAB10">
<mods:title id="1037A8255278A7F3323DEE9ACFDFD15B">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="1C6C3C3B746340A6BDE279F282AAFBA0">
<mods:date id="F91C354919B9F811CA3FE2B5A9825B27">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="30B9948585CE585601ED7E97572E2256" type="volume">
<mods:number id="5E149C8DACA167EF58613E15FACE9D9F">101</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="5A692272044029516E752A2103CA4F43" unit="page">
<mods:start id="769B90C07D42AE0390040FE1BA980B16">51</mods:start>
<mods:end id="4569AE2A598645CCC805E24A44F6AA8C">80</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="1BF40915A0D46F5A532C74D912EC1179">
<mods:url id="876EB412643943E659B6AFB8B675193D">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.101.1182</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="E4FCD058DE69F41E1A34BAEE7DA2AC6B">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="56DAE4D5B903D52AEDCD0DAF026946A0" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.101.1182</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="BC6D3DA2D35595D219DF4C5B81329B18" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-101-51</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="9D20E9D4A7DBFA890597B894F7863A34" type="ZooBank">2378DEB0-816E-4667-9E5E-192F88CD76F2</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="AD2DD9C9DABA704EF24249A560EDD5A3" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152029510" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1DA0608B-A874-4338-BDAE-FECE7D9E7FEA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AD2DD9C9DABA704EF24249A560EDD5A3" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">
<subSubSection id="ECEB210CEB0ABC8D9EA3C8D51BD1F459" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="31AC436652171C59C9990587033B1944" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">
<taxonomicName id="5030BDA6E8E2FF82FD60620B3F86661D" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1DA0608B-A874-4338-BDAE-FECE7D9E7FEA" authority="Engel" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma ((Alocanthedon)) odontophorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="odontophorum" subGenus="(Alocanthedon)">Chalicodoma (Alocanthedon) odontophorum Engel</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="21076B152305627FD090BFBFE76F6CE3" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1926-28
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8CF8DF8728750E0BCC473C0860D4DDEA" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" type="holotype">
<paragraph id="7CA0AE51F749E76EFC96A4C6509A8F46" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E9C8C41F48331F5B7E24C301A4627C15" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Thailand: ♂, Sakaerat DDF [Nakhon Ratchasima Province, Sakaerat Environmental Research Area, ca. 40 km South Nakhon Ratchasima], 20 June 1995 (SEMC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1780FCEAF26851C990745663B603B9EB" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" type="paratypes">
<paragraph id="44A091C4FF2BF0D1F5C020ED480B363A" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Paratypes.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4A44D5BEF48E5BD7494B9046EBF8D688" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Thailand: ♀, Sakaerat DDF [Nakhon Ratchasima Province, Sakaerat Environmental Research Area, ca. 40 km South Nakhon Ratchasima], 17 June 1995 (SEMC); 1♂, Siam (SEMC).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0B362ED98C636012D12D9199A723587C" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Myanmar: 1♀, Middle Tenasserim, Thaungyin Valley, 5.93 [May 1893], C.T. Bingham (NHML).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D95478144C5F1F5E908A5D0AEB638EC1" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="35E23985B47B9A6C9F4345BD3860D7B8" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="91D46390F87D5B3E0C1BDB73FA9AEB03" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Both sexes of this species have yellow forewings with grayish hyaline apex. The male can be easily distinguished by the clypeus densely covered by long, appressed, apically-directed setae obscuring integument (Fig. 2) and the shape of the modified protarsi (Fig. 5). The female of this species is recognized by the clypeus with a pronounced, erect, medioapical tubercle (Fig. 8), the elongate mandibles and the labrum, with apical margin medially convex and apical fringe of erect setae separated from labral apical margin by at least one median ocellar diameter or slightly more.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F30A7A2A79BAFCF8CE49EAB77D285AE2" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="3" pageNumber="54" type="description">
<paragraph id="A3845D3476118E0C8B8B28A50325665F" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4F881AE6A11109AE379F97405DD8F95B" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="3" pageNumber="54">
As for the subgenus with the following additions: Male: Total body length 20 mm; forewing length 13.3 mm. Head broader than long (width 5.3 mm, length 4.0 mm); inner orbits of compound eyes slightly divergent below; intertorular distance 1.6 times torulorbital distance; interocellar distance 1.8 times median ocellar diameter, slightly shorter than ocellocular distance; ocelloccipital distance 4.2 times median ocellar diameter; compound eye about 2.2 times longer than wide, 1.2 times wider than gena in profile. Mandible with three teeth, with prominent, broad median inferior protuberance bearing dense, short, black setae. Juxtamandibular flange about 
<pageBreakToken id="37B679559C5965AAD238EF609489F760" pageId="4" pageNumber="55" start="start">twice</pageBreakToken>
as long as posterior height. Labrum rectangular, with apical row of stiff, erect, long setae. Clypeus broad, width more than three times medial length. Scape length about 2.5 times width; first flagellomere short, nearly one-third length of second flagellomere; remaining flagellomeres all much longer than wide, apicalmost flagellomere with broadly rounded apex, not tapering. Mesoscutum with distinct notauli and parapsidal lines. Procoxal spine elongate, with weak depression between spine and medial, transverse carina of procoxa, posterobasally setose on spine, anterior surface not setose; protibia with strong, outer, posterior carina running along apical three-quarters of length, apically produced into small posteriorly-directed spine before continuing transversely across apex to outer, anterior border where it forms definite ridge but not carinate, apical anterior surface faintly depressed in profile view; protarsus modified as in figure 5; meso- and metafemora somewhat swollen; mesotibial spur curved, with bluntly rounded apex; mesobasitarsus with inner surface concave basally, posterior border along concavity relatively straight; outer metatibial spur blunt at apex (not tapering to acute apex); pretarsal claws long, curved, apically cleft. Postgradular depressions deeper than in female; terga 
<normalizedToken id="B9165E69C20F01406A50722DAF944B02" originalValue="II–V">II-V</normalizedToken>
with apical transverse ridge (caudad postgradular depression), somewhat sinuate laterally, weak medially on terga 
<normalizedToken id="59A714EEFC67DA25200ACAF51C6CC483" originalValue="II–IV">II-IV</normalizedToken>
; preapical carina of sixth tergum produced, weakly and broadly concave medially (Fig. 6). Genitalia as in figures 26-28.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5C192406842BF181C8689D2E73102E51" pageId="4" pageNumber="55">Integument black throughout except tegula, legs, and metasomal sterna largely dark reddish brown (nearly black in many areas), and expansion of protarsi more translucent brown. Wings orange-yellow except apical margin of forewing and apical and posterior margins of hind wing grayish hyaline (Fig. 1); venation ferruginous to orange-yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C52CAA99053003E4BE761C3A14148DE9" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="57" pageId="4" pageNumber="55">
Mandible with outer surface dull, irregularly punctate and microreticulate; labrum strongly imbricate and impunctate; clypeus with small, contiguous punctures, with thin mediolongitudinal impunctate area; supraclypeal area and face below ocelli with small, contiguous punctures, punctures becoming more irregular at level of median ocellus; area between ocelli with small, contiguous punctures; ocellocular area with 
<pageBreakToken id="4FC5BD84B075337AC733C025BBFE8113" pageId="5" pageNumber="56" start="start">somewhat</pageBreakToken>
larger, coarser punctures separated by areas of finely imbricate integument; vertex with coarse, shallow punctures separated by a puncture width or less, integument between finely imbricate, punctures becoming more shallow and faint toward preoccipital carina; upper gena with irregular, elongate punctures separated by finely imbricate integument, remainder of gena and posterior postgena with more regular 
<pageBreakToken id="A10B55EB829798054DBB36D799A5860E" pageId="6" pageNumber="57" start="start">punctures</pageBreakToken>
separated by a puncture width or less, integument otherwise finely imbricate; postgenal surface inside of deep postgenal depression with scattered minute punctures separated by faintly imbricate to smooth integument; outer surface of juxtamandibular lamella with irregular punctures and imbricate integument. Pronotum imbricate, with small punctures separated by a puncture width or less; mesoscutum anteriorly and medially transversely wrinkled with irregular punctures, such integument blending laterally outside of parapsidal lines and posteriorly to coarsely punctate, punctures separated by a puncture width or less, those outside of parapsidal lines somewhat smaller and more regularly defined than those posteriorly, integument between punctures finely imbricate; tegula finely imbricate and minutely punctate, punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except along outer rim impunctate; axillae and mesoscutellum coarsely and contiguously punctate except mediobasally on mesoscutellum with punctures smaller and gradually becoming separated by a puncture width or less; metanotum imbricate with small punctures separated by a puncture width or less; pleura coarsely and contiguously punctate, those punctures along omaular ridge and ventrally somewhat dorsoventrally elongate, giving ventral surface a somewhat dorsoventrally rugulose appearance; declivitous basal area of propodeum with single row of coarse alveolae along extreme basal border, row interrupted medially, otherwise surface imbricate and impunctate; lateral surface imbricate with small punctures separated by less than a puncture width, gradually becoming more widely spaced posteriorly and on posterior surface. Anterior-facing surface of first metasomal tergum finely imbricate, dorsal-facing surface imbricate with small punctures separated by a puncture width or less, nearly contiguous in most areas; remaining terga sculptured as on dorsal-facing surface of first metasomal tergum; terga with narrow impunctate apical rims; sterna smooth to finely imbricate, with small punctures separated by less than a puncture width.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2748B580D327D0D136AA515741A5626E" pageId="6" pageNumber="57">Pubescence generally dark fuscous to black except as follows: clypeus, supraclypeal area, and face outside of antennal toruli with dense, long, minutely-branched, tawny to white setae, largely obscuring the integument, those on clypeus more strongly tawny and largely appressed and apically directed; thin fringe of short, fine, silvery white setae along outer border of patch of black setae on median inferior protuberance and running proximally to mandibular condyle; dense patch of white pubescence immediately posterior to dense patch of somewhat shorter black setae at posterior end of postgenal depression, white patch largely occupying area at meeting of postgena and ventral area of gena; white, long setae on pronotal lateral surfaces, outer borders of propleura, outer base of procoxa, and preomaular area; white and black setae arranged on protarsus and apex of protibia as in figure 5; and white setae on propodeal lateral surface, most dense ventrally, near metacoxa; wing setae generally yellow or tawny yellow except dense cluster of short, black setae forming a conspicuous spot in posterior half of forewing medial cell (Fig. 4).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4CC16B7E2140CD78FDCAE026F9758FEC" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="6" pageNumber="57">
Female: As for the male except in usual sexual differences and as follows: Total body length 19-21 mm; forewing length 14.9 mm. Head broader than long (width 6.1 mm, length 4.5 mm); intertorular distance about as long as torulorbital distance; 
<pageBreakToken id="417BCBB872509605D533B03D2727BF08" pageId="7" pageNumber="58" start="start">interocellar</pageBreakToken>
distance 2.4 times median ocellar diameter, 0.8 times ocellocular distance; ocelloccipital distance 6.9 times median ocellar diameter; compound eye about twice as long as wide, slightly narrower than gena in profile. Mandible with four teeth; body of mandible elongate, basal section distinctly longer than apical, dentate margin (Fig. 8). Labrum rectangular, with apical row of stiff, erect, long setae separated from apical margin by at least one median ocellar diameter; apical margin medially convex. Clypeus with pronounced, medioapical tubercle (all species have a minute point here, but not distinctly tuberculate as in this species) (Fig. 8). Scape length more than three times width; first flagellomere short, about one-half length of second flagellomere; re 
<pageBreakToken id="00F084BD38198F5B0ADDF5977AE48C86" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" start="start">maining</pageBreakToken>
flagellomeres all about twice as long as wide. Procoxae, tibiae, tarsi, and spurs unmodified; pretarsal claws long, curved, simple. Postgradular depressions faint; terga without transverse ridges, with slight lateral swellings on terga II and III.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="78C24207F2DFF8FB39A5B050A714C6B7" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">Clypeus imbricate with coarse, shallow punctures separated by less than a puncture width in basal half except medially such punctures restricted to basal border; supraclypeal area with smaller coarse punctures than those on clypeus, punctures separated by less than a puncture width; face below ocelli with small, contiguous punctures, punctures becoming more irregular at level of median ocellus; ocellocular area with somewhat larger, coarser punctures separated by areas of finely imbricate integument; vertex with coarse, shallow punctures separated by 0.5-1.5 times a puncture width, integument between finely imbricate, punctures becoming more shallow and faint toward preoccipital carina; postgena strongly rugulose; hypostoma imbricate. Mesoscutum anteriorly and medially transversely wrinkled, more weakly so than in male, with irregular punctures, such integument blending laterally and posteriorly to faintly coarsely punctate, punctures separated by less than a puncture width, those outside of parapsidal lines sparse, integument between punctures finely imbricate; axillae and mesoscutellum strongly coarsely and contiguously punctate except mediobasally on mesoscutellum with punctures smaller and gradually becoming separated by a puncture width or less. Dorsal-facing surface of first metasomal tergum imbricate with small punctures separated by a puncture width or less medially and nearly contiguous laterally; remaining terga sculptured as on lateral areas of dorsal-facing surface of first metasomal tergum.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F557874C04D4A11C0ACCD959BC42DF9D" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">Usual sex differences in setation; pubescence dark fuscous to black except microtrichia on inner surface of mandible dark golden and small dirty white patch on lateral surface of propodeum near metacoxa; clypeus and supraclypeal area not obscured by dense pubescence; ventral surfaces of mesepisternum, coxae, trochanters, base of femora, anterior margins of metatibia and metafemur, and sternal scopa with capitate setae.</paragraph>
<caption id="E5BC4D0155718C15653C5F924396B68B" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph id="397231D86BAC0C138CE763C27DAE68DD" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
Table 1. Summary of currently included species in subgenus 
<taxonomicName id="154026A8C583064660A1CB3B403505C2" authority="Engel &amp; Gonzalez, 2011" authorityName="Engel &amp; Gonzalez" authorityYear="2011" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Alocanthedon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Alocanthedon" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Alocanthedon</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="53DAD0DABECC622428C3E09A3C6DC41B" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<table id="53A37D78A82FE03D22E6EA912133D4EE" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<tr id="FF46094DB482866BAEDBC281A1C48080" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<th id="445355AA339B2426F23A39C41A2083B0" colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Species</th>
<th id="F06D7CA78B6020297A61AF6DAFE0758E" colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">General distribution</th>
</tr>
<tr id="4F13CD40EBDA5BD2EC980195B3BF3734" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<td id="546317FD21CAEBD1E0C1AD10B1A6697A" colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName id="9727ED2D5E806E386E3ECB08DEFBCF0D" authority="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau, 1841" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma apoicola" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="apoicola">Chalicodoma apoicola</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr id="31DE1D34E1E52FD20A56FF3DFDA6944D" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<td id="2FB527ED7BBA9DD1FD00A3CF48C79A0C" colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName id="6A71881D1908C0D2F135BF9940282013" authority="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau, 1841" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma aterrimum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aterrimum">Chalicodoma aterrimum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr id="FE530802D2CABE3465A1942B67566C8D" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<td id="B8EE8BEB32C49CC202D9D0504D7B4D32" colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rowspan="3">
<taxonomicName id="27EEFFEFA391C9B31BFDB42772E48F57" authority="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau, 1841" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma atratiforme" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="atratiforme">Chalicodoma atratiforme</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr id="2CD655AF40EB1AFBDECDB3D5E13CCBC7" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<td id="3AB3BF327D194BF3F83665CA8B802373" colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rowspan="1">
<taxonomicName id="A2C093D350A03155B252C998CAA0C9FD" authority="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau, 1841" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma memecylonae" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="memecylonae">Chalicodoma memecylonae</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
<tr id="94FD8C3FE91E2189D0DB345C8BD87B07" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<td id="B9C342910C5D4E47B1116FC105BE376A" colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rowspan="2">
<taxonomicName id="893C2377A49A0C907215D8950900E72F" authority="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau, 1841" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma odontophorum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="odontophorum">Chalicodoma odontophorum</taxonomicName>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<caption id="C5E13D722AFE47F82ABB89EC41DABD67" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph id="BEDF9B25E54D9E4671CDE1E1FF3E7AD6" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
Figures 1-6. Photomicrographs of male of 
<taxonomicName id="3F7315C12BCAE063BDBDECE054AFEC6B" authority="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau, 1841" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Chalicodoma</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName id="503FCC772C4AF5A660D98491ABD34295" authority="Engel &amp; Gonzalez, 2011" authorityName="Engel &amp; Gonzalez" authorityYear="2011" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Alocanthedon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Alocanthedon" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Alocanthedon</taxonomicName>
) odontophorum Engel, sp. n. 1 Dorsal habitus 2 Facial aspect 3 Dorsal aspect of mesoscutum and mesoscutellum 4 Detail of forewing medial cell 5 Protarsus, pro-pretarsus, and protibia 6 Dorsal aspect of metasomal terga V and VI.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="2F8DAE0BDF805E6A26E22F4A1AB71E64" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph id="2589C175257DD300D9260D1E13C67187" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
Figures 7-9. Photomicrographs of female of 
<taxonomicName id="196E1A973E5EBBF02E015F7944778E13" authority="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau, 1841" authorityName="Lepeletier de St.Fargeau" authorityYear="1841" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Chalicodoma" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chalicodoma" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Chalicodoma</taxonomicName>
(
<taxonomicName id="0CA8A80314368093E8E0785AB7AD0327" authority="Engel &amp; Gonzalez, 2011" authorityName="Engel &amp; Gonzalez" authorityYear="2011" class="Insecta" family="Megachilidae" genus="Alocanthedon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Alocanthedon" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Alocanthedon</taxonomicName>
) odontophorum Engel, sp. n. 7 Dorsal habitus 8 Facial aspect (with expanded detail of clypeus, arrow indicating medioapical tubercle) 9 Dorsal aspect of mesoscutum and mesoscutellum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E0E746DF0B2AE8F92FA71E1490CB2361" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="0E2DC9D14CB8102B5A9EB0B1F4795227" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2DC7E00AC340A3BEC3C09DD9F42874C1" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
The specific epithet is a combination of the Greek word odontos (meaning, 
<normalizedToken id="54DE5FF5E192F413233F5334214DC6D2" originalValue="“teeth”">&quot;teeth&quot;</normalizedToken>
) and suffix -phor (meaning, 
<normalizedToken id="D7D7DADCAE474E1D79206786C49548C9" originalValue="“carry”">&quot;carry&quot;</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7F3E095C3ABA6DB65A8BF05F913C244D" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" type="floral records">
<paragraph id="CC41046A5B9B65C8013F08522CF17D82" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">Floral records.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="507963E774FAC6E0F890C8ADF9F7AB4B" pageId="8" pageNumber="59">
The holotype and paratype from Sakaerat were captured at flowers of 
<taxonomicName id="8A5B37EF4ADCE60DDECDC79344B9892F" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fabaceae" genus="Sindora" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Sindora siamensis" order="Fabales" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="siamensis">Sindora siamensis</taxonomicName>
Teijsman &amp; Miquel (Fabales: 
<taxonomicName id="19E4F8705DC0C7AE077E4E27A762FA99" genus="Fabaceae" lsidName="Fabaceae" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rank="genus">Fabaceae</taxonomicName>
: 
<taxonomicName id="12551DA76056B007307034F07E8FD3E7" genus="Caesalpinioideae" lsidName="Caesalpinioideae" pageId="8" pageNumber="59" rank="genus">Caesalpinioideae</taxonomicName>
: Detarieae).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>