<document id="A28C0769F231EA2A006B5FFFE0D6B570" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6292876" ID-GBIF-Dataset="620aac46-b4c8-42a1-a0a0-409792b70c2b" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100130609" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6292876" ModsDocID="3948" checkinTime="1243374478140" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Forel, A." docDate="1893" docId="AF006A15421A8337B70A9A4814CFF57C" docLanguage="en" docName="3948" docOrigin="Transactions of the Entomological Society of London 1893" docSource="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/social_insects/ants/publications/3948/3948.pdf" docTitle="Odontomachus haematodes var. hirsutiusculus , Smith" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="355" masterDocId="3C86B8CE88F3E20382761CE3CF3BA529" masterDocTitle="Formicides de l'Antille St. Vincent. Récoltées par Mons. H. H. Smith." masterLastPageNumber="418" masterPageNumber="333" pageNumber="354" updateTime="1645845610579" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="65BBB9DA9632FF782F4212130AF36EA5" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="44B1B549E8D9CC66FDF01DCE1583ADCE">
<mods:title id="BA406FB39D02697E78AA5BFD16CE11B8">Formicides de l'Antille St. Vincent. Récoltées par Mons. H. H. Smith.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="13BDFA59DC68B6F26992FB22DFE15510" type="personal">
<mods:role id="4E99EC046C10A4AD2D24F353EE1A7B5F">
<mods:roleTerm id="41CD343BED6953E3593DF17C52F3FDF9">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7F91042A4DCA770CA771F8F24453C1E7">Forel, A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="9C42FC7AFBDAF5D88C8B121B05311273">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="7CA1ABD4A5587BF413746FF111ECC676" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="4CD380875C17A5748B79FD838059D4AE">
<mods:title id="64D81FD334176191B4C1EF9C7CF7D7F4">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="584D8B27851DBF2521F7B8F151276CFF">
<mods:date id="5ABB9E27FD81BBDE96FC595C25EF6255">1893</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="42CAB16C77047238A06C4BCE4256D32C" type="volume">
<mods:number id="E811B1B5F31091575722EAFB0E9127FE">1893</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="D65FE5FC1FF5608A815392F05B130BD9" unit="page">
<mods:start id="8CB09756B9269546B1E03E532802918F">333</mods:start>
<mods:end id="473871862E22BAE534A0F4209DD45444">418</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="A12CB3BA89E1F26D302E675DB3DF03C7">
<mods:url id="3A2E60A7EF79A2963DC6431284A16E21">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/social_insects/ants/publications/3948/3948.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="96907794113027C080448247FA9E44BF">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="4CCE93BD7BB13FB5B10830F7F62931EB" type="HNS-PUB">3948</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8FF5B4E7030ADC2136DDE1C7A191F045" type="ZooBank">5E6A481F-664E-428C-A636-08D4BD5A1EF0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="AF006A15421A8337B70A9A4814CFF57C" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6292876" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100130609" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6292876" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:AF006A15421A8337B70A9A4814CFF57C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF006A15421A8337B70A9A4814CFF57C" lastPageNumber="355" pageNumber="354">
<subSubSection id="35A25E02D2E8150B93E3B074DF03D080" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="755B4617B71D95AA58E6E44720D0329B" pageNumber="354">
<taxonomicName id="7574D72D67DAB242D5C22F94DD3DAA29" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:187968" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Odontomachus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Odontomachus haematodes var. hirsutiusculus Smith" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="354" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="variety" species="haematodes" variety="hirsutiusculus">O. haematodes, L. var. hirsutiusculus, Smith</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="79C955913BD9D6BD3132D50198F423B7" type="description">
<paragraph id="BE370C451CECA37C235DD080B2FF08FB" pageNumber="354">(No 5 a a 5 d). [[ worker ]] [[ queen ]].</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7C3999BAA29764DDE7E31D502532AE37" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph id="1BDAD88C84426AC5730FEBF6557438E3" pageNumber="354">(4). Very common, especially in the forest, but also in open land; 2500 ft. to sea-level. Formicarium generally under a log; sometimes in rotten wood, or under stones. It may consist of many, hundred individuals, but is oftener small. Winged males are rarely found in the colonies, but the winged females may escape observation from their ' close resemblance to the workers. When disturbed the ants move above lazily, and are not very pugnacious; a large nest, however, is not to be examined with impunity, as the ants sting rather severely if they get on the skin. In the daytime the ants keep to shady places, and are nearly always found on the ground or on logs. I do not know if they also forage at night. These ants accumulate the mounds of earth and dead flowers sometimes found in the forest, but I have never seen them cutting leaves or flowers; they may do so at night. The females fly at night. The workers walk about with. the jaws wide open, at right angles to the head, but close them quickly when disturbed.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3DB32EC873CA1965FB49CF49177ECD0B" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="AA0531F8F649CB9B4BA553E35ABDA833" pageNumber="354">(4 a). Lot 14 Estate; shady place, 500 ft. May. Under a log (a large formicarium, probably 2000 individuals).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="27BD85AB8AEE662739420E8FD51C0B95" pageNumber="354">(4 b). Cavolries, S. slope of Mt. St. Andrews, 1400 ft.; open place. Two only, found under a stone.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4A8DA23C2C163FD93476D13C7100772F" pageNumber="354">(4 c). Females; came to light at light. Golden Grove Estate (leeward), 400 ft. April.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BCE82F6B1AE560CE7E25F062B76706AD" pageNumber="354">(4 d). Camden Park Estate; leeward, near Kingstown, Nov. 19 th. Seashore; under a stone. About fifty ants were seen. '.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6638EA560A47026B0C5DE7D2E3916703" pageNumber="354">(4 e). Near Barronallie (leeward); open places near sea-level; under a log. Jan. 15 th.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5065F1401EA083437648BF419E496D38" pageNumber="354">(4 f). Golden Grove Estate (leeward), 300 ft. Jan. 26 th. Came to light at night.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C7534953A2A7796BB369595A9E416D29" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph id="4D7DF7FF42241749BBA942990A25A0EF" lastPageNumber="355" pageNumber="354">This species, so far as I can judge, makes extensive underground works; probably those found under stones, logs, &amp; c., are merely at the surface ends of tunnels leading to the deeper and perhaps large formicarium. In the woods are often seen mounds of sand and bits of earth, from which tunnels lead downward; and these ants are always found in the tunnels. The mounds may be two feet in diameter, and a foot high, indicating extensive works, from which the earth ia taken. Mingled with the earth there are nearly always quantities of small flowers, probably picked up on the ground when they fell from trees; great quantities of the flowers are also frequently seen under the stones and logs, where the ants are found with their pupae. I have not seen the ants gathering these flowers, and judge that they collect them at night.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="BA9978E9EC87038A54C79FB1A8075395" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="57AD0F13BD9796D1F4B3209E16BCFA2B" pageNumber="355">(5). Rather rare; distinct from No 4. All seem more like the specimens sent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="67B560117309B9E7A372C7F7B3982A75" pageNumber="355">(5 a). Thickets by sea-shore at the &quot; Villa &quot; Estate; southern end of the island. Oct. 14 th. Under a stone in loamy sand at the root of a tree. About forty individuals in the nest, apparently all workers; they had many larvae, which, when disturbed, were carried to deep passages under the stone.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9AEA1F94279FCA2B2AC16D9B77D3BA5B" pageNumber="355">(5 b). Richmond Estate (leeward); open valley near sea-level. Oct. 31 st. Under a. log. Apparently a formicarium, but I could find no winged ones.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="64E3F8667CAFC6A7A04D80357B929E48" pageNumber="355">(5 c). Fitz-Hugh Estate (leeward), Nov. 13 th. Open place near sea-level; under a stone. Only a few ants seen.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="64E3A05920C4E73A899F4C486ECF1F73" pageNumber="355">(5 d). Windward side; shady bed of Dry River; near the sea. Jan. 2 nd. Under a stone. The species is common along the windward coast, under stones and logs. The communities apparently are not large; but, like No. 4, this species seems to make extensive underground works, with outlets under stones and logs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A1A32DFBC5D1D4A922D84323179D974A" pageNumber="355">(6 a). These males, as I suppose, belong to No. 4 or 5; they came to light at night. Golden Grove Estate (leeward), 500 ft. The date was lost, but if my memory serves, they were taken in July or August.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="873E770657D431A3080D1F15395E1860" pageNumber="355">(6 b). Forest, Morne a Garou, 2000 ft. Nov. 1 st. Beaten from foliage. No 4 is common in this forest.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7842309554D4BDD7324CBDE1E5D36DDE" pageNumber="355">(15 a). Richmond Estate; open valley near sea-level. Oct. 31 st. A single specimen found under a log. Many workers of No. 4 were under the same log.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="02E2CA2267469C037940CA8279151A78" pageNumber="355">(15 b). Near the Wallibou River (leeward), 500 ft. Jan. 10 th. Open damp hill-side. Found alone under a stone.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>