<document id="1FB3150DACF633428353DFE4EDD43127" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6250989" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3828b471-8ba7-459e-b81a-a07e8e088d46" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134143" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6250989" ModsDocID="21337" checkinTime="1243372357116" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Early, J. W., Masner, L. &amp; Johnson, N. F." docDate="2007" docId="B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F" docLanguage="en" docName="21337" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1655" docSource="http://128.146.250.117/pdfs/21337/21337.pdf" docTitle="Archaeoteleia dispar Early, Masner &amp; Johnson, 2007, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="13" lastPageNumber="28" masterDocId="42A7F90238ABEF8A8CF4DEB1D4013591" masterDocTitle="Revision of Archaeoteleia Masner (Hymenoptera: Platygastroidea, Scelionidae)." masterLastPageNumber="48" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="25" updateTime="1645655855348" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="EC7A20EAECAA9D16F0F345F28179EEB0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="068E33E96CD5F3D549F389700C8C493C">
<mods:title id="D501C759A3EFA4D63EB1D52EB941FB49">Revision of Archaeoteleia Masner (Hymenoptera: Platygastroidea, Scelionidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="83E7D928A5B9452348557397E6EBCB2D" type="personal">
<mods:role id="2D17B4310DE31211D375E67D701081AF">
<mods:roleTerm id="3DFB00E028E38FE3ADF90C5ABAC8029E">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="A0332DC227F80AF1A4123DDCE6980F7E">Early, J. W.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="1E9E4CA3943F409E0DEDE350F65F8985" type="personal">
<mods:role id="828523E9C041B5A7E3E238F023823997">
<mods:roleTerm id="73625044C593CBF92588AC98AD4A0334">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7651B947A7D174E50FB0EA21710EE59D">Masner, L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="613934244974E0187A3CEF22F29D8055" type="personal">
<mods:role id="06BDE69C288B23B3638F5714E25D4D7C">
<mods:roleTerm id="C19E0E62500DE42FF5A8270B2A96B0FC">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="BBA91A95F6931AD826886A01BB9E2EB8">Johnson, N. F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="A0115E82F207DB43582D6D20D0F3D6FA">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="A172C604950CC55E764BEE09A935218C" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="A311F357695E7E1681D3190BBDD0F880">
<mods:title id="32FD5E7E972CF85D3C93C37E5F9AA4D1">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="0224733B52E6B415AAA4AF7509A75654">
<mods:date id="B6D9B1F0E96E38DB439BC372F47927B9">2007</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="6C903F38340DD963C65F6EE938721E46" type="volume">
<mods:number id="3721393741B3F7502C61A4BBBA91CA0C">1655</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="5BF2F595C0EA4080B582B10B1D51BB7F" unit="page">
<mods:start id="2581836A5D7E4BD4CBCDB3B76C723FF8">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="2E2A8AF6FD9F17EC41E00ED63059EF4C">48</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="6BD17BE9DCA4287637C55186E546C7AB">
<mods:url id="5B593E6547D626BA166C5E6BAB879D47">http://128.146.250.117/pdfs/21337/21337.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="A3798FC0DD0D88991C1D8DAB842D82F6">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="9F12A166A9B906C8448CFD6801254BFB" type="HNS-PUB">21337</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="869479EF935206B73C6E6B7B32973280" type="ZooBank">EB6AF94E-8EEB-4E53-A98D-1F4E24493623</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6250989" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134143" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6250989" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F" lastPageNumber="28" pageNumber="25">
<subSubSection id="E3D63F9559CF7E9A5C7F86206C727156" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="E79CB3D9EA6AC8C9A66339F7ACF7DC15" pageNumber="25">
<taxonomicName id="12A174632F66858A9FE190EE56CBA369" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:190981" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Archaeoteleia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Archaeoteleia dispar Masner" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dispar">
<pageStartToken id="2CE444B6EE4BEBF1706A31FBCAC7AEF5" pageNumber="25">Archaeoteleia</pageStartToken>
dispar Masner
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="82A48663EE3400C1BDBF725A1FE9F85E" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="89FE3C8D99A52E0053D76FF26DF16964" type="description">
<paragraph id="FC4E91DAC726771F0F5B8E1B3C5B8E95" pageNumber="25">Description: Female. Length 3.0-4.8 mm. Color: body light brown; A1-A5 bright yellow, A6-A12 almost black; legs, including coxae, bright yellow; gena, ventral and lateral portions of mesosoma dark brown, metasomatic sternites darker than tergites.</paragraph>
<caption id="EA30DE3756ACF0E6169FCEEBC90CB5AC">
<paragraph id="F40680B98C2DD0E0481DE5C3F5E72FE4" pageNumber="25">Figures 36-41</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="85BF1A9ECE1374CD47E60FBEE4F8CD50" pageNumber="25">Head (Figs. 36, 37, 40): vertex, temples, upper frons densely punctate, setose; patches of longitudinal rugulosity along inner orbits, middle portion of frons below anterior ocellus with fine, dense punctures, with fine, appressed pilosity; upper gena rugose punctate, sculpture more finely expressed in smaller specimens; eye sparsely setose; vertex between posterior ocelli and occipital carina slightly concave medially; LOL subequal to OOL; occipital carina sharp, acute, complete, simple to deeply crenulate; frons medially with strong keel reaching about half distance to anterior ocellus; striae on lower frons reaching inner orbits, striae on lower gena well developed; clypeus transversely striate, punctate dorsally, anterolateral corners strongly projecting; antennal toruli confluent with dorsal margin of clypeus; A1 4.6-5.5 times longer than wide; A2 2.5-2.7 times longer than wide; A3 1.9-2.3 times as long as A2; flagellum with fairly long, semierect setae; claval formula A6-A12/2-2-2-2-2-2-1.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="999C5BA2D9B623950E8BD378E41C58FA" lastPageNumber="26" pageNumber="25">Mesosoma (Figs. 36, 37): transverse pronotal carina almost straight, bladelike sharp, median tooth not pronounced, anterolateral corners only moderately angular, not spinelike; vertical epomia absent; horizontal epomia turned downward posteriorly, distinctly separated from mesoscutum, pronotal shoulders very broad, with rough rugulosity; side of pronotum glabrous, almost entirely smooth and shining; netrion distinctly delimited by arc of foveolae; mesoscutum strongly reduced, moderately convex, deeply punctured, with fine, scattered pilosity; admedian lines absent; notaulus deep, broad, coarsely foveolate; parapsidal line absent; transscutal articulation deep, strongly foveolate; scutellum strongly transverse, striplike, length 0.5-0.6 times length of mesoscutum, deeply punctate, with appressed pilosity, apical margin distinctly crenulate, slightly invaginated medially; scutellar spines strong, straight, sharply pointed, at about 45° angle to longitudinal axis of body or greater; mesopleural carina absent; mesopleuron predominantly glabrous, smooth, mesepisternum ventrally predominantly smooth, shining, almost glabrous, with row of deep crenulae above mid coxa; acetabular carina distinct, crenulate; posterior margin of mesopleuron with complete chain of deep foveolae reaching ventrally to coxal cavity; metapleuron predominantly glabrous, with only very few small, scattered setae, shining, with row of foveolae along anterior margin and arcuate foveolar line at meson, roughly rugulose above hind coxa, smooth and shining medially; propodeum moderately setose, posteromedially almost without sculpture, nearly smooth, submedian keels weakly developed or absent; tegula minute, but present; fore wing represented in form of scale behind tegula, twice as long as tegula in largest specimens; hindwing represented by small scale, more elongate in larger specimens, not reaching past propodeal spiracles; legs: robust, but not shortened; pretarsal claws strong; hind coxa unusually large, robust, only slightly shorter than hind femur, twice as long as mid coxa, reaching posteriorly nearly as far as apex of T2, posterior surface of distal portion with transverse wrinkles.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="84CC4E25CD18B2B5F30855DAD71D9387" pageNumber="26">
<pageStartToken id="3F2364FC682C15BCF94550A6F4D9E7CC" pageNumber="26">Metasoma</pageStartToken>
relatively elongate, spindlelike, length 4.1-4.8 times width; length of T1 1.4 times width, dorsal surface of horn with transverse rugulosity, posterior part of tergite with irregular, rough rugulosity, near horn transversely oriented, near posterior margin longitudinally oriented; T2-T5 each with pair of longitudinal deep depressions; length of T2 0.7-0.8 times width; length of T3 0.6 times width; length of T4 0.6 times width; T2-T4 with exceptionally coarse, irregular rugulosity, becoming concentric in middle of sclerite, with sparse, semi-appressed setae, without bristles; length of T5 0.5-0.6 times width, depressions shallower, shorter; T6 distinctly elongate, length 2.3-2.8 times width, with finer irregular rugulosity, fairly dense semierect pilosity; small specimens with posterior surface of T1, entire T2-T4 predominantly longitudinally rugose, T5 with irregular rugulosity and punctures.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FDFBC80B4897DE72BCFF410F77BCE924" pageNumber="26">Male. Length: 2.8-4.6 mm. Color: light honey-brown with pleural and ventral region of mesosoma distinctly darker; wings slightly yellowish, not clear, with appreciable dark cloud under marginal vein; antenna and legs concolorous with body.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E84C979B7CB6F9BF985093D693AA84ED" pageNumber="26">Head (Figs. 38, 39, 41): vertex, temples, frons rugose punctate, frons with dense appressed pilosity, upper gena entirely rugose punctate, sculpture finer in smaller specimens; eye with scattered hairs; vertex behind ocelli with moderate median longitudinal depression; LOL distinctly shorter than OOL, lateral ocelli far from inner orbits, ocellar triangle very compact; occipital carina sharp, complete, finely crenulate; median keel distinct, reaching midpoint between antennal insertion and anterior ocellus; facial striae strong, reaching inner orbit, extending to lower third of eye; clypeus very high, higher than wide, anterolateral corners strongly projecting, lower half with transverse rugae, upper half almost smooth; toruli contiguous with upper margin of clypeus; A1 3.9-4.0 times as long as wide; A2 1.3 times as long as wide; A3 4.4 times as long as A2; A5-A9 gently to distinctly arched, elongate; A4 and A5 with distinct keels, keel longer on A4, in smaller specimen keels subequal in length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7074010760F8DCE6AA315C0C76F2FA79" lastPageNumber="27" pageNumber="26">Mesosoma (Figs. 38, 39): transverse pronotal carina complete, well developed, anterolateral corners angular, but not spinelike, no middle tooth; vertical epomial carina absent; horizontal epomial carina well developed, pronotal shoulder fairly broad, rugose punctate; side of pronotum partly smooth, with scattered punctures at margins; netrion well developed; mesonotum entirely covered by fine appressed pilosity, middle lobe of mesoscutum mesally with transverse rugulae, laterally densely rugospunctate; admedian lines rudimentary; notaulus complete, deeply incised, with fine foveolae; parapsidal line evanescent; transscutal articulation broad, with large foveolae; scutellum almost rectangular, densely punctate, length 0.5 times length of mesoscutum; scutellar spines short, straight, acute, pointing diagonally backwards; mesopleural carina not developed, but replaced by 3-4 longitudinal furrows on mesepisternum; upper portion of mesopleuron entirely smooth, shining, glabrous, mesepisternum below partly smooth, with scattered punctures; acetabular carina fine; chain of foveolae on posterior margin of mesopleuron complete, extending ventrally to coxal cavity; metapleuron largely glabrous, with only scattered fine hairs, with rough irregular rugulosity above hind coxa, area topped by arcuate of foveolae medially, upper metapleuron with smooth glabrous mirror, carina between metapleuron and propodeum sharply raised; propodeum with irregular, rough rugulosity, relatively sparse pilosity, median keels not developed, but with two irregular rudiments in area of keels; fore wing slightly to strongly exceeding tip of metasoma, basal vein strongly pigmented, delicate infuscated cloud below marginal vein, postmarginal vein distinctly tracheate, length 2.5 times length of stigmal vein, stigmal vein distinctly arched and slightly to distinctly hooklike at apex, Rs, M, Cu well-defined by nebulous streaks; hind basitarsus relatively strong, hind coxa very large, on posterior surface with irregular rugulosity and several transverse wrinkles above apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2D6EF0039562EB28018698BD5339D96D" pageNumber="27">
<pageStartToken id="792222F87C493201BFEAB1D5D42A906D" pageNumber="27">Metasoma</pageStartToken>
(Figs. 38, 39) distinctly elongate, length 3.3-3.6 times width; length of T1 equal to width; length of T2 0.6 times width; length of T3 0.6 times width; length of T4 0.6 times width; length of T5 0.5 times width; all five basal tergites with longitudinal costae, some irregular rugulae at sides; width of T6 0.6 times length; tergites beyond T6 extremely small, length of T7 0.3 times width, length of T8 0.6 times width.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="164628CBAF32510C93255BFEC9464380" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="1BA8D03E774F6CFC967AAEBC71B94ABB" pageNumber="27">
Diagnosis: The female is differentiated from the other flightless species, 
<taxonomicName id="32422BCFB71B80F10D48A19CE04EDFC7" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:4042" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Archaeoteleia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Archaeoteleia pygmea Masner" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pygmea">A. pygmea</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="A358C3928B251345855CC463FE1FA588" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:190987" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Archaeoteleia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Archaeoteleia submetallica Masner" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="submetallica">A. submetallica</taxonomicName>
, by the presence of short stubs of wings, deeply incised and foveolate notaulus, well-developed and foveolate transscutal articulation, and the elongate metasoma with pairs of longitudinal sublateral depressions on T2- T5. The male is distinguished from most Chilean species by the elongate, tracheate postmarginal vein, a character shared with 
<taxonomicName id="3F9E75CA84E6C2C3E7CB6B474540FFA6" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:4042" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Archaeoteleia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Archaeoteleia pygmea Masner" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pygmea">A. pygmea</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="22F27218D76300387315E21F9FD0E257" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:190986" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Archaeoteleia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Archaeoteleia robusta Masner" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robusta">A. robusta</taxonomicName>
. From those two species the male may be distinguished by the well-developed notauli (absent in 
<taxonomicName id="430B6479C427BC5276CBCDEF97915566" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:4042" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Archaeoteleia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Archaeoteleia pygmea Masner" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pygmea">A. pygmea</taxonomicName>
) and the gentle, but distinct bowlike curving of antennomeres 5- 8 (straight and cylindrical in the other two species).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="819460400A76C8E084F03EE9C4FA7385" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="990CB66543845994D1D9A8305520C925" pageNumber="27">Etymology: The specific epithet dispar, Latin for unlink or different, stresses the strong secondary sexual dimorphism of the males and females.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="44651DDA5C25F940229D2C60A13E9A3D" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="C442A189E37157AE556FDA233E8BA0AA" pageNumber="27">Link to Distribution Map. [http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu:210/hymenoptera/eol_scelionidae.content _page?page_level=3&amp;page_id=taxon_page_data&amp;page_version=190981 &amp;page_option1=M]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="61451D1E2A78F78DCFFCD3DFEAAC4C60" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="097E3774A8D690B3F63F52C5551CC85D" pageNumber="27">
Material Examined: 
<materialsCitation id="72A5EFFE88C892A547164AA86B8DEAEF" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892435" collectingDate="1988-02-22" collectingMethod="pan trap" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="L. Masner" country="CHILE" location="Chiloe Is., Ahoni Alto, 70 m, primary forest" specimenCode="OSUC 163624" stateProvince="Chiloe Prov., Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Holotype">
<typeStatus id="BFCCEBFAE2CF8E069D3A43CE9372FF96">Holotype</typeStatus>
female: 
<collectingCountry id="E34DE56DEC11C5C8A90E87040F8FBB7C">CHILE</collectingCountry>
: 
<collectingRegion id="527D4091B70D21BF587396084B22C56C">Los Lagos</collectingRegion>
, 
<location id="9CB2DC8FB2BE95FE2A8CD71B1C1BDAEA" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:9CB2DC8FB2BE95FE2A8CD71B1C1BDAEA" country="CHILE" name="Chiloe Is., Ahoni Alto, 70 m." stateProvince="Los Lagos">Chiloe Is., Ahoni Alto, 70 m.</location>
, 
<date id="2EB9FAC75292CD08E344A7AB0A49B9EF" day="22" month="02" value="1988-02-22" year="1988">
<collectingDate id="26B4C71BE909FF4477C2AC80F9AC1C5A" day="22" month="02" value="1988-02-22" year="1988">22.II.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<location id="195CCA40A5FAD0B434B7C86A48E5BE2E" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:195CCA40A5FAD0B434B7C86A48E5BE2E" country="CHILE" name="primary forest" stateProvince="Los Lagos">primary forest</location>
, 
<collectingMethod id="E9A7CF0FE9734DF45F99627EB4D0A78B">pan trap</collectingMethod>
, 
<collectorName id="13CE03DF5C49617BD3BDE4C99240337A">L. Masner</collectorName>
, 
<specimenCode id="0CBC60DF7F425A1C5C549C902EDF8C68">OSUC 163624</specimenCode>
. Deposited in 
<collectionCode id="96DE9C78A1EA5BD1CC5265126A35977A" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C71FEDDF14B16FDE9AA2FA74E2C32343" pageNumber="27">
<materialsCitation id="CECAEB251F642DFFB45944465E8E5CCB" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892433" collectingDate="1988-02-22" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="J. Peck, S. Peck" country="CHILE" location="Parque Nacional Rio Simpson, 70 m, 33 km E Puerto Aisen" specimenCode="OSUC 146498" stateProvince="Aisen Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<typeStatus id="118F975EE6350E03D5BFEA792F0777BA">Paratypes</typeStatus>
: 
<collectingCountry id="AF06683115A8DF03C84685CF1824D879">CHILE</collectingCountry>
: 
<collectingRegion id="9D7C36B392E27E8B89CB5D9A438AF659">Aisen</collectingRegion>
, 
<location id="0AD05EB0F49F321FD5136F8518A2FE6E" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:0AD05EB0F49F321FD5136F8518A2FE6E" country="CHILE" name="Parque Nacional Rio Simpson, 70 m, 33 km E Puerto Aisen" stateProvince="Aisen">Parque Nacional Rio Simpson, 70 m, 33 km E Puerto Aisen</location>
, 
<date id="BD97044E48130DBC2CF5840E099EE403" day="22" month="02" value="1988-02-22" year="1988">
<collectingDate id="487F3F8F08493A7E3E43814FDF79B1B3" day="22" month="02" value="1988-02-22" year="1988">22.II.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="29036EB6F10B6E65D1775D434DFF8C1C">J. Peck, S. Peck</collectorName>
, male, 
<specimenCode id="2A59309396492646C5295059D8DB1745">OSUC 146498</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="A5A2C7B4E90672D5CA42297D52A52F9B" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation id="786AE77612CE69DCDAFAE4777EF42799" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892442" collectingDate="1985-02-10" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="J. Peck, S. Peck" country="Chile" location="Lago Caburgua, 21 km NE Pucon, 600 m" specimenCode="OSUC 146496" stateProvince="Araucania Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<collectingRegion id="CA612BFC50A88C95A592E3B7A078FB0F">Araucania</collectingRegion>
, 
<location id="FB58BE0AB68FB42263DD6E84FC142917" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:FB58BE0AB68FB42263DD6E84FC142917" country="Chile" name="Lago Caburgua, 21 km NE Pucon, 600 m" stateProvince="Araucania">Lago Caburgua, 21 km NE Pucon, 600 m</location>
, 
<date id="528DE3C80473552FD88154889A00259E" day="15" month="12" value="1984-12-15" year="1984">
<collectingDate id="482D7F5FF5B62BB96B02D7C9CDE893A3" day="15" month="12" value="1984-12-15" year="1984">15.XII.1984</collectingDate>
</date>
-
<date id="8226BC82B4359FF19B953E004F18B90A" day="10" month="02" value="1985-02-10" year="1985">
<collectingDate id="DD326DDD57D3754A47ACAA5AE9A6DD1E" day="10" month="02" value="1985-02-10" year="1985">10.II.1985</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="1B31DB5E9B8094AA7855209111A082B0">J. Peck, S. Peck</collectorName>
, female, 
<specimenCode id="0FBC026E30D202BEB34BD27BE143AEE2">OSUC 146496</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="640789025B15537007DD18EB4B2EAD8C" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation id="4AFDE49BBAE92B875089B90289A4044C" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892459" collectingDate="1989-05" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="L. E. Pena" country="Chile" location="N of Correntoso, El Chingue" specimenCode="OSUC 146499" stateProvince="Prov. de Llanquihue, Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<collectingRegion id="BEAA7624735BA162626A56DF13C2853A">Los Lagos</collectingRegion>
, 
<location id="1FDB9BB1118B8DE0235D36B6A1CEB239" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:1FDB9BB1118B8DE0235D36B6A1CEB239" name="N of Correntoso, El Chingue" stateProvince="Los Lagos">N of Correntoso, El Chingue</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="5116F92EDFCE1E66BFF2AD450976E1F9">Prov. de Llanquihue</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingDate id="A5BE78E18D5A390E7A1FE0B4FB1ED78B">IV-V.1989</collectingDate>
, 
<collectorName id="3E92C4E0537383F2C9B3BAD8E930BDAB">L.E. Pena</collectorName>
, male, 
<specimenCode id="AC613A62011C20A5C7972DD2A271B6A5">OSUC 146499</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="F20697F2964A6CC71CC52C1F685771DB" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="3EA9E79357A558C4EE12F4FD8A6177F7" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892467" collectingDate="1988-02-10" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="G. B. Edwards" country="Chile" location="La Union, 600 m" locationDeviation="30 km W" specimenCode="OSUC 146497" stateProvince="Prov. de Valdivia" typeStatus="Paratype">
<locationDeviation id="F94665B683BE25B57DAD9647CF7F1EBB">30 km W</locationDeviation>
<location id="F673662112D49B607B71C49E366F5577" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:F673662112D49B607B71C49E366F5577" name="La Union, 600 m" stateProvince="Prov. de Valdivia">La Union, 600 m</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="F16B77B72A1807623CEE6B0CD624BB25">Prov. de Valdivia</collectingRegion>
, 
<date id="A16548222B7B967C563E92FAE737AF27" day="10" month="02" value="1988-02-10" year="1988">
<collectingDate id="042108618AF3D9034C9C85973F524DA4" day="10" month="02" value="1988-02-10" year="1988">10.II.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="B6C6533CD25783735BBC4797C7A58896">G.B. Edwards</collectorName>
, female, 
<specimenCode id="75FAD69D7CACBC2786EDD061B75DCE6E">OSUC 146497</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="1E4840C6920187366EF89D9A9B23EF65" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="C5BF32772CD12172A5CB84167295326B" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892443" collectingDate="1985-02-07" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="J. Peck, S. Peck" country="Chile" location="La Union, 700 m" locationDeviation="34 km W" specimenCode="OSUC 146495" stateProvince="Prov. de Valdivia" typeStatus="Paratype">
<locationDeviation id="C7E036EA51DE5B8E78E0DF2E6CCFCAC2">34 km W</locationDeviation>
<location id="DCC602BFC39B46636B6A7F760CF01F33" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:DCC602BFC39B46636B6A7F760CF01F33" name="La Union, 700 m" stateProvince="Prov. de Valdivia">La Union, 700 m</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="94977AC6BA13C160D94DF9DFBFA893F1">Prov. de Valdivia</collectingRegion>
, 
<date id="D03D43AAA858BC167BD138362AC4C817" day="17" month="12" value="1984-12-17" year="1984">
<collectingDate id="1059DB8D78753BEEC91D6C06BFC577CD" day="17" month="12" value="1984-12-17" year="1984">17.XII.1984</collectingDate>
</date>
-
<date id="B3837E75E6E277036776C4E45A747419" day="07" month="02" value="1985-02-07" year="1985">
<collectingDate id="7CC956AEE67E95192D418B1EF4836145" day="07" month="02" value="1985-02-07" year="1985">7.II.1985</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="FB75BA05360EE7C266CA7FC9B7252CF7">J. Peck, S. Peck</collectorName>
, female, 
<specimenCode id="AD1574EF903DAAA15ACEA334F3BA6CE3">OSUC 146495</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="F2C5648D1F219CCF46CBC2C8CC6E1729" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="32C5E0971C46046B4C126F3D95ED454D" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892477" collectingDate="1985-01-30" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="J. Peck, S. Peck" country="Chile" location="Chaiten, 60 m" locationDeviation="37 km SE" specimenCode="OSUC 146494" stateProvince="Prov. de Palena" typeStatus="Paratype">
<locationDeviation id="BF47B62DC63DED48069A3C433B0CF2E1">37 km SE</locationDeviation>
<location id="5B8DB48814AAB3C0C6A36A812B7EE8C5" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:5B8DB48814AAB3C0C6A36A812B7EE8C5" name="Chaiten, 60 m" stateProvince="Prov. de Palena">Chaiten, 60 m</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="78430C93D3DB2CB1A60A5CFE9E904613">Prov. de Palena</collectingRegion>
, 
<date id="8021046510E2FB91F2747AF532DE57AE" day="28" month="12">
<collectingDate id="CDCDBFA0FF34E7B6A5315EFD3416AF71" day="28" month="12">28.XII-</collectingDate>
</date>
<date id="24071DB6C0C641B5E1E574A50FBEAC0A" day="30" month="01" value="1985-01-30" year="1985">
<collectingDate id="C111EF0AB9B9A9EEB4FC6569C1F6E270" day="30" month="01" value="1985-01-30" year="1985">30.I.1985</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="66650205587DC9328AD6F61143461A01">J. Peck, S. Peck</collectorName>
, female, 
<specimenCode id="EDA6C8FA7B83CC9A18C335704071CC48">OSUC 146494</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="43DA9A04DD6EB577B0B81D8EA542595F" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="E3E4C9B330C6CE6A38D4082AC36961FB" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892457" collectingDate="1988-04" collectingMethod="Malaise trap" collectorName="L. Masner" country="Chile" location="Ahoni, 70 m, primary forest, Isla Chiloe" specimenCode="AMNZ 75763" stateProvince="Chiloe Prov., Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<location id="294821ADD436D6A43F9E97AD1E55F818" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:294821ADD436D6A43F9E97AD1E55F818" name="Ahoni, 70 m, primary forest" stateProvince="Isla Chiloe">Ahoni, 70 m, primary forest</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="1430742E4843B43FE60EF5782512974F">Isla Chiloe</collectingRegion>
, 
<date id="57AE4D67CF94BECA98548699632E15C8" month="04" value="1988-04" year="1988">
<collectingDate id="CB5203C5E2B5F2EACE6B77E6F1A1FED7" month="04" value="1988-04" year="1988">IV.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="98F2A8216061A02C4D6AC27A30B60838">L. Masner</collectorName>
, 
<collectingMethod id="BFC696CBA34D61F1A299899213FF92F2">Malaise trap</collectingMethod>
, male, 
<specimenCode id="C5BBAA7DE67D7483D14CF2D7894468DE">AMNZ 75763</specimenCode>
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation id="B0105234A11AB74E6C84DA05C37E27CE" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892449" collectionCode="CNCI" country="Chile" latitude="-42.0" location="Chepu, 120 ft, mixed forest, Isla Chiloe" specimenCode="OSUC 163623" stateProvince="Chiloe Prov., Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<location id="9C3B0AEBC2C6ED3D955000F972D00B5F" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:9C3B0AEBC2C6ED3D955000F972D00B5F" latitude="-42.0" name="Chepu" stateProvince="Isla Chiloe">Chepu</location>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="9209FE38F9810C3696F29D1F32870668" direction="south" orientation="latitude" value="-42.0">42°S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<location id="6808C6D06A05ACC319CA634BB6215D12" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:6808C6D06A05ACC319CA634BB6215D12" latitude="-42.0" name="120 ft, mixed forest" stateProvince="Isla Chiloe">120 ft, mixed forest</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="D3359BEF83ADEAD6260A72F07E4F3091">Isla Chiloe</collectingRegion>
, female, 
<specimenCode id="FAEA64A2D8E248B86F1FC1BE1F05AD81">OSUC 163623</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="2A1573F925026516A0EFE8A15F87CDEB" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="76AFEF12E8D8953BA7D2732ABD7EDFEA" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892450" collectingDate="1988-02-22" collectingMethod="pan trap" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="L. Masner" country="Chile" location="Chiloe Is., Ahoni Alto, 70 m, primary forest" specimenCode="OSUC 146500, 163625" stateProvince="Chiloe Prov., Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Paratypes">
<collectingRegion id="78771E1C468EB45F2C4F12521C0F41F4">Chiloe Is.</collectingRegion>
, 
<location id="67F929270625B92BBB9E53AFA7F605C6" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:67F929270625B92BBB9E53AFA7F605C6" country="Chile" name="Ahoni Alto, 70 m." stateProvince="Chiloe Is.">Ahoni Alto, 70 m.</location>
, 
<date id="3ECA01EAEB79E25655F1BDFE39A76AFC" day="22" month="02" value="1988-02-22" year="1988">
<collectingDate id="B2177B63C6BB8B685B7F741BBE716243" day="22" month="02" value="1988-02-22" year="1988">22.II.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<location id="206DD05EE87CFAA4114EBF5A71A48A33" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:206DD05EE87CFAA4114EBF5A71A48A33" country="Chile" name="primary forest" stateProvince="Chiloe Is.">primary forest</location>
, 
<collectingMethod id="CBD019E4E234B91436CB2245EEBE56CE">pan trap</collectingMethod>
, 
<collectorName id="F9067683BC5045B7651ED4BC659C54A2">L. Masner</collectorName>
, 
<specimenCode id="CD39E3880AC434D73143CA7879ABB890">OSUC 146500, 163625</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="02CE0912891F0C8149EBA4F79521AD32" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="CE877A0D27286F200A2031CBB9360EF0" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892455" collectingDate="1988-02-07" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="L. Masner" country="Chile" location="Las Trancas, 500 m, 30 km W La Union" specimenCode="OSUC 146501" stateProvince="Prov. de Valdivia" typeStatus="Paratype">
<location id="8DE82915AEF8653C39A55644146887AB" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:8DE82915AEF8653C39A55644146887AB" name="Las Trancas, 500 m, 30 km W La Union" stateProvince="Prov. de Valdivia">Las Trancas, 500 m, 30 km W La Union</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="17DF13356D9DD764F42A898CE7BC3B19">Prov. de Valdivia</collectingRegion>
, 
<date id="C8B0618D8740892EF0323E1D840574B9" day="07" month="02" value="1988-02-07" year="1988">
<collectingDate id="A22882E3DFCE26679ECADB9D68310877" day="07" month="02" value="1988-02-07" year="1988">7.II.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="190FFE0DC1253365DCFF2A23C99756EB">L. Masner</collectorName>
, male, 
<specimenCode id="68E1FE45A7C7F17730184FD70F4D263E">OSUC 146501</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="86CBDA61DF0E8880C596C1FF097DC0B7" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="0CED17EED5E806B2AFF2CA6BEDC109E7" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892454" collectingDate="2002-12-12" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="L. Masner" country="Chile" latitude="-42.333332" location="Parque Nacional Chiloe, sea level, Isla Chiloe" longitude="-74.116667" specimenCode="OSUC 146504" stateProvince="Chiloe Prov., Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<location id="B6DBAB2F5510076E192B824561847B7B" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:B6DBAB2F5510076E192B824561847B7B" latitude="-42.333332" name="Parque Nacional Chiloe" stateProvince="Isla Chiloe">Parque Nacional Chiloe</location>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="486974FFFFD51247640A63471B663AB5" direction="south" orientation="latitude" value="-42.333332">42°20'S</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate id="F7B63F99C85C032E7533D055E49FB781">747'W</geoCoordinate>
, 
<location id="B37EBB43406B0CB89CF9367603728637" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:B37EBB43406B0CB89CF9367603728637" latitude="-42.333332" name="sea level" stateProvince="Isla Chiloe">sea level</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="DEAB3BDDEFB62594DAF2A73B579464FC">Isla Chiloe</collectingRegion>
, 11-
<date id="5A31385518AFF21B74530D81B1A89DC9" day="12" month="12" value="2002-12-12" year="2002">
<collectingDate id="F62ACCFA94E17B0A160E5D972EB03612" day="12" month="12" value="2002-12-12" year="2002">12.XII.2002</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="A336C1BFB1C2425DFBB661D2A08D9D17">L. Masner</collectorName>
, male, 
<specimenCode id="FD1FD55137178751D42404784C7AC9D5">OSUC 146504</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="07C34E20FFD1CA865CE038178894F99D" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="373F1245CE77E346ED54DF420160804C" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892452" collectingDate="1995-02-15" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="A. Ugarte" country="Chile" location="Piopio, Isla Chiloe" specimenCode="OSUC 146503" stateProvince="Chiloe Prov., Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<location id="1C60C74A460B36F56ABB54A5B0575B2C" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:1C60C74A460B36F56ABB54A5B0575B2C" name="Piopio" stateProvince="Isla Chiloe">Piopio</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="4E59BADF3079E39E5DD9748FCC737772">Isla Chiloe</collectingRegion>
, 3-
<date id="6AB995677B8CEEA9237548D33DC5DD69" day="15" month="02" value="1995-02-15" year="1995">
<collectingDate id="44AC1772955FC8B17099B8125D0C3138" day="15" month="02" value="1995-02-15" year="1995">15.II.1995</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="9C7463181158B780A390D96608533A51">A. Ugarte</collectorName>
, male, 
<specimenCode id="F8379237BEA6F7329AB3CD77558A6287">OSUC 146503</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="76FE9A999944A37609F13DED6C325DBC" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
; 
<materialsCitation id="B70AC0F63E7CB9F9881AE4484EFC6B42" ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923892479" collectingDate="1988-02-24" collectionCode="CNCI" collectorName="L. Masner" country="Chile" location="Rio Puntra and Rt. 5, 100 m, Isla Chiloe" specimenCode="OSUC 146502" stateProvince="Chiloe Prov., Los Lagos Reg." typeStatus="Paratype">
<location id="285F1BE3CDF0C6EDCCF6B9229E7DE1D9" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B573A0CF4D41D671CE814FEF61C3BB5F:285F1BE3CDF0C6EDCCF6B9229E7DE1D9" name="Rio Puntra &amp; Rt. 5, 100 m" stateProvince="Isla Chiloe">Rio Puntra &amp; Rt.5, 100m</location>
, 
<collectingRegion id="649BE7A2602C0CC0D91CACCB9DD7F74C">Isla Chiloe</collectingRegion>
, 
<date id="650DABCF7BB337EB00880A50026FF4B9" day="24" month="02" value="1988-02-24" year="1988">
<collectingDate id="B01373FF3196EFEA10FDE5E657A54881" day="24" month="02" value="1988-02-24" year="1988">24.II.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="D6BB9C35CA8FD65C0D2837B3FF9126CB">L. Masner</collectorName>
, male, 
<specimenCode id="DBA6F2432D9CC53E3584840319BCA9C1">OSUC 146502</specimenCode>
(
<collectionCode id="5C302D0E69245D55580731DBD8EDA25E" collectionName="Canada, Ontario, Ottawa, Canadian National Collection of Insects">CNCI</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSection id="43619DDAEC5EEE8A20C4F03CB3731415" type="multiple">
<caption id="3A037D1FAC5083C040636C296BADC5BE">
<subSubSection id="185BB33F2BF2CE387F8F1E88618A1FE0" type="description">
<paragraph id="FA3313DE17757DA0457B5537B45AE191" pageNumber="28">
<pageStartToken id="1C18B745A8EE72F58C3FA103A0FD596A" pageNumber="28">
<pageStartToken id="934ACC6522F1DA0547E35AD8EE3E1BA3" pageNumber="28">
<pageStartToken id="AADEF38B0088833AB1EAE6A183115F2B" pageNumber="28">FIGURES</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
36-41. 
<taxonomicName id="28E44ED0095F0F4070EB5A81C287A685" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:190981" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Archaeoteleia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Archaeoteleia dispar Masner" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="28" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dispar">Archaeoteleia dispar</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="16A52CE47B368D905977F809C1615E8F" rank="species">n.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
36, Lateral habitus, paratype female (OSUC 146494); 37, dorsal habitus, paratype female (OSUC 146494); 38, lateral habitus, paratype male (OSUC 146499); 39, dorsal habitus, paratype male (OSUC 146499); 40, head, frontal view, paratype female (OSUC 146494); head, frontal view, paratype male (OSUC 146499). Scale bars in millimeters.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</caption>
</subSection>
</treatment>
</document>