<document id="93238E8BBC922BE2D22FE2B342DDE1C9" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3848791" ID-GBIF-Dataset="1cd473d9-9d96-438f-bab4-29c5e56f82b8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="164160343" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3848791" _generate="added" approvalRequired="419" approvalRequired_for_bibRefs="3" approvalRequired_for_document="1" approvalRequired_for_illustrations="56" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="14" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="345" checkinTime="1589568044974" checkinUser="valdenar" docAuthor="Rio, Cédric Del, Stull, Gregory W. &amp; Franceschi, Dario De" docDate="2020" docId="B7038788FF86C3428097FCEAFC440145" docLanguage="en" docName="ejt-645_del-rio_stull_de-franceschi.pdf.imf" docOrigin="European Journal of Taxonomy 645" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@465f6cda" docStyleName="ejt.0000.journal_article" docTitle="Iodes Blume 1825" docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="31" masterDocId="4B3AFFF0FF98C35C8232FFABFF9D0760" masterDocTitle="Survey of the fruits and endocarps of Icacinaceae (Lamiids, Icacinales)" masterLastPageNumber="130" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" updateTime="1643448554399" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="0D7A5C1982659B620CE2BFD139F1D207" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="741C319DDF200DB5CDCE939492FB3E78">
<mods:title id="0609C4F173CD51992787D26DA16CD6CD">Survey of the fruits and endocarps of Icacinaceae (Lamiids, Icacinales)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="2DE8A7DD6FE989C5364BD5B730E57EE4" type="personal">
<mods:role id="23C286B91F27D4E4F0A75F770621EA15">
<mods:roleTerm id="B35F35E0E777FD7AE1F2EC07834FC813">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2115C62829EAA093BEBB1856576B94E9">Rio, Cédric Del</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="680789F56BB5EB8816ECBFAD6626B2C3" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D017430F72CD98CCE2BA7E3B0F41903F">
<mods:roleTerm id="5DDD4BF1E5E6CFDCB20A80904947C520">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="950C10D41D9094BB6C4378D2F0C536BE">Stull, Gregory W.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="8BBAC5BB46220DB168A083242540CF58" type="personal">
<mods:role id="21F9F2A9BD42C887AE21002F80EC0913">
<mods:roleTerm id="60B28AB9D4CBDD06E47DA9266E13A061">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7B4B93C08E75ECD611270CEEA16A4DB0">Franceschi, Dario De</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="6FB9416CC48F338C16B4A5EDE22A35AE">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="77606C1E70B7E5A1289F6A27FEF71E91" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="56400BFF2AEB2F740A9AB640FE09A6BE">
<mods:title id="0FBAB08D0775CDED0EFB9DFA1FA94FE0">European Journal of Taxonomy</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="1AEFC4990D21841529431B27704BB934">
<mods:date id="1C5FC23122C625E87D22B0041A8EDEA1">2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="B150462D2DDB3470CAAE4460F8AC949A" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="2734DE6F71920561290490E684C33883">2020-05-14</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="C5EFCECCC256FB434FE8ED3C64C92CD4" type="volume">
<mods:number id="11D3244411F58EC8486D4CDFE9F32D51">645</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="D2F4737C3AA2002D613F7FC9CB5E5370" unit="page">
<mods:start id="4AAEA72F72B606DA65FCA4DDDB005CA7">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="73818D8DD36E87B7EE9BD42A0A285EA8">130</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="7F3FE138BDEA5E63CE806AEDA51DE176">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="4B89D67B7F401E1BF3AD60E94BA33CF2" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.645</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E75820939B45F5C64B5EBBC72D15E73D" type="GBIF-Dataset">1cd473d9-9d96-438f-bab4-29c5e56f82b8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="A223614F7FF4051754AF86C6EBFDDC0F" type="Zenodo-Dep">3829651</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="B7038788FF86C3428097FCEAFC440145" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3848791" ID-GBIF-Taxon="164160343" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3848791" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B7038788FF86C3428097FCEAFC440145" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B7038788FF86C3428097FCEAFC440145" lastPageNumber="31" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<subSubSection id="77B06515FF86C3428097FCEAFC13043B" box="[677,910,832,859]" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="3F15369EFF86C3428097FCEAFC13043B" blockId="30.[655,933,832,896]" box="[677,910,832,859]" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<heading id="645D81F2FF86C3428097FCEAFC13043B" box="[677,910,832,859]" centered="true" fontSize="11" level="2" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" reason="2">
Genus 
<taxonomicName id="F8AA4D1DFF86C34280C5FCEBFC13043B" authority="Blume" authorityName="Blume" authorityYear="1825" box="[759,910,832,859]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Icacinaceae" genus="Iodes" kingdom="Plantae" order="Icacinales" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="0DDEEA8CFF86C34280C5FCEBFCA5043B" bold="true" box="[759,824,832,859]" italics="true" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Iodes</emphasis>
Blume
</taxonomicName>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="77B06515FF86C34280BDFCCEFC440145" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" type="description">
<paragraph id="3F15369EFF86C34280BDFCCEFC38041F" blockId="30.[655,933,832,896]" box="[655,933,869,896]" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<figureCitation id="A7912A1BFF86C34280BDFCCEFC8804E0" box="[655,789,869,896]" captionStart-0="Fig" captionStart-1="Fig" captionStart-2="Fig" captionStart-3="Fig" captionStartId-0="33.[189,232,1472,1498]" captionStartId-1="35.[189,232,1439,1465]" captionStartId-2="39.[189,232,1437,1463]" captionStartId-3="41.[189,232,1402,1428]" captionText-0="Fig. 12. Fruits of Icacinaceae Miers. 1–9. Iodes africana Welw. Ex Oliv. (R.P. Tisserant s.n.). 1. Dried fruit, lateral view. 2–6. Endocarp. 2. Lateral view of the endocarp showing a reticulate pattern of ridges. 3. Dorsal view of the endocarp. 4. Opposite lateral view. 5. Apical view. 6. Basal view. 7. SEM image of the pericarp in transverse section. 8. SEM image of the endocarp wall in transverse section and papillae on the inner surface. 9. SEM surface view of the papillae lining the locule. – 10–13. Iodes balansae Gagnep. (Liu 171). 10. Dried fruit, lateral view. 11. Lateral view of a part of the endocarp showing the double reticulation (arrow = horn-like protrusions). 12. SEM image of primary ridges in transverse section. 13. SEM image of secondary ridges in transverse section. – 14–23. Iodes cirrhosa Turcz (B. Hayata 672). 14. Dried fruit, lateral view. 15–19. Endocarp. 15. Lateral view showing the ridges and roughness. 16. Dorsal view showing a keel surrounding the endocarp. 17. Opposite lateral view. 18. Apical view. 19. Basal view. 20. SEM image of a vascular bundle embedded within endocarp wall in transverse section of the pericarp (arrow). 21. SEM image of an endocarp ridge in a transverse section of the pericarp. 22. SEM image of the lower part of the endocarp wall in transverse section and papillae on the inner surface. 23. SEM surface view of the papillae lining the locule. Images taken from Del Rio (2018). Scale bars: 1–6, 10–11, 14–19 = 10 mm; 12 = 1 mm; 13, 20–21 = 500 μm; 7, 9 = 300 μm; 8, 23 = 50 μm; 22 = 20 μm." captionText-1="Fig. 13. Fruits of Icacinaceae Miers. 1–9. Iodes kamerunensis Engl. (G.A. Zenker 2032). 1. Dried fruit, lateral view. 2–6. Broken endocarp. 2. Lateral view showing a reticulate pattern of ridges. 3. Dorsal view showing a keel surrounding the endocarp. 4. Opposite lateral view. 5. Apical view. 6. Basal view. 7. SEM image of a vascular bundle embedded within the endocarp wall (arrow) in a transverse section of the pericarp. 8. SEM image of a ridge in transverse section of the pericarp. 9. SEM image of the endocarp wall in transverse section. – 10–18. Iodes klaineana Pierre (R.P. Klaine 3064). 10. Dried fruit, lateral view. 11–15. Endocarp. 11. Lateral view showing a reticulate pattern of ridges. 12. Dorsal view showing the keel surrounding the endocarp. 13. Opposite lateral view. 14. Apical view. 15. Basal view. 16. SEM image of a vascular bundle embedded within the endocarp wall (arrow) in a transverse section of the pericarp. 17. SEM image of a ridge in transverse section of the pericarp. 18. SEM image of the cells of the endocarp. – 19–27. Iodes liberica Stapf (J.G. Adam 3833). 19. Broken dried fruit, lateral view. 20–24. Broken endocarp. 20. Lateral view showing a reticulate pattern of ridges. 21. Dorsal view showing a keel surrounding the endocarp. 22. Opposite lateral view. 23. Apical view. 24. Basal view. 25. SEM image of a vascular bundle embedded within the endocarp wall (arrow). 26. SEM image of a ridge and endocarp wall in transverse section. 27. Portion of the endocarp wall. Images taken from Del Rio (2018). Scale bars: 1–6, 10–15, 19–24 = 10 mm; 7, 16, 25 = 1 mm; 8, 17 = 500 μm; 26 = 300 μm; 9 = 200 μm; 27 = 100 μm; 18 = 50 μm." captionText-2="Fig. 14. Fruits of Icacinaceae Miers. 1–9. Iodes madagascariensis Baill. (Chapelier s.n.; MNHN- P-P04472113). 1. Dried fruit, lateral view. 2–6. Broken endocarp. 2. Lateral view showing a reticulate pattern of ridges. 3. Dorsal view showing a keel surrounding the endocarp. 4. Opposite lateral view. 5. Apical view. 6. Basal view. 7. SEM image of the pericarp in a transverse section showing the vascular bundle embedded within the endocarp wall (arrow). 8. Other view of the pericarp in a transverse section showing the endocarp wall. 9. Detail showing the papillae on the locule surface. – 10–18. Iodes ovalis Blume (Hiep HLF 203). 10. Broken dried fruit, lateral view. 11–15. Broken endocarp. 11. Lateral view showing the reticulation and roughness. 12. Dorsal view showing a keel surrounding the endocarp. 13. Opposite lateral view (arrow = horn-like protrusion). 14. Apical view. 15. Basal view. 16. SEM image of the vascular bundle embedded within the endocarp wall (arrow). 17. SEM image of a ridge in transverse section. 18. SEM image of the papillae on the locule surface. – 19–27. Iodes perrieri Sleumer (Perrier de la Bâthie 17843). 19. Dried fruit, lateral view. 20–24. Endocarp. 20. Lateral view showing a reticulate pattern of faintly marked ridges. 21. Dorsal view of endocarp. 22. Opposite lateral view. 23. Apical view. 24. Basal view. 25. SEM image of a ridge and endocarp wall in transverse section. 26. Detail showing the endocarp cells in the upper part. 27. SEM image of the papillae on the locule surface. Images taken from Del Rio (2018). Scale bars: 1–6, 10–15, 19–24 = 10 mm; 16 = 1 mm; 7–8, 17, 25 = 500 μm; 26 = 200 μm; 9, 18, 27 = 50 μm." captionText-3="Fig. 15. Fruits of Icacinaceae Miers. 1–9. Iodes philippinensis Merr. (A.D.E. Elmer 16418). 1. Dried fruit, lateral view. 2–6. Broken endocarp. 2. Lateral view showing the primary ridges and secondary reticulation. 3. Dorsal view showing a keel surrounding the endocarp. 4. Opposite lateral view. 5. Apical view. 6. Basal view. 7. SEM image of the uncinate hairs on the epicarp surface. 8. SEM image of the vascular bundle embedded within the endocarp wall (arrow) seen in a transverse section of the pericarp. 9. SEM image of the endocarp wall in transverse section. – 10–17. Iodes scandens (Becc.) Utteridge &amp; Byng (MO). 10. Lateral view of the endocarp showing a reticulate pattern of ridges. 11–14. Endocarp. 11. Dorsal view showing a keel surrounding the endocarp partially splitted in the same plane. 12. Opposite lateral view. 13. Apical view. 14. Basal view. 15. SEM image of a ridge in transverse section. 16. SEM image of the endocarp wall in transverse section. 17. SEM image of the endocarp cells and potential papillae on the locule surface (arrow). – 18–26. Iodes seguinii (H.Lév.) Rehder (Abbé Cavalerie 3932). 18. Dried fruit, lateral view. 19–23. Endocarp. 19. Lateral view showing the smooth surface with the vasculature on a faintly marked channel. 20. Dorsal view showing the channel. 21. Opposite lateral view. 22. Apical view with the channel seen on the left side. 23. Basal view. 24. SEM image of the channel containing the vascular bundle. 25. SEM image of endocarp wall in transverse section. 26. Detail showing the endocarp basal cells. Images taken from Del Rio (2018). Scale bars: 1–6, 10–14, 18–23 = 10 mm; 7, 15 = 1 mm; 8, 16, 24 = 500 μm; 9, 25 = 200 μm; 26 = 50 μm; 17 = 30 μm." pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Figs 12–15</figureCitation>
, 16.1–16.18
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3F15369EFF86C342828FFC0CFED304A1" blockId="30.[189,334,935,961]" box="[189,334,935,961]" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">
<heading id="645D81F2FF86C342828FFC0CFED304A1" bold="true" box="[189,334,935,961]" fontSize="11" level="3" pageId="30" pageNumber="31" reason="3">
<emphasis id="0DDEEA8CFF86C342828FFC0CFED304A1" bold="true" box="[189,334,935,961]" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">Description</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3F15369EFF86C342828FFC7DFC1D033B" blockId="30.[189,1399,982,1115]" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">FRUIT.Elliptical, occasionally globose, asymmetrical at the apex, laterally compressed, red to brown when mature. Epicarp strigose or puberulent, scarcely pilose, with simple hairs with granular ornamentation and / or uncinate hairs or long and thin hairs, ridged or rugged-rugose to smooth when dry, revealing the underlying endocarp ornamentation. Calyx persistent or not.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3F15369EFF86C342828FFB28FC440145" blockId="30.[189,1399,1155,1574]" pageId="30" pageNumber="31">ENDOCARP. Cream to brown, elliptical, occasionally globose in lateral view, lenticular, occasionally globose in transverse section. Keel often surrounding the endocarp in the plane of symmetry, with the thicker margin containing a vascular bundle embedded within the endocarp wall; occasionally replaced by channel containing the primary vascular bundle. Apex asymmetrical in lateral view; base symmetrical or cleft. Outer surface of the endocarp smooth, rugged -rugose, and /or ridged, with ridges rounded to sharp comprising a diffuse to reticulate pattern with or without freely ending ridgelets. Secondary ridges (i.e., small ridges delimiting a reticulum inside or between the primary reticulation/ ridges) occasionally present. Endocarp possessing a symmetrical pair of horn-like protrusions compressed on the keel, sometimes much reduced and forming pores, positioned eccentrically and subapically on the endocarp faces, absent in African species. Vasculature resting on ridges when present, occasionally between ridges or rugosities. Endocarp wall with two or three cell layers. Locule surface with regularly spaced and rounded papillae. Locule surfaces more or less lacunate.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>