<document id="934AD1F1801235256B796E8ED4072FEC" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.411.7346" ID-GBIF-Dataset="1a14389f-0fa3-4298-a954-34e40b95944d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152053131" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-411-105" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-411-105" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 411" ModsDocTitle="Morphological and molecular affinities of two East Asian species of Stenhelia (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)" checkinTime="1451245854623" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Karanovic, Tomislav, Kim, Kichoon &amp; Lee, Wonchoel" docDate="2014" docId="BB3153F919364DB170372CAF8550E40E" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 411: 105-143" docOrigin="ZooKeys 411" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.411.7346" docTitle="Stenhelia pubescens Chislenko 1978" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="120" masterDocId="F46ECF3CFFDAFFDFFFA49E09FFBB2A4D" masterDocTitle="Morphological and molecular affinities of two East Asian species of Stenhelia (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)" masterLastPageNumber="143" masterPageNumber="105" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" updateTime="1643519241544" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="29FF1977A78413530CA71D33FB0F3FBF" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="2B639CACA8ECDC143E773B085B903BD4">
<mods:title id="DB24E55D17FFBFF4B0DD091F68CCE9B8">Morphological and molecular affinities of two East Asian species of Stenhelia (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="5D15F664DBB81C0773663117A32FA03C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="6B25AECFF2D20E1FEE01FD9AA1CDBC7E">
<mods:roleTerm id="ECCDAE460B22D849B94F4CEC9229665F">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="286E5DFC37C6D72E28D5B1E215202621">Karanovic, Tomislav</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="87D6E7101E6140AD7304D39AB46AC3F6" type="personal">
<mods:role id="92314F8F89D53153AB3234BB7FF40E3A">
<mods:roleTerm id="0584562B97861C463E9377BA5F5D2DB0">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="6454BE6B3B55FFD298CB34B31E22B128">Kim, Kichoon</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="1A1D93BDD0E884042B15D4B21048D90C" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9A2BB4B53C78785D7B1ADDC5BC5EF4B6">
<mods:roleTerm id="C0BFF5A1F559EAD6F269B3F7BD7A8D76">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="1168E9FEB4705E7CE9F908588C625B62">Lee, Wonchoel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="1A45BB7550947848422D6A65F316076A">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="3F40EE9EB5113AD0E7FB1F19CC8EB977" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="8CCDAA71C181843A0342A53AD6835B7E">
<mods:title id="58CF0AA4564325C8398C52B0431CABD6">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="8F7F614FAD8DB49C6CFD958BDCDFB522">
<mods:date id="FDC74785CA89B418C5D17596385F6A78">2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="FB42516145894FB30B13FCF31E7B213D" type="volume">
<mods:number id="D4B8736E2BC6A5CF0A5FEE8059281E8B">411</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="784DCE18A0BF3975F070FD6063F123E7" unit="page">
<mods:start id="A3E72D6C4BA8BD26D65675CBCF4AD5F8">105</mods:start>
<mods:end id="31353FAD348EC31FB27B755C346D4DE3">143</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="394441638E751F29F30FA2A26FC2951A">
<mods:url id="7732F9912C6F9374A9F942CF1207572A">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.411.7346</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="94E3129A18461DA30ACC0FE0DB2FB749">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="37C3AB5240C0553E9B86FFA406987165" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.411.7346</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="C350BC0020C7D0F3F8F15B72ECF567FF" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-411-105</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="BB3153F919364DB170372CAF8550E40E" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152053131" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BB3153F919364DB170372CAF8550E40E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BB3153F919364DB170372CAF8550E40E" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="120" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
<subSubSection id="29433C7EC2721F10A5336812EB9D1C9F" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="890258F9C8E2C2879CF500949C995750" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
<taxonomicName id="C267193FA456AEB07DDA77C6D892EB40" LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Stenhelia_pubescens" authority="Chislenko, 1978" authorityName="Chislenko" authorityYear="1978" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens Chislenko, 1978</taxonomicName>
Figs 1-7
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3FC35C5EED5F61A2E223AAB22144AEB2" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" type="synonymy">
<paragraph id="6C24B44207EEC8063A53C5B17F4065AE" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">Synonymy.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FCAAE87BF846A478951964A79E8C7C23" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
<taxonomicName id="D4779385E998392E0C22EBEA6979CE43" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia (Stenhelia) pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens" subGenus="Stenhelia">Stenhelia (Stenhelia) pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, sp. n. - 
<bibRefCitation id="29E32182128F96807AD00A05E7F04F05" author="Chislenko, LL" journalOrPublisher="Trudy Zoologicheskogo Instituta, Akademii Nauk SSSR, Leningrad" pageId="26" pageNumber="131" pagination="161 - 192" title="New species of harpacticoid copepods (Copepoda, Harpacticoida) from Posyet Bay, Sea of Japan." volume="61" year="1978">Chislenko 1978</bibRefCitation>
: p. 173, Figs 9-11.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="414BBC75A721A397014B07BD030AA740" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" type="type locality">
<paragraph id="C59BEF460F43F732A7BF5561B833135F" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="938D5C9F87A2AD8496D7526F80AD4CA2" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
Russia, Primorsky Krai, Sea of Japan, Posyet Bay, Minonosok inlet, benthic sands at 3-4 m depth, 
<geoCoordinate id="9594E0D119F380B85A1E732E85EF430A" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="42.609257">42.609258°N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="5868FDB963AC57E81ADC24E2DE1569D0" direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="130.86166">130.861661°E</geoCoordinate>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4686E45AD51FE4EEE347F2EFE04CEC65" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" type="specimens examined">
<paragraph id="ACED423C60AFD9603D66BACA7B70CF0B" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">Specimens examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E91CAA2A6070FE7C2F14F2784027EAB8" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">Two females (one ovigerous) together on one SEM stub (collection number NIBRIV0000232715), one female dissected on one slide (collection number NIBRIV0000232716), one female in ethanol (collection number NIBRIV0000232717), and two ovigerous females destroyed for DNA sequences (GenBank accession nos. KF524870 &amp; KF524871); all from type locality, 6 May 2012, leg. Y. Trebukhova.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="25EB908ABD54FB2AB678FFB0ADF6370C" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="120" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" type="redescription of female">
<paragraph id="04274316422F197F9A4186251302EB3B" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">Redescription of female.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D4C556832E12F42B8287737BEECA2457" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
Total body length, measured from tip of rostrum to distal margin of caudal rami, from 558 to 583 
<normalizedToken id="D79DD48FCCF229BE6856EDF9CE60506E" originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
(n = 6). Colour of preserved specimens yellowish; live specimens not observed. Nauplius eye not visible. Several filamentous bacterial colonies in various places, some resembling sensilla (see Fig. 1C). Prosome comprising cephalothorax with completely fused first pedigerous somite, and three free pedigerous somites; urosome comprising first urosomite (= fifth pedigerous somite), genital double-somite (fused genital and third urosomites) and three free urosomites (last one being anal somite). Short sclerotized joint between prosome and urosome only discernible on ventral side. Habitus (Figs 1A, 2A) robust, spindle shaped in dorsal view, widest at posterior end of cephalothorax and tapering posteriorly, boundary between prosome and urosome conspicuous; prosome/urosome length ratio about 1.2, but prosome much wider and more voluminous. Body length/width ratio about 2.9; cephalothorax 1.65 times as wide as genital double-somite. Free pedigerous somites without lateral or dorsal expansions, pleurons only partly covering coxae of legs in lateral view (Fig. 1C). Integument of all somites relatively weakly sclerotized, generally very smooth, without cuticular windows or pits. Hyaline fringe of all somites broad and smooth, except for fourth pedigerous somite with narrow fringe dorsally, and for anal somite without hyaline fringe. Surface ornamentation of somites and caudal rami consisting of three unpaired dorsal pores, 61 paired pores and sensilla, and posterior row of spinules on last four urosomites only.
</paragraph>
<caption id="EDB21001589E88E94EE12D8EB14EFF37" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
<paragraph id="2E6E678B4D491D165EB2200BDBB132EE" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName id="094980080294A14BC0A32661C74E78D8" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, 1978, scanning electron micrographs, female 1: A habitus, lateral B cephalothorax, lateral C free thoracic somites, lateral D fifth pedigerous somite and genital double-somite, lateral, with one spermatophore attached on ventral side E fourth and fifth urosomites, lateral F anal somite and caudal rami, lateral G first legs and proximal part of second and third legs, lateral H distal part of right antennula, dorsal.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="A660B24A124081177E588F01983C4F36" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
<paragraph id="F54487D897650BCA7958B4FA204BE367" pageId="5" pageNumber="110">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName id="C260428B1791E34E8E226CDEB77230AB" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="5" pageNumber="110" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, 1978, scanning electron micrographs, ovigerous female 2: A habitus, ventral B rostrum and left antennula, ventral C mouth appendages, ventral D first leg, anterior E second, third, and fourth legs, anterior F exopod of fifth leg and sixth leg, ventral G anal somite and caudal rami, ventral H posterior part of left caudal ramus, ventral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="250CCE091BCC1E1EF283C2034EB3A084" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">
<pageBreakToken id="DB52380B5E960948040FC1184276B9A1" pageId="6" pageNumber="111" start="start">Rostrum</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 1B, 2B, 3C) large, trapezoidal, clearly demarcated at base, reaching midlength of second antennular segment, with bilobate tip, about as long as wide, with smooth dorsal surface and central keel on ventral surface, with two large lateral sensilla near tip inserted into deep recesses.
</paragraph>
<caption id="686D0C7AB3D8B789FBDF4D07B14CAA63" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">
<paragraph id="0AF932600FCBCA7B3C783B365C37BBF7" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName id="DFD826AA51D022D32EE934105558FAFF" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="6" pageNumber="111" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, 1978, line drawings, female 3: A urosome, dorsal B urosome, ventral (armature on left caudal ramus omitted) C rostrum, dissected and compressed, dorsal D sixth leg, dorso-lateral E sixth leg, ventro-lateral F fifth leg second endopodal seta from inner side, anterior.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="C6C8B1C7B83F64BEE42014EC0218A2D6" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">Cephalothorax (Figs 1B, 2A, B, D) tapering anteriorly in dorsal view, about as long as wide; comprising 35% of total body length. Surface of cephalothoracic shield with three pairs of small pores near antero-ventral corner between antennula and antenna (Fig. 2B), one dorsal unpaired pore in anterior half, and 25 pairs of long sensilla (Fig. 1B); of those only eight pairs of sensilla belonging to first pedigerous somite incorporated into cephalothorax (Figs 1B, 2D)</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DDB2751022247D42EF6DD04135C2185D" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">Pleuron of second pedigerous somite (first free) (Fig. 1C) with nearly rectangular lateral section, without pores but with seven pairs of large sensilla, two of them near lateral margin; serial homologies with sensilla on posterior part of cephalothorax (belonging to first pedigerous somite) difficult to define, except perhaps for anterior lateral sensilla and two other posterior pairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A7A8ED0883FB95C42F3E093169968169" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">Pleuron of third pedigerous somite (Fig. 1C) somewhat shorter than that of second pedigerous somite and with slightly more rounded lateral section, but also with no pores and with seven pairs of large sensilla; recognising sensilla serially homologous to those on pleuron of second pedigerous somite easy for all seven pairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="349CC57634532293790CE76C574745BD" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">Pleuron of fourth pedigerous somite (Fig. 1C) much shorter and with more rounded lateral section than those of previous two somites, especially narrow in dorsal view, with only five pairs of large sensilla; serial homology of sensilla to those on two previous somites relatively difficult to establish, but probably two dorsal pairs homologous to two dorsalmost pairs on pleuron of third pedigerous somite and two lateral pairs homologous to those near lateral margin on two previous somites.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DEC49C49F56FF9955D81E05D7AF80698" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">First urosomite (Figs 1D, 3A, B) about as long and as wide as fourth pedigerous somite but with wider hyaline fringe, with only three dorso-lateral pairs of long sensilla and no pores or spinules.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="72BD9057E0D59DFA79C972B341A1D9DC" pageId="6" pageNumber="111">Genital double-somite (Figs 1D, 3A, B) about 1.2 times as wide as long (ventral view); completely fused ventrally but with deep suture indicating original segmentation between genital and third urosomites dorso-laterally, thus dividing double-somite into equally long halves; anterior half of genital double-somite 1.2 times as wide as posterior, inflated laterally; anterior part with one unpaired dorsal pore and two pairs of long dorsal sensilla; serially homologous sensilla of anterior part of double-somite and those of first urosomite not easy to establish; posterior part with three pairs of posterior sensilla (one dorsal, one lateral, and one ventral) and long row of posterior dorso-lateral spinules of various length; establishing serially homologous sensilla of posterior and anterior part of double-somite not easy; hyaline fringe wider than in first urosomite. Female genital complex (Fig. 3B) weakly sclerotized and hardly distinguishable from internal sutures and soft tissue, copulatory pores not exposed on surface but their position could be deduced from attached spermatophores (Fig. 1D); paired genital apertures situated ventro-laterally, close to anterior margin and covered by reduced sixth legs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D75338EC99D72E0C0B21113FE8F4D5C1" pageId="7" pageNumber="112">
<pageBreakToken id="8A0EE3326C06A013B992BA1D55AE3A27" pageId="7" pageNumber="112" start="start">Third</pageBreakToken>
urosomite (Figs 1E, 3A, B) slightly narrower than posterior half of gential double-somite, but about as long and ornamented very similarly with three pairs of posterior sensilla and posterior row of spinules of various size, interrupted dorsally and ventrally; all sensilla with homologous pairs on posterior half of genital double-somite; hyaline fringe as wide as in genital double-somite.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="856132663AA83B49CEE5F73A655DC471" pageId="7" pageNumber="112">Fourth urosomite (preanal) (Figs 1E, 3A, B) without sensilla or pores, only ornamentation posterior row of spinules with wider dorsal and ventral interruption than in previous two somites; hyaline fringe slightly narrower than in third urosomite.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="65A07FE8661079E54EC9452E809EFAFB" pageId="7" pageNumber="112">Fifth urosomite (anal) (Figs 1F, 2G, 3A, B) clefted medially in posterior half, without anal operculum, with one pair of large dorsal sensilla, one pair of ventral pores, and posterior row of spinules at base of each caudal ramus; anal sinus with several diagonal rows of hair-like spinules on both sides of median cleft, widely open, with weakly sclerotised walls, and without chitinous projections.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E199981C0BFAC135A52D1D6072CB7D22" pageId="7" pageNumber="112">Caudal rami (Figs 1F, 2G, H, 3A, B) short and slender, cylindrical, about as long as anal somite, 1.5 times as long as wide (dorsal view), slightly divergent, with space between them about one ramus width; armature consisting of seven setae (three lateral, one dorsal and three apical), all in posterior sixth of ramus length; ornamentation consisting of one ventral pore at midlenght, one posterior ventral tubular pore, several spinules at base of each lateral seta and at base of dorsal seta, and two large posterior ventral spinules at base of innermost apical seta. Dorsal seta slender, plumose at distal tip, inserted close to inner margin, about 1.2 times as long as caudal ramus, triarticulate at base (i.e. inserted on two pseudojoints). Lateral setae all bipinnate and uniarticulate; ventralmost one longest and most slender, with distal tuft of longer pinnules, inserted very close to distal margin, about 1.3 times as long as caudal ramus; dorsalmost one strongest, without distal tuft of long pinnules, about 0.8 times as long as ventralmost one, inserted slightly more anteriorly than ventralmost one, at about same level as dorsal seta; central one half as long as dorsalmost one, also strong, inserted at about same level, also without distal tuft of long pinnules. Inner apical seta only slightly shorter than ventralmost lateral seta but very similar in thickness and ornamentation, i.e. also with distal tuft of long pinnules. Principal apical setae not fused basally, both with breaking planes; middle apical seta much stronger and longer, about 2.2 times as long as outer apical one, bipinnate; outer apical seta smooth, about 3.8 times as long as caudal ramus.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EBECB11947D39CD5DFCF2088CC1CA4DC" pageId="7" pageNumber="112">Antennula (Figs 1H, 2B, 5A) eight-segmented, joined to cephalotholax with small triangular cuticular plate, about half as long as cephalothorax, with single short anterior row of spinules on first segment. Fourth segment sometimes with suture along caudal margin. Distal caudal corner of first segment not produced. Long aesthetasc on fourth segment slender, fused basally with adjacent large seta, and reaching beyond tip of appendage; slender short apical aesthetasc on eighth segment fused basally with two apical setae, forming apical acrothek. Setal formula: 1.11.9.6+ae.3.4.4.6+ae. All setae smooth, dorsalmost setae on second segment with breaking plane, two caudal setae on seventh segment and four caudal setae on eight segment biarticulate. Length ratio of antennular segments, measured along caudal margin, 1: 0.4: 0.3: 0.4: 0.3: 0.4: 0.4: 0.5.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1210B83A57F469F2A7FE1E86534306EE" pageId="8" pageNumber="113">
<pageBreakToken id="EE155376CCD49FA47190F8804B759EAD" pageId="8" pageNumber="113" start="start">Antenna</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 2C, 5B, C) relatively short, composed of coxa, allobasis, one-segmented endopod and three-segmented exopod. Coxa short, with arched row of long posterior spinules. Allobasis with smaller or bigger suture marking ancestral division between basis and first endopodal segment, most robust segment of antenna, more than four times as long as coxa and about as long as endopod, widest at base and about 2.5 times as long as wide, with single unipinnate inner seta at about midlength and several longer and smaller spinules in proimal half. Endopod about as wide as distal part of allobasis, almost cylindrical, about 3.6 times as long as wide, with two surface frills subdistally, row of large spinules all along anterior margin, two lateral spines flanking two thin setae, apical armature consisting of seven pinnae setae (four strong, long, and geniculate, innermost one strong but short, and two short and slender); two caudalmost setae fused basally. Exopod long and slender, almost cylindrical, about as long as allobasis but only half as wide; armature formula 1.1.4 and length ratio of segments 1: 0.3: 1.1; proximal segment with transverse distal row of small anterior spinules, bearing a unipinnate seta close to distomedial corner; second segment unornamented, with a unipinnate setae at distomedial corner; distal segment with two parallel longitudinal anterior rows of small spinules joining at distal margin, with one bipinnae inner seta, at about first third of its length, and three apical slender (two smooth and one bipinnate).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C00E33922730215D940C9A6593E8B253" pageId="8" pageNumber="113">Labrum (Fig. 2C) large and complex tri-dimensional structure, trapezoidal in anterior view, rigidly sclerotized, with relatively wide convex cutting edge, subapically and apically with several rows of short slender spinules, with one additional transverse row of small anterior spinules and another patch of small posterior spinules.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="843A94238A204868430988B8E5C6BCEF" pageId="8" pageNumber="113">Paragnaths (Fig. 2C) also forming complex tri-dimensional structure, trilobate, with two ellipsoid anterior lobes and one central, much shorter posterior lobe, all lobes fused at base; anterior lobes with one long row of slender spines along inner margin and one additional and parallel row of stronger spinules on anterior surface; posterior (central) lobe similar in shape and ornamentation to distal part of labrum but much smaller.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1ADA066E662A91849AC0BFB1B59AEAE3" pageId="8" pageNumber="113">Mandibula (Figs 2C, 4A) with wide cutting edge on relatively short coxa, with three strong bicuspidate teeth ventrally, eight smaller unicuspidate teeth dorsally, and single unipinnate dorsalmost seta; seta fused basally to neighbouring tooth and twice as long as it; only ornamentation on coxa short row of six slender posterior spinules. Palp biramous, comprising basis, one-segmented exopod, and one-segmented endopod. Basis with somewhat inflated central part, about 2.5 times as long as wide, with three slender but pinnate distal outer setae, and with three transverse rows of strong spinules, distalmost one with strongest spinules. Exopod 0.6 times as long as basis and less than half as wide, narrowest medially, curved back towards coxa and almost parallel with basis, with three lateral and five apical setae; all lateral and three apical setae slender, two apical setae strong and geniculate, longer one of them almost four times as long as exopod; two apical setae unipinnate, all other exopodal setae smooth. Endopod 0.8 times as long as exopod, 3.8 times as long as wide, with one inner, three apical, and two outer slender setae; inner seta bipinnate, proximal outer and inner apical setae unipinnate, others smooth.</paragraph>
<caption id="56BCE40C423D1B8635D3E0BA7D23F5F8" pageId="8" pageNumber="113">
<paragraph id="077F067207AB64200147EB3372AB6E04" pageId="8" pageNumber="113">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="5486A040760FEFAB43B1FD94F2C4BB2B" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="8" pageNumber="113" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, 1978, line drawings, female 3: A mandibula, posterior B mandibular coxa, anterior C maxillula, praecoxa arthrite, posterior D maxilular palp, posterior E maxilla, anterior F maxilliped, anterior.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="FD9E5570A42DC9110C9ADBE1218266A8" pageId="9" pageNumber="114">
<pageBreakToken id="565DEF4EB2C306C78115386E88297736" pageId="9" pageNumber="114" start="start">Maxillula</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 2C, 4C, D) composed of praecoxa, coxa, basis, one-segmented endopod, and one-segmented exopod; endopod and exopod fused basally. Praecoxa large; arthrite rectangular, without spinules, with nine strong curved spines apically and subapically, all except ventralmost spine with dense tuft of distal spinules along convex margin; dorsalmost spine on praecoxal arthrite longest, ventralmost one shortest. Coxa with anterior arched row of short spinules, endite shorter than praecoxal arthrite, with three slender pinnate apical (on inner margin) setae. Basis wider and longer than coxa, with two endites, with dorsal row of strong spinules and three unipinnate setae on dorsal endite, and another three unipinnate setae on ventral endite. Endopod minute, rectangular, with four slender bipinnate apical setae. Exopod smaller than endopod, with two slender bipinnate apical setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="11304948164BC1D7BA88FBFDB448EE07" pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Maxilla (Figs 2C, 4E) composed of large syncoxa, small basis and even smaller one-segmented endopod. Syncoxa with four rows of outer long spinules and with three endites; dorsal endite smallest, with one subapical and two apical strong pinnate setae; central and ventral endites slender, with three apical pinnate setae each, setae on ventral endite longest; two distal rows of spinules parallel on anterior surface, two proximal rows of spinules near outer margin, one on anterior, one on posterior surface, posterior distal surface smooth. Basis slightly larger than ventral endite of syncoxa, with anterior row of minute spinules, apically with two strong and geniculate, unipinnate spines, and two slender setae on ventral and posterior surfaces. Endopod much smaller than basis, twice as long as wide, with basal tubular pore, no spinules, with three lateral and three apical slender setae of similar length; two lateral setae unipinnate, others smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2F2253991CBB2C062CAC0A281D4EB14C" pageId="9" pageNumber="114">Maxilliped (Figs 2C, 4F) prehensile, four-segmented, composed of coxa, basis, and two-segmented endopod. Coxa short, almost triangular, unarmed and unornamented. Basis largest and longest segment, about 1.8 times as long as wide and nearly five times as long as coxa, with one arched posterior row and two longitudinal anterior rows of slender spinules, with three strong unipinnate distomedial setae of about same length. First endopodal segment 0.8 times as long as basis but slightly wider, almost ovoid in shape, also with one posterior and two anterior rows of spinules but spinules much longer and stronger, with two smooth distomedial setae, one of them slightly longer and considerably stronger. Second endopodal segment minute, nearly rectangular, 1.6 times as long as wide, 0.4 times as long as first endopodal segment, unornamented, with apical strong prehensile smooth spine, and with subapical shorter and much more slender, unpinnate seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A95448BB9429B20AC7BF3F2AD591715A" pageId="9" pageNumber="114">All swimming legs (Figs 1A, 2A) of similar size and long in comparison to body length, composed of small triangular and unarmed praecoxa, large rectangular and unarmed coxa, shorter and nearly pentagonal basis, slender three-segmented exopod, and slender three-segmented endopod; pair of legs joined by simple intercoxal sclerite.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A92672B9B77656CE4BE9A3F0CBCB555A" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="116" pageId="9" pageNumber="114">
First leg (Figs 1G, 2D, 5D) with smooth and short intercoxal sclerite, its distal margin nearly straight. Praecoxa longer than wide, longer than intercoxal sclerite but shorter than coxa, unornamented. Coxa 1.8 times as wide as long, with longitudinal row of long and slender inner spinules, three transverse rows of shorter but stronger 
<pageBreakToken id="641A1D4BC5DDB4D782D71589A2077C94" pageId="10" pageNumber="115" start="start">anterior</pageBreakToken>
spinules, and two short rows of even smaller posterior spinules. Basis with one long strong and finely bipinnate outer spine, one shorter but stronger bipinnate inner spine, and four transverse rows of large anterior spinules (one at base of each spine, one at base of endopod, and one on proximal inner corner; latter with longest spinules). 
<pageBreakToken id="F06A91CFEA7C52B2548CDCE05F04A147" pageId="11" pageNumber="116" start="start">Exopod</pageBreakToken>
with all segments of similar length, each about twice as long as wide and with strong outer spinules and subdistally on anterior surface; first segment with anterior pore near distal outer corner; second segment with slender inner spinules; first two segments with single strong and finely bipinnate distolateral spine; third segment with two strong and finely bipinnate outer spines and two slender and finely bipinnate apical setae; apical setae not prehensile; length ratio of elements on third segment, starting from outer margin, 1: 1.4: 2: 2.4. Endopod three-segmented, prehensile, about 1.4 times as long as exopod; first endopodal segment about as long as entire exopod and 3.3 times as long as wide, with slender and long inner spinules, shorter and stronger outer and anterodistal spinules, with single bipinnate inner seta, the latter slender and about 0.4 times as long as segment; second segment small, rhomboidal, slightly longer than wide and only one sixth of first 
<normalizedToken id="E9B225A07CEA6D455B98C186C560039D" originalValue="segment’s">segment's</normalizedToken>
length, with several strong anterodistal spinules, and single slender and bipinnate inner seta; latter about 1.6 times as long as segment; third segment about 2.5 times as long as wide and 1.4 times as long as second segment, with several strong inner spinules and three smaller antero distal spinules, with one slender inner seta, one strong and long apical seta, and another shorter and stronger outer apical spine; apical spine 1.7 times as long as third segment, half as long as apical seta, and 1.5 times as long as inner seta on third segment; longest seta on exopod and endopod of about same length.
</paragraph>
<caption id="A74B3A1158D8377AEC5DF3D27F106A1D" pageId="11" pageNumber="116">
<paragraph id="E9EF46E4C345EC73632FF4942950372A" pageId="11" pageNumber="116">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName id="5E317799905458B5A3DBF06E8E807789" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="11" pageNumber="116" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, 1978, line drawings, female 3: A antennula, ventral B basis, endopod, and first exopodal segment of antenna, anterior C antennal exopod, anterior D first leg, anterior. Arrowhead indicates the presence of caudal suture on the fourth antennular segment.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="F7FEDF3F742623F47ED1AAC9B626D485" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="119" pageId="11" pageNumber="116">
Second leg (Figs 1G, 2E, 6A), intercoxal sclerite about as long as wide, unornamented, with two sharp and inwardly pointed distal processes. Praecoxa very short, unornamented. Coxa nearly 1.5 times as wide as long, with anterior pore near distomedial corner, three short rows of strong anterior spinules (one at distomedial corner, one near proximal outer corner, and one near distal outer corner), and two short rows of minute anterior spinules. Basis with nearly smooth (minute pinnules bearly visible), short and slender outer spine; inner distal corner produced into long and sharp process directed inwardly, another smaller distal process between exopod and endopod; with transverse row of long anterior spinules near inner margin, several smaller spinules ar base of outer spine, and discontinuous row of minute spinules at base of endopod. First exopodal segment widest, third segment slender and about 2.3 times as long as wide, 1.4 times as long as second segment, and about as long as first one; first and second segment with strong outer and anterodistal spinules and with distomedial frills, third segment with several outer strong spinules in proximal half and with anterior pore; first and second segments with single strong and finely bipinnate outer distal spine and slender bipinnate inner dista seta; third segment with three strong finely bipinnate outer spines, two apical strong bipinnate setae, and one slender bipinnate inner seta; inner apical seta on third segment longest, about 1.2 times as long as outer apical one, 2.4 times as long as third segment, and 2.7 times as long as outer distal spine; outer distal corner of first and second segment produced into small spiniform process. Endopod about as long as exopod; all segments of about same length, but progressively narrower from proximal to distal end, each with outer distal corner produced into strong spiniform process (first segment also with distomedial smaller process), and each with row of strong outer spinules, 
<pageBreakToken id="6467C4BD52BC8D4D21E4F5913F3ABF58" pageId="12" pageNumber="117" start="start">first</pageBreakToken>
two segments additionally with small distomedial frills, and first and third segments with anterior cuticular pore; armature consisting of single bipinnate inner seta on first segment, two pinnate slender inner setae on second segment, and one inner and three apical elements on third segment (probably outermost spine and two strong setae); seta on first segment about as long as segment, those on second seg 
<pageBreakToken id="AB74FAC19039E338695A2BF0D9432E81" pageId="13" pageNumber="118" start="start">ment</pageBreakToken>
about 1.4 times as long as segment, and those on third segment about twice as long as segment, except outer spine, which is about 1.4 times as long as segment. Two apical exopodal and endopodal setae each with shorter and stronger outer pinnules, 
<pageBreakToken id="1D9E4C7C34140981BF1C08547AE197AA" pageId="14" pageNumber="119" start="start">inner</pageBreakToken>
setae on third exopodal and endopodal segments and proximal inner seta on second endopodal segment with shorter inner pinnules, all other bipinnate setae and spines with symmetrical pinnules.
</paragraph>
<caption id="E208DC3D8447BA5C7D2C52D09AD77324" pageId="14" pageNumber="119">
<paragraph id="BA6790D6FD666F89084324D0F07ED5FA" pageId="14" pageNumber="119">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName id="D19AEED7CCB4208F17A8BF1B80B1EF90" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="14" pageNumber="119" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, 1978, line drawings, female 3: A second leg, anterior B third leg, anterior.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="AA00FAA531294309DF3E2F35FC2B77DD" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">
<pageBreakToken id="807900586868BA0B10BD4107B4615B37" pageId="15" pageNumber="120" start="start">Third</pageBreakToken>
leg (Figs 2E, 6B) similar to second leg, except for slightly less sharp processes on intercoxal sclerite, absence on distomedial row of strong spinules on coxa, smaller spiniform distomedial process on basis, two inner setae on third exopodal segment, one inner seta on second endopodal segment, and three inner seta on third endopodal segment; proximal inner seta on third endopodal and exopodal segment with long pinnules on both sides, distal inner seta on third exopodal segment with short pinnules on inner margin in addition to long ones, other setae and spines as in second leg.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B91E5E780CAFA193E92679E8ABBE30B5" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">Fourth leg (Figs 2E, 7A) relatively similar to third leg, but with endopod only about 0.6 times as long as exopod, with slightly shorter distomedial process on basis, much longer seta on first endopodal segment, only two inner setae on third endopodal segment, and three inner setae on third exopodal segment; central inner seta on third exopodal segment spiniform and characteristically curved inwards; all setae on third exopodal segment proportionately longer than in second or third leg.</paragraph>
<caption id="2AAEB08A08B72314BF6B19ED866B481C" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">
<paragraph id="5DB1F66E868AC018C948609A60725C70" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName id="144895957E4DBFED0B5391DECE6C3807" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia pubescens" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="15" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pubescens">Stenhelia pubescens</taxonomicName>
Chislenko, 1978, line drawings, female 3: A fourth leg, anterior B fifth leg, dissected and flattened, anterior.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="AFB7510CC9FCAD6CA93A78658D91D740" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">Fifth leg (Figs 1D, 2F, 3B, F, 7B) composed of wide baseoendopod (fused basis and endopod) and much smaller and almost ovoid exopod, pair of legs joined by minute trapezoidal sclerite. Baseoendopod about 1.8 times as wide as long, more or less pentagonal, unornamented, with short and blunt process at base of exopod; outer basal seta slender and smooth, arising from short setophore, about 1.6 times as long as segment; endopodal lobe relatively narrow and short, more or less trapezoidal, not extending beyond proximal fifth of exopod, with five stout, bipinnate setae, their length ratio, starting from inner side, 1: 0.8: 1.2: 1: 0.8. Second endopodal seta from inner side with stout and smooth proximal half, characteristic transverse serrate comb near mid-length, and distal slender finely bipinnate whip; whip about as long as proximal part of seta. Exopod about 2.1 times as long as its maximum width, more or less ovoid, with narrower base than rest of it, with strong outer and inner spinules and single anterior pore close to distal margin, with six setae; innermost and second inner seta slender, others shorter and spiniform, second seta from inner side smooth, other setae bipinnate; length ratio of exopodal setae, starting from inner side, 1: 1: 1.4: 1.4: 0.6: 0.6.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="48A39556E31B11D40B3F6240A846D6C2" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">Sixth leg (Figs 2F, 3B, D, E) minute flap covering ventro-lateral genital aperture, mostly fused to somite, unornamented, with single short bipinnate seta near outer margin and one minute inner spine. Sixth legs seemingly joined on ventral side by fold-like suture which hides copulatory pores.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8EFFB51CAF5BD9B78DDED4E1141D3A56" pageId="15" pageNumber="120" type="variability">
<paragraph id="C6B4F3B7013810FCB0AC75670E47D952" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">Variability.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="75F67A83B17FE2F4F96DE243BB7DFD9A" pageId="15" pageNumber="120">
Most morphological features in examined topotypes were conservative, including the sensilla and pores pattern on somites, and length ratio of different armature on appendages. The only significant form of morphological variability, except for the body length, was presence/absence of caudal suture on the fourth antennular segment (compare Figs 2B and 5A; arrowed in Fig. 5A) and the size of suture on the antennar allobasis indicating remnants of ancestral arthroidal membrane (Fig. 5B). We redescribe this species in order to show some previously unreported characters, so they can be compared with those of 
<taxonomicName id="9A53960F76D60B8600547B2FD0580232" class="Hexanauplia" family="Miraciidae" genus="Stenhelia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenhelia taiae" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="15" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="taiae">Stenhelia taiae</taxonomicName>
. Differences from the original description of 
<bibRefCitation id="7970D81DE02B266B5A8354754725FE67" author="Chislenko, LL" journalOrPublisher="Trudy Zoologicheskogo Instituta, Akademii Nauk SSSR, Leningrad" pageId="26" pageNumber="131" pagination="161 - 192" title="New species of harpacticoid copepods (Copepoda, Harpacticoida) from Posyet Bay, Sea of Japan." volume="61" year="1978">Chislenko (1978)</bibRefCitation>
are given in the Discussion section below.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>