<document id="64F63F5B26420D1E67A9350528E4C8C9" ID-ISSN="1175­5334" _generate="added" approvalRequired="44" approvalRequired_for_originalDoi="1" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="8" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="30" approvalRequired_for_treatments="5" checkinTime="1629706483752" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Martynov, Alexander" docDate="2010" docId="BC5D5914FF85527EFF48FBC9867FFF42" docLanguage="en" docName="zt02697p154.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 2697" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1.1:Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleId="D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Ophiocymbium Lyman 1880" docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageId="52" lastPageNumber="53" masterDocId="4064216CFFB6524AFFDFFFEC840FFFBE" masterDocTitle="Reassessment of the classification of the Ophiuroidea (Echinodermata), based on morphological characters. I. General character evaluation and delineation of the families Ophiomyxidae and Ophiacanthidae 2697" masterLastPageNumber="154" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" updateTime="1630054009333" updateUser="GgImagineBatch" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="B7AB6C4873BA070EAC9633DC48FA3D18" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="29A5E98D17002786FBFCDDB7AA9A0922">
<mods:title id="A29E28BC9E87B4E03CE2EB71C4427A0C">Reassessment of the classification of the Ophiuroidea (Echinodermata), based on morphological characters. I. General character evaluation and delineation of the families Ophiomyxidae and Ophiacanthidae 2697</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A9C4937D538DB35FF743667E9630673F" type="personal">
<mods:role id="50671D4C609B50E5BD450ABADC352B63">
<mods:roleTerm id="4C842189CCE77546EB237B9E03790EBF">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="9730D5F32EDFD7F1855826BB407E8003">Martynov, Alexander</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="ED0F32518973390D0983E8FEEA84CEAA">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="201FC166D12DFF4BEF101C2F7A495213" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="A876984E85417DD00C7E43CEF5C8E7B8">
<mods:title id="1902ECD6332DA6EEAA5039B12A6360C1">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="9343D27024CCE5A8A3A120CC5BBC3821">
<mods:date id="2CDB48C94EAE2E3069EE8243FF0766BF">2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="2001CC546A630EF340D4FEC5C1A947B8" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="7A1A7323743DC69E7AFDF09FDB702A5F">2010-12-03</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="F2063AE10A4D538AD5B8353048B38BA6" type="volume">
<mods:number id="167E3865DF9F6D37A37ACD1AC42563FD">2697</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="50DDCD8A31DC75C68FB54896DF284AEF" unit="page">
<mods:start id="4455DABE5574EBE74881E4B73DFEFD31">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="E5E6507293A91537964000587A02F199">154</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="78611E7E36BA3E58A642592062E938E3">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="F9AEC8881AFD27397811BECF35A7ABB3" type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="BC5D5914FF85527EFF48FBC9867FFF42" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BC5D5914FF85527EFF48FBC9867FFF42" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BC5D5914FF85527EFF48FBC9867FFF42" lastPageId="52" lastPageNumber="53" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<subSubSection id="7CEEBB89FF855279FF48FBC98640FB81" box="[151,591,1061,1087]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="344BE802FF855279FF48FBC98640FB81" blockId="51.[151,1311,1061,1122]" box="[151,591,1061,1087]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<heading id="6F035F6EFF855279FF48FBC98640FB81" bold="true" box="[151,591,1061,1087]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" reason="1">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FF48FBC98640FB81" bold="true" box="[151,591,1061,1087]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
Genus 
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF855279FF31FBC98640FB81" authority="Lyman, 1880" authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[238,591,1061,1087]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FF31FBC985A7FB81" bold="true" box="[238,424,1061,1087]" italics="true" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Ophiocymbium</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="506595F3FF855279FE70FBC98640FB81" author="Lyman, T." box="[431,591,1061,1087]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" pagination="3 - 12" refId="ref90203" refString="Lyman, T. (1880) A structural feature, hitherto unknown among Echinodermata, found in deep-sea ophiurans. Anniversary Memoirs of the Boston Society of Natural History, 3 - 12." type="book chapter" year="1880">Lyman, 1880</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7CEEBB89FF855279FF48FBA48110FBDC" box="[151,1311,1096,1122]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="description">
<paragraph id="344BE802FF855279FF48FBA48110FBDC" blockId="51.[151,1311,1061,1122]" box="[151,1311,1096,1122]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FF48FBA485ABFBDC" box="[151,420,1096,1122]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="13.[151,256,1339,1363]" captionTargetBox="[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetId="figure-434@13.[282,1312,194,1330]" captionTargetPageId="13" captionText="FIGURE 4. Genital plates and radial shields of various taxa of the families Asteronychidae, Gorgonocephalidae and Ophiomyxidae. A. Gorgonocephalus arcticus Leach, 1819, ZMMU D-613, 39 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, showing articulation surface, dorsal view; B. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; C. Asteronyx loveni Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-833, 17.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; D. same, articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view. E. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; F. same, radial shield showing articulation surface, ventral view; G. same, articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; H. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, dissected disk showing most proximal vertebrae and absence of the both genital plates and radial shield, dorsal view; I. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, adradial and abradial genital plates in situ, ventral view; J. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., paratype ca. 17 mm dd, ZMMU D-792, dissected disk showing articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield in situ, dorsal view; K. same, separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; L. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; M. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, 4 mm dd, ZMMU D-814, adradial genital plate, dorsal view; N. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate adradial genital plate, dorsal view; O. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, adradial and abradial genital plates, dorsal view; P. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., separate articulating adradial genital plate and radial shield, dorsal view; Q. articulation surface of the adradial genital plate, dorsal view; R. radial shield, ventral view, showing distally the distinctive excavated articulation surface; S. articulation surface of the radial shield, ventral view; T. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, radial shield, ventral view; U. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, same, articulation surface of the radial shield, proximal view; Scale bars: A– B,1 mm; C–D, 300 µ; E–F, 100 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 200 µ; J, 1000 µ; K, 300 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 300 µ; N, 300 µ; O, 200 µ; P, 100 µ; Q–T, 100 µ; U, 200 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Figures 4E–G, H, L, T</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FE6EFBA48657FBDC" box="[433,600,1096,1122]" captionStart="FIGURE 12" captionStartId="21.[151,255,1049,1073]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetId="figure-465@21.[158,1428,194,1027]" captionTargetPageId="21" captionText="FIGURE 12. Dental plates and jaws of the genera Ophioscolex, Ophiocymbium and Ophiologimus. A–B, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, dental plates; C–D, Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., paratype 11 mm dd, ZMMU D-801, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; E. same, dental plate; F. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-803, dental plate; G. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, dental plate; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, dental plate; I–J, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, dental plates; K–L, Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-805, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; M. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, jaw, adradial view; N–O, Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, abradial and adradial views of the jaws respectively; Scale bars: A, 200 µ; B, 200 µ; C–D, 300 µ; E, 100 µ; F, 300 µ; G, 100 µ; H, 300 µ; I–J, 100 µ; K–L, 300 µ; M, 100 µ; N–O, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">12C–G; H, M</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FD83FBA48680FBDC" box="[604,655,1096,1122]" captionStart="FIGURE 15" captionStartId="25.[151,255,1443,1467]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1422]" captionTargetId="figure-293@25.[158,1428,194,1422]" captionTargetPageId="25" captionText="FIGURE 15. Inside mouth views of the oral structures of various ophiuroid taxa. A. Gorgonocephalus arcticus Leach, 1819, ZMMU D-613, 39 mm dd; B. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd; C. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd; D. Asteronyx loveni Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-833, 17.5 mm dd; E. Ophiotoma assimilis Koehler, 1904, ZMMU D-807, 18.5 mm dd; F. Ophiacantha bidentata R/V “Sevastopol” sta. 1238, ZMMU D-750; G-H, Ophiocomina nigra (Abildgaard in O.F. Müller, 1789), ZMMU D-309, 18 mm dd; I. Ophiozonella alba Lütken, 1899, IORAS 15.109, 7.5 mm dd; J. Ophioconis vivipara Mortensen, 1925, ZMMU D –834, 6.5 mm dd; K. Dougaloplus derjugini (Djakonov, 1949), ZMMU D-838, 9.5 mm dd, inside mouth view; L. Amphioplus cernuus (Lyman, 1879), IORAS N. 1.89, 13 mm dd; M. Amphiura carchara H.L. Clark, 1911, ZMMU D- 835, 5.5 mm dd; N. Ophiactis abyssicola (M. Sars, 1861), ZMMU D-631, 6 mm dd; O. Ophiopholis aculeata (L., 1767), ZMMU D-559,15 mm dd; P. Ophiopenia tetracantha H.L. Clark, 1911, ZMMU D-580, 8.5 mm dd; Scale bars: A,1 mm; B, 300 µ; B, 300 µ; C–H, 300 µ; D, 1 mm; I, 300 µ; I, 300 µ; J, 300 µ; K, 300 µ; L, 300 µ; M, 300 µ; N, 300 µ; O, 300 µ; P, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">15B</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FD44FBA48782FBDC" box="[667,909,1096,1122]" captionStart="FIGURE 17" captionStartId="27.[151,255,1036,1060]" captionTargetBox="[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetId="figure-399@27.[161,1426,186,1015]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURE 17. Vertebrae of various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A. Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-843, 18 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal and ventral views; B. same, distal segments, dorsal and ventral views; C. same, proximal segments, proximal view; D. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm dd, proximal segments, dorsal view; E. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, proximal segments, dorsal view; F. Ophioscolex glacialis, proximal segments, distal view; G. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-795, proximal segments, proximal view; H. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-804, ventral view; I. same, proximal view; J. same, distal view; K. Ophiomyxa pentagona, ZMMU D-553, 21 mm dd, distal view; L. Ophioplexa condita gen. et sp. nov., holotype ca. 18 mm dd, ZMMU D-788, proximal segments, dorsal view; M. same, ventral view; N. same, proximal view; O. same, distal view; P. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype 9.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-799, proximal segments, dorsal view; Q. same, ventral view; R. same, distal view; S. same, proximal view. Scale bars: A, 1000 µ; B, C, 200 µ, D, 200 µ; E, 300 µ; F, 200 µ; G, 200 µ; H, 300 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 1000 µ; L–S, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">17D, E, G–H, J, P, S</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FC45FBA48029FBDC" box="[922,1062,1096,1122]" captionStart="FIGURE 27" captionStartId="38.[151,256,1544,1568]" captionTargetBox="[158,1428,194,1521]" captionTargetId="figure-295@38.[158,1428,194,1523]" captionTargetPageId="38" captionText="FIGURE 27. Arm spine articulations and spines of the various taxa of the family Ophiomyxidae. A–C, Ophioscolex glacialis Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842, ZMMU D-817, 27 mm dd; spine articulations of the proximal segments; D. spine, lateral view, E. spine, ventral view showing large nerve opening; F. Ophiomyxa brevirima H.L. Clark, 1915, ZMMU D- 725, 19 mm dd, distal segments; G. Ophiomyxa brevirima, proximal segments; H. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, ZMMU D-794, 9.5 mm dd, proximal segments; I. Ophiocymbium cavernosum, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm, proximal segment; J. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype, ZMMU D-799, 9.5 mm dd, proximal segments; K. same, middle segments; L. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-815, 4 mm dd, proximal segments; M. same a proximal segment with spines; N. same, details of the articulations of the proximal segments; O. Ophiobyrsa rudis Lyman, 1878, ZMMU D-868, 12.5 mm dd; P. Ophiologimus cf. secundus, most proximal segments; Q. Ophiolycus purpureus (Düben &amp; Koren, 1846), ZMMU D-845, 5.5 mm dd, most proximal segments; R. same, proximal segments; S. Ophiolycus nutrix Mortensen, 1936, ZMMU D-818, 8 mm dd, proximal segments with spines; T. same, other proximal segments; U. same, spine base, ventral view; Scale bars: A-B, 300 µ; C, 200 µ; D, 400 µ; E, 150 µ; F, 100 µ; G, 150 µ; H, 100 µ; I, 100 µ; J, 100 µ; K, 200 µ; L, 100 µ; M, 100 µ; N, 100 µ; O, 250 µ; P, 100 µ; Q, 100 µ; R, 100 µ; S–T, 120 µ; U, 150 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">27H–I; J, K</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FBECFBA4808FFBDC" box="[1075,1152,1096,1122]" captionStart-0="FIGURE 40" captionStart-1="FIGURE 41" captionStart-2="FIGURE 42" captionStart-3="FIGURE 43" captionStartId-0="52.[151,256,1746,1770]" captionStartId-1="53.[151,255,1505,1529]" captionStartId-2="60.[151,255,1706,1730]" captionStartId-3="62.[151,255,1255,1279]" captionTargetBox-0="[188,1398,309,1725]" captionTargetBox-1="[158,1428,194,1484]" captionTargetBox-2="[158,1428,296,1686]" captionTargetBox-3="[158,1428,343,1234]" captionTargetId-0="figure-160@52.[188,1398,309,1725]" captionTargetId-1="figure-189@53.[158,1428,194,1484]" captionTargetId-2="figure-218@60.[158,1428,296,1686]" captionTargetId-3="figure-425@62.[158,1428,343,1234]" captionTargetPageId-0="52" captionTargetPageId-1="53" captionTargetPageId-2="60" captionTargetPageId-3="62" captionText-0="FIGURE 40. External views of the genera Ophiocymbium and Ophiologimus. A. Ophiocymbium cavernosum Lyman, 1880, holotype, BMNH 82.12.23.391, 8.3 mm dd, dorsal view; B. same, ventral view; C. Ophiocymbium cavernosum, ZMMU D-795, 10.5 mm dd, dorsal view; D. Ophiocymbium cavernosum, ZMMU D-795, 8.5 mm dd, ventral view; E. Ophiocymbium tanyae sp. nov., holotype 9.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-799; F. same, ventral view; G. Ophiocymbium rarispinum sp. nov., holotype 9.2 mm dd, ZMMU D-798, dorsal view; H. same, ventral view; I. Ophiologimus cf. secundus Koehler, 1914, ZMMU D-814, 8 mm dd, dorsal view; J. same, ventral view. Photos: Tatiana Korshunova." captionText-1="FIGURE 41. External views and vertebrae of Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov. A. paratype, ZMMU D-804, 5.5 mm dd, dorsal view; B. holotype 6.8 mm dd, ZMMU D-802, 6.8 mm dd, ventral view; C. paratype 6.5 mm dd, ZMMU D-803, ventral view; D. paratype, ZMMU D-803, 6.1 mm dd, ventral view; E. holotype, dorsal view, ZMMU D-802, 6.8 mm dd, F. vertebra, ventral view; G. vertebra, dorsal view; Scale bars: F,G, 300 µ. Photos: A–F Tatiana Korshunova; F–G Alexander Martynov." captionText-2="FIGURE 42. Ophiocymbium antarcticus sp.nov., holotype USNM 1106263, 13 mm dd, external views and details. A. dorsal view; B. dorsal disk view, details showing small radial shields; C. ventral view, details; D. ventral view; E. arm spine articulations, proximal segments; F. slit-shaped ventralmost arm spine articulation, proximal segments; G. proximal vertebra, dorsal view; H. same, proximal view; I. same, ventral view; J. same, distal view; K. spine; L. tentacle scale; M. hollow spine, transversally sectioned; N. spine, ventral view. Scale bars: E–F; G–J, 300 µ; K-N, 100 µ; Photos: A–D Tatiana Korshunova; E–N Alexander Martynov." captionText-3="FIGURE 43. Ophiocymbium rarispinum sp. nov., holotype, ZMMU D-798, 9.2 mm dd, details. A. proximal lateral arm plate showing spine articulations; B–C, spine articulations, proximal segments; D. proximal spine; E. same, ventral view; F. hollow proximal spine, sectioned transversally; G. proximal vertebra, dorsal view; H. same, ventral view; I. same, distal view. Scale bars: A, D, G–I, 300; B–C, E–F, 100 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">40–43</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FB54FBA480EEFBDC" box="[1163,1249,1096,1122]" captionStart="FIGURE 55" captionStartId="80.[151,258,1764,1788]" captionTargetBox="[209,1364,194,1740]" captionTargetId="figure-174@80.[209,1364,194,1740]" captionTargetPageId="80" captionText="FIGURE 55. Ophioplexa condita gen. nov., sp. nov. and Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., details. A. Ophioplexa condita gen. nov., sp. nov., paratype 19 mm dd, ZMMU D-791, disk ventral view; B. same oral frame showing clusters of the ventral teeth (apical papillae); C. same, one interradius showing apical, oral and adoral shield papillae; D-F, same, most proximal arm segments showing tentacle scales and spines; G-H, arm spine articulations, distal segments; I. Ophiocymbium ninae sp. nov., paratype 5 mm dd, ZMMU D-803, details, part of the oral frame and ventral arm side; J. same, jaw and oral papillae, one interradius; K. ventral arm view showing spines and tentacle scales; L. most proximal segments showing details of tentacle scales and spines; M-N, arm spine articulations, proximal segments; Scale bars: A– B, 1 mm; C–D, 500 µ; E–F, 200 µ; G–H, 100 µ; I, 1 mm; J–N, 300 µ. Photos: Alexander Martynov." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">55 I–N</figureCitation>
; 
<figureCitation id="ACCFF487FF855279FB32FBA48110FBDC" box="[1261,1311,1096,1122]" captionStart="FIGURE 67" captionStartId="98.[151,255,1494,1518]" captionTargetBox="[188,1398,679,1473]" captionTargetId="figure-460@98.[188,1398,679,1473]" captionTargetPageId="98" captionText="FIGURE 67. External views of various taxa of the families Ophiacanthidae and Ophiomyxidae. A. Ophiotoma alberti (Koehler, 1896), ZMMU D-810, 12 mm dd, dorsal view showing ventral teeth, soft disk damaged in centre after fixation; B. same, ventral view; C. same, ventro-lateral view showing long genital slits bordered by well-defined genital plates; D. Ophiotoma assimilis Koehler, 1904, ZMMU D-807, 18.5 mm dd, dorsal view; E. same, ventral view; F. Ophioplexa condita gen. nov., sp. nov., paratype 19 mm dd, ZMMU D-790, ventro-lateral view, the grooves between arm bases are not the genital slits, genital plates are not evident; G. Ophiocymbium rarispinum sp. nov., holotype 9.2 mm dd, ZMMU D-798, 9.2 mm dd. Photos: Tatiana Korshunova." pageId="51" pageNumber="52">67G</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7CEEBB89FF855279FF48FB7985E7FB12" box="[151,488,1173,1196]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="344BE802FF855279FF48FB7985E7FB12" blockId="51.[151,902,1173,1228]" box="[151,488,1173,1196]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<treatmentCitationGroup id="14E4CF2CFF855279FF48FB7985E7FB12" box="[151,488,1173,1196]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<treatmentCitation id="B555CE13FF855279FF48FB7985E7FB12" author="Lyman, T." box="[151,488,1173,1196]" page="7" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" year="1880">
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF855279FF48FB7985E7FB12" authority="Lyman, 1880: 7" authorityName="Lyman" authorityPageNumber="7" authorityYear="1880" box="[151,488,1173,1196]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FF48FB798535FB12" box="[151,314,1173,1196]" italics="true" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Ophiocymbium</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="506595F3FF855279FE9FFB7985E7FB12" author="Lyman, T." box="[320,488,1173,1196]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" pagination="3 - 12" refId="ref90203" refString="Lyman, T. (1880) A structural feature, hitherto unknown among Echinodermata, found in deep-sea ophiurans. Anniversary Memoirs of the Boston Society of Natural History, 3 - 12." type="book chapter" year="1880">Lyman, 1880: 7</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
</treatmentCitation>
</treatmentCitationGroup>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7CEEBB89FF855279FF48FB598789FB72" box="[151,902,1205,1228]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="344BE802FF855279FF48FB598789FB72" blockId="51.[151,902,1173,1228]" box="[151,902,1205,1228]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<typeStatus id="EB4F56A0FF855279FF48FB5984C3FB72" box="[151,204,1205,1228]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Type</typeStatus>
species: 
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF855279FEF2FB5986E2FB72" authority="Lyman, 1880" authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[301,749,1205,1228]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="cavernosum">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FEF2FB598657FB72" box="[301,600,1205,1228]" italics="true" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Ophiocymbium cavernosum</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation id="506595F3FF855279FD81FB5986E2FB72" author="Lyman, T." box="[606,749,1205,1228]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" pagination="3 - 12" refId="ref90203" refString="Lyman, T. (1880) A structural feature, hitherto unknown among Echinodermata, found in deep-sea ophiurans. Anniversary Memoirs of the Boston Society of Natural History, 3 - 12." type="book chapter" year="1880">Lyman, 1880</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
, by monotypy
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7CEEBB89FF855279FF48FB1B87D8F96C" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="344BE802FF855279FF48FB1B87D8F96C" blockId="51.[151,1437,1271,2007]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FF48FB1B8518FAAF" bold="true" box="[151,279,1271,1297]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
The disk is covered with numerous small, uniform scales covered by a thin skin layer, not evident when dried. The dorsal disk surface can bear a few sparsely placed spinelets. The radial shield and adradial genital plate are small and externally inconspicuous or totally absent. The articulation surface of the radial shield is distinctly excavated ventrally, distally with a groove. The abradial genital plate is absent. The genital slits are small. The jaws bears a few block-shaped oral papillae. The adoral shield papillae, if any, differ considerably from the oral papillae and are placed around the second tentacle pore. The jaws are slightly elongated. The distal adradial sides of the jaws bear a few sharp straight folds. The dental plate is entire, small, with a few rounded sockets and devoid of folds. The teeth are spiniform and numerous, ventralmost teeth (apical papillae) of similar shape. The dorsal and ventral arm plates are well developed. The tentacles scales are placed on the lateral arm plate, and usually occur only on a few proximal segments. The arm spine articulations are compressed transversally. Some proximal articulations may have a distinct nerve opening. The sigmoidal fold is absent. The arm spines are relatively short and flattened, hollow. Distal hooks absent. The vertebrae with a blunt distal keel and zygospondylous articulation.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7CEEBB89FF85527EFF19F931867FFF42" lastPageId="52" lastPageNumber="53" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="344BE802FF855279FF19F9318193F869" blockId="51.[151,1437,1271,2007]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FF19F9318530F949" bold="true" box="[198,319,1757,1783]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Remarks.</emphasis>
Until recently, this genus was monotypic (
<bibRefCitation id="506595F3FF855279FC9CF93187D1F949" author="Lyman, T." box="[835,990,1757,1783]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" pagination="3 - 12" refId="ref90203" refString="Lyman, T. (1880) A structural feature, hitherto unknown among Echinodermata, found in deep-sea ophiurans. Anniversary Memoirs of the Boston Society of Natural History, 3 - 12." type="book chapter" year="1880">Lyman 1880</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation id="506595F3FF855279FC33F9318096F949" author="Paterson, G. L. J." box="[1004,1177,1757,1783]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" pagination="1 - 162" refId="ref91221" refString="Paterson, G. L. J. (1985) The deep-sea Ophiuroidea of the North Atlantic Ocean. Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History), Zoology Series 49, 1 - 162." type="book chapter" year="1985">Paterson 1985</bibRefCitation>
). In the present study four other abyssal and ultra-abyssal new species have been discovered. This facilitates an appropriate discussion on the variability of different features within the genus. The taxonomic placement of 
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF855279FF48F8A18545F8D8" authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[151,330,1869,1894]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FF48F8A18545F8D8" box="[151,330,1869,1894]" italics="true" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Ophiocymbium</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
will be evaluated after a general discussion on the taxonomic value of ophiuroid characters. R/ V “Akademik Kurchatov” ultra-abyssal sampling in the Sandwich trench discovered another unknown ophiuroid, seemingly belonging to the family 
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF855279FD6EF8748763F80C" authorityName="Ljungman" authorityYear="1867" box="[689,876,1944,1970]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophiacanthidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophiacanthida" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="family">Ophiacanthidae</taxonomicName>
, and similar to the genus 
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF855279FB48F8748145F80F" authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[1175,1354,1944,1969]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FB48F8748145F80F" box="[1175,1354,1944,1969]" italics="true" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Ophiocymbium</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. Close examination suggests that it is an undescribed genus and species, named here 
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FBF4F8518193F869" bold="true" box="[1067,1436,1981,2007]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF855279FBF4F8518118F869" authority="Martynov, 2010" authorityName="Martynov" authorityYear="2010" box="[1067,1303,1981,2007]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophioplexa" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="51" pageNumber="52" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="species" species="condita" status="gen. et sp.">
<emphasis id="06803410FF855279FBF4F8518118F869" bold="true" box="[1067,1303,1981,2007]" italics="true" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">Ophioplexa condita</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="1DB3896BFF855279FAC0F8518193F869" box="[1311,1436,1981,2007]" pageId="51" pageNumber="52">gen. et sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="344BE802FF82527EFF48FF7B8158FF69" blockId="52.[151,1436,151,252]" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">
<emphasis id="06803410FF82527EFF48FF7B84C0FF0F" bold="true" box="[151,207,151,177]" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">nov.</emphasis>
It is of importance for the present study since, like 
<emphasis id="06803410FF82527EFC55FF748059FF0F" box="[906,1110,152,177]" italics="true" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF82527EFC55FF74805DFF0F" authorityName="Lyman" authorityYear="1880" box="[906,1106,152,177]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophioscolecidae" genus="Ophiocymbium" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophioscolecida" pageId="52" pageNumber="53" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="genus">Ophiocymbium</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
it apparently belongs in 
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF82527EFF48FF518530FF69" box="[151,319,189,215]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophiurinidae" genus="Ophiurina" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophiurida" pageId="52" pageNumber="53" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Ophiotominae">Ophiotominae</taxonomicName>
and simultaneously has affinities to 
<taxonomicName id="F3F49381FF82527EFD34FF518792FF69" authorityName="Ljungman" authorityYear="1867" box="[747,925,189,215]" class="Ophiuroidea" family="Ophiomyxidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Ophiacanthida" pageId="52" pageNumber="53" phylum="Echinodermata" rank="family">Ophiomyxidae</taxonomicName>
. It will be listed and described below.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="344BE802FF82527EFF19FF0E867FFF42" blockId="52.[151,1436,151,252]" box="[198,624,226,252]" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">
<emphasis id="06803410FF82527EFF19FF0E865DFF42" bold="true" box="[198,594,226,252]" pageId="52" pageNumber="53">Number of species in the genus:</emphasis>
5.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>