<document id="08A12ADBD66D8FE78A0A5CB29ABC6E47" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.261.4371" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3e25fb03-d83a-4fe0-a5ad-eb9370132780" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152039775" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-261-41" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-261-41" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 261" ModsDocTitle="The first euthemistid damsel-dragonfly from the Middle Jurassic of China (Odonata, Epiproctophora, Isophlebioptera)" checkinTime="1451247745303" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Li, Yongjun, Nel, Andre, Shih, Chungkun, Ren, Dong &amp; Pang, Hong" docDate="2013" docId="BD144760F158305D7A83E03B48327193" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 261: 41-50" docOrigin="ZooKeys 261" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.261.4371" docTitle="Sinoeuthemis daohugouensis Li, Nel, Shih, Ren &amp; Pang, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="46" masterDocId="FF9B4C4EFFABFF847A2D81722071FFA2" masterDocTitle="The first euthemistid damsel-dragonfly from the Middle Jurassic of China (Odonata, Epiproctophora, Isophlebioptera)" masterLastPageNumber="50" masterPageNumber="41" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" updateTime="1643537330809" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="624B61D9BEDE5060BD078B648B82CC47" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="3E4B63AE0CB469AAA68543329A2B920C">
<mods:title id="1B3E7F98A9CB9DC3429DD5E325BB0D5A">The first euthemistid damsel-dragonfly from the Middle Jurassic of China (Odonata, Epiproctophora, Isophlebioptera)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="4D73F0772051C33A25CB9B06A854BC7D" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A6612AFF97B58660A0950033D5C2810F">
<mods:roleTerm id="6304AD09849CB44EA442EE7AB9E8E2C4">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="6036245ACDA66FE27164817E46C83395">Li, Yongjun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="28F3BD405C9EF79D588F6D7791508FCA" type="personal">
<mods:role id="42A302B9E4C2FFD3BF6FB5FC0F6FEC4A">
<mods:roleTerm id="E81AB99B9E952B08A0588A621418E82D">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="B1A335F67200D8178B15E673C646CB23">Nel, Andre</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="3035A40584F39DBCE7DE5A90ABEA209B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="3044158CD7307EFA44BA3F8961C809DD">
<mods:roleTerm id="DAFA03658A7771DA8E3365ED35324B66">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="6376AFA04C86A6F47AE983FFF2433804">Shih, Chungkun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="561192F3A25E0D10BAEFCA75DEF82EA5" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F7DB8320A83C4A1D927B3BFE83782BAA">
<mods:roleTerm id="E5076F93C7CE209332C2A04C70FEF9AC">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="143E1B17412C0A08DAEEB602A382D178">Ren, Dong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="1A0AA1EC04E51A88C82B4507EC2B03D1" type="personal">
<mods:role id="44A344D012ABBB70EEB358A8AD2B3ECA">
<mods:roleTerm id="8A939E901AC3338FB128751DDCB199DA">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7CAFB7F5DE159D64F8AD0DCCAC4F2124">Pang, Hong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="A9F821D92C6FCD623238E0C5DF22D1E6">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="9C315279BCA6A31AEAA59BCDE37AB67F" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="D1C378D8D67526838C2764D2629599F5">
<mods:title id="6290FB416BCC074981F9E66954CCCFFF">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="AF553E3D2E1D8ABE04054B2FD7DE032C">
<mods:date id="504B6191DD464D14D41E6AFFF6A60522">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="96F9170B3FA611A3D47782E3A561A745" type="volume">
<mods:number id="ABDAE402864079853396BDF6B44E74C8">261</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="D7817A899D4820100C953552A455E213" unit="page">
<mods:start id="596394B5C79B95EA1D88D1BB04513A7C">41</mods:start>
<mods:end id="DEFE763EC2BEDC77836DE132FD71D795">50</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="5AC3669152AD27524FF44F6C379831AE">
<mods:url id="527C4D2AFE595FB901202385457077D3">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.261.4371</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="52CBD27ECF07BCE6E5548E3093B846FC">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="1F14EE8B500F47038868DEBC55D2E943" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.261.4371</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="5FF8C2AA5C674E60DE07AC4A83C1CA22" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-261-41</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="BD144760F158305D7A83E03B48327193" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152039775" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:BD144760F158305D7A83E03B48327193" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BD144760F158305D7A83E03B48327193" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<subSubSection id="F081725499E8927174263D18295A4584" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="BF3F558A53D526A61048C83CE363ABDB" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
<taxonomicName id="D202D43162AF19C84154DB784BCDCC58" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6783C7B8-8791-48B0-9722-010427CECC6E" authority="Li, Nel, Shih, Ren &amp; Pang, 2013" authorityName="Li, Nel, Shih, Ren &amp; Pang" authorityYear="2013" class="Insecta" family="Euthemistidae" genus="Sinoeuthemis" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinoeuthemis daohugouensis" order="Odonata" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="daohugouensis">Sinoeuthemis daohugouensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="6B3932D3C76170BB4E6CAC11E4E50017" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figure 1
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C3CCFF55C36E6890D4CE1BB240B940E1" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="material">
<paragraph id="7452BDE7762F83A98C54D8264E06C687" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F31E1F6D8160950DC5CE3A574FD00F10" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Holotype specimen No. CNU-ODO-NN2012004.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D530EE7523FF9F05A93D7296644BBA74" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="1EC6BD88E18F23A6CA1A4239B181111A" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="18A30B4EC54FF474A2D99185386057DF" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">As for the genus.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3F03F986266A6E1B2C989EF3D3437EB9" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="1" pageNumber="42" type="description">
<paragraph id="1F49F3D512174D340803C4C624F0F6E8" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3962E365C0B18924EC7611F97D02BDC1" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="1" pageNumber="42">
A body with a thorax, abdomen, head, two legs and forewings and hindwing articulated. Body (Fig. 1; Fig. 2D, F) 53.0 mm long (from head to anal appendages); head 5.1 mm long, 5.2 mm wide, with broad eyes, 1.7 mm long, well separated, 1.0 mm apart in the mid level; thorax about 8 mm long, max width 6.5 mm; 
<pageBreakToken id="39D4CC5ABABBE21152423378F6D2E906" pageId="2" pageNumber="43" start="start">abdomen</pageBreakToken>
about 3.8 mm wide in the mid part, slightly narrowed at the end; cercus and epiproct very short; there is no secondary genital structure on segment 2 and anal area rounded (female). Forewing (based on negitive imprint, two forewing fragments combined; Fig. 2A, B), preserved with basal half, 22.4 mm long; no petiole (AA and AP separate at wing base); one row of cells between posterior wing margin and AA; AA parallel to MP + Cu; median and submedian areas free; a curved strong vein CuP between submedian and subdiscoidal areas, in a distal position just basal of arculus; subdiscoidal space free of cross-veins, transverse; discoidal space basally opened; RP+MA nearly straight, separated at nearly a right angle from RA in arculus; distance between base of RP and point of separation between MAa and MAb 0.4 mm, RP and MA well parallel; MAb 0.9 mm long, well aligned with distal free part of CuA; CuA separates from MP 4.3 mm from wing base and directed towards posterior wing margin for 0.6 mm; distal free part of CuA strong, CuA distally fused with AA; CuA divided into a very short CuAb directed towards posterior wing margin and CuAa basally more or less parallel to posterior wing margin and distally delimitating a short and narrow cubito-anal area, with 1-2 posterior branches and 1-2 rows of cells at its broadest part; apex of CuA slightly distal level of base of RP3/4; area between CuA and MP with one row of cells; distal of apex of CuA, area between MP and posterior wing margin very long and broad; MP nearly straight, certainly reaching posterior wing margin well distal of nodus level; MAa more or less parallel with MP, nearly straight in its preserved part; postdiscoidal area with one row of cells, 1.0 mm wide near discoidal cell and narrowing distally; Ax0 not preserved; Ax1 0.6 mm basal of arculus, disposed obliquely to ScP and R + MA, Ax2 2.4 mm distal of arculus, with inverted obliquity; eight preserved secondary antenodal cross-veins between C and ScP distal of Ax2; 13 visible secondary antenodal cross-veins between ScP and RA distal of Ax2; 15 preserved cross-veins in area between RA and RP between arculus and subnodus; base of RP3/4 5.0 mm distal of arculus, closer to arculus than to nodus; base of IR2 close to that of RP3/4, 3.8 mm distally; no visible antefurcal cross-vein in space between RP and MA basal of midfork (base of RP3/4); nodal structures not preserved; area between MA and RP3/4 narrow basally but distally widening. Hindwing (mainly based on right hindwing of positive imprint, combined with anal area of left hindwing on negitive imprint; Fig. 2C, E) hyaline, more complete than forewing, 39.7 mm long, estimate 8 mm wide at the level of nodus; primary antenodal crossveins Ax0, Ax1 and Ax2 are well preserved; Ax1 nearly perpendicular to ScP; Ax2 slightly oblique; distance form base to Ax1 3.6 mm, to arculus 4.2 mm, to nodus 18.7 mm; distance from arculus to the first fork of RP 2.8 mm; Ax1 0.4 mm basal of arculus and Ax2 1.9 mm distal of arculus; nine secondary antenodal cross-veins between C and ScP, but 11 secondary antenodal cross-veins between ScP and RA, distal of Ax2; no petiole; anal area about 6 mm long, 1.7 mm wide, rather rounded elongate in shape, with two rows of irregular cells between AA and AP; no anal angle; no membranule; AA distally strongly bent towards posterior wing margin and nearly parallel with MP + CuA, distally fused with CuAb; median and submedian areas free; curved vein CuP slightly basal of arculus; subdiscoidal area transverse, posteriorly closed, short and broad, with one cross-vein, 1.3 mm long, 0.8 
<pageBreakToken id="218AF21B92E20EE38D386AB857C941DA" pageId="3" pageNumber="44" start="start">mm</pageBreakToken>
wide; discoidal cell basally closed, 1.6 mm long, 0.5 mm wide, free of cross-veins, length of proximal side, 0.8 mm; RP + MA separates at approximately a right angle from RA and strongly curved in arculus; RP separated from MA 0.3 mm distally; just distal of arculus base, MA basally strong and divided into MAa and MAb distally; MAb short, 0.8 mm long, aligned with distal free part of CuA; MP + CuA separated into MP and CuA at distal end of MAb; distal free part of CuA strong, separates from 
<pageBreakToken id="3052DF7059EDB863CC578E9B7230BB40" pageId="4" pageNumber="45" start="start">MP</pageBreakToken>
6.1 mm from wing base and extends towards posterior wing margin for 0.7 mm; CuA distally divided into CuAa and CuAb, CuAb short, 0.5 mm long, extending towards basal wing margin and meets main branch of AA; CuAa basally more or less parallel to posterior wing margin with two rows of cells between them; CuAa short, as long as in forewings, ending on posterior wing margin 5.8 mm from its base; area between CuAa and MP with one-two rows of cells, 0.9 mm wide; distal of end of CuAa, area between MP and posterior wing margin very long and broad; MP nearly straight, reaching posterior margin well distal of nodus level; MAa parallel with MP, nearly straight in its basal part, postdiscoidal area mm wide, narrower distally; 14 cross-veins in area between RA and RP, between arculus and nodus; base of RP3/4 2.7 mm distal of arculus, closer to arculus than to nodus; base of IR2 close to that of RP3/4, 4.9 mm distally; no antefurcal cross-vein in space between RP and MA basal of midfork 
<pageBreakToken id="A707EF7131A2AE64B3BE53AD116CD13A" pageId="5" pageNumber="46" start="start">(</pageBreakToken>
base of RP3/4); nodus oblique with subnodus aligned; more than seven postnodal cross-veins between C and RA and postsubnodal cross-veins between RA and RP1 not aligned with postnodals; pterostigmal brace probably not preserved; at least three cells below pterostigma; pterostigma sclerotized, long, 3.9 mm long, 0.8 mm wide; RP2 aligned with subnodus; oblique vein 
<normalizedToken id="DAD97056ED35EC10720C23684020A51C" originalValue="‘O’">'O'</normalizedToken>
4.3 mm and five cells distal of base of RP2; IR2 and RP2 nearly straight; area between MA and RP3/4 wider distally; area between RP3/4 and IR2 broadening distally; area between IR2 and RP2 with one row of cells and wider distally; several long intercalary veins between IR1 and RP1, and between IR1 and RP2 (but IR1 not clearly discernible), as well as between RP3/4 and IR2, and between IR2 and RP2 (these intercalaries are visible along posterior wing margin and parallel to the main longitudinal veins and have no apparent origin on them, but originate in the cross-venation).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B67C344CA39D040885C658B1B4B31D6B" pageId="5" pageNumber="46" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="3010D8DDA12300151053B4829D33AE60" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CCFC5A1B50DF0E5CD35F0251F4ADEE5E" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">Named after Daohugou Village, from where the specimen was collected.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2154355A0F971F3D15B12925118326CD" pageId="5" pageNumber="46" type="type locality and horizon">
<paragraph id="8FBAE85F48D82234DCCB5BC51D3FED31" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">Type locality and horizon.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D2C660470C92887DFD0F0DE2A28706BE" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">Jiulongshan Formation, Middle Jurassic (Bathonian-Callovian boundary interval, ca 164-165 Ma); near Daohugou Village, Wuhua Township, Ningcheng County, Inner Mongolia, China.</paragraph>
<caption id="F123344686A7FCD6B712DBA4C7898F77" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">
<paragraph id="B1614939BD75BD43972AA07F39DC71E8" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">Figure 1. Photo of positive imprint of CNU-ODO-NN2012004. Scale bar represents 10 mm.</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="E276BB073C4D43F88C283A6910D17C73" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">
<paragraph id="0DF828DE8EDE2C486A4EB6562B3CA12F" pageId="5" pageNumber="46">
Figure 2. A, B Drawing of forewings, from negative imprint C Drawing of hindwing, from positive imprint, combined with anal area of the negative imprint (dotted line) D Detail photo and drawing of head and thorax, from negative imprint E Detail photo and drawing of hindwing anal area, from negative imprint F Detail photo and drawing of the lower part of abdomen, from positive imprint. Scale bars represent 5 mm in 
<normalizedToken id="9A308EBFFB7230B4E99CBD4971973CFB" originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
and 1 mm in 
<normalizedToken id="3E48BE94774CA5A2F9AFA1B347C50E90" originalValue="D–F">D-F</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>