<document id="E31E55B5FE6A1A4A215D149C11DEE19B" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.46.5733" ID-GBIF-Dataset="7bb10d36-390a-4cc9-95f5-854e2f09ac22" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127877277" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1314-2607-46-1" ID-ZBK="4F1FCDE2FA504353BE950DC837444A88" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D5DD3CA8-F38B-4DB1-BC89-6E7E612E3952" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1314-2607-46-1" ModsDocOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 46" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the Rhopalomutillinae (Hymenoptera, Mutillidae): 1, generic review with descriptions of three new genera" checkinTime="1451252163854" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Brothers, Denis J." docDate="2015" docId="CAFB7AE793855B64A0E6A88DC4EF14A6" docLanguage="en" docName="JourHymenoptRes 46: 1-24" docOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 46" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.46.5733" docTitle="Rimulotilla Brothers, gen. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="D5DD3CA8-F38B-4DB1-BC89-6E7E612E3952" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" masterDocId="E03BFFABFF9EFF8AFFFDFF968E107450" masterDocTitle="Revision of the Rhopalomutillinae (Hymenoptera, Mutillidae): 1, generic review with descriptions of three new genera" masterLastPageNumber="24" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" updateTime="1643511481986" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="FF1D0446D8FF3FCF2F84446C2A721F5B" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="6B46B146736D39209BAE7C3B3BB1F3EB">
<mods:title id="373CD33C409AE3B5E502F9AD67BD73ED">Revision of the Rhopalomutillinae (Hymenoptera, Mutillidae): 1, generic review with descriptions of three new genera</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="423C77E31DF243A07A9FA504976C22B9" type="personal">
<mods:role id="E09FDBD62C92D55BB7B87F99CC6DB5F7">
<mods:roleTerm id="01F3CC4B03D013380A01F2FADAA3BB38">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="4E0A92284A18134F8BC64696E0B4E895">Brothers, Denis J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="0DF22F9DC7821F25507E6DB8395044E6">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="F19EE001FC8E5367E95EA44A60D7468D" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="2E8080E26E7EC363F1B1774EBC47934A">
<mods:title id="A78E917850AB344B306B1B3D8EB04CE0">Journal of Hymenoptera Research</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D1CF5432437A6108781F7312E2FDB848">
<mods:date id="EE27AD3F479CC856D118ABC948954177">2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="B6F3573D0E2D007C6840B8F6231740A9" type="volume">
<mods:number id="FF074D463CECDE52EFC1052D3355D5FB">46</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="1294D4D68D311754BEAF73FFAAC70A75" unit="page">
<mods:start id="0F36D7674D7F569F98CFE5E1EB5760D6">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="2CF999C1F4D113BFA1E55741B2B9C474">24</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="B8D151902191244700F2C23659EC727F">
<mods:url id="B037FF985BFF42C7DF5C5AB1BA88A9EE">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.46.5733</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="939E7C29FB8DE188B1BF1E66E48B3606">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="758B7AE0418F8CDFEE5D1F2E191CC916" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/JHR.46.5733</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B4C1A94512CD88208F3AE01F9B377500" type="Pensoft-Pub">1314-2607-46-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="BEDA62BAC68B0B4ED194E8ECBF1C363C" type="ZBK">4F1FCDE2FA504353BE950DC837444A88</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="8FE9FBDF286FBA29356948EA46D49147" type="ZooBank">4F1FCDE2FA504353BE950DC837444A88</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="CAFB7AE793855B64A0E6A88DC4EF14A6" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127877277" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D5DD3CA8-F38B-4DB1-BC89-6E7E612E3952" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CAFB7AE793855B64A0E6A88DC4EF14A6" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<subSubSection id="0C7756DC311E627549FB01C8BCC6E8E7" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="multiple">
<paragraph id="A58344C93A9EC80397720FFD8B81AB5F" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Mutillidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D187E6436AFC0932D365CEB89E833F4C" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="ADEECE3D11BECAB7750CEFDD869AED0F" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName id="DC81B372311DA440E493D806C3980D8E" LSID="http://zoobank.org/D5DD3CA8-F38B-4DB1-BC89-6E7E612E3952" authority="Brothers" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" rank="genus">Rimulotilla Brothers</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="945B332CE15FB4D0BE78A77B37CAA8A2" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">gen. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 3-10, 31-32, 39-40
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="031A96458B169A227F7B7D7FF790FE8A" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="type species">
<paragraph id="5D3919A6634A85B3327354CAF8CCF934" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Type species.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E16732AFAF56610B52C1C87A9AE5C04F" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName id="F5D8F8771271CAA74A755CEF570D899F" authority="Linnaeus, 1758" authorityName="Linnaeus" authorityYear="1758" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Mutilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mutilla (Rhopalomutilla) tongaana" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tongaana" subGenus="Rhopalomutilla">Mutilla (Rhopalomutilla) tongaana</taxonomicName>
<normalizedToken id="F3029857145629270B7B1AEB394C3ACB" originalValue="Péringuey">Peringuey</normalizedToken>
, 1909: 386, male
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C325B0E5B0661718C44107CC47A5AAB5" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="530EFDEEF75B7FB7628A1EAF298F5E70" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FDD52093DDE31F14BDBEB02B70D19A55" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">MALE. Head strongly transverse with vertex dorsally produced as an angle behind ocelli in anterior view; no genal carina; mandible bidentate; scutellum almost conical with strong transverse apical tubercle; S6 with posterior margin simple; S8 weakly and evenly convex, slightly elevated posteriorly with deep median notch in posterior margin; penis valves symmetrical, each almost triangular with many long setae along posterodorsal margin; paramere without any stronger setae. FEMALE. Head slightly longer than wide in anterodorsal view; mesosoma elongate with abrupt concave narrowing between metathoracic spiracle and propodeal spiracle, lateral margins of propodeum converging posteriad; disc of propodeum posteriorly with strong transverse median tubercle (scutellar scale) and small tooth at lateral angle; metasoma strongly elongate with T1 broad and long; pygidial plate broad and poorly defined, posterior margin deeply concave between strong apical teeth.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8D126C4311A035A2DAA485B6A53B018D" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="description">
<paragraph id="686B9F7EA85EEF26BF4ABDF0BFC7B73F" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EF524E3F096DACE3AC8991A3EDD2DA7B" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">MALE. Body black (sometimes with mesosoma partly dark red), wings entirely infuscated (sometimes hyaline basally). Head: vertex more or less evenly rounded laterally but strongly elevated behind ocelli, posterodorsal margin of head in anterior view more or less straight on each side but forming a marked angle mesally; antennal scrobe above with diagonal transverse carina and secretory tubercle; clypeus with sculptured median area, inner marginal teeth stronger than lateral teeth; genal carina absent (sometimes an irregular slight vertical ridge present), postgena slightly convex; postmandibular carina present, strong to weak; pleurostomal carina forming a ridge from posterior mandibular articulation to margin of oral fossa much anterior to half its length; mandible apically bidentate, subapical tooth smaller than apical tooth, ventral basal lamella scarcely developed. Mesosoma: mesoscutum with anteroadmedian lines weakly developed; notaulus incomplete anteriorly; parapsidal line incomplete posteriorly or complete; tegula convex, densely punctate; scutellum strongly convex, tapering posteriorly, with very strong elevated transverse tubercle; metanotal dorsellum with sides irregular but more or less straight, sculpture variable; propodeum with disc and declivity abruptly differentiated; lateral face of pronotum not strongly tapered, anteroventral margin carinate and continuous with anteroventral tooth; mesepisternum with transverse depression well developed and extending diagonally from scrobe towards ventral extremity of pronotum; mesosternum without any distinct projections. Legs: pubescence denser on tibiae and tarsi; claws deeply cleft apical to broad lamellate base; fore tibia without any apical secretory structure or with a vertically elongate preapical groove/pore on inner (anterior) surface; mid and hind tibiae with few inconspicuous preapical dorsal spines, and fewer very inconspicuous lateral spines (seldom absent). Metasoma: T2 widest posterior to midlength; T2 and S2 without any traces of lateral felt lines; pygidium (T7) with apical margin convex, edges slightly recurved (seldom not); S1 with a median tooth near base; S6 with posterior margin entire, with sparse apical fringe; hypopygium (S8) weakly convex, forming a slightly elevated lamelliform plate with deep median apical notch overlying true posterior margin, without any separate ventrally-projecting lateral lobes. Genitalia: basal ring very short; paramere almost straight with fairly broad apex, densely and finely setose on outer surface, without any differentiated strong setae; penis valves symmetrical, short, triangular, with a row of long fairly strong setae along posterodorsal margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="089301D32503776E01CA96A6DEDEFA35" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
FEMALE. Head: slightly elongate in anterodorsal view; sides behind eyes evenly and weakly convex, produced far beyond eye, well differentiated from posterodorsal margin of head; posterodorsal margin convex, without any distinct oblique depression at each side; clypeus with median lamellate tubercle dorsally, a median tubercle above obtusely triangular ventral concavity, a tooth at each side of concavity; gena broad, genal carina weak or absent; postmandibular carina weak and long or strong and short, separated from postgenal carina; pleurostomal carina forming a ridge from posterior mandibular articulation to margin of oral fossa; mandible more or less straight and evenly tapering distally, apically unidentate; maxillary palp unsegmented, cylindrical; labial palp two- or unsegmented, cylindrical; antennal scape with or without a weak blunt tubercle posterolaterally, flattened anteromesal surface not delimited by any carinae; pedicel without any distinct tuft of fine setae. Mesosoma: elongate, very distinctly longer than wide; anterodorsal margin distinct with short anterior face; humeral angle blunt; lateral margin fairly even and smooth, anteriorly 
<pageBreakToken id="E0972F09829CC922E418C1A345D6D26F" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" start="start">gently</pageBreakToken>
rounded and weakly convex, very abruptly and strongly converging and concave to base of propodeum then almost straight to posterolateral angle with short tooth; disc of propodeum posteriorly with small tubercles on each side of strong smooth tubercle (scutellar scale) slightly overhanging margin; posterior face of propodeum nearly vertical; lateral face of pronotum with anterior oblique carina absent or scarcely indicated, a straight carina running along anteroventral margin, ventral margin straight, anteroventral extremity blunt; mesepisternum weakly and evenly convex. Legs: fore leg with femur flattened below, tibia with prominent preapical oval to arcuate secretory pore on inner (anterior) surface, tibial calcar with blade finely pectinate on margin; mid and hind femora longitudinally concave below, each with a narrow elongate preapical lamella anteroventrally; mid and hind tibiae with preapical dorsal spines strong and fairly easy to distinguish, preapical lateral spines fairly weak and moderately difficult to distinguish. Metasoma: slender; T1 with anterior face meeting dorsal face at a rounded right angle, dorsal face long, broad and somewhat transverse, almost as wide as T2, sides weakly convex and weakly diverging from base; T2 &lt;0.75 
<normalizedToken id="70194380617D248B96E79A9DF82B45C3" originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length T3-T6, with broad deep basal depression weakly convex posteriorly, sides beyond basal depression diverging then weakly convex and scarcely converging posteriorly, no trace of felt-line patch, posterior margin weakly concave to straight; T3 with posterior margin straight; T5 without any lateral tuft of long setae; pygidium (T6) with pygidial plate broad, with an irregular lateral bounding ridge basally, apical margin forming a semicircular concavity between two strong acute teeth; S1 with a short simple median carina anterior to a broad flat triangular area elevated anteriorly and becoming somewhat depressed posteriorly; S2-S4 with simple posterior margins; S5 with posterior margin lobed (sometimes tuberculate) on each side, with a posterolateral cluster of denser setae (sometimes without); S6 with apex acute, sides carinate, no flattened strong setae.
</paragraph>
<caption id="0F7863CDEF642239016DA7C376DDE389" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<paragraph id="9FD04D26D5A1178F0946C13E4A97B4AD" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Figures 3-10. 
<taxonomicName id="AF5476948625CCFEB37EADCCAFFBD265" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="genus">Rimulotilla</taxonomicName>
gen. n. 3-6 
<taxonomicName id="2205E620E8B16A620D38347613C5250A" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla tongaana" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="tongaana">Rimulotilla tongaana</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken id="E025165CAC79B424CA9F3365CE0B97AA" originalValue="Péringuey">Peringuey</normalizedToken>
) 3-4 male, dorsal &amp; lateral views 5-6 female, lateral &amp; dorsal views 7-10 
<taxonomicName id="1F68FF1D6F778DAC82E395D90204DEFE" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla conifera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="conifera">Rimulotilla conifera</taxonomicName>
(Bischoff) 7-8 male, dorsal &amp; lateral views 9-10 female, lateral &amp; dorsal views. Scales = 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="063AE2D3688F70AC86E223FC77FCB5E9" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="species included">
<paragraph id="83CE656FC559F43853725C832299F3D3" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Species included.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3D8C7B50CB5C18F138ED4EB89D4894FD" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<taxonomicName id="73FB3CFF33980F3D3FFCB842AD1A6C6E" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla basalis" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="basalis">Rimulotilla basalis</taxonomicName>
(Bischoff, 1920), male &amp; female?, stat. n., comb. n.; 
<taxonomicName id="6DBF98D2BA47FAF669A672DF6525EE88" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla conifera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="conifera">Rimulotilla conifera</taxonomicName>
(Bischoff, 1920), male &amp; female?, comb. n.; 
<taxonomicName id="72A8C02571DD8D4C59201C20A8B6D125" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla tongaana" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="tongaana">Rimulotilla tongaana</taxonomicName>
(
<normalizedToken id="B8B4B73C93C217E8327894CD9C789671" originalValue="Péringuey">Peringuey</normalizedToken>
, 1909), male &amp; female, comb. n.; two undescribed species, one male only, the other male &amp; female.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="9B88E66B97FF5DC1103B85F6419E1245" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="AD89ECFB8D6C6E1C09799311E1DA2EBF" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5485031CBD976882161C45BDA93E3C79" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Central, eastern and southern Africa (Burundi, Democratic Republic of Congo, Kenya, Malawi, Mozambique, Namibia, South Africa, Tanzania, Zambia, Zimbabwe).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3A9DCA714DF7D70C30C278C9FE2654A1" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="C4DB9D63B1B498362067787B739615D7" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D4E54E43827B114420DCFB4FF2F2D741" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
From the Latin noun rimula, a small cleft (referring to the form of S8), combined with -tilla, a common suffix derived from the genus 
<taxonomicName id="AE8239D67551064DE388F68AFE3611CD" authority="Linnaeus, 1758" authorityName="Linnaeus" authorityYear="1758" class="Insecta" family="Mutillidae" genus="Mutilla" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mutilla" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Mutilla</taxonomicName>
; gender feminine.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1B7EE7552737AE7D3782AC2C7C58393C" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="comments">
<paragraph id="5B2FA15270E7FF410614DF0B8D657DE6" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="927182EEAFB2CEC88CC4B7B3A6CAC8B5" pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Phoretic copulation in this genus probably has a shorter duration than in the other genera of 
<taxonomicName id="5BDC1FE0C4936F49BB86B0ABB6E7F2E0" lsidName="" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Rhopalomutillinae">Rhopalomutillinae</taxonomicName>
since there are few recorded copulating pairs in collections and the apical sterna of the males are less modified than in the other genera. The only species for which I have seen directly associated male and female specimens (and actually collected a mating pair myself) is 
<taxonomicName id="7E327D31B9285B256611CE3102815506" genus="Rimulotilla" lsidName="Rimulotilla tongaana" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" rank="species" species="tongaana">Rimulotilla tongaana</taxonomicName>
, hence its designation as the type species. Other sex associations have mainly been based on collection of both sexes in malaise traps at similar times and places.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>