<document id="F93E58D65E373C778D51CEA63584A96A" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.24538" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d9a51558-64a6-46be-800c-4dcaca5951bb" ID-GBIF-Taxon="149667410" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-796-33" ID-ZBK="86B38AD6896048C1A65D54FAE73AEF66" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A16BB301-C41B-44CB-8426-B04E2C8C625F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-796-33" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 796" ModsDocTitle="A new Xenicocephalus species from Ecuador (Heteroptera, Enicocephalomorpha, Enicocephalidae)" checkinTime="1542332377462" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Stys, Pavel &amp; Baňar, Petr" docDate="2018" docId="CB25DF2B2BC06E7B52D7B7F294CD0500" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 796: 33-47" docOrigin="ZooKeys 796" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.24538" docTitle="Xenicocephalus tomhenryi Stys &amp; Baňar, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="A16BB301-C41B-44CB-8426-B04E2C8C625F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="33" masterDocId="FFCF8631B314FFCD4E33FFAEFFACFFE1" masterDocTitle="A new Xenicocephalus species from Ecuador (Heteroptera, Enicocephalomorpha, Enicocephalidae)" masterLastPageNumber="47" masterPageNumber="33" originalUpdateDomain="Boston" originalUpdateTime="1542332377462" originalUpdateUser="pensoft" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" updateTime="1643464363518" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="A1D12A6D85EC2A2EB8B052845D0AB70A" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="21F6652F8C868F0FACD81D13D87C95B4">
<mods:title id="A3DC970E228161BA787272AB0C156769">A new Xenicocephalus species from Ecuador (Heteroptera, Enicocephalomorpha, Enicocephalidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="A7F00160BBAB9CAF926B145A9723BA1B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="C25D4D7DE11F9DB1F90E6953CA5E922C">
<mods:roleTerm id="4EB8648ED047F1FF9FA70D491BD730A8">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5F956ABBA05551C92E3DE4D08B75B444">Stys, Pavel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="122B8C45A134DFA1A4C765CA1203EE02" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B0C3A193A5403F69C5A25953F6E85BD3">
<mods:roleTerm id="C850E1D4BB316E46E07368BDCCF39295">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="FFAA05F9720EED990AF2ABC141E90839">Baňar, Petr</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="73BC08F3781C0D80AB6F3B8FF6989406">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="BEA780B5811A1127A79081647F6F342E" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="CA6E2AD2D5BC3D0D49B996CF49F3AF39">
<mods:title id="9408A3C6DD36D2CF5E706F843D8D14F6">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="8B58E659A645F2DA8AB443D8798361F1">
<mods:date id="9CEC348DC2140AE0F362A65FB79F01A9">2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="23FFCB0960E792AB7F995B66168004FB" type="volume">
<mods:number id="6FB3F0A0B9558ED876311187E2734185">796</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="C0C0D784821AFC9DDEB26F6170E739F2" unit="page">
<mods:start id="C23B9F8B1BB9D3120F8C0A79A770D067">33</mods:start>
<mods:end id="E0BF0C98A4FA06B12F582B8E9ADDC59C">47</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="3E516E7EFBF7D4E71F0515BA14481843">
<mods:url id="3CB6AB3F4BD1FF4C8C9E372FAC11A5D0">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.24538</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="C7A5397101354BA33F03C840E71F24C0">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="159798B47546F89B68889412A2CD63F8" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.796.24538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="C062EA1A5C28B32A82FE8E89FC9993DD" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-796-33</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="55756FEF00AA579EA4B764D7EF737B27" type="ZBK">86B38AD6896048C1A65D54FAE73AEF66</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="911E21430A56F92F5D457006DEC82EB4" type="ZooBank">86B38AD6896048C1A65D54FAE73AEF66</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="CB25DF2B2BC06E7B52D7B7F294CD0500" ID-GBIF-Taxon="149667410" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A16BB301-C41B-44CB-8426-B04E2C8C625F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CB25DF2B2BC06E7B52D7B7F294CD0500" lastPageNumber="33" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<subSubSection id="90835875F77D8C13431200BD0C627BD8" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="B2226F88B9BC01ABBDDA3D179AA323DE" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<taxonomicName id="FCD1EE8023CBDD49ED063CB587D5DE15" LSID="http://zoobank.org/A16BB301-C41B-44CB-8426-B04E2C8C625F" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus tomhenryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">Xenicocephalus tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="45A652399211DA1E31A17BFD4534420F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A1B502857932094143F097214E533053" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" type="description">
<paragraph id="7ED79EA7197E1166AFB3D034457B1C31" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7AE390013B182F12D5F95C9C4540C560" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Measurements (in mm) of female holotype; L = length; W = width. Total body L 8.60. Head: total L (without neck) 1.31; posterior lobe, L 0.51, posterior lobe, W 0.71; distance eye-apex of antennifer 0.37; maximum width across eyes 0.67; dorsal minimum interocular distance 0.33; ventral minimum interocular distance 0.20; eye L 0.22. Labium total L 0.60. Antenna: Segment I L 0.40; segment II L 0.96, segment III L 0.89, segment IV L 0.82. Pronotum: total L (maximum) 1.64; collum, L (median) 0.28, maximum W 0.78; midlobe, L (median) 0.64, midlobe, W (maximum) 1.42; hindlobe, L (maximum) 0.87, hindlobe, L (median) 0.40; hindlobe, W (maximum) 2.02. Foreleg: femur L 1.49, femur, maximum W 0.51, tibia L 1.36, tibia maximum W 0.29. Forewing L 5.95, W 2.18. Hindwing L 4.94, W1.92.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BFFF6AEA365A1DBA3033DBD82C7D6D30" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Coloration dark brown (Figure 1A), legs, labium, antennomere IV and base of forewing paler, light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A007CC9C324C2E58B940E0DDA28F9DC4" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Pilosity. Antennae densely covered with short, semi-erect setae, dorsal and lateral parts of head covered with long, semi-erect setae of variable orientation, mixed with shorter, erect setae similar to those on antennae and compound eyes. Venter of head with long semi-erect setae. Vestiture on pronotum, lateral, and ventral parts of thorax similar to that on dorsum of head. Forelegs with numerous long semi-erect setae of different orientation, setae on ventral face of foretibia shorter and erect. Forewing veins with short semi-erect to erect setae; hindwing veins bare. Dorsum of abdomen with semi-erect and erect setae, longest on 
<normalizedToken id="36CC10096ADCD521F4F668BFF12453AC" originalValue="“outer”">&quot;outer&quot;</normalizedToken>
laterotergites, becoming shorter to nearly absent toward medial parts of mediotergites. Lateral faces of laterotergites only with short, erect setae. Venter of abdomen densely covered with vestiture, becoming denser and longer towards apex of abdomen.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1D7CCC4024D87F71F07CCF15D1C85B18" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Texture. Body faces, including forewing, densely covered with countless cuticular microgranules, giving a matt appearance. Foretibia along almost entire ventral face (except proximal sixth) with two rows (posterior and anterior one) of irregularly placed large, semi-globular to slightly conical, strongly sclerotized granules (Figure 3D, E), appearing under lower magnification as impression of two deeply brown to blackish lines (Figure 1F). Forefemur similar but with anterior row of large granules, more developed, situated on slightly elevated rim; granules in posterior row smaller, nearly subglobular proximally, becoming lens-like platelets distally. Surface of forefemoral concavity with countless lens-like platelets.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="CAF510298DC57778FFD23C09F130FF04" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" type="structure">
<paragraph id="AA15D8262576E298CDD646AAF682410E" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Structure.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F3048DFFF86D54E004E1953D09732B2E" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Head. Rather narrow, strongly elongate (Figs 1B, C, 5A, B). In dorsal view, preocular margins (formed largely by antennifers) strongly diverging distad, moderately convex, much shorter than strongly produced medial clypeo-mandibular projection. Eyes prominent, semiglobular, with numerous separate, convex facets, eye width much shorter than synthlipsis, dorsal ocular index 1.94. Postocular part and postocular constriction (long and shallow) hardly distinguishable from each other, long, laterally strongly concave, about as long as antero-posterior length of eye. Postocular lobe short and broad, widest in middle, slightly wider than transocular width, lateral sides broadly rounded. Ocellar tubercles strikingly large and prominent, large ocelli directed anterolaterad: ocellar tubercles in 
<taxonomicName id="ED6DAD17A88FB1D6582DEAF0913AFC71" authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Enicocephalomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" infraorder="Enicocephalomorpha" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Enicocephalomorpha" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="infraorder">Enicocephalomorpha</taxonomicName>
bear ocelli dorsally or dorsolaterally; entire dorsal surface of ocellar tubercles sometimes occupied by ocelli with their tubercles hardly indicated. Tubercles and ocelli are mostly not distinguished in descriptive papers (including some of ours). Interocellar distance 1.5 times as long as distance of ocellar tubercle to eye. Neck simple. Eyes in ventral view strongly produced laterad and sunken mesad, longest axis strongly diagonal and directed antero-laterad, eye much wider than minimum interocular distance, ventral ocular index 0.85.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7B760453AAECC25025BDB7DB6AB972FF" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Antennae. Insertion nearly subterminal, segment 1 with a large prescapite, segment itself strongly widening distad, much surpassing apex of head, segment 2 terete, slightly thickening distad, segments 3 and 4 long, thinner, but less than subflagelliform. Antennal formula (longest segment first): II:III:IV:I.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="761D87D8BC1FEDBD793A670E65EB6DF7" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Labium. Short, reaching anterior margins of eyes. Labial formula (longest segment first) III-IV-II=I. The dorsal (morphologically ventral) outline of segment III moderately convex, ventral one straight.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2CE2CC9BC3579888E7C76DF98BD5D1F1" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Pronotum (Figure 1D). Lateral and posterior outlines of collum large and moderately sized, wider midlobe strongly convex, midlobe laterally much exceeded by moderately convex lateral margins of hindlobe. Convex posterior margin of hindlobe subdivided into two separately convex parts by deep subtriangular median gulf reaching nearly half length of hindlobe median. Details of surface shape of pronotal lobes undetectable. Ratio width to median length of collum 2.78; of the midlobe 2.22 and ratio of maximum width of hindlobe to maximum length 2.32.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="06E7C850606247AF4E74054B39817B14" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" type="other parts of thorax">
<paragraph id="78944DF8612CC640C046AC7AFC450623" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Other parts of thorax.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D336337F47674EA6797040D29321505B" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Fore acetabula widely separated and widely open. Mesoscutellum broadly triangular, apex not produced but provided with transversely oval swelling with marginally radiating macrotrichia. Mesonotum and metanotum (Figure 1E).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6E16567ABBECE15C5899342A526FED34" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Forelegs. Foretrochanter (Figs 1F, 3A, B) produced as subtriangular process over anterior base of forefemur, anterior margins of latter diagonal and thickened by marginal inversely L-shaped ridge; posterior margins of process perpendicular to femur, posterior face of process concave. Only areas ventral to process and small inner angles of inversely L-shaped ridges with granules, remainder of trochanter smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9220910FE8E8E9FE6717143302C8D30A" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Forefemur (Figs 1F, 3C) strikingly thick and curved, arcuate, dorsal face convex, ventral face deeply and percurrently concave; groove delimited by two marginal rows of densely packed minute subglobular platelets, surface of concavity densely pilose. (Neopatella [cf. 
<bibRefCitation id="D106EFFAF3CD93C5393DD37A943CBFA7" author="Stys, P" journalOrPublisher="Acta Entomologica Musei Nationalis Pragae" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" pagination="3 - 15" title="The first species of Systelloderes (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Enicocephalidae) from New Caledonia." volume="47" year="2007">
<normalizedToken id="91155234F208B85C1A9A0E2F18077DC3" originalValue="Štys">Stys</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken id="57790C0C776FDD168B68D225D14A26E1" originalValue="Baňař">Baňar</normalizedToken>
2007
</bibRefCitation>
] not studied.)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B0EABAB90FFF6E642FA485013EC015B2" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Foretibia (Figs 1F, 3D) thick, flattish, rather uniformly broad, very moderately arcuate, ventral face deeply percurrently concave and densely pilose, concavity about as long as that of forefemur, margins of concavity delimited as in forefemur by subglobular platelets (Figure 3E). Apicitibial armature (Figs 4A, C, D, 6A, B). Tibial process long and thin, about as long as foretarsus, strikingly delimited from remainder of tibia by concavity containing medial part of bristle-comb formed by ca. 28 palisade-like spines (Figure 4B). Apiciventral tibial spines formed by two groups: (a) more dorsal cluster of four long, thin, slightly curved spines (their proximal parts with parallel grooves), cluster separated from (b) more ventral area by shorter, thicker, and less pointed, finger-shaped spine above conspicuous ventral-most rounded projection of process. Foretarsus. Tarsus with four (Figs 4B, 6C) somewhat thicker setae (two anterior + two posterior = two dorsal + two ventral) distributed among normal macrotrichia, not longer than these, and recognizable only by presence of longitudinal grooving.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D58B1EDEE350444AE27B7B81E8EC3405" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Midlegs and hindlegs short and robust, first tarsomeres very short. Apices of middle and hind tibiae with two bristle combs, anterior and posterior ones each consisting of ca. 12-15 isomorphic setae, and two or three much longer, ventrally placed setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0FF98F82353743413FD9FD53EDF287DE" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Post-tarsi could not be studied in detail. Fore post-tarsus with strikingly split unguitractor plate along median. Claws heteromorphic, strikingly slender and short, longest at foreleg (posterior claw reduced to stump), shortest at midleg. Fore claw and hind claws nearly straight, middle claw basally thick and distally regularly arcuate.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FDC629DB21CFD8802619FDF89BE4DB00" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Forewing (Figure 2A) veins with short, semi-erect to erect setae. Basal and discal cells closed; indistinct ambient vein marginal, coinciding with wing margin; costal fracture (or node) absent. Veins C+Sc and R and R1 so strongly thickened that anteradial furrow displaced laterad at inner edge of C&amp;Sc. Medial furrow (= postradial furrow) absent. Basal anchor-like vein short and thick; distinctly diagonal, vein-like r-m entering MA in middle of discal cell (r-m teratologically doubled on right wing). M and Cu branching rather proximally; basal cell thus long and pointed but still slightly shorter than pointed discal cell. Discal cell nearly reaching wing margin, connecting with it by very short M&amp;Cu1a and longer Cu1b; cu-an entering discal cell much more proximally relative to branching point of Cu1a and Cu1b. AA1+2 and AA3+4 meeting to form joint distal sector of AA in ca. 2/5 length of AA before joining cu-an. Entire wing diffusely melanized except base.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="20C5AFFC499CE11383318E4903359EAF" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Hindwing (Figure 2B). Pregenital abdomen moderately broad, oval, apex nearly pointed. Dorsum with peculiar system of elevated longitudinal (lateral and medial) rails and transverse rungs resembling lattice of ladder (Figure 2C). MTG I subdivided into two hemitergites by median desclerotization; separate LTG lacking. MTG II very short, strongly thickened, forming first rung of 
<normalizedToken id="A9A2AFD988B5AEA7732AE5E964E731A1" originalValue="“ladder”">&quot;ladder&quot;</normalizedToken>
; LTG I &amp; II laterally embracing MTG I. Mediotergites 
<normalizedToken id="5551F2300C0D4C78DE771242C634CFE4" originalValue="III–VIII">III-VIII</normalizedToken>
each with rung along posterior margin (extending on segments 
<normalizedToken id="CC414BB16DB03F914BB25B4C0FF070EC" originalValue="III–VI">III-VI</normalizedToken>
to connexival margin). Segments 
<normalizedToken id="1D20B23C19CFE9661579C4C66E177A15" originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
with strong lateral rails forming lateral margins of MTG, separating them from DLTG area subdivided in inner DLTG (= lateral-most parts of MTG?) and outer DLTG; subdivision of DLTG area indistinct on dorsite VIII. MTG 
<normalizedToken id="7281E4B344E2B0D5BC0A5FA5FB08D94C" originalValue="III–V">III-V</normalizedToken>
with distinct and wide (VI with indistinct and diffusing) median rail. Dorsites VIII and IX simple. Opening of dorsal gland at anterior margin of MTG IV formed by semicircular depression provided with pair (sic!) of large, posterior, nearly contiguous openings. Venter (Figure 2D). Details of ventrite I not discernible. Ventrites 
<normalizedToken id="784A9FCF08E5726FCDCF9BE02FFC2F6C" originalValue="II–VII">II-VII</normalizedToken>
with more complex lattice than on dorsum but details not studied. Transverse, narrow, and long genital slit between ventrites VII and VIII; any other genital or proctigeral structures not observed.
</paragraph>
<caption id="9844EAB2B7100FAB4212F445F0823494" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<paragraph id="E4CF838C72D5A8D58F0E9B8C29A27685" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName id="5F72A7FBFFDAF6953C3F4F7546F2FE2C" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus tomhenryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">Xenicocephalus tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype A forewing B hindwing C abdomen, dorsal view D abdomen, ventral view. Scale bars in mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7D57E21EA0A3BFC8B1A53A55F09EB7B2" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" type="type material">
<paragraph id="1C8E2BDB7A7EF0E8B73EAE171DCC6DF8" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="696F4B50C20ECBC9D778F56E3D8BEAA2" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Holotype female, labelled: 'Ecuador camino / Aloag-Tandapi / Pr. Pichincha 2600m / 12.II.1983 A. Roig [handwritten] // Drake Colln. ex / J. Maldonado C. / Coll. 1996 [printed] // 
<taxonomicName id="0BADC588C5FE1299F276980BA7E39F4F" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Xenicocephalus</taxonomicName>
/ sp. nov. / P. 
<normalizedToken id="49B1F91C8F5ED5206505E0E0B6D38776" originalValue="Baňař">Baňar</normalizedToken>
det. 2014 [handwritten, partly printed] // HOLOTYPE / 
<taxonomicName id="3FC1745718759760FF1272ECC7C88235" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Xenicocephalus</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName id="693B1C548F2D45060CCB7139A8E96632" authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Enicocephalomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Enicocephalomorpha tomhenryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. / P. 
<normalizedToken id="10B9B11E0123644883525D8C76159BBD" originalValue="Štys">Stys</normalizedToken>
&amp; P. 
<normalizedToken id="C0348D8C34E29029D4704105F045E9E7" originalValue="Baňař">Baňar</normalizedToken>
det. 2018 [printed red label]'. Dry-mounted, left foreleg and right wings mounted separately; right middletarsus missing. Deposited in Department of Entomology of National Museum of Natural History, Washington, D.C. (USNM).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="161665EBFCDEF3288E655A29156C5A04" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="B233E03B9B402B8EC75F79733A046652" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Etymology and dedication.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="384A56A6253BAE235C67B8AAD20108C5" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Dedicated to our dear colleague Thomas J. Henry, eminent student of the 
<taxonomicName id="8452A792635DDC22856F0AD292185A6F" authority="" authorityName="" class="Insecta" family="Miridae" genus="Heteroptera" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Heteroptera" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="suborder" suborder="Heteroptera">Heteroptera</taxonomicName>
, for long-standing cooperation and friendship. Pavel will always remember 
<normalizedToken id="2D740342F8DE8F13F943F2B6B5F8638D" originalValue="Tom´s">Tom's</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken id="AE2BF473614FACB064B56BA4ADC233B5" originalValue="Katy´s">Katy's</normalizedToken>
hospitality and kind assistance during his stay at their house in Silver Spring, Maryland, after his mishap in 2014.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="4905C1C787F0E64570D62D5E92B698CD" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" type="species comparison">
<paragraph id="2635E8DDA61C83F753AC0DC510B28F0E" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Species comparison.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="43FEB795405301D165D6130A7B29FBEC" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
The following comparative paragraphs are intended to serve as a diagnosis and comparative diagnosis. Because of the paucity of material, we could not always determine whether the differences are species-specific, sex-specific, or represent individual variation. The last alternative may particularly involve characters of the forewing venation, which is notoriously variable and subject to teratological mutations (cf. 
<bibRefCitation id="51CA43E101175718F103D1E7A93AAEC1" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<normalizedToken id="DAD63766E08FD9D298D57EB3CE7BE764" originalValue="Štys">Stys</normalizedToken>
1980
</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="3F58E45F2F3A024F07C3B0EC4C862980" author="Wygodzinsky, PW" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" pagination="1 - 265" title="Revision of the New World Enicocephalomorpha (Heteroptera)." volume="200" year="1991">Wygodzinsky and Schmidt 1991</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation id="2659299A69CE1C674F4B23B42D52E2FD" author="Stys, P" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" pagination="1220 - 1232" title="A new species of Tornocrusus (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Aenictopecheidae) from Ecuador, and morphological notes." volume="110" year="2008 b">
<normalizedToken id="4E7338D697770BBD06CFE330F449887D" originalValue="Štys">Stys</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken id="6DA96B440A0CBD8A450B725A9FA50D19" originalValue="Baňař">Baňar</normalizedToken>
2008b
</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="168FE76F6AC7DA5BF83156B901FBE00F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
The data on 
<taxonomicName id="6D759F920971DE1FAF3CBCD03AA2249F" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Xenicocephalus</taxonomicName>
species are organized as follows: (1) 
<taxonomicName id="B05959FBE497397F5C7D91A9B54964AC" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
female from Ecuador (holotype), (2) 
<taxonomicName id="5C6870428F8ABF187947CDD36CF8B991" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
male from Suriname (holotype), (3) 
<taxonomicName id="583CDBE5C12A0E063F0579768196FD81" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
female from Colombia (incomplete holotype), (4) 
<taxonomicName id="8D8E0D92A0BFE967AB7D8CDB22501313" genus="X." lsidName="X." pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="genus">X.</taxonomicName>
sp., larva 5 from Colombia: (Santa Marta: San Sebastian de Marago) assumed by 
<bibRefCitation id="242E4750CD40C61EF04FA5837F47918D" author="Wygodzinsky, PW" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" pagination="1 - 265" title="Revision of the New World Enicocephalomorpha (Heteroptera)." volume="200" year="1991">Wygodzinsky and Schmidt (1991)</bibRefCitation>
to be conspecific with 
<taxonomicName id="11197EBB61B2D8510D58453E1A75D2FA" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
and used by them in completing the diagnosis of 
<taxonomicName id="B75BDDCA8E0CD048B6240EBA079DD999" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Xenicocephalus</taxonomicName>
. The important autapomorphic diagnostic character states are in boldface type.
</paragraph>
<caption id="5C4F8A2D77C4DCA669BAD0754A4FC436" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<paragraph id="422CD7E2141F517EFDB6B83D1379BAD4" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName id="48BEDFD640F0F8B7FD06B8BF9B65AA22" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus tomhenryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">Xenicocephalus tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype, left foreleg, scanning electron micrographs A coxa, trochanter and basis of femur, anterior view B coxa and trochanter, ventral view C femur, anterior view D tibia, anterior view E detail of ventral concavity of tibia F bristle comb of tibial apex, anterior view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="B818B7C9884CA0D69EDA1DA3E785A5B0" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Antennae</paragraph>
<paragraph id="490B6F82FBFA3B76911FEFC3EF8DE42F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="47816C345C0203AF8DDA2AE4B6CDCD16" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - segment I long, strikingly thickening distad; II long, terete, slightly thickening distad, about as long as head.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="DB6B6B08D2B23D5EB3583BAB554501A1" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="A32B7F31F042821F971EB104F746F444" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - segment I short, thick, not thickening distad; II short, thicker but not thickening distad, about 1.5 times as long as head.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="03BCE513A858085CCF95A053943C1974" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="8D5EE27F65F008535D8A779A1299E5F5" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F -?
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="14D0DCFC422407B072F81DCF04E123FF" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="5561C8EA351CCCC93C88F550F0FF7901" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - segment I short, thickening distad; II long, terete, not thickening distad, about as long as head.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5EAC37089985442C821C70A7EAA47F30" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Head (size of eyes sexually dimorphic?)</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FD41623F889D2CA1BE8E6756264384E8" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="997415D2623612F47A3DC8C80C6C0AA7" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - preocular part of head long, eyes short, distances anterior margin of eye-insertion of antenna and posterior margin of eye-ocellus longer than maximum length of eye; postocular part of anterior lobe &amp; transverse constriction strikingly long; ocelli submarginal.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="380FA388E056B7DD235E61A39BFE3615" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="607BF20FC38F67E86FCB0FCA05B76BED" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - preocular part of head short, eyes long, distance anterior margin of eye-insertion of antenna and posterior margin of eye-ocellus much shorter than maximum length of eye; postocular part of anterior lobe not present, constriction narrow; ocelli marginal.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A8214F4EF36E7DA226469F327BDBA21D" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="D5209F55DBD1525360E6B7276A9D6E9A" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F -?
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5D503DD7D29698760461124959D59C01" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="95DA82267EE758FF8B9654FD97C601B2" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(F?) L 5 - preocular part of head long, eyes minute, lateral, distance anterior margin of eye-insertion of antennae as long as maximum length of eye; postocular part of anterior lobe nearly as long as eye; constriction deep and narrow; ocelli not mentioned in original description, but their rudiments indicated (
<bibRefCitation id="933BE5694A48FA83C2D634AF9E75C869" author="Wygodzinsky, PW" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" pagination="1 - 265" title="Revision of the New World Enicocephalomorpha (Heteroptera)." volume="200" year="1991">Wygodzinsky and Schmidt 1991</bibRefCitation>
: fig. 149B, p. 206).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E6701910BF1907661180F50302FAA4F4" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Pronotum</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0C516C375E301616123B476D87A47A44" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="944337A2C76B7A037F13FDC6AA0C387E" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - posterior margin of collum strongly convex, encroaching onto midlobe region; hind lobe 
<normalizedToken id="30AFED2C2A8FFC5B40136532CDB674C3" originalValue="“entire,“">&quot;entire,&quot;</normalizedToken>
median part not differentiated; anterolateral parts of hindlobe embracing posterolateral parts of midlobe, posteromedial notch of hind lobe ca. twice as deep as maximum median length of hindlobe.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A84B4B40AFE4969D729CBC57DDF80EEC" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="EA37DBE9EE51FE17AC4DA15AAA3B7D90" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - posterior margin of collum transverse; hindlobe 
<normalizedToken id="703B8FB8DDA3E4DF180D2281BB8C218C" originalValue="“bipartite,”">&quot;bipartite,&quot;</normalizedToken>
creating impression of two opposite leaves attached to broad and weakly sclerotized median region; anterolateral parts of hindlobe not extending cephalad, posteromedial notch of hind lobe ca. half as deep as maximum median length of hindlobe.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2B8969DC9D206D0DD9F15E18550A616E" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="07D21F51D8057E0B642873F6C89DA6B9" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F -?
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2110D43FE552C2BFCEC594C51E144FBF" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="A7BDF690B0BA6843E8251ED551A3D7BD" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - posterior margin of collum very moderately convex; mid- and hindlobes not differentiated.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AFC971C055D387CEF3CE111EB5023CA1" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Mesoscutellum</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E213358EFD1926F5F97F09E8E9008038" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="6D84F138B9A62A8E1B8CDB132F4BEB7F" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - broadly rounded, apex with transversely oval swelling with radiating marginal macrotrichia.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5AA507A16C85DC698F6C9C1663E65FE0" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="C23241C5F9D1C84ADE7B3BB93A469DB0" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - amply triangular, apically mucronate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="AF38A7CAEB5A5F39CD60BB7CE348CAC8" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="EF63040CB0BE671D142A47DE247A16A9" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F - amply triangular, apically mucronate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="25C358FCF52A7691394B8DAE2E172D99" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="4FD7C7455A286F42E324FE7EEBF56167" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - 0.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9AB59E562701567031DA77F74B87D1D9" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Forewings (individual variation and most potential teratologies could not be assessed). We are not certain about the presence of AP in any 
<taxonomicName id="5A52C2E5E1D28ED6F23CF85B5F9350D0" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Xenicocephalus</taxonomicName>
species (contrary to our previous statement on 
<taxonomicName id="491A5E6860ABDBE246855AB9A102CE81" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation id="28321C658E4F894F44A41BC735BA3AB1" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<normalizedToken id="950BED9519770C75049C794E5E7782AB" originalValue="Štys">Stys</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken id="32EA42F13CDC030ECD912D1CB671A27B" originalValue="Baňař">Baňar</normalizedToken>
2008a
</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1D8AE6B4C15FB15862E41C7B97B5903F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="374344694BCB095904BD2A01B9D8AE81" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - C&amp;Sc, R and Rs extremely strongly thickened, anteradial furrow along edge of C&amp;Sc; veins delimiting base of discal cell (part of M and part of Cu proximal to cu-an) unequally long, M about three times as long as Cu; r-m vein-like; apex of discal cell close to wing margin, 2 short distal veins entering wing margin; fork Cu1a-Cu1b far distad to cu-an. Forewing macropterous, conspicuously exceeding apex of abdomen.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1582A1C0AA24492844484045C8062EEA" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="E8406689C46E42BC80587D27469F3077" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - C&amp;Sc, R and Rs moderately thickened, anteradial furrow within subcostal cell; veins delimiting base of discal cell (part of M and part of Cu proximal to cu-an) equally long; r-m point-like; apex of discal cell close to wing margin,1 hardly distinct distal vein entering wing margin; fork Cu1a-Cu1b coinciding with position of cu-an. Forewing macropterous, exceeding apex of abdomen.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="780DF8D4A892027FCFCA850674648C96" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="46E1D01E54F8C9D877A0BFA91256CF79" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F - C&amp;Sc, R and Rs extremely strongly thickened but anteradial furrow within subcostal cell; veins delimiting base of discal cell (part of M and part of Cu proximal to cu-an) equally long; r-m vein-like; apex of discal cell distant from wing margin,1 distinct vein reaching wing margin; fork Cu1a-Cu1b far distad to cu-an. Forewing submacropterous, not exceeding apex of abdomen.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="385A5A942C69918DDEEE2494462C265E" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="D59A50F0938EFA8632B059212F306510" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - 0.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="53FC634589D46BC425E4C3EB57EFC8AA" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Foretrochanter (perceived shape strikingly dependent on angle of observation).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="82D08A73E54DC6F3D7DD325ECD23811E" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="17C5D85E38DF432EDA81F06D520365DA" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - broadly rounded, apex with transversely oval swelling with radiating marginal macrotrichia.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="571EE80CD089F3DDA1F875A69422EE22" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="07C9688FF8E08CBCA348BFABC7991C72" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - ventral side with prominent ridge terminating in small ventral tubercle exceeding base of femur ventrad and only inconspicuous distad.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6394D74C8F1194D4568F8EF53E627571" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="F68EF392446670755B8F56130B8429D6" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F -?
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EFF54032E06AC87DFC2E6C3E729AE37F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="483F0E4CBCBE78AA061C4F9F71327767" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - ventral side with prominent strongly sclerotized ridge-like projection exceeding base of femur ventrad but not distad.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E8F83D6E1C12B4CBD09BFDA8DE3E4C17" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Forefemur</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2B89886289BFB00F247C448E8364C0F4" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="C1DC7125AA96C81217D0F6119CCB26C5" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - strikingly thick and curved, arcuate, dorsal face convex, ventral face deeply and percurrently concave; groove delimited by two marginal rows of densely packed minute subglobular platelets of stronger sclerotization, anterior row of large granules more developed, on slightly elevated rim, granules in posterior row smaller, nearly subglobular proximally, becoming lens-like platelets distally, appearing in lower magnification as impression of two deeply brown to blackish lines. Surface of forefemoral concavity with countless lens-like platelets, heavily sclerotized, blackish, the surface of the concavity densely pilose. No other blackish platelets or granules present.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="57DFF474BC086DF9FD4C19A86E69A8F2" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="A11276721C59268EEE5B7DAE416CD995" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - distinctly curved, moderately C-shaped; ventral face concave, with vestiture lacking, parallel-sided and sharply delimited at anterior and posterior edges by row of macrotrichia and irregularly distributed black granules intermixed with row of conspicuous, high, non-setigerous conical tubercles.Ventral concavity with numerous small, broad, transverse scale-like structures. Blackish granules also on distal two thirds of lateral and dorsal faces.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0BBA7065EF3D62A122749078AA610CC3" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="23665725CD488982714EF2A4B26C75FD" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F -?
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4AD4AD922C4FE36237691792E57C98F1" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="971EC648147E0EFA8EFD1AD05F993EFC" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - conspicuously curved, bearing numerous cuticular granules dorsally and ventrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5C6C39170BB476F8F76BDACF2E3B9D74" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Foretibia</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7795BEAFCB2D2375D9155767CDA3CA0B" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="766410220508A4E3B6916B5F786CF8AC" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - thick, flattish, rather uniformly broad, very moderately arcuate, ventral face deeply percurrently concave and densely pilose, concavity about as long as that of forefemur, margins of concavity delimited as in forefemur by subglobular platelets. Foretibia along ventral face (except proximal sixth) with two rows (posterior and anterior) of irregularly placed large, semi-globular to slightly conical, strongly sclerotized granules, appearing in lower magnification as impression of two deeply brown to blackish lines. No other blackish platelets or granules present.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3B7A9B41BEE2DE25DAE085351057A360" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="48F44F81094D95C762F0124D24BBECA5" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M -cylindrical, of uniform width, only dorsal outline slightly curved. Entire ventral face moderately concave, vestiture lacking, edges of tibial concavity less sharply delimited than those of femoral one. Anterior edge with 14, posterior edge with numerous conical tubercles of same shape as on femur. Anterior face with ca. 50 black granules, posterior face with several hundred. Ventral concavity with numerous small, broad, transverse scale-like structures.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="630F6F2F63BF9D2EAF831CDA84E53229" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="9589E7042B46E04BE12017341712C22E" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F -?
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C66D9E3BC6C0E1E6D842930DCC1DDCCF" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="8DE9D9DC2380047B4CE3585BD7C3E8A5" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 -inner apical angle in form of pointed, strongly sclerotized projection bearing 3-5 straight, slender spines inserted below apex. Apex of central portion of inner surface of foretibia with field of short, stout setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="23BFB4F4BFFA6D1552BAF8DD04AD6D34" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Apicitibial and tarsal armature of foreleg</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F77E24146C2F82E50DEA126EA58F05F9" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="4CEC726F21C9FD95DCC95713F73E9B75" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - tibial process long and narrow, strikingly differentiated from remainder of distal tibial edge, with four slender and more dorsal spines, and one ventral thick, short, conical spine from more ventral tubercle. Tarsal armature from four somewhat thicker setae (two anterior + two posterior = two dorsal + two ventral) distributed among normal macrotrichia, not longer than these, and recognizable only by presence of longitudinal grooving.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="099862D8C36FC8DB3E1150C1FFE82ADD" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="8E5B9EE962AB997E876D23E16F517E96" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - tibial projection moderately large, rounded, with seven slender subapical spines, four in ventral row, three in dorsal row; tarsal armature from four spines, three of them very long and slender, one stout and conspicuously shorter.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8BA9BCB1ED855CB04FA09D8E71314713" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="5AC8ADA121C7824AA170100AE3ED1AC9" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F -?
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="338A09C7B71D49FAF38BF23598FBDDA5" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="F1DD3CF165BC114C06EB39C3530AA796" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - tibial projection acutangular but not markedly differentiated from distal edge of tibia; with 3-5 slender subapical spines.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="43B53C20378DCDD13FB3E77B764AF928" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">Pregenital abdomen, dorsum (a comparative study required)</paragraph>
<paragraph id="917A391E7A6436630C7404B4D6A1DB1E" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(1) 
<taxonomicName id="E785B8922BC92126A926F97EDE823E2D" genus="X." lsidName="X. tomhenryi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">X. tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
F - complex lattice system (elevated rails and rungs)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="63F014A08310F446F55C1A3E3EECAE5C" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">present.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="A321C6FEA5D60ACFBAD60CD412FCE1C4" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(2) 
<taxonomicName id="3330725E1B4A2D06FCEFEFFAA621F732" genus="X." lsidName="X. josifovi" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="josifovi">X. josifovi</taxonomicName>
M - lattice absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F491D28BD3F37C3FE182723E3CCFEE1F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(3) 
<taxonomicName id="E21986AD2EB5395EFF9E015A6969454C" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
F - lattice absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C4C6B8C3787B084DDD7F285ECDC007B1" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
(4) 
<taxonomicName id="052D822536633C82ABF624E3950F4371" genus="X." lsidName="X. giganticus" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" rank="species" species="giganticus">X. giganticus</taxonomicName>
(?) L 5 - lattice absent.
</paragraph>
<caption id="69789E2962905274982B7E5F7D23FD93" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<paragraph id="B28CA3D64381697D881355ED31E61A0F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="A0489FDA26875EA681E5D3C56D248670" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus tomhenryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">Xenicocephalus tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype, left foreleg, scanning electron micrographs A apicitibial armature, ventral view B tarsal armature, ventral view C apicitibial armature, posterior view D apicitibial armature, anterior view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="34EE861DE8D60D4E34F02EA3CD20FF8F" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<paragraph id="3DC9045DCA4F08BE721AB2EAE2D37B87" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName id="AFABFA553530C95303B5BC5A67B993D4" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus tomhenryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">Xenicocephalus tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype, head A dorsal view B ventral view. Scale bar in mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="E3EF759B2FAA6449BA8824495460B7BF" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
<paragraph id="28FC7F15F9729A4B3346D5B70A70C938" pageId="0" pageNumber="33">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName id="A65A0CDDA86FC2FE8909A46C35ED4962" authority="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt, 1991" authorityName="Wygodzinsky &amp; Schmidt" authorityYear="1991" class="Insecta" family="Enicocephalidae" genus="Xenicocephalus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Xenicocephalus tomhenryi" order="Hemiptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="33" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tomhenryi">Xenicocephalus tomhenryi</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype, left foreleg, schemes, not measured. A apicitibial armature, antero-ventral view B apicitibial armature, ventral view C tarsal armature, ventral view, other macrotrichia omitted.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>