<document id="0DA4C3DDFE6530BC7C9A9477C4DDE85F" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="cb9064bf-69b5-45fb-9079-0d3c1ae939ea" ModsDocID="5834" checkinTime="1243376566889" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1946" docId="CBB7B9F331C6E0C8580CE0818527FE44" docLanguage="en" docName="5834" docOrigin="Proceedings of the Royal Entomological Society of London 15" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5834/5834.pdf" docTitle="Dodous trispinosus Donisthorpe, 1946, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="147" masterDocId="48CDA7FDE1A36C627B011C613BE6C2AE" masterDocTitle="A new genus and species of Formicidae (Hym.) from Mauritius." masterLastPageNumber="147" masterPageNumber="145" pageNumber="145" updateTime="1569525771843" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="FA33599EF8C035431A4CB94A74E19DB4" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="E073F95D68C551A27BCD41B24FA48AEB">
<mods:title id="232C390AB035E10CF8F2B82C82C6301F">A new genus and species of Formicidae (Hym.) from Mauritius.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="B21DB789D7F9B53A9F9B8C8202841BEA" type="personal">
<mods:role id="495E9B9609A61DE90A91651C5BA4DA36">
<mods:roleTerm id="737234C456BD11A3D6C7AC8441AFAE28">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="E469736C627384E6B0551AEC4BD36DBA">Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="B8FA16AFDE893367463AD71FD1AAC1F9">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="E66C917B4B2C229A797FB87BF300AE18" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="7A2C8BEF0D52C0C5832971DC4F9EFEEB">
<mods:title id="1B09D95E9BA4D61C360306A19E53CDEC">Proceedings of the Royal Entomological Society of London</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="821CA168B30893D154D8C6FC74B2B0CB">
<mods:date id="B42C6AC887DC517970856C92F1C2D19A">1946</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="93E3193464A7347DD6D1FDD7BA09B534" type="volume">
<mods:number id="1503D5F2C4EDA1EF5230859CD3326742">15</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="7281DB2F235B6FB8619A7427F731107F" unit="page">
<mods:start id="512BF4542264C9DAF8B64F3A93876F2E">145</mods:start>
<mods:end id="59EB358D5A6526DC3D6A144841A3B17A">147</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="4225510C766A5DCA908CADA63814DE85">
<mods:url id="833ED175D7D000437619D34FE7AD8201">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5834/5834.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="D3A6688856D7D6D42A14CBC1B9064129">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="BAFE1D954563C83202F36DF095724376" type="HNS-PUB">5834</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="CBB7B9F331C6E0C8580CE0818527FE44" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:CBB7B9F331C6E0C8580CE0818527FE44" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CBB7B9F331C6E0C8580CE0818527FE44">
<subSubSection id="E7BA1890AC2800F5E6014A24CF020AF4" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="CE8A320AE9AF66BB54D0452445DB1AB7" pageNumber="145">
<taxonomicName id="8CE501B6CE51E5C5C3455B62E51E846A" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:143662" authority="Donisthorpe" authorityName="Donisthorpe" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Dodous" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dodous trispinosus Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Dodous trispinosus Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="145" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trispinosus">Dodous trispinosus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="C46A782884A77D55BA5750900ADC6E12" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="E210383507CA945A1F939AFDE45BF290" type="description">
<paragraph id="AD2D3AE121D9721A5534E73E6099AEF7" pageNumber="145">[[ worker ]]. Light reddish or yellowish-brown, legs a little lighter, funiculi and gaster slightly darker; whole body furnished with short fine scattered outstanding yellow hairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2796028D3E3CCF33ECBADD1D35530C6E" pageNumber="145">Head round, slightly longer than broad, cheeks and posterior angles rounded, posterior border somewhat excised. Sculpture of head consisting of ridges which are straight down the centre, spreading out in semicircles on each side and round the antennal foveae, gradually becoming straighter towards the temples and base.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D9EE34C742B776FCB81264CC941E8097" lastPageNumber="146" pageNumber="145">Mandibles long, triangular, powerful, smooth and shining, masticatory border armed with 3 teeth at apex, the two apical ones long and pointed, the one preceding them short but sharp, a very short blunt tooth is present at basal angles; clypeus with anterior border projecting in centre, armed with 5 short teeth, the one in centre being most prominent, two small sharp teeth are present situated one on each side outside the projecting central portion, the basal portion is prolonged between the insertion of the antennae and carinae, extending from thence to the apex of the anterior teeth, the outer carina is continued to form the semicircular frontal carinae; frontal area wanting; antennal foveae large, deep, surrounded by circular carinae; eyes round, prominent, situated on the upper part of the sides of the head a little behind the centre; palpi short, maxillary palpi 1 - jointed; labial palpi 2 - jointed; antennae long, 11 - jointed, scape reaching base of pronotum, funiculus with all joints longer than broad, 1 st and 2 nd joints of about equal length, 3 rd to 5 th shorter, subequal, 6 th and 7 th a little longer, club 3 - jointed, well marked, last joint equal in length to the two preceding taken together. Thorax longer than broad, slightly contracted in middle, sculpture consisting of ridges which are coarser than those of the head, circular on the pronotum, enclosing the mesonotum, and along the sides and dorsal surface of the epinotum; pronotum with anterior angles rounded, armed on each side with a sharp curved spine; mesonotum circular, somewhat prominent, divided from the pronotum and epinotum by the interstice between two of the ridges, rugose in centre and armed on each side before base with a slightly curved spine, which is shorter and blunter than those of the pronotum; a rather deep furrow is present between the mesonotum and epinotum; epinotum armed with a pair of long sharp spines, joined together at base, projecting upwards, divergent and slightly curved downwards at apex, declivity behind the base of the spines transversely striate, and armed with two short sharp teeth at base. Petiole, post petiole and gaster smooth and shining; petiole long and narrow, furnished at apex with a node which is rounded above, and slightly broader than peduncle; post petiole rounded at sides and above, slightly broader than petiole, with a very short tooth or projection beneath pointing forwards; gaster round oval, first segment taking up the greater part of the gaster above. Legs long, femora and tibiae spindle-shaped. Length 4.5 - 5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="99EA5C76B029F93293692772A4530B39" lastPageNumber="147" pageNumber="146">[[ male ]]. Shining dark reddish-brown, legs and antennae somewhat lighter, clothed with more abundant outstanding hairs than in the [[ worker ]]. Head transverse, cheeks, posterior angles, and posterior border rounded; mandibles undeveloped, represented by very small round hairy bosses; clypeus transverse, convex, anterior border rounded; gradually becoming straighter towards the temples and base; frontal carinae very short, divergent; eyes large, very prominent, situated on each side of the head; ocelli moderate, anterior ocellus slightly larger than the other two, situated in a slight depression; antennae 12 - jointed, all joints longer than broad, scape short, only a little longer than 1 st joint of funiculus, all the other joints longer and of about equal length and breadth, except the last, which is longer and pointed, about equal in length to the two preceding taken together. Thorax broader in front than behind, broadest just before insertion of fore-wing; pronotum transverse and narrow anteriorly, broader at sides; scutum of mesonotum convex and prominent, rounded in front and at sides; mayrian furrows indistinct, marked by a few shallow punctures, the space between being also shallowly punctured; parapsidal furrows also somewhat indistinct; prae-scutellum transverse, very narrow in middle; scutellum convex, prominent; metanotum transverse, very narrow, with sharp raised edges at sides; epinotum with dorsal surface concave in middle, shorter than declivity, angle between dorsal surface well marked, declivity straight, flat. Petiole long, with two short blunt teeth, or projections, situated one on each side before node, which is round, but rather flat; post petiole rounded above and at sides, not or scarcely broader than node of petiole, a small tooth or projection is present beneath as in the [[ worker ]]; gaster long oval, broadest at apex of first segment, which takes up over half the dorsal surface of the gaster. Genitalia exserted in one of the specimens; the stipites are rather broad and bluntly pointed, the volsellae possess a broad lobe at the base on the outer side (dorsal view), the inner side consisting of long sharply pointed very thin sickle-shaped hooks; the sagittae are rather narrow slightly curved appendages, which, however, are not so thin nor so sharply pointed as the hooks of the volsellae.</paragraph>
<caption id="FC150B8FFC0203A6A7AD848F323F3F0A">
<paragraph id="191FD59BF9FD54868361F363C273AC52" pageNumber="146">
Fig. 1. — 
<taxonomicName id="B5C1965078284DB6E054E632D8CA0D92" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:143662" authority="Donisthorpe" authorityName="Donisthorpe" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Dodous" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dodous trispinosus Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Dodous trispinosus Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="146" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trispinosus">Dodous trispinosus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="BAA6A656A52740488B7BCEC11532BF14" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
[[ worker ]]. Fig. 2. — 
<taxonomicName id="64BE8732CC0C5F48A8D320BFF1EC85B1" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:143662" authority="Donisthorpe" authorityName="Donisthorpe" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Dodous" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Dodous trispinosus Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Dodous trispinosus Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="146" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="trispinosus">Dodous trispinosus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="34110E85C03A3B54EF2824FD8EE0B236" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
[[ worker ]] in profile. Fig. 3. — Male. Fig. 4. — Larva.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="F2875F01AAF5A8E5B48BA16FF96E1B02" pageNumber="147">Legs long and slender. Wings dusky and hairy; fore-wing with lower margin of apical half somewhat broadly lobate, pterostigma and veins brown, one fairly large cubital cell is present, no discoidal cell, and the fairly long, radial cell is open. Long. 4 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C341BD55BA83827EDCAE6A5803BA4D9C" pageNumber="147">Larva. Dirty yellowish-white (in spirit specimens), of the gourd-shaped type with a crooked neck. The head is prolonged into a beak (the mandibles, etc.); the whole body clothed with short outstanding hairs of different lengths and structure. (N. B. — The dark spot in the figure where the eye might be supposed to be is, of course, not an eye at all, as ant larvae never possess eyes.)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="2D625A39B3EB6CDC0FB67EDA0117C8B9" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="0EEEE9AD62BCC6E0C03FC15FF6D11A06" pageNumber="147">Described from a number of workers and two males, Cocotte Mt., Mauritius (R. Mamet). Type and [[ male ]] type in British Museum (Natural History). Mr. Mamet took 30 workers, two males, larvae, and pupae from a colony nesting under a flat stone on 27 th December 1941 (No. 26); and again in similar circumstances 40 workers, larvae, and pupae, on 6 th February 1943 (No. 6). He remarks: &quot; A curious species which when disturbed simulates death. &quot;</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>