<document id="110C7B4489049C6BEAB9EF52DEF373CC" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.97.741" ID-GBIF-Dataset="fba76003-5593-4218-834b-c1d921f2f826" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159365181" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-97-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3AB00DB0-9D69-4B29-A19D-D70212713323" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-97-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 97" ModsDocTitle="A remarkable new species of the sharpshooter genus Egidemia (Insecta, Hemiptera, Cicadellidae, Cicadellinae)" checkinTime="1451250443455" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Mejdalani, Gabriel &amp; Garcia, Claudia" docDate="2011" docId="CD37E85E3681B23C676114B397E1B95C" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 97: 1-10" docOrigin="ZooKeys 97" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.97.741" docTitle="Egidemia impudica Mejdalani &amp; Garcia, 2011, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="3AB00DB0-9D69-4B29-A19D-D70212713323" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="7" masterDocId="6F7AFFB3FFE86B67FFAB2A4BF664FFBC" masterDocTitle="A remarkable new species of the sharpshooter genus Egidemia (Insecta, Hemiptera, Cicadellidae, Cicadellinae)" masterLastPageNumber="10" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" updateTime="1643718231671" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="3DEF7ED9ECFA72D8A9A36FE798BDC8EC" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="B2AC176A3F9D27CBA76A2FD883EDBEBE">
<mods:title id="9280A3044CA45D25E556B7B12F614581">A remarkable new species of the sharpshooter genus Egidemia (Insecta, Hemiptera, Cicadellidae, Cicadellinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="1F288994FD4670D3682096C22A420F2E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9BE5E39CBB6B45AFB159B6AECBDFC658">
<mods:roleTerm id="9BB2E7772DDF11F39DAB30CD3C0CAB21">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="905CA6BB9F3268F1BCB6FFE7ED8AC65B">Mejdalani, Gabriel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="7E8CEC53EEDFF5DBCB53284B1C829F14" type="personal">
<mods:role id="AA9A10A4F785F25E0367F46ED1B476A4">
<mods:roleTerm id="0132E5261D7FAB279314F802DAD8927F">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C859D9C923F4CCB515129107C4377631">Garcia, Claudia</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="4D019AB51632F7A68792F88742C07547">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="C21C467AC6F81E7A3AB855F36718AF93" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="CE9A1D08AA02FAE1DF3D8DB045FD0175">
<mods:title id="0B00292C9300454E85DE02EDEED8D1EB">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="98C47BC2ECB05EDA23EAEA1F38BED5AA">
<mods:date id="502E2920AFEB054ACAD4FA78B8AD5A19">2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="7A142D9C88B5EEFAE93B887E5DA8DA52" type="volume">
<mods:number id="D01C7C197AC947E4469ACF4BFD7179DD">97</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="E6C6F79C920F93581702FE40CD9ABDF5" unit="page">
<mods:start id="536C9C8594FED74306C17A8DB31694E2">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="AB46655EB2EF93B6C2DCCFD72F0CAEB1">10</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="0B1AA926DCB0B3F5BB7A97C5A17CBA59">
<mods:url id="65A47D39B0264C0B5EC9C97464CE3CE7">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.97.741</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="CFC50B816C857C6B8F2B39445C02DA27">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="B87EB57D5A81D60C1A51360A404D1CAA" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.97.741</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B5134CE330B4C29A4994804474C0368A" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-97-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E85AB85856D599E280DF35847FE8C300" type="ZooBank">89D58892-EC1E-4C9F-AA41-984BFE5599B5</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="CD37E85E3681B23C676114B397E1B95C" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159365181" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3AB00DB0-9D69-4B29-A19D-D70212713323" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CD37E85E3681B23C676114B397E1B95C" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<subSubSection id="42B9AE8D0A9A7963376B59E0E131E176" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="2812845224C9AB1A35BFBA41128AD74B" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<taxonomicName id="74981044EFFB27AEC58934AA774EA4E2" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3AB00DB0-9D69-4B29-A19D-D70212713323" class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Egidemia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Egidemia impudica" order="Hemiptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="impudica">Egidemia impudica</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="E94BB52D52904BF79E948B52B0683E47" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 110
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="7587632DD25441F50E1023BAB4E3B2DE" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" type="description of the male holotype">
<paragraph id="A0303607AF17A67A3DE8B09C9A972D90" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Description of the male holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="413F9B903DC4A1B281C82FDB9FC04EA8" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Length, 11.5 mm (male paratype, 12 mm) including wings in repose. Head (Fig. 2), in dorsal view, well produced anteriorly; median length of crown approximately seven-tenths interocular width and four-tenths transocular width. Crown (Fig. 2), in dorsal view, with anterior margin broadly rounded; without carina at transition from crown to face; without median fovea; ocelli located slightly behind imaginary line between anterior angles of eyes, each ocellus closer to adjacent eye angle than to median line of crown; without longitudinal keel laterad of each ocellus; with broad M-shaped elevation bordering posterior margin; with pubescence; frontogenal sutures extending onto crown and approaching ocelli; coronal suture distinct. Antennal ledges (Fig. 2), in dorsal view, protuberant; in lateral view (Fig. 3), with dorsal carina, anterior margin strongly declivous and with concavity. Face (Fig. 3) pubescent, especially on inferior portions; frons convex, swollen, muscle impressions distinct, median portion granulate; epistomal suture incomplete medially; clypeus not produced, its contour continuing profile of frons.</paragraph>
<caption id="305E098525B0F10EA2EDC1C437BF94D7" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph id="ED874B32B3B8577AE11DB79DA23172F1" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Figure 1.Egidemia impudica sp. n. Male holotype (IAHC), body in dorsal view (antennae and legs not depicted, abdomen removed for dissection). Length, 11.5 mm.</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="EB94C42C7A9CBFE06013A5CAC1C58E7B" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Thorax (Fig. 2), in dorsal view, with pronotal width less than transocular width of head; pronotum with lateral margins slightly sinuous and slightly divergent anteriorly; pronotal surface rugose and punctate (except on anterior third) and pubescent; posterior margin distinctly concave; dorsopleural carinae (Fig. 3) complete, slightly arched downward anteriorly, strongly declivous posteriorly. Mesonotum (Fig. 2) with scutellum only very slightly striate. Forewings (Fig. 4) mostly hyaline with large sclerotized area extending mainly over outer discal cell, outer and median anteapical cells and adjacent portions of costal margin; veins elevated and distinct; claval veins fused through most of their length, separated only basally and apically; outer discal cell reduced, about half length of inner discal cell; with three closed anteapical cells (inner one broadened anteriorly) and four apical cells, base of fourth more proximal than base of third; without anteapical plexus of veins and without supernumerary anteapical cross veins to costal margin. Hindwings extending almost as far posteriorly as forewings; vein R2+3 incomplete. Hindleg with femoral setal formula (visible only on right leg of holotype) 2:1:1:1 (with additional, unaligned slender seta located anteriorly to the row of three setae; this additional seta absent in the male paratype); length of first tarsomere less than combined length of second and third ones; first tarsomere with two parallel rows of small setae on plantar surface.</paragraph>
<caption id="E1C4151EF5864F08065E868187BC0415" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
<paragraph id="C936CFAD21C9E1C112B23A1E8925CEAD" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Figures 2-4.Egidemia impudica sp. n. 2 crown, pronotum and mesonotum, dorsal view (the white circle on the mesonotum is the pin perforation) 3 anterior portion of body, lateral view 4 left forewing.</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="6B53266A44D5B46AECB4F1F992C5AE90" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<pageBreakToken id="A635C5E1535A30C3F63152E150BA2D4B" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">Color</pageBreakToken>
. Anterior dorsum (Figs 1-3) mostly brown. Crown with three maculae anteriorly (median one elongate), outer portion of antennal ledges, macula adjacent to inner eye margin, area around ocelli, and elongate macula from posterior margin to interocellar portion, pale yellow; inner portion of antennal ledges and pair of conspicuous maculae on posterior coronal margin, dark brown. Pronotum with irregular maculae on anterior third, five distinct, transversely aligned maculae on median third and pair of maculae on posterior third at lateral margins, pale yellow. Mesoscutum with median macula basally, pair of maculae basilaterally, and pair of irregular areas medially, pale 
<pageBreakToken id="CBF443B0AEA51F1C61CF5C205ED19B5D" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" start="start">yellow</pageBreakToken>
; mesoscutellum with pair of maculae basally and macula on apical portion, pale yellow. Forewings (Figs 1, 4) mostly translucent with brown veins; small brown area along basal portion of costal margin; distal half of costal margin, outer discal cell, outer anteapical cell, median anteapical cell, and part of inner anteapical cell brown (mostly darker than other wing portions); outer discal, outer anteapical, and median anteapical cell each with distinct orange macula; additional orange macula on costal area adjacent to anterior limit of outer anteapical cell; additional irregular yellow to orange marks also present in this area; apical cells brown. Body (Fig. 3), in lateral view, with broad yellow area extending from lateral portions of frons to posterior limit of thorax, bordered inferiorly by irregular brown marks. Face (Fig. 3) mostly pale yellow; muscle impressions and diffuse area on median portion of frons, brown to dark brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C1F9D0C12D2EB7D254316019568924C0" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Male genitalia with pygofer (Fig. 5), in lateral view, short, considerably reduced posteriorly, exposing aedeagal shaft; posterior margin obliquely truncate; ventroapical portion with conspicuous long process directed mesally; in caudal view (Fig. 7), processes crossing each other medially; pygofer surface with small setae distributed mostly ventrally and on posterior half. Valve (Fig. 8), in ventral view, with short lateral 
<pageBreakToken id="C5341B89A35A5222D48D9B76AFD5594A" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" start="start">margins</pageBreakToken>
; posterior margin distinctly produced posteriorly. Subgenital plates (Fig. 8), in ventral view, triangular, narrowing gradually toward apex; not fused to each other, close to each other for short distance on basal portion and then with distinct space between inner margins; surface with many scattered small setae; in lateral view (Fig. 5), plates extending beyond pygofer apex, with small dentiform projection associated with style apical portion. Connective (Fig. 9), in dorsal view, broadly Y-shaped with both arms and stalk short; with short median keel. Styles (Fig. 9), in dorsal view, elongate, extending posteriorly distinctly beyond apex of connective, portion before connective approximately of same size as portion behind it; apical portion directed posteriorly, not distinctly curved; apex obtuse. Aedeagus (Fig. 10) symmetrical; shaft, in lateral view, simple, directed dorsally, lobulate apically; dorsal and ventral margins sinuous; gonopore located on apex. Paraphyses absent. Anal tube (Figs 5, 6), in dorsal view, strongly developed in comparison to pygofer size; segment X (Fig. 5), in lateral 
<pageBreakToken id="F84F8F636171AD4F51B837EE8988C5D7" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" start="start">view</pageBreakToken>
, longer than dorsal pygofer margin, expanded toward apex; in dorsal view (Fig. 6), broad, distinctly rounded.
</paragraph>
<caption id="20D55E025BC7111EC0A5C79BAE7E7B54" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<paragraph id="384BFFEFF21FC2A6995985E56C6EA096" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Figures 5-10.Egidemia impudica sp. n., male genitalia 5 genital capsule, lateral view (arrow indicates the exposed aedeagus) 6 pygofer and anal tube, dorsal view (arrow indicates the expanded segment X of the anal tube) 7 pygofer, caudal view 8 valve and subgenital plates, ventral view 9 connective and right style, dorsal view 10 aedeagus, lateral view.</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B63C191F8B368A703751EB05117D6C04" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="female">
<paragraph id="B83AEE9D799148EF62615F162577221C" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Female</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6CD7DA4BDE73D64C04FB19BDB3CCF5C5" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="668869AF800AAA8254FD7B683B32E778" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="type specimens">
<paragraph id="BB8914DBC7D60AD4F3E16D1918000040" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Type specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="17AABA675E3BB993CB6993CE7E478584" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
Colombia, Magdalena Department. Male holotype (IAHC) with labels &quot;COLOMBIA Magdalena \ PNN Tayrona Zaino \ 
<geoCoordinate id="99D50F758D0CE5BC884AB35F713BF129" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="11.333333">
11
<normalizedToken id="5341DB9143288F175EC1A07BC60CC2CB" originalValue="º20’">°20'</normalizedToken>
N
</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate id="E280C7AD188575D4C06ABA5CBCF328AE" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="925" value="-74.03333">
74
<normalizedToken id="9D92E56A3BC03E57701E6ECC3294DF36" originalValue="º2’">°2'</normalizedToken>
W
</geoCoordinate>
50 m&quot; and &quot;Malaise 7/17/00-7/28/00 \ R. Henriquez, leg. M.299&quot;. Male paratype (MNRJ) with same data as holotype, excepting 
<normalizedToken id="BA967889DF92AEBC2435261C50331301" originalValue="“6/14/00-6/29/00”">&quot;6/14/00-6/29/00&quot;</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken id="38669F6AD53336A0ACEB1D0D15FA66F7" originalValue="“M.240”">&quot;M.240&quot;</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="F10963072CD053CCF014657CA04645BE" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="31858AC8E56607BFAE8B2AED050BAB56" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="90EBA1C540FBDAE938D0DA24F76D5821" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">The new species name, impudica, refers to the distinctly reduced male pygofer, which results in the partial exposure of the aedeagus.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>