<document id="041F3DF15E32CB66F8D6499E9967F346" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c990e4df-7ee4-4898-96ff-c96f45456873" ModsDocID="5831" checkinTime="1243376545748" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1946" docId="CF6B960227DFF6B584EB523F38E1B7EA" docLanguage="en" docName="5831" docOrigin="Annals and Magazine of Natural History 12" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5831/5831.pdf" docTitle="Solenopsis mameti Donisthorpe, 1946, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="778" masterDocId="8D8AC18485F43A7290ED28CAFA476F2F" masterDocTitle="New species of ants (Hym., Formicidae) from the island of Mauritius." masterLastPageNumber="782" masterPageNumber="776" pageNumber="777" updateTime="1569525771911" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="8CF1D88A0E69F99A7B6E9DC6F20B6192" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="652BA77A0189A8EF8193B6D0F6DE27A8">
<mods:title id="DC9476F0D291C09263D332C7C6F7D35D">New species of ants (Hym., Formicidae) from the island of Mauritius.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="0D18114B9CB1DC2A76045BE663697CEC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="707D25A2CAEBC83E5FD271C1ADA2DA62">
<mods:roleTerm id="E3E03D97BDA906F44CF03E034EBAF5B1">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="36EFC3CF9E0A9008DCA66CC67ABED403">Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="EEE782FFA5BE41EF7D2AA8616022233F">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="E8530F2BB52FC206B777A942C62D2101" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="55F6750D67C3813D521CA2BF249CB6CA">
<mods:title id="8299E216C52AAC0B0BC2CE7436A1BB51">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="9EA57D2F4C6685007198C00952A051C2">
<mods:date id="3E1C8B75EA9D5E149BD5B088855BDDCD">1946</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="606C999C292E901F1DB37E1AEB476BD5" type="volume">
<mods:number id="61EF853FD3EE5754613A56C53370B85A">12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="D94127B91621CFDF59846D1A9C7007BE" unit="page">
<mods:start id="66026A793C2C64EA4C3F44599D6962F0">776</mods:start>
<mods:end id="841FC641AC19CAFD2439A7FC01A07DCA">782</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="EA350E34A094CC802C697042D2EDBB6A">
<mods:url id="2C6134D1F58AED7CFBF217111D087188">http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5831/5831.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="16E6BFC50CCD9F615E7629D6E18C0205">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="3FDD55864F69FCF4D30C08BD843EF9F1" type="HNS-PUB">5831</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="CF6B960227DFF6B584EB523F38E1B7EA" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:CF6B960227DFF6B584EB523F38E1B7EA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CF6B960227DFF6B584EB523F38E1B7EA">
<subSubSection id="D27BEF6C576E382171FFF3A39015B085" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="C974D8FA87A21C0E2F08BC31FEE39905" pageNumber="777">
<taxonomicName id="D7EE8EC95DCFE32FBC806907988BF7B3" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:36308" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Solenopsis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Solenopsis mameti Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Solenopsis mameti Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="777" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mameti">Solenopsis mameti</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="F4A21D0B3398F25BC1B4EEC9EE22EF8A" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AA00CA0EB2E6CF55048851250CF92ECA" type="description">
<paragraph id="662BE1B2F98FD6DACCA6C5E32FCD8395" pageNumber="777">[[ worker ]]. Dark yellowish brown, legs and antennae lighter, gaster a little darker, very smooth and shining, whole body furnished with sparse, longer and shorter, yellow, outstanding hairs, more abundant on gaster.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D8E5D5BD1B0B082CDF03D94DFF8C9AEC" pageNumber="777">Head subquadrate, slightly broader in front than behind, broadest about centre, posterior angles rounded, posterior border almost straight; mandibles rather long, narrow, masticatory border armed with three teeth, the apical one longest and sharpest, the two at the base shorter and blunter; clypeus narrow, triangular, bicarinate, the carinae ending at anterior border in two small teeth, posterior border bluntly pointed, extending between frontal carinae; frontal carinae short, flat, not wide apart, slightly divergent posteriorly; antennas 10 - jointed, scape not reaching posterior border of head, funiculus with first joint longer and broader than the following short six joints, last two joints forming a large club considerably longer and broader than all those preceding, last joint pointed at apex, considerably longer, but as broad as the preceding one; eyes small, flat, situated at sides in front of middle of head. Thorax narrow, longer than broad, narrower than head, broadest in middle of pro-mesonotum; prosternum forming a neck, no suture between pro- and mesonotum; promesonotum oval, convex, rounded in front and at sides; meso-epinotal suture well marked; epinotum convex on dorsal surface, angle between dorsal surface and declivity rounded, dorsal surface longer than declivity, declivity concave. Petiole with a high node, rounded above, pointed in profile; post-petiole slightly transverse, broader than node of petiole, rounded above, in front, and at sides; gaster oblong oval, truncate at base.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F0A0482EB95E51A274BA747796D4D614" pageNumber="777">Long. 1.8 - 2 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="9B7D81D03967B85416A0B427FD5CFD93" lastPageNumber="778" pageNumber="777">[[ queen ]]. Colour the same as in the worker, but considerably larger in size; outstanding hairs more abundant. Head longer in proportion; mandibles with longer and sharper teeth; clypeus as in [[ worker ]]; antennae 11 - jointed, otherwise similar in construction to [[ worker ]]; eyes large and much more prominent; ocelli present. Thorax long, narrow, dorsal surface rather flat; promesonotum rounded in front, considerably longer than broad, finely but not closely punctured; praescutellum narrow, transverse; scutellum short, round oval, smooth and shining; metanotum narrow, transverse, slightly raised; epinotum smooth and hining, dorsal surface flat, longer than declivity, with a very blunt tubercle at each side of angle between it and declivity, declivity concave; petiole with rather high node, rounded above, pointed in profile, posterior surface slightly convex; post-petiole transverse, rounded above and at sides, broader than node of petiole, anterior surface concave, posterior surface convex, a small, short, pointed tooth is present on under side; gaster long oval, pointed at apex, rather deeply excised at junction with postpetiole.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="66EFE201963547018CDB987AC0E9618D" pageNumber="778">Long. 3.5 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="6FD5EBCEABF516DD334B37290871D74F" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="1D0608F9D98447F152E28FF2B24907D6" pageNumber="778">Described from 54 workers, and three dealated females taken by R. Mamet on Corps de Garde Mt., Mauritius, December 26, 1945. The colony was nesting under a stone in a shady place. Larvae were present, and also four specimens of a Bethylid.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="34BC05DC56EB51D9BD99D7CBD609378C" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="A18D5AD1F73FD71717545A58E7CD2B86" pageNumber="778">Type in B. M. Coll.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>