<document id="B63EF7B5F12BF74792BEA91924A89F61" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280257" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120190" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280257" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="D9E7A9A1FC61836509F335DCE89F788A" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys livens Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="688" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="688" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="56B6164092CA5826651047279E411769" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="535A0F1E8F3AB1222CA51107B9CF3EB9">
<mods:title id="D80A0085ED4D456910F3202A15840669">The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="3C1B647824D49380BEA865550E99F50E" type="personal">
<mods:role id="2BF8F28EFC0A94FC150CE35EABA508A8">
<mods:roleTerm id="681E3AE07C1AFC2AC093FF79D71FFC1F">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="EEAA9EBE580F17A15D0D6B953C15B148">Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="A02348267C7F9495C501F63C2570502A">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="E807AB5FE9BA99E05B1646176449288B" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="87A643C8DFA0619EAB1DB3F079E53DFE">
<mods:title id="513167D882CB12632315F46A6B657430">Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="96489433654EB0C178E6716B9AAED625">
<mods:date id="72931B4DA9C79F53AB946F17D4EA0F1D">2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="322CF891767BFE264B8E12DC5F1C04A4" type="volume">
<mods:number id="B1F8421F51C24DAB2BB7728735612B71">65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="A87A30FF02FB861DFA024E2660AA0624" unit="page">
<mods:start id="F0BEADB6EDEBE7A604719C886DBC6114">1</mods:start>
<mods:end id="A20222FFDC931B5224DC779A737F1928">1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="7038BF455A79495254AE763718778454">
<mods:url id="AACB800A47F821B461F8475F6E6957CA">http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="E908F795760DF0B6AA4C4612FFF89349">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="319E5C4176E7D98E4F868D71A2DC5331" type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="7E4927464C374EC5DCE6D12D82E26C3F" type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="D9E7A9A1FC61836509F335DCE89F788A" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280257" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120190" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280257" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:D9E7A9A1FC61836509F335DCE89F788A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D9E7A9A1FC61836509F335DCE89F788A" lastPageNumber="688" pageNumber="688">
<subSubSection id="015C6419C7DD4432A4E0775D893BBC9B" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="D2D0976358F197B5B43CD6A3B293EECC" pageNumber="688">
Strumigenys 
<taxonomicName id="F1BE6B9BC3A18E82CB389B3D77B493E8" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155867" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys livens Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys livens Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="688" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="livens">livens</taxonomicName>
Fisher 
<taxonomicNameLabel id="8E38287F8B76D383FD2A9036EA7BFB4A" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="0A9202AF6FAA2F432AF02C6707B4D5DD" type="description">
<paragraph id="802E8924837E3A85F6996DA3437D7EA9" pageNumber="688">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 2.4, HL 0.57, HW 0.45, CI 79, ML 0.31, MI 54, SL 0.37, SI 83, PW 0.27, AL 0.60. Characters of scotti-complex. Mandibles in full-face view with outer margins very shallowly and evenly convex, width approximately constant from the level of the proximal preapical tooth to near the base. Upper scrobe margin shallowly concave immediately behind the frontal lobe, posteriorly evenly and shallowly convex in full-face view, not bordered by a rim or flange except immediately behind the frontal lobes, the eyes visible. Maximum diameter of eye approximately equal to or slightly greater than maximum width of scape, with 5 - 6 ommatidia in longest row. Scape subcylindrical, curved and narrowed near the base; hairs on leading edge of scape slender, slightly flattened or spoon-shaped apically. Cephalic dorsum densely clothed with short, slender filiform ground-pilosity. The upper scrobe margin fringed with hairs which are more sharply curved but otherwise similar in shape and size as those on the leading edge of the scape. Cephalic dorsum with 6 standing filiform hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate; humeral angles bluntly marginate. Mesonotum with a pair of standing filiform to narrowly remiform hairs on anterior margin, a shorter more posteriorly situated pair of erect filiform hairs, and with an even shorter pair of erect fine hairs on posterior margin. Propodeum with one pair of short, fine, posteriorly curved hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Dorsal alitrunk with inconspicuous, sparse, appressed fine groundpilosity. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and posteriorly gently sloping to the declivity. Metanotal groove shallowly impressed. Anterior mesonotum with a thin carina above a narrow mesothoracic spiracle; mesopleural gland set in a small circular notch. Propodeal tooth triangular, pointed apically, and subtended by a very narrow lamella. Pronotal dorsum longitudinally rugulose-striolate; mesonotal and propodeal dorsa reticulate-punctate. Sides of alitrunk glassy smooth. Postpetiole disc more or less smooth, faintly longitudinally striolate. In profile ventral spongiform tissue of petiolar peduncle a narrow irregular strip along the base of the peduncle, usually widest in the posterior third, the deepest point in the anterior two-thirds less than or approximately equal to the maximum width of eye. Ventral spongiform tissue of postpetiole moderately developed. Basigastral costulae short and sharply defined, radiating on each side of a broad central clear area. Petiolar disc with two pairs of filiform hairs, postpetiole with three pairs of erects hairs of similar length, dorsal surface of gaster with standing filiform hairs which are slightly thickened apically. Colour light brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3992B3EA960C6AF3EEB852D586840460" pageNumber="688">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 2.2 - 2.6, HL 0.51 - 0.60, HW 0.42 - 0.47, CI 77 - 82, ML 0.28 - 0.33, MI 53 - 56, SL 0.35 - 0.40, SI 82 - 86, PW 0.23 - 0.30, AL 0.56 - 0.65 (6 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="8E0FA7ADE25045BBACC9BEF67E98A9D8" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="514DFD8B35C216CC707339F7684BACF5" pageNumber="688">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 40 km. S Ambalavao, Res. Andringitra, 22 Â° 13 ' S, 46 Â° 58 ' E, 1275 m., 15. x. 1993, sifted litter (leaf mold rotten wood), montane rainforest # 793 (4) - 9 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ). Paratypes. 7 workers and 2 queens (dealate) with same data as holotype but coded (7) - 7, (8) - 10, (9) - 10, (10) - 11, (20) - 9, (34) - 9 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0E3768E96AB65A0AF5271B5725C239EC" pageNumber="688">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: 40 km. S Ambalavao, Res. Andringitra 1275 m. (B. L. Fisher); 8.0 km. NE Ivohibe, 1200 m. (S. Razafimandimby); 6.5 km. ESE Ivohibe, R. S. Ivohibe, 1575 m. (5. Razafimandimby).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1D5D32AD239FF14E4B32D3516BC7C42B" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="D71B5EDC87F77DC0F5EE6F4C729D4426" pageNumber="688">
S. 
<taxonomicName id="4D9F1C8A520AF751C8F0154E447EE336" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155867" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys livens Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys livens Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="688" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="livens">livens</taxonomicName>
is closely related to lexex; see under the latter for discussion of distinguishing characters.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>