<document id="A697BA65A8FA291BDE5173F5358915CC" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472" ID-GBIF-Dataset="64686cef-cf34-47d6-9cf4-3bd4e0dc9160" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152049023" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-345-73" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E349C77C-E5BB-4A7E-B1E0-3BF3B2AB5D88" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-345-73" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 345" ModsDocTitle="The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)" checkinTime="1451246762417" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Belokobylskij, Sergey A., Tang, Pu &amp; Chen, Xue-xin" docDate="2013" docId="E5D9BE6C52812E25AFE28AE55A495510" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 345: 73-96" docOrigin="ZooKeys 345" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472" docTitle="Ontsira rugivertex Belokobylskij, Tang &amp; Chen, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="E349C77C-E5BB-4A7E-B1E0-3BF3B2AB5D88" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="90" masterDocId="FF94FFF6852CFFA9582EFF9DAB3CFF96" masterDocTitle="The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)" masterLastPageNumber="96" masterPageNumber="73" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" updateTime="1643696211464" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="5D6F1D3714C87FA0DA49A606D6FE5726" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="43A760F179375766C4302A4C77B1B96C">
<mods:title id="D7AB88861779EAC3027DBC6E649EB05E">The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="FD0F9922795CBF3C9595DDECD10278B5" type="personal">
<mods:role id="180EF6920579C71DB68AFE9B625E6E8C">
<mods:roleTerm id="F582CEFC2ED8587307B5E41DAF4A170D">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C395499BE5F5DB502E09648757586043">Belokobylskij, Sergey A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="BE18622077BBB7741DD12DF657436DD4" type="personal">
<mods:role id="A645422FC8E8D2FFD833F4E67F3555D6">
<mods:roleTerm id="6D1932F28D3CB5522A3D90DCDED10365">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="07D8FEF5041B636590650439F03C8ABF">Tang, Pu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="51F193B9EB7C5762B1ABEF214D5C783B" type="personal">
<mods:role id="1772112C67562867E2B7FF033D5A2AAC">
<mods:roleTerm id="8B47752E432E1181DEABEE1BE4F33C27">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="28ABFADA8C61F68C0C240FAF16389DB0">Chen, Xue-xin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="697ECF5D9EF6AB97E73A6084C22896F9">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="34B253370D9F63745067DAC957DE4019" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="3494ACC3263DBE3574B89A2111A7F5D9">
<mods:title id="3983C667381155EED106F1AAD2FB4569">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="07BC0A64CF1DA0452C907BE9C3C8686C">
<mods:date id="195508058C079DE0522B6507205C3CF3">2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="3E990A72E9B715C4D55D76FBE14DE095" type="volume">
<mods:number id="1D8971FDE35A72972E35A7DA16EBAE59">345</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="37CD5D05C0717E9F95655B767B1809F6" unit="page">
<mods:start id="A2E309FA79DF5E0BE82E4EE14C4439B6">73</mods:start>
<mods:end id="A822921253B168E30D8FB8ADD80F8A87">96</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="DA119937380666BDE2F8D4FB6397C128">
<mods:url id="07C470C7485FF576B2A9EBB72622EF21">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="05B8902035C6CC663CB735CC82F807EB">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C520EB59C9D8EFFA8C92A7EF8F4B018A" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="DCA456AA999B39436D5C10B94A538FE8" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-345-73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="672C6F439CDDADE81A327A1E0F8FD6A8" type="ZooBank">5F4F3D22-2655-4E1B-A9D2-714D9E6F5991</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="E5D9BE6C52812E25AFE28AE55A495510" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152049023" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E349C77C-E5BB-4A7E-B1E0-3BF3B2AB5D88" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E5D9BE6C52812E25AFE28AE55A495510" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">
<subSubSection id="E2450F70F5E032B0010D61D211FD4501" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="5C228083DFCB5BCEDAF6622D864E7000" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">
<taxonomicName id="7D95AEED013B3D67E5F5FC26A29CEB8A" LSID="http://zoobank.org/E349C77C-E5BB-4A7E-B1E0-3BF3B2AB5D88" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira rugivertex" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugivertex">Ontsira rugivertex</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="16244157C2D6878FED3F90CC4CDFFB6D" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Fig. 4
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="AADF4E172A16556B6F13E36FB6B3930D" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" type="type material">
<paragraph id="1A17279509759134E42AF58B2E57142B" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5ACB4AD8462582651D20A40D775B6D7E" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Holotype: female, China, Henan, Neixiang, 14.VII.1998 (Chen Xuexin), N 988629 (ZJUH).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="609AB0CAFFFF3A2C9E1CC1764357D515" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Paratype. China: 1 female, Shaanxi, Zhouzhi, Houzhenzi, 13.VI.1998 (Ma Yun), N 981419 (ZJUH).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C72D826C61A967D80A02B153C36F6EAC" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="7A647AD904AC645CECCB1810D844779B" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F0241420CE8761E31A1C5C15655B8558" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">
After Latin 
<normalizedToken id="C4EC3D3FA212A3543C4DCC8A41619285" originalValue="“rugae”">&quot;rugae&quot;</normalizedToken>
meaning 
<normalizedToken id="60079DA3245133FED9DEB52D733EB2B1" originalValue="“wringle”">&quot;wringle&quot;</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken id="99CDB6FF61A094A9C1A48E492B922AAF" originalValue="“vertex”">&quot;vertex&quot;</normalizedToken>
meaning &quot;vertex, top&quot; because of the vertex almost entirely and coarsely undulately striate.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="C8EEDBEF6BA9EC7A150AF5448CFBA385" lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="90" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" type="description">
<paragraph id="EC168D17CD6F28D03614C7BDD9785E9C" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="74BDCADE50047E058453070198FC0828" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Female. Body length 5.5-7.0 mm; fore wing length 5.0-6.2 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="04799B276D47979176DC5E63F0B8C198" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="14" pageNumber="87">
Head width 1.2-1.3 times as long as its median length, 1.1 times as long as width of mesoscutum. Frons without carina, with shallow or very shallow median furrow. 
<pageBreakToken id="50AFFC732194EC3E13535BD06C931AA2" pageId="15" pageNumber="88" start="start">Head</pageBreakToken>
behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex anteriorly, roundly narrowed posteriorly; transverse diameter of eye 1.0-1.1 times as long as temple. Ocellar triangle situated distinctly behind middle of head (dorsal view), its anterior ocellus situated behind middle level of eyes. Ocelli medium-sized, in triangle with base 1.2-1.3 times as long as its sides. POL 1.0-1.2 times Od, 0.35-0.40 times OOL. Eye rather densely and shortly setose, with shallow or very shallow emargination opposite antennal sockets, 1.3 times as high as broad. Face along eyes without distinct carinae, with distinct small shallow elongate depressions above clypeus; width of face 1.2 times as long as height of eye and 1.20-1.25 times as long as height of face and clypeus combined. Diameter of antennal socket 1.0-1.3 times as long as distance between sockets and 1.5-1.7 times as long as distance between socket and eye. Malar suture indistinct. Malar space 0.45-0.50 times as long as height of eye and 0.8-0.9 times as long as basal width of mandible. Clypeus with wide flange ventrally. Clypeal suture distinct and complete. Hypoclypeal depression round, its width almost equal to distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.45 times as long as width of face. Occipital carina ventrall fused with hypostomal carina at upper base of mandible. Maxillary palpi long, 1.3-1.4 times as long as head height.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FFA334AE679137361EBA59E9104B5038" pageId="15" pageNumber="88">Antennae rather thick, almost filiform, 37-43-segmented, almost as long as body. Scape 1.8-2.0 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment 3.6-3.8 times as long as its apical width, 1.2-1.3 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 2.0-2.2 times as long as wide, 0.4 times as long as first flagellar segment, 0.7 times as long as apical segment; the apical segment distinctly pointed apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2A3FB5D56FE39023556E66712F037917" pageId="15" pageNumber="88">Mesosoma. Length 1.8-1.9 times as long as high. Pronotum not convex dorsally (lateral view), with fine pronotal carina in posterior 0.4. Median lobe of mesoscutum (dorsal view) rather distinctly protruding forward, without or with shallow median furrow. Notauli deep, wide, densely coarsely crenulate and partly with rugosity. Prescutellar depression rather deep, without median carina, with several striae, coarsely rugose entirely, about 0.5 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum convex, without lateral carinae. Metanotum (dorsal view) with two strongly convergent and fused posteriorly lateral carinae, without median carinae; with short and obtuse metanotal tooth. Subalar depression shallow, wide, coarsely rugose-reticulate. Sternaulus deep, almost straight, densely and coarsely crenulate, connected with prepectal carina anteriorly, running along anterior 0.60-0.65 of the lower part of mesopleuron. Metapleural flange rather short, wide, rounded apically. Propodeum with distinct, short, thick lateral tubercles.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="178AB57079DA0F69DF58E2138E4F2CE4" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="89" pageId="15" pageNumber="88">
Wings. Fore wing 3.4 times as long as its maximum width. Radial vein arising weakly behind or from middle of pterostigma. Radial cell not shortened; metacarp 1.3-1.4 times as long as pterostigma. First radial abscissa 0.6-0.7 times as long as maximum width of pterostigma. Second radial abscissa 3.5-3.7 times as long as first abscissa, 0.5-0.6 times as long as the straight third abscissa, 1.3-1.5 times as long as first radiomedial vein. Second radiomedial cell 2.2 times as long as maximum width, 1.1-1.2 times as long as brachial cell. First medial abscissa almost straight. Mediocubital vein not curved. Recurrent vein 2.5-3.0 times as long as second abscissa of medial vein. Distance from nervulus to basal vein 0.4-1.0 times as long as nervulus. Parallel 
<pageBreakToken id="06D4D3DC72192B697552D67599AD72E5" pageId="16" pageNumber="89" start="start">vein</pageBreakToken>
arising from posterior 0.15-0.25 of distal margin of brachial cell. Hind wing 4.5-4.8 times as long as its maximum width. First costal abscissa 0.7 times as long as second abscissa. First abscissa of mediocubital vein 1.2-1.5 times as long as second abscissa. Radial cell weakly narrowed posteriorly. Mediocubital cell large, distinctly widened toward apex, about 6.5 times as long as wide, 0.40-0.45 times as long as whole length of wing. Recurrent vein weakly and evenly curved, interstitial, sclerotized.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1D97706EBC223BE7ECC53FA4AB750541" pageId="16" pageNumber="89">Legs. Fore tibia with rather numerous slender spines arranged in narrow stripe. Hind coxa without dorsal tooth, 1.6 times as long as wide. Hind femur 4.5 times as long as wide. Hind tarsus equal to hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.70-0.75 times as long as second-fifth segments combined. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.5 times as long as basitarsus, 1.6-1.8 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="CE0B876ACBE6D0751E77C5D5B03E35E4" pageId="16" pageNumber="89">Metasoma 1.1 times as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite with large dorsope, with small spiracular tubercles in basal quarter, rather weakly and almost linearly widened from base to apex. Maximum width of first tergite about twice as long as its minimum width; length 1.3-1.4 times as long as its apical width. Second tergite without basomedian area, 0.75-0.80 times as long as its basal width, 1.2 times as long as third tergite. Second suture straight, very shallow, almost absent medially. Third tergite without transverse furrow. Ovipositor sheath 1.1-1.2 times as long as body, 2.1-2.4 times as long as metasoma, 3.1-3.4 times as long as mesosoma, 1.2-1.4 times as long as fore wing.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4B6C36C47442C6FD5D88A475A9B001E7" pageId="16" pageNumber="89">Sculpture and pubescence. Vertex entirely or mostly more or less coarsely undulately striate, almost smooth near ocellar triangle; frons entirely coarsely rugose-reticulate; face distinctly and rather densely transverse striate, rugose medially, almost smooth below; temple coarsely rugose in upper 0.20-0.25, smooth on remaining part. Sides of pronotum entirely coarsely rugose-striate. Mesoscutum densely and distinctly rugose with dense fine granulation between rugae, coarsely and sparsely rugose in medioposterior half. Scutellum rather densely punctate, sometimes with very fine granulation between punctulae. Mesopleuron coarsely rugose-striate, rather narrowly smooth medially. Propodeum with distinctly delineated by carinae areas; basolateral areas large, entirely coarsely rugose-areolate; areola short and rather narrow, 1.4-1.5 times as long as wide; dorsal carina rather long, about twice as long as areola fork. Hind coxae almost entirely rugose-striate, partly with fine granulation, sculpture below fine. Hind femur dorsally and laterally rugose with fine granulation, almost smooth ventrally. First tergite densely, coarsely and linearly striate with fine rugulosity between striae. Second tergite densely striate in basal 0.3. Remaining tergites smooth. Vertex with rather dense, short and semi-erect setae; mesoscutum entirely with dense, short and semi-erect pale setae. Hind tibia dorsally with short, very dense and semi-erect setae, length of these setae about 0.5 times as long as maximum width of hind tibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="E0FC46C80F6D4F58F3B0BB90D5D7209B" pageId="16" pageNumber="89">Colour. Body black; metasoma medially or behind first tergite reddish brown. Antennae black, dark reddish brown basally. Palpi pale yellow. Legs light reddish brown, all coxae, trochanters and tibiae basally yellow, the remaining tibiae and tarsi sometimes reddish brown to dark reddish brown. Ovipositor sheath black. Fore wing membrane faintly infuscate. Pterostigma brown, shortly paler basally and apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="40AE537FE65F48FE57A4088F7FDA1B1D" pageId="17" pageNumber="90">
<pageBreakToken id="1E8B73FE7C2AA7C712B50342BF36B980" pageId="17" pageNumber="90" start="start">Male</pageBreakToken>
unknown.
</paragraph>
<caption id="ADCE7C78A24ACCC18AA49C47AA605291" pageId="17" pageNumber="90">
<paragraph id="D4AD382F7AE2001724A7D9BFC1E3CB29" pageId="17" pageNumber="90">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="2BD83831CDF2791576A54F5898EE5215" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira rugivertex" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugivertex">Ontsira rugivertex</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (female). A habitus, dorsal view B head, dorsal view C mesosoma, dorsal view D head, front view E fore and hind wings F mesosoma, dorsal view G basal segments of antenna H metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bar 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="1EB113F05685A1347BA2EEAD00572591" pageId="17" pageNumber="90" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="C13538A9ECC97F430061ECFA3915EF57" pageId="17" pageNumber="90">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3092A4A3B222779FBD3FBB20F3278448" pageId="17" pageNumber="90">China (Henan, Shaanxi).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="937D2B3DA430CE81D2374D011DF9149B" pageId="17" pageNumber="90" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="0F361ED43BC899639A252D30CF3019B2" pageId="17" pageNumber="90">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="463C7D7DFCE10C700A3619F1C4F98E75" pageId="17" pageNumber="90">
The new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName id="35C0FD8F1C765114128F289548BE3F44" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira ignea" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ignea">Ontsira ignea</taxonomicName>
Ratzeburg, but differs in having the vertex coarsely rugose-striate entirely or almost entirely, the first flagellar segment shorter, the second tarsal segment of hind leg distinctly longer than fifth segment (without pretarsus), and the mesoscutum coarsely rugose-granulate.It resembles 
<taxonomicName id="86BE9707A1595295B527AC1D77583E83" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira robusta" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robusta">Ontsira robusta</taxonomicName>
sp. n., but their differences are listed after the description of 
<taxonomicName id="A7D766BBA5002DC8C7D65C4233B5CAB5" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira robusta" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="17" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robusta">Ontsira robusta</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>