<document id="707893292980196B98ECC42AAF5DDEB9" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6250515" ID-GBIF-Dataset="93c110f2-57ec-48b7-9cab-df15d6408462" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134226" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6250515" ModsDocAuthor="Yoshimura, M. &amp; Onoyama, K." ModsDocDate="2007" ModsDocID="21296" ModsDocOrigin="http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=21296" ModsDocTitle="A new sibling species of the genus Strumigenys, with a redefinition of S. lewisi Cameron." checkinTime="1243372343105" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Yoshimura, M. &amp; Onoyama, K." docDate="2007" docId="EE12E1773ADBE4C45CFEDBDCA304F793" docLanguage="en" docName="21296" docOrigin="Advances in ant systematics (Hymenoptera: Formicidae): Homage to E. O. Wilson - 50 years of contributions. (Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 80)" docSource="http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=21296" docTitle="Strumigenys lewisi Cameron" docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageNumber="673" masterDocId="E4BFFF33191432E45A6BCE8A3B0CCD6A" masterDocTitle="A new sibling species of the genus Strumigenys, with a redefinition of S. lewisi Cameron." masterLastPageNumber="690" masterPageNumber="664" pageNumber="671" updateTime="1645651769775" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="F0256601C5BC993B6C8F4A3F22C92A39" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="CCB73C4E012BF42D88E5308DC410D8CF">
<mods:title id="C5B06DA9838351827DD4EF6CF5178827">A new sibling species of the genus Strumigenys, with a redefinition of S. lewisi Cameron.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="9F6EE008D976CAAEDE6DF73373918583" type="personal">
<mods:role id="921C2CF567E5EE601032563F9370E4EC">
<mods:roleTerm id="4538CE9044B11FCDC6051A74F6A31D6C">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="7772A876956B038691D5C1E049701D06">Yoshimura, M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="17050A15683282155943F0718ECB20DC" type="personal">
<mods:role id="24531668C26AA8B2BA9F657B230342CD">
<mods:roleTerm id="633BF7B2558CFF51EBB9D58921339369">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="8B0E67EFEA3B7617499C720CD63C1427">Onoyama, K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="1DE0A6982F201695621685450BF062C9">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="FBAA22A3E133A3E24B98DD129A5D7939" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="67EF884EC16935C85BED28F4A95FECF5">
<mods:title id="E86DA51773996EA8B7C0363C53B75715">Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="CB54073E6BF312E734FE5ACE9A567D3A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="F072D53C0EF37D0451759B9CEEBED87C">
<mods:roleTerm id="ADDD005EF50F12CBB14589DCA4AC9C79">Editor</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2A498331010187F62C2887DAC1CEB4DC">Snelling, R. R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="BE4FCDB67966145D2E749AD93C74FB1A" type="personal">
<mods:role id="37BC06DDD7FFA858AE680EFA366786F9">
<mods:roleTerm id="2045E8EF71DB264EB23A10D84966EA1F">Editor</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="35BAE835ECFF75AD12F27BA6B8EDE3B4">Fisher, B. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="93DC00847EC0DC0243FBE478733A80FB" type="personal">
<mods:role id="B00DCC85678E388392F3863B0DE9F502">
<mods:roleTerm id="26B2634899226D253D3C843CB63660E7">Editor</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="A198E9468E3DE51B6250754CF5F6F095">Ward, P. S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:part id="E7D56BAC16127FE331B32CFF424C5B8E">
<mods:date id="59AFAE24B99DE5AE832E1FFDDCC57132">2007</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="91DBF950844B32D3E3CDE0219AD0B32F" type="title">
<mods:title id="0C5D44DA20D8549705664DF31936F95C">Advances in ant systematics (Hymenoptera: Formicidae): Homage to E. O. Wilson - 50 years of contributions.</mods:title>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="155B3C8280527794BAFEDEB156ED0DA6" type="volume">
<mods:number id="CB8F69FF693D5172AF3FB178768E49B6">80</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="74D6D23408E7BB3D5A97FA6655C952A4" unit="page">
<mods:start id="5964879D498B5E26CC2445979A544ACA">664</mods:start>
<mods:end id="CA792A2561B24650602480380E7E00A8">690</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="AE75DD43A33B1108729D01B40BADCA12">
<mods:url id="210DF87D3B7C808EE0982774951D7CAA">http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=21296</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="F0BCAAE7888596B4B62DFFBE7B3B47E4">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="658C78C1D408A76990E50FC431833490" type="HNS-PUB">21296</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="EE12E1773ADBE4C45CFEDBDCA304F793" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6250515" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134226" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6250515" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:EE12E1773ADBE4C45CFEDBDCA304F793" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EE12E1773ADBE4C45CFEDBDCA304F793" lastPageNumber="673" pageNumber="671">
<subSubSection id="800823B3563678F356FB13AE7C0B9A24" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="5CA2E30109F2365B67E04C3C895A16F9" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="09F7D60327972E47A4F79334CE7E89F2" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:36635" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys lewisi Cameron" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lewisi">Strumigenys lewisi Cameron</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FA086430C06FEA0910680B9DEB4150B9" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="DEF852B12C784449F773770AF686E410" pageNumber="671">[Japanese name: Uroko-ari (= Minami-uroko-ari)]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D65B7CA434D90FB7582508F1C33BBF02" type="reference_group">
<paragraph id="73BAC6EBA3AAB379BDA349C922F419D7" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="80527BD317A4DE0AF8BBD16012BC4D45" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:36635" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys lewisi Cameron" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lewisi">Strumigenys lewisi Cameron</taxonomicName>
, 1886: 229. Syntype workers and queen. Type locality: Japan, Nagasaki, 3. iii, George Lewis leg [syntype queen was examined].
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="49C4C08A1A3E3A93DCB608F4350A25DE" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="55EB6D3E70CBBE544A1F86BE8D111855" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:36635" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys lewisi Cameron" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lewisi">Strumigenys lewisi</taxonomicName>
: Ogata, 1991 [first description of male]; Bolton, 2000 (in part); JADG, 2003 a, 2003 b, 2003 c.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="28511565F20AFC6DBB1FCEDB3C7F2A0B" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="3BFC3933740145F931BF8ED3F37371C9" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2458" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys Smith" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Strumigenys</taxonomicName>
sp. A: Onoyama, 1976.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3B610265275036B076DCFAEE88678390" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="6B980961A4EEFB223ECD6A569D0FB482" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2458" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys Smith" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Strumigenys</taxonomicName>
sp. 9: Onoyama et al., 1992: JADG, 2003 a, 2003 b, 2003 c.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7FBDDFA53369DD8E08C38F1D752463DC" pageNumber="671">
<taxonomicName id="49855C930888E63DCDD5E7066432B602" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2458" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys Smith" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Strumigenys</taxonomicName>
sp. D: Terayama, 1999.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D21575BEAAE248E8B9BEA1B9E658183A" type="description">
<paragraph id="F5C04A4BE338353E3F887C873FB1D6E4" pageNumber="671">
Worker (Figs 10 - 16). HL 0.65 - 0.71, HW 0.48 - 0.50 CI 69.8 - 76.0, ML 0.31 - 0.35, MI 46.9 - 50.0, SL 0.37 - 0.40, SI 76.4 - 82.0, DSA 3 L 0.12 - 0.13, DSA 
<geoCoordinate id="CDBCD676E051403DE919006D3B064ECB" direction="west" orientation="longitude" value="-3.0">3 W</geoCoordinate>
0.19 - 0.20, DSA 3 I 140.0 - 155.6 (6 measured).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="46BF9ED241ECBC07274EC71DE388DCC2" pageNumber="671">Ventrolateral margin of head at level of eye not extended outward. Antenna consisting of 6 segments. Fully closed mandible in full-face view curvilinear. On the mandible, a distinct, long and spiniform preapical tooth present close to apical teeth. Apical teeth consisting of two distinct spiniform teeth and three small intercalary teeth between them: basal of the two spiniform teeth longer than the apical one: basal one of the three intercalary teeth distinctly smaller than apical two. With mesosoma in lateral view, the diameter of the excavated area of mesopleural gland moderate, much less than the maximum width of the first coxa. Mesosoma except for propodeal declivity without spongiform tissue. Propodeal declivity equipped with a broad and conspicuous lamella; propodeal tooth very feeble and not sclerotized; posterior margin of the lamella convex, and immediately under the propodeal tooth of the margin sometimes slightly concave. Ventral margin of petiole in lateral view with longitudinal spongiform tissue. With petiole in lateral view, anteriormost point of lateral spongiform lobe nearly reaching level of anterior face of node.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="680F9B58D40B03D65C871E3DD955D856" pageNumber="671">Dorsal and lateral surfaces of pronotum entirely reticulate-punctate, sometimes with a small patch above the fore coxa. Metapleuron and side of propodeum entirely smooth. Limbus distinct. Abdominal tergite IV longitudinally sculptured at the basal portion, but not entirely covered.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D95033C736776C521F66C96BF398A457" pageNumber="671">With head in full-face view, a pair of long, curved distally plumose filiform hairs, rarely not serrate, present on apicoscrobe; hairs posterior to the apicoscrobal hairs with shorter barbs, laterally projecting filiform hairs; anterior to the apicoscrobal hairs without laterally projecting hair. With head in lateral view, dorsal surface from level of eye to preoccipital margin with erect to reclinate ground-pilosity; hair on vertex margin distinctly differentiated from that on level of eye; from highest point of vertex to preoccipital margin with the anteriorly directed ground-pilosity, which is very feebly curved basally so that each hair is elevated and inclined upward away from the cephalic outline. A pair of hairs present on the pronotal humeri and mesonotum; those on the humeri usually flagellate; those on the mesonotum usually short filiform hairs but sometimes long curved. Dorsum of hind femur without short erect hairs, but with two or three (usually two) long erect flagellate hairs. Dorsal surface of hind basitarsus with one freely projecting flagellate hair. The whole of the dorsal surface of abdominal tergite IV with flagellate hairs. Basal portion of abdominal sternite IV covered with matted hair-like tissue.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="99853776CCD6C8AC662D0224A141F697" pageNumber="671">Body almost unicolorous, reddish brown to yellowish brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B0179A40766BF50D86251E82882525A2" pageNumber="671">
Queen (Figs 23 - 28, 43). HL 0.63 - 0.70, HW 0.45 - 0.52 CI 71.5 - 80.0, ML 0.29 - 0.33, MI 44.8 - 49.2, SL 0.33 - 0.38, SI 67.9 - 76.2, DlO 0 - 0.02, DlOI 0 - 4.94, EL 0.08 - 0.11, EI 16.6 - 21.6, HD 0.30 - 0.32, PrH 0.18 - 0.22, MsW 0.26 - 0.31, MsWI 50.4 - 60.6, MsH 0.07 - 0.13, MsHI 14.2 - 27.0, DSA 3 L 0.12 - 0.15, DSA 
<geoCoordinate id="51F4C2E1D5E425AB86DC8C325842F4C5" direction="west" orientation="longitude" value="-3.0">3 W</geoCoordinate>
0.19 - 0.24, DSA 3 I 146.9 - 188.7 (10 measured).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6D23C5F31EEFE1E300472B6C51985AB3" lastPageNumber="672" pageNumber="671">
Generally similar to the worker with the usual caste differences. Head thinner than that of queen of 
<taxonomicName id="B7729EC92B8D4A0E12E7AC0C27B6DD08" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:237928" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys kumadori" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="671" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kumadori">S. kumadori</taxonomicName>
in lateral view. With head in full-face view, the ocelli weakly developed situated at posterior 1 / 4 of the head with brown pigment around them, but ocelli often vestigial and visible only with the pigments. Eye relatively small. A distinct, long spiniform preapical tooth present close to apical teeth. Apical teeth consisting of two spiniform teeth and three, rarely two, small intercalary teeth: basal one of the two spiniform teeth longer than another apical one: basal one of the three (or two) intercalary teeth distinctly smaller than the apical two (or the apical one). With mesosoma in lateral view, the highest point of the mesoscutum situated anterior to extension line of the mesopleural wing process in most cases; mesopleural gland orifice distinct but its maximum width not reaching maximum width of the procoxa; the pits on the mesepisternum invisible. Metanotum in lateral view slightly convex posteriorly. Propodeal spine developed and weakly sclerotized, and under which the lobe of spongiform tissue distinctly developed. With the spongiform tissue on propodeal declivity in lateral view, its posterior margin weakly concave under the propodeal spine. With mesoscutum in dorsal view, its anterior margin relatively sharp, both lateral margins strongly constricted at posterior 1 / 3, lateral corners by the constriction strongly angular. Transverse furrow on the mesoscutum nearly straight. Mesoscutum narrow (MsWI less than 63), its width not reaching 3 / 4 of the head width in frontal view. With petiole in lateral view, the lobe of spongiform tissue strongly developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="1FBD004BADB2DCBA5D3D084E0AD4FB71" pageNumber="672">Both of the fore and hind wings distinctly reduced in width at distal 1 / 2. Only costal (C) and radial (R 1) veins and r-rs cross vein clearly present on fore wing. Vestiges of the radial sector (Rs), M + Cu, and cubital (Cu) veins sometimes visible as pigmented lines but not sclerotized. On the hind wing, radial (R) vein present, reaching to costal margin and extended distally; jugal lobe absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EB563A510E809E617DA74244F8BE5D30" pageNumber="672">Head, pronotum, mesonotum, and metanotum entirely reticulate-punctate. Central part of mesepisternum and most part of propodeum ventral to propodeal spiracle not punctate and smooth. Dorsal margin of petiole reticulate-punctate. Dorsal surface of postpetiole not punctate and smooth. Limbus present on abdominal tergite IV. Abdominal tergite IV longitudinally sculptured at the basal portion, but sculptures not extended to posterior half of the tergite.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="79D548980B0A63F34C8770502A5C04C7" pageNumber="672">Hairs on the pronotal humeri long and flagellate. Mesonotal dorsum with erect, straight or flagellate hairs. Dorsum of hind femur without short erect hairs, but with 2 or 3 (usually 2) long erect flagellate hairs. Dorsal surface of abdominal tergite IV with long filiform hairs. Hair-like tissue on the basal portion of abdominal sternite IV developed. Fore and hind wings densely hairy.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8C0EAF81453A5207BE4FFBE9E2087A56" pageNumber="672">Body almost unicolorous, reddish brown to yellowish brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="FEB09E6DD4F5CCFED01A41A4E043E254" pageNumber="672">Male (Figs 35 - 40, 44, 49 - 52). HL 0.44 - 0.46, HW 0.43 - 0.46, CI 95.9 - 101.3, SL 0.09 - 0.11, SI 20.8 - 23.0, DlO 0.05 - 0.06, EL 0.18 - 0.19, HD 0.36 - 0.37, PrH 0.21 - 0.22, MsW 0.40, MsWI 91.5 - 94.0, MsH 0.16 - 0.17, MsHI 35.1 - 38.7 (3 measured).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="B05EAE32E9C9B65889E7AAF43B4274BC" lastPageNumber="673" pageNumber="672">
With head in full-face view, portion of posterior to the eyes subglobose; anterior to the eyes distinctly narrowed anteriorly. Ocelli distinct; the median ocellus situated about posterior 1 / 4 of the head length, the lateral ocelli not reaching to the posterior border of the head. Eyes distinctly developed and prominent, occupying central 1 / 3 of lateral margin of the head in full-face view. Eye in lateral view broadened ventrally, and its outer margin expanded anteroventrally and flattened posteriorly. Anterior tentorial pits unclear. Anterior margin of the clypeus in full-face view slightly convex, but nearly straight. Frontal carinae undeveloped and antennal insertions exposed. Antennae long and filiform, consisting 13 segments. Scape short and broad. Pedicel short and broadened apically. With mandible in full-face view, its apical portion gradually curved and narrowed; the basal lamella distinctly recognized and strongly projected; apical to the lamella edentate. Mandible in lateral view subtriangular, but broader than that of 
<taxonomicName id="5BB4DC052DB129505F63698821ABF0D8" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:237928" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys kumadori" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="672" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kumadori">S. kumadori</taxonomicName>
. With labrum in full-face view; its apical portion distinctly extended laterally; the distal lobes entirely reduced, and apical margin of the labrum concave toward the midpoint. Palp formula 1, 1 (1 observed on SEM). Mesosoma in lateral view shorter and higher than that of the queen. Mesoscutum distinctly developed and strongly raised dorsally in lateral view. Mesoscutellum developed and slightly extended posteriorly. With the mesonotum in dorsal view, the median notal suture weakly impressed but mostly invisible; the notauli weakly impressed; the parapsidal furrows impressed and continued to the distinct transscutal suture; anterior margin of the scuto-scutellar suture distinctly sculptured longitudinally, but weak on the lateral portion, so that the division of the axillae often indistinct. Metanotum in lateral view slightly extended posteriorly. With the propodeum in lateral view, a distinct spiracle situated at the midheight; the posterior margin with distinct corner, but the spine or dent reduced; the lamella absent ventral to the propodeal corner, even if its ventral portion with a carina along the propodeal declivity. With the petiole in lateral view, the node more gently raised than that of worker and queen; the lateral spongiform lobe entirely reduced; the longitudinal spongiform tissue feebly present. Ventral margin of abdominal sternite III without a distinct process except for its extreme anterior part. Abdominal segment IV in lateral view thicker than that of worker and queen, the ventral expansion more gentle.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D55094483785349177DC749B827B346C" pageNumber="673">With genitalia in ventral view, the basal ring broader than long; lateral margins of the parameral plate weakly concave; the cuspis of volsella distinctly shorter than the digitus. With genitalia in lateral view, an anteriorly directing process, such as the barb, present at apical 1 / 4 of its ventral margin; the digitus of volsella abruptly curved ventrally and broadened at the corner.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8799A9600D90AB17258548E811C055D3" pageNumber="673">Only costal (C) and radial (R 1) veins and r-rs cross vain clearly present on fore wing. Vestiges of the radial sector (Rs), M + Cu, and cubital (Cu) veins sometimes visible as pigmented lines but not sclerotized. On the hind wing, radial (R) vein present, reaching costal margin and extended distally; jugal lobe absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C76EC2D8A93CE7F4846253DED1A94759" pageNumber="673">Head, pronotum, mesonotum, and metanotum entirely reticulate-punctate. Central part of mesepisternum and most part of propodeum ventral to propodeal spiracle not punctate and smooth. Dorsal margin of petiole reticulate-punctate. Dorsal surface of postpetiole not punctate and smooth. Limbus absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="06B89BAD1D16CA0F8ABEFC509F5A33D1" pageNumber="673">Two pairs of standing filiform hairs present on vertex. With head in lateral view, long and frontally projecting hairs absent anterior to median ocellus. Mesonotum with long, erect, and filiform to flagellar hairs present. Dorsal surface of the petiole, abdominal tergite III and IV with sparse filiform hairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6864733AF0C68F6C655C8DA79249C530" pageNumber="673">Body almost unicolorous, blackish brown to reddish brown, legs same or lighter.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A4ADE5CB2C0DDA8BB92AACB0461EEE8A" type="distribution">
<paragraph id="4785A59972EB47E64309154A5A9C9BDB" pageNumber="673">Distribution. Japan: Honshu, Shikoku, Kyushu, Tsushima I., Yaku I., Amami Is, Okinawa I., Ishigaki I., Iriomote I.; Korea; China; Taiwan.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>