<document id="DB78C08CE61ECB20DD2E6E194852A260" ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d152d656-ef98-4767-b61b-d7a3c93f4df2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902674" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-657-43" ID-ZBK="7C34835207274F90915A5D5CBA9A9F83" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1A041782-E9FC-4455-9D57-82A8A2A07DE1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-657-43" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 657" ModsDocTitle="On some new species of Ancorabolidae Sars, 1909 from the Gulf of California: the genera Ceratonotus Sars, 1909, and Dendropsyllus Conroy-Dalton, 2003 (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)" checkinTime="1487401282446" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gomez, Samuel &amp; Diaz, Karen" docDate="2017" docId="F5242C74FF708B9D941A232D7ABF786B" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 657: 43-65" docOrigin="ZooKeys 657" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725" docTitle="Ceratonotus elongatus Gomez &amp; Diaz, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="1A041782-E9FC-4455-9D57-82A8A2A07DE1" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" masterDocId="FFB1A87FFFCCB62CFFCA5E18FFA7FFD5" masterDocTitle="On some new species of Ancorabolidae Sars, 1909 from the Gulf of California: the genera Ceratonotus Sars, 1909, and Dendropsyllus Conroy-Dalton, 2003 (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="43" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" updateTime="1643558546598" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" xmlns:dwc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/2003/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tax="http://www.taxonx.org/schema/v1" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<mods:mods id="467DAFD85B2ECC7731BA27283C6F9271" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="B4A2B4474B7C3CDDBB50D6FB3E8CD8DA">
<mods:title id="54CDB1D1EEE117BB287EA735DB56CD26">On some new species of Ancorabolidae Sars, 1909 from the Gulf of California: the genera Ceratonotus Sars, 1909, and Dendropsyllus Conroy-Dalton, 2003 (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="CE685A3482FF65A8C4D22EE256DF93B6" type="personal">
<mods:role id="9FB5A743836DDA51B21731D2BE148781">
<mods:roleTerm id="92FA516787F9690803336E5473F22CCD">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="5E06126B738B746933834E42DA929948">Gomez, Samuel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="70AC6900914FE2F8CF231CA740D61AD8" type="personal">
<mods:role id="0B92250DE8609957554B655E80A025C1">
<mods:roleTerm id="B0D11495EEF9B0BB3E967D2E63D30364">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="C5AB15F757C7F1C9EAD1F1ACEB8C2790">Diaz, Karen</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="A53160E6201A2731193F519C7FC949CA">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="D163746E3BC0563EE969A4B51682EF26" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="38FE91CE5ED81F7CD4286A07C1D349BA">
<mods:title id="857DFB7378E2B8C262AE78701241564F">ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="D7E88460073EEBF446CF386ACAC5B72E">
<mods:date id="12DF357041D86B5D4EB52B6D2515F1EF">2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="5D43A3DF70561FBF461142191967F7B9" type="volume">
<mods:number id="64693EE54A31347ADC9E01890A9BF9A7">657</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="787F1A841B56B4056486CEDEA60747EB" unit="page">
<mods:start id="31F9D709C20D250465292424375BBE5C">43</mods:start>
<mods:end id="C1B0767C3CA0ABD24C30A244B3D127D5">65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="865EE63346F50DFCA60EC911E5232392">
<mods:url id="4439041D1FFCFD6A04541BDB8E757ADD">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="3A405E45D54B148867C2B7A3BD331267">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="CEF2B9CCD69C441CBCDCA4AC7C151BAE" type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.10725</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="20E33157772CB7220F33B229D338BAF8" type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-657-43</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="4ADCF697379AB68207A5BD31BE0CB67E" type="ZBK">7C34835207274F90915A5D5CBA9A9F83</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="80ABF63D126B027603C3FAB7390BA280" type="ZooBank">7C34835207274F90915A5D5CBA9A9F83</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="F5242C74FF708B9D941A232D7ABF786B" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902674" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1A041782-E9FC-4455-9D57-82A8A2A07DE1" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F5242C74FF708B9D941A232D7ABF786B" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<subSubSection id="77159EF247D349D31B5AABC403FEE96A" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="AB5A9F8D9065E3BA4DEF487730B92B1C" pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
<taxonomicName id="1BAAC8DCD848EEA7577134E494EC8869" LSID="http://zoobank.org/1A041782-E9FC-4455-9D57-82A8A2A07DE1" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Ceratonotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceratonotus elongatus" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongatus">Ceratonotus elongatus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="D15DFABD36DB4B0A9DE0E60A815486AD" pageId="1" pageNumber="44">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="B68271556C642599220C367302ECEA3B" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="1" pageNumber="44" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="75A4D1EE84B1D16B4EC39029B029B866" pageId="1" pageNumber="44">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8ECB097C77CE15AED08D94519D51CB15" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="45" pageId="1" pageNumber="44">
One female holotype as follows: body partially dissected (leaving cephalothorax with right first antennulary segment and antenna, first thoracopod to fifth urosomite, and right P5 intact) and preserved in alcohol (ICML-EMUCOP-100207-01), left antennule and antenna, pair of mandibles, maxillules, maxillae 
<pageBreakToken id="962F8493D74EEB5C3C4C0808586C6A16" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" start="start">and</pageBreakToken>
maxillipeds, P1-P4 and left P5, and anal somite with caudal rami dissected and mounted on four slides (ICML-EMUCOP-100207-04).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D5340F65C8FC10D1ADA91C260688C09B" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="type locality">
<paragraph id="6288FB8C46EAFB711D276F458ED6ED3C" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C26C8495C5E8B0489EDAE31214B4557E" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
Southern Trough of Guaymas Basin, Gulf of California, 
<normalizedToken id="A8B37CB41CC72371707D515F39EA72DB" originalValue="México">Mexico</normalizedToken>
(
<geoCoordinate id="19A4AB442F0AFAAE101D09844341600F" direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="925" value="27.016666">27°01'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="125A22DDF135A4F7CD6E1D54C7B1A769" direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="-110.884445">110°53'04&quot;W</geoCoordinate>
), 1642 m depth (see Fig. 1); coll. S. 
<normalizedToken id="CC403285D249FB94A44F1AE60844ED98" originalValue="Gómez">Gomez</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="714A07C9FB7848084FB6D1581FE42753" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph id="14F1365AC8EFB74CB2321FE4878B5376" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">Diagnosis</paragraph>
<paragraph id="BE06FB086EE31BE1F76FB8B45DB8D001" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="46" pageId="2" pageNumber="45">
(based on the female only). 
<taxonomicName id="3B8432010E5C86401E66848F283E3AF5" family="Ancorabolidae" lsidName="" pageId="2" pageNumber="45" rank="family">Ancorabolidae</taxonomicName>
. Cephalothorax without anterior horn-like processes, with bilateral constriction in anterior half. First half of genital double-somite without, posterior half with well-developed dendroid processes. 
<pageBreakToken id="FF6EAFC54B961E1B6AFD7DCCDD2A319F" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" start="start">With</pageBreakToken>
dorsal elongate tubercles and paired tube-pores on fourth urosomite. Caudal rami divergent, approximately 11 times as long as wide, with seven setae of which seta IV fused at base of seta V. Antennule three-segmented. Antenna with allobasis bearing one abexopodal seta; without exopod; endopod with nine setae/spines. Palp of mandible one-segmented, with five setae. Maxillule with two surface setae and seven spines on praecoxal arthrite; coxal endite with two elements; basis with six setae; exopod represented by two, endopod by three elements. Maxilla with two syncoxal endites, each with three setae; endopod represented by two setae. Maxilliped with one seta on syncoxa; endopodal claw with one accessory seta. Exopod of P1 two-segmented, of P3-P4 three-segmented. Endopod of P1-P4 two segmented; endopod of P1 as long as exopod, second endopodal segment approximately 1.7 times as long as first endopodal segment; first endopodal segment of P2 and P3 reduced, smaller than second endopodal segment; endopod of P4 much smaller than in P2 and P3, first endopodal segment twice as long as second. P5 with exopod and endopodal lobe distinct; endopodal lobe a tiny pedestal with one seta and one tube-pore; exopod elongate, slender, with three elements.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="A38105A254FA7CA5426245CE90615AC8" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="3" pageNumber="46" type="description">
<paragraph id="C335E904F9B6E4A2105B5135CBC9890C" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">Description of female.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="92FC361BE6102D48BDA6D5311AF5614A" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
Total body length, 920 
<normalizedToken id="531054FCFBEE09AD1D8BAA393D8E1216" originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
measured from anterior outer corner of cephalothorax to posterior margin of caudal rami; length of caudal rami, 222.5 
<normalizedToken id="0972B327B0C22B6AAF67FA0469072643" originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
(ca. 24% total body length). Body (Fig. 2A) cylindrical, rather slender, tapering slightly posteriorly, without clear demarcation between prosome and urosome; integument moderately chitinised; general pattern of dendroid processes as for the genus; dendroid processes well developed. Cephalothorax without anterior horn-like processes, with bilateral constriction in anterior half; with large tube-pore medially along anterior margin; anterior corners of cephalothorax with two anterior sensilla associated with a tube-pore (Fig. 3A); dorsal dendroid processes well developed (Fig. 2A); lateroventral processes situated rather anteriorly. Rostrum fused to cephalothorax, absorbed into anteroventral surface of cephalothorax, with paired sensilla and well-developed midventral tube-pore (Figs 2A, 3A).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="EF0CA183EBDAE988F8AB19D6B8BCDC13" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">P2-P4-bearing somites with medial tube-pore and two posterior sensilla; dorsal dendroid processes well developed. P5-bearing somite with dorsal tube-pore, without posterior sensilla; with well-developed dorsal processes, nearly as long as in preceding somites and without backwardly directed excrescent.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="8B53EC028398D2DC49E0D49589EE415E" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="47" pageId="3" pageNumber="46">
Original segmentation of genital double-somite indicated by bilateral constriction; first half of genital double-somite with dorsal tube-pore, without dendroid processes, without spinular ornamentation ventrally, genital field as shown (Fig. 3C); posterior half without dorsal tube-pore, with well-developed dendroid process, though smaller than those of P5 bearing-somite (Fig. 2A), ventrally without spinular ornamentation but with paired tube-pores (Fig. 3C). Fourth urosomite (second abdominal somite) with elongate tubercles and paired tube-pores dorsally (Figs 2A, 3B), ventrally with medial short spinular row close to posterior margin and with paired tube-pores (Fig. 3C). Fifth urosomite (third abdominal somite) with paired tube-pores and with fine spinules along posterior margin dorsally (Fig. 2A), with four medial sets of spinules and paired tube-pores ventrally (Fig. 3C). Anal somite cleft medially (Fig. 2A, C); with 
<pageBreakToken id="4892BA03210AD0204DDB5B0273EFBCC1" pageId="4" pageNumber="47" start="start">tube-pore</pageBreakToken>
and small spinules ventrally as shown (Fig. 2C); rounded anal operculum smooth (Fig. 2A).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3F9687DCFC14A173C5F446D2D038B332" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="48" pageId="4" pageNumber="47">
Caudal rami elongate, divergent, cylindrical, approximately 11 times as long as wide (Fig. 2A, C); with some spinules at base of setae I, II and III, and close to posterior margin ventrally; with conspicuous tube-pore proximally (Fig. 2A); with seven setae; seta I minute, ventral to seta II (Fig. 2A, C,E), both situated on proximal fifth of ramus; seta II bipinnate; seta III inserted on proximal margin of distal third, as long as seta II, bipinnate (Fig. 2A, C); seta IV fused at base of seta V (Fig. 2B, D, F), the latter longest, ornamented as shown (Fig. 2D); seta VI shorter than seta IV, inserted on distal 
<pageBreakToken id="539873D22F167A0D70A36427FDB74345" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" start="start">inner</pageBreakToken>
corner of ramus (Fig. 2B, C, F); dorsal seta VII triarticulate, arising from small pedestal close to posterior margin (Fig. 2B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5CC3D6E44B9D112BDA6E031F511998F4" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">Antennule (Fig. 4A) three-segmented, segments elongate and slender. Armature formula as follows: 1-[9], 2-[7+(1+ae)], 3-[9+acrothek].</paragraph>
<paragraph id="3BDEE55AC67CF2F39887059DE4F4FDE7" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">Antenna (Fig. 4B). Coxa represented by sclerite; with allobasis and one-segmented endopod. Allobasis with membranous insert indicating original division between basis and first endopodal segment; with small spinules along inner margin of proximal half; with well-developed pinnate abexopodal seta in endopodal half. Exopod absent. Endopod with small spinules along inner margin of proximal half; with two inner lateral spines and one slender seta; with two outer subdistal frills; apically with two pinnate spines, two geniculate single setae, and one geniculate element fused to tiny seta basally; with additional distal tube-pore (arrowed in Fig. 4B).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6810D019DC4B1A5E9E0742680AD7CF43" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">Mandible (Fig. 5A) with robust coxa. Gnathobase with distal teeth as shown, with one lateral pinnate seta accompanied by spine-like element. Palp one-segmented, well developed, with two inner (basal) setae, and three apical (endopodal) setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="C7DA1FB8CF481D2C9CD516795E38C1FA" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="49" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
Maxillule (Fig. 5B). Praecoxal arthrite with two surface setae and some posterior spinules (some of them very long), distally with seven spines (two of them spinulose) and two pinnate setae. Coxal endite with some spinules distally, with one strong and 
<pageBreakToken id="E62542599F9772D3A3253DA0BA551EA0" pageId="6" pageNumber="49" start="start">spinulose</pageBreakToken>
element and one slender seta ornamented with very few spinules. Proximal endite of basis with four, distal endite with two setae. Exopod and endopod incorporated into basis, the former represented by one small and one strong seta, the latter represented by three pinnate elements.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D479854A9EF49F7A66AA4B5F93E4DDC8" pageId="6" pageNumber="49">Maxilla (Fig. 5C). Syncoxa with spinulose patches as shown, with two endites; proximal endite with one strong spinulose element fused to endite, and two spinulose setae, distal endite with three spinulose elements. Allobasis drawn out into strong claw; accessory armature consisting of one spinulose strong spine, and one bare and one pinnate seta. Endopod represented by two setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="4B5FF36880B94BF1EE5D5D1177BACDDE" pageId="6" pageNumber="49">Maxilliped (Fig. 5D) subchelate, slender. Syncoxa with one pinnate seta. Basis with spinules as figured. Endopod drawn into long, curved claw finely pinnate with one accessory small seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D9DDD144C75093B68BF4DE53AF4A2B8C" pageId="7" pageNumber="50">
<pageBreakToken id="3518B00CB00B11F255F678B04C0F559A" pageId="7" pageNumber="50" start="start">P</pageBreakToken>
1 (Fig. 6A). Coxa with one outer spinule. Basis transversely elongate, with anterior tube-pore, with some spinules at base of outer seta, the latter well-developed, inner seta lost during dissection. Exopod two-segmented; first segment with pinnate spine longer than entire ramus; second segment with two pinnate outer spines and three geniculate apical setae. Endopod two-segmented, nearly as long as exopod; first segment unarmed; second segment 1.7 times as long as first one, with two apical setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="F923503EFE5C76859373878F1AD3855E" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="7" pageNumber="50">
P2-P4 (Fig. 6
<normalizedToken id="FE7E81A482E74EB5C442EAAB7F164ACB" originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
) with trapezoid coxa ornamented with spinules on lobate outer process. Basis transversely elongate, with anterior tube-pore midway length of basis, 
<pageBreakToken id="6BE3CD174770AC10CA69A96C3FE4B4A6" pageId="8" pageNumber="51" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
some spinules at base of outer seta. Exopod three-segmented; first segment with outer bipinnate elongate spine; second segment with outer bipinnate elongate spine and inner seta; third segment with two outer elongate spines, two apical elements and one (P2 and P4) or two (P3) inner setae, with (P2 and P3) or without (P4) tube-pore. Endopod two-segmented; P2ENP1 and P3ENP1 reduced, smaller than ENP2, the 
<pageBreakToken id="1325C9CC9F31D80761BC474E7D1F1A2A" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" start="start">latter</pageBreakToken>
with two setae, inner one smaller; P4ENP much smaller than in preceding legs, ENP1 twice as long as ENP2, the latter with one seta.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2ECF9980C7AEBDC007E52B8462EFE581" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Armature formula as follows:</paragraph>
<caption id="47AB416EEED768DA30D3D1D64CB2F4C3" ID-Table-UUID="47AB416EEED768DA30D3D1D64CB2F4C3" httpUri="http://table.plazi.org/id/47AB416EEED768DA30D3D1D64CB2F4C3" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<paragraph id="683A9B0943DF4D8D4F3980A5ED24239C" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">. &amp;nbsp;</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph id="40F8822FF8502448672DE552DF557D16" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<table id="6847A25067A610D3D1528A3396183895" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<tr id="50B58FEBD1E69EEBCBBC72AFCC1B291F" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<th id="FC990D1559B438AE5ACFBED78D3466E8" colspan="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">EXP</th>
<th id="3E8D0A6FA3CEC75EAE2DFFF55B6659FD" colspan="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" rowspan="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">ENP</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="06BBE8F87FB07E60404FD8D9795D7311" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">P5 (Fig. 6E) without baseoendopodal setophore; outer basal seta bare, accompanied by tube-pore. Endopodal lobe represented by tiny pedestal armed with one seta and accompanied by tube-pore. Exopod distinct, long, slender, with three elements as figured.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="252DE5866468CF9BF0FBB496F4F214AC" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="description">
<paragraph id="7389B92D3C46E1B900EFF72731ED1BCA" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Description of male.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="2EFB6069BEF1556F9E40E95FEBAF1403" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="D338420BBAE022BC724BB9192EB90030" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="07AB2EEFEF3A973DE25A26A90B21E09E" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="6FC8F36F5711BE78F3E2B89B00DD5FBD" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">The specific epithet, elongatus, makes reference to the elongate dorsal tubercles on the second abdominal somite.</paragraph>
<caption id="6F7C73A1070DBD2F056B8EAA67044E55" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<paragraph id="34C78B53FE71E8BBCD192D034EDFD841" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName id="977A2ACD8C8BA3644DDDD8C9A3EE9AAD" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Ceratonotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceratonotus elongatus" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongatus">Ceratonotus elongatus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A habitus, dorsal B distal part of caudal ramus, dorsal C anal somite and right caudal ramus, ventral D caudal setae IV and V E caudal setae I and II, indicating position of reduced seta I F distal part of caudal ramus, ventral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="3B9C136BF999EAF4FE8F6CC2DB617DBC" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<paragraph id="C8CEBC01641DE91B0DFCB5D42A3AF356" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName id="20276B39D1AE1182F92BE127CD28B974" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Ceratonotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceratonotus elongatus" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongatus">Ceratonotus elongatus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A anterior corner of cephalothorax B fourth urosomite (second abdominal somite), dorsal C genital double-somite, and fourth and fifth urosomites (second and third abdominal somites), ventral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="1D0D7BE327841B2C29E61DECA2C03C1A" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<paragraph id="40FD8E5904825AE540897C81904F169D" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName id="7A17E293B2580B21AEC00D9B21A08008" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Ceratonotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceratonotus elongatus" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongatus">Ceratonotus elongatus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A antennule B antenna.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="910E8F556E14CAAC9F479E08F1C4EE1E" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<paragraph id="51D63451B6F3543ED38013D68F1CF6F2" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName id="0C1BD6D0D1A15302FA6FC46EEE33888D" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Ceratonotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceratonotus elongatus" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongatus">Ceratonotus elongatus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A mandible B maxillule C maxilla, showing insertion of proximal endite D maxilliped.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption id="A849BBACB330A048E8C1C42A89239030" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
<paragraph id="1C38BC2B3A3899466994ECA4037AD71B" pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName id="DC30815E2D08089C902DDFBC05FB3095" class="Hexanauplia" family="Ancorabolidae" genus="Ceratonotus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ceratonotus elongatus" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="9" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongatus">Ceratonotus elongatus</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A P1, anterior B P2, anterior C P3, anterior D P4, anterior, showing insert of endopod E P5, lateral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>