<document id="65C2B4DC2A46DFB4C171C21F996F0BA9" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5053577" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5053577" ID-ZooBank="CD3B18C1-A499-4748-8487-6AD98DC3903A" _generate="added" approvalRequired="25" approvalRequired_for_bibRefs="1" approvalRequired_for_document="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="23" checkinTime="1591959525949" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio, Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto De L. &amp; Júnior, José Osvaldo Silva" docDate="2020" docId="F57087F2853EFFADFF6F9B430292FEA1" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4790.3.8.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4790 (3)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D.9:Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleId="647186512141C8FC8976D5BCC54AEB7D" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2013-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="9" docTitle="Plistonax antonkozlovi Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior 2020, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="548" masterDocId="0949FF8A8539FFA4FFF898200006FFE2" masterDocTitle="Description of two new Acanthoderini, and description of the male of Oreodera advena Martins &amp; Galileo (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="550" masterPageNumber="540" pageId="7" pageNumber="547" updateTime="1625138114683" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="CF4EC4ABD1D06C01F577EDD829C72A0B" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="AFB966891B8EF137092B2DE0D07C71BB">
<mods:title id="3A8CFBD8C38140DBA0C0BC5B0A251EF4">Description of two new Acanthoderini, and description of the male of Oreodera advena Martins &amp; Galileo (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="AC46C7553D2117D24DF549FD87F11BE1" type="personal">
<mods:role id="0E2D5372FA0A971EC20F2D133D733020">
<mods:roleTerm id="0A8E92757FB975FB33DCDFF2C5EACE07">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="8501D38BC6749D5F76F0FE7550B496CC">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="E2236040ECD24CB1C15844EEC5ABAA3B">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, SP, Brazil &amp; toncriss @ uol. com. br; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0001 - 7128 - 1418</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="A4A9E62F1156130AE649A74351F05DA8" type="personal">
<mods:role id="14BE298460277A5BDC18AED4C221CC56">
<mods:roleTerm id="754D5376D708F60920369F9CE0DF640D">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="DD6AA2003A779E1C0EDF70CDE23D4C5A">Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto De L.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="1A00B7923E7B4A70B4C639D51A71D9EC">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, SP, Brazil &amp; eribnascimentofl @ gmail. com; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0002 - 5047 - 8921</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="39A85DA7BA302AADFBAD19948C979383" type="personal">
<mods:role id="232131DC2CB476C807B018BDA348CCE0">
<mods:roleTerm id="A8C43DCA7A9E9724B60FEC72E4EBBBA7">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="3B28BC31A28C596FEC09AE2562A3C8DC">Júnior, José Osvaldo Silva</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="A3C0C6D4F448C801F7C848CA7EA884E5">Department of Zoology, Setor de Ciências Biológicas, Universidade Federal do Paraná, Curitiba, PR, Brazil. &amp; juniorbio 0230 @ gmail. com; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0002 - 2569 - 4278</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="C2AF7AF7B97AF3C0E4ECCB9957476AFA">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="F9D30CB6720F6EBCE5540557A27907C1" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="8D62517482A45D0017EDD511B4C35F43">
<mods:title id="869B64EEDEDBE850FEAB278BC9D20B17">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="10D31D33148F610AEEB86FFA500C5E36">
<mods:date id="CD221D7F1A95E0C8439BA800E6A5EBC4">2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="8C58F50861FBEC18DC5AF7A9C86FFF6D" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="2E58B812D2B3C860B98240498A4F46E0">2020-06-12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="635FFB35D4F233A8BFFAAC3C31755CD6" type="volume">
<mods:number id="39E6F80C98F9D74EE9456C7B8F38DC72">4790</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="777392C87E893ED1E05B1DD319881928" type="issue">
<mods:number id="406AC13D4A683049E6BBDFC452FC68EA">3</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="A841055C83AB307E87E827121B391D6E" unit="page">
<mods:start id="9131694816DC641204E1FD80A74F6027">540</mods:start>
<mods:end id="41DD69C482BD86A5A37494D562AB0EF0">550</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="ECE117B669C65FA855DA4FDF6D0FE1AC">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="0AB15A4917522AA9FA1B0C79E8B99E9B" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4790.3.8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E9D6452CCCA6883C897E39A7256A1683" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="6AED185F8794FA3CE5B8A625479BC79F" type="Zenodo-Dep">3891319</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="2CF6D8225E268FAEC7904B6BF2892265" type="ZooBank">CD3B18C1-A499-4748-8487-6AD98DC3903A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="F57087F2853EFFADFF6F9B430292FEA1" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5053577" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5053577" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F57087F2853EFFADFF6F9B430292FEA1" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F57087F2853EFFADFF6F9B430292FEA1" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="548" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">
<subSubSection id="35C3656F853EFFA3FF6F9B430216FC9C" box="[151,528,867,894]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853EFFA3FF6F9B430216FC9C" blockId="7.[151,528,867,930]" box="[151,528,867,894]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">
<heading id="262E8188853EFFA3FF6F9B430216FC9C" bold="true" box="[151,528,867,894]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="7" pageNumber="547" reason="1">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853EFFA3FF6F9B430216FC9C" bold="true" box="[151,528,867,894]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853EFFA3FF6F9B4301AAFC9C" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior" authorityYear="2020" box="[151,428,867,894]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Plistonax" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="547" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853EFFA3FF6F9B4301AAFC9C" bold="true" box="[151,428,867,894]" italics="true" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">Plistonax antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="549E578D853EFFA3FE4B9B440216FC9C" box="[435,528,868,894]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F853EFFACFF6F9BA80505F901" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="548" pageId="7" pageNumber="547" type="description">
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853EFFA3FF6F9BA80128FC40" blockId="7.[151,528,867,930]" box="[151,302,904,930]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">
(
<figureCitation id="E5E22A61853EFFA3FF679BA80120FC40" box="[159,294,904,930]" captionStart="FIGURES 17–24" captionStartId="9.[151,264,1828,1853]" captionTargetBox="[164,1428,360,1724]" captionTargetId="figure@9.[151,1435,345,1803]" captionTargetPageId="9" captionText="FIGURES 17–24. Plistonax antonkozlovi, holotype male: 17) Dorsal habitus; 18) Ventral habitus; 19) Lateral habitus; 20) Head, frontal view; 21) Mesoventral process, ventral view; 22) Mesoventral process, lateral view; 23) Elytral setae within punctures; 24) Antennomeres VII–IX." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891325" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891325/files/figure.png" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">Figs. 17–24</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853EFFA3FF6F9BEF02EEFBB4" blockId="7.[151,1437,975,2010]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853EFFA3FF6F9BEF0170FC08" bold="true" box="[151,374,975,1002]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">Description. Male.</emphasis>
Integument mostly dark brown, almost black; mouthparts mostly orangish-brown, maxillary palpomeres II–IV, and labial palpomeres II–III brown, with apex of each palpomere reddish brown; anteclypeus reddish brown centrally, orangish brown laterally; labrum dark reddish brown except anterior area somewhat orangish brown; posterior area of gulamentum reddish brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853EFFACFF3F9C400518FE69" blockId="7.[151,1437,975,2010]" lastBlockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="548" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853EFFA3FF3F9C400108FB98" bold="true" box="[199,270,1120,1146]" pageId="7" pageNumber="547">Head.</emphasis>
Frons and vertex coarsely, sparsely punctate; frons mostly with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument, narrow pale yellow pubescent band close to eyes, oblique pale yellow pubescent band on each side close to postclypeus; a few moderately long, erect brown setae close to inferior area of eyes; vertex with yellowish-brown pubescence laterally between antennal tubercles (darker, sparser centrally), remaining surface more sepia. Area behind eyes with narrow pale yellow pubescent band close to eyes (widened toward inferior margin of lower eye lobe), glabrous on remaining surface. Genae 1.3 times length of lower eye lobe; nearly smooth; with pale yellow pubescence, dense on some areas, sparser on others, except partially glabrous longitudinal band close to frons, and glabrous apex. Antennal tubercles with pale yellow pubescence, dense anteriorly and posteriorly, sparse centrally. Wide central area of postclypeus with yellowish-brown pubescence, with pale yellow pubescence interspersed, bristly close to anteclypeus, glabrous laterally; with one long, erect pale seta on each side of pubescent area close to frons, and a few long, erect setae on sides of wide central area close to anteclypeus. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior 2/3, oblique at anterior third; with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument on coplanar area, glabrous on anterior third, with fringe of golden short setae on anterior margin; with moderately long, both golden and brown setae on sides of anterior third. Gulamentum mostly smooth and glabrous, with narrow anterocentral area depressed, with a few minute yellowish setae close to anterior margin. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.38 times length of scape (0.25 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.90 times length of scape (0.61 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 1.4 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at apex of antennomere X. Scape with transverse pale yellow pubescent band centrally, not reaching ventral surface, with sparse pale yellow pubescence dorsally and laterally on anterior and posterior areas, more abundant near apex, and brown pubescence on remaining dorsal and lateral surfaces; ventral surface with grayish-white pubescence on basal half, not obscuring integument, minute very sparse pubescence on posterior half, and a few long, erect pale setae on apex. Pedicel with brownish pubescence, with pale yellow short, decumbent setae interspersed dorsally and laterally, with brownish pubescence on basal half, and pale yellow pubescence on distal half; with a few long, erect, nearly golden setae ventrally. Antennomeres III–IV with two pale yellow pubescent rings, one basally, another about middle; remaining surface with brownish pubescence, with pale yellow decumbent setae interspersed between the two rings. Antennomeres V–VII with pale yellow pubescence on basal half (paler than bands on previous antennomeres), brownish on remaining surface. Antennomeres VIII–XI with pale yellow pubescence on basal third (paler than bands on III–IV), brownish on remaining surface. Antennomeres III–V with long, erect, nearly golden setae ventrally (gradually sparser toward V); ventral apex of antennomeres III–IX with tuft of thick, short golden setae directed backward. Antennomeres VI–IX ventrally with distinct tubercle near to apex (
<figureCitation id="E5E22A618531FFACFE14996D0246FE85" box="[492,576,333,359]" captionStart="FIGURES 17–24" captionStartId="9.[151,264,1828,1853]" captionTargetBox="[164,1428,360,1724]" captionTargetId="figure@9.[151,1435,345,1803]" captionTargetPageId="9" captionText="FIGURES 17–24. Plistonax antonkozlovi, holotype male: 17) Dorsal habitus; 18) Ventral habitus; 19) Lateral habitus; 20) Head, frontal view; 21) Mesoventral process, ventral view; 22) Mesoventral process, lateral view; 23) Elytral setae within punctures; 24) Antennomeres VII–IX." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891325" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891325/files/figure.png" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Fig. 24</figureCitation>
). Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.81; pedicel = 0.23; IV = 0.69; V = 0.46; VI = 0.37; VII = 0.31; VIII = 0.27; IX = 0.26; X = 0.25; XI = 0.28.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E48531FFACFF3F99B5059BFBB9" blockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFF3F99B50126FE4D" bold="true" box="[199,288,405,431]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Thorax</emphasis>
. Prothorax distinctly transverse; with large, conical tubercle (blunt apex) at center of each side. Pronotum with one large, conical, elevated tubercle (blunt apex) on each side of anterior half, and subelliptical, longitudinal, slightly elevated gibbosity on center of posterior half (not reaching posterior margin), prolonged as slightly elevated carina toward anterior margin; coarsely, somewhat abundantly punctate (punctures coarser posteriorly), except impunctate anterolateral tubercles and central gibbosity; pubescence mostly greenish-brown, not obscuring integument, with subtriangular pale yellow macula anterocentrally, short pale yellow band posterocentrally, irregular pale yellow pubescent band surrounding central gibbosity, and irregular pale yellow pubescent macula close to posterior area of lateral tubercles of prothorax. Sides of prothorax coarsely, abundantly punctate (punctures coarser than on pronotum, denser anteriorly); with pale yellow pubescence not obscuring integument, distinctly sparser on anterior half. Prosternum nearly smooth; with pale yellow pubescence distinctly not obscuring integument. Prosternal process nearly vertically posteriorly; laterocentral margins expanded to apex, more strongly after middle; dorsal surface carinate laterally; with sparse yellowish-white pubescence; narrowest area 0.4 times width of procoxal cavity. Mesoventrite with pale yellow pubescence close to mesocoxal cavities, sparser, yellowish white on remaining surface; mesanepisternum and mesepimeron with pale yellow pubescence not obscuring integument. Mesoventral process with sides sinuous, tab-shaped on apex; with distinct tubercle on each side of anterior area (
<figureCitation id="E5E22A618531FFACFAFD9BAD0589FC45" box="[1285,1423,909,935]" captionStart="FIGURES 17–24" captionStartId="9.[151,264,1828,1853]" captionTargetBox="[164,1428,360,1724]" captionTargetId="figure@9.[151,1435,345,1803]" captionTargetPageId="9" captionText="FIGURES 17–24. Plistonax antonkozlovi, holotype male: 17) Dorsal habitus; 18) Ventral habitus; 19) Lateral habitus; 20) Head, frontal view; 21) Mesoventral process, ventral view; 22) Mesoventral process, lateral view; 23) Elytral setae within punctures; 24) Antennomeres VII–IX." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891325" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891325/files/figure.png" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Figs. 21–22</figureCitation>
); with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument. Metanepisternum, sides of metaventrite, and area of metaventrite close to metacoxae with abundant pale yellow pubescence; area of metaventrite close to mesocoxae with sparse pale yellow pubescence; remaining surface of metaventrite with minute, sparse, slightly distinct yellowish-white pubescence. Scutellum transverse, with oblique sides and straight apex, with dense, longitudinal pale yellow pubescence centrally, with brownish pubescence on sides of anterior half, subglabrous on sides of posterior half.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E48531FFACFF6F9C450262F9CD" blockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFF6F9C4500ECFB9D" bold="true" box="[151,234,1125,1151]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Elytra.</emphasis>
Coarsely, somewhat abundantly punctate (punctures slightly finer toward apex); humeri slightly rounded projected forward; centrobasal crest distinct, with rounded, glabrous tubercles on top, reaching about 1/4 of elytra; apex together rounded; pubescence mostly yellowish brown, irregularly surrounded by dark, sparse pubescent areas, with some yellowish-white pubescent maculae interspersed, areas with pubescence more yellowish-brown, and white pubescent maculae close to suture on posterior half; single thick whitish seta, or single slender dark brown seta placed within anterior area of punctures (
<figureCitation id="E5E22A618531FFACFD5B9D3902FCFAD1" box="[675,762,1305,1331]" captionStart="FIGURES 17–24" captionStartId="9.[151,264,1828,1853]" captionTargetBox="[164,1428,360,1724]" captionTargetId="figure@9.[151,1435,345,1803]" captionTargetPageId="9" captionText="FIGURES 17–24. Plistonax antonkozlovi, holotype male: 17) Dorsal habitus; 18) Ventral habitus; 19) Lateral habitus; 20) Head, frontal view; 21) Mesoventral process, ventral view; 22) Mesoventral process, lateral view; 23) Elytral setae within punctures; 24) Antennomeres VII–IX." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891325" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891325/files/figure.png" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Fig. 23</figureCitation>
). 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFCF79D390348FAD1" bold="true" box="[783,846,1305,1331]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora with irregular pale yellow pubescence ring about middle of club (less distinct on metafemora, especially dorsally), and transverse band of same color on apex of dorsal surface; peduncle and anterior area of club with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument; remaining surface of club with yellowish-brown pubescence, with both, whitish and pale yellow short setae interspersed. Tibiae with three yellow pubescent bands, one basally, one about middle, another on apex, not reaching ventral surface, more distinctly so in protibiae; remaining surface with brownish pubescence, with short, erect, pale yellow setae interspersed, except basal 2/3 of ventral surface with yellowish-white pubescence, and posterior third with dense yellowish-brown pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E48531FFACFF3F9E1800F9F979" blockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFF3F9E180145F9B1" bold="true" box="[199,323,1592,1619]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with thick, moderately abundant pale yellow pubescence laterally, yellowish-white, finer, sparser centrally; ventrites I–IV with glabrous areas laterally. Apex of ventrite V truncate, very slightly emarginated centrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E48531FFACFF3F9E840505F901" blockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFF3F9E8401A2F95D" bold="true" box="[199,420,1700,1727]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Dimensions (mm).</emphasis>
Total length, 14.65; prothoracic length, 2.90; anterior prothoracic width, 3.75; posterior prothoracic width, 4.00; maximum prothoracic width, 5.00; humeral width, 5.80; elytral length, 9.65.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F8531FFACFF3F9ECD036FF8C9" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="7D6636E48531FFACFF3F9ECD036FF8C9" blockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFF3F9ECD0177F8E5" bold="true" box="[199,369,1772,1799]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Type material</emphasis>
. 
<materialsCitation id="CDB13CB98531FFACFE7B9ECD036FF8C9" collectingDate="2019-06-01" collectionCode="MZSP" collectorName="La Verrugosa &amp; A. Kozlov &amp; Y. Kovaleva" country="Panama" latitude="8.78008" location="Fortuna Cabins" longLatPrecision="1" longitude="-82.19103" municipality="La Verrugosa" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Ngobe-Bugle" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="A26288468531FFACFE7B9ECD01EDF8E5" box="[387,491,1773,1799]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry id="05CE76748531FFACFD809ECD02F4F8E5" box="[632,754,1773,1799]" name="Panama" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">PANAMA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFCF89ECD0392F8E5" box="[768,916,1773,1799]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<collectingRegion id="BF1DF8068531FFACFCF89ECD0392F8E5" box="[768,916,1773,1799]" country="Panama" name="Ngobe-Bugle" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Ngöbe-Buglé</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<collectorName id="D02C53328531FFACFC5E9ECD0445F8E5" box="[934,1091,1773,1799]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<collectingMunicipality id="9D02AC9E8531FFACFC5E9ECD0445F8E5" box="[934,1091,1773,1799]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">La Verrugosa</collectingMunicipality>
</collectorName>
, 
<location id="7806603F8531FFACFBA99ECD0502F8E5" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F57087F2853EFFADFF6F9B430292FEA1:7806603F8531FFACFBA99ECD0502F8E5" box="[1105,1284,1773,1799]" country="Panama" latitude="8.78008" longLatPrecision="1" longitude="-82.19103" municipality="La Verrugosa" name="Fortuna Cabins" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" stateProvince="Ngobe-Bugle">Fortuna Cabins</location>
, 
<geoCoordinate id="18ED50238531FFACFAEA9ECD058CF8E5" box="[1298,1418,1773,1799]" degrees="8.78008" direction="north" orientation="latitude" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" precision="1" value="8.78008">8.78008ºN</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate id="18ED50238531FFACFF6F9F310122F8C9" box="[151,292,1809,1835]" degrees="82.19103" direction="west" orientation="longitude" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" precision="1" value="-82.19103">82.19103ºW</geoCoordinate>
, 
<date id="096710248531FFACFED79F3101A5F8C9" box="[303,419,1809,1835]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" value="2019-06-01">
<collectingDate id="1923E9CC8531FFACFED79F3101A5F8C9" box="[303,419,1809,1835]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" value="2019-06-01">1.VI.2019</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName id="D02C53328531FFACFE559F310227F8C9" box="[429,545,1809,1835]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">A. Kozlov</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName id="D02C53328531FFACFDBC9F3102C8F8C9" box="[580,718,1809,1835]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Y. Kovaleva</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode id="1BC8AE218531FFACFCF59F31035AF8C9" box="[781,860,1809,1835]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F8531FFACFF3F9F1501EBF891" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="7D6636E48531FFACFF3F9F1501EBF891" blockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFF3F9F150148F8AD" bold="true" box="[199,334,1845,1871]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Etymology.</emphasis>
The new species is named in honor of Anton Olegovich Kozlov (AKPC), who sent and donated the 
<typeStatus id="A26288468531FFACFF6F9F7900FFF891" box="[151,249,1881,1907]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">holotype</typeStatus>
for MZSP collection.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F8531FFADFF3F9F5D0292FEA1" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="549" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="7D6636E48531FFADFF3F9F5D0292FEA1" blockId="8.[151,1437,153,2015]" lastBlockId="9.[151,1437,153,323]" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="549" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFF3F9F5D013DF875" bold="true" box="[199,315,1917,1943]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D678531FFACFEBC9F5D0243F875" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior" authorityYear="2020" box="[324,581,1917,1943]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Plistonax" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFEBC9F5D0243F875" box="[324,581,1917,1943]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Plistonax antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFDB69F5D02AFF875" bold="true" box="[590,681,1917,1943]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="549E578D8531FFACFDB69F5D02AFF875" box="[590,681,1917,1943]" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
differs from all other species currently placed in the genus by the elytral pubescent pattern (which resembles some species of 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D678531FFACFCBC9F8103E6F859" authorityName="Haldeman" authorityYear="1847" box="[836,992,1953,1979]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFCBC9F8103E6F859" box="[836,992,1953,1979]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Aegomorphus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), mesoventral process with distinct tubercles on anterior area (indistinct, small or absent in other species of 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D678531FFACFC509FE50414F83D" authorityName="Thomson" authorityYear="1864" box="[936,1042,1989,2015]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Plistonax" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="548" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68531FFACFC509FE50414F83D" box="[936,1042,1989,2015]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="548">Plistonax</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), centrobasal crests reaching about 1/4 of elytra (at least reaching about 1/3 of elytra in the other species of the genus), and elytra with two 
<typeStatus id="A26288468530FFADFAFE98B90547FF51" box="[1286,1345,153,179]" pageId="9" pageNumber="549">types</typeStatus>
of setae placed within of punctures: thick whitish seta and slender dark brown seta (other species in the genus present only the former). Some characters shared with other species in the genus are: distal antennomeres with tubercle at inner face, and elytral apex rounded, both characters occurring in 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D678530FFADFCB899260470FEC2" authority="(Bates, 1861)" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1861" box="[832,1142,261,288]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Plistonax" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="549" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="albolinitus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68530FFADFCB8992603D2FEFD" box="[832,980,261,287]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="549">P. albolinitus</emphasis>
(Bates, 1861)
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D678530FFADFB7B9926059AFEFD" authority="Lane, 1960" authorityName="Lane" authorityYear="1960" box="[1155,1436,261,287]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Plistonax" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="549" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="inopinatus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68530FFADFB7B99260513FEFD" box="[1155,1301,262,287]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="549">P. inopinatus</emphasis>
Lane, 1960
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D678530FFADFF3F990A0297FEA1" authority="Tavakilian &amp; Neouze, 2013" authorityName="Tavakilian &amp; Neouze" authorityYear="2013" box="[199,657,297,323]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Plistonax" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="549" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="senecauxi">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68530FFADFF3F990A0156FEA1" box="[199,336,298,323]" italics="true" pageId="9" pageNumber="549">P. senecauxi</emphasis>
Tavakilian &amp; Néouze, 2013
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>