<document id="9DFFBC7E67B628D876131FCF08D9B194" ID-DOI="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4790.3.8" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3891319" ID-ZooBank="CD3B18C1-A499-4748-8487-6AD98DC3903A" _generate="added" approvalRequired="25" approvalRequired_for_bibRefs="1" approvalRequired_for_document="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="23" checkinTime="1591959525949" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Santos-Silva, Antonio, Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto De L. &amp; Júnior, José Osvaldo Silva" docDate="2020" docId="F57087F28538FFA0FF6F9A8F047AFE15" docLanguage="en" docName="zootaxa.4790.3.8.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4790 (3)" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@4c5204af" docStyleName="zootaxa.2013.journal_article" docTitle="Aegomorphus antonkozlovi Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior 2020, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="544" masterDocId="0949FF8A8539FFA4FFF898200006FFE2" masterDocTitle="Description of two new Acanthoderini, and description of the male of Oreodera advena Martins &amp; Galileo (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="550" masterPageNumber="540" pageId="1" pageNumber="541" updateTime="1625109365363" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods id="12F1065CE331D4F2BE6993A42B975E15" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="45F2AB0CDEFD1EA88F707E870ACF0648">
<mods:title id="9FDBA1027CE31F8570FF29FBFE5070F0">Description of two new Acanthoderini, and description of the male of Oreodera advena Martins &amp; Galileo (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="C261A8D6783B50D2E2DFD8DE6E261551" type="personal">
<mods:role id="E322005E9FB61AD85E0DDC05F60EBA74">
<mods:roleTerm id="B7F3951BB98ECFBBED486356AD79FF7B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="8606175F870FF92C73AEE94784E2F06B">Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="6DE142C203B0D75BF525EF1055DB3518">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, SP, Brazil &amp; toncriss @ uol. com. br; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0001 - 7128 - 1418</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="07A5E5768C7096251D9D9180BFC50B24" type="personal">
<mods:role id="75BAA45501FCA5E3DFA88642D658267F">
<mods:roleTerm id="A81721A521909B27F5424EE3BFF2CD23">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="FF33B0B652008226286DE1A30F8A44F2">Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto De L.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="69FA75A0E192DA87C910D51CA74F1F78">Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, SP, Brazil &amp; eribnascimentofl @ gmail. com; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0002 - 5047 - 8921</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name id="9EFAC91F144F643FD83A3D7A4D7E7AE9" type="personal">
<mods:role id="DB9AE94D54F4BCB259C900C1178A83DD">
<mods:roleTerm id="84CECCC978580DC61AADD680E2E26C52">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="2A6AAB30C16D68A0F6B1644CF764C8BB">Júnior, José Osvaldo Silva</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation id="C6912B9EDA3C1CBC0B72722846195E87">Department of Zoology, Setor de Ciências Biológicas, Universidade Federal do Paraná, Curitiba, PR, Brazil. &amp; juniorbio 0230 @ gmail. com; https: // orcid. org / 0000 - 0002 - 2569 - 4278</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="65AD584296851147CCCC702BB5B3DDFE">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="8A15B49E33D95D06F1CFA5B9B3147CF7" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="CF586DE53FC987D67D0BCACC86642835">
<mods:title id="47ADA0E33A5C5B27C96A616DB300099A">Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="A9A968964B5E056F614128052C7B1BA9">
<mods:date id="0E82099927E9063C036E99C84A78944D">2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="6369DCDB643CC7288B28C65E55D59467" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="D8F676BAA357E403C8519E259DB9556A">2020-06-12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="ED0F08E231DAED516BAA1D2AA1067A2D" type="volume">
<mods:number id="5673E83FCD2921DC1CA8AB0E0D991AFE">4790</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="D0AC2F9BD1EBB83BA862F1EAF5E1A0DC" type="issue">
<mods:number id="109DC5CD0FCD7F98CB88A1FD6FD1A852">3</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="28B1899176E91E87953F1B462F72A6BC" unit="page">
<mods:start id="FFED761AF5D1EF46E214632E11AA5F25">540</mods:start>
<mods:end id="00C6BE112A0A4BF2499AEDDD2C0FC8BA">550</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="0C435BD759E254852CD4CCF7BA28504F">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="C559EFF6158F7DEE4A90171B42267302" type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4790.3.8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="E2CC5764DE99C9DBEA19FC4FC38F8AD7" type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="527BAFCEE85066FA5C0FF5E4656F391F" type="Zenodo-Dep">3891319</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="FFE05C82150953D2CED351A41038D5F1" type="ZooBank">CD3B18C1-A499-4748-8487-6AD98DC3903A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="F57087F28538FFA0FF6F9A8F047AFE15" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F57087F28538FFA0FF6F9A8F047AFE15" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F57087F28538FFA0FF6F9A8F047AFE15" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="544" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">
<subSubSection id="35C3656F8538FFA5FF6F9A8F024EFD28" box="[151,584,687,714]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="7D6636E48538FFA5FF6F9A8F024EFD28" blockId="1.[151,584,687,750]" box="[151,584,687,714]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">
<heading id="262E81888538FFA5FF6F9A8F024EFD28" bold="true" box="[151,584,687,714]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="541" reason="1">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68538FFA5FF6F9A8F024EFD28" bold="true" box="[151,584,687,714]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D678538FFA5FF6F9A8F01E5FD28" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior" authorityYear="2020" box="[151,483,687,714]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="541" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68538FFA5FF6F9A8F01E5FD28" bold="true" box="[151,483,687,714]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">Aegomorphus antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="549E578D8538FFA5FE129A90024EFD28" box="[490,584,688,714]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F8538FFA6FF6F9AF303D9F8C9" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="542" pageId="1" pageNumber="541" type="description">
<paragraph id="7D6636E48538FFA5FF6F9AF30114FD0C" blockId="1.[151,584,687,750]" box="[151,274,723,750]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">
(
<figureCitation id="E5E22A618538FFA5FF679AF3010FFD0C" box="[159,265,723,750]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–8" captionStartId="3.[151,264,1967,1992]" captionTargetBox="[181,1409,183,1934]" captionTargetId="figure@3.[177,1409,179,1940]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURES 1–8. Aegomorphus antonkozlovi. 1–5) Holotype male: 1) Dorsal habitus; 2) Ventral habitus; 3) Lateral habitus; 4) Head, frontal view; 5) Eye. 6–8) Paratypes: 6) Female, dorsal habitus; 7) Female, ventral habitus; 8) Male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891321" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891321/files/figure.png" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">Figs. 1–8</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E48538FFA5FF6F9B340180FBAD" blockId="1.[151,1437,788,2039]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68538FFA5FF6F9B3401DBFCCD" bold="true" box="[151,477,788,815]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">
Description. 
<typeStatus id="A26288468538FFA5FED79B35019AFCCD" box="[303,412,789,815]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">Holotype</typeStatus>
male
</emphasis>
(
<figureCitation id="E5E22A618538FFA5FE149B350251FCCD" box="[492,599,788,815]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–8" captionStartId="3.[151,264,1967,1992]" captionTargetBox="[181,1409,183,1934]" captionTargetId="figure@3.[177,1409,179,1940]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURES 1–8. Aegomorphus antonkozlovi. 1–5) Holotype male: 1) Dorsal habitus; 2) Ventral habitus; 3) Lateral habitus; 4) Head, frontal view; 5) Eye. 6–8) Paratypes: 6) Female, dorsal habitus; 7) Female, ventral habitus; 8) Male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891321" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891321/files/figure.png" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">Figs. 1–5</figureCitation>
). Integument mostly dark brown, almost black; mouthparts reddish brown, except maxillary palpomeres II–IV and labial palpomeres II–III dark brown or dark reddish brown with apex yellowish brown or reddish brown; antennomere III brown on basal third, gradually reddish brown toward beginning of posterior fifth, then dark brown toward apex; antennomere IV reddish brown on anterior third, slightly lighter on central third, dark brown on posterior third; antennomeres V–X orangish on about basal 2/3, dark brown on remaining surface; antennomere XI reddish brown on basal half, dark brown on apical half. Protibiae slightly reddish near middle; mesotibiae reddish near middle and on apex; metatibiae dark brown basally and remaining surface mostly reddish (slightly brownish before and after middle). Yellowish-white and grayish-white pubescence whiter depending on light intensity.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E48538FFA6FF3F9C7901FEFF19" blockId="1.[151,1437,788,2039]" lastBlockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="542" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF68538FFA5FF3F9C790108FB91" bold="true" box="[199,270,1113,1139]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">Head.</emphasis>
Frons coarsely, sparsely punctate; with yellowish-white pubescence partially obscuring integument, but exposing punctures, slightly yellowish brown on some areas. Area between antennal tubercles and upper eye lobes with sculpturing and pubescence as on frons; remaining surface of vertex and area behind upper eye lobes coarsely punctate only close to eyes, with dense yellowish-white pubescence close to eyes, with oblique glabrous band on each side, nearly glabrous on central area of vertex close to prothorax, and sparsely pubescent on remaining surface behind upper eye lobes. Area behind lower eye lobes finely, somewhat abundantly punctate; with narrow yellowish-white pubescent band on superior area close to eye, with wide white pubescent macula close to inferior area of eye, glabrous on remaining surface. Genae minutely striate-punctate except smooth apex; with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument on striate-punctate area, glabrous on smooth area. Postclypeus coarsely punctate on sides of wide central area, smooth centrally and laterally; glabrous on smooth areas, with yellowish-white pubescence on punctate areas, and tuft of long golden-yellow setae directed forward on each of wide central area close to anteclypeus. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior 2/3, oblique at anterior third; with yellowishwhite pubescence not obscuring integument on posterior 2/3, nearly glabrous on anterior third, and with fringe of golden-yellow setae on anterior margin. Antennal tubercles densely, minutely punctate; pubescence as on frons. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous on wide posterior area; depressed, somewhat finely striate, with sparse yellowishwhite pubescence on narrow anterior area. Distance (only 
<typeStatus id="A26288468538FFA5FCDE9E55038EF96D" box="[806,904,1653,1679]" pageId="1" pageNumber="541">holotype</typeStatus>
measured) between upper eye lobes 0.35 times length of scape (0.21 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.86 times length of scape (0.52 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 1.7 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at basal third of antennomere VIII. Scape with yellowish-white pubescence nearly obscuring integument, except dorsal surface with part of surface with yellowish-brown pubescence. Pedicel with yellowish-white pubescence, distinctly denser on apex of dorsal and lateral areas, sparser on some areas of anterior 2/3. Antennomere III with three yellowish-white pubescent rings, one basally, one between middle and posterior quarter, another narrow at apex; remaining surface with brownish pubescence, with short, decumbent yellowishwhite setae interspersed. Remaining antennomeres with yellowish-white pubescence on anterior 2/3, brownish on posterior third. Inner area of ventral surface with short, erect, sparse yellowish setae; apex of antennomere IX with moderately long brownish setae at apex of inner area of ventral surface; ventral surface of posterior third of anten- nomere X, and basal third of XI with long, erect, moderately abundant brown setae. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.65; pedicel = 0.29; IV = 0.77; V = 0.57; VI = 0.46; VII = 0.42; VIII = 0.37; IX = 0.35; X = 0.29; XI = 0.26.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853BFFA6FF3F99250450FB25" blockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF3F99250121FEFD" bold="true" box="[199,295,261,287]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax with large, conical laterocentral tubercles, with apex curved upward. Pronotum with large, elevated, subconical tubercle on each side of anterior half (apex rounded), and longitudinal, slightly elevated gibbosity on center of posterior half; coarsely abundantly punctate, except smooth central gibbosity and anterolateral tubercles; with dense yellowish-white pubescence, except glabrous top of anterolateral tubercles, yellowish-brown pubescent macula on each side of posterior half, on central gibbosity, and surrounding outer area of anterolateral tubercles; with a few long, erect yellowish-white setae interspersed. Sides of prothorax coarsely, somewhat abundantly punctate; with dense yellowish-white pubescence, not obscuring punctures. Prosternum with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, denser laterally. Prosternal process with straight laterocentral margins; narrowest area slightly narrower than half of width of procoxal cavity. Mesoventrite almost glabrous centrally, with grayish-white pubescence laterally. Mesoventral process slightly expanded to apex, covered with grayish-white setae. Mesanepisternum and mesepimeron with grayish-white pubescence almost obscuring integument, slightly yellower on small area of mesanepisternum close to procoxal cavity. Metanepisternum with yellowish-brown pubescence basally, grayish-white on remaining surface. Metaventrite with grayish-white pubescence, denser more yellowish on transverse band on each side near to metacoxae. Scutellum semicircular, with yellowish-white pubescence. 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF1E9ADD013FFCF5" bold="true" box="[230,313,765,791]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Elytra.</emphasis>
With slightly elevated, longitudinal, centrobasal crest on anterior fifth; humeri rounded, somewhat projected forward; surface coarsely, somewhat abundantly punctate (punctures slightly finer toward apex, somewhat scabrous basally); posterior margin concave, with outer and sutural angles rounded (sutural angle wider); elytral pubescence both yellowish-white, yellowish-brown, dark brown, and white, forming complex pattern (
<figureCitation id="E5E22A61853BFFA6FB0A9B490535FC61" box="[1266,1331,873,899]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–8" captionStartId="3.[151,264,1967,1992]" captionTargetBox="[181,1409,183,1934]" captionTargetId="figure@3.[177,1409,179,1940]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURES 1–8. Aegomorphus antonkozlovi. 1–5) Holotype male: 1) Dorsal habitus; 2) Ventral habitus; 3) Lateral habitus; 4) Head, frontal view; 5) Eye. 6–8) Paratypes: 6) Female, dorsal habitus; 7) Female, ventral habitus; 8) Male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891321" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891321/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Fig. 1</figureCitation>
); surface with moderately long, erect brown setae throughout, inserted into anterior portion of punctures. 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FB309BAD0501FC45" bold="true" box="[1224,1287,909,935]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Legs.</emphasis>
Femora with grayish-white pubescence partially obscuring integument. Protibiae with three grayish-white pubescent bands, on basally, forming distinct ring, on about middle, not reaching ventral surface, another on apex, not reaching ventral surface; remaining dorsal and lateral surfaces with sparse grayish-white pubescence; ventral surface with dense, bristly yellowish-brown pubescence on posterior 2/3. Meso- and metatibiae with three grayish-white pubescent bands dorsally and laterally, one basally, one about middle, another on apex; remaining dorsal and lateral surfaces with sparse grayish-white pubescence, except posterior half of mesotibiae with short, erect, thick yellowish-brown setae on outer margin; ventral surface entirely covered with grayish-white pubescence, except apex of ventral surface with yellowish-brown pubescence. Protarsomeres with long black setae laterally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853BFFA6FF3F9CF004DCFAED" blockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF3F9CF00145FB09" bold="true" box="[199,323,1232,1259]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Ventrites with grayish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, slightly denser near apex, which is glabrous centrally on ventrites I–IV; apex of ventrite V truncate, slightly emarginated centrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853BFFA6FF3F9D390198FA99" blockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF3F9D390118FAD1" bold="true" box="[199,286,1305,1331]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Female</emphasis>
(
<figureCitation id="E5E22A61853BFFA6FED59D39019FFAD6" box="[301,409,1305,1332]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–8" captionStartId="3.[151,264,1967,1992]" captionTargetBox="[181,1409,183,1934]" captionTargetId="figure@3.[177,1409,179,1940]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURES 1–8. Aegomorphus antonkozlovi. 1–5) Holotype male: 1) Dorsal habitus; 2) Ventral habitus; 3) Lateral habitus; 4) Head, frontal view; 5) Eye. 6–8) Paratypes: 6) Female, dorsal habitus; 7) Female, ventral habitus; 8) Male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891321" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891321/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Figs. 6–7</figureCitation>
). Antennae slightly shorter, reaching elytral apex at apex of antennomere VII; protarsomeres without long black setae laterally; scape distinctly more slender; abdominal ventrite V longer, longitudinally sulcate from base to near apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853BFFA6FF3F9DA402EEF979" blockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF3F9DA40139FA7D" bold="true" box="[199,319,1412,1439]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Variation.</emphasis>
All structures of the mouthparts almost entirely dark brown, almost black; antennomeres entirely dark brown or with some slightly reddish areas; pubescent rings of the basal antennomeres absent or nearly so ventrally; tibiae with or without reddish rings; vertex and area behind upper eye lobes entirely pubescent (pubescence from yellowish-white to slightly brownish); genae somewhat minutely rugose-punctate; dorsal surface of scape mostly with yellowish-brown pubescence or with pubescence entirely yellowish-white; pedicel with dorsal and lateral pubescence mostly yellowish-brown; scutellum glabrous on some areas; elytral centrobasal crest absent or nearly so; elytral pubescence very variable (
<figureCitation id="E5E22A61853BFFA6FD7B9E7D030FF995" box="[643,777,1629,1655]" captionStart="FIGURES 1–8" captionStartId="3.[151,264,1967,1992]" captionTargetBox="[181,1409,183,1934]" captionTargetId="figure@3.[177,1409,179,1940]" captionTargetPageId="3" captionText="FIGURES 1–8. Aegomorphus antonkozlovi. 1–5) Holotype male: 1) Dorsal habitus; 2) Ventral habitus; 3) Lateral habitus; 4) Head, frontal view; 5) Eye. 6–8) Paratypes: 6) Female, dorsal habitus; 7) Female, ventral habitus; 8) Male, dorsal habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891321" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891321/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Figs. 1, 6, 8</figureCitation>
), often with one or two arched dark band on posterior half, or with large dark macula centrally and/or anteriorly.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853BFFA6FF3F9E8403D9F8C9" blockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF3F9E8403DEF95D" bold="true" box="[199,984,1700,1727]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
Dimensions (mm), 
<typeStatus id="A2628846853BFFA6FE5C9E85020DF95D" box="[420,523,1701,1727]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">holotype</typeStatus>
male/ 
<typeStatus id="A2628846853BFFA6FDAA9E8402C1F95D" box="[594,711,1700,1727]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">paratypes</typeStatus>
male/ 
<typeStatus id="A2628846853BFFA6FCF79E840382F95D" box="[783,900,1700,1727]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">paratypes</typeStatus>
female
</emphasis>
. Total length, 12.90/10.95–14.65/12.50– 14.65; prothoracic length, 2.55/2.00–2.75/2.20–2.55; anterior prothoracic width, 3.35/2.80–3.75/3.10–3.80; posterior prothoracic width, 3.20/2.65–3.60/2.95–3.55; maximum prothoracic width, 4.25/3.50–4.85/3.90–4.75; humeral width, 5.15/4.15–5.75/4.90–5.70; elytral length, 9.05/6.65–9.80/8.35–9.35.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F853BFFA6FF3F9F1504DEF875" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853BFFA6FF3F9F1504DEF875" blockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF3F9F150177F8AD" bold="true" box="[199,369,1844,1871]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Type material</emphasis>
. 
<materialsCitation id="CDB13CB9853BFFA6FE799F15046EF891" collectingDate="2016-12-21" collectionCode="V, MZSP" collectorName="Sinyaev" country="Peru" elevation="1300" latitude="-7.8861666" location="Chagual" longLatPrecision="13" longitude="-77.621" municipality="Sanchez Carrion Province" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="La Libertad" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus id="A2628846853BFFA6FE799F1501EFF8AD" box="[385,489,1845,1871]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry id="05CE7674853BFFA6FD8C9F1502B8F8AD" box="[628,702,1845,1871]" name="Peru" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">PERU</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion id="BF1DF806853BFFA6FD349F150351F8AD" box="[716,855,1845,1871]" country="Peru" name="La Libertad" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">La Libertad</collectingRegion>
: 
<collectingMunicipality id="9D02AC9E853BFFA6FC9C9F150497F8AD" box="[868,1169,1845,1871]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Sánchez Carrión Province</collectingMunicipality>
, road PE 10C km 109, 
<geoCoordinate id="18ED5023853BFFA6FF6F9F780103F891" box="[151,261,1880,1907]" degrees="7" direction="south" minutes="53.17" orientation="latitude" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" precision="9" value="-7.8861666">7º53.17’S</geoCoordinate>
/ 
<geoCoordinate id="18ED5023853BFFA6FEE69F7901A0F891" box="[286,422,1881,1907]" degrees="77" direction="west" minutes="37.26" orientation="longitude" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" precision="9" value="-77.621">77º37.26’W</geoCoordinate>
, near 
<location id="7806603F853BFFA6FE139F79024DF891" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F57087F28538FFA0FF6F9A8F047AFE15:7806603F853BFFA6FE139F79024DF891" box="[491,587,1881,1907]" country="Peru" latitude="-7.8861666" longLatPrecision="13" longitude="-77.621" municipality="Sanchez Carrion Province" name="Chagual" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" stateProvince="La Libertad">Chagual</location>
, 
<quantity id="BA219B01853BFFA6FDA09F7902B6F891" box="[600,688,1881,1907]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.3" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" unit="m" value="1300.0">
<elevation id="F6F4D1D7853BFFA6FDA09F7902B6F891" box="[600,688,1881,1907]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.3" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" unit="m" value="1300.0">1300 m</elevation>
</quantity>
, 
<date id="09671024853BFFA6FD459F79034FF891" box="[701,841,1881,1907]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" value="2016-12-21">
<collectingDate id="1923E9CC853BFFA6FD459F79034FF891" box="[701,841,1881,1907]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" value="2016-12-21">21.XII.2016</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectionCode id="1BC8AE21853BFFA6FCAD9F79036FF891" box="[853,873,1881,1907]" country="Canada" lsid="urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:13946" name="Royal British Columbia Museum - Herbarium" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="Museum">V</collectionCode>
. 
<collectorName id="D02C5332853BFFA6FC8D9F7903C9F891" box="[885,975,1881,1907]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Sinyaev</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode id="1BC8AE21853BFFA6FBE99F790466F891" box="[1041,1120,1881,1907]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<typeStatus id="A2628846853BFFA6FB8C9F7904E7F891" box="[1140,1249,1881,1907]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Paratypes</typeStatus>
– 
<specimenCount id="6BDFFD6D853BFFA6FAF89F79055CF891" box="[1280,1370,1881,1907]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="male">8 males</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount id="6BDFFD6D853BFFA6FA9F9F7900DDF875" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="female">2 females</specimenCount>
, 
<materialsCitation id="CDB13CB9853BFFA6FF1F9F5D04D2F875" box="[231,1236,1917,1943]" collectingDate="2016-12-21" collectionCode="AKPC, MZSP" collectorName="Sinyaev" country="Peru" elevation="1300" latitude="-7.8861666" location="Chagual" longLatPrecision="13" longitude="-77.621" municipality="Sanchez Carrion Province" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" specimenCount="10" specimenCount-female="2" specimenCount-male="8" stateProvince="La Libertad" typeStatus="paratype">
same data as holotype (
<specimenCount id="6BDFFD6D853BFFA6FE159F5D0240F875" box="[493,582,1917,1943]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="male">3 males</specimenCount>
, 
<collectionCode id="1BC8AE21853BFFA6FDA89F5D0298F875" box="[592,670,1917,1943]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">AKPC</collectionCode>
; 
<specimenCount id="6BDFFD6D853BFFA6FD529F5D02FEF875" box="[682,760,1917,1943]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="male">1 male</specimenCount>
, CCT-UFMG; 
<specimenCount id="6BDFFD6D853BFFA6FC589F5D03FFF875" box="[928,1017,1917,1943]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="male">4 males</specimenCount>
, 
<specimenCount id="6BDFFD6D853BFFA6FBFC9F5D0475F875" box="[1028,1139,1917,1943]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="female">2 females</specimenCount>
, 
<collectionCode id="1BC8AE21853BFFA6FB869F5D04CAF875" box="[1150,1228,1917,1943]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F853BFFA6FF3F9F81035CF83D" pageId="2" pageNumber="542" type="etymology">
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853BFFA6FF3F9F81035CF83D" blockId="2.[151,1437,153,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853BFFA6FF3F9F810148F859" bold="true" box="[199,334,1953,1979]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">Etymology.</emphasis>
The new species is named in honor of Anton Olegovich Kozlov (AKPC), who sent the types, and donated the 
<typeStatus id="A2628846853BFFA6FED89FE50184F83D" box="[288,386,1989,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">holotype</typeStatus>
and some 
<typeStatus id="A2628846853BFFA6FE039FE50260F83D" box="[507,614,1989,2015]" pageId="2" pageNumber="542">paratypes</typeStatus>
for MZSP collection.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<caption id="29A6666C853AFFA7FF6F9F8F056CF80E" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3891321" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3891321" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3891321/files/figure.png" pageId="3" pageNumber="543" startId="3.[151,264,1967,1992]" targetBox="[181,1409,183,1934]" targetPageId="3">
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853AFFA7FF6F9F8F056CF80E" blockId="3.[151,1437,1967,2028]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FF6F9F8F013DF82A" bold="true" box="[151,315,1967,1992]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">FIGURES 1–8.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853AFFA7FEBB9F90025EF82A" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior" authorityYear="2020" box="[323,600,1968,1992]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="543" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FEBB9F90025EF82A" box="[323,600,1968,1992]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">Aegomorphus antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
. 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FD9E9F8F0293F82A" bold="true" box="[614,661,1967,1992]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">1–5)</emphasis>
Holotype male: 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FCB99F8F0350F82A" bold="true" box="[833,854,1967,1992]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">1)</emphasis>
Dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FBF89F8F0413F82A" bold="true" box="[1024,1045,1967,1992]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">2)</emphasis>
Ventral habitus; 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FB3C9F8F04DCF82A" bold="true" box="[1220,1242,1967,1992]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">3)</emphasis>
Lateral habitus; 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FA7F9F8F059BF82A" bold="true" box="[1415,1437,1967,1992]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">4)</emphasis>
Head, frontal view; 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FE9A9FF30171F80E" bold="true" box="[354,375,2003,2028]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">5)</emphasis>
Eye. 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FE499FF301D9F80E" bold="true" box="[433,479,2003,2028]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">6–8)</emphasis>
Paratypes: 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FDAE9FF3026DF80E" bold="true" box="[598,619,2003,2028]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">6)</emphasis>
Female, dorsal habitus; 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FC9B9FF3037FF80E" bold="true" box="[867,889,2003,2028]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">7)</emphasis>
Female, ventral habitus; 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853AFFA7FB819FF30489F80E" bold="true" box="[1145,1167,2003,2028]" pageId="3" pageNumber="543">8)</emphasis>
Male, dorsal habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<subSubSection id="35C3656F853DFFA0FF3F98B9047AFE15" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" type="discussion">
<paragraph id="7D6636E4853DFFA0FF3F98B9047AFE15" blockId="4.[151,1437,153,503]" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FF3F98B90132FF51" bold="true" box="[199,308,153,179]" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">Remarks</emphasis>
. 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FEBB98B90270FF51" authority="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior, 2020" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior" authorityYear="2020" box="[323,630,153,179]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FEBB98B90270FF51" box="[323,630,153,179]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">Aegomorphus antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FD8698B902DFFF51" bold="true" box="[638,729,153,179]" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">
<taxonomicNameLabel id="549E578D853DFFA0FD8698B902DFFF51" box="[638,729,153,179]" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FC8898B904CDFF51" authority="(Gyllenhal, 1817)" baseAuthorityName="Gyllenhal" baseAuthorityYear="1817" box="[880,1227,153,179]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="modestus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FC8898B903FEFF51" box="[880,1016,153,179]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. modestus</emphasis>
(Gyllenhal, 1817)
</taxonomicName>
, but differs as follows: upper eye lobes wide, width distinct larger than basal diameter of the antennomere III; distance between upper eye lobes slightly larger than width of one lobe. In 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FD3498C10355FF19" baseAuthorityName="Gyllenhal" baseAuthorityYear="1817" box="[716,851,225,251]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="modestus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FD3498C10355FF19" box="[716,851,225,251]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. modestus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, upper eye lobes about as wide as the basal diameter of the antennomere III, and the distance between upper eye lobes larger than three times the width of one lobe. It differs from 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FEDF990903BBFEA1" authority="galapagoensis (Linell, 1898)" authorityName="galapagoensis (Linell" authorityYear="1898" baseAuthorityName="Linell" baseAuthorityYear="1898" box="[295,957,297,323]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="galapagoensis" subSpecies="galapagoensis">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FEDF99090310FEA1" box="[295,790,297,323]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">Aegomorphus galapagoensis galapagoensis</emphasis>
(Linell, 1898)
</taxonomicName>
, 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FC329909047BFEA1" box="[970,1149,297,323]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. g. vonhageni</emphasis>
(Mutchler, 1938), and 
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FA7C9909011DFE85" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. g. williamsi</emphasis>
(Linsley &amp; Chemsak, 1966) by the distance between upper eye lobes slightly larger than width of one lobe (more than two times in the three subspecies of 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FD1E995103A1FE69" box="[742,935,369,395]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="galapagoensis">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FD1E995103A1FE69" box="[742,935,369,395]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. galapagoensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
). 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FC46995104F6FE69" authorityName="Santos-Silva &amp; Nascimento &amp; Júnior" authorityYear="2020" box="[958,1264,369,395]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="antonkozlovi">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FC46995104F6FE69" box="[958,1264,369,395]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">Aegomorphus antonkozlovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FA7C99510230FE4D" authority="(Chemsak &amp; Hovore, 2002)" baseAuthorityName="Chemsak &amp; Hovore" baseAuthorityYear="2002" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="penrosei">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FA7C995100F0FE4D" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. penrosei</emphasis>
(Chemsak &amp; Hovore, 2002)
</taxonomicName>
by the antennomere III in male distinctly longer than IV (slightly longer in 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FA7C99B500F0FE31" baseAuthorityName="Chemsak &amp; Hovore" baseAuthorityYear="2002" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="penrosei">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FA7C99B500F0FE31" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. penrosei</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
). It can be separated from 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FDDA999903B7FE31" authority="(Galileo &amp; Martins, 2012)" baseAuthorityName="Galileo &amp; Martins" baseAuthorityYear="2012" box="[546,945,441,467]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pictus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FDDA99990282FE31" box="[546,644,441,467]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. pictus</emphasis>
(Galileo &amp; Martins, 2012)
</taxonomicName>
by the elytral apex not rounded (rounded in 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FF6F99FD00FFFE15" baseAuthorityName="Galileo &amp; Martins" baseAuthorityYear="2012" box="[151,249,477,503]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pictus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FF6F99FD00FFFE15" box="[151,249,477,503]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. pictus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
), and elytral centrobasal crest slightly elevated (distinctly elevated in 
<taxonomicName id="BAD94D67853DFFA0FBF199FD046DFE15" baseAuthorityName="Galileo &amp; Martins" baseAuthorityYear="2012" box="[1033,1131,477,503]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Aegomorphus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="544" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pictus">
<emphasis id="4FADEAF6853DFFA0FBF199FD046DFE15" box="[1033,1131,477,503]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="544">A. pictus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>