<document id="F8A7A269B1651545CA34CCB885D62E76" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5286216" ID-ISSN="0253-116X" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5286216" _generate="added" approvalRequired="13" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="12" approvalRequired_for_treatments="1" checkinTime="1630047546148" checkinUser="marcus" docAuthor="M, Alexander" docDate="2015" docId="FF316C04FFB7FF83FF6EFA0B075F1AE0" docLanguage="en" docName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2015.47.2.1865-1884.pdf" docOrigin="Linzer biologische Beiträge 47 (2)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0.7:LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleId="24E5EB772D355DE2EE23B1E8D07853E0" docStyleName="LinzerbiolBeitr.2006-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="7" docTitle="Londokia kasparyani M 2015, nov.sp." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="1879" masterDocId="0308147CFFBCFF8DFFDCFFCD041B1A10" masterDocTitle="Ichneumon flies of the tribe Joppocryptini of Palaearctic. Description of new genus Londokia nov. gen. and two new species L. kasparyani nov. sp. and L. leleji nov. sp. (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae)" masterLastPageNumber="1884" masterPageNumber="1865" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876" updateTime="1630059861267" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods id="A4C7C9B1EF18EAF955E09A984F75B416" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="12F802252267D9AB8D72840D8EF2E6E9">
<mods:title id="E9988ECB6636878863D721F01BEFE52C">Ichneumon flies of the tribe Joppocryptini of Palaearctic. Description of new genus Londokia nov. gen. and two new species L. kasparyani nov. sp. and L. leleji nov. sp. (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ichneumoninae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="BD5EB99525837C5CF472EB724C9D5595" type="personal">
<mods:role id="0A85381E77BBF057682A019009A3EC58">
<mods:roleTerm id="8D80F534519595628DC6B959D293211B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="0346EB8C9F361AD3525BE25CEC5B37AF">M, Alexander</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="A4CD74AE24BA56E101DC6D4F4DF20754">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="8785377E89BB35CB4115AC2B7A0FFB94" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="73FBDB37B2B6C54130F005B117D0FD7D">
<mods:title id="4418450082B69FA8D6B841BA96385F0E">Linzer biologische Beiträge</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="6CD677955066DE436E98A4098735714C">
<mods:date id="9EF82503BEFA58DDF9CD046293E96DA3">2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="0ED3BD8352BC899D9FE05F04C1CB0342" type="pubDate">
<mods:number id="1BAA3D19E59FC3F558EBD53A01A79358">2015-12-30</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="82A7258034199547589191C73A145364" type="volume">
<mods:number id="A90BC95F0BA557FB986F4F71266D7F70">47</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail id="B3D51FB51513AEC5D3E10608CD117C38" type="issue">
<mods:number id="77CE57E0F5BE977A0181BF5F5B427C96">2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="8DBB1F5570B7206E6C12D0D70F2F8B65" unit="page">
<mods:start id="F6F6C35658A46AC314B84780B875E9C2">1865</mods:start>
<mods:end id="DD2A4B7780B6C0B3EFCC7DED41679396">1884</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification id="5E5090F0774FBAD66242E0E027A698CF">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="F417E9F29D6B5C1BE6F855CFA522E303" type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5286216</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="B295E7E442E5DF888C14178EC503DBC5" type="ISSN">0253-116X</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier id="034369ED9B8886A5C07D3555D7566380" type="Zenodo-Dep">5286216</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="FF316C04FFB7FF83FF6EFA0B075F1AE0" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:FF316C04FFB7FF83FF6EFA0B075F1AE0" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FF316C04FFB7FF83FF6EFA0B075F1AE0" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="1879" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876">
<subSubSection id="3F828E99FFB7FF86FF6EFA0B05EE1C22" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB7FF86FF6EFA0B06581FCC" blockId="11.[178,579,1478,1500]" box="[178,579,1478,1500]" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876">
<heading id="2C6F6A7EFFB7FF86FF6EFA0B06581FCC" box="[178,579,1478,1500]" fontSize="8" level="2" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876" reason="2">
<emphasis id="45EC0100FFB7FF86FF6EFA0B06581FCC" bold="true" box="[178,579,1478,1500]" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876">
<taxonomicName id="B098A691FFB7FF86FF6EFA0B05941FCC" authority="M, 2015" authorityName="M" authorityYear="2015" box="[178,399,1478,1500]" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Londokia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kasparyani" status="nov.sp.">
<emphasis id="45EC0100FFB7FF86FF6EFA0B05941FCC" bold="true" box="[178,399,1478,1500]" italics="true" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876">Londokia kasparyani</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="5EDFBC7BFFB7FF86FE4AFA0B05F91FCB" box="[406,482,1478,1499]" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876" rank="species">nov.sp.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Plate 2)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB7FF86FF6EFA2105EE1C22" blockId="11.[178,1085,1516,1586]" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876">
H o l o t y p e, Russian Far East, Evrejskaja AO, zh-d. st. Londoko, Querceetum and flood plain, 03.08.198 1, Kasparyan leg. The 
<typeStatus id="A82363B0FFB7FF86FD8EF9C906B91C0A" box="[594,674,1540,1562]" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876">holotype</typeStatus>
is deposited in the collection of Zoologycal Institute RAS, 
<collectingRegion id="B55C13F0FFB7FF86FEB3F9D105EA1C22" box="[367,497,1564,1586]" country="Russia" name="Saint Petersburg" pageId="11" pageNumber="1876">St. Petersburg</collectingRegion>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="3F828E99FFB0FF83FF6EFF16075F1AE0" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="1879" pageId="12" pageNumber="1877" type="description">
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB0FF81FF6EFF1604E51AE0" blockId="12.[178,254,219,241]" box="[178,254,219,241]" pageId="12" pageNumber="1877">M a l e</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB0FF81FF6EFECC07E71B41" blockId="12.[178,1086,256,337]" pageId="12" pageNumber="1877">F l a g e l l u m: Bristle-shaped, 30-segments, ribbed from segment 4, not widened behind middle; distinct tyloides absent, only big indistinct oval darkenings on their place. Flagellum 1,1 times shorter than front wing and 1,4 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB0FF81FF6EFEAD07731EF4" blockId="12.[178,1086,352,1252]" pageId="12" pageNumber="1877">H e a d: Head contour from front roundly narrowed downwards, transversal, 1,2 times wider than height; eyes large, temples from front visible in 1/5 of lower part of an eye; genae short, malar space 10,4 times shorter than height of an eye; head from above rather stout, 2 times wider than length in middle. Vertex from lateral behind hind ocelli smoothly, but sharply slanting down to occipital carina; temples rather narrow, 1,1 times shorter than longitudinal diameter of an eye in the middle, from above sharply roundly narrowed behind eyes, from side parallel to hind margin of an eye; occipital carina from above slightly roundly impressed far not reach level of eyes and hind ocelli, sharp all round, meeting with hypostomal carina practically reach of mandible base; hypostomal carina on short distance before meeting with occipital one curves and situated adjoining to occipital carina; hypostomal carina not visible from lateral; malar space short, 3 times shorter by length then mandible base width; mandibles sickle-shaped, strongly curved and bordered by lover (inner) margin, upper tooth long and sharp, lower one only just marked, but distinct, strongly moved inside in comparison with upper tooth, not visible from front; clypeus two times broader than height, convex at base and impressed from middle to apex, only just visible separated from face by very weak broad impression, clypeus with distinctly emarginate front margin, lateral margins oblique with rounded angles, bordered by front margin; clypeal foveae sharp, slit-like with broad impression around them; labrum narrow, triangle, equal by breadth to central part of front margin of clypeus; middle field of face very slightly elevated above lateral fields and only just marked, approximately equal by breadth to lateral fields in middle; antennal cavities not great, not sharp, almost merged in middle, laterally reach borders of eyes without distinct upper border, with weak lateral tubercles, tubercle between antennal fossae only just marked; antennal fossae small, front margins of antennal fossae quite high elevated above lateral fields; ocelli of normal size, diameter of lateral ocellus 1,1 times less than distance from ocellus to an eye; ocellar triangle only just elevated. Upper part of clypeus punctured by big connivent smoothed punctures more sparse to apex, apical third smooth, front and lateral margins bordered; surface of face punctured by big smoothed convinient punctures; frons under front ocellus with weak smoothed wrinkling and puncturation; vertex and temples with sparse smoothed irregular punctures; surface of head between sculptural formations characteristically smoothly-granulated, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB0FF80FF6EFB39003918D5" blockId="12.[178,1085,1267,1582]" lastBlockId="13.[178,1085,219,709]" lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="1878" pageId="12" pageNumber="1877">
T h o r a x: Collar of pronotum long with straight front margin, transverse furrow of pronotum narrow, shallow, not interrupted by keel; pronotal base almost straight with sharp apical angle; epomiae strong, pronotal ridge slightly thickened; surface of pronotum in upper half densely punctured by small smoothed punctures and smoothly wrinklypunctured in lower one. Mesonotum moderately convex, 1,1 times longer than breadth; notauli narrow, distinct almost to middle of mesonotum; surface of mesonotum very densely punctured by connivent punctures, dull, interspaces between punctures with granulated sculpture; prepectus with smoothed wrinkling, shining; prepectal carina apically far not reach margin of pronotum; subalarum thickened; speculum smooth, not punctured; mesopleural fovea not expressed, but area around it broadly impressed; lower part of mesopleurae (mesosternum) not separated angularly, with gradual bend; sternauli absent; mesopleurae densely smoothly wrinkly-punctured by irregular punctures; surface of mesopleurae polished in upper 2/3 and with granulated sculpture between punctures in lower part; scutellum high elevated above postscutellum, bordered laterally by carinae up to apex, horizontal part of scutellum convex, densely punctured by round punctures, matt, with granulated sculpture between punctures; vertical surface of scutellum and postscutellum sculpturated similarly. Hind margin of metanotum with triangle projections opposite lateral longitudinal carinae. Propodeum from lateral of broken 
<typeStatus id="A82363B0FFB1FF80FC38FE4600091BB0" box="[996,1042,395,416]" pageId="13" pageNumber="1878">type</typeStatus>
, but more over slanted backwards with convex horizontal part, its horizontal part 1,7 times shorter than area posteromedia in middle; all carinae of propodeum sharp; basal area short, convex with weak knoll; area superomedia hexagonal, with equal length and breadth, narrowed and rounded from costulae anteriad; costulae in middle of area superomedia; areae dentiparae at apices without denticles; carina closing area dentipara and area spiraculifera at apex broadened almost leaf-like; spiracles long, 2,7 times longer than width. Surface of area superomedia polished, area dentipara with big angular connivent punctures, area spiraculifera wrinkled; metapleurae with big irregular punctures with polished intervals between them; surface of propodeum without microsculpture, polished; propodeum, with exception of area superomedia, with long light pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB1FF80FF6EFD1806E01918" blockId="13.[178,1085,724,776]" pageId="13" pageNumber="1878">L e g s: Very long and slender, hind femur and tibiae slightly thickened; hind coxae with dense smoothed puncturation; claws curved in upper third.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB1FF80FF6EFCDA079E1995" blockId="13.[178,1085,791,901]" pageId="13" pageNumber="1878">W i n g s: Areolet pentagonal, symmetrical with quite narrow base; stigma narrow, dark; radius slightly sinuous, almost straight; nervulus intersticial, ramulus expressed, short; veins of both of wings light, normally sclerotized, including apical ones; membrane of wings hyaline. Length of front wing 1,3 times shorter than body length.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB1FF80FF6EFC5E00101F21" blockId="13.[178,1086,915,1329]" pageId="13" pageNumber="1878">A b d o m e n: From above rather narrow, fusiform, with distinct constriction between tergites 2-3; second tergite from above 1,1 times shorter than width at apex. First tergite from lateral with gradual bend of petiolus to postpetiolus, almost stright; petiolus not bordered by carinae, only with indistinct trace of dorsolateral carina, lateral surface of petiolus sculpturated weakly expressed smoothed transversal ribs, shining; petiolus narrow, from above gradually broadened to postpetiolus; middle field of postpetiolus distinctly elevated, not bordered, wider than lateral fields, smooth; lateral fields with some big smoothed punctures laterally, surface of postpetiolus shining. Gastrocoeli deeply impressed and almost not oblique; thyridia sharp, 1,1 times wider than interval between them; lunulae distinct, oval, sharply different by color, situated behind middle of second tergite; surface of tergite 2 densely punctured by small punctures, longitudinally wriklypunctured between gastrocoeli and up to middle, other tergites densely punctured by superficial punctures which are decreasing in diameter towards the apex; interspaces between punctured with smoothed granulated sculpture, but abdomen shining. Sternites 2- 5 almost completely unsclerotized with fold. Hypopygium with oblong roundeg apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB1FF80FF6EFA8D05E71C50" blockId="13.[178,1086,1344,1600]" pageId="13" pageNumber="1878">C o l o r a t i o n: Black with abundant white (yellow) pattern: scapus in front, face entirely, frontal and vertical orbits, temples in lower part broadly, mandibles except apex and palpae, margin of pronotal base broadly, collar and upper margin of pronotum, propleurae, tegulae, subalarum, lower half of mesopleurae and base of front wing, scutellum except middle and postscutellum, metanotum partially, spots on apex of propodeum, base and apex of first tergite, base, lateral margins and apex of tergites 2-3, tergites 4-5 with stripe on apex. Front and middle legs predominantly white, coxae of hind legs ventrally and trochanteres 1 white; femora tibiae and tarsi predominantly reddish-brown; apices of hind femora and tibiae darkened.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="7727DD12FFB2FF83FF6EFF16075F1AE0" blockId="14.[178,836,219,241]" box="[178,836,219,241]" pageId="14" pageNumber="1879">S i z e: Body length – 8,5; front wing – 6,5; flagellum – 6,0 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>