<document id="4CA7E87CE142FA5B269C310EC5633CA7" ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282596" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4d306393-ac5c-43b1-ab3a-19d9894998f0" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127269" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282596" ModsDocID="6438" checkinTime="1243377138618" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="1981" docId="FFB7FA5B4DF66FE171AF4007222E6032" docLanguage="en" docName="6438" docOrigin="Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology 43" docSource="http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6438" docTitle="Baracidris meketra Bolton, 1981, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="256" masterDocId="BC898CD1404B6DE3B19A96923068ACC3" masterDocTitle="A revision of six minor genera of Myrmicinae (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in the Ethiopian zoogeographical region." masterLastPageNumber="307" masterPageNumber="245" pageNumber="255" updateTime="1645805167815" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods id="D0CC7829202CF75C35D2468A2D82975C" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo id="0E58BE682EC4A0759B0FB3B7C5822275">
<mods:title id="B6E80DCCE6F587D8F02FF237A4377C37">A revision of six minor genera of Myrmicinae (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in the Ethiopian zoogeographical region.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name id="4D01AFE768897921F67540DF05A022B9" type="personal">
<mods:role id="D88B5E98139B4459370A4528EF97DBAD">
<mods:roleTerm id="FF91F091208A2ADC26BD3902723E232B">Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart id="8F07AD1A41FB73CCBBAAA3547D18E2F2">Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource id="B1C7C84A94D19F7E48F35FEE2746B813">text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem id="957190702C57E2C37BD8E7BD7DA584CB" type="host">
<mods:titleInfo id="8C211538CA5AFB82A17381B4419B06CF">
<mods:title id="D30E279B1FB73EDD7F524273A962BC2A">Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part id="297118CD4FD1E2B4FBCC075B023C2855">
<mods:date id="3C9FD447CA78E9267679E7BD9E936BA4">1981</mods:date>
<mods:detail id="9714EC14558F969DFA91ED1668DA7350" type="volume">
<mods:number id="390E700DF8863ADB57E1C1CC4BEE8162">43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent id="763A8DEF92C2CA6589ECEBC592CDA9C8" unit="page">
<mods:start id="D48CB75BD0980B2E3191167594BDEC4B">245</mods:start>
<mods:end id="BD792DA376601F523AA966D134A9808B">307</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location id="B3992D558378F6F0E5925121D84683E9">
<mods:url id="887D4280E768BFBADBE6EF01EF2D39D7">http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6438</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification id="847BD441232DB895322362DCF0E0F46A">journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier id="0BAD9EA57DDB34370B30EB5179840DB4" type="HNS-PUB">6438</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment id="FFB7FA5B4DF66FE171AF4007222E6032" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282596" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127269" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282596" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:FFB7FA5B4DF66FE171AF4007222E6032" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFB7FA5B4DF66FE171AF4007222E6032" lastPageNumber="256" pageNumber="255">
<subSubSection id="F47672868E1297695F98BACA97E7DC73" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="BF7B61B124B239DC61F80F34832D52B3" pageNumber="255">
<taxonomicName id="6C689954FD0052A573FD882CE7563F31" LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:26042" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Baracidris" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Baracidris meketra Bolton" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="255" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="meketra">Baracidris meketra</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel id="D7FD2AA0707FA887D902E6BFF44F1852" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
<paragraph id="641D020999B3B3E11916EFAFB2DBAEF5" pageNumber="255">(Figs 12,13)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FF5A1BAFF0D97678BCF42759F5EEB477" type="description">
<paragraph id="B33DECE4CFB39178458D9BC811843F43" pageNumber="255">Holotype worker. TL 1.8, HL 0.44, HW 0.36, CI 82, SL 0.28, SI 78, PW 0.26, AL 0.50.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="D238218E2E48DF76654939D0567CE6D7" pageNumber="255">Mandibles sculptured with fairly large scattered pits, shining, without striate sculpture. Apical tooth of mandible large, the second smaller, the remaining three teeth very small. Anterior clypeal margin projecting forwards medially but not forming a narrow truncated lobe. Structure of clypeus and frontal lobes as given in generic diagnosis. Antennal scapes short and stout (SI 75 - 79 in entire type-series), when laid back on the head distinctly failing to reach the occipital margin. First funicular segment large, longer than broad; segments 2 - 9 of funiculus annular and distinctly broader than long. The two apical funicular segments which form the strong club dissimilar in size, the preapical much shorter than the apical (005 as opposed to 0 - 22). Eye minute, with a single ocellus of diameter c. 0.015 0.020, approximately 0.05 x HW. With head in full-face view the occipital margin indented or slightly concave medially. Promesonotum forming a single long shallow convexity in profile, the metanotal groove impressed. Propodeal dorsum in profile feebly convex and sloping posteriorly to the short but quite broad triangular teeth. The propodeal teeth are joined by a lamella below to the enlarged, strongly prominent and very broadly rounded plate-like metapleural lobes, the two together forming an efficient shield all down the propodeal declivity. Propodeal spiracle round. With alitrunk in dorsal view the promesonotum three times longer than the propodeum (0.32 and 0.10 respectively), the pronotal shoulders broadly rounded. Propodeal dorsum terminating posteriorly in a sharply defined arch between the bases of the laterally flattened teeth, the declivity almost vertical and bounded on each side by the very prominent teeth and metapleural lobes, and the lamella which links them. A single small carina traverses the declivity at the level of the propodeal teeth. Petiole in profile with a short, thick anterior peduncle which is distinctly shorter than the length of the node; the peduncle with a small anteroventral process. Postpetiole in profile with the sternite produced into a large truncated ventral process. In dorsal view the petiole node as long as broad (c. 012), the anterior peduncle broader than long and much shorter than the dorsal length of the node; the node itself scarcely broader than the peduncle. Postpetiole dorsally slightly broader than long, about equal in length to the petiole node and parallel-sided, appearing short-cylindrical. Base of first gastral tergite concave at the postpetiolar articulation. Dorsum and sides of head with small, close-packed foveolate punctures, the spaces between which are smooth and shining. Spaces between punctures usually smaller than the diameter of the punctures. On the sides of the head above and behind the eyes there is a tendency for the punctures to be aligned. Dorsal alitrunk similarly sculptured but the punctures less conspicuous and more widely scattered, with extensive smooth shining spaces between them. Sides of alitrunk and all surfaces of pedicel segments punctate, denser on the meta-pleuron than elsewhere on the alitrunk and denser on the sides of the petiole and postpetiole than dorsally. First gastral tergite unsculptured except for scattered minute punctulae. Hairs absent except on clypeus, mouthparts and gastral apex. All dorsal surfaces of head and body thinly and sparsely clothed with extremely fine short appressed pubescence. Colour uniform light brown, the appendages lighter in shade than the body.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0903A7E97AED7B0B1E61EB84DB4E107D" lastPageNumber="256" pageNumber="255">Paratype workers. TL 1.7 - 1.8, HL 0.44 - 0.47, HW 0.36 - 0.38, CI 80 - 82, SL 0.27 - 0.30, SI 75 - 79, PW 0.26 - 0.28, AL 0.49 - 0.50 (4 measured). As holotype but the Ghana specimens slightly darker in colour than those from Nigeria and with the cephalic sculpture somewhat more sharply defined. Propodeal teeth vary slightly in length and width but are always shorter than the metapleural lobes. One or two fine transverse carinae may be present on the propodeal declivity, between the teeth.</paragraph>
<paragraph id="0395D3A83699A77A5C68014922658A34" pageNumber="256">Paratype female (dealate). TL 20, HL 0.46, HW 0.39, CI 85, SL 0.28, SI 72, PW 0.30, AL 0.56. As worker but eyes larger (maximum diameter 010, c. 0.26 x HW) and with ocelli present. Alitrunk with full complement of flight sclerites, the pronotum forming a clearly visible collar anteriorly in dorsal view. Mesoscutellum much higher than and somewhat overhanging the propodeal dorsum. Mesoscutum and scutellum with foveolate punctures and a smooth unsculptured median longitudinal strip; otherwise as holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="09203FAA6E4A4BA140AC767E342005DF" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph id="D12F2B8F2E0AEFC8F8D88B8E1EB551A0" pageNumber="256">Holotype worker, Nigeria: Ile-Ife, 21. vii. 1971 (J. T. Medler) (BMNH).</paragraph>
<paragraph id="5F29C2B7A29236564B1CC50122B06CE4" pageNumber="256">Paratypes. Nigeria: 1 worker with same data as holotype. Ghana: 1 worker and 1 dealate female, Tafo, 4. ix. 1970, cocoa litter sample (B. Bollori). Ivory Coast: 1 worker, Abidjan, Banco Forest, i. 1963 {W. L. Brown) (BMNH; MCZ, Cambridge).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection id="FA9514D987EEB0786C26C4DF319EE2CA" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph id="B7236BD9B9DD94F6B205EC7979B52F63" pageNumber="256">All specimens originated in forest; those from Ghana were extracted from a sample of cocoa leaf litter which had built up between the roots of a large forest tree, left in the plantation to provide shade for the cocoa.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>