<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" ID-GBIF-Dataset="92d38eff-94a4-404e-a09c-d535155922c8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043396" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-292-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EB1E6D51-A930-4C70-A5E0-A07ABC1816AB" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-292-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 292" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" checkinTime="1451247388242" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="696370CE1DCE295A810C8F33A6874E87" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 292: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 292" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" docTitle="Oxyscelio crateris Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="EB1E6D51-A930-4C70-A5E0-A07ABC1816AB" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" masterDocId="FFB8FF92FF98D87CFFAE2F6B1E57FFC8" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="80" pageNumber="81" updateTime="1643694823285" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>292</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-292-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043396" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EB1E6D51-A930-4C70-A5E0-A07ABC1816AB" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/696370CE1DCE295A810C8F33A6874E87" lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="80" pageNumber="81">
<subSubSection lastPageId="81" lastPageNumber="82" pageId="80" pageNumber="81" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph lastPageId="81" lastPageNumber="82" pageId="80" pageNumber="81">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EB1E6D51-A930-4C70-A5E0-A07ABC1816AB" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio crateris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="80" pageNumber="81" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="crateris">Oxyscelio crateris Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="80" pageNumber="81">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
<pageBreakToken pageId="81" pageNumber="82" start="start">Figures</pageBreakToken>
129-132Morphbank49
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="81" pageNumber="82" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="81" pageNumber="82">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="81" pageNumber="82">Female. Body length 4.65 mm (n=1).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="81" pageNumber="82">Radicle color: same color as scape. Scape color: Yellowish. A4: longer than broad. A5: longer than broad. Antennal club: formed, segments compact.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="82" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="81" pageNumber="82">
Interantennal process: not elongate. Median longitudinal elevation in frontal depression: absent. Frontal depression: concave. Frontal depression sculpture: with 3 or more broadly interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: strong, formed by a sharp raised carina. Submedian carina medially: without peak. Concavity across dorsal part of frontal depression: absent. Depression extending ventrally from median ocellus: absent. Upper frons: not hood-like. Malar area near antennal foramen: without carina or expansion. Malar area at mouth corner: with radiating striae. Smooth strip along posterior side of malar sulcus: present, broad throughout its length. Middle genal carina: present. Direction of middle genal carina dorsally: parallel to eye margin. Major sculpture of gena anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate; rugose. Major sculpture of gena posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: granulate. Median carina extending 
<pageBreakToken pageId="82" pageNumber="83" start="start">posteriorly</pageBreakToken>
from hyperoccipital carina: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: complete, continuous with anterior genal carina. Lateral connection between hyperoccipital and occipital carinae: present as a distinct carina. Area between vertex and occipital carina: irregularly rugose. Occipital carina medially: convex, with a sharp median peak. Lateral corners of occipital carina: sharp and protruding.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Lateral pronotal area: without bulge projecting towards anterior pit. Epomial corner: weak. Netrion surface anteriorly: not inflexed. Mesoscutum anteriorly: not steep. Mesoscutal median carina: present and complete. Longitudinal carina between median carina and notauli: absent. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate; transversely rugose. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: granulate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum: umbilicate-foveate; transversely rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum medially: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum laterally: granulate. Mesoscutellar apex: convex or straight. Setae along anterior limit of femoral depression: arising from tiny pits. Number of carinae crossing speculum above femoral depression: 3. Number of carinae crossing femoral depression: 3-5. Mesepimeral sulcus pits: more than 5. Metascutellum dorsally: concave. Metascutellar sculpture dorsally: smooth or with transverse carinae. Median carina of metascutellum: absent or branched. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellar apex: deeply emarginate. Metapleuron above ventral metapleural area: crossed by carinae. Metasomal depression setae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae anteromedially: weakly diverging. Anterior areoles of metasomal depression: absent. Anterior longitudinal carinae in metasomal depression: absent. Lateral propodeal areas: separated medially. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex: reaching middle of T6.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">T1 midlobe: with 5 longitudinal carinae. T1: without anterior bulge. T2: with straight longitudinal striae or rugae. T6: longer than broad. Apical flange of T6: exposed apically. Metasomal apex: rounded. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate-punctate; longitudinally striate or rugose. Microsculpture of T6: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Male. Body length 3.8-4.5 mm (n=10). A5 tyloid: carina-like, not expanded. A11: longer than broad. Median tooth of frontal depression: absent. Median lobe of T1: with 5 longitudinal carinae. Metasomal apex: with no distinct corners.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="82" pageNumber="83" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Both sexes: Frons without flange between antennal foramen and eye. Hyperoccipital carina present, continuous with an anterior genal carina, connected with occipital carina by a distinct longitudinal carina. Mesoscutellum with granulate sculpture. Metascutellum weakly emarginate or apically incised, posterior corners narrow. Female: A4, A5 longer than broad. T6 strongly narrowed but not sharply pointed. Male: A11 not longer than broad. T7 with weakly rounded lobes posterolaterally.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="82" pageNumber="83" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">
Latin noun, genitive case, meaning 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“crater.”">&quot;crater.&quot;</normalizedToken>
Refers to the outlined concave area on the dorsal part of the occiput.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="82" pageNumber="83" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=275506]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="82" pageNumber="83" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="82" pageNumber="83">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="83" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="82" pageNumber="83">
Holotype, female: THAILAND: Chiang Mai Prov., Doi Phaluang, T2846, Doi Phahompok National Park, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="20.0161">20°00.966'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="99.15965">99°09.579'E</geoCoordinate>
, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="83" pageNumber="84" start="start">1449</pageBreakToken>
m, 13.
<normalizedToken originalValue="VII–">VII-</normalizedToken>
20.VII.2007, malaise trap, P. Wongchai, OSUC 336014 (deposited in QSBG). Paratypes: (12 males) MALAYSIA: 2 males, OSUC 369012-369013 (CNCI). THAILAND: 10 males, OSUC 368749, 464036-464037 (CNCI); OSUC 322088, 322115 (OSUC); OSUC 322130, 352921, 368545, 368548 (QSBG); OSUC 322129 (WINC).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
Figures 129-132. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio crateris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="crateris">Oxyscelio crateris</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype female (OSUC 336014) 129 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 130 Head, posterodorsal view 131 Body, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 322129) 132 Body, dorsal view. Morphbank49
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>