<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.322.5492" ID-GBIF-Dataset="36ad3806-c865-4b7b-9d42-8d190cfd5d97" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047117" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-322-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6439FF2D-9514-4FA9-8596-1113C64492C3" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-322-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 322" ModsDocTitle="The Mecyclothorax beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Moriomorphini) of Tahiti, Society Islands" checkinTime="1451247045918" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Liebherr, James K." docDate="2013" docId="1E32AEAD4DC81FD70E46944CC3C34066" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 322: 1-170" docOrigin="ZooKeys 322" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.322.5492" docTitle="Mecyclothorax maninamata Liebherr, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="6439FF2D-9514-4FA9-8596-1113C64492C3" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="104" lastPageNumber="105" masterDocId="20750D3CFFB5F54CB8239531171AFFB8" masterDocTitle="The Mecyclothorax beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Moriomorphini) of Tahiti, Society Islands" masterLastPageNumber="170" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" updateTime="1643696676186" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Mecyclothorax beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Moriomorphini) of Tahiti, Society Islands</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Liebherr, James K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>322</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>170</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.322.5492</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.322.5492</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-322-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2370DEC9-70F5-425A-BBD0-C02DCC2F4835</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047117" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6439FF2D-9514-4FA9-8596-1113C64492C3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1E32AEAD4DC81FD70E46944CC3C34066" lastPageId="104" lastPageNumber="105" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
<subSubSection pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
86. 
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/6439FF2D-9514-4FA9-8596-1113C64492C3" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Mecyclothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mecyclothorax maninamata" order="Coleoptera" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maninamata">Mecyclothorax maninamata</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="102" pageNumber="103">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="104" lastPageNumber="105" pageId="102" pageNumber="103" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="102" pageNumber="103">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="103" lastPageNumber="104" pageId="102" pageNumber="103">
Among species of the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Mecyclothorax" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Mecyclothorax globosus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="103" pageNumber="104" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="globosus">
<pageBreakToken pageId="103" pageNumber="104" start="start">Mecyclothorax</pageBreakToken>
globosus
</taxonomicName>
group with two supraorbital setae each side and one dorsal elytral seta - setal formula 2111 - this species can be diagnosed by the pallid body coloration (Fig. 45A) and very small eyes, ocular ratio 1.35. A horizontal diameter of the compound eye crosses 15 ommatidia. Standardized body length 3.7 mm. Head with frontal grooves very fine and shallow posteriorly, the convex frons immediately mesad the supraorbital carina crossed by transverse wrinkles, deeper and broader anteriorly at frontoclypeal suture, the grooves extended laterally onto labrum; ocular lobe little protruded, eyes little convex; antennae moderately elongate, submoniliform, antennomere 8 length 1.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximal breadth. Pronotum transverse, lateral margins maximally curved at lateral pronotal setae; MPW/PL = 1.29; base moderately constricted, MPW/BPW = 1.48, lateral margins subparallel for 0.14
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length anterad slightly obtuse, well-defined hind angles; median base depressed relative to disc, ~7 punctures each side bordered by larger depressions mesad the laterobasal depression; anterior transverse impression broad, shallow medially, crossed by a dense array of distinct longitudinal strigae that extend nearly to pronotal anterior margin, more narrowly incised laterally near rounded, non-protruded front angles; lateral marginal depression narrow, margin beaded, depression hardly wider inside front angles; laterobasal depression consisting of two pits separated by an oblique transverse bar that crosses from base to lateral margin anterad the hind angle. Elytra narrowly ovate, the lateral margins evenly curved posterad the proximate, angulate humeri, MEW/HuW = 2.29; elytral disc broadly convex, the surface flat between the fourth intervals at midlength, sides downturned to near vertical juncture with lateral marginal depression; discal elytral striae moderately incised, punctate, the rounded punctures expanding strial width; striae 1-5 shallow basally, but traceable to basal groove; discal elytral intervals broadly, moderately convex; striae 1-7 well-developed apically, the associated intervals convex, eighth interval subcarinately upraised above stria 7 dorsad subapical sinuation, the interval convexly bulging from there to apex; lateral elytral setae 7 + 6. Microsculpture of frons obsolete, surface glossy between the transverse wrinkles, shallow transverse mesh visible on neck; pronotal disc glossy over parts, the surface appearing lapped due to irregular transverse wrinkles, an indistinct transverse mesh visible over complementary parts, sculpticell breadth 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–4×">-4x</normalizedToken>
length; pronotal median base with evident isodiametric and transverse sculpticells between the punctures; discal elytral intervals with an indistinct transverse mesh, sculpticell breadth 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–3×">-3x</normalizedToken>
length visible outside areas of reflected light. Coloration of head pale rufous; antennomeres 1-4 flavous, 5-11 rufobrunneous; pronotal disc pale rufous, all margins concolorous; elytra pale rufous, lateral marginal depressions narrowly rufoflavous; femora and tibiae flavous.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="104" pageNumber="105">
<pageBreakToken pageId="104" pageNumber="105" start="start">Female</pageBreakToken>
reproductive tract. Bursa copulatrix elongate, narrowly rounded apically, length 2.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width when compressed under microslide cover slip (Fig. 44B); spermathecal duct broad, almost as broad as the spermathecal reservoir; basal gonocoxite 1 broad apically, narrow basally, with apical fringe of 3 setae set laterally, and 6-7 small setae arrayed along the mesal margin (Fig. 9H); apical gonocoxite 2 broad basally, narrowly arcuate apically, with broadly arcuate lateral margin; apical coxite with two elongate lateral ensiform setae, a dorsal ensiform seta, and an apical sensory furrow with two apical nematiform setae and two furrow pegs.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="104" pageNumber="105">
Holotype female (MNHN) labeled: Mt. Marau, Tahiti / 1200-1400 m / XII-1977 / J. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Gourvès">Gourves</normalizedToken>
(on reverse) (pink paper) // Museum Paris / 1994 / Coll. G. Perrault (pink paper) // 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ƶ">Ƶ</normalizedToken>
(white paper) // HOLOTYPE / Mecyclothorax maninamata / J.K. Liebherr 2013 (black-bordered red label).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="104" pageNumber="105">Etymology. The species epithet compounds the Tahitian words manina, in this usage meaning flat, and mata, herein meaning eye. The name therefore refers to the flat eyes diagnostic of this species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="104" pageNumber="105" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="104" pageNumber="105">Distribution and habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="104" pageNumber="105">
The holotype specimen was placed at the end of the Georges Perrault collection, with the tertiary label 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Ƶ”">&quot;Ƶ&quot;</normalizedToken>
indicating his recognition of it as distinct, though undescribed. It was collected between 1200 and 1400 m elevation on Mont Marau, though the situation within which Professeur 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Gourvès">Gourves</normalizedToken>
collected it was not recorded.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>