<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6288972" ID-GBIF-Dataset="bb80e4cc-617f-4019-87a5-1a3193415847" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134737" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6288972" ModsDocAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." ModsDocID="20597" checkinTime="1243371947323" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." docDate="1922" docId="F69AC8F9625093E4756CE0358F54CF9A" docLanguage="en" docName="20597_1" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 45" docSource="http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097" docTitle="Euponera (Mesoponera) ingesta Forel, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageNumber="83" masterDocId="76DE4446B070FF79F438A6FC084F5E35" masterDocTitle="The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition." masterLastPageNumber="269" masterPageNumber="39" pageNumber="82" updateTime="1645826828520" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wheeler, W. M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1922</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>45</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>39</mods:start>
<mods:end>269</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">20597</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6288972" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134737" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6288972" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:F69AC8F9625093E4756CE0358F54CF9A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F69AC8F9625093E4756CE0358F54CF9A" lastPageNumber="83" pageNumber="82">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="82">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:141721" authority="Forel" authorityName="Forel" class="Hexapoda" family="Formicidae" genus="Euponera" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Euponera (Mesoponera) ingesta Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ingesta" subGenus="Mesoponera">Euponera (Mesoponera) ingesta</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="82">Text Figure 14</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="82">Worker.- Length 5.5 to 6 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="82">Head somewhat longer than broad and about as broad in front as behind, with evenly convex sides and feebly excavated posterior border. Eyes small, flat, broadly elliptical, placed at the anterior fifth of the sides of the head. Clypeus carinate, its anterior border entire, rounded and projecting in the middle, sinuate at the sides.</paragraph>
<caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="82">
Fig. 14. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:141721" authority="Forel" authorityName="Forel" class="Hexapoda" family="Formicidae" genus="Euponera" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Euponera (Mesoponera) ingesta Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="82" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ingesta" subGenus="Mesoponera">Euponera (Mesoponera) ingesta</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
, Worker, a, head from above; b, thorax and Abdomen in profile.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="82">Mandibles moderately long, convex, their apical borders with 8 or 9 subequal teeth. Antennal scapes extending slightly beyond the posterior border of the head; first and second funicular joints subequal, about one and one-half times as long as broad, joints 4 to 6 somewhat shorter, remaining joints, except the last, as broad as long. Pronotum as long as broad, somewhat depressed above and very bluntly submarginate on the sides. Mesonotum convex, transversely elliptical, nearly twice as broad as long, completely surrounded by a strong suture; mesoepinotal constriction distinct. Epinotum nearly as long as the pro- and mesonotum together, but somewhat lower, the base and declivity straight, subequal, forming an obtuse angle with each other, the former horizontal in profile, the latter fiat; marginate on the sides. Petiolar scale in profile high and cuneate, its anterior surface feebly convex from side to side, its posterior surface flat, with a shallow longitudinal impression in the middle; the border evenly rounded, semicircular from behind, slightly narrowed ventrally. Gaster short, postpetiole sharply truncated in front, the constriction between it and the gaster feeble. Legs moderately long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="82">Mandibles shining, finely and rather indistinctly punctate; remainder of body subopaque; clypeal carina and legs more shining; very finely and densely punctate, especially the head, scapes and thorax.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="83">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="83">Hairs</pageStartToken>
almost lacking on the head, thorax, and appendages; on the gaster pale yellow, sparse, erect, slender, and rather uniformly distributed; pubescence very fine, yellowish, moderately abundant, investing the whole body, including the appendages.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="83">Castaneous; legs somewhat paler; mandibles deep red, with black teeth; in some specimens the extensor surfaces of the tibia? arc yellowish.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="83">Described from six specimens taken from the stomachs of toads (Bufo funereus and polycercus) from Akenge (type locality), one from Niapu, also from a toad's stomach (B. polycercus), a single specimen from Faradje, and another from Lubila (Lang and Chapin).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>