<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153" ID-GBIF-Dataset="248dd503-13d6-4dae-a0aa-d7d5fdc867a2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127871325" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-657-93" ID-ZBK="199B466C0D1C4E2D81331C0D77FCBD3F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F9EB81F9-7C6A-4FD3-90FC-411FDA09C65F" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-657-93" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 657" ModsDocTitle="Descriptions of three new carbonaria-group species of Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy from China, with a key to the carbonaria-group species (Diptera, Fanniidae)" checkinTime="1487401264803" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Wang, Ming-fu, Li, Wei, Zhao, Yu-wan, Wu, Jie &amp; Zhang, Dong" docDate="2017" docId="0B962931A726D18BF1B84B80F7C9C172" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 657: 93-107" docOrigin="ZooKeys 657" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153" docTitle="Fannia submaculata Wang &amp; Zhao, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="F9EB81F9-7C6A-4FD3-90FC-411FDA09C65F" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="101" masterDocId="FF85FFD5FF9BFFAFC117966BD410FFC8" masterDocTitle="Descriptions of three new carbonaria-group species of Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy from China, with a key to the carbonaria-group species (Diptera, Fanniidae)" masterLastPageNumber="107" masterPageNumber="93" pageId="7" pageNumber="100" updateTime="1643572775644" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Descriptions of three new carbonaria-group species of Fannia Robineau-Desvoidy from China, with a key to the carbonaria-group species (Diptera, Fanniidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wang, Ming-fu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Wei</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhao, Yu-wan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wu, Jie</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhang, Dong</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>657</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>93</mods:start>
<mods:end>107</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.657.9153</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-657-93</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">199B466C0D1C4E2D81331C0D77FCBD3F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">199B466C0D1C4E2D81331C0D77FCBD3F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127871325" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F9EB81F9-7C6A-4FD3-90FC-411FDA09C65F" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0B962931A726D18BF1B84B80F7C9C172" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="101" pageId="7" pageNumber="100">
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="100" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/F9EB81F9-7C6A-4FD3-90FC-411FDA09C65F" authority="Wang &amp; Zhao" class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia submaculata" order="Diptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="100" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="submaculata">Fannia submaculata Wang &amp; Zhao</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="7" pageNumber="100">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Fig. 3
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="100" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">This species is characterized as follows: postsutural acr in two rows; pra stout, 3/4 of the length of posterior notopleural seta; calypters and haltere in lighter color; knees and base of fore tibia yellow; hind tibia with four ad; tergite 5 with a distinct dark median stripe; cercal plate slender in ventral view; surstylus with a distinct notch on inner margin in median part; bacilliform sclerite becoming gradually narrower towards apex.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="100">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia submaculata" order="Diptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="100" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="submaculata">Fannia submaculata</taxonomicName>
Wang &amp; Zhao, sp. n., male, holotype (specimen from Ningxia, deposited in IESNU). A Terminalia, ventral view B Terminalia, lateral view C Sternite 5, ventral view. Scale bars 0.25 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="101" pageId="7" pageNumber="100" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="100">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="101" pageId="7" pageNumber="100">
MALE. Body length 5.0 mm. Eye bare; upper inner facets larger than the rest; postocular setae in one row, irregular in length, curved anteriorly, with some occipital setae behind the postocular setae on vertex; fronto-orbital plate and parafacial with grayish white pollinosity; at narrowest point frons equal to the distance between outer margins of two posterior ocelli, equal to the width of postpedicel; frontal stripe black and narrow; frontal setae nine or ten all stout, situated on the lower 4/5 of fronto-orbital plate, nearly reaching ocellar triangle; parafacial bare, at middle 1/2 as wide as the width of postpedicel; antenna black, postpedicel 2.0 times longer than wide, arista haired and black, the longest hair equal to basal aristal width; epistoma not projecting beyond vibrissal angle, vibrissal angle behind frontal angle in profile; subvibrissal setulae in one row, gena and genal dilation with black setulae, upper margin of gena without upcurved seta; proboscis stout, labella large; prementum with grayish yellow pollinosity, 2.0 times longer than wide; palpus black, claviform, as long as prementum. Thorax black in ground color, shining, notum with thin brown pollinosity; acr biserial, slightly stout, prescutellar pairs stout; the distance between acr rows narrower than the distance between acr row and dc row, dc 2+3, ia 0+2, pra 1, 3/4 of the length of posterior notopleural seta, notopleuron without setula; proepisternal setae 2, proepimeral seta 1; basisternum, proepisternum, anepimeron, meron and katepimeron bare; katepisternal setae 1+1, katepisternum without ventral spine; anterior spiracle small and dark brown, posterior one dark brown; calypters yellowish, the lower one distinctly projecting beyond the upper one. Wing brownish; veins dark brown; wing base being similar color as rest of wing; tegula black; basicosta brownish; costal spine 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="101" start="start">inconspicuous</pageBreakToken>
; node of Rs bare on ventral and dorsal surfaces; vein R4+5 straight, veins R4+5 and M1+2 parallel to each other distally; crossveins without obvious cloud; haltere brown. Legs entirely black, except knees and base of fore tibia yellow; fore coxa without anterior spine on ventral surface, fore femur with complete pv row, fore tibia without ad and median p, fore first tarsomere with several short basal setae on ventral surface; mid coxa without any hook-like spine or spine-like seta, mid femur with complete av row, stout in basal half, becoming gradually shorter and denser towards apex, without gap, pv row complete, in one row, with one slender p row, mid tibia slightly swollen in distal half, with two ad, two pd, and with numerous slender setulae on ventral surface, the longest one 3/4 as long as mid tibial width in distal part, mid first tarsomere without basal tooth-like spine on ventral surface; hind coxa bare on posterior surface, hind femur with av row, setula-like in basal half, with four long av in distal 2/5, without pv, hind tibia with two av, four ad and one median d. Abdomen oval and flattened, black in ground color, shining, with thin gray pollinosity; syntergite 1+2 to tergite 5 each with a dark median stripe; sternite one with slender setulae, sternite 5 broad, concave on posterior margin (Fig. 3C); cercal plate slender in ventral view, separated into two branches at apex, pointed anteriorly and posteriorly, respectively, in lateral view (Fig. 3A, B); surstylus with a distinct notch on inner margin at middle in ventral view (Fig. 3A); bacilliform sclerite short, becoming gradually narrower towards apex (Fig. 3B)
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">FEMALE. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="101" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">
This new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia maculosa" order="Diptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="101" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculosa">Fannia maculosa</taxonomicName>
Nishida, 2003 but can be characterised by its postsutural acr in two rows; pra long, 3/4 of the length of posterior notopleural seta; wing base being similar color as rest of wing; calypters and all haltere in lighter color; knees and base of fore tibia yellow; hind tibia with four ad; tergite 5 with a distinct dark median stripe; sternite 5 broad (Fig. 3C); cercal plate slender in ventral view (Fig. 3A); surstylus with a distinct notch on inner margin in median part (Fig. 3A); bacilliform sclerite becoming gradually narrower towards apex (Fig. 3B).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="101" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">
This specific name refers to the similarity between the new species and 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Fanniidae" genus="Fannia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Fannia maculosa" order="Diptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="101" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculosa">Fannia maculosa</taxonomicName>
Nishida.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="101" type="holotype">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">Holotype.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">Male: China, Ningxia, Jingyuan, Dongshanpo, 2200 m, 27.VI.2008, Coll. M.F. Wang (IESNU).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="101" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="101">Known only from the type locality in Ningxia, China.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>