<document ID-ISSN="0024-4082" ID-ZooBank="C1B0E492-7846-4103-87E0-A137D16A590D" approvalRequired="18" approvalRequired_for_originalDoi="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="8" approvalRequired_for_treatments="9" checkinTime="1630097932376" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Jin, Didi, Qu, Zhishuai, Wei, Bojue, Montagnes, David J. S., Fan, Xinpeng &amp; Chen, Xiangrui" docDate="2021" docId="038387D3FFCBFFE6B19EFEA1FE039D7C" docLanguage="en" docName="zlaa086.pdf" docOrigin="Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society 191" docStyle="DocumentStyle:36B3BD6A90C22AB4F7F465C853188CC8.4:ZoolJLinnSoc.2017-.journal_article" docStyleId="36B3BD6A90C22AB4F7F465C853188CC8" docStyleName="ZoolJLinnSoc.2017-.journal_article" docStyleVersion="4" docTitle="Kyaroikeus paracetarius Jin &amp; Qu &amp; Wei &amp; Montagnes &amp; Fan &amp; Chen 2021, SP. NOV." docType="treatment" docVersion="1" lastPageNumber="944" masterDocId="FFBAFFABFFC8FFE5B166FFDEFF899E2E" masterDocTitle="Two parasitic ciliates (Protozoa: Ciliophora: Phyllopharyngea) isolated from respiratory-mucus of an unhealthy beluga whale: characterization, phylogeny and an assessment of morphological adaptations" masterLastPageNumber="960" masterPageNumber="941" pageId="3" pageNumber="944" updateTime="1630097933780" updateUser="felipe">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Two parasitic ciliates (Protozoa: Ciliophora: Phyllopharyngea) isolated from respiratory-mucus of an unhealthy beluga whale: characterization, phylogeny and an assessment of morphological adaptations</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jin, Didi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Qu, Zhishuai</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wei, Bojue</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Montagnes, David J. S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fan, Xinpeng</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chen, Xiangrui</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2021</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>191</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>941</mods:start>
<mods:end>960</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0024-4082</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">C1B0E492-7846-4103-87E0-A137D16A590D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:038387D3FFCBFFE6B19EFEA1FE039D7C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038387D3FFCBFFE6B19EFEA1FE039D7C" lastPageNumber="944" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
<subSubSection box="[248,693,383,407]" pageId="3" pageNumber="944" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="3.[248,693,383,407]" box="[248,693,383,407]" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
<heading box="[248,693,383,407]" centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="3" pageNumber="944" reason="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[248,587,383,406]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
<taxonomicName authority="Jin &amp; Qu &amp; Wei &amp; Montagnes &amp; Fan &amp; Chen, 2021" authorityName="Jin &amp; Qu &amp; Wei &amp; Montagnes &amp; Fan &amp; Chen" authorityYear="2021" box="[248,580,383,406]" class="Cyrtophoria" family="Kyaroikeidae" genus="Kyaroikeus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Chromista" order="Dysteriida" pageId="3" pageNumber="957" phylum="Ciliophora" rank="species" species="paracetarius" status="sp. nov.">KYAROIKEUS PARACETARIUS</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
<emphasis bold="true" box="[595,693,383,407]" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[595,693,383,407]" pageId="3" pageNumber="944" rank="species">SP. NOV.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="944" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="3.[357,584,429,454]" box="[357,584,429,454]" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
(
<figureCitation box="[365,469,429,454]" captionStart-0="Figure 1" captionStart-1="Figure 2" captionStart-2="Figure 3" captionStart-3="Figure 4" captionStart-4="Figure 5" captionStartId-0="4.[144,222,996,1018]" captionStartId-1="5.[162,238,1391,1413]" captionStartId-2="6.[147,225,1321,1343]" captionStartId-3="7.[163,241,1673,1695]" captionStartId-4="8.[145,223,1085,1107]" captionTargetBox-0="[146,1411,197,955]" captionTargetBox-1="[165,1443,197,1350]" captionTargetBox-2="[146,1427,196,1281]" captionTargetBox-3="[164,1445,196,1632]" captionTargetBox-4="[306,1261,198,1042]" captionTargetId-0="figure-340@4.[145,1425,195,956]" captionTargetId-1="figure-76@5.[163,1443,195,1351]" captionTargetId-2="figure-197@6.[145,1428,195,1282]" captionTargetId-3="figure-26@7.[163,1446,195,1633]" captionTargetId-4="figure-330@8.[303,1266,195,1046]" captionTargetPageId-0="4" captionTargetPageId-1="5" captionTargetPageId-2="6" captionTargetPageId-3="7" captionTargetPageId-4="8" captionText-0="Figure 1. Kyaroikeus paracetarius from life (A–D) and after protargol impregnation (E–J).A, ventral view to show the body shape, densely arranged cilia, lip-like structure on the right side of oral cavity (green region), the podite and the attachment thread. B–D, variants of cell shape. E, the oral region: the blue area indicates the kineties of right field on cell apex and the arrowhead indicates the lip-like structure. F, the cytostome and the circumoral kineties (brown lines). G, the oral region, to show the pre-oral kinety (arrowhead) and circumoral kineties. H, I, ventral (H) and dorsal (I) views of infraciliature: the arrowhead indicates the lip-like structure and the arrow indicates the equatorial fragment. J, enlargement of the anterior ventral part of infraciliature to show details of the oral structure, right and left somatic kineties and non-ciliated stripes. Abbreviations: C, cytostome; Co, circumoral kineties; FT, fibrous tracts; KF, kinetofragments; LF, left field; Ma, macronucleus; NS, non-ciliated stripe; P, podite; Po, pre-oral kinety; RF, right field; T, attachment thread. Scale bars = 60 μm (A, H–J)." captionText-1="Figure 2. Photomicrographs of Kyaroikeus paracetariusfrom life (A–E) and after protargol impregnation (F–R).A, ventral viewof a representative individual; the green region is the lip-like structure on the right side of oral cavity.B, ventral view of the anterior, to show the oral area, with the arrowhead indicating the cytopharynx. C, enlargement of the anterior of the cell. D, anterior of the cell, with the arrowhead indicating the non-ciliated stripe. E, posterior of the cell, with the arrow indicating the podite and arrowhead indicating the attachment thread. F, G. ventral and dorsal views of the infraciliature, with the arrowhead indicating the kinetofragments, the arrow indicating the podite, and the red dots outlining the non-ciliated area. H–J, mid-ventral region of several specimen with different shapes and number of kinetofragments, normal individual with four lines (H), individuals in early stage of fission with more lines (I, J). K, L, equatorial fragment (arrowheads), next to the middle part of the rightmost right kinety. M, the heteromeric macronucleus. N, the podite. O, P, enlargement of the oral region, with the arrows indicating the circumoral kineties and the arrowheads indicating the pre-oral kinety. Q, dorsal view of the anterior, showing the densely arranged right kineties (RK) and left kineties (LK).R, enlargement of the oral region, with the arrow indicating the pellicular fold, the arrowhead indicating the pre-oral kinety, and green region highlighting the lip-like structure. Abbreviations: C, cytostome; Co, circumoral kineties; FT, fibrous tracts; LF, left field; Ma, macronucleus; RF, right field. Scale bars = 60 μm (A–C, F, G) or 30 μm (O–R)." captionText-2="Figure 3. Scanning electron micrographs of Kyaroikeus paracetarius. A, the general body shape and the podite in posterior end (white circle). B, C, anterior portion of cell, showing the pellicular fold in the non-ciliated stripe, which hooks over the anterior end. D, G, oral area, with arrows indicating the circumoral kineties observed in different individuals. E, F, the non-ciliated stripe, with the arrowheads indicating the pellicular pores, which occur in the grooves between the pellicular folds. H, I, a de-ciliated specimen, showing the densely arranged kinetosomes (arrowheads) of ciliary rows and the pellicular ridges (arrow) in the right field of cell. J, the podite, indicating the secretion pore (arrow). Abbreviations: NS, non-ciliated stripe; P, podite. Scale bars = 50 μm (A), 10 μm (B), 5 μm (C, D, G, J) or 2 μm (E, F, H, I)." captionText-3="Figure 4. Transmission electron micrographs of Kyaroikeus paracetarius. A, cross-section showing the non-ciliated stripe, ciliated area (the surface part other than NF), cytopharyngeal tube and a food vacuole. B, D, details of cytopharyngeal tube, which is a flat vesicle. The arrows indicate the microtubule sheets with thinner ends, the double arrowhead indicates one of even thickness and the arrowhead indicates the narrow space of cytopharyngeal tube. C, the pellicular ridges, which were present between ciliary rows and supported by postciliary microtubules, and the parasomal sacs. E, the oral region, showing the two circumoral kineties that were composed of a single row of kinetosomes. F–I, the pellicular folds in the non-ciliated stripe, arrows indicate the sacs regularly occurred beneath the pellicle of each groove, arrowheads mark the sacs that" captionText-4="Figure 5. The cortex of the non-ciliated stripe of Kyaroikeus paracetarius, showing the arrangement of microtubules and a proposed material secretion system containing cytoplasmic vesicles, sacs and pellicular pores." pageId="3" pageNumber="944">FIGS 1–5</figureCitation>
; 
<tableCitation box="[481,576,429,454]" captionStart="Table 1" captionStartId="9.[163,227,196,217]" captionText="Table 1. Morphometric data of Kyaroikeus paracetarius (upper line) and Planilamina ovata (lower line) based on Protargol-stained specimens" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">TABLE 1</tableCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[163,778,470,522]" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
<emphasis box="[163,281,470,491]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">Zoobank:</emphasis>
<uri pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
<uuid pageId="3" pageNumber="944">199C1DAD- F159-4EA7-ACB2-C03492F12B00</uuid>
</uri>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[163,779,552,850]" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">
<emphasis box="[163,282,553,574]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">Diagnosis:</emphasis>
Size 150–400 × 20–40 μm 
<emphasis box="[597,673,553,574]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="944">in vivo</emphasis>
; spindleshaped; deep oral cavity composed of a pre-oral kinety and two circumoral kineties; no nematodesmal rods; 37–69 right kineties, seven to 13 left kineties; four kinetofragments located near equatorial position; equatorial fragment positioned next to the middle part of the rightmost right kinety; non-ciliated stripe underlain by 11–16 fibrous tracks; a bifurcated secretory organelle opened at the tip of podite; one ovoid macronucleus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>