<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282657" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4d306393-ac5c-43b1-ab3a-19d9894998f0" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127299" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282657" ModsDocID="6438" checkinTime="1243377138618" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="1981" docId="A9BAFB77C4972CD6D7BC076169E88AF2" docLanguage="en" docName="6438" docOrigin="Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology 43" docSource="http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6438" docTitle="Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="279" masterDocId="BC898CD1404B6DE3B19A96923068ACC3" masterDocTitle="A revision of six minor genera of Myrmicinae (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in the Ethiopian zoogeographical region." masterLastPageNumber="307" masterPageNumber="245" pageNumber="279" updateTime="1645805167815" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of six minor genera of Myrmicinae (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in the Ethiopian zoogeographical region.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1981</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>43</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>245</mods:start>
<mods:end>307</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://atbi.biosci.ohio-state.edu/HymOnline/reference-full.html?id=6438</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6438</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6282657" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127299" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6282657" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A9BAFB77C4972CD6D7BC076169E88AF2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A9BAFB77C4972CD6D7BC076169E88AF2" lastPageNumber="279" pageNumber="279">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="279">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:32963" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Ocymyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="279" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="turneri">Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="279">(Fig 25)</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="279">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:32963" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Ocymyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="279" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="turneri">Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe</taxonomicName>
, 1931: 499. Holotype worker, South West Africa: Walvis Bay, 1. xii. 1927 {R. E. Turner) (BMNH) [examined].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="279">Worker. TL 5.8, HL 1.40, HW 1 - 28, CI 91, SL 1.40, SI 109, PW 0.80, AL 1.76.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="279">Small species. Anterior clypeal margin without a median impression, on the contrary the middle of the anterior clypeal margin projecting forward as a low, broad triangular prominence. Eyes relatively large, maximum diameter 0.36, about 0.28 x HW. In full-face view the eyes very conspicuously breaking the outline of the sides of the head. Antennal scapes relatively long, SI&gt; 100. Promesonotum in profile rounded, with a low transversely arched crest running across the dorsum at the junction of pronotum and mesonotum, arching forward from the mesothoracic spiracle on each side. Posterior part of mesonotum and anterior part of propodeum concave in profile, the posterior portion of the propodeum convex and curving evenly into the declivity behind. Petiole node in profile high, subconical, with a narrowly rounded dorsum, the posterior face convex, the anterior face longer, almost flat and less steeply sloped than the posterior face. Petiole node in dorsal view longer than broad, the postpetiole broader than long. First gastral tergite without a constricted basal neck. Dorsum of head glossy, sculptured with very feeble superficial rugulae which are transversely arched and are almost effaced occipitally. Ground-sculpture between the faint rugulae absent. Dorsal alitrunk unsculptured, smooth and highly polished except for vestiges of faint transverse rugulae on the extreme anterior portion of the pronotum and the propodeal declivity. On the sides of the alitrunk the pleurae with strong, widely spaced and roughly parallel rugae, otherwise unsculptured except for vestiges on the sides of the pronotum near the base. Petiole and postpetiole only with faint superficial patterning which is almost effaced in places. All dorsal surfaces of head and body with scattered hairs of varying length but the holotype (and only known specimen) appears to be considerably abraded and in life this species may well be as hairy as other species in the genus. Alitrunk jet black and shiny, head and gaster blackish brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="279">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:32963" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Ocymyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Ocymyrmex turneri Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="279" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="turneri">O. turneri</taxonomicName>
is one of the smallest species known in the genus and is easily distinguished from all others by having an unconstricted base to the gaster, large eyes which break the outline of the sides of the head, reduced sculpture, relatively long antennal scapes and a clypeal margin which projects medially into a low triangular prominence. To date it remains known only from the holotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>