<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5251132" ID-ISSN="1175­5334" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5251132" approvalRequired="61" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="17" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="21" approvalRequired_for_treatments="23" checkinTime="1629769444124" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Belokobylskij, Sergey A. &amp; Kula, Robert R." docDate="2012" docId="B9118782FFDEFFA41099AF0FFE7092F8" docLanguage="en" docName="zt03240p062.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 3240 (1)" docSource="https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.3240.1.1" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1.1:Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleId="D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Pambolus erogolus Belokobylskij &amp; Kula 2012, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="26" masterDocId="4528FFFAFFC8FFBD100EAA10FFAD937F" masterDocTitle="Review of the brachypterous, micropterous, and apterous Braconidae of the cyclostome lineage (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonoidea) from the Palearctic Region 3240" masterLastPageNumber="62" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" updateTime="1629854041381" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the brachypterous, micropterous, and apterous Braconidae of the cyclostome lineage (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonoidea) from the Palearctic Region 3240</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Belokobylskij, Sergey A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kula, Robert R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2012-03-20</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3240</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>62</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.3240.1.1</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.3240.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5248977</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5251132" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5251132" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B9118782FFDEFFA41099AF0FFE7092F8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B9118782FFDEFFA41099AF0FFE7092F8" lastPageId="25" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<subSubSection box="[151,642,1311,1337]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,642,1311,1374]" box="[151,642,1311,1337]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,642,1311,1337]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,642,1311,1337]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<taxonomicName authority="Belokobylskij" authorityName="Belokobylskij &amp; Kula" authorityYear="2012" box="[151,562,1311,1337]" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erogolus" status="sp. n.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,383,1311,1337]" italics="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Pambolus erogolus</emphasis>
Belokobylskij
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[576,642,1311,1337]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,349,1350,1374]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,642,1311,1374]" box="[151,349,1350,1374]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,288,1350,1374]" captionStart="FIGURES 33–42" captionStartId="24.[151,263,1759,1782]" captionTargetBox="[160,1427,193,1742]" captionTargetId="figure-126@24.[142,1427,193,1790]" captionTargetPageId="24" captionText="FIGURES 33–42. Pambolus erogolus Belokobylskij, sp. n., female. 33. Head, front view. 34. Head, dorsal view. 35. Head, lateral view. 36. Scape and pedicel, lateral view. 37. Basal and apical segments of antenna, ventral view. 38. Mesosoma, lateral view. 39. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 40. Hind femur, lateral view. 41. Fore femur, lateral view. 42. Metasoma, dorsal view." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5248987" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5248987/files/figure.png" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Figs 33–42</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[299,341,1350,1374]" captionStart="FIGURES 117–126" captionStartId="49.[151,264,1813,1836]" captionTargetBox="[189,1376,233,1757]" captionTargetId="figure-97@49.[151,1436,193,1792]" captionTargetPageId="49" captionText="FIGURES 117–126. Habitus photos of brachypterous, micropterous, and apterous cyclostome braconids (117, 122–124 [dorsal view]; 118–121, 125–126 [lateral view]). 117. Dimeris mira Ruthe (female). 118. Eupambolus apterus Tobias (female, holotype). 119. Pambolus erogolus sp. n. (female, holotype). 120. Pambolus ovchinnikovi sp. n. (female, holotype). 121. Hormius minialatus Tobias (female, holotype). 122. Aleiodes hemipterus Marshall (female, lectotype). 123. Bracon barbieri sp. n. (female, holotype). 124. Chasmodon apterus (Nees) (female). 125. Lodbrokia mariae Sterzinski (female, holotype). 126. Panerema kamtshatica sp. n. (female, holotype)." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5249003" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5249003/files/figure.png" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">119</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="22" pageNumber="23" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,1437,1427,2033]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,329,1427,1452]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" reason="1">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation collectingDate="1975-08-03" collectionCode="ZISP" country="Mongolia" county="Aymak" location="Ero-gol River" municipality="Dulan-Khan" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Selenge" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[340,449,1428,1452]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Holotype</typeStatus>
: female, “ 
<collectingCountry box="[568,682,1428,1452]" name="Mongolia" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Mongolia</collectingCountry>
, Selenginskiy Aymak, Dulan-Khan, r.[eka] Ero-gol, step’, 
<date pageId="22" pageNumber="23" value="1975-08-03">
<collectingDate pageId="22" pageNumber="23" value="1975-08-03">3.VIII 1975</collectingDate>
</date>
, Narchuk” [
<collectingCountry box="[343,457,1466,1490]" name="Mongolia" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Mongolia</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[469,557,1466,1490]" country="Mongolia" name="Selenge" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Selenga</collectingRegion>
<collectingCounty box="[564,647,1466,1490]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Aymak</collectingCounty>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[658,799,1466,1490]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Dulan-Khan</collectingMunicipality>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B9118782FFDEFFA41099AF0FFE7092F8:3467604FFFDEFFAB1325AFAAFC6A96AD" box="[811,967,1466,1490]" country="Mongolia" county="Aymak" municipality="Dulan-Khan" name="Ero-gol River" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" stateProvince="Selenge">Ero-gol River</location>
, steppe, 
<date box="[1063,1198,1466,1490]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" value="1975-08-03">
<collectingDate box="[1063,1198,1466,1490]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" value="1975-08-03">3.VIII 1975</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B9118782FFDEFFA41099AF0FFE7092F8:3467604FFFDEFFAB14B4AFAAFAB096AD" box="[1210,1309,1466,1490]" country="Mongolia" county="Aymak" municipality="Dulan-Khan" name="Narchuk" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" stateProvince="Selenge">Narchuk</location>
] (
<collectionCode box="[1331,1394,1466,1490]" country="Russia" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/vmfx-g997" name="Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">ZISP</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[201,992,1505,1530]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,1437,1427,2033]" box="[201,992,1505,1530]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,335,1505,1529]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" reason="1">Etymology.</emphasis>
From “Ero-gol,” the name of the river of the 
<typeStatus box="[846,894,1506,1530]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">type</typeStatus>
locality.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="24" lastPageNumber="25" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,1437,1427,2033]" box="[201,701,1543,1568]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,346,1543,1568]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" reason="1">Description.</emphasis>
Female. Body length 
<quantity box="[594,697,1543,1567]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.9" pageId="22" pageNumber="23" unit="mm" value="2.9">2.90 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="22.[151,1437,1427,2033]" pageId="22" pageNumber="23">Head (dorsal view) 1.40 times as wide as median length, 1.55 times as wide as mesosoma at level of tegulae. Head behind eyes strongly, regularly, and weakly roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 2.00 times longer than temple (dorsal view). Ocelli in equilateral triangle. POL 1.60 times Od, 0.60 times OOL. Antennal sockets situated rather close to each other, diameter of socket 1.20 times distance between sockets, 1.40 times distance between socket and eye. Eye with short and sparse setae, almost without emargination opposite antennal socket, 1.25 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.70 times as high as eye, 1.80 times as high as basal width of mandible. Malar suture absent. Face very weakly convex, width 1.20 times eye height and 1.15 times height of face and clypeus combined. Tentorial pits rather large, distance between pits 0.85 times distance between pit and eye. Clypeus distinctly convex, straight on ventral margin, about twice as wide as high. Hypoclypeal depression oval, width 0.70 times distance from depression to eye, 0.45 times width of face. Occipital carina coarse, complete dorsally, joined ventrally with hypostomal carina above base of mandible. Hypostomal flange wide. Mandible rather slender, distinctly twisted. Head below eyes distinctly and convex-roundly narrowed (frontal view).</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1437,151,2030]" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Antenna rather thick, filiform, with 19 flagellomeres, 0.80 times as long as body. Scape short and wide, with very distinct excavation in apical and outer margin, 1.30 times longer than wide; inner length about twice as long as outer length. First flagellomere about twice as long as apical width, almost as long as second flagellomere. Penultimate flagellomere 1.70 times longer than wide, 0.70 times as long as first flagellomere, 0.85 times as long as apical flagellomere; the latter weakly pointed apically and without spine.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1437,151,2030]" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Mesosoma weakly reduced in size, short, length 1.50 times height. Pronotum rather short, weakly convex dorsally, with distinct pronotal keel in anterior 0.40, anterior margin of pronotum almost straight and with narrow flange (dorsal view). Mesoscutum rather highly and almost perpendicularly elevated above pronotum, marginated laterally by distinct carina, 0.80 times as long as wide. Notauli rather deep and wide anteriorly, shallow and narrow posteriorly, complete, very sparsely crenulate with coriaceous sculpture. Prescutellar depression relatively deep, long, with three high wrinkles, almost smooth, 0.50 times as long as scutellum dorsally. Scutellum weakly convex, with rather distinct lateral carinae, almost as long as basal width. Metanotal tooth distinct, but small, subpointed. Subalar depression rather deep, strigate-granulate. Mesopleural pit developed, but shallow. Furrow along mesopleural suture distinct and coarsely crenulate. Precoxal suture rather shallow, wide, oblique, sparsely and distinctly crenulate, running along anterior 0.60 of lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina very wide and coarse. Postpectal carina distinct. Metapleural lower lobe long, rather wide basally, rounded apically, directed forward. Propodeum (lateral view) strongly abrupted from basal 0.40, with long, subround (in dissection), wide basally and distinctly narrowed toward apex, weakly rounded apically lateral processes in posterior 0.35. In lateral view, mesothorax (on medial line) almost equal to prothorax and propodeum. Tegulae present.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1437,151,2030]" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Wings. Size of wings strongly reduced, wings rather wide, subpointed apically, with three short basal veins, with rather large sclerotized spot in apical 0.40, protruding shortly behind base of propodeum.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1437,151,2030]" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Legs. Femora thick and wide, without dorsal protuberance. Hind femur not curved basally, 3.00 times longer than maximum width. Hind tibia distinctly widened posteriorly. Hind tarsus 0.90 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.70 times as long as second through fifth tarsomeres combined. Second tarsomere of hind tarsus 0.40 times as long as basitarsus, 0.90 times as long as fifth tarsomere (without pretarsus). Claws distinctly curved in apical half.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1437,151,2030]" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Metasoma 1.80 times longer than maximum width, 1.10 times longer than head and mesosoma combined. First tergum with distinct lateral tubercles in basal 0.20, strongly, almost linearly and regularly, widened from base to apex, with weakly convex and narrow median area, with subparallel and narrowly separated dorsal carinae, dorsope deep, without spiracular tubercles, spiracles situated behind middle of tergum, in basal 0.55; length of tergum 0.90 times apical width, 1.10 times length of propodeum; apical width of tergum 2.40 times minimum basal width. Groove between second and third terga absent. Median length of second and third terga combined 1.55 times basal width of second tergum, 1.10 times maximum width. Apical terga shortly protruding behind third tergum. Ovipositor straight, very short, sheath 0.55 times as long as first metasomal tergum, 0.30 times as long as hind tibia, 0.80 times as long as hind basitarsus, 0.25 times as long as mesosoma.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="23.[151,1437,151,2030]" pageId="23" pageNumber="24">Sculpture and pubescence. Vertex very densely and distinctly granulate; frons densely granulate, additionally distinctly transversely strigate in median 0.30–0.50; face entirely densely granulate with fine strigation; temple densely granulate, finely granulate-coriaceous below, with coarse short rugosity along occipital carina. Sides of propleuron carinate-rugose medially, densely granulate below and above. Mesoscutum entirely distinctly and densely granulate, with rugosity anteriorly. Scutellum rather distinctly and densely granulate. Mesopleuron entirely and densely granulate, below with rugosity. Metapleuron coarsely areolate-rugose with dense and fine granulation. Propodeum densely and distinctly granulate in basal 0.40, coarsely rugose-carinate with dense granulation at least partially in posterior 0.60; areola more or less distinctly delineated by carina, long and narrow, with short basal carina. Hind coxa entirely densely granulate. Hind femur almost entirely with small but distinct granulae. First tergum distinctly and rather densely carinate medially, without carination laterally, entirely densely granulate-coriaceous. Second tergum very finely areolate-coriaceous basally, mostly smooth. Terga posterior to second tergum smooth. Vertex almost entirely with rather dense, short, and almost recumbent pale setae. Mesonotum with rather dense, short, semi-erect pale setae spaced rather widely along notauli and narrowly laterally. Second and third terga with very sparse, short, and almost erect setae; terga posterior to third tergum each with single row of semi-erect short setae along subposterior margin. Hind tibia dorsally with dense, short, and semi-erect setae, length of those setae 0.40–0.45 times as long as maximum width of hind tibia.</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5248987" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5248987" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5248987/files/figure.png" pageId="24" pageNumber="25" startId="24.[151,263,1759,1782]" targetBox="[160,1427,193,1742]" targetPageId="24">
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1436,1759,1843]" pageId="24" pageNumber="25">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,339,1759,1782]" pageId="24" pageNumber="25">FIGURES 33–42.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Belokobylskij" authorityName="Belokobylskij &amp; Kula" authorityYear="2012" box="[345,690,1760,1782]" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="24" pageNumber="25" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erogolus" status="sp. n.">
<emphasis box="[345,540,1760,1782]" italics="true" pageId="24" pageNumber="25">Pambolus erogolus</emphasis>
Belokobylskij
</taxonomicName>
, 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[700,756,1760,1781]" pageId="24" pageNumber="25">
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[700,756,1760,1781]" pageId="24" pageNumber="25" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
, female. 33. Head, front view. 34. Head, dorsal view. 35. Head, lateral view. 36. Scape and pedicel, lateral view. 37. Basal and apical segments of antenna, ventral view. 38. Mesosoma, lateral view. 39. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 40. Hind femur, lateral view. 41. Fore femur, lateral view. 42. Metasoma, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="24.[151,1436,1882,2015]" pageId="24" pageNumber="25">Color. Body predominantly light reddish brown, metasoma almost black on wide median part in posterior 0.30. Three basal flagellomeres of antenna light reddish brown, fourth through 13th flagellomeres dark reddish brown to black, six apical flagellomeres yellowish brown. Palpi yellow. Legs brownish yellow. Ovipositor sheath black. Male. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1440,151,392]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,323,151,176]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" reason="1">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
This new species is very similar to 
<taxonomicName authorityName=": Belokobylskij" authorityYear="1986" box="[741,901,152,176]" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="brevipennis">
<emphasis box="[741,901,152,176]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">P. brevipennis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
from 
<collectingCountry box="[973,1024,151,175]" name="Italy" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Italy</collectingCountry>
but differs as follows: temple long; occipital carina joined with hypostomal carina; mesoscutum rather highly and distinctly elevated above pronotum; fore wing very short, oval, and without distinct venation; first tergum long, carinate only medially and entirely densely granulate-coriaceous; and antenna dark medially. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Belokobylskij &amp; Kula" authorityYear="2012" box="[797,1013,260,284]" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="erogolus">
<emphasis box="[797,1013,260,284]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Pambolus erogolus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
differs from the Western Palearctic 
<taxonomicName authority="(Ruthe)" baseAuthorityName="Ruthe" baseAuthorityYear="1854" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tricolor">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">P. tricolor</emphasis>
(Ruthe)
</taxonomicName>
as follows: head behind eyes weakly convex, antennal flagellomeres slenderer and short, propodeum subvertically slanted in posterior half, all femora (especially fore femur) thick, and ovipositor short.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[201,477,367,392]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1440,151,392]" box="[201,477,367,392]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,354,367,392]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" reason="1">Distribution.</emphasis>
<collectingCountry box="[361,473,367,391]" name="Mongolia" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Mongolia</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>