<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5251136" ID-ISSN="1175­5334" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5251136" approvalRequired="61" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="17" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="21" approvalRequired_for_treatments="23" checkinTime="1629769444124" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Belokobylskij, Sergey A. &amp; Kula, Robert R." docDate="2012" docId="B9118782FFD1FFA71099A922FE5C94D5" docLanguage="en" docName="zt03240p062.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 3240 (1)" docSource="https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.3240.1.1" docStyle="DocumentStyle:D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1.1:Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleId="D239614CE4198176A422035174489AB1" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2009-2012.monograph" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Pambolus ovchinnikovi Belokobylskij &amp; Kula 2012, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="26" lastPageNumber="27" masterDocId="4528FFFAFFC8FFBD100EAA10FFAD937F" masterDocTitle="Review of the brachypterous, micropterous, and apterous Braconidae of the cyclostome lineage (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonoidea) from the Palearctic Region 3240" masterLastPageNumber="62" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" updateTime="1629854041381" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the brachypterous, micropterous, and apterous Braconidae of the cyclostome lineage (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonoidea) from the Palearctic Region 3240</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Belokobylskij, Sergey A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kula, Robert R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2012-03-20</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3240</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>62</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>https://biotaxa.org/Zootaxa/article/view/zootaxa.3240.1.1</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.3240.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5248977</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5251136" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5251136" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B9118782FFD1FFA71099A922FE5C94D5" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B9118782FFD1FFA71099A922FE5C94D5" lastPageId="26" lastPageNumber="27" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<subSubSection box="[151,694,818,844]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,694,818,877]" box="[151,694,818,844]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,694,818,844]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,694,818,844]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<taxonomicName authority="Belokobylskij" authorityName="Belokobylskij &amp; Kula" authorityYear="2012" box="[151,614,818,844]" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ovchinnikovi" status="sp. n.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,435,818,844]" italics="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Pambolus ovchinnikovi</emphasis>
Belokobylskij
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[628,694,818,844]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[151,351,853,877]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,694,818,877]" box="[151,351,853,877]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,288,853,877]" captionStart="FIGURES 43–55" captionStartId="27.[151,263,1765,1788]" captionTargetBox="[202,1429,177,1747]" captionTargetId="figure-92@27.[169,1429,177,1773]" captionTargetPageId="27" captionText="FIGURES 43–55. Pambolus ovchinnikovi Belokobylskij, sp. n., female. 43. Head, front view. 44. Head, dorsal view. 45. Head, lateral view. 46. Basal and apical segments of antenna, dorsal view. 47. Scape and pedicel, lateral view. 48. Fore wing. 49. Mesosoma, lateral view. 50. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 51. Propodeum, dorso-posterior view. 52. Fore femur, lateral view. 53. Hind femur, lateral view. 54. Apex of metasoma and ovipositor, lateral view. 55. Metasoma, dorsal view." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5248989" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5248989/files/figure.png" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Figs 43–55</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[299,342,853,877]" captionStart="FIGURES 117–126" captionStartId="49.[151,264,1813,1836]" captionTargetBox="[189,1376,233,1757]" captionTargetId="figure-97@49.[151,1436,193,1792]" captionTargetPageId="49" captionText="FIGURES 117–126. Habitus photos of brachypterous, micropterous, and apterous cyclostome braconids (117, 122–124 [dorsal view]; 118–121, 125–126 [lateral view]). 117. Dimeris mira Ruthe (female). 118. Eupambolus apterus Tobias (female, holotype). 119. Pambolus erogolus sp. n. (female, holotype). 120. Pambolus ovchinnikovi sp. n. (female, holotype). 121. Hormius minialatus Tobias (female, holotype). 122. Aleiodes hemipterus Marshall (female, lectotype). 123. Bracon barbieri sp. n. (female, holotype). 124. Chasmodon apterus (Nees) (female). 125. Lodbrokia mariae Sterzinski (female, holotype). 126. Panerema kamtshatica sp. n. (female, holotype)." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5249003" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5249003/files/figure.png" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">120</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,925,2020]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,325,925,950]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" reason="1">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation collectingDate="1994-10-17" collectionCode="ZISP" collectorName="S. Ovchinnikov" country="Kyrgyzstan" location="Kirgizia" municipality="Yu" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Bishkek Shaary" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[332,441,925,949]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Holotype</typeStatus>
: female, “ 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B9118782FFD1FFA71099A922FE5C94D5:3467604FFFD1FFA41227A98DFD2490CA" box="[553,649,925,949]" country="Kyrgyzstan" municipality="Yu" name="Kirgizia" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" stateProvince="Bishkek Shaary">Kirgizia</location>
, 
<collectingMunicipality box="[660,695,925,949]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Yu</collectingMunicipality>
[zhnaia] okraina g. 
<collectingRegion box="[911,1005,925,949]" country="Kyrgyzstan" name="Bishkek Shaary" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Bishkek</collectingRegion>
, predgor’ia, pod kamnem, 
<date box="[1310,1432,925,949]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" value="1994-10-17">
<collectingDate box="[1310,1432,925,949]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" value="1994-10-17">17.X 1994</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName box="[151,331,961,985]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">S. Ovchinnikov</collectorName>
” [
<collectingCountry box="[355,489,962,986]" name="Kyrgyzstan" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Kyrgyzstan</collectingCountry>
, south outskirts of 
<collectingRegion box="[708,803,961,985]" country="Kyrgyzstan" name="Bishkek Shaary" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Bishkek</collectingRegion>
, foothills, under stone, 
<date box="[1071,1194,961,985]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" value="1994-10-17">
<collectingDate box="[1071,1194,961,985]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" value="1994-10-17">17.X 1994</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName box="[1207,1384,961,985]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">S. Ovchinnikov</collectorName>
leg] (
<collectionCode box="[159,222,997,1021]" country="Russia" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/vmfx-g997" name="Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">ZISP</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[201,1159,1033,1057]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,925,2020]" box="[201,1159,1033,1057]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,335,1033,1057]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" reason="1">Etymology.</emphasis>
In honor of the late Dr. Sergey Ovchinnikov, who collected the 
<typeStatus box="[1053,1154,1033,1057]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">holotype</typeStatus>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="26" lastPageNumber="27" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,925,2020]" box="[201,701,1069,1094]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,346,1069,1094]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" reason="1">Description.</emphasis>
Female. Body length 
<quantity box="[594,697,1069,1093]" metricMagnitude="-3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.6" pageId="25" pageNumber="26" unit="mm" value="2.6">2.60 mm</quantity>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,925,2020]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Head (dorsal view) 1.80 times as wide as median length, 1.50 times as wide as mesosoma at level of tegulae. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) very weakly in anterior 0.30, and distinctly in posterior 0.70, roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 1.15 times longer than temple (dorsal view). Ocelli in triangle with base 1.10 times sides. POL 2.20 times Od, 0.50 times OOL. Antennal sockets situated rather widely from each other, diameter of socket equal to distance between sockets, 1.40 times distance between socket and eye. Eye with very short and sparse setae, without emargination opposite antennal socket, 1.20 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.90 times as high as eye, 1.90 times as high as basal width of mandible. Malar suture absent. Face convex, width 1.50 times eye height and 1.35 times height of face and clypeus combined. Tentorial pits rather large, distance between pits 0.80 times distance between pit and eye. Clypeus convex, almost straight on medioventral margin, about 2.50 times as wide as high. Hypoclypeal depression oval, width 0.70 times distance from depression to eye, 0.45 times width of face. Occipital carina distinct, complete dorsally, joined ventrally with hypostomal carina above base of mandible. Hypostomal flange wide. Mandible rather slender, weakly twisted. Head below eyes (front view) distinctly and roundly narrowed.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,925,2020]" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Antenna rather thick, filiform, with 22 flagellomeres, almost as long as body. Scape short and wide, with very distinct excavation in apical and outer margin, 1.30 times longer than wide; inner length about twice as long as outer length. First flagellomere 2.40 times longer than apical width, as long as second flagellomere. Penultimate flagellomere 2.00 times longer than wide, 0.60 times as long as first flagellomere, 0.85 times as long as apical flagellomere; the latter obtuse apically and without spine.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="25.[151,1437,925,2020]" lastBlockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" lastPageId="26" lastPageNumber="27" pageId="25" pageNumber="26">Mesosoma weakly reduced in size, short, length 1.50 times height. Pronotum rather short, convex dorsally, without pronotal keel, anterior margin of pronotum weakly convex and with wide flange (dorsal view). Mesoscutum highly and roundly elevated above pronotum, margined laterally by distinct carina, 0.60 times as long as wide. Notauli shallow and wide, complete, sparsely crenulate. Prescutellar depression deep, long, with three high wrinkles, finely granulate, 0.50 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum weakly convex, with distinct lateral carinae, almost as long as basal width. Metanotal tooth distinct, but short and rounded. Subalar depression shallow, narrow, strigate-granulate. Mesopleural pit distinct and elongate. Furrow along mesopleural suture distinct and finely shortly crenulate. Precoxal suture shallow, wide, oblique, sparsely crenulate, running along anterior 0.50 of lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina wide and coarse. Postpectal carina rather distinct and short. Metapleural lower lobe long, wide, subpointed apically. Propodeum (lateral view) strongly abrupted from basal 0.40, with long, thick, subtriangular (in dissection), wide basally and distinctly narrowed toward apex, subpointed apically submedian lateral processes. In dorsal view, mesothorax (on medial line) about 4.00 times longer than prothorax and 1.50 times longer than propodeum. Tegulae present.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Wings. Size of fore wing strongly reduced, wing oval, rounded apically, with three short basal veins, with large sclerotized spot in apical 0.40, protruding shortly behind base of propodeum. Size of hind wing very strongly reduced and apically with small sclerotized spot.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Legs. Femora thick and wide, without dorsal protuberance. Hind femur evenly curved (dorsal view), not curved basally (lateral view), 3.10 times longer than wide. Hind tibia distinctly widened posteriorly. Hind tarsus 0.90 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.60 times as long as second through fifth tarsomeres combined. Second tarsomere of hind tarsus 0.50 times as long as basitarsus, 1.20 times longer than fifth tarsomere (without pretarsus). Claws weakly curved in apical half.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Metasoma 2.00 times longer than maximum width, 1.20 times longer than head and mesosoma combined. First tergum with short and wide lateral tubercles in basal 0.20, weakly widened basally, then strongly, almost linearly, and regularly widened to apex, with weakly convex, narrow, and parallel-sided median area, with weakly convergent dorsal carinae, dorsope deep, without spiracular tubercles, spiracles situated behind middle of tergum, in basal 0.60; length of tergum 0.70 times apical width, equal to length of propodeum; apical width of tergum 2.80 times minimum basal width. Groove between second and third terga absent. Median length of second and third terga combined 1.35 times basal width of second tergum, equal to maximum width. Apical terga distinctly protruding behind third tergum. Ovipositor weakly upcurved, rather long, sheath 1.60 times longer than first metasomal tergum, 0.70 times as long as hind tibia, 2.00 times longer than hind basitarsus, 0.70 times as long as mesosoma.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Sculpture and pubescence. Vertex entirely, finely, and densely granulate, partly coriaceous; frons densely granulate, with fine carination medially and laterally; face widely smooth, with two narrow submedian vertical stripes with strigulation; temple densely granulate in upper 0.30, finely coriaceous to smooth below, with fine short rugae along carina. Sides of propleuron carinate-rugulose, with dense granulation below. Mesoscutum entirely finely and densely granulate, with very fine rugosity anteriorly, with three longitudinal wrinkles and fine rugulosity in medioposterior half. Scutellum mostly smooth, finely coriaceous laterally. Mesopleuron finely coriaceous, partly smooth. Metapleuron coarsely rugose-areolate, with dense and fine granulation anteriorly only. Propodeum finely granulate-coriaceous in basal half, coarsely strigate in apical half; areola distinctly delineated by carina, short and rather narrow, basal carina short, about as long as anterior fork of areola; petiolate area long, wide anteriorly and narrow posteriorly. Hind coxa densely carinate. Hind femur almost entirely and distinctly granulate. First tergum medially distinctly and densely carinate with very fine granulation, laterally almost smooth and partly coriaceous. Terga posterior to first tergum smooth. Vertex almost entirely with rather dense, long, and semi-erect pale setae. Mesonotum with dense, long, semi-erect pale setae spaced rather widely along notauli and narrowly laterally. Second tergum entirely and third tergum mostly with sparse, long, and almost erect setae; terga posterior to third tergum each with single row of semi-erect long setae along subposterior margin. Hind tibia dorsally with dense, short, and semi-erect setae, length of those setae about 0.50 times as long as maximum width of hind tibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Color. Head yellowish brown, light reddish brown to reddish brown in upper 0.30. Mesosoma and first metasomal tergum yellowish brown or light reddish brown, metasomal terga posterior to third tergum black. Antenna predominantly black, brown apically, two basal segments yellowish brown. Palpi yellow. Legs predominantly yellow, hind femur yellowish brown. Ovipositor sheath black.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" box="[201,390,1613,1637]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Male. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="26" pageNumber="27" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,323,1649,1674]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" reason="1">Diagnosis.</emphasis>
This new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName authorityName=": Fahringer" authorityYear="1930" box="[682,808,1649,1673]" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="biglumis">
<emphasis box="[682,808,1649,1673]" italics="true" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">P. biglumis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(see description of female in Belokobylskij, 1986) but differs as follows: temple and malar space long, antenna with more flagellomeres, penultimate flagellomere long, mesoscutum laterally without depressions, propodeum obliquely slanted in posterior 0.70, first metasomal tergum short and wide, ovipositor long, mesonotum finely granulate, and propodeum mostly smooth with areolation. 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Belokobylskij &amp; Kula" authorityYear="2012" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ovchinnikovi">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Pambolus ovchinnikovi</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
also resembles 
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="Ruthe" baseAuthorityYear="1854" box="[558,676,1793,1817]" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Pambolus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tricolor">
<emphasis box="[558,676,1793,1817]" italics="true" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">P. tricolor</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
but differs as follows: antenna dark in apical half; mesopleuron widely smooth and only partly finely coriaceous; temple finely or very finely granulate and partly with additional fine strigation; mesoscutum finely coriaceous; ovipositor upcurved; and metasoma behind first tergum with long, almost erect and rather dense setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[201,497,1937,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" type="distribution">
<paragraph blockId="26.[151,1437,151,1962]" box="[201,497,1937,1962]" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[201,354,1937,1962]" inLineHeading="true" pageId="26" pageNumber="27" reason="1">Distribution.</emphasis>
<collectingCountry box="[361,493,1938,1962]" name="Kyrgyzstan" pageId="26" pageNumber="27">Kyrgyzstan</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>