<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.79.56481" ID-GBIF-Dataset="572dc92e-ca99-49fa-8ca4-9b912651f0fa" ID-GBIF-Taxon="168745952" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1314-2607-79-57" ID-Pensoft-UUID="9D10009F3B4355EC848CDAC4C04CDBC9" ID-ZooBank="F878BBE5F79C458FBB527012279F4A79" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:583DCA0A-F26B-4599-87BB-53DE68D3CDA8" ModsDocID="1314-2607-79-57" checkinTime="1604097868884" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Timokhov, Alexander V. &amp; Belokobylskij, Sergey A." docDate="2020" docId="10BF25F1B0BD507891984D9B1F453B39" docLanguage="en" docName="JourHymenoptRes 79: 57-76" docOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 79" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.79.56481" docTitle="Vanhornia yurii Timokhov &amp; Belokobylskij 2020, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docUuid="583DCA0A-F26B-4599-87BB-53DE68D3CDA8" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" id="9D10009F3B4355EC848CDAC4C04CDBC9" lastPageNumber="57" masterDocId="9D10009F3B4355EC848CDAC4C04CDBC9" masterDocTitle="Review of the rare genus Vanhornia Crawford, 1909 (Hymenoptera, Proctotrupoidea, Vanhorniidae) with description of a new species from the Russian Far East" masterLastPageNumber="76" masterPageNumber="57" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" updateTime="1643441940842" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the rare genus Vanhornia Crawford, 1909 (Hymenoptera, Proctotrupoidea, Vanhorniidae) with description of a new species from the Russian Far East</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Timokhov, Alexander V.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Department of Entomology, Lomonosov Moscow State University, Moscow 119234, Russia</mods:affiliation>
<mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7040-6290</mods:nameIdentifier>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Belokobylskij, Sergey A.</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, St. Petersburg 199034, Russia</mods:affiliation>
<mods:nameIdentifier type="email">doryctes@gmail.com</mods:nameIdentifier>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of Hymenoptera Research</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>79</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>57</mods:start>
<mods:end>76</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.79.56481</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.79.56481</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1314-2607-79-57</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F878BBE5F79C458FBB527012279F4A79</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-UUID">9D10009F3B4355EC848CDAC4C04CDBC9</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="168745952" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:583DCA0A-F26B-4599-87BB-53DE68D3CDA8" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/10BF25F1B0BD507891984D9B1F453B39" lastPageNumber="57" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="57" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<taxonomicName LSID="10BF25F1-B0BD-5078-9198-4D9B1F453B39" authority="Timokhov &amp; Belokobylskij" authorityName="Timokhov &amp; Belokobylskij" authorityYear="2020" class="Insecta" family="Vanhorniidae" genus="Vanhornia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Vanhornia yurii" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yurii" status="sp. nov.">Vanhornia yurii Timokhov &amp; Belokobylskij</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="57">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 1" captionStartId="F1" captionText="Figure 1. Vanhornia yurii sp. nov. (female, holotype) A habitus, dorsal view B mandible, antero-lateral view C head, lateral view D head, front view E head, dorsal view F antenna G mesosoma, dorsal view H mesosoma, lateral view I hind leg." figureDoi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure1" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469453" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Figs 1</figureCitation>
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 2" captionStartId="F2" captionText="Figure 2. Vanhornia yurii sp. nov. (female, holotype) A wings B metasomal tergite 6, posterior view C metasoma, dorsal view D metasoma, ventral view E metasoma, lateral view." figureDoi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure2" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469454" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">, 2</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="57" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Holotype</emphasis>
, ♀, &quot;RUSSIA, Primorskiy kray [Territory], Lazovsk. z-k [Lazovsky Nature Reserve], b. [bukhta = Bay] Proselochnaya, 21-25.VII.2008, Yu. Sundukov [coll.]&quot; (ZISP).
</paragraph>
<caption doi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure1" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469453" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" start="Figure 1" startId="F1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Figure 1.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authorityName="Timokhov &amp; Belokobylskij" authorityYear="2020" class="Insecta" family="Vanhorniidae" genus="Vanhornia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Vanhornia yurii" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yurii">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Vanhornia yurii</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. (female, holotype) 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">A</emphasis>
habitus, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">B</emphasis>
mandible, antero-lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">C</emphasis>
head, lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">D</emphasis>
head, front view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">E</emphasis>
head, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">F</emphasis>
antenna 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">G</emphasis>
mesosoma, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">H</emphasis>
mesosoma, lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">I</emphasis>
hind leg.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption doi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure2" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469454" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" start="Figure 2" startId="F2">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Figure 2.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authorityName="Timokhov &amp; Belokobylskij" authorityYear="2020" class="Insecta" family="Vanhorniidae" genus="Vanhornia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Vanhornia yurii" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="yurii">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Vanhornia yurii</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
sp. nov. (female, holotype) 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">A</emphasis>
wings 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">B</emphasis>
metasomal tergite 6, posterior view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">C</emphasis>
metasoma, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">D</emphasis>
metasoma, ventral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">E</emphasis>
metasoma, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="57" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Female.</emphasis>
Body length 3.9 mm; fore wing length 2.6 mm; antenna length 1.5 mm; ovipositor length 2.7 mm.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Head</emphasis>
: In dorsal view 1.35 times as wide as its medium length, 1.3 times as wide as maximum width of mesoscutum; in lateral view 1.1 times as high as long; vertex distinctly roundly convex. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex in anterior two-thirds, then weakly roundly narrowed. Vertex posteriorly without median longitudinal sulcus. Temple bulging, almost equal to transverse diameter of eye (dorsal view). Eyes suboval, slightly narrowed ventrally, bare. Ocelli weakly enlarged, arranged in obtuse triangle with base (POL) 1.5 times as large as its sides (LOL). POL almost 4.0 times OD, 1.6 times OOL. Occipital carina interrupted dorsally over wide distance, present laterally. Occiput dorsally with effaced vertical median sulcus. Frons distinctly widely convex medially, with small shallow but distinctly rounded submedian depression. Antennal scrobes present as shallow, smooth, subvertical oblique lateral furrows, without marginal carinae delimiting them from the central area of frons. Interantennal process present as obtuse low convex vertical cushion. Clypeal suture distinct and deep. Clypeus narrow and very wide, with two medio-lateral acuminate corners, distinctly concave medially and weakly concave laterally, about 5.0 times as wide as median height. Malar space very short. Temple along its lower margin (between occipital carina and eye) with transverse crenulate narrow furrow. Mandible with four distinct and thick teeth and small additional tubercle on antero-lateral surface; apically two anterior teeth rather acuminate and two posterior teeth rounded and obtuse; anterior tooth distinctly separate from more closely situated three posterior teeth. Clypeus and base of mandibles covered by rather dense long whitish setae. Vertex and temple entirely in distinct but small, numerous and rather dense setiferous punctation; frons finely and sparsely punctate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Antennae</emphasis>
: Thickened, setiform, gradually weakly narrowed apically, 13-segmented, with very dense and short setosity. Scapus widened distally, 1.7 times as long as maximum apical width, about 2.5 times as long as subglobal pedicel. First flagellomere longest and widest, evenly widened towards apex, 2.6 times as long as its maximum width, 1.3 times as long as second flagellomere. Antennomeres A5-A9 elongate, uniform in length. Penultimate segment 2.0 times longer than wide, 0.75 times as long as apical segment; the latter weakly acuminate apically.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Mesosoma</emphasis>
: Almost as high as wide, 2.1 times as long as maximum width (dorsal view), 1.9 times as long as maximum height (lateral view). Pronotal collar elongate, rugose-reticulate posteriorly and medially (dorsal view). Netrion almost spindle-shaped, smooth, distinctly delimited by complete and crenulate with rugosity netrion sulcus. Mesoscutum distinctly transverse, 1.5 times wider than medial length, weakly convex, almost entirely distinctly and rather densely (but fine and sparse posteriorly, including between notauli) punctate with short and pale setae. Notauli arcuate, deep, complete throughout, distinctly and rather sparsely crenulate, not widened posteriorly. Parapsidal lines present and narrow. Scutoscutellar (prescutellar) sulcus deep, curved, with seven rather narrow foveae separated by distinct high striae. Scutellum rather large, distinctly narrowed posteriorly, almost as wide anteriorly as its median length, posterior fifth of scutellum separated by deep and distinctly crenulate transverse curved mesoscutellar sulcus. Metanotum (dorsal view) medially with subsquare and coarsely rugose convex area, laterally coarsely and sparsely crenulate with rugosity. Mesopleuron in wide and mainly concave median area (femoral depression) smooth and bare, antero-ventrally with wide crenulation at short distance; mesopleural carina (anterior ridge of mesopleuron) sharp, rugulose-crenulate in antero-dorsal half, extending posteroventrad as low and effaced ridge to postpectal (ventral mesopleural) carina; speculum smooth; mesepimeral sulcus comprised of large subcircular foveae above and smaller transversely elongate foveae below; lower convex longitudinal area of mesopleuron anteriorly distinctly rugulose-punctate, finely and sparsely punctate posteriorly; mesodiscrimen wide, percurrent, foveolate, in sparse and coarse crenulation. Propodeum mostly coarsely reticulate-areolate; basally with two curved short medial keels and two long, oblique, posteriorly converging lateral keels, delimiting three rather small mainly smooth but rugose posteriorly basal areas; with complete high coarse transverse curved keel in posterior 0.4 of propodeum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Fore wing</emphasis>
: About 3.0 times as long as maximum width, entirely in dense and dark setosity. Radial cell distinctly shortened, surpassed by postmarginal vein, 3.5 times as long as maximum width. Costal section of radial cell 1.4 times length of pterostigma, about 1.5 times distance from apex of radial cell to apex of wing. Apical (terminal) abscissa of radial vein (3-Rs) weakly curved basally and almost straight in distal half, 3.0 times as long as preceding abscissa of this vein (2-Rs). Medial cell small and narrow, strongly narrowed distally. Vein cu-a straight and interstitial to vein 1-M.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Legs</emphasis>
: Slender. Hind femur distinctly narrowed basally and apically, 4.0 times as long as maximum width. Trochantelli absent on all legs. Tibial spurs short, their formula 1/2/2.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Metasoma</emphasis>
: Narrow (dorsal view). Syntergite 2-5 (dorsal view) without any traces of fusion of tergites, 2.4 times as long as its maximum width; basally with high and coarse weakly curved transverse keel, medially and laterally with coarse longitudinal keels in basal quarter of syntergite, with several and rather sparse longitudinal striation on basal 0.2; remaining part of syntergite entirely in rather dense but fine setiferous punctation. Synsternite 2-5 with a percurrent deep, relatively narrow and almost smooth groove on midline, almost entirely in dense and fine setiferous punctation, upper smooth on narrow stripe, posteriorly in narrow area in dense, straight or weakly curved vertical striation. Cowled tergite 6 abruptly deflexed, mostly in sparse and fine setiferous punctation, almost smooth in anterior vertical third; in posterior view, rather narrow, subtriangular shape, strongly narrowed to lower margin and distinctly convex upper, 1.4 times as high as maximum width, with distinct median obtuse and smooth vertical bar. Ovipositor mostly exposed, slender and flexible, its visible part 0.7 times as long as body.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Colour</emphasis>
: Body mainly black, metasoma with brown parts. Antenna black; mandibles mostly brown with black teeth; palpi light brown to brown. Legs brown to dark reddish brown, fore and middle tibiae and tarsi and hind tarsus yellow to partly brownish yellow. Tegula dark brown. Fore wing faintly infuscate; sclerotised veins brown; pterostigma black. Ovipositor yellow.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Male.</emphasis>
Unknown.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="57" type="comparative diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Comparative diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
This new species is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="V." lsidName="V. quizhouensis" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" rank="species" species="quizhouensis">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">V. quizhouensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(He &amp; Chu, 1990) from China (Guizhou) (Fig. 
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 3" captionStartId="F3" captionText="Figure 3. Vanhornia quizhouensis (He &amp; Chu, 1990) (female, holotype) A habitus, dorsal view B mandible, ventro-lateral view C head, front view D head, dorsal view E mesosoma, dorsal view F mesosoma, lateral view G metasoma, dorsal view H metasoma, lateral view I wings." figureDoi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure3" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469455" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">3</figureCitation>
) and Thailand, but differs from it in having the vertex without median longitudinal sulcus (vs. such sulcus present), mesoscutum in fine, small and dense setiferous punctation (vs. punctation distinct, enlarged and rather sparse), scutoscutellar (prescutellar) sulcus with seven narrow foveae (vs. only five foveae), vein cu-a in fore wing straight and interstitial to vein 1-M (vs. curved posteriorly and antefurcal); metasoma narrow, syntergite 2-5 in dorsal view 2.4 times as long as its maximum width (vs. 1.9 times).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
The new species is also similar to the North American 
<taxonomicName genus="V." lsidName="V. eucnemidarum" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" rank="species" species="eucnemidarum">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">V. eucnemidarum</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
Crawford, 1909 (Fig. 
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 4" captionStartId="F4" captionText="Figure 4. Vanhornia eucnemidarum Crawford, 1909 (female, specimens from USA) A habitus, dorsal view B body, dorsal view C body, lateral view D antennae, head and mesosoma, ventral view E right mandible, lateral view F head and mesoscutum, dorso-lateral view G head, front view H mesosoma, lateral view I metasoma, dorsal view J metasoma, ventral view K wings." figureDoi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure4" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469456" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">4</figureCitation>
), but differs from it in the scutoscutellar (prescutellar) sulcus with seven narrow foveae (vs. only five foveae), metasoma narrow, syntergite 2-5 in dorsal view 2.4 times as long as its maximum width (vs. 1.86-2.07 times), femoral depression on mesopleuron mostly smooth and with crenulation anteroventrally (vs. with areolation medially and without lower crenulation), vertex without median longitudinal sulcus (vs. sulcus extends back from anterior ocellus proceeding into occipital vertical median sulcus), as well as distribution, in the East Palaearctic (vs. North America).
</paragraph>
<caption doi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure3" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469455" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" start="Figure 3" startId="F3">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Figure 3.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName baseAuthorityName="He &amp; Chu" baseAuthorityYear="1990" class="Insecta" family="Vanhorniidae" genus="Vanhornia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Vanhornia quizhouensis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quizhouensis">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Vanhornia quizhouensis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(He &amp; Chu, 1990) (female, holotype) 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">A</emphasis>
habitus, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">B</emphasis>
mandible, ventro-lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">C</emphasis>
head, front view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">D</emphasis>
head, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">E</emphasis>
mesosoma, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">F</emphasis>
mesosoma, lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">G</emphasis>
metasoma, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">H</emphasis>
metasoma, lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">I</emphasis>
wings.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption doi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure4" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469456" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" start="Figure 4" startId="F4">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Figure 4.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authorityName="Crawford" authorityYear="1909" class="Insecta" family="Vanhorniidae" genus="Vanhornia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Vanhornia eucnemidarum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="eucnemidarum">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Vanhornia eucnemidarum</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
Crawford, 1909 (female, specimens from USA) 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">A</emphasis>
habitus, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">B</emphasis>
body, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">C</emphasis>
body, lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">D</emphasis>
antennae, head and mesosoma, ventral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">E</emphasis>
right mandible, lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">F</emphasis>
head and mesoscutum, dorso-lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">G</emphasis>
head, front view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">H</emphasis>
mesosoma, lateral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">I</emphasis>
metasoma, dorsal view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">J</emphasis>
metasoma, ventral view 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">K</emphasis>
wings.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="57" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">This species is named in honour of its collector, Dr Yuriy N. Sundukov, a Russian coleopterist and hymenopterist.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="57" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Distribution</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
(Fig. 
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 8" captionStartId="F8" captionText="Figure 8. Map of distribution of Vanhornia in Eurasia. Green spot - V. yurii sp. nov., blue spots - V. leileri, yellow spots - V. quizhouensis, red spot - specimen from South Korea determined as V. eucnemidarum (Choi &amp; Lee, 2012)." figureDoi="10.3897/jhr.79.56481.figure8" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/469460" pageId="0" pageNumber="57">8</figureCitation>
). Russian Far East (Primorskiy Territory).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="57" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="57">
According to the illustration (
<bibRefCitation DOI="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aspen.2011.08.003" author="Choi, MB" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Asia-Pacific Entomology" pageId="0" pageNumber="57" pagination="59 - 61" refId="B9" refString="Choi, MB, Lee, JW, 2012. First record of Vanhorniidae (Hymenoptera: Proctotrupoidea) from Korea. Journal of Asia-Pacific Entomology 15: 59 - 61, DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aspen.2011.08.003" title="First record of Vanhorniidae (Hymenoptera: Proctotrupoidea) from Korea." url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aspen.2011.08.003" volume="15" year="2012">Choi and Lee 2012</bibRefCitation>
), the specimen found in South Korea could also belong to this species, but study of this specimen is necessary for correct confirmation of this suggestion.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>