<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490" ID-GBIF-Dataset="6202b897-11c1-4686-99d8-94b8174ac809" ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359745" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-55-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2010" ModsDocID="1313-2970-55-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 55" ModsDocTitle="Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) – review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America" checkinTime="1451251020634" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Gary A. P., Gibson" docDate="2010" docId="74461FD38A2E3170AEEF0B9880A50CAA" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 55: 1-75" docOrigin="ZooKeys 55" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490" docTitle="Calosota longiventris" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" masterDocId="FF9456530D10AC187F08FFB0FC42FFD0" masterDocTitle="Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) - review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America" masterLastPageNumber="75" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" updateTime="1643559592688" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea, Eupelmidae) - review of the New World and European fauna including revision of species from the West Indies and Central and North America</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gary A. P., Gibson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2010</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>55</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>75</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.55.490</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-55-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="159359745" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:74461FD38A2E3170AEEF0B9880A50CAA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/74461FD38A2E3170AEEF0B9880A50CAA" lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="32" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
<taxonomicName authority="Ashmead" class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris (Ashmead)</taxonomicName>
Figs 61831, 3745
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="31" pageNumber="32" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
<taxonomicName authority="Walker, 1837" authorityName="Walker" authorityYear="1837" class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosoter" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosoter longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosoter longiventris</taxonomicName>
<bibRefCitation author="Ashmead, WH" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington" pageId="54" pageNumber="55" pagination="4 - 20" title="On the genera of the Eupelminae." volume="4" year="1896">Ashmead 1896</bibRefCitation>
: 12-13. Lectotype ♀ (USNM, type no. 3463; examined), designated by 
<bibRefCitation author="Burks, BD" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences" pageId="55" pageNumber="56" pagination="26 - 31" title="North American species of Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera: Eupelmidae)." volume="63" year="1973">Burks 1973</bibRefCitation>
: 30.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Peck, O" journalOrPublisher="United States Department of Agriculture Monograph" pageId="56" pageNumber="57" pagination="507 - 514" title="Family Eupelmidae. In: Muesebeck CFW, Krombein KV, Townes HK (Eds), Hymenoptera of America north of Mexico: synoptic catalog." volume="2" year="1951">Peck 1951</bibRefCitation>
: 474.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="33" lastPageNumber="34" pageId="31" pageNumber="32" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="31" pageNumber="32">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="32" lastPageNumber="33" pageId="31" pageNumber="32">
FEMALE (Figs 18, 37). Length about 4.6-8.2 mm. Color. Head dark with limited green luster to largely green dorsally to entirely greenish or bluish-purple, except usually with variably distinct, dark to coppery region on vertex (when apparent region forming complete band between inner orbits or reduced to variably large and conspicuous regions adjacent to upper inner orbit and behind ocellar triangle), and usually with more or less M-like dark or coppery region (region sometimes narrowly divided below anterior ocellus, Fig. 6), the lateral arm of region sometimes extending dorsally to posterior ocellus lateral to anterior ocellus and ventrally toward but not distinctly merging with inner orbit; lower face often with slight coppery luster toward oral margin under some angles of light; back of head dark or greenish with slight coppery luster to bluish-purple under some angles of light but at most only obscurely different 
<pageBreakToken pageId="32" pageNumber="33" start="start">iated</pageBreakToken>
∩-shaped band along outer orbit and occiput. Maxillary and labial palpi dark. Antenna dark brown except scape often and pedicel sometimes with slight metallic luster. Tegula dark. Mesoscutum (Fig. 18) uniformly dark to dark greenish or bluish-green similar to head except notauli, anteroadmedian lines and parapsidal lines sometimes coppery or at least differentiated by a slightly different color and/or mesoscutum with a relatively obscure longitudinal dark or coppery band adjacent to combined notauli/anteroadmedian line; scutellar-axillar complex similar in color to most of mesoscutum or, more commonly, most of scutellum other than frenal area with more distinct coppery luster than any longitudinal bands of mesoscutum. Acropleuron dark brown to greenish or bluish-purple, the microsculptured region without distinct coppery luster. Legs sometimes dark except knees, extreme apices of tibiae, and tarsi extensively yellowish, but middle and hind (less commonly front leg) sometimes almost uniformly yellowish-orange (Fig. 37), though mesofemur often more distinctly orange compared to somewhat lighter tibia and metafemur sometimes with up to about basal half brownish or with slight metallic luster. Fore wing hyaline or variably distinctly brownish behind venation from about level of parastigma to apex of stigmal vein, often only anterior to mediocubital fold or also with longitudinally on convex portion of fold, but sometimes completely to hind margin excluding longitudinal folds; setae uniformly brown. Gaster (Figs 18, 37) sometimes entirely dark brown, more commonly brown dorsally with basal terga basolaterally and apical terga more extensively bluish-purple.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="33" lastPageNumber="34" pageId="32" pageNumber="33">
Structure/setation. Head in dorsal view about 1.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2.1×">-2.1x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, with IOD about 0.36
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.40×">-0.40x</normalizedToken>
head width, LOL usually slightly greater than OOL with OOL about 0.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
and LOL about 0.75
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1×">-1x</normalizedToken>
MPOD, and POL about 1.25
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.7×">-1.7x</normalizedToken>
MPOD; in frontal view about 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.3×">-1.3x</normalizedToken>
as wide as high, with dorsal margin of torulus at level of lower orbits; malar space about 0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="–0.7×">-0.7x</normalizedToken>
height of eye. Head (Fig. 6) with frontovertex and parascrobal region meshlike reticulate to about level of dorsal limit of interantennal region, medially the reticulations tapered ventrally between dorsal limits of smooth and shiny scrobes; lower parascrobal region and interantennal region much shallower meshlike reticulate to coriaceous-reticulate; clypeal region microcoriaceous and paraclypeal region obliquely reticulate-alutaceous. Head with dark setae on frontovertex and more conspicuous white setae on parascrobal region, interantennal region and lower face. Antenna with scape about 4.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="–5.2×">-5.2x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; pedicel about 2.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="–3.3×">-3.3x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; length of flagellum + pedicel about 1.45
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.6×">-1.6x</normalizedToken>
head width; flagellum not conspicuously clavate, the funiculars subequal in width and clava only slightly wider than funicle; combined length of fu1 + fu2 about 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.2×">-1.2x</normalizedToken>
as long as pedicel; fu1 about 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.9×">-1.9x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; subsequent funiculars all longer than wide with fu2 about 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2.5×">-2.5x</normalizedToken>
and fu8 about 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.6×">-1.6x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; clava often slightly collapsed, but about as long as apical 2-2.75 funiculars. Mesoscutum (Fig. 18) meshlike reticulate, the reticulations usually somewhat larger medially than laterally, with inconspicuous white setae; notaulus extending from spiracle as curved furrow on inclined anterior surface, its posterior limit contiguous dorsally with posterior limit of anteroadmedian line and together extending posteriorly (sometimes for almost entire length of mesoscutum) as very slightly concave 
<pageBreakToken pageId="33" pageNumber="34" start="start">parallel</pageBreakToken>
lines of much smaller reticulations (usually obscure unless differentiated also by color); parapsidal line usually quite a distinct region of microsculpture. Axillae elongate-triangular, separated by about 3.5
<normalizedToken originalValue="–5×">-5x</normalizedToken>
own width. Scutellum low convex, about 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; meshlike reticulate, the reticulations similar in size or smaller than on mesoscutum laterally and more elongate, at least medially; with inconspicuous white setae. Mesopleuron with exposed, bare, lower mesepimeron (cf. Fig. 55); acropleuron of smaller individuals sometimes meshlike coriaceous anteriorly but usually variably extensively though shallowly meshlike reticulate anteriorly, the sculpture becoming more coriaceous to obliquely coriaceous-alutaceous anterior to oblique microsculptured region and very finely, longitudinally coriaceous-alutaceous posteriorly. Fore wing with cc: mv: stv: pmv about 41-50: 22-25: 10: 12-15; basal cell entirely setose; cubital area bare except sometimes anteriorly along mediocubital fold and closed by setae along posterior margin over about apical third to half; disc setose except for short region of mediocubital fold just beyond basal fold or more distinct, often arcuate bare band along basal fold and mediocubital fold, the bare region sometimes separated from costal cell by line of setae but usually contiguous with costal cell. Metacoxa setose along dorsal, ventral and basal margins, and sometimes outer surface with up to about basal half sparsely setose. Propodeum with callus setose to posterior margin; bare anteriorly between spiracle and foramen. Gaster (Figs 18, 37) about 2.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="–3×">-3x</normalizedToken>
as long as mesosoma; more or less uniformly covered with white, hairlike setae; posterior margin of syntergum usually extending to or slightly beyond level of syntergum; syntergum about 3.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="–5.3×">-5.3x</normalizedToken>
as long as transcercal width, obviously compressed beyond level of cerci, and about 1.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="–2.5×">-2.5x</normalizedToken>
as long as penultimate tergum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">MALE (Fig. 45). Similar to female except as follows. Length about 2.6-4.1 mm. Color. Fore wing hyaline and middle leg usually more or less uniformly yellowish-orange beyond mesocoxa, the mesofemur sometimes slightly brownish and metafemur extensively brown with only knee or at most up to about apical quarter yellowish (Fig. 45); mesoscutum distinctly bluish or bluish-green except sometimes with more greenish or greenish-coppery paramedial bands in region of notauli/anteroadmedian lines, and scutellum dark with coppery luster.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
Structure/setation. Antenna with scape and pedicel both about 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; length of flagellum + pedicel about 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.4×">-1.4x</normalizedToken>
as long as head width; fu1 slightly widened distally and only about as long as maximum width; fu2 about 1.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.5×">-1.5x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; fu8 about 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="–1.3×">-1.3x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; and clava about equal in length to combined length of apical 2.5 funiculars. Fore wing with cc: mv: stv: pmv = 43-47: 22-24: 10: 10-11. Propodeum sometimes setose anteriorly only to level about equal with posterior margin of spiracle, and then often with 1 or 2 setae behind spiracle.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="biology">
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Unknown, but very probably a parasitoid of some wood-boring beetle.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="33" pageNumber="34">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="34" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="33" pageNumber="34">
USA. Arizona: Parker Cr., Sierra Ancha, 20.IV.47, H&amp;M Townes (1♀ AEIC). California: Santa Cruz Mts (♀ lectotype, 1♂ paralectotype). Marin Co., Mt. Tamalpais Watershed Area, Pine Mountain Fire Rd, 1100', 11.VII.04, R.L. Zuparko, ex. 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Fagaceae" genus="Quercus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Quercus agrifolia" order="Fagales" pageId="33" pageNumber="34" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="agrifolia">Quercus agrifolia</taxonomicName>
(1♀ RLZC). Mono Co., Sonora Pass, 11.VIII.73, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="34" pageNumber="35" start="start">L</pageBreakToken>
. Lacey (1♀ FSCA). Napa Co., E slope Mt. St. Helena, 1.4 mi. NE summit Hwy 53, VIII.66, H.B. Leech, emerged from cone picked from living 
<taxonomicName class="Pinopsida" family="Pinaceae" genus="Pinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Pinus attenuata" order="Pinales" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="attenuata">Pinus attenuata</taxonomicName>
(7♀, 1♂ CASC, CNC Photo 2009-40, 2009-23, CNC SEM 2009-44). Placer Co., 17.5 mi. E of Foresthill, Mosquito Ridge Rd, 4150', 11, 12, 14.IV, 20.V, 1, 29, 30.VI, 7, 13, 15, 21.VII, VII.66 (21♀, 3♂ CASC), 15.II, 16.IV, 24.VI.67 (2♀, 1♂ CASC, CNC Photo 2009-21, 2009-22), H.B. Leech, emerged from cone picked from living 
<taxonomicName class="Pinopsida" family="Pinaceae" genus="Pinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Pinus attenuata" order="Pinales" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="attenuata">Pinus attenuata</taxonomicName>
. Riverside Co., Menifee Valley, hills on W end, 33°39'N; 117°13'W, 1800', 1.
<normalizedToken originalValue="VII–">VII-</normalizedToken>
1.VIII.95, J.D. Pinto (1♀ UCRC). San Luis Opisbo Co., 6 mi. SE Pozo, R16E, T315, sects. 4-5, 1500', 2.
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–">IV-</normalizedToken>
4.V.89, W.E. Wahl (1♀ CNC). Shasta Co., Cayton, 14.VII.18, E.P. VanDuzee (1♀ EMEC). Tuolumne Co., Stanislaus Natl For., Clark Fork Rd, 1 mi. N Hwy 106, 38°21'50N; 119°52'20W, 556', 12.VII.06, S. Fullerton, E. Zoll, S. Kelly, R.P. Russell, Manzatia scrub (21♂ UCFC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Nearctic: southwestern USA (Map 3).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
As stated by 
<bibRefCitation author="Burks, BD" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences" pageId="55" pageNumber="56" pagination="26 - 31" title="North American species of Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera: Eupelmidae)." volume="63" year="1973">Burks (1973)</bibRefCitation>
, the lectotype of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
is 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“fragmentary”">&quot;fragmentary&quot;</normalizedToken>
, including about the apical half of the syntergum broken off and glued to the plastic point, to which separately are glued the remainder of the metasoma, leg parts, and the mesosoma plus head. The head lacks the left antenna beyond fu2 and the right antenna beyond fu6. However, the body parts remaining are sufficient to readily place the name, including the relatively short funiculars [fu1-fu6 = 13(9), 26(10), 27(10), 29(10), 29(10), 21(10)], conspicuously long syntergum, and yellowish-orange middle and hind legs. As noted by 
<bibRefCitation author="Burks, BD" journalOrPublisher="Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences" pageId="55" pageNumber="56" pagination="26 - 31" title="North American species of Calosota Curtis (Hymenoptera: Eupelmidae)." volume="63" year="1973">Burks (1973)</bibRefCitation>
, the remaining fore wing is hyaline; additionally, the lectotype is one of few females observed with a line of setae separating the cubital area from the short bare region of the convex part of the mediocubital fold (most setae abraded but setal pattern indicated by sockets). The male paralectotype from the same locality has the same setal pattern, but I identify the male paralectotype from Argus Mts as a male of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota aestivalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aestivalis">Calosota aestivalis</taxonomicName>
based on leg color.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="34" pageNumber="35" type="recognition">
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">Recognition.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="34" pageNumber="35">
Females of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
are most similar to those of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota elongata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongata">Calosota elongata</taxonomicName>
, as discussed under the latter species. A few females of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
do not have the penultimate tergum extending to the level of the cerci so that there is a visible precercal portion of the syntergum similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota elongata" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elongata">Calosota elongata</taxonomicName>
, but this likely is an artifact of preservation in these very few females. The single female from Arizona (Map 3) is unusually dark, lacking distinct metallic lusters except for on the interantennal region and scape, and having the legs except the tarsi mostly dark, but in other features is similar to typical 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
from California. If males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
from Arizona also have mostly dark legs, unlike those from California, they will closely resemble males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota aestivalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aestivalis">Calosota aestivalis</taxonomicName>
. However, males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota aestivalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aestivalis">Calosota aestivalis</taxonomicName>
have the ventrolateral arm of the coppery region below the anterior ocellus quite obviously contiguous with the inner orbit (Fig. 2), whereas typical males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
from California have the arm separated from the inner orbit (cf. Fig. 5) and it is possible that dark males from Arizona may even lack the coppery region. Males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota aestivalis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aestivalis">Calosota aestivalis</taxonomicName>
also commonly have fu1 quite distinctly elongate, whereas fu1 is quadrate to slightly transverse in males of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Eupelmidae" genus="Calosota" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Calosota longiventris" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="34" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longiventris">Calosota longiventris</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>