<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.617.9970" ID-GBIF-Dataset="009e9922-b41f-4d4c-beac-e07a023454b4" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127864983" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-617-65" ID-ZBK="A22B0E2CF24E4C80B0E505794FC95DA3" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-617-65" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 617" ModsDocTitle="Taxonomic revision of the New World genus Callotillus Wolcott (Cleridae, Tillinae), with the description of the new genus Neocallotillus, and an illustrated key of identification to species" checkinTime="1474013904775" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burke, Alan F. &amp; Zolnerowich, Gregory" docDate="2016" docId="88711D32BB7226FF28742A944FF27B87" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 617: 65-89" docOrigin="ZooKeys 617" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.617.9970" docTitle="Callotillus eburneocinctus Wolcott 1911" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="86" masterDocId="FFE5FF88FF9EFFE7331FFFB4FFA0FF8D" masterDocTitle="Taxonomic revision of the New World genus Callotillus Wolcott (Cleridae, Tillinae), with the description of the new genus Neocallotillus, and an illustrated key of identification to species" masterLastPageNumber="89" masterPageNumber="65" pageId="19" pageNumber="84" updateTime="1643489490495" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Taxonomic revision of the New World genus Callotillus Wolcott (Cleridae, Tillinae), with the description of the new genus Neocallotillus, and an illustrated key of identification to species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burke, Alan F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zolnerowich, Gregory</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>617</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>65</mods:start>
<mods:end>89</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.617.9970</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.617.9970</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-617-65</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">A22B0E2CF24E4C80B0E505794FC95DA3</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">A22B0E2CF24E4C80B0E505794FC95DA3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127864983" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:88711D32BB7226FF28742A944FF27B87" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/88711D32BB7226FF28742A944FF27B87" lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="86" pageId="19" pageNumber="84">
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="84" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="84">Taxon classification Animalia Coleoptera Cleridae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="84" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="84">
<taxonomicName authority="Wolcott, 1911" authorityName="Wolcott" authorityYear="1911" class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Callotillus" higherTaxonomySource="treatment-meta" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Callotillus eburneocinctus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="19" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="eburneocinctus">Callotillus eburneocinctus Wolcott, 1911</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="84" type="holotype depository">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="84">Holotype depository.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="84">United States National Museum of Natural History(USNM). Holotype locality: Key West, Monroe Co., Florida.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="19" pageNumber="84" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="84">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="19" pageNumber="84">USA: FL (Fig. 8E).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="20" pageNumber="85" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">
<pageBreakToken pageId="20" pageNumber="85" start="start">Differential</pageBreakToken>
diagnosis.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Callotillus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Callotillus eburneocinctus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="20" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="eburneocinctus">Callotillus eburneocinctus</taxonomicName>
is most similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Callotillus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Callotillus bahamensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="20" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bahamensis">Callotillus bahamensis</taxonomicName>
. Characters to distinguish these species appear in the diagnosis section of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Callotillus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Callotillus bahamensis" order="Coleoptera" pageId="20" pageNumber="85" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="bahamensis">Callotillus bahamensis</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="86" pageId="20" pageNumber="85" type="redescription">
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">Redescription.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">Form: Body moderately elongate, robust; head and pronotum somewhat slender; elytra gradually expanded toward apex, then abruptly narrowing behind distal fourth. Color: head, antennae, mouthparts, pronotum, and anterior half of elytral disc testaceous to rufous; legs brunneous; distal end of mandibles, abdomen and posterior half of elytral disc fuscous; thorax bicolored, metaventrite anteriorly and internally ferrugineous, posteriorly and distally fuscous; each elytron with a transverse, median, pale fascia that runs from the epipleural fold to the elytral suture, this band may be protruded in most individuals (Fig. 1H).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">
Head: Including eyes not wider than pronotum; eyes small, taller than wide, not bulging laterally, finely faceted, strongly, sub-triangularly emarginate; surface integument corrugate; antennal notch located in front of antennal emargination; frons not bi-impressed. Antennae of males consisting of 10 antennomeres; second antennomere short, robust; third antennomere about 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
the length of previous antennomere, moderately serrate; fourth antennomeres slightly longer than third antennomere; antennomeres 4-9 about the same length, strongly serrate; last antennomere elongate, about 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
the length of ninth antennomere, slightly ovoid in shape, laterally compressed (Fig. 3H). Anterior portion of clypeus narrow, approximately 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
the length of eye emargination (Fig. 6B).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">Thorax: Pronotum globose, as broad as long; surface rugulose, profusely, finely punctate; punctations narrow, shallow; sides subparallel in dorsal view, then abruptly constricted on posterior fourth; disc strongly convex; anterior transverse depression and subbasal tumescence absent. Prosternum wider than long; surface smooth, rugulose, glabrous. Mesoventrite smooth, shiny, glabrous; surface very finely punctate. Metaventrite strongly convex; surface smooth, feebly, finely punctate; longitudinal depression present; metaventral process absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">Elytra: Robust; humeri indicated, gradually expanding toward elytral apex; surface convex on first third, then moderately depressed on second third, and conspicuously convex again on last third; a pair of long, stiff, erect tuft of dark setae located on the anterior fourth each elytron; surface of elytral disc rugulose; sculpturing absent; elytral apices rounded, moderately dehiscent; epipleural fold complete, narrowing toward apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="20" pageNumber="85">Legs: Femora moderately swollen; surface shiny, smooth. Tibiae longitudinally rugulose; two tarsal denticles, outer denticle digitiform in shape, interior denticle triangular.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="21" lastPageNumber="86" pageId="20" pageNumber="85">
Abdomen: Ventrites 1-3 broadly convex, smooth, shiny, subquadrate, feebly punctate, not depressed laterally. Fourth ventrite moderately punctate, medially depressed. Fifth ventrite shiny, strongly excavated; lateral margins subparallel; posterior margin broadly, shallowly emarginate. Sixth ventrite triangular in shape; small; moderately excavated; feebly punctate; conspicuously broader than long; lateral margins strongly oblique, moderately arcuate; posterior margin shallowly, narrowly emarginate; posterolateral angles rounded (Fig. 5I). Fifth tergite subquadrate; moderately, coarsely punctate; posterior margin truncate. Sixth tergite subtriangular in shape; feebly convex; wider than long; surface moderately punctate; lateral margins strongly oblique, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="21" pageNumber="86" start="start">moderately</pageBreakToken>
arcuate; posterior margin very shallowly, narrowly emarginate; posterolateral angles broadly rounded. Sixth tergite extending beyond apical margin of sixth ventrite, fully covering sixth ventrite in dorsal view.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="86">Aedeagus: Phallobasic apodeme present; phallus with copulatory piece feebly swollen at apex, petiolate; phallobase subparallel; phallic plate armed with one irregular row of denticles; intraspicular plate present, elongate; phallobasic lobes free; tegmen complete, fully covering phallus; phallobasic lobes rounded distally; phallobasic apodeme moderately short, expanded distally; endophallic struts short, robust distally (Fig. 7D).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="86">
Female variation: The structure of the antennae will help to differentiate females of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cleridae" genus="Callotillus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Callotillus eburneocinctus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="21" pageNumber="86" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="eburneocinctus">Callotillus eburneocinctus</taxonomicName>
from males. Females have the third antennomere feebly serrate and the antennomeres 4-9 are moderately serrate (Fig. 3J), males have the third antennomere moderately serrate and antennomeres 4-9 are strongly serrate (Fig. 3H). Females also have the sixth ventrite subquadrate in shape and the posterior margin is broadly truncate (Fig. 5J), males have this segment subtriangular in shape with the posterior margin narrow and feebly emarginate (Fig. 5I).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="21" pageNumber="86" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="86">Material examined (N=35).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="21" pageNumber="86">
2 males, 3 females: Monroe Co., FL, Big Pine Key, 17-IV-1978, E. Giesbert; 1 male, 1 female: Monroe Co., FL, Everglades Nat. Park, Flamingo, 16-V-1991, R. Morris; 1 male, 2 females: FL, Miami, 13-VI-1963, B. K. Dozier; 1 female: FL, Tavernier, on Key Largo, 19-VI-1970, beating 
<taxonomicName genus="Laguncularis" lsidName="Laguncularis racemosa" pageId="21" pageNumber="86" rank="species" species="racemosa">Laguncularis racemosa</taxonomicName>
(L.), G. H. Nelson; 2 males, 3 females: FL, Miami, Virginia Key, 23-VI-1970, beating 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Combretaceae" genus="Conocarpus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Conocarpus erecta" order="Myrtales" pageId="21" pageNumber="86" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="erecta">Conocarpus erecta</taxonomicName>
L., G. H. Nelson. 1 male: Miami-Dade Co., FL, Miami, 25-VI-1965, B.K. Dozier; 4 specimens: FL, No Name Key, 29-V-1997, R. Turnbow, ex. 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Anacardiaceae" genus="Metopium" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Metopium toxiferum" order="Sapindales" pageId="21" pageNumber="86" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="toxiferum">Metopium toxiferum</taxonomicName>
L., emerged 31-III-1979, R. Turnbow; 1 specimen: FL, Sugarloaf Key, 2-V-2000, 30-V-1997, R. Turnbow; 4 males, 9 females: Monroe Co., FL, Big Pine Key, reared from wood, E. Giesbert.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>