<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="efa9651f-1288-4447-a21e-62ed135be72a" ModsDocID="21388" checkinTime="1252707017166" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Cambridge, O. P." docDate="1879" docId="CC115329FE08D02F3331A0A9F95D7993" docLanguage="en" docName="21388.xml" docOrigin="Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London 1879" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15394" docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageNumber="121" masterDocId="2E11AEF7882F1062802034BAD2E93267" masterDocTitle="On a new genus and species of spiders of the family Salticides." masterLastPageNumber="121" masterPageNumber="119" pageNumber="120" updateTime="1643599508189" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>On a new genus and species of spiders of the family Salticides.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cambridge, O. P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1879</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1879</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>119</mods:start>
<mods:end>121</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15394</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">21388</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:CC115329FE08D02F3331A0A9F95D7993" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CC115329FE08D02F3331A0A9F95D7993" lastPageNumber="121" pageNumber="120">
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="120">Length of the adult female 1 3 / 4 line.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="120">Cephalothorax deep blackish brown, the ocular area being black; it has a narrow submarginal line of white hairs; and its whole upper surface is thinly clothed with similar hairs.</paragraph>
<caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="120">Fig. 1. Spider enlarged, a. Natural length of Spider. 2. Ditto, in profile, without legs or palpi. 3. Leaf of plant with nest on midrib (natural size).</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="120">Falces small, set rather back beneath the fore margin of the cephalothorax, nearly vertical, and of a dark-brown hue.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="120">Maxilla and labium dull brownish, tipped with a paler colour.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="121">Sternum oval, pointed behind, and similar in colour to the cephalothorax.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="121">Legs pale dull yellowish, the femora being dark brown, and the tibiae, metatarsi, and tarsi marked with brown, giving them a somewhat annulated appearance; beneath the terminal claws is a small claw-tuft.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="121">The palpi are short, and of a more uniform pale-yellowish colour, clothed with, among others, some pale scale-like hairs above; while the digital joints have numerous longer, blackish ones beneath.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="121">Abdomen short-oval, and of dark maroon-brown colour, thinly clothed with short, pale grey, or whitish, rather shining, somewhat squamose hairs; an indistinct pale stripe runs obliquely from just beneath each side of the fore extremity to, or towards, the spinners; the central longitudinal line is broadly blackish, but not very distinctly defined; and there are, on its hinder part, some very indistinct paler, sharply angular lines in a longitudinal scries; on the underside is a broad, longitudinal, central blackish band, somewhat narrowing to the spinners.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageNumber="121">Hab. Blumenau, Sta. Catherina, Brazil. On the leaves of various herbaceous plants, in little three-entranced, white, silken nests.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>