<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.723.20578" ID-GBIF-Dataset="2a8a3dd1-2fc9-4ba1-8afb-7d9710805f9c" ID-GBIF-Taxon="139337049" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-723-43" ID-ZBK="A0ACADAC574B495882E3D9612547B8CC" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DDD47504-FDE1-4FD1-BA0C-12C4DDA3DAF3" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-723-43" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 723" ModsDocTitle="New species of Indocloeon Müller-Liebenau from South-East Asia (Ephemeroptera, Baetidae)" checkinTime="1513622332636" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Kaltenbach, Thomas &amp; Gattolliat, Jean-Luc" docDate="2017" docId="722D344C596EA7244D95CBF4EC779250" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 723: 43-60" docOrigin="ZooKeys 723" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.723.20578" docTitle="Indocloeon timorense Kaltenbach &amp; Gattolliat, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="DDD47504-FDE1-4FD1-BA0C-12C4DDA3DAF3" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" masterDocId="21147C55576AFF9EB1398C728138A803" masterDocTitle="New species of Indocloeon Mueller-Liebenau from South-East Asia (Ephemeroptera, Baetidae)" masterLastPageNumber="60" masterPageNumber="43" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" updateTime="1643593945100" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species of Indocloeon Mueller-Liebenau from South-East Asia (Ephemeroptera, Baetidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kaltenbach, Thomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gattolliat, Jean-Luc</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>723</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>60</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.723.20578</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.723.20578</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-723-43</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">A0ACADAC574B495882E3D9612547B8CC</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">A0ACADAC574B495882E3D9612547B8CC</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="139337049" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DDD47504-FDE1-4FD1-BA0C-12C4DDA3DAF3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/722D344C596EA7244D95CBF4EC779250" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="48" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="48">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/DDD47504-FDE1-4FD1-BA0C-12C4DDA3DAF3" class="Insecta" family="FAMILIA" genus="Indocloeon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Indocloeon timorense" order="ORDO" pageId="5" pageNumber="48" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="timorense">Indocloeon timorense</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="5" pageNumber="48">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1b, c, 4, 5
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="50" pageId="6" pageNumber="49" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="49">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="49" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="50" pageId="6" pageNumber="49">
Larva. Following combination of characters: A) labrum with submarginal arc of setae composed of one central medium, simple seta plus six medium, simple setae (Fig. 4a); B) distomedial protuberance at segment II of labial palp moderately 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="50" start="start">developed</pageBreakToken>
, apically rounded (Fig. 4h); C) claw with two rows of denticles, each with five larger denticles apically and many small denticles basally (Fig. 5b); D) gills with serrate margin and pointed scales along margin (Fig. 5f).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="50">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Baetidae" genus="Indocloeon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Indocloeon timorense" order="Ephemeroptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="50" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="timorense">Indocloeon timorense</taxonomicName>
sp. n., larva morphology: a Labrum b Right mandible c Right prostheca d Hypopharynx e Left mandible f Left prostheca g Maxilla h Labium.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="7" pageNumber="50">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Baetidae" genus="Indocloeon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Indocloeon timorense" order="Ephemeroptera" pageId="7" pageNumber="50" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="timorense">Indocloeon timorense</taxonomicName>
sp. n., larva morphology: a Middle leg b Middle tarsal claw c Middle leg, bipectinate seta d Tergum IV e Paraproct f Gill VII.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="7" pageNumber="50" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Larva (Figs 1b, c, 4, 5). Body length 4.6 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Colouration. Head, thorax and abdomen dorsally brown. Head and thorax with bright dorsal line, forewing pads with bright striation (Fig. 1b). Thorax and abdomen ventrally brown, legs brown (Fig. 1c). Caudal filaments colourless, but light brown at base.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Antenna with scape and pedicel subcylindrical; flagellum with broad spines on apex of each segment and with scales. In the middle part of the flagellum without large spines on apex of segments at outer lateral margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">
Labrum (Fig. 4a). Rectangular, length 0.7
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximum width. Distal margin with medial emargination and small process. Dorsally with medium, fine, simple setae scattered over surface; submarginal dorsal arc of setae composed of 1 + 6 long, apically pointed simple setae. Ventrally with submarginal row of setae composed of lateral long and medial shorter, feathery setae and anterolateral simple setae; ventral surface with short, spine-like setae near lateral and anterolateral margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Right mandible (Fig. 4b, c). Incisors fused. Outer and inner sets of denticles with 4 + 3 denticles respectively. Inner margin of innermost denticle with a row of thin setae. Prostheca robust, apicolaterally denticulate. Margin between prostheca and mola straight, tuft of setae present. Tuft of spine-like setae at base of mola absent. Tuft of setae at apex of mola present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Left mandible (Fig. 4e, f). Incisors fused. Outer and inner sets of denticles with 4 + 3 denticles respectively. Prostheca robust, apically denticulate, with comb-shape structure. Margin between prostheca and mola straight, with minute denticles towards subtriangular process. Tuft of setae between prostheca and mola small and directed proximally. Tuft of spine-like setae at base of mola absent. Subtriangular process wide, slightly above level of area between prostheca and mola. Denticles of mola apically constricted. Tuft of setae at apex of mola absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Both mandibles with lateral margins almost straight. Basal half with fine, simple setae scattered over dorsal surface.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Hypopharynx (Fig. 4d). Lingua shorter than superlingua. Lingua longer than broad. Medial tuft of setae present; distal half laterally expanded. Superlingua apical margin slightly concave; lateral margin rounded; simple setae scattered over lateral and distal margin, finer and longer at distal margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="50">Maxilla (Fig. 4g). With two simple, robust apical setae under crown. Inner dorsal row of setae with three denti-setae, distal denti-seta teeth-like, middle and proximal denti-setae slender and pectinate. Medially with one spine-like seta and five long, simple setae. Maxillary palp longer than length of galea-lacinia; three segmented; setae on maxillary palp fine, simple, scattered over surface of segments II and III. Palp segment II about as long as segment I. Palp segment III about as long as segment II. Apex segment III slightly pointed.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="52" pageId="8" pageNumber="51">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="51" start="start">Labium</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 4h). Glossa basally broad, narrowing toward apex. Slightly shorter than paraglossa. Inner margin with 13 long, simple setae. Apex with three long, robust, pectinate setae. Outer margin with nine long, simple setae. Ventral surface 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="52" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
long, fine, simple, scattered setae. Paraglossa sub-rectangular, apex obliquely truncate and slightly rounded. Apex with three rows of robust, pectinate setae. Outer margin with row of four long, spine-like setae. Dorsally with row of four long, simple setae. Ventrally with five long, simple setae near inner margin. Labial palp with segment I 0.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of segments II and III combined. Segment I covered with micropores and some short, fine, simple setae as well as with very short, robust, simple setae along inner margin. Segment II with apically rounded distomedial protuberance; distomedial protuberance 0.3
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of base of segment III; inner margin with short, fine, simple setae; outer margin with short, fine, simple setae; dorsally with row of eight long, simple setae. Segment III subquadrangular, asymmetrical; length subequal to width; covered with medium, simple setae and short, fine, simple setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Hind wing pads absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Middle leg (Fig. 5a, b, c). Ratio of middle leg 1.6:1.0:0.7:0.2. Middle femur. Length approximately 6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximum width. Dorsally with 20-25 bipectinate, acute setae on margin and close to margin (pectination in lateral view difficult to see); length of setae 0.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
maximum width of femur. Apex rounded; with two long, curved, spine-like setae. Ventrally with around 20 bipectinate, stout setae, predominantly arranged in one row. Tibia. Dorsally with row of ten bipectinate, stout setae on margin, two of them near apex (pectination in lateral view difficult to see). Ventrally with many bipectinate, stout setae on margin and close to margin (pectination in lateral view difficult to see). Anterior surface with many bipectinate, stout setae. Tibio-patellar suture present on basal half. Tarsus. Dorsally bare. Ventrally with many bipectinate, stout setae on margin and close to margin (pectination in lateral view difficult to see). Tarsal claw with two rows of numerous minute denticles and five large, apical denticles; subapical setae absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Terga (Fig. 5d). Surface with abundant scales or scale-bases and micropores. Posterior margin with row of irregular triangular or pentagonal spines.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Gills (Fig. 5f). On segments I - VII. Margin serrate with small spines and with pointed scales along margin. Tracheae extending from main trunk to inner and outer margins. Gill I little longer than segment II; oblong. Gill IV as long as length of segments V and VI combined; oval. Gill VII as long as length of segments VIII and IX; oblong.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Paraproct (Fig. 5e). With 18 marginal stout spines, laterally smaller. Surface with scale bases, micropores, and a few short, fine, simple setae. Postero-lateral extension (cercotractor) with small marginal spines.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">After the type locality, the island of Timor (Indonesia).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Indonesia: Timor.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="biological aspects">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Biological aspects.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">The specimen was collected at an altitude of 1580 m a.s.l.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="52" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">Type-material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="52">
Holotype. Larva (on slide, GBIFCH 00280822), Indonesia, Timor, Mt. Mutis, 1580 m, 01.10.2011, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="-9.635333">9°38.12'S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="124.21333">124°12.80'E</geoCoordinate>
, leg. M. Balke. Temporary deposited in the Museum of Zoology Lausanne (MZL) before definitely housed in the Museum Zoologicum Bogoriense (MZB) in Indonesia.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>