<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.382.6740" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d40c1ac9-ab79-424c-b188-39f71c5a3080" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051104" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-382-1" ID-ZBK="CD66F0CCE2DC42BAA822EE97EB36438F" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:96870F47-6129-474B-AB13-677EDD9D12C4" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1313-2970-382-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 382" ModsDocTitle="A remarkably modified species of the tribe Platynini (Coleoptera, Carabidae) from a limestone cave in Jiangxi Province, eastern China" checkinTime="1451246298810" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Pang, Jianmei &amp; Tian, Mingyi" docDate="2014" docId="F8FB92D367E6C513DDB39B410A3365FB" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 382: 1-12" docOrigin="ZooKeys 382" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.382.6740" docTitle="Morimotoidius zhushandong Pang &amp; Tian, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="96870F47-6129-474B-AB13-677EDD9D12C4" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="7" masterDocId="FFC2FFCCC10C8F30C325A13A7C487A4C" masterDocTitle="A remarkably modified species of the tribe Platynini (Coleoptera, Carabidae) from a limestone cave in Jiangxi Province, eastern China" masterLastPageNumber="12" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" updateTime="1643668779336" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A remarkably modified species of the tribe Platynini (Coleoptera, Carabidae) from a limestone cave in Jiangxi Province, eastern China</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Pang, Jianmei</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tian, Mingyi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>382</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>12</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.382.6740</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.382.6740</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-382-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">CD66F0CCE2DC42BAA822EE97EB36438F</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">CD66F0CCE2DC42BAA822EE97EB36438F</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152051104" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:96870F47-6129-474B-AB13-677EDD9D12C4" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F8FB92D367E6C513DDB39B410A3365FB" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/96870F47-6129-474B-AB13-677EDD9D12C4" authority="Pang &amp; Tian" class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong Pang &amp; Tian</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="1" pageNumber="2">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1-19
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="6" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Length: 11.5-12.5 mm; width: 3.6-3.7 mm. Habitus as in Figure 1. Body extremely slender and elongate, with very long antennae, legs and mouthpart palps.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n., habitus of male, paratype.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Black, but ventral surface, femora (except basal and apical tips), clypeus, labrum and apical half of mandibles dark brown, legs including basal and apical tips of femora, antennae, palps, and basal half of mandibles yellow to yellow brown; elytra with indistinct purplish metallic sheen.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Macrosculpture: Strongly shining, surface glabrous, polish and smooth, but base of pronotum, mesosternum, meso- and metepisterna coarsely and sparsely punctate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Microsculpture: Engraved meshes moderately transverse on labrum, clypeus and base of frons, and base of pronotum; strongly transverse on head; striate on disc of pronotum and elytra, but clearly isodiametric on scutellum.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Head very long and narrow, strongly elongated, much longer than wide, HL/HW = 2.04-2.15 (mean 2.11); widest at level of eyes, and gradually narrowed backwards to neck constriction which is short but distinct, tempora almost straight but slightly curved just before neck constriction; eyes rather flat, more or less depressed; ventral margins of eye well separated from buccal fissure; supraorbital areas with two pairs of setiferous pores, anterior closer to margin of eye than posterior; posterior pore at about middle of head from clypeal suture to neck; interspaces between anterior pores distinctly wider than that between posterior ones; distance between anterior and posterior pores slightly longer than diameter of eye; distance between eye to buccal fissure distinctly shorter than that between posterior pore to eye, but slightly longer than that between anterior pore to eye; frontal impressions rather shallow and wide, ending before anterior supraorbital pores; frons and vertex moderately convex; clypeus moderately transverse, bisetose, labrum subquadrate, almost straight at front, sexsetose; mandibles elongate, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="3" start="start">gently</pageBreakToken>
and gradually narrowed towards apex, apical teeth slightly hooked; right mandible with a small but distinct anterior retinacular tooth at about median portion which is far from other teeth; both right and left mandibles with short and blunt terebral and posterior retinacular teeth near base; ligula broad, bisetose at apex; labial suture well developed; mentum bisetose, apical margin biconcave, with a long and simple median 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="4" start="start">tooth</pageBreakToken>
which is widened at apex, epilobes evenly rounded; submentum bearing two pairs of setae, inner ones much long the outer; palps long and slender, subcylindrical, glabrous and asetose except for labial palpomere 2 which is bisetose on inner margin; labial palpomere 2 distinctly longer than 3; maxillary palpomere 3 slightly longer than 4. Antennae long and slender, filiform, extending at about apical 1/5 of elytra in female, but 1/6 in male; antennomeres 1-3 glabrous, antennomere 1 with a long subapical seta, 2 with a short subapical seta, 3 with several apical setae; finely pubescent from antennomere 4, each of 4 to 11 with several apical setae; antennomere 2 the shortest, half as long as 1, antennomeres 3-5 longer than other, each about twice as long as 1; gradually shortened from antennomeres 6 to 11, antennomere 11 almost as long as 1.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="5" start="start">Pronotum</pageBreakToken>
narrow and strongly elongate, barrel-like, distinctly shorter than head, almost as wide as head including eyes; much longer than wide, PL/PW = 1.59-1.62 (mean 1.60) in male, 1.40-1.43 (mean 1.41) in female; front slightly narrower than base, PWB/PWA = 1.11-1.14 (mean 1.13) in male, 1.09-1.12 (mean 1.10) in female; widest at about middle, gently narrowed towards both fore and hind angles; front and base finely bordered, lateral margins unbordered, but with evenly and distinctly explanate-reflexed areas throughout, marginal setae absent; basal foveae wide and long; fore angle nearly rectangular, hind angle broad though somewhat rectangular; both front and base almost straight; median line deep and long; disc slightly convex, basal area rather flat, with lateral areas of basal parts evidently depressed; propleura faintly tumid, faintly visible from above, at least at the widest part; prosternal process unbordered at apex; scutellum moderately sized.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="6" start="start">Elytra</pageBreakToken>
very slender, elongate-ovate, much wider than head and pronotum; well bordered at base, base small, shoulders indistinct; widest at a little behind middle, EL/EW = 1.62-1.78 (mean 1.74), more contracted towards apices than towards base; disc moderately convex though rather flat in basal 1/4; striae very deep, continuous and smooth, weakly punctured; intervals strongly convex, stria 3 with three dorsal setiferous pores, basal one close to stria 3, both middle and subapical ones close to stria 2; other intervals without pore; subapical sinuation rather straight, apex broad; preapical and two apical pores present; marginal series of umbilicate pores not aggregated, which are composed of about nineteen pores, denser in subhumeral and subapical areas, sparser in middle portion; three pores (one at subhumerus, other two at subapical area) bearing much longer setae than others, which is distinctly longer than metatarsomere 4; scutellar pores present; scutellar striae deep and rather long. Hind wings reduced.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Legs very long and slender; fore leg short and stout (Figs 2-5); procoxa asetose, meso- and metacoxae bisetose, inner seta of metacoxa absent; trochanters unisetose; femora very slender, profemora unisetose ventrally, meso- and metafemora with three and two ventral setae respectively; tibiae and tarsomeres 1-3 longitudinal bisulcute dorsally; protarsomeres 1-3 slightly dilated in male, with two rows of short and sparse spongy setae ventrally (Fig. 3), while much narrower and without spongy setae in female (Fig. 5); protarsomeres 4 shortly but distinctly emarginate at apex, with lobes nearly symmetric, each with a row of three setae ventrally; meso- and metatarsomeres 4 without subapical setae (Figs 6-10); tarsomeres 5 glabrous ventrally; claws smooth.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Figures 2-10. Tarsi of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 2 protarsi, dorsal view, male 3 protarsi, ventral view, male 4 protarsi, dorsal view, female 5 protarsi, ventral view, female 6 mesotarsomeres 3-5, dorsal view, male 7 mesotarsomeres 3-5, ventral view, male 8 mesotarsomeres 3-5, lateral view, male 9 metatasomeres 3-5, dorsal view, male 10 metatasomeres 3-5, ventral view, male.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Each of abdominal ventrite 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–VI">IV-VI</normalizedToken>
with pair of paramedian setae in both sexes; ventrite VII with two pairs of marginal setae in female, but only one pair in male.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Male genitalia (Figs 11-13): The median lobe of aedeagus rather stout, basal bulb large, strongly arcuate in middle portion in lateral view, gently and gradually narrowed towards apex, blunt at tip; dorsal opening wide, nearly as half as whole length, reaching 1/3 from base; apical lamella rather long, nearly twice as long as wide, not parallel-sided, rounded at apex; internal sac with a long copulatory piece covered with scales, and a strongly sclerotized spine dorsally; left paramere styloid, not elongated, smaller and shorter than the right.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Figures 11-13. Male genitalia of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n., 11 median lobe, lateral view 12 apex of median lobe, dorsal view 13 parameres.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Female reproductive tract (Fig. 14): Ventrite X sparsely setose; gonosubcoxite bearing about a dozen fringe setae along apical area, gonocoxite strongly curved, sharp at apex, bearing three lateral and one dorsal ensiform setae; bursa copulatrix wide, with middle part evidently folded, basally narrower; spermathecal gland very large, elongate ovate; spermathecal gland duct thin and long, connected below base of spermathecal reservoir, which is shorter than spermathecal duct.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Figure 14. Female reproductive tract of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n., bc bursa copulatrix; co common oviduct; gcx gonocoxite; gscx gonosubcoxite; sd spermathecal duct; sg spermathecal gland; sgd spermathecal gland duct; sp spermatheca.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="sexual dimorphisms">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Sexual dimorphisms.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Apart from protarsomeres 1-3 and ventrite VII, sexual differences are also shown on antennae and pronotum: a little longer or more elongate in male than in female.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="variability">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Variability.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">In general, maxillary palpomere 3 distinctly longer than 4, but reverse in a male specimen which left maxilla with palpomere 3 shorter than 4.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Within platynines, the chaetotaxy on pronotum and meso- and metatarsi are important characters (
<bibRefCitation author="Habu, A" journalOrPublisher="Keigaku-Sha, Ltd., Tokyo" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" title="Carabidae Platynini (Insecta: Coleoptera)." volumeTitle="Japanese Faunica" year="1978">Habu 1978</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Liebherr, JK" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="1 - 163" title="Phylogeny and revision of the Anchomenus clade: the genera Tetraleucus, Anchomenus, Sericoda, and Elliptoleus (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Platynini)." volume="202" year="1991">Liebherr 1991</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Schmidt, J" journalOrPublisher="Entomologische Blaetter" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="211 - 218" title="Archicolpodes n. gen. - eine neue Laufkaefergattung der Tribus Platynini aus China (Coleoptera: Carabidae)." volume="96" year="2001">Schmidt 2001</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Liebherr, JK" journalOrPublisher="Mitteilungen des Museums fuer Naturkunde Berlin, Deutsche entomologische Zeitschrift" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="151 - 206" title="Phylogeny and biogeography of the Laurasian genus Agonum Bonelli (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Platynini)." volume="51" year="2004">Liebherr and Schmidt 2004</bibRefCitation>
). We treat this peculiar species a member of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Morimotoidius</taxonomicName>
Habu, 1954 due to the fact that it shares the following combined generic characters with other species of this genus: pronotal setae absent, submentum quadrisetose, meso- and metatarsomeres 4 without subapical setae, meso- and metafemora bearing two or three setae, and tarsomeres 5 glabrous ventrally. Certainly, other remarkably modified characters such as the very elongate and rhadinoid body shape, the slender and markedly porrected mandibles, the very thin palps, reduced eyes, the markedly prolonged temples and the very small elytral base must be autapomorphies to adapt the subterranean habitat. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is the first member of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius" order="Coleoptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="6" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Morimotoidius</taxonomicName>
found in mainland China. Other species of the genus are living either in Japan (two species) or in Taiwan Province of China (one species) (
<bibRefCitation author="Habu, A" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of the National Institute of Agricultural Sciences (Series C (Plant Pathology and Entomology ))" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="263 - 279" title="On Trephionus otuboi Habu (Coleoptera: Carabidae)." volume="4" year="1954">Habu 1954</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="Habu, A" journalOrPublisher="Keigaku-Sha, Ltd., Tokyo" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" title="Carabidae Platynini (Insecta: Coleoptera)." volumeTitle="Japanese Faunica" year="1978">1978</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Terada, K" journalOrPublisher="Miscellaneous Reports of the Hiwa Museum for Natural History" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="163 - 216" title="A checklist of the Carabidae (Coleoptera) of Taiwan." volume="45" year="2005">Terada et al. 2005</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
This new species is named after its type locality. In Chinese, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Zhushan”">&quot;Zhushan&quot;</normalizedToken>
means a mountain or hill which is covered with bamboo forest, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Dong”">&quot;Dong&quot;</normalizedToken>
means cave.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="6" type="materials examined">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">Materials examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="6">
Holotype: male, Zhushan Dong II, Dongkou Cun, Mabu Xiang, Wanzhai Xian, western Jiangxi, China, 28°02'880&quot;N, 114°22'216&quot;E, 142 m, 2-X-2012, Mingyi Tian &amp; Jingli Cheng leg. in the insect collections of South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, China (SCAU); paratypes: 6 males and 9 females, ibid. in SCAU, except one male and one female in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Muséum">Museum</normalizedToken>
National 
<normalizedToken originalValue="d’Histoire">d'Histoire</normalizedToken>
Naturelle, Paris, France, and one male and one female in Coll. J. Schmidt (Admannshagen, Germany), respectively.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="7" start="start">Distribution</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">China (Jiangxi) (Fig. 15).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
Figure 15. Distribution map of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="habits">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Habits.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
There is unknown about the biology and ecology of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n. The beetles move quickly on walls and ceilings, feeding on other small arthropods, probably including eggs of the crickets which are common in the cave. The extremely modified troglomorphic characters mentioned above reveal that this beetle has ability to adapt underground environment and probably a troglobite though it has reduced eyes and pigmented body.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="about the locality cave of m. zhushandong sp. n">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
About the locality cave of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Zhushan Dong is a touristic cave in western Jiangxi Province, located at Dongkou Cun, Mabu Xiang, Wanzai Xian, not far from the border between Wanzhai Xian and Yichun Shi (=City) (Fig. 15). Actually, there are two limestone caves in the Zhushan Dong scenic areas. Zhushan Dong I is a well-developed touristic cave, as long as 3985 m, with an underground river throughout the main passage. Zhushan Dong II is about 50 meters far from Zhushan Dong I. It is a small cave, about 30 m in length, with a small streamlet moving out at about 5 m inside of the entrance (Fig. 16, indicated by arrowhead). It is still closed for visitors. The beetles were collected by hands on walls and ceilings of the cave (Figs 17-19).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
Figures 16-19. Zhushan Dong II. 16 entrance 17-18 cave walls where the type specimens were collected 19 an adult of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Carabidae" genus="Morimotoidius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Morimotoidius zhushandong" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zhushandong">Morimotoidius zhushandong</taxonomicName>
sp. n. running on cave ceiling.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>