<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c990e4df-7ee4-4898-96ff-c96f45456873" ModsDocID="5831" checkinTime="1243376545748" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1946" docId="DAD65781AE78688B824C073105683933" docLanguage="en" docName="5831" docOrigin="Annals and Magazine of Natural History 12" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5831/5831.pdf" docTitle="Strumigenys (Cephaloxys) raymondi Donisthorpe, 1946, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="780" masterDocId="8D8AC18485F43A7290ED28CAFA476F2F" masterDocTitle="New species of ants (Hym., Formicidae) from the island of Mauritius." masterLastPageNumber="782" masterPageNumber="776" pageNumber="779" updateTime="1569525771911" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species of ants (Hym., Formicidae) from the island of Mauritius.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1946</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>12</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>776</mods:start>
<mods:end>782</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5831/5831.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">5831</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:DAD65781AE78688B824C073105683933" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DAD65781AE78688B824C073105683933">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="779">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:144222" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys (Cephaloxys) raymondi Donisthorpe" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys (Cephaloxys) raymondi Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="779" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="raymondi" subGenus="Cephaloxys">Strumigenys (Cephaloxys) raymondi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="780" pageNumber="779">[[ worker ]]. Brownish red, body clothed with scattered, not very abundant outstanding, clavate hairs, and fine subappressed hairs situated chiefly on head. Head narrow, triangular, considerably narrower at apex than at base, broadest just before posterior angles, posterior angles rounded, posterior border sharply excised in middle, vertex somewhat convex, sculpture closely and finely granulate; mandibles narrow, not very long, slightly convex above and bent downwards at apex, base hidden beneath clypeus, masticatory border curved to a sharp, fine point at apex, rest of border without teeth, underside somewhat hollowed out; clypeus broad diamond-shaped, slightly raised, but rather flat, anterior border slightly projecting; frontal area indicated by a small, somewhat deep pit; frontal furrow very faint and short; frontal carinae slightly raised, sinuate behind, and continued along upper rims of scrobes, which are slightly serrate; scrobes situated above eye, and extending nearly to posterior angles; antennae 6 - jointed, scape curved and extending to end of base of scrobe, funiculus with first joint not quite as long as fourth, second and third very short, last joint long and pointed, nearly as long as the rest of the funiculus; eyes very small, situated beneath scrobes considerably behind centre of sides of head. Thorax rather shining, sculpture finer than that of head, longer than broad, broadest behind posterior angles, dorsal surface round, convex, considerably contracted at meso-epinotal suture; pronotum narrow, transverse, forming a neck in front, humeral angles slightly projecting, mesonotum furnished with two small teeth or projections at base before meso-epinotal furrow, which is transverse, smooth, and deep; epinotum armed with two small sharp, slightly divergent, projecting teeth, or spines, dorsal surface convex, somewhat longer than declivity, declivity concave. Petiole with a long narrow peduncle and short, slightly transverse node at base, rounded above and at sides; post-petiole rather broad, transversely elliptical, broader than node of petiole, convex, rounded, smooth and shining above; spongiform appendages fairly well developed, situated between petiole and postpetiole, and post-petiole and gaster, most prominent beneath post-petiole; gaster oblong ovate, smooth and shining except for a number of short longitudinal striae at base; sting exserted. Legs fairly long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="780">Long. 2.5 - 2.7 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="780">[[ queen ]]. Colour, general structure, sculpture, and hairs, as in [[ worker ]].</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="780">Mandibles slightly longer; ocelli rather small, situated on a small prominence on vertex of head; eyes large. Thorax broader and more convex; anterior angles of pronotum prominent; suture between pro- and mesonotum deep; mesonotum convex; scutellum convex, rather prominent; spines of epinotum stouter.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="780">Long. 2.8 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="780">Described from a number of workers, and two dealated females from Mauritius. All collected by Mr. Raymond Mamet as follows: —</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="781" pageNumber="780">No. 8. On Le Pouce Mt., 15 [[ worker ]] [[ worker ]], nesting in old, rotten tree stump, 24. xii. J 942. No. 12. Ditto, 36 [[ worker ]] [[ worker ]], and larvae, 13. xi. 1943. No. 19. On Corps de Garde Mt., 10 [[ worker ]] [[ worker ]], and 1 dealated [[ queen ]]; caught on tree trunk. 17. i. 1944. No. 20. On Corps de Garde Mt., nesting in tree trunk, 55 [[ worker ]] [[ worker ]], larvae and pupae, 1 dealated [[ queen ]]. No. 28. &quot; Collected on Cocotte Mt. &quot; 18 [[ worker ]] [[ worker ]], 24. i. 1942. Type and [[ queen ]] type in B. M. Coll.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>