<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6237196" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9e4bbe9b-2885-4ff1-ae8e-c8442883bb50" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100123475" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6237196" ModsDocID="z01406p025" checkinTime="1247406085107" checkinUser="thomas" docAuthor="Heok Hee Ng &amp; Heok Hui Tan" docDate="2007" docId="B90837C4766002A4BB4C474206711912" docLanguage="en" docName="2007_Ng_Tan_gg2.xml" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1406" docSource="http://www.zoobank.org/urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:EC50E44D-9698-4C65-ADFB-6868AE486DFD" docTitle="Pseudecheneis maurus Ng &amp; Tan, 2007, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="11" lastPageNumber="31" masterDocId="3D9C851E2B7DC0FC87CC13067DE9067C" masterDocTitle="Pseudecheneis maurus, a new species of glyptosternine catfish (Teleostei: Sisoridae) from Central Vietnam." masterLastPageNumber="32" masterPageNumber="25" pageNumber="26" updateTime="1645594015906" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Pseudecheneis maurus, a new species of glyptosternine catfish (Teleostei: Sisoridae) from Central Vietnam.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Heok Hee Ng</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Heok Hui Tan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2007</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1406</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>25</mods:start>
<mods:end>32</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.zoobank.org/urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:EC50E44D-9698-4C65-ADFB-6868AE486DFD</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank-PUB">z01406p025</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6237196" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100123475" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6237196" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B90837C4766002A4BB4C474206711912" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B90837C4766002A4BB4C474206711912" lastPageNumber="31" pageNumber="26">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="26">
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">Pseudecheneis maurus</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="26">(Fig. 1)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="26">
Type material. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="923900650" collectingDate="2005-02-28" collectionCode="ZRC" collectorName="H. H. Tan, A. D. Tran" country="Vietnam" latitude="16.01089" location="Song Thuy Loan drainage, Ban Na hill station, Cat Lon stream, ca. 9 km along road before summit, 722 m asl" longitude="108.017395" specimenCode="ZRC 50638" stateProvince="Da Nang province" typeStatus="Holotype">
<typeStatus>Holotype</typeStatus>
: 
<specimenCode>
<collectionCode>ZRC</collectionCode>
50638
</specimenCode>
, 54.8 mm SL; 
<collectingCountry>Vietnam</collectingCountry>
: 
<collectingRegion>Da Nang province</collectingRegion>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B90837C4766002A4BB4C474206711912:F0F78287E11E75EF3944CA8C7957EAE7" country="Vietnam" latitude="16.01089" longitude="108.017395" name="Song Thuy Loan drainage, Ban Na hill station, Cat Lon stream, ca. 9 km along road before summit" stateProvince="Da Nang province">Song Thuy Loan drainage, Ban Na hill station, Cat Lon stream, ca. 9 km along road before summit</location>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" value="16.01089">16°0'39.2&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" value="108.017395">108°1'2.6&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:B90837C4766002A4BB4C474206711912:E8A7C5C22175FAC94D341943252F19A2" country="Vietnam" latitude="16.01089" longitude="108.017395" name="722 m asl" stateProvince="Da Nang province">722 m asl</location>
; 
<collectorName>H. H. Tan &amp; A. D. Tran</collectorName>
, 
<date day="28" month="02" value="2005-02-28" year="2005">
<collectingDate day="28" month="02" value="2005-02-28" year="2005">28 February 2005</collectingDate>
</date>
.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="26">
Diagnosis. 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">Pseudecheneis maurus</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from all congeners in having a shorter adipose-fin base (1.2 times length of anal-fin base vs. 1.5-2.0 times; 15.7% SL vs. 17.6-30.6), (except for 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="sympelvica">P. sympelvica</taxonomicName>
) thoracic adhesive apparatus with sulcae not meeting (vs. meeting) at midline and (except for 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="immaculata">P. immaculata</taxonomicName>
) in lacking (vs. having) distinct pale spots on the body. It further differs from 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="immaculata">P. immaculata</taxonomicName>
in having a shorter pectoral fin (24.3% SL vs. 32.0) and shorter and deeper caudal peduncle (length 21.2% SL vs. 28.8; depth 6.0% SL vs. 4.0). from. It differs from 
<taxonomicName LSID-ZBK="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:31513E00-E57B-4618-A71C-41681FF7E329" class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-ZBK="Pseudecheneis paviei Vaillant 1892:126 [2]" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="paviei">P. paviei</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="sympelvica">P. sympelvica</taxonomicName>
in having an elongate body with 38 vertebrae (vs. short body with 33-35 vertebrae) and from 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="26" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="sympelvica">P. sympelvica</taxonomicName>
in having separate (vs. fused) pelvic fins.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="26">Description. Biometric data as in Table 1. Head and abdominal region narrow and strongly depressed. Dorsal profile rising gently from tip of snout to origin of dorsal fin, then almost horizontal or sloping very gently ventrally to end of caudal peduncle. Ventral profile horizontal to anal-fin base, then sloping very gently dorsally to end of caudal peduncle. Caudal peduncle long and moderately compressed. Anus and urogenital openings located at posteriormost extent of pelvic fin. Skin smooth, tuberculate in some areas. Lateral line complete and midlateral. Vertebrae 19+19=38.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="26">Head acutely rounded when viewed from above. Gill openings moderate, extending from posttemporal region to base of first pectoral-fin element. Head covered with thick, tuberculate skin. Ventral surface of head with unculiferous collar on distal margin of branchiostegal membrane immediately anterior to thoracic adhesive apparatus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="26">Thoracic adhesive apparatus consisting of 13 transverse ridges (laminae) separated by grooves (sulcae); sulcae not meeting at midline of adhesive apparatus. Adhesive apparatus extending from immediately posterior to collar on distal margin of branchiostegal membrane to immediately posterior to level of last pectoralfin ray.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="26">Barbels flattened, and in four pairs. Maxillary barbel with ventral surface densely covered with papillae, and pointed tip; barbel extending about two-thirds of distance between its base and base of first pectoral-fin element. Distal half of barbel attached to snout via large, thin flap of skin. Nasal barbel with small flap of thin skin fringing posterior margin and extending midway to distance between posterior nares and anterior orbital margin. Inner mandibular-barbel densely covered with papillae; origin close to midline, extending to collar on distal margin of branchiostegal membrane. Outer mandibular barbel originating posterolateral of inner mandibular barbel, extending to level of anterior orbital margin. Eye small and almost rounded, subcutaneous and located on dorsal surface of head.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="26">Mouth inferior, with moderately broad, thin papillate lips. Rictal lobe large and papillate. Premaxillary tooth band not exposed when mouth is closed. Premaxillary teeth short and conical, arranged in irregular rows on a moderately large quadrangular patch. Dentary teeth long, thin and somewhat rounded at tip; arranged in irregular rows on two separated, roughly triangular patches.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="28">Dorsal-fin origin located at point through anterior third of body. First and second dorsal fin-ray elements not ossified, bearing i,6 rays, and fin margin straight. Adipose fin with very short base, 1.2 times anal-fin base length; located in middle third of postdorsal region. Adipose fin margin gently convex; posterior end deeply incised. Caudal fin forked, with i,7,8,i principal rays; procurrent rays symmetrical and extend only slightly anterior to fin base. Anal fin with short base extending less than half of adipose fin-base length and iii,7,i rays. Anal fin margin almost straight.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="28">Pelvic-fin origin at vertical through second or third dorsal fin-ray base. Pelvic fin greatly enlarged, extending to base of first anal-fin ray. Anterior fin margin strongly convex, first element broadened and with regular striae on ventral surface; with i,5 rays. Pectoral fin greatly enlarged and with convex anterior margin, reaching to just beyond pelvic-fin base. First element not ossified, broadened and with regular striae on ventral surface; fin with i,1 1,i rays.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="29" pageNumber="28">Coloration. In 70% ethanol: chestnut brown on dorsal and lateral surfaces of head and body, fading to light brown on ventral region. Dorsal surfaces of head and body with indistinct light brown patches on supraoccipital spine and immediately anterior to dorsal-spine base. Lateral surfaces of body with very faint light brown patches: one patch immediately posterior to last dorsal-fin ray and an elongate ovate spots on side of body immediately ventral to origin of adipose fin. Dorsal and anal fins with chestnut brown base and subdistal band. Adipose fin chestnut brown, with light brown anterior margin and margin along posterior twothirds of fin. Caudal fin chestnut brown, with small hyaline spot on lobes near horizontal midline and hyaline distal margin. Dorsal surfaces of pectoral and pelvic fin bases chestnut brown, with hyaline distal margin; ventral surfaces hyaline. Maxillary and nasal barbels chestnut brown dorsally and light brown ventrally.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="29">Distribution. Presently known only from the Song Thuy Loan River drainage (of which the Cat Lon stream is a tributary) that drains the eastern face of the Annam Cordillera in central Vietnam (Fig. 2).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageNumber="29">Habitat. The single specimen was obtained from a riffle zone of a small hill stream (ca 2-4 m wide, ca 10-30 cm deep). The bottom consists of fine gravel and granitic rocks, with exposed boulders along the banks and streamline (Fig. 3). The water was swift flowing and cool (ca 24 °C). No other fish were obtained from this habitat, although at least six species of amphibian tadpoles were present (unpub. data).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="etymology">
<paragraph pageNumber="29">Etymology. From the Greek mauros, meaning dark, in reference to the absence of distinct pale spots on the body of this species. Used as a noun in apposition.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="29">Discussion</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="31" pageNumber="29">
The relatively short adipose-fin base of 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">P. maurus</taxonomicName>
easily distinguishes the species from congeners. The thoracic adhesive apparatus of 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">P. maurus</taxonomicName>
is also distinctive, with the sulcae not meeting at the midline. Only 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="sympelvica">P. sympelvica</taxonomicName>
has an adhesive apparatus with a similar morphology, but it can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">P. maurus</taxonomicName>
by the characters mentioned in the diagnosis. 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">Pseudecheneis maurus</taxonomicName>
represents the first record of the genus in river drainages draining the eastern face of the Annam Cordillera. The most geographically proximate species is 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="sympelvica">P. sympelvica</taxonomicName>
, which is found in the Nam Theun river drainage (part of the Mekong River drainage) that drains the western face of the Annam Cordillera (ca. 400 km to the northwest). However, in addition to the different vertebral counts, fused pelvic fins, different color pattern and longer adipose fin base of 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="sympelvica">P. sympelvica</taxonomicName>
as outlined in the diagnosis, 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="sympelvica">P. sympelvica</taxonomicName>
further differs from 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="29" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">P. maurus</taxonomicName>
in having a more slender caudal peduncle (depth 4.7-4.8% SL vs. 6.0).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="31">
The description of 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="31" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">Pseudecheneis maurus</taxonomicName>
from only a single specimen (only one specimen was obtained in spite of intensive sampling lasting about an hour on each of three separate occasions at the type locality) is justifiable in this case because of the clear differences in the morphology of this species from all its congeners. These differences are present in morphological characters (e.g. length of adipose-fin base, depth of caudal peduncle) that have been shown to be useful for diagnosing other congeners (Ng, 2006a; 2006b; Ng &amp; Edds, 2005). Furthermore, 
<taxonomicName class="Actinopterygii" family="Sisoridae" genus="Pseudecheneis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Siluriformes" pageNumber="31" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="maurus">P. maurus</taxonomicName>
is known from an area where the genus has not been previously recorded and where considerable endemicity in the freshwater ichthyofauna has been demonstrated (e.g. Freyhof &amp; Serov, 2000).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>