<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284650" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5f96e565-1778-4154-8f67-81830690657d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135922" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284650" ModsDocID="6751" checkinTime="1243377290804" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Brown, W. L." docDate="1975" docId="2A8C6278FA2D3DD905DDDEA500A54983" docLanguage="en" docName="6751" docOrigin="Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station 15" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf" docTitle="Platythyrea zodion Brown, 1975, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="56" masterDocId="5EF94453F8BE2CD657C7B1F34B08FD04" masterDocTitle="Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini." masterLastPageNumber="115" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="55" updateTime="1645811814098" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Brown, W. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1975</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>15</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>115</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6751</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">45422C7B-83F2-4F5A-9EE4-74C51F2C2BFE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284650" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135922" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284650" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:2A8C6278FA2D3DD905DDDEA500A54983" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2A8C6278FA2D3DD905DDDEA500A54983" lastPageNumber="56" pageNumber="55">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="55">
[18] 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:34251" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Platythyrea" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platythyrea zodion Brown" lsidName-HNS="Platythyrea zodion Brown" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="zodion">Platythyrea zodion</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="55">(Figs. 34, 35, 36)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="55">Holotype worker: TL 4.9, HL 0.92, HW (behind eyes) 0.83 (CI 90), greatest diameter of eye 0.24, W across frontal lobes 0.47, scape L 0.54, ML 0.24, WL 1.56, fore femur L 0.75, fore femur maximum W 0.31 (W / L 41 %), petiolar node dorsal view L 0.63, W 0.54 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="55">Shape of head, propodeum, and petiole shown in figs. 34, 35, 36. Note the broad convex mandibles with cultrate masticatory margins, apex of mandible subtruncate viewed end on; masticatory margin rounding evenly into basal margin. Basidorsal groove very fine, indistinct, not reaching lateral margin. Clypeus gently concave in the middle and with free margin medially concave. Clypeus not distinctly delimited from the frontal lobes, but the frontal area forming a distinct pit that trails a shallow sulcus back to the center of the vertex. Eyes taking up approximately a third of length of sides of head, separated from antennal insertion by about 0.15 mm, or a little more than half the eye length. Undermouthparts closed, but palpi apparently with maxillary 6 and labial 4 segments (4 and 3 segments visible respectively); palpi short, in repose barely surpassing the posterior buccal border.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="55">Antennae with pedicel very slightly longer than broad and very slightly longer than the succeeding (second funicular) segment; second segment very slightly broader than long; remaining funicular segments broader than long, except for apical segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="55">
Trunk robust, with a weakly convex dorsal profile as seen from side view, about 2 1 / 2 times as long as broad seen from above, with rounded humeri and steep sides of pronotum, but not really marginate dorsolaterally. Sides of pronotum with an impression in posterior part. Promesonotal suture distinct, impressed, apparently flexible; metanotal groove obsolete, marked by a feeble impression at sides of dorsum. Mesopleuron distinctly bounded by complete sutures above and behind. Propodeal declivity concave, bounded by distinct margins that are especially prominent at the upper corners, but weak in the upper-middle portion due to a feeble median posterior impression of the dorsal face, seen best in oblique light. Upper part of declivity shining, very finely punctulate; lower part coarsely, transversely striate. Femur of anterior leg strongly incrassate — almost as strongly as in 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:34214" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Platythyrea" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platythyrea angusta Forel" lsidName-HNS="Platythyrea angusta Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="angusta">P. angusta</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="55">Node well shown in figs. 34 and 35; note the lack of posterolateral teeth or angles and the faint vestige of a median tooth. Subpetiolar process rounded ventrally, with a small notch behind. Gaster with first 2 segments (postpetiole and true abdominal segment IV) about equal in width, with the second segment a little longer than the first, constriction between them moderately distinct. Sting robust, compressed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="55">
Sculpture of the usual opaque kind in 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:24826" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Platythyrea" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platythyrea Roger" lsidName-HNS="Platythyrea Roger" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Platythyrea</taxonomicName>
, very finely and densely reticulate with fine, overlying pruinosity, the reticulation becoming more transversely elongate on gaster, and slightly more shining here. Coarse punctures abundant on vertex mesad of and behind eyes, but rather weak and inconspicuous. Coarser punctures on sides and posterior dorsum of trunk, on petiolar node, especially sides and anterior dorsum, and on dorsum of postpetiole. Fine, short erect hairs on mandibles, anterior clypeal margin, and gastric apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="55">Color black; mandibles, antennae, and tarsi brownish yellow; tibiae and gastric apex dull yellowish brown; femora brown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="55">Holotype a worker from Ecuador: 2 - 8 miles N of Puyo, Pastaza (or Napo), about 950 m, 9 February 1955 (E. I. Schlinger and E. S. Ross), deposited in CAS — San Francisco.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph lastPageNumber="56" pageNumber="55">
This species is distinguished from all New World Platythyrea except 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:34226" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Platythyrea" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platythyrea exigua Kempf" lsidName-HNS="Platythyrea exigua Kempf" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exigua">P. exigua</taxonomicName>
by its very small size. It differs from 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:34226" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Platythyrea" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platythyrea exigua Kempf" lsidName-HNS="Platythyrea exigua Kempf" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="exigua">exigua</taxonomicName>
by its much shorter head and virtually unarmed petiolar node. The node is also different in shape from those of all other neotropical species. The anterior femur is broadened almost as much as in 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:34245" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Platythyrea" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platythyrea sinuata (Roger)" lsidName-HNS="Platythyrea sinuata (Roger)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sinuata">P. sinuata</taxonomicName>
, and the basidorsal groove of the mandible is present, though very fine. The type locality is in western Amazonian forest with small clearings, just out of sight of the Andes to the west (notes from E. S. Ross).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<caption>
<subSubSection type="multiple">
<paragraph pageNumber="56">
Figures 7 - 10. Two 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
of 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:24827" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Probolomyrmex" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Probolomyrmex Mayr" lsidName-HNS="Probolomyrmex Mayr" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="56" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Probolomyrmex</taxonomicName>
, holotype workers, both from S India, petiole and adjacent structures in side view (7, 8) and dorsal view (9, 10), X 73.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</caption>
</treatment>
</document>