<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.530.6063" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e7c51075-cb03-45f1-858a-8f4e28646063" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152062884" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-530-15" ID-ZBK="DC6C1B50B660461FBF0E4A101C1CD551" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:75FDE441-CD57-41C4-B154-1E3D29ECAC3E" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1313-2970-530-15" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 530" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Jesogammarus from the Iki Island, Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Anisogammaridae)" checkinTime="1451243844287" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Tomikawa, Ko" docDate="2015" docId="1DFEF6642791449B8D29609AD3226303" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 530: 15-36" docOrigin="ZooKeys 530" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.530.6063" docTitle="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis Tomikawa, 2015, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="75FDE441-CD57-41C4-B154-1E3D29ECAC3E" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="26" masterDocId="6F6EFA3DAD47FFD2FFBAF05A451E720C" masterDocTitle="A new species of Jesogammarus from the Iki Island, Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Anisogammaridae)" masterLastPageNumber="36" masterPageNumber="15" pageId="4" pageNumber="19" updateTime="1643649148336" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of Jesogammarus from the Iki Island, Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Anisogammaridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tomikawa, Ko</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>530</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>15</mods:start>
<mods:end>36</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.530.6063</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.530.6063</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-530-15</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">DC6C1B50B660461FBF0E4A101C1CD551</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">DC6C1B50B660461FBF0E4A101C1CD551</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152062884" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:75FDE441-CD57-41C4-B154-1E3D29ECAC3E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1DFEF6642791449B8D29609AD3226303" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="4" pageNumber="19">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="19" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="19">Taxon classification Animalia Amphipoda Anisogammaridae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="19" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="19">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/75FDE441-CD57-41C4-B154-1E3D29ECAC3E" class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="4" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="4" pageNumber="19">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="19" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="19">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="19">
Holotype: NSMT-Cr 24107, male (13.1 mm, 8 slides), river at Ishida (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="33.750473">33°45'1.7&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="129.74269">129°44'33.7&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
), Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan, collected by K. Tomikawa and S. Tashiro on 9 March 2012. Paratypes: NSMT-Cr 24108, ovigerous female (10.4 mm, 6 slides), NSMT-Cr 24109, 1 male and 1 ovigerous female in ethanol vial, data same as for holotype; NSMT-Cr 24110, 2 males and 2 ovigerous females in ethanol vial, river at Ishida (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="33.750473">33°45'1.7&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="129.74269">129°44'33.7&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
), Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan, collected by K. Tomikawa and S. Tashiro on 2 April 2015; NSMT-Cr 24111, male (12.0 mm, 6 slides), NSMT-Cr 24112, ovigerous female (9.4 mm, 5 slides), river at Katsumoto (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="33.825027">33°49'30.1&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="129.71431">129°42'51.5&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
), Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan, collected by K. Tomikawa and S. Tashiro on 8 March 2012; NSMT-Cr 24113, male (11.9 mm, 5 slides), NSMT-Cr 24114, ovigerous female (10.0 mm, 5 slides), river at Ashibe (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="33.784195">33°47'3.1&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="129.75105">129°45'3.8&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
), Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan, collected by K. Tomikawa and S. Tashiro on 9 March 2012; NSMT-Cr 24115, male (9.2 mm, 5 slides), NSMT-Cr 24116, female with offsprings (7.4 mm, 5 slides), irrigation ditch at Gonoura (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="33.72389">33°43'26&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="129.69778">129°41'52&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
), Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan, collected by K. Tomikawa and S. Tashiro on 9 March 2012.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="21" pageId="4" pageNumber="19" type="description of male">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="19">Description of male</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="20" pageId="4" pageNumber="19">
(holotype, NSMT-Cr 24107). Head (Fig. 4) with short rostrum; ventral margin of lateral cephalic lobe weakly concave; antennal sinus rounded; eyes reniform, major axis 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
height of head. Dorsal surfaces of pereonites smooth (Fig. 4). Dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3 (Fig. 9
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–E">C-E</normalizedToken>
) with three, two, and two setae, respectively. Posterior margin of epimeral plate 1 rounded with seta, anteroventral cor 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="20" start="start">ner</pageBreakToken>
with many setae (Fig. 9I); posterior margin of plate 2 with one seta, posteroventral corner quadrate, anteroventral corner with three setae, ventral submargin with four robust setae (Fig. 9J); posterior margin of plate 3 with two setae, posteroventral corner quadrate, anteroventral to ventral margin with six setae (Fig. 9K). Urosomites 1-3 (Fig. 9
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
) with seven, four, and two robust setae associated with slender setae.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 13.1 mm, NSMT-Cr 24107, Ishida, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan. Habitus, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Antenna 1 (Fig. 5A): length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
body length; peduncular articles 1-3 in length ratio of 1.0: 0.9: 0.5; posterodistal corner of peduncular article 1 with one robust seta, posterior margin of peduncular article 2 with one cluster and three pairs of setae, posterior margin of peduncular article 3 with one cluster and one pair of setae; accessory flagellum seven-articulate; primary flagellum 29-articulate, each article with one aesthetasc.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 13.1 mm, NSMT-Cr 24107, Ishida, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan. A peduncular articles 1-3, accessory flagellum, and flagellar articles 1-4 of antenna 1, medial view (posterio-marginal setae on peduncular articles 2 and 3 indicated by arrowheads) B peduncular articles 1-5 and flagellar articles 1-3 of antenna 2, medial view (posterio-marginal setae on peduncular articles 4 and 5 indicated by arrowheads) C calceolus of antenna 2, medial view D upper lip, anterior view E lower lip, ventral view F left mandible except palp, medial view G incisor and lacinia mobilis of right mandible, lateral view H palp of right mandible, medial view I maxilla 1, dorsal view J outer plate of maxilla 1, dorsal view K Maxilla 2, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Antenna 2 (Fig. 5B): length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
antenna 1; posterior margin of peduncular article 4 with three clusters of setae, posterior margin of peduncular article 5 with three clusters of setae and one single seta; flagellum 18-articulate, calceoli present (Fig. 5C).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Mouthparts. Upper lip (= labrum) (Fig. 5D) with rounded distal margin, bearing fine setae. Lower lip (= labium) (Fig. 5E) with broad outer lobes, inner lobes indistinct. Mandibles (Fig. 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
) with left and right incisors six- and four-dentate, respectively, left lacinia mobilis five-dentate, right one bifid, bearing many teeth; molar process triturative, with plumose seta; accessory setal rows of left and right mandibles each with seven blade-like setae; left palp three-articulate with length ratio of 1.0: 3.8: 3.8, palp article 1 bare, article 2 with 28 setae, article 3 with two clusters and one pair of A-setae, one pair of B-setae, and many C-, D-, and E-setae, article 3 of right palp with three clusters of A-seta and one B-seta. Maxilla 1 (Fig. 5I) with inner and outer plates and palp; medial margin and apical submargin of inner plate with 31 plumose setae; outer plate subrectangular, with 11 serrate teeth apically (Fig. 5J); right palp two-articulate, much longer than outer plate, article 1 lacking marginal setae, article 2 with seven robust and six slender setae on its apical margin, outer margin with three setae, left palp lacking setae on outer margin of article 2. Maxilla 2 (Fig. 5K) with oblique inner row of 23 plumose setae on inner plate; outer plate slightly longer than inner plate. Maxilliped (Fig. 6A) with inner and outer plates and palp; inner plate (Fig. 6C) with six robust setae along apical and inner margins; outer plate (Fig. 6B) with plumose setae on apical margin and robust setae on inner margin; palp four-articulate, article 2 with inner marginal and submarginal rows of setae, article 3 with facial setae, article 4 slightly curved inward, with slender nail.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="20" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 13.1 mm, NSMT-Cr 24107, Ishida, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan. A maxilliped, dorsal view B outer plate of maxilliped, dorsal view C inner plate of maxilliped, dorsal view D gnathopod 1, medial view E palmar margin of propodus and dactylus of gnathopod 1, medial view F gnathopod 2, medial view G palmar margin of propodus and dactylus of gnathopod 2, medial view H coxal gill of gnathopod 2, medial view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Gnathopod 1 (= pereopod 1) (Fig. 6D): coxa (= article 1) with six setae on ventral margin; anterior and posterior margins of basis (= article 2) with long setae; carpus (= article 5) length 1.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, anterior margin with seta; propodus (= article 6) length 1.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of carpus and 1.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×width">xwidth</normalizedToken>
of propodus, anterior margin with one pair and two clusters of setae, palmar margin (Fig. 6E) oblique, weakly convex, with 16 peg-spines (= robust setae); dactylus (= article 7) (Fig. 6E) as long as palmar margin, with posterior accessory blade longer than nail, blade basally elevated.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="21" pageId="5" pageNumber="20">
Gnathopod 2 (= pereopod 2) (Fig. 6F): coxa with seven marginal and one submarginal setae on ventral part, posteroproximal part with two setae; anterior and posterior 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="21" start="start">margins</pageBreakToken>
of basis with long setae; carpus length 1.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, anterior margin with cluster of setae and single seta; propodus almost as long as carpus and 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of propodus, anterior margin with two clusters of setae, palmar margin (Fig. 6G) oblique, weakly convex, with 12 peg-spines (= robust setae) and one serrate seta; dactylus (Fig. 6G) as long as palmar margin, with posterior accessory blade longer than nail.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">Pereopod 3 (Fig. 7A, B): coxa with seven marginal setae on ventral part, posterio-proximal part with two setae; anterior and posterior margins of basis with long setae, anterio-distal corner of basis with robust seta.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 13.1 mm, NSMT-Cr 24107, Ishida, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan. A 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–merus">coxa-merus</normalizedToken>
and coxal gill of pereopod 3, lateral view B 
<normalizedToken originalValue="carpus–dactylus">carpus-dactylus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 3, lateral view C 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–merus">coxa-merus</normalizedToken>
and coxal gill of pereopod 4, lateral view D 
<normalizedToken originalValue="carpus–dactylus">carpus-dactylus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 4, lateral view E coxal gill of pereopod 5, lateral view F 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–merus">coxa-merus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 5, lateral view G 
<normalizedToken originalValue="carpus–dactylus">carpus-dactylus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 5, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 7C, D): coxa expanded with posterior concavity, bearing one seta on anterodistal corner and five setae on posterodistal margin; anterior and posterior margins of basis with long setae, anterodistal corner with robust seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">Pereopod 5 (Fig. 7F, G): coxa bilobed, anterior lobe with apical seta, ventral margin of posterior lobe with three setae; posterior margin of basis weakly expanded, with ten setae; anterior and posterior margins of merus to propodus with robust and slender setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">Pereopod 6 (Fig. 8A, B): coxa bilobed, anterior lobe with apical seta and anterio-proximal setae, ventral margin of posterior lobe with three setae; posterior margin of basis weakly expanded, with 18 setae; anterior and posterior margins of merus to propodus with robust and slender setae.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
Figure 8. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 13.1 mm, NSMT-Cr 24107, Ishida, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan. A 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–merus">coxa-merus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view B 
<normalizedToken originalValue="carpus–dactylus">carpus-dactylus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view C coxal gill of pereopod 6, lateral view D 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–merus">coxa-merus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view E 
<normalizedToken originalValue="carpus–dactylus">carpus-dactylus</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view F coxal gill of pereopod 7, lateral view G pleopod 1, medial view, distal parts of rami omitted H retinacula on peduncle of pleopod 1, medial view I bifid plumose seta (clothes-pin seta) on inner basal margin of inner ramus of pleopod 1, medial view J uropod 1, dorsal view K uropod 2, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">Pereopod 7 (Fig. 7D, E): ventral margin of coxa weakly concave, bearing slender setae on anterior part and three setae on posteroventral part; posterior margin of basis weakly expanded, with 20 setae; anterior and posterior margins of merus to propodus with robust and slender setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">Coxal gills on gnathopod 2 and pereopods 3-5 (Figs 6H, 7A, C, E) with two accessory lobes, gills on pereopods 6 and 7 (Fig. 8C, F) each with one accessory lobe.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">Pleopods 1-3 (Fig. 8G) each with paired retinacula (Fig. 8H) on inner margin of peduncle, and bifid plumose setae (= clothes-pin setae) (Fig. 8I) on inner basal margin of inner ramus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
Uropods. Uropod 1 (Fig. 8J): peduncle with robust seta on basofacial part, inner and outer margins each with three robust setae, inner proximal part with three short setae; inner ramus length 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
peduncle, inner margin with three robust setae and outer margin with robust seta and minute seta; outer ramus length 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
inner ramus, inner and outer margins each with two and three robust setae. Uropod 2 (Fig. 8K): peduncle with three robust setae on inner and outer margins, respectively; inner ramus length 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
peduncle, its inner and outer margins with two robust setae, respectively; outer ramus length 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
inner ramus, its outer margin with robust seta. Uropod 3 (Fig. 9A): peduncle length 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus; inner ramus length 0.25 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus (both proximal and terminal articles), with two robust setae on inner margin; outer ramus two-articulate, inner margin of proximal article with five plumose setae, and several robust setae and simple setae, outer margin with robust setae and simple setae, terminal article length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
proximal article, with short setae apically.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="6" pageNumber="21" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., Ishida, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan. Holotype, male, 13.1 mm, NSMT-Cr 24107 (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–K">A-K</normalizedToken>
) and paratype, female, 10.4 mm, NSMT-Cr 24108 (L and M). A uropod 3, dorsal view B telson, dorsal view 
<normalizedToken originalValue="C–E">C-E</normalizedToken>
pleonites 1-3, respectively, dorsal views 
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
urosomites 1-3, respectively, dorsal views 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–K">I-K</normalizedToken>
epimeral plates 1-3, respectively, lateral views L peduncular articles 1-3, accessory flagellum, and flagellar articles 1-5 of antenna 1, medial view M peduncular articles 1-5 and flagellar articles 1-3 of antenna 2, medial view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="21">
Telson (Fig. 9B) length 1.1 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, cleft for 59% of length in V-shape; each lobe with one lateral and one apical robust seta.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="23" pageId="7" pageNumber="22" type="description of ovigerous female">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="22">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="22" start="start">Description</pageBreakToken>
of ovigerous female
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="22">
(paratype, NSMT-Cr 24108). Antenna 1 (Fig. 9L): length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
body length; peduncular articles 1-3 in length ratio of 1.0: 0.8: 0.5; accessory flagellum seven-articulate; primary flagellum 36-articulate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="22">
Antenna 2 (Fig. 9M): length 0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
antenna 1; flagellum 12-articulate, calceoli absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="23" start="start">Gnathopod</pageBreakToken>
1 (Fig. 10A): carpus length 1.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, with cluster of setae and single seta on anterior margin; propodus almost as long as carpus and 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of propodus, bearing two clusters and one pair of setae on anterior margin; palmar margin (Fig. 10B) with seven robust setae and two pectinate setae.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype, female, 10.4 mm, NSMT-Cr 24108, Ishida, Iki, Nagasaki Prefecture, Japan. A 
<normalizedToken originalValue="ischium–dactylus">ischium-dactylus</normalizedToken>
of gnathopod 1, lateral view B posterodistal part of palmar margin of propodus and part of dactylus of gnathopod 1, medial view C 
<normalizedToken originalValue="ischium–dactylus">ischium-dactylus</normalizedToken>
of gnathopod 2, lateral view D posterodistal part of palmar margin of propodus and part of dactylus of gnathopod 2, medial view E brood plate of gnathopod 2, lateral view F 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 5, lateral view G 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view H 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 7, lateral view I uropod 3, ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="8" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus (Jesogammarus) ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., not preserved. A precopula pair (male: upper, female: lower) B male, approx. 13 mm. Photographed by Ryu Uchiyama.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 10C): carpus length 2.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, with one cluster, one pair, and one single seta on anterior margin; propodus length 0.9 and 2.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
carpus and width of propodus, respectively, bearing one cluster and one pair of setae on anterior margin; palmar margin (Fig. 10D) with two robust and 10 pectinate setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
Posterior margin of bases of pereopods 5-7 more expanded than in male (Fig. 10
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–H">F-H</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Brood plates (= oostegites) (Fig. 10E): broad, with numerous marginal setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
Uropod 3 (Fig. 10I): peduncle length 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus; inner ramus length 0.3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus (both proximal and terminal articles), with robust seta on inner margin; inner margin of proximal article of outer ramus with plumose seta, terminal article length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
proximal article.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Egg number: 175.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="24" pageId="8" pageNumber="23" type="variations">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="23">Variations.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="24" pageId="8" pageNumber="23">
The number of setae and/or setal bundles on posterior margin of peduncular articles of antennae is variable: antenna 1, two or three on article 1, three or four on article 2, one or two on article 3; antenna 2, two to four on article 4, three to 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="24" start="start">five</pageBreakToken>
on article 5. Most specimens have a pair of setae on dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3 but several specimens have three setae. The length ratio of inner ramus of uropod 3 to outer ramus ranged from 0.2 to 0.3 in both sexes. The number of plumose setae on inner margin of outer ramus of uropod 3 varied from two to eight in males and one to three in females. Ovigerous females have 58 to 175 eggs.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="24">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="26" pageId="9" pageNumber="24">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is assigned to the subgenus 
<taxonomicName lsidName="(Jesogammarus)" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" rank="subGenus" subGenus="Jesogammarus">Jesogammarus</taxonomicName>
in having well developed posterior accessory lobe of coxal gills on gnathopod 2 and pereopods 3-5, and pectinate setae on palmar margin of female gnathopod 2. The new species is distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus fontanus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fontanus">Jesogammarus fontanus</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, 2004, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus hebeiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hebeiensis">Jesogammarus hebeiensis</taxonomicName>
Hou &amp; Li, 2004, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus hinumensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hinumensis">Jesogammarus hinumensis</taxonomicName>
Morino, 1993, and 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus spinopalpus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinopalpus">Jesogammarus spinopalpus</taxonomicName>
Morino, 1985 by absence (vs. presence) of setae on article 1 of mandibular palp. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus mikadoi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mikadoi">Jesogammarus mikadoi</taxonomicName>
Tomikawa, Morino &amp; Mawatari, 2003 by absence (vs. presence) of setae on dorsal margin of pereonites 5-7 and two or three (vs. more than seven) setae on dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus paucisetulosus" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="24" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="paucisetulosus">Jesogammarus paucisetulosus</taxonomicName>
Morino, 1984 by medium eye, major axis of eyes 0.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
height of 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="25" start="start">head</pageBreakToken>
(vs. small, less than 0.3), posterodistal corner of peduncular article 1 of antenna 1 with a robust (vs. slender) seta, posterior margin of peduncular article 2 of antenna 1 with three or four (vs. more than five) setae and/or setal bundles, and posterio-marginal setae on peduncular article 4 of antenna 2 shorter (vs. longer) than width of 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="26" start="start">article</pageBreakToken>
4 in male;. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
differs from the 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus jesoensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jesoensis">Jesogammarus jesoensis</taxonomicName>
complex including 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus fujinoi" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fujinoi">Jesogammarus fujinoi</taxonomicName>
Tomikawa &amp; Morino, 2003, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus hokurikuensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="hokurikuensis">Jesogammarus hokurikuensis</taxonomicName>
Morino, 1985, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus jesoensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="jesoensis">Jesogammarus jesoensis</taxonomicName>
(Schellenberg, 1937), 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus shonaiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="shonaiensis">Jesogammarus shonaiensis</taxonomicName>
Tomikawa &amp; Morino, 2003, by two or three (vs. more than seven) setae on dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3 and three or four (vs. two) setae and/or setal bundles on posterior margin of peduncular article 2 of antenna 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ikiensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ikiensis">Jesogammarus ikiensis</taxonomicName>
differs from 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Anisogammaridae" genus="Jesogammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Jesogammarus ilhoii" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="26" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ilhoii">Jesogammarus ilhoii</taxonomicName>
Lee &amp; Seo, 1992 by absence (vs. presence) of pectinate setae on palmar margin of propodus of male gnathopod 2 and two or three (vs. more than ten) setae on dorsal margins of pleonites 1-3.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="26" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">The specific name is from the Latinized Japanese ikiensis (of Iki), referring to the type locality of the new species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="26" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Known only from Iki Island.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="26" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="26">River and irrigation ditch.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>