<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" ID-GBIF-Dataset="92d38eff-94a4-404e-a09c-d535155922c8" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043378" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-292-1" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2281CD64-1094-4081-8DF4-7C4296E0B115" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-292-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 292" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" checkinTime="1451247388242" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="46EEBFEA08CFE0FD0543EA7DFE158DFD" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 292: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 292" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867" docTitle="Oxyscelio sinuum Burks, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="2281CD64-1094-4081-8DF4-7C4296E0B115" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="208" lastPageNumber="209" masterDocId="FFB8FF92FF98D87CFFAE2F6B1E57FFC8" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="205" pageNumber="206" updateTime="1643694823285" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>292</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.292.3867</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-292-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043378" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2281CD64-1094-4081-8DF4-7C4296E0B115" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/46EEBFEA08CFE0FD0543EA7DFE158DFD" lastPageId="208" lastPageNumber="209" pageId="205" pageNumber="206">
<subSubSection lastPageId="206" lastPageNumber="207" pageId="205" pageNumber="206" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph lastPageId="206" lastPageNumber="207" pageId="205" pageNumber="206">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2281CD64-1094-4081-8DF4-7C4296E0B115" authority="Burks" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio sinuum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="205" pageNumber="206" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sinuum">Oxyscelio sinuum Burks</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="205" pageNumber="206">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
<pageBreakToken pageId="206" pageNumber="207" start="start">Figures</pageBreakToken>
395-398Morphbank105
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="207" lastPageNumber="208" pageId="206" pageNumber="207" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="206" pageNumber="207">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="206" pageNumber="207">Female. Body length 4.1-4.65 mm (n=4).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="206" pageNumber="207">Radicle color: same color as scape. Scape color: Brown. A4: longer than broad. A5: broader than long. Antennal club: formed, segments compact.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="206" pageNumber="207">Interantennal process: not elongate. Median longitudinal elevation in frontal depression: absent. Frontal depression: concave. Frontal depression sculpture: with 3 or more broadly interrupted transverse carinae. Submedian carina: strong, formed by a sharp raised carina. Submedian carina medially: with sharp peak. Concavity across dorsal part of frontal depression: absent. Depression extending ventrally from median ocellus: absent. Upper frons: not hood-like. Malar area near antennal foramen: without carina or expansion. Malar area at mouth corner: with radiating striae. Smooth strip along posterior side of malar sulcus: absent or not consistently broad. Middle genal carina: present. Direction of middle genal carina dorsally: parallel to eye margin. Major sculpture of gena anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate; rugose. Major sculpture of gena posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent. Median carina extending posteriorly from hyperoccipital carina: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: indicated by rugae. Lateral connection between hyperoccipital and occipital carinae: present as a weak elevation. Area between vertex and occipital carina: umbilicate-foveate. Occipital carina medially: divided into concave halves, meeting at median peak. Lateral corners of occipital carina: sharp and protruding.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="206" pageNumber="207">Lateral pronotal area: without bulge projecting towards anterior pit. Epomial corner: strong. Netrion surface anteriorly: not inflexed. Mesoscutum anteriorly: not steep. Mesoscutal median carina: present and complete. Longitudinal carina between median carina and notauli: absent. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Major sculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: umbilicate-foveate. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum anteriorly: absent. Microsculpture of medial mesoscutum posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum: umbilicate-foveate; longitudinally rugose. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum medially: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum laterally: absent. Mesoscutellar apex: convex or straight. Setae along anterior limit of femoral depression: arising from rows of foveae. Number of carinae crossing speculum above femoral depression: 3. Number of carinae crossing femoral depression: 3-5. Mesepimeral sulcus pits: 3-5. Metascutellum dorsally: flat. Metascutellar sculpture dorsally: with scattered rugae. Median carina of metascutellum: absent or branched. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellar apex: convex or straight; weakly emarginate. Metapleuron above ventral metapleural area: crossed by carinae. Metasomal depression setae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae anteromedially: strongly diverging. Anterior areoles of metasomal depression: absent. Anterior longitudinal carinae in metasomal depression: absent. Lateral propodeal areas: separated medially. Postmarginal vein: present. Fore wing apex: reaching apex of T4.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="207" lastPageNumber="208" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">
T1 midlobe: obscured by other raised sculpture. T1: with long anterior bulge, reaching metascutellum. T2: with straight longitudinal striae or rugae. T6: longer than 
<pageBreakToken pageId="207" pageNumber="208" start="start">broad</pageBreakToken>
. Apical flange of T6: not exposed apically. Metasomal apex: rounded. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate-punctate. Microsculpture of T6: granulate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="207" pageNumber="208">Male. Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="208" lastPageNumber="209" pageId="207" pageNumber="208" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="207" pageNumber="208">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="208" lastPageNumber="209" pageId="207" pageNumber="208">
Female: Occipital carina complete as a distinct carina, but medial portions concave and meeting at a rounded peak. Mesoscutellum with many narrow longitudinal rugae. Netrion not concave. Metascutellum broad and subrectangular, not 
<pageBreakToken pageId="208" pageNumber="209" start="start">concave</pageBreakToken>
. Fore wings long enough to reach apex of T4. T1 midlobe with anterior horn. T6 longer than broad and tapering to a narrow but rounded apex.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="208" pageNumber="209" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">Latin noun, 4th declension, genitive case, referring to the medially sinuate occipital carina.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="208" pageNumber="209" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=275539]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="208" pageNumber="209" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">
Holotype, female: THAILAND: Nakhon Si Thammarat Prov., TV aerial, T3103, Namtok Yong National Park, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="8.2377">08°14.262'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="99.80482">99°48.289'E</geoCoordinate>
, 966m, 18.
<normalizedToken originalValue="VIII–">VIII-</normalizedToken>
25.VIII.2008, malaise trap, Paiboon, OSUC 352506 (deposited in QSBG). Paratypes: (3 females) SINGAPORE: 1 female, OSUC 376755 (MCZC). THAILAND: 2 females, OSUC 352505 (OSUC); OSUC 361953 (QSBG).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="208" pageNumber="209" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio sinuum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="208" pageNumber="209" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sinuum">Oxyscelio sinuum</taxonomicName>
resembles some other species with a complete, sinuate occipital carina. It differs in a combination of characters, including the flat, rugose metascutellum.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="208" pageNumber="209">
<paragraph pageId="208" pageNumber="209">
Figures 395-398. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio sinuum" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="208" pageNumber="209" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sinuum">Oxyscelio sinuum</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype female (OSUC 352505) 395 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 396 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 397 Head, anterior view 398 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank105
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>