<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001" ID-GBIF-Dataset="9cccfd73-da48-4ef6-be1b-1764337602de" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152062789" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-528-1" ID-ZBK="7BABDD295E484320B8964E8306B0ECE8" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:24BAD6A8-9225-47B5-9174-FDAB2B7E7A4A" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1313-2970-528-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 528" ModsDocTitle="Phylogenetic revision of Minyomerus Horn, 1876 sec. Jansen &amp; Franz, 2015 (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) using taxonomic concept annotations and alignments" checkinTime="1451243880599" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Jansen, M. Andrew &amp; Franz, Nico M." docDate="2015" docId="4ADEF62F481EA764A31C42948AC57E37" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 528: 1-133" docOrigin="ZooKeys 528" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001" docTitle="Minyomerus rutellirostris [JF 2015] Jansen &amp; Franz sec. Jansen &amp; Franz 2015, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="24BAD6A8-9225-47B5-9174-FDAB2B7E7A4A" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="88" lastPageNumber="89" masterDocId="535DFFBEFFB3FFF3FFC56E31063DFF88" masterDocTitle="Phylogenetic revision of Minyomerus Horn, 1876 sec. Jansen &amp; Franz, 2015 (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) using taxonomic concept annotations and alignments" masterLastPageNumber="133" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" updateTime="1643511826791" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Phylogenetic revision of Minyomerus Horn, 1876 sec. Jansen &amp; Franz, 2015 (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) using taxonomic concept annotations and alignments</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jansen, M. Andrew</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Franz, Nico M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>528</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>133</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.528.6001</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-528-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">7BABDD295E484320B8964E8306B0ECE8</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">7BABDD295E484320B8964E8306B0ECE8</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152062789" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:24BAD6A8-9225-47B5-9174-FDAB2B7E7A4A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4ADEF62F481EA764A31C42948AC57E37" lastPageId="88" lastPageNumber="89" pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<pageBreakToken pageId="83" pageNumber="84" start="start">Taxon</pageBreakToken>
classification Animalia Coleoptera Curculionidae
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/24BAD6A8-9225-47B5-9174-FDAB2B7E7A4A" authority="Jansen &amp; Franz sec. Jansen &amp; Franz (2015)" class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus rutellirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="symbols" species="rutellirostris" symbols="[JF2015]">Minyomerus rutellirostris [JF2015] Jansen &amp; Franz sec. Jansen &amp; Franz (2015)</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="83" pageNumber="84">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 46, 47, 48
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus rutellirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rutellirostris">Minyomerus rutellirostris</taxonomicName>
[JF2015] can be readily differentiated from other congenerics by the separated procoxae and the size of the rostrum, which is as wide as the head, and distinctly square in dorsal view. In the males, the dilation of the rostrum is greatly exaggerated, and the lateral margins are flared. The ramus of the spermatheca is basally narrow, forming a stalk that tapers into an apical bulb. The aedeagus is elongate, narrowing towards the apexmore strongly in the region of the ostium.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="87" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="83" pageNumber="84" type="description – female">
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Description - female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Habitus. Length 4.47-5.29 mm, width 1.84-2.12 mm, length/width ratio 2.39-2.60, widest at anterior 1/4 of elytra. Integument orange-brown to black. Scales with variously interspersed colors ranging from slightly off-white to manila/tan to dark coffee brown, in some specimens appearing semi-translucent (in others opaque). Setae sub-recumbent, brown; with larger, more erect white setae interspersed throughout on even numbered elytral intervals, shorter setae arranged in rows on all elytral intervals.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Mandibles. Covered with opalescent scales, with 4 longer setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Maxillae. Cardo bifurcate at base with an inner angle of ca. 115°, inner (mesal) arm sub-equal in length to outer arm, inner arm of equal width to outer arm, arms of bifurcation equal in length to apically outcurved arm. Stipes sub-quadrate, nearly equilateral, roughly equal in length to inner arm of bifurcation of cardo, with a single lateral seta. Galeo-lacinial complexapically incurved (mesally); complexmembranous; setose in basal 2/3; dorsally with 8 apicomesal lacinial teeth; ventrally with 4 reduced lacinial teeth. Palpiger with a lateral patch of setae, sclerotized on basal 2/3.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Maxillary palps. Palpomeres I and II with apical ends facing mesally and forming a 45° angle with base, each with 2 apical setae; II with 1 mesoventral seta in addition to apical seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="83" pageNumber="84">Labium. Prementum completely roughly hexagonal; apical margin straight, medially weakly or not projected (ligula reduced), weakly angulate; lateral margins slightly incurved; basal margin broadly arcuate. Labial palps 3-segmented, I with apexreaching margin of prementum; III slightly longer than II.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="84" lastPageNumber="85" pageId="83" pageNumber="84">
Rostrum. Length 0.57-0.77 mm, appearing distinctly flattened, anterior portion 2.5-3.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
broader than long, rostrum/pronotum length ratio 0.46-0.53, rostrum length/width ratio 0.86-1.00; shape in cross section elongate rectangular. Dorsal outline of rostrum sub-rectangular, anterior half of dorsal surface slightly concave and weakly impressed, posterior half strongly rugose. Rostrum in lateral view rectangular; apical margin with 2 large vibrissae. Nasal plate defined by broad, Y-shaped concavities, convex, integument completely covered with scales similar to those of body. Margins of mandibular incision directed 30° outward dorsally in frontal view; ventrolateral sulci well defined, beginning as a sulcus dorsad of insertion point of mandibles, running parallel to scrobe, becoming fainter posteriorly and disappearing ventrally. Integument dorsad of sulcus expanded somewhat laterally. Dorsal surface of rostrum with median sulcus running from fovea at posterior end of anterior half rostrum to midpoint of pos 
<pageBreakToken pageId="84" pageNumber="85" start="start">terior</pageBreakToken>
half of rostrum; ventrolateral margins sub-parallel, in some specimens diverging. Rostrum ventrally lacking foveae in line with insertion point of mandibles. Oral cavity with lateral margins feebly curved.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="86" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="85" pageNumber="86">
<pageBreakToken pageId="85" pageNumber="86" start="start">Antennae</pageBreakToken>
. Dorsal margin of scrobe overhangs forming a small tooth ventrad of anterior margin of eye. Funicular antennomeres evenly progressing from elongate to broader than long; terminal segment lacking appressed scales, having instead a cover 
<pageBreakToken pageId="86" pageNumber="87" start="start">ing</pageBreakToken>
of apically-directed pubescence with interspersed sub-erect setae. Club 2.5-3.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
Head. Eyes separated in dorsal view by 4-5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
their anterior-posterior length, touching anterior prothoracic margin. Head without transverse post-ocular impression.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="87" lastPageNumber="88" pageId="86" pageNumber="87">
Pronotum. Length/width ratio 0.94-0.99, sub-cylindrical to globular; widest near anterior 1/3; median sulcus absent. Anterior margin broadly arcuate, lateral margins 
<pageBreakToken pageId="87" pageNumber="88" start="start">curved</pageBreakToken>
and widening into a bulge at anterior 1/3 of pronotum, thence straight to posterior margin, posterior margin straight. Pronotum in lateral view setae that reach beyond anterior margin; these setae becoming evenly longer laterally, nearly reaching into anterior 1/2 of eye at their maximum length. Anterolateral margin with a reduced tuft of post-ocular vibrissae present, consisting of 4-6 setae, emerging near ventral margin of eye; vibrissae achieving a maximum length 3/4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
anterior-posterior length of eye.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">Pleurites. Metepisternum covered by elytron near posterior 1/5 of metasternum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Abdominal sterna. Procoxal cavities positioned at midpoint, contiguous, prosternal process complete between coxae, slightly elevated. Mesocoxal cavities separated by distance 1/2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width of mesocoxal cavity. Metasternum without apprent transverse sulcus; metacoxal cavities widely separated by 3-4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
their width.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Legs. Profemur/pronotum length ratio 0.83-0.93; profemur with distal 1/5 produced ventrally as an oblique projection covering tibial joint. Protibia/profemur length ratio 0.87-0.94; mucro reduced to a small laterally projected tooth. Protarsus with tarsomere I 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as II; I and III similar in length, III equilateral. Metatibial apexwith almond shaped convex ity ringed by 11-13 short, widely separated, spiniform setae. Elytra. Length/width ratio 2.78-3.09; widest at anterior 1/4; anterior margins jointly 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than posterior margin of pronotum; lateral margins sub-parallel after anterior 1/4, more strongly rounded and converging in posterior 1/2. Elytra in lateral view sculpted with a shallow depression at anterior 1/3; posterior declivity angled at nearly 70° to main body axis. Elytral striae defined; punctures visible, separated by 3-5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
their diameter; intervals elevated, with every other interval slightly more raised and with interspersed, sub-erect, white setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Abdominal sterna. Ventrite III elevated and set off from IV along lateral 1/4 of its length. Sternum VII mesally 3/5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide; anterior margin weakly curved.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">Tergum. Pygidium (tergum VIII) sub-conical; medial 1/3 of anterior 2/3 of pygidium less sclerotized.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">Sternum VIII. Anterior laminar edges each incurved forming a 110° angle with lateral margin; less sclerotized medially.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Ovipositor. Coxites slightly sclerotized, in dorsal view 2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as broad.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Spermatheca.?-shaped; collum short, apically with a small, hood-shaped projection angled at 90° to ramus, nearly equal in length to stalk of ramus and contiously aligned with curvature of bulb of ramus; collum sub-contiguous with, and angled at 90° to ramus; ramus basally elongate, forming a stalk, equal in length to collum, bulbous apically, 3 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
thicker than stalk; corpus not swollen, of equal thickness to collum and cornu; cornu elongate, apically, gradually narrowed, strongly recurved in basal 1/4, straight along mesal 1/2, and curved near apical 1/4 such that apexis parallel to collum and corpus.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Figure 46. Habitus of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus rutellirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rutellirostris">Minyomerus rutellirostris</taxonomicName>
[JF2015], female A lateral view B dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Figure 47. Habitus of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus rutellirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rutellirostris">Minyomerus rutellirostris</taxonomicName>
[JF2015], male A lateral view B dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">
Figure 48. Diagnostic features and terminalia of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus rutellirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rutellirostris">Minyomerus rutellirostris</taxonomicName>
[JF2015] A aedeagus, dorsal view B aedeagus, lateral view C labial prementum, ventral view D spermatheca E lamina of sternum VIII.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="88" lastPageNumber="89" pageId="87" pageNumber="88" type="male">
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">Male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="87" pageNumber="88">Similar to female, except where noted. Length 4.03-5.28 mm, width 1.36-1.80 mm, length/width ratio 2.70-3.17. Rostrum length 0.63-0.78 mm, rostrum/pronotum length ratio 0.49-0.55, rostrum length/width ratio 0.90-0.95. Pronotum length/width ratio 0.98-1.05. Profemur/pronotum length ratio 0.82-0.91, protibia/profemur length ratio 0.87-0.97. Elytra length/width ratio 3.01-3.21.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">
<pageBreakToken pageId="88" pageNumber="89" start="start">Rostrum</pageBreakToken>
. Rostrum similar to female, but generally more sculpted. Rostrum dorsally significantly more concave, emarginate, and with margins flared outwardly. Ventrolateral margins expanded laterally, each appearing as a semicircular projection beneath insertion point of scrobe. Scrobe channel less curved than female. Dorso-ventrally thinner than female.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Head. More sculpted than female, and with a more pronounced post-ocular impression. Thorax. More globular than female, but otherwise similar.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Elytra. In lateral view, dorsum flat, declivity significantly sharper, angled at 90° to main body axis. Intervals raised and all of uniform height and setation; lacking any of larger, more erect setae found on female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Abdomen. Sternum VII more broadly arcuate posteriorly, 1/2 as long as wide. Tergum VII with posterior margin straight. Pygidium (tergum VIII) with posterior 1/2 punctate; anterior 1/2 rugose. Posterior 1/4 constricted and depressed, with posterior margin flaring out and slightly projected dorsally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Sternum VIII. Consisting of 2 sub-contiguous, sub-triangular sclerites; posterior margins widely angulate. Laminar alae of spiculum gastrale lateral with lateral margins basally parallel, apically outcurved.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Aedeagus. Length/width ratio 4.36-4.73; lateral margins converging posteriorly, somewhat more strongly converging in region of ostium. Width of pedon in lateral view becoming gradually narrower posteriorly in anterior 1/2, ventral margins in posterior 1/2 becoming straight towards apex, then abruptly curving to meet dorsal margins at a sharp apical point; apexacutely angulate. Flagellum apically with a small conical sclerite.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="88" pageNumber="89" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">
Named in reference to the dilated, concave rostrum of the male, which has the appearance of a shovel; rutellum = shovel, rostrum = beak or nose, rutellirostris = with a shovel-nose; Latin adjective (
<bibRefCitation author="Brown, RW" journalOrPublisher="Smithsonian Institution Press, Washington, DC" pageId="106" pageNumber="107" title="Composition of Scientific Words, Revised Edition." year="1956">Brown 1956</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="88" pageNumber="89" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">
Holotype - female &quot;MEXICO: BAJA 
<normalizedToken originalValue="CALI–">CALI-</normalizedToken>
, FORNIA SUR: 3 km N., San Ignacio at km 77, 5-I-1979, Stop 79-33, Calif. Acad. Sci. Coll./ COLLECTORS:, David Weissman, Robert Love, Vincent Lee, Carolyn Mullinex&quot; (CAS). Paratypes - same label information as female holotype (CAS: 1 female); &quot;La Paz, L. Cal., X-7-41/ Ross &amp; Bohart, Collectors&quot; (CAS: 1 male); &quot;San Pedro, L. Cal. X-7-41/ Ross &amp; Bohart, Collectors/ 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Elissa" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Elissa" order="Coleoptera" pageId="88" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Elissa</taxonomicName>
sp. # 1&quot; (CAS: 3 females, 5 males); &quot;MEX: 12 mi. NW La Paz, Baja Calif. IX-18-67/ J. Chemsak, A. &amp; M. Michelbache, Collectors&quot; (EMEC: 1 female, 1 male); &quot;MEX: Baja Sur, 8 mi. S. Mulege, X-7-1983 BLACKLIGHT, Faulkner &amp; Andrews/ 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="88" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Minyomerus</taxonomicName>
sp.&quot; (CSCA: 2 females); &quot;MEX: Baja Calif. Sur, 34.4 mi. SE. Guerrero, Negro IX-22-1981, F. Andrews &amp; D. Faulkner/ Collected in, Cereal bowl, Pit trap&quot; (CSCA: 1 female); &quot;Purissima, Oct. '73, Baja Calif., WM Mann. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Minyomerus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Minyomerus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="88" pageNumber="89" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Minyomerus</taxonomicName>
sp., DET. A T HOWDEN&quot; (USNM: 1 male).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="88" pageNumber="89" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">This species is found in Baja California Sur (Mexico) (Fig. 52).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="88" pageNumber="89" type="natural history">
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">Natural history.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="88" pageNumber="89">
Host plant unknown, though possibly creosote bush (
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Zygophyllaceae" genus="Larrea" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Larrea tridentata" order="Zygophyllales" pageId="88" pageNumber="89" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="tridentata">Larrea tridentata</taxonomicName>
[DC.] Coville [non-focal]; 
<taxonomicName family="Zygophyllaceae" genus="Tanymecina" lsidName="Tanymecina" pageId="88" pageNumber="89" rank="family">Zygophyllaceae</taxonomicName>
[non-focal]). No host plant associations have been documented.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>