<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280227" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120162" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280227" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="868E73C7285AB79369852D2B47FFDB31" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys deverra Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="676" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="675" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280227" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120162" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280227" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:868E73C7285AB79369852D2B47FFDB31" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/868E73C7285AB79369852D2B47FFDB31" lastPageNumber="676" pageNumber="675">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="675">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155855" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys deverra Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys deverra Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="675" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="deverra">Strumigenys deverra Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="675">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 3.1, HL 0.74, HW 0.56, CI 76, ML 0.30, MI 41, SL 0.44,</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="676">SI 78, PW 0.35, AL 0.80. Characters of chroa-complex. Mandibles almost straight and at full closure parallel except at base. Basal half of proximal preapical mandibular tooth confluent with lamella on inner margin which extends to base of mandible; in full-face view inner margin of lamella more or less straight. Upper scrobe margin a narrow lamella, about half as wide as scape. Maximum diameter of eye about equal to or slightly smaller than maximum width of scape. Hairs on leading edge of scape spatulate. Cephalic dorsum with rows of curved narrow spatulate to spoon-shaped ground-pilosity, the upper scrobe margins fringed with a dense row of hairs which are the same shape and size as those on the dorsum. Cephalic dorsum with 6 standing remiform to clavate hairs arranged in a transverse row of 4 close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated pair. Pronotal humeral hair flagellate. Anterior margin of mesonotum with a pair of stout remiform hairs; posterior mesonotum with 2 additional pairs which are similar in shape but shorter. Propodeum with a pair of narrow remiform hairs immediately anterior of propodeal spines. Ground-pilosity on alitrunk sparse and similar in size and shape as on head. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and more or less flat posteriorly; posterior portion of mesonotum slightly depressed below the anterior margin of propodeum. Humeral angle centrally marginate. Anterior mesonotum with a lamellate extension above a deeply impressed mesothoracic spiracle. Propodeal tooth broadly triangular, lamellate, pointed apically; subtended by a greatly expanded lamella. Alitrunk dorsum densely reticulate-punctate; pleurae mostly smooth and shiny, peripherally reticulate-punctate. Disc of postpetiole conspicuously broader than long, smooth and shiny with superficial longitudinal carinulate sculpture laterally. Ventral and lateral spongiform tissue of petiole and postpetiole moderately developed. Base of first gastral tergite with short costulae radiating on each side of a narrow central clear area. Dorsal surfaces of petiole, postpetiole and gaster with standing remiform to broadly clavate hairs. Colour dull yellowish brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="676">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 2.9 - 3.2, HL 0.71 - 0.79, HW 0.53 - 0.60, CI 74 - 77, ML 0.29 - 0.31, MI 39 - 43, SL 0.42 - 0.46, SI 77 - 81, PW 0.32 - 0.37, AL 0.75 - 0.83 (5 measured). As holotype except that they showed variation in the strength of the development of the lamella on the propodeal declivity.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="676">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 45 km. S Ambalavao, 22 Â° 13 ' S, 47 Â° 0 rE, 785 m., 25. ix. 1993, sifted litter (leaf mold rotten wood), rainforest # 696 (35) - 12 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="676">Paratypes. 1 worker with same data as holotype; 4 workers with same data but coded (18) - 13, (11) - 15 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="676">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: 45 km. S Ambalavao (B. L. Fisher); Res. Andohahela 420 m. (B. L. Fisher); 2.7 km. WNW 302 Â° Ste Luce, 20 m. (B. L Fisher).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="676">Members of these series slightly extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.70 - 0.76, HW 0.52 - 0.57, CI 74 - 77, ML 0.29 - 0.31, MI 41 - 42, SL 0.40 - 0.44, SI 76 - 79 (3 measured).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="676">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155855" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys deverra Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys deverra Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="676" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="deverra">S. deverra</taxonomicName>
is distinguished from other species in the chroa-complex by having a lamellate upper scrobe margin, pronotal humerus with a flagellate hair, and remiform to broadly clavate hairs on petiole, postpetiole and first gastral tergite.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>