<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.572.7823" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c25da304-e8ef-4115-86bb-68b449e397f0" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127857293" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-572-7" ID-ZBK="2322CF201A944A0DBE3FF8212E737812" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:28BA81B1-6B62-4770-9A14-92E4F176A188" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-572-7" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 572" ModsDocTitle="Description of two new species of bat fleas of the genus Araeopsylla (Siphonaptera) from Kenya and Madagascar with notes on miscellaneous bat fleas" checkinTime="1458099780245" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Hastriter, Michael W." docDate="2016" docId="E640337DF7F25DD8BA52CDA64245289A" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 572: 7-21" docOrigin="ZooKeys 572" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.572.7823" docTitle="Araeopsylla smiti Hastriter, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="28BA81B1-6B62-4770-9A14-92E4F176A188" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="13" masterDocId="FFE8FF80E75BFFE8AD58FFC9FF97FF9B" masterDocTitle="Description of two new species of bat fleas of the genus Araeopsylla (Siphonaptera) from Kenya and Madagascar with notes on miscellaneous bat fleas" masterLastPageNumber="21" masterPageNumber="7" pageId="3" pageNumber="10" updateTime="1643492559198" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Description of two new species of bat fleas of the genus Araeopsylla (Siphonaptera) from Kenya and Madagascar with notes on miscellaneous bat fleas</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Hastriter, Michael W.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>572</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>7</mods:start>
<mods:end>21</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.572.7823</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.572.7823</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-572-7</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">2322CF201A944A0DBE3FF8212E737812</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2322CF201A944A0DBE3FF8212E737812</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127857293" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:28BA81B1-6B62-4770-9A14-92E4F176A188" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E640337DF7F25DD8BA52CDA64245289A" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="13" pageId="3" pageNumber="10">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="10" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="10">Taxon classification Animalia Siphonaptera Ischnopsyllidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="10" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="10">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/28BA81B1-6B62-4770-9A14-92E4F176A188" authority="Hastriter" class="Insecta" family="Ischnopsyllidae" genus="Araeopsylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Araeopsylla smiti" order="Siphonaptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="10" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="smiti">Araeopsylla smiti Hastriter</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="3" pageNumber="10">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 8-13
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="11" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="11">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="11" start="start">Diagnosis</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="11">
Distinguished from all other species of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ischnopsyllidae" genus="Araeopsylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Araeopsylla" order="Siphonaptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Araeopsylla</taxonomicName>
by the details of the telomere and distal arm of S-IX. The telomere is acutely pointed at apex and has a broadly rounded lobe along its ventral margin (Fig. 10). The ventral lobe at the base of the distal arm of S-IX that is present in other 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ischnopsyllidae" genus="Araeopsylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Araeopsylla" order="Siphonaptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Araeopsylla</taxonomicName>
species is short, pencil-like and without an expanded lobe at its apex. The ventral lobe of the new species is drastically longer and adorned with an ornate apical lobe (Fig. 11). The eighth sternum, unlike all other species, has a lobe (paired) with tufts of long, coarse setae (Fig. 11).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="11">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="11">
Figures 8-13. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ischnopsyllidae" genus="Araeopsylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Araeopsylla smiti" order="Siphonaptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="smiti">Araeopsylla smiti</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype male (BJH-5634). 8 Head and pronotum 9 Terminal segments, before dissection 10 Basimere, telomere, and eighth tergum 11 Aedeagus, eighth sternum, and distal arm of ninth sternum, (Cr. Scl. = Crescent Sclerite, LL = Lower Lobe, M.D.L. = Median Dorsal Lobe, S.I.T. = Sclerotized Inner Tube) 12 Hind tibia 13 Fourth and fifth segments of distitarsomere 2. Scale: 200 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µ">µ</normalizedToken>
(8-12), 100 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µ">µ</normalizedToken>
(13).
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="13" pageId="4" pageNumber="11" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="11">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="11">
Head. Margin of frons gradually thickened from falx to oral angle. Frontal row of 9-10 minute setae. Area between frons and frontal row of setae with small punctate structures and two placoid pits. Area between frons and frontal row not white or clear, but moderately sclerotized. One placoid pit postad to frontal row of setae near base of genal tooth. Seven to eight minute setae postad to frontal row; group of 6-7 variable sized setae near ventral margin of antennal fossa. Eye fused into darkly sclerotized genal lobe. Genal lobe tapered and broadly rounded at apex; with minute apical tooth. Setae in occipital area rather randomly arranged. Five setulae along dorsal margin of antennal fossa; each as long as other randomly arranged setae in occipital area. Two small setae postad to antennal fossa in position of what is usually 4-5 spiniform setae in other 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ischnopsyllidae" genus="Araeopsylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Araeopsylla" order="Siphonaptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Araeopsylla</taxonomicName>
species. Apex of scape enlarged; three long setae along upper margin and three marginal setae at apex. Pedicel with several fine setae along apical margin; none extending beyond first segment of antenna. Clavus asymmetrical; not extending beyond margin of head. Five segmented labial palpus extended to 1/3 length of fore coxa. Proximal segment of five segmented labial palpus rather bulbous in form (Fig. 8).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="11">Thorax. Pronotum with 26 ctenidia; each acutely pointed and only slightly shorter than length of pronotum. Setae on pronotum randomly arranged. Two dorsal and two ventral pseudosetae under mesonotal collar. Metanotum with three rows of setae; two marginal short, stout spinelets at dorsal apex of sclerite. Pleural rod nearly centrally attached to sclerotic dome. Ventral portion of metasternum lobed downward between coxae. Pleural arch absent. Metepisternum with squamulum and one long seta at dorsal margin. Metepimeron with nine setae; spiracle large and round.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="12">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="12" start="start">Legs</pageBreakToken>
. Fore coxa with ~40 lateral setae. Fore femur with 2 minute setae on mesal surface; none on lateral surface. Mesal surface of mesotibia with single row of five setae; multiple setae on lateral surface. Mesal surface of metatibia with single row of seven setae; multiple setae on lateral surface. Meso- and metatibiae with five well defined notches; two setae at each. Multiple single setae interspersed along margins between defined notches. Each tarsal segment longer than adjacent more distal segments on meso- and metatarsi. Five lateral plantar bristles on all distitarsomeres; first pair displaces between second pair. Two pre-apical plantar bristles on each distitarsomere (Figs 12-13).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="12">
Unmodified abdominal segments. Single spinelet on apex of T-I. Globular sclerotized incrassation at base of each terga (
<normalizedToken originalValue="T-I–VII">T-I-VII</normalizedToken>
). Pigmented banding extends slightly ventrally from each incrassation. Each terga with single uninterrupted row of setae; one seta below level of each round spiracle. Single long antesensilial bristle. Ventral margin of each sternite is heavily sclerotized. Sternites 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–III">II-III</normalizedToken>
with one minute seta in row; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="S-IV–VI">S-IV-VI</normalizedToken>
with two minute setae in each row.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="13">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="13" start="start">Modified</pageBreakToken>
abdominal segments. Basimere without lobes or sinuses. Telomere with large lobe on lower ventral margin; a few fine setae along ventral margin of telomere above lobe. Tergum VIII encompassing basimere and telomere with all setae restricted to dorsal half of sclerite (Fig. 10). Sternum VIII with large lobe bearing tuft of long coarse setae. Crescent sclerite of aedeagus long, thin, and inverted so tectum is directed cephalad. Sclerotized inner tube straight, somewhat broad. Crochet with prominent truncate upper lobe and sharp ventral lobe. Distal arm of S-IX with sigmoid lobe similar to many bat species, but what is usually a small pencil-like lobe in other species, this lobe is greatly extended and expanded at its apex. The expansion bears two small setae at base of expansion, two setae on apico-dorsal surface, and one seta on ventral margin of expansion. A group of very fine hairs adorns the base of the ventral lobe of the distal arm of S-IX (Figs 9-11).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="13" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="13">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="13">
Mr. F.G.A.M. Smit, during his long tenure at the British Museum, London was without doubt, a major contributor to our knowledge of the global flea fauna. It is thus fitting to name this flea 
<taxonomicName lsidName="smiti" pageId="6" pageNumber="13" rank="species" species="smiti">smiti</taxonomicName>
in his honor as a noun in apposition.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="13" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="13">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="13">
This is the first record of the genus 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ischnopsyllidae" genus="Araeopsylla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Araeopsylla" order="Siphonaptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="13" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Araeopsylla</taxonomicName>
occurring in Kenya, although the genus has been recorded throughout tropical Africa.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="13" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="13">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="13">
Holotype ♂, Kenya, Rift Valley, Maji Moto, 4.8 km W of Lake Harrington (
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-0.26666668">00°16'00&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="3.101111">03°6'04 &quot;E</geoCoordinate>
), 
<taxonomicName class="Mammalia" family="Molossidae" genus="Chaerephon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Chaerephon bivittatus" order="Chiroptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="13" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="bivittatus">Chaerephon bivittatus</taxonomicName>
(USNM Host 437-287), 25 VIII 1968, BJH-5634.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>