<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.68.28403" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5366a031-3ce6-4ee8-9dfd-9cee1533f7ca" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154472905" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1314-2607--19" ID-ZBK="A22026337406409393A116D485327A08" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="1314-2607--19" ModsDocOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research " ModsDocTitle="A new species of Platygaster (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea) from India with an unusual antenna" checkinTime="1553125412899" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Popovici, Ovidiu Alin, Veenakumari, Kamalanathan &amp; Mitroiu, Mircea-Dan" docDate="2019" docId="5A639C2FDD13F75262C612D2F1C6695D" docLanguage="en" docName="JourHymenoptRes 68: 19-28" docOrigin="Journal of Hymenoptera Research 68" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.68.28403" docTitle="Platygaster harpagoceras Popovici &amp; Veenakumari" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageNumber="19" masterDocId="A858CD3CFFADFF91083CF4430F56FFFB" masterDocTitle="A new species of Platygaster (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea) from India with an unusual antenna" masterLastPageNumber="28" masterPageNumber="19" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" updateTime="1643460489834" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of Platygaster (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea) from India with an unusual antenna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Popovici, Ovidiu Alin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Veenakumari, Kamalanathan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Mitroiu, Mircea-Dan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of Hymenoptera Research</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>68</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>19</mods:start>
<mods:end>28</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.68.28403</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.68.28403</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1314-2607--19</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">A22026337406409393A116D485327A08</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">A22026337406409393A116D485327A08</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="154472905" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:5A639C2FDD13F75262C612D2F1C6695D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5A639C2FDD13F75262C612D2F1C6695D" lastPageNumber="19" pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="19" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
<taxonomicName authority="Popovici &amp; Veenakumari" class="Insecta" family="Platygastroidea" genus="Platygaster" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platygaster harpagoceras" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="harpagoceras">Platygaster harpagoceras Popovici &amp; Veenakumari</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="19" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Female (Figs 1, 3, 8-10). Colour (Figs 3, 8): Head, mesosoma, and metasoma dark brown with uneven patches of black, posterior tergites paler than anterior tergites; black band above occipital carina; legs and tegula yellowish brown; A1-A4 yellowish brown, A5-A6 slightly darker than preceding antennomeres, A7-A9 blackish brown; mandibles yellowish brown. The lighter colour of the specimens pictured in Figs 1 and 2, compared with the specimen in Figs 3 and 8, is attributed to the older age of these specimens.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Head. Shape of head in dorsal view: subellipsoidal, 1.8-1.9 times as wide as long; occipital carina: present, not crenulate, weak; sculpture of posterior vertex: coriaceous-imbricate, transversally arranged; pilosity of posterior vertex: sparse, short setae, generally in two transverse rows; sculpture of temple: coriaceous-imbricate; hyperoccipital carina: absent; sculpture of interocellar area: coriaceous-imbricate to reticulate; ratio OOL/OD: OOL 2.3-2.5 times as long as OD; OOL/POL/LOL: 1:2:1; sculpture of frons: reticulate, but above toruli similar to sculpture of posterior vertex; IOS/EH: IOS longer than EH (IOS 1.8-1.9 times as long as EH); setation of eyes: short, with fine scattered hairs (visible at 70 X magnification); interantennal process: not prominent, concave; width of interantennal process: about equal to diameter of torulus; mandible: bidentate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Antenna (Figs 4, 5). Number of female antennomeres: 9; number of clavomeres: 4; abrupt clava: absent; compact clava: absent; sensillar formula (A9-A6): 1:1:1:1; A6-A8: distinctly projecting anteroventrally, resembling a tooth; A9: distinctly acuminate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Dorsal mesosoma (Figs 1, 3, 9). Pronotum: distinctly visible; pronotal shoulders: not enlarged; epomial carina: well developed; cervical pronotal area: weakly concave; setation of cervical pronotal area: absent; sculpture of mesoscutum: finely imbricate-coriaceous; sculpture of mesoscutellum: reticulate; antero-admedian line: absent; parapsidal line: absent; notauli: abbreviate, superficial, convergent posteriorly; mid lobe on posterior margin of mesoscutum: extending onto mesoscutellum; transaxillar and axillular carinae: fused, the resulting carina clearly visible; posterior mesoscutellar rim: not distinct; metanotum: narrow, smooth; metascutellum: not visible dorsally, covered by mesoscutellum; setation of propodeum: long, dense laterally, absent medially; lateral propodeal carinae: distinct, parallel; metasomal depression: narrow; propodeal spiracle: clearly visible.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Lateral mesosoma (Figs 8, 10). Transverse pronotal sulcus: weak, glabrous; lateral propleural area: weakly convex; sculpture of lateral propleural area: uniform imbricate-coriaceous; setation of lateral propleural area: some sparse setae on the dorsal half; transaxillar carina, in lateral view: with numerous longitudinal striae; mesopleural depression: weakly indicated; transepisternal line: weakly indicated; transepisternal line: almost transverse, deep, and sharply incised, nearly parallel with mesopleural carina; sculpture of mesopleuron: absent, except for sparse striae dorsally; setation of mesopleuron: absent; sculpture of metapleuron: absent; setation of metapleuron: relatively dense, present throughout; metapleural carina: prominent, well developed; metapleural pit: not visible; metapleural sulcus: not visible.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Fore wing (Fig. 7).Venation: absent; colour of fore wing: faintly infuscate; setation of fore wing: short, sparse microtrichia; fore wing length/width ratio: 2.6 times as long as wide; marginal fringe of fore wing: absent. Hind wing (Fig. 7).Venation: absent; colour of hind wing: hardly infuscated; number of hamuli: 2; setation of hind wing: rare, sparse microtrichia; hind wing length/width ratio: 4.3-4.4 times as long as wide; marginal fringe of hind wing: short, almost 0.2 times as long as hind wing width.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
Figures 1-8. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Platygaster" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platygaster harpagoceras" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="harpagoceras">Platygaster harpagoceras</taxonomicName>
: 1 Holotype female (dorsal) stored in HNHM (Budapest) 2 Paratype male (dorsal) stored in HNHM (Budapest) 3 Paratype female (dorsal), stored in NBAIR (Bengaluru) 4 Female antenna-light microscopy 5 Female antenna (SEM) 6 Male antenna-light microscopy 7 Fore and hind wing 8 Paratype female (lateral), stored in NBAIR (Bengaluru).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Metasoma. Length of metasoma: shorter than head and mesosoma combined; shape of metasoma in lateral view: convex dorsally; number of visible tergites: 6; shape of T1: trapezoidal; anterior pits of T1: clearly visible; sculpture of T1: medially costate, costae longer laterally; setation of T1: sparse laterally, absent on medial sculptured area; the largest tergite: T2; anterior pits of T2: present; setation of T2: few setae on lateral T2; sculpture of anterior T2: smooth between anterior pits, laterally longitudinally striate); length of striae on T2: surpassing the middle of T2; sculpture of T3-T6: absent; setation of T3-T5: sparse (~ 12-14 setae), in a single transverse row; laterotergites: present, distinct; setation of S1: present throughout; setation of S2: absent; setation of S3-S6: sparse to absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Male (Fig. 2): similar to female, differing in the structure of antenna (Fig. 6), with A4 longer than A3, A5-A8 having almost the same shape and size, and metasoma consisting of 7 visible tergites with a rounded apex.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="19" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
In 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Platygaster" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platygaster" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Platygaster</taxonomicName>
, a 9-merous antenna is known only from 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. harpagoceras" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" rank="species" species="harpagoceras">P. harpagoceras</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. novemarticulata" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" rank="species" species="novemarticulata">P. novemarticulata</taxonomicName>
Buhl, 2009. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Platygaster" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platygaster harpagoceras" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="harpagoceras">Platygaster harpagoceras</taxonomicName>
can be distinguished by the acuminate A9, A6-A8 transverse, A6-A8 with anteroventral projection, frons reticulate, and longitudinal striae on T2 surpassing the middle of T2.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="19" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
The epithet &quot; 
<taxonomicName genus="Platygastroidea" lsidName="Platygastroidea harpagoceras" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" rank="species" species="harpagoceras">harpagoceras</taxonomicName>
&quot; given to this species refers to the characteristic antenna (gr. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“harpagos”">&quot;harpagos&quot;</normalizedToken>
- hook, and gr. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“kéras”">&quot;keras&quot;</normalizedToken>
- horn).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="19" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
Holotype: 1 female, &quot;India, Orissa Jajpur-Keonjahr Dists., Daitari, 28.xii.1966, leg. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Topál”">Topal&quot;</normalizedToken>
(Deposited in HNHM); Paratypes: 1 male and 1 female the same data as the holotype (HNHM); 1 female, India, Tamil Nadu, Kanyakumari, Manalodai, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="11.2522">11.25220°N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="78.6968">78.69680°E</geoCoordinate>
, yellow pan trap, 13.v.2013, leg. A. Rameshkumar (NBAIR).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="19">
Figures 9, 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Platygaster" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Platygaster harpagoceras" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="19" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="harpagoceras">Platygaster harpagoceras</taxonomicName>
, female (SEM): 9 Habitus, dorsal 10 Habitus, lateral.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>