<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5631900" ID-GBIF-Dataset="a62484fc-dc73-4df6-b2ec-483c9f2973fd" ID-GBIF-Taxon="117196161" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5631900" ID-ZooBank="613D14BD-01D3-4649-A30F-8DF276CF3B23" checkinTime="1457456102581" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Papáč, Vladimír, Lukić, Marko &amp; Kováč, Ľubomír" docDate="2016" docId="D512281BFFC56843D0D8FF56FE0EF9E3" docLanguage="en" docName="15547-5069-1-PB.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 4088 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@a49bdf" docStyleName="zootaxa.2013.journal_article" docTitle="Neelus murinus Folsom, 1896 sensu Schneider" docType="treatment" docVersion="11" lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="70" masterDocId="292B5063FFD76850D04FFF8DFFDAFFEB" masterDocTitle="Genus Neelus Folsom, 1896 (Hexapoda, Collembola) reveals its diversity in cave habitats: two new species from Croatia" pageId="18" pageNumber="69" updateTime="1635667035849" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Genus Neelus Folsom, 1896 (Hexapoda, Collembola) reveals its diversity in cave habitats: two new species from Croatia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Papáč, Vladimír</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lukić, Marko</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kováč, Ľubomír</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>4088</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal volume</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.4088.1.2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">a62484fc-dc73-4df6-b2ec-483c9f2973fd</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">255700</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">613D14BD-01D3-4649-A30F-8DF276CF3B23</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5631900" ID-GBIF-Taxon="117196161" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5631900" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:D512281BFFC56843D0D8FF56FE0EF9E3" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D512281BFFC56843D0D8FF56FE0EF9E3" lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="70" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">
<subSubSection pageId="18" pageNumber="69" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,847,219,279]" box="[151,847,219,246]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,847,219,246]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="18" pageNumber="69" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,847,219,246]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">
<taxonomicName authority="Folsom, 1896 sensu Schneider" authorityName="Folsom, 1896 sensu Schneider" box="[151,723,219,246]" class="Entognatha" family="Neelidae" genus="Neelus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Collembola" pageId="18" pageNumber="69" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="murinus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,343,219,245]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Neelus murinus</emphasis>
Folsom, 1896 sensu Schneider
</taxonomicName>
(in press)
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,847,219,279]" box="[151,232,254,279]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Table 4</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">
Revision of 
<taxonomicName box="[296,372,324,349]" class="Entognatha" family="Neelidae" genus="Neelus" kingdom="Animalia" order="Collembola" pageId="18" pageNumber="69" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[296,372,324,349]" italics="true" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Neelus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
specimens from Croatia revealed that this species inhabits many caves across the country. Individuals have many tertiary rods on Th. III and abdomen, 3+3 posterior manubrial chaetae (1+1 proximal and 2+2 distal) and almost smooth a1 labral chaetae (with 1 small basal tooth).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="70" pageId="18" pageNumber="69" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,437,431,456]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Material examined.</emphasis>
Papuk, Slatinski Drenovac, Jarcoder, Smrečna špilja Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2907), 23.ix.2010, leg. A. Komerički.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" box="[199,1411,503,528]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Samobor, Otruševac, Stara grgosova špilja Cave, 4 ex. on slides (No. CLL 4466), 26.xi.2014, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" box="[199,1322,540,565]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Kamanje, Obrež, Hrenov grič Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 1940), 21.iii.2009, leg. H. Cvitanović.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Ogulin–Plaški karst plateau, Bosiljevo, Dani, Dobra canyon, Danetska pećina Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1772), 12.v.2009, leg. J. Bedek. Ogulin, Trošmarija, Dobra canyon, Izvor špilja kod Trošmarije Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1779), 10.v.2009, leg. A. Kirin. Generalski Stol, Pećani, Dobra canyon, Pećina pod Pećanima Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1724), 09.v.2009, leg. J. Bedek; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1727), 13.v.2009, leg. M. Lukić. Bosiljevo, Podumol, Dobra canyon, Špilja kod Podumolskog mlina Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1678), 14.v.2009, leg. M. Lukić. Generalski Stol, Podjakšići, Dobra canyon, Špilja u kanjonu Dobre ispod Podjakšića Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1683), 13.v.2009, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Rijeka, Kostrena, Rožmanići, Humčine, Bunetova jama Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2157), 26.iv.2009, leg. M. Lukić. Kostrena, Špilja u uvali Predpeć Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 4491), 23.i.2011, leg. M. Lukić. Kostrena, Špilja u uvali Svežanj Cave, 3 ex. on slides (No. CLL 776), 06.iv.2008, leg. J. Bedek. Kostrena, Urinjska špilja Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 2167), 29.iv.2009, leg. H. Cvitanović; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2169), 29.iv.2009, leg. M. Lukić; 5 ex. on slides (No. CLL 3114), 05.vi.2010, leg. A. Komerički; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3116), 05.vi.2010, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Ćićarija, Lupoglav, Semići, Podbrus, Jama pod Križ Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2042), 27.vi.2009, leg. M. Lukić; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2215), 04.vi.2010, leg. M. Lukić. Veprinac, Brložnik, Pećina pod Brložnikom Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1966), 13.ix.2008, leg. P. Bregović. Lupoglav, Brgudac, Stržen, Pećina pod Stržen Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2032), 27.vi.2009, leg. P. Bregović. Buzet, Rakitovec, Radota jama Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3170), 27.xi.2010, leg. J. Bedek.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Učka, Vela draga, Boljun, Pikulići, Jama iznad Vranjske drage Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2497), 02.vi.2010, leg. A. Kirin. Mala Učka, Jama kod crvenog gloga Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 426), 07.xi.2006, leg. P. Rade. Veprinac, Menderi, Jama kod potoka Banine 3 Cave, 4 ex. on slides (No. CLL 695), 17.ix.2007, leg. J. Bedek; 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 700), 05.iv.2008, leg. J. Bedek. Veprinac, Menderi, Lovranski Lazići, Jama na Lovranskim Lazićima Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 423), 04.xi.2006, leg. M. Lukić. Veprinac, Kaverna u tunelu Učka Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 447), 04.x.2006, leg. M. Pavlek. Učka, Mala Učka, Podmaj, Petrc, Petrčeva jama Cave, 3 ex. on slides (No. CLL 753), 17.ix.2007, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Pula, Premantura, Špilja na Gradini kod Premanture Cave, 13 ex. on slides (No. CLL 4009), 05.iii.2011, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Cerovlje, Gologorica, Jaklići, Piskovica špilja Cave, 8 ex. on slides (No. CLL 3142), 03.iii.2011, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" box="[199,1382,1620,1645]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Gračac, Kesići, Donja Cerovačka špilja Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2664), 03.viii.2006, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Velebit, Starigrad Paklenica, Paklenica, Borova kosa, Jama iza Borove kose Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1603), 27.ix.2008, leg. L. Đud. Starigrad Paklenica, Paklenica, Manita peć Cave, 2 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3958), middle part of the Cave, 23.x.2012, leg. M. Lukić; 4 ex. on slides (No. CLL 3959), extraction with Berlese funnel, entrance part of the Cave, 20.xii.2012, leg. M. Lukić; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3966), middle part of the Cave, 20.xii.2012, leg. M. Lukić. Starigrad Paklenica, Seline, Markova špilja Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 4492), 19.xii.2012, leg. M. Lukić. Obrovac, Gornji Čabrići, Plitki dolovi, Plitka peć Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3494), 29.ix.2010, leg. P. Bregović. Obrovac, Gornji Čabrići, Špilja Šupljača Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3437), 28.ix.2010, leg. N. Raguž &amp; M. Hodžić. Obrovac, Gronji Čabrići, Velika pećina Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 2763), 01.viii.2006, leg. H. Bilandžija.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="18.[151,1437,324,2005]" lastBlockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" lastPageId="19" lastPageNumber="70" pageId="18" pageNumber="69">Knin, Kistanje, Verovići, Jama kod zaskoka Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2415), 06.v.2010, leg. A. Kirin; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2416), 06.v.2010, leg. J. Bedek. Roški slap, Liševica, Jama na Bibinovcu Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3660), 22.x.2012, leg. J. Bedek; 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 3667), 15.xii.2012, leg. M. Pavlek. Roški slap, Bogatići, Jama na Selinama Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3656), 22.x.2012, leg. M. Lukić. Drniš, Ključ, Čikola canyon, Torak, Jama nasuprot Torka Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2864), 09.x.2010, leg. A. Kirin. Oklaj, Puljane, Krka canyon, Jazinka Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2846), 10.x.2010, leg. M. Lukić; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3727), 16.xii.2012, leg. M. Lukić. Oklaj, Ljubotić, Makeljina jama Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 4154), 21.v.2013, leg. T. Čuković. Oklaj, Miljacka 1 Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2832), 08.x.2010, leg. M. Lukić. Oklaj, Miljacka 2 Cave, 4 ex. on slides (No. CLL 2381), 04.v.2010, leg. A. Kirin; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2826), 08.x.2010, leg. A. Kirin; 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 3742), 18.x.2012, leg. A. Kirin; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3750), 18.x.2012, leg. M. Lukić &amp; J. Bedek. Oklaj, Miljevački Bogatići, Krka canyon, Oziđana pećina Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2420), 06.v.2010, leg. M. Lukić. Kistanje, Burze, Krka canyon, Sedrena špilja s jamskim ulazom Cave, 2 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3673), 14.xii.2012, leg. A. Komerički.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Šibenik, Konjevrate, G. Krnići, Punčka draga, Stara jametina Cave, 7 ex. on slides (No. CLL 2366), 07.v.2010, leg. M. Lukić; 22 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2372), 07.v.2010, leg. J. Bedek; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2380), 07.v.2010, leg. K. Miculinić; 3 ex. on slides (No. CLL 3772), 15.xii.2012, leg. M. Lukić. Skradin, Krka canyon, Špilja u skradinskom buku Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 2425), 07.v.2010, leg. A. Komerički.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Svilaja, Lemeš, Dvostruka jama Lemeš 1 Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 3783), 17.xii.2012, leg. J. Bedek; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3787), 17.xii.2012, leg. K. Miculinić. Lemeš, Dvostruka jama Lemeš 2 Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3791), 17.xii.2012, leg. K. Miculinić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Sinj, Bitelić, Rumin, Crvenkuša - Tamnica - Suhi Rumin Cave system, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 1626), 28.vii.2007, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Biokovo, Gornja Brela, Jamina Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 147), 22.xi.2005, leg. J. Bedek; 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 156), 26.x.2006, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" box="[199,1411,980,1005]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Brač island, Pučišća, Jama za Mahrincem Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3309), 12.iii.2011, leg. T. Čuković.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Korčula island, Lumbarda, Gudavica špilja Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3364), 17.iii.2010, leg. L. Đud. Račišće, Samograd Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 2994), 30.ix.2007, leg. P. Bregović.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Mljet island, Ropa, Crna klada, Bezdan Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 839), 01.v.2008, leg. J. Bedek. Babino polje, Jama za Sv. Ilijom Cave, 3 ex. on slides (No. CLL 834), 02.v.2008, leg. M. Lukić. Ropa, Grabova glava, Male ponte jama Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 540), 09.iv.2007, leg. M. Pavlek; 4 ex. on slides (No. CLL 824), 27.iv.2008, leg. M. Lukić. Babino polje, Dračevac, Movrica špilja Cave, 1 ex. on slides (No. CLL 877), 28.iv.2008, leg. M. Lukić.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" box="[199,1137,1268,1293]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Metković, Glušci, Čekrk jama Cave, 2 ex. on slides, 24.ix.2014, leg. H. Cvitanović.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="19.[151,1437,151,1544]" pageId="19" pageNumber="70">Dubrovnik, Osojnik, Jama u Zabirađu Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 4490), 02.xi.2008, leg. J. Bedek. Riđica, Zadubravica, Zadubravica Cave, 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 4418), 03.xi.2008, leg. M. Lukić, 1 ex. on slide, 24.viii.2014, leg. G. Rnjak. Osojnik, Močiljska špilja Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 910), 01.xi.2008, leg. D. Župan; 2 ex. on slides (No. CLL 2238), 28.iv.2010, leg. J. Bedek; 2 ex. on slides, (No. CLL 2234), 28.iv.2010, leg. M. Lukić. Komolac, Sumporača mala Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 946), 29.iii.2008, leg. M. Lukić. Cavtat, Šipun Cave, 1 ex. on slide (No. CLL 3084), 06.vi.2011, leg. J. Bedek. Konavle, Gruda, Kaverna 183 Cave, 1 ex. on slide, 22.IX.2014, leg. N. Hanzek.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>