<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284664" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5f96e565-1778-4154-8f67-81830690657d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135911" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284664" ModsDocID="6751" checkinTime="1243377290804" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Brown, W. L." docDate="1975" docId="DE7AE43240F6C72914FDF41270E6BDAA" docLanguage="en" docName="6751" docOrigin="Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station 15" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf" docTitle="Cerapachys kodecorum Brown, 1975, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="71" masterDocId="5EF94453F8BE2CD657C7B1F34B08FD04" masterDocTitle="Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini." masterLastPageNumber="115" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="70" updateTime="1645811814098" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Brown, W. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1975</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>15</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>115</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6751</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">45422C7B-83F2-4F5A-9EE4-74C51F2C2BFE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284664" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135911" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284664" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:DE7AE43240F6C72914FDF41270E6BDAA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DE7AE43240F6C72914FDF41270E6BDAA" lastPageNumber="71" pageNumber="70">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="70">
[58] 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27927" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys kodecorum Brown" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys kodecorum Brown" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="70" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kodecorum">Cerapachys kodecorum</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="70">(Figs. 74 - 78)</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Holotype worker: TL 4.3, HL 0.85, HW 0.76 (CI 89; HL includes frontal lobes, and HW is taken just behind eyes), ML 0.15, scape L 0.51, greatest diameter of eye 0.20, WL 1.13, petiolar node L 0.42, W 0.51, postpetiole L 0.52, W 0.63 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Paratype workers (19 from type nest series) range downward slightly from the size of the holotype; smallest worker TL 3.7, HL 0.79, HW 0.70 (CI 89), ML 0.12, scape L 0.47, greatest diameter of eye 0.19, WL 1.00 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">General habitus, sculpture, and a number of particular characters are shown reasonably well in figs. 74 - 78, so I shall restrict my description to emphasizing the distinctive features and to those traits not well shown in the figures. The descriptive remarks apply to the whole type series.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="71" pageNumber="70">Head broad, seen in full-face view posterior margin border straight to feebly convex, usually feebly concave in the middle, posterior border meeting convex sides at definite but obtuse angles. Eyes prominent, their middles situated slightly in front of midlength of head. Just anterior to each eye is a shallow but prominent indentation or scrobe running across the cranium to become subconfluent with its opposite mate at the midline, and together they form an arcuate sulcus (fig. 78) bounded in front by a sharp, irregular, semicircular carina that connects the flanking cheek carinae (the carina does not show up well in fig. 78) and separates the anterodorsal part of the head, bearing frontal carinae and lobes and antennal insertions, from the main part of the vertex. Frontal lobes sharply obliquely raised, close together but not touching; extending posteriad a short way as fine carinae, these also close together, subparallel, but separate. Descending anterior face of clypeus with an obscure median carina that appears as a minute tooth or tubercle in full-face view; translucent free apron of clypeus narrow, gently convex. Mandibles triangular, strongly curved ventrad, their basal margins curving into apical margins; the latter indistinctly denticulate (crenulate), smooth and shining, with spaced, coarse punctures. Anterior corners of head formed by prominent, subrectangular cheek carinae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Antennae unusually strongly incrassate, especially across apex of scape (maximum width in holotype 0.23 mm; see fig. 78) and apical segment of funiculus (L 0.40, W 0.22 mm in holotype); 11 segments total in antennae, the 3 ring segments following the pedicel (III, IV and V from base of antenna) extremely short; all segments except scape and apical segment wider than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Trunk well shown in figs. 74 - 76; transverse anterior pronotal margin complete, sharp, raised; propodeal declivity also bounded by a distinct continuous margin. Petiole with a distinct anterodorsal margin. Subpetiolar process deep, narrowly rounded and laterally compressed, with a circular fovea in the middle.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Sculpture mostly well shown in the figures. Narrow interfoveolar interspaces of dorsum of head and trunk smooth and shining, also broad, smooth, and shining areas on dorsum of trunk in middle of mesonotum and propodeum, and on sides of trunk centered on mesopleura (figs. 74, 76). Propodeal declivity nearly smooth, shining.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Petiole and postpetiole densely and fairly coarsely foveolate, prevailingly subopaque both above and below. Base of first gastric (IV abdominal) segment a little less coarsely, but still densely, foveolate at base, the foveolae becoming more spaced, and the intervals broad, smooth, and shining posteriad. Pygidium densely punctate on sides, but smooth and shining on the midline. Legs finely and superficially punctulate, weakly shining. Clypeus mostly smooth; area just in front of arched carina of face nearly smooth, but crossed by sparse fine rugulae, behind antennal sockets.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Pilosity abundant, consisting of fine, obliquely erect hairs 0.10 - 0.20 mm long, sparse on legs and antennae, and shorter suberect to reclinate hairs, densest on petiole and postpetiole, but not forming a thick pubescence there. Legs with fairly abundant, fine, appressed pubescence, not very well shown in the figures.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Color dark reddish brown, legs lighter and more reddish.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Of the paratypes, one is abnormal, with head markedly flatter and broader than usual, with an asymmetrical impression in the left ventrolateral margin; this specimen has only 7 funicular segments on the left side and 6 on the right. It is probably the result of damage to the growing larva or pupa.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="71">Holotype (MCZ) and paratypes from a single nest (No. B- 43) in a hollow, rotten stick embedded in leaf litter of mature lowland rain forest 20 - 25 km W of Batulitjin, SE Kalimantan (Borneo), at the end of June 1972 (W. L. Brown, Jr.). This locality is within the timber tract then being worked by the Korea Development Company (Kodeco), and the new species is named for my gracious Korean hosts, who made possible an exciting week of collecting in the forest.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">
Paratypes are deposited in MCZ, BMNH — London, ANIC — Canberra, and Cornell University Insect Collection, Ithaca, New York. This species is a rather typical 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2431" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys Smith" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys Smith" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Cerapachys</taxonomicName>
, resembling members of the 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27896" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys dohertyi Emery" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys dohertyi Emery" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="dohertyi">dohertyi</taxonomicName>
group, but it may be distinguished from all known members of this group by means of its unusually thick antennae, with only 11 segments total and extremely short ring segments, and by the broad facial scrobal impressions to receive the retracted antennae in part (fig. 78). 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27927" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys kodecorum Brown" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys kodecorum Brown" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="kodecorum">C. kodecorum</taxonomicName>
is easily told from other 11 - segmented Indo-Australian 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:2431" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys Smith" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys Smith" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Cerapachys</taxonomicName>
by its relatively large eyes and coarse, partly open sculpture.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="71">No obvious queen, ergatoid or otherwise, was found in colony B- 43, and the male remains unknown. The apparantly pathological individual with reduced antennal segment numbers is interesting in pointing up how unstable the segment count, previously held to be a subgeneric character, can occasionally be even in a single nest series.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="71">
[59] C 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27908" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys fossulatus Forel" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys fossulatus Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fossulatus">fossulatus</taxonomicName>
is bicolored like 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27864" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys aitkenii Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="71" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="aitkeni">C. aitkeni</taxonomicName>
, but is much larger and has a petiolar node longer than broad; the postpetiole is also just about as long as broad. The 11 - merous antennae are of course diagnostic.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>