<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.606.9656" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d2c13afd-d2ea-40eb-a3dc-87ed3020dfb1" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127892084" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-606-25" ID-ZBK="27861105EE114CE38A40E29A11B068AA" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C8E5EB50-4F3D-4071-9DE7-BFB816F31CE2" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-606-25" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 606" ModsDocTitle="Revision of the genus Paralipsis Foerster, 1863 (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), with the description of two new species" checkinTime="1469161638554" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="van Achterberg, Cornelis &amp; Carron, Nilo F. Ortiz de Zugasti" docDate="2016" docId="90F7B5FAE558CB95F6AE031BEB72B763" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 606: 25-39" docOrigin="ZooKeys 606" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.606.9656" docTitle="Paralipsis planus van Achterberg, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="C8E5EB50-4F3D-4071-9DE7-BFB816F31CE2" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="30" masterDocId="FFE6FFB469743C5B6477496E6F05FFD6" masterDocTitle="Revision of the genus Paralipsis Foerster, 1863 (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), with the description of two new species" masterLastPageNumber="39" masterPageNumber="25" pageId="4" pageNumber="29" updateTime="1643626375456" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision of the genus Paralipsis Foerster, 1863 (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), with the description of two new species</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>van Achterberg, Cornelis</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Carron, Nilo F. Ortiz de Zugasti</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>606</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>25</mods:start>
<mods:end>39</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.606.9656</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.606.9656</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-606-25</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">27861105EE114CE38A40E29A11B068AA</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">27861105EE114CE38A40E29A11B068AA</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127892084" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C8E5EB50-4F3D-4071-9DE7-BFB816F31CE2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/90F7B5FAE558CB95F6AE031BEB72B763" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="30" pageId="4" pageNumber="29">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="29" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">Taxon classification Animalia Hymenoptera Braconidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="29" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/C8E5EB50-4F3D-4071-9DE7-BFB816F31CE2" authority="van Achterberg" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Paralipsis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paralipsis planus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="planus">Paralipsis planus van Achterberg</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="4" pageNumber="29">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 16-20
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="29" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">Material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">Holotype, ♀ (RMNH), &quot;Nederland: Wijster (Dr.), opposite Biol. Stat., 28.vii.-14.viii.1972, C. v. Achterberg&quot;.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="29" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">
Similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Paralipsis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paralipsis enervis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="enervis">Paralipsis enervis</taxonomicName>
(Nees, 1834), but differs by the slenderer fore tarsus, the partly widened hind tibia and femur (Fig. 16) and the scapus distinctly widened dorsally in lateral view (vase-shaped: Fig. 17). Close to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Paralipsis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paralipsis tibiator" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tibiator">Paralipsis tibiator</taxonomicName>
sp. n., but 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Paralipsis" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Paralipsis planus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="29" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="planus">Paralipsis planus</taxonomicName>
has the vertex and mesoscutum shiny and with sparse short pubescence between long setae, the first tergite flat and shiny, its maximum width at level of spiracles of ♀ 0.7 times distance between spiracle and apex of tergite (Fig. 19), the mesopleuron shiny, the apical antennal segments with long erect setae (Figs 17, 20), the fore basitarsus rather robust, the fifth antennal segment with few rhinaria and the hind basitarsus robust (Fig. 16).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">Holotype, ♀, length of fore wing 2.0 mm, and of body 2.1 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="30" pageId="4" pageNumber="29" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="29">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="30" pageId="4" pageNumber="29">
Head. Head 1.6 times wider than long medially in dorsal view and roundly narrowed behind eyes; antenna with 15 (left) or 16 (right) segments and 0.9 times as long as body, segments long erect setae (Figs 17, 20), third segment dull and 1.1 times as long as fourth segment, thirdfourth segments without rhinaria and widened apically and fifth segments with few rhinaria, third, fourth and penultimate (= 14th) segments 2.2, 1.8 and 1.4 times as long as wide, respectively; maxillary and labial palpi with 2 and 1 segments, respectively; length of maxillary palp 0.2 times height of head; distance between anterior tentorial pits 1.4 times distance between pit and eye; eye with rather long setae; face mainly smooth, convex ventrally and laterally rather sparsely setose, with setae directed downwards; clypeus distinctly convex and smooth, with few erect setae; frons nearly flat (except superficial impression in front of anterior ocellus), without median groove, shiny, punctulate and rather densely setose; vertex with sparse short pubescence between sparse long setae and temple roundly narrowed 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="30" start="start">posteriorly</pageBreakToken>
and shiny; eye 0.9 times as long as temple in dorsal view; OOL:diameter of posterior ocellus:POL = 12:3:11; stemmaticum distinctly wider posteriorly than laterally; length of malar space 1.7 times basal width of mandible, malar depression absent.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Mesosoma. Length of mesosoma 1.3 times as long as high; pronotal side smooth and largely glabrous, with deep oblique groove and anteriorly short; mesopleuron mainly smooth, shiny, punctulate but superficially rugulose anteriorly and medially convex; pleural sulcus distinctly crenulate; metapleuron mainly rugose; mesoscutum with some micro-sculpture, posteriorly shiny and with dense short pubescence between long setae, but sparsely so posteriorly, antero-medially slightly depressed and with few striae; notauli absent on disc; scutellar sulcus very deep; scutellum strongly convex but slightly depressed antero-medially, posteriorly distinctly above level of mesoscutum, largely rugulose and with long setae; dorsal face of propodeum smooth and shiny, posterior face subvertical and indistinctly rugulose, without areolation and laterally with short setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Wings. Fore wing: pterostigma straight baso-posteriorly (Fig. 18), but slightly concave in right wing; pterostigma twice as long as wide and vein 1-R1 largely absent; first subdiscal cell open posteriorly and apically (Fig. 18), but veins 2-1A and CU1b as faintly pigmented and unsclerotized veins present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Legs. Hind coxa mainly smooth, punctulate and setose; tarsal claws medium-sized and very slender; fore tarsal segments slender (secondfourth segments distinctly longer than wide in dorsal view), with long setae and with long apical bristles, but fore basitarsus rather robust; length of femur, tibia and basitarsus of hind leg 3.4, 6.1 and 4.8 times as long as wide, respectively; hind basitarsus robust (Fig. 16); hind femur subbasally and hind tibia medially widened (Fig. 16), both with erect setae; inner hind tibial spur 0.2 times as long as hind basitarsus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Metasoma. First tergite smooth, flattened and shiny, its maximum width at level of spiracles of ♀ 0.7 times distance between spiracle and apex of tergite (Fig. 19), parallel-sided posteriorly, tergite 1.1 times long as wide apically; second tergite smooth and glabrous except some setae, third and following tergites smooth and only with a subapical row of long setae; length of visible (and sparsely setose) part of elliptical ovipositor sheath 0.05 times fore wing.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Colour. Head (including clypeus), mesosoma (but notaulic courses and posterior part of mesoscutum, scutellum, metanotum laterally and propodeum brown) and metasoma (but first tergite and second tergite basally brownish yellow) dark brown;, palpi, mandible, tegulae (but tegulum brown) and legs (but femora and tibiae brown and tarsi pale yellowish) brownish yellow; antenna brown, but pedicellus pale yellowish; ovipositor sheath pale brownish yellow, distinctly paler than tergites; pterostigma (but basally and apically pale yellowish) and veins mainly brown; wing membrane infuscate near vein 1-M of fore wing.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="30" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="30" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Netherlands.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="30" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="30">
Named &quot; 
<taxonomicName lsidName="planus" pageId="5" pageNumber="30" rank="species" species="planus">planus</taxonomicName>
&quot; (Latin for &quot;smooth, even&quot;) because of the smooth and even first metasomal tergite.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>