<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3671449" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5ab481de-4d58-4fd0-a117-2a69558723be" ID-GBIF-Taxon="162146808" ID-ISSN="1942-1354" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3671449" ID-ZooBank="245CB278-D68A-4248-B9BC-8DB801F5A1EC" checkinTime="1581944937083" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Wappes, James E. &amp; Santos-Silva, Antonio" docDate="2019" docId="03EA9D1AFFEF9210DAB4F8B55D3FF8E9" docLanguage="en" docName="InsectaMundi.0695.1-19.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Insecta Mundi 695" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@4bae288a" docStyleName="insectamundi.2009-2019.journal_article" docTitle="Odontocera elllanocarti Wappes and Santos-Silva 2019, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="7" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="11" masterDocId="FFD3E562FFE5921CDA74FFFA5C69FFA8" masterDocTitle="Descriptions of one new genus and seven new species of Rhinotragini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae: Cerambycinae)" masterLastPageNumber="19" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="10" pageNumber="9" updateTime="1643462967603" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-NC-3.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Descriptions of one new genus and seven new species of Rhinotragini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae: Cerambycinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wappes, James E.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Insecta Mundi</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2019-03-29</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>695</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>19</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3670526</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">5ab481de-4d58-4fd0-a117-2a69558723be</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1942-1354</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">3670526</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">245CB278-D68A-4248-B9BC-8DB801F5A1EC</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3671449" ID-GBIF-Taxon="162146808" ID-Zenodo-Dep="3671449" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EA9D1AFFEF9210DAB4F8B55D3FF8E9" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03EA9D1AFFEF9210DAB4F8B55D3FF8E9" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="10" pageNumber="9">
<subSubSection box="[192,1051,1871,1896]" pageId="10" pageNumber="9" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="10.[192,1051,1871,1928]" box="[192,1051,1871,1896]" pageId="10" pageNumber="9">
<heading bold="true" box="[192,1051,1871,1896]" fontSize="10" level="2" pageId="10" pageNumber="9" reason="3">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,1051,1871,1896]" pageId="10" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authority="Wappes and Santos-Silva" authorityName="Wappes and Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2019" box="[192,874,1871,1896]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="10" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elllanocarti" status="new species">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,521,1871,1895]" italics="true" pageId="10" pageNumber="9">Odontocera elllanocarti</emphasis>
Wappes and Santos-Silva
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[888,1051,1872,1896]" pageId="10" pageNumber="9" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[192,338,1904,1928]" pageId="10" pageNumber="9" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="10.[192,1051,1871,1928]" box="[192,338,1904,1928]" pageId="10" pageNumber="9">
(
<figureCitation box="[201,330,1904,1928]" captionStart="Figures 18–26. 18–21" captionStartId="19.[192,287,1819,1841]" captionTargetBox="[228,1403,213,1784]" captionTargetId="figure@19.[228,1403,213,1785]" captionTargetPageId="19" captionText="Figures 18–26. 18–21) Paraeclipta Ʋandenberghei new species, holotype female: 18) Dorsal habitus. 19) Ventral habitus. 20) Lateral habitus. 21) Head, frontal view. 22) Ecliptoides Ʋandenberghei, holotype female, dorsal habitus. 23–26) Odontocera elllanocarti new species, holotype male: 23) Head, frontal view. 24) Dorsal habitus. 25) Ventral habitus. 26) Lateral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3670532" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/3670532/files/figure.png" pageId="10" pageNumber="9">Fig. 23–26</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="11" pageNumber="10" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="11.[192,1440,221,569]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,792,221,245]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
Description of male 
<typeStatus box="[471,591,221,245]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">holotype</typeStatus>
and 
<typeStatus box="[660,786,221,245]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">paratype</typeStatus>
.
</emphasis>
Integument mostly black; mouthparts dark reddishbrown, except parts of galea yellowish-brown and distal palpomeres dark brown; scape yellowish basally and ventrally, dark reddish-brown in remaining area; pedicel light reddish-brown; antennomeres III–VI light reddish-brown basally, gradually dark reddish-brown toward apex; antennomeres VII–IX yellowishbrown in basal third, brown on remaining surface; antennomeres X–XI brown; vitreous area of elytra starting at apex of basal sixth, becoming slightly translucent at distal sixth; profemora dark brown; mesofemora dark brown on base of peduncle, dark reddish-brown in remaining area of peduncle, dark brown on club; metafemora pale yellow on peduncle, dark brown on club; pro- and mesotibiae dark brown in basal half of dorsal surface, gradually dark reddish-brown on remaining surface except yellowishbrown basal third of ventral surface; metatibiae yellow in basal third, dark brown on remaining surface; pro- and mesotarsi mostly dark reddish-brown; metatarsi mostly dark brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="11.[192,1441,593,1492]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,273,593,617]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">Head.</emphasis>
Frons moderately finely, abundantly punctate, with yellowish-white pubescence obscuring integument (whiter depending on light intensity). Vertex and area behind upper eye lobes moderately coarsely, abundantly punctate, except central area of vertex close to prothorax, with punctures shallower and nearly indistinct; with sparse, short and long yellowish setae, nearly absent in area with shallower punctures, and sparser behind upper eye lobes. Area behind lower eye lobes rugose-punctate; with sparse, short yellowish setae, and sparse, moderately long, erect yellowish-brown setae close to eye. Antennal tubercles slightly elevated, moderately coarsely, sparsely punctate (most punctures shallow); with sparse, long, erect yellowish setae. Genae slightly shorter than half length of lower eye lobe; finely, moderately abundantly punctate except apex smooth; with sparse, decumbent yellowish-brown setae except glabrous smooth area, with long, erect setae of same color interspersed toward ventral surface. Median groove indistinct. Postclypeus with sculpturing as on frons in wide central area, smooth laterally; with yellowish-white pubescence partially obscuring integument in wide central area, glabrous laterally; with one long, erect, brownish seta on each side of wide central area. Gulamentum smooth, glabrous in posterocentral area; moderately coarsely, sparsely punctate, with long, erect brownish seta emerging from each puncture on sides of posterior area; somewhat transversely striate-punctate in central transverse area, with sparse, long, erect brownish setae; depressed anteriorly (except elevated anterior margin), centrally smooth and glabrous, moderately coarsely punctate, with sparse, long, erect brownish setae. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.68 times length of scape; in frontal view, lower eye lobes almost contiguous, distance between them 0.10 times length of scape. Antennae 1.3 times elytral length, almost reaching posterior quarter of elytra. Scape moderately finely, very sparsely punctate; with sparse, long, erect yellowish and brownish setae. Pedicel and antennomeres III–VIII with long, erect dark setae ventrally, gradually sparser toward VIII (only at apex in VII–VIII); pedicel and antennomeres III–IV with short, erect yellowish and brownish setae dorsally; antennomeres V–XI with yellowish pubescence in light area, slightly brownish in dark area; antennomere III–IV nearly cylindrical, very slightly widened toward apex; antennomeres V–X gradually more widened toward apex; antennomeres VII–XI together moderately club-shaped. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III (only 
<typeStatus box="[260,364,1435,1459]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">holotype</typeStatus>
measured): scape = 0.68; pedicel = 0.27; IV = 0.54; V = 0.73; VI = 0.63; VII = 0.61; VIII = 0.54; IX = 0.49; X = 0.46; XI = 0.61.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="11.[192,1441,1516,1928]" lastBlockId="12.[192,1441,217,625]" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,300,1516,1540]" pageId="11" pageNumber="10">Thorax.</emphasis>
Prothorax distinctly longer than wide; anterior and posterior constrictions well-marked; sides slightly, uniformly rounded from anterior to posterior constriction; posterior margin slightly sinuous. Pronotum coarsely, abundantly punctate; with wide, oblique yellowish-white pubescent band on each side of anterior area, not notably dense, whiter near sides; with transverse yellowish-white pubescent band, not obscuring integument posteriorly, more brownish or somewhat golden depending on angle and intensity of light source, distinctly whiter close to margins; remaining surface glabrous; with sparse, long, erect yellowish-brown setae throughout. Sides of prothorax with sculpturing as on pronotum, except anterior and posterior areas nearly smooth (anterior one gradually widened toward prosternum); with dense pubescence in punctate area, not obscuring integument, with color very variable depending on angle and intensity of light source, silvery, whitish, yellowish or slightly brownish, with long, erect yellowish-brown setae interspersed; anterior and posterior areas glabrous. Prosternum coarsely, abundantly punctate posteriorly (this area covering slightly more than posterior half); with transverse band of punctures in central area of anterior half, remaining surface nearly smooth; with abundant, long, erect brownish setae posteriorly, sparser anteriorly. Narrowest area of prosternal process about 5 times narrower than procoxal cavity; posterior area pentagonal. Ventral surface of mesothorax with abundant yellowish pubescence (whiter, especially laterally, depending on angle and intensity of light source), denser laterally in posterior 2/3 of mesanepisternum and entire mesepimeron. Metanepisternum not pubescent in anterior 3/4, densely pubescent in posterior quarter (pubescence white, silvery or more yellowish depending on angle and intensity of light source); with sparse, long, erect yellowish setae throughout. Sides of metaventrite not pubescent, with sparse, long, erect yellowish setae; anterior area surrounding mesocoxal cavities with dense white pubescence (more silvery depending on angle and intensity of light source), widened toward sides, not reaching central area of metaventrite, with long, erect yellowish setae interspersed; remaining central area with yellowish-white pubescence nearly obscuring integument (whiter or somewhat yellower depending on angle and intensity of light source), except narrow longitudinal central area, with long, erect yellowish setae interspersed. Scutellum with dense white pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1441,649,929]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,287,649,673]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Elytra.</emphasis>
Sides concave from near base to near apex; sutural margins slightly divergent from posterior third; apex truncate, very slightly projected at outer and sutural angles; coarsely, abundantly punctate on dark area, sparser in vitreous area; with sparse, long, erect yellowish setae, gradually shorter and sparser toward apex. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[459,531,745,769]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Legs.</emphasis>
Pro- and mesocoxae with tuft of long, erect yellowish setae near trochanters; pro- and mesotrochanters with tuft of long, erect yellowish setae; pro- and mesofemora with long, erect, yellowish-brown setae dorsally and laterally, noticeably denser ventrally, especially in peduncle; metafemora with sparse, long, erect yellowish setae throughout. Pro- and mesotibiae with sparse, long, erect dark setae dorsally and laterally, with dense yellowish-brown pubescence ventrally from near base; metatibiae with sparse dark setae basally, distinctly denser toward apex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1440,953,1201]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,329,953,977]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Abdomen.</emphasis>
Nearly cylindrical. Ventrite I very sparsely, moderately coarsely punctate except smooth distal area; laterally with dense white pubescent macula near apex; with sparse, long, erect yellowishbrown setae except in smooth distal area. Ventrites II–IV with punctures and erect setae distinctly more abundant than on I (setae denser laterally), except in smooth and glabrous distal area; II with white pubescent macula near apex. Central area of ventrite V gradually depressed from near base to apex, making sides somewhat carina-shaped (central area of depressed region higher than its sides); with moderately abundant, long, erect yellowish-brown setae throughout; apex truncate with central area rounded, slightly projected.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1441,1225,1282]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,329,1225,1249]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Variation.</emphasis>
Elytral area on each side of scutellum orange; ventral pubescence of thorax mostly yellowishbrown (somewhat golden depending on angle and intensity of light source).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1440,1305,1393]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,875,1305,1329]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
Dimensions (mm), 
<typeStatus box="[454,574,1305,1329]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">holotype</typeStatus>
male– 
<typeStatus box="[666,790,1305,1329]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">paratype</typeStatus>
male.
</emphasis>
Total length 11.95–10.55; prothoracic length 2.05–1.85; anterior prothoracic width 1.20–1.15; posterior prothoracic width 1.25–1.20; maximum prothoracic width 1.40–1.35; humeral width 1.55–1.40; elytral length 4.75–4.30.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1440,1417,1506]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,392,1417,1441]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Type material.</emphasis>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2565891004" collectingDate="1995-04-21" collectingDateMax="1995-04-30" collectingDateMin="1995-04-21" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="E. Giesbert" country="Panama" location="El Llano" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Panama" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[399,509,1417,1441]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry box="[646,771,1418,1442]" name="Panama" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">PANAMA</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis box="[782,885,1418,1441]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<collectingRegion box="[782,885,1418,1441]" country="Panama" name="Panama" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Panama</collectingRegion>
</emphasis>
: 
<quantity box="[899,1004,1417,1442]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="8.5" metricValueMax="10.0" metricValueMin="7.0" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" unit="km" value="8.5" valueMax="10.0" valueMin="7.0">7–10 km</quantity>
N 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03EA9D1AFFEF9210DAB4F8B55D3FF8E9:8E9C7AD7FFE99210DE7BFA735812FA09" box="[1039,1147,1417,1441]" country="Panama" name="El Llano" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" stateProvince="Panama">El Llano</location>
, 
<date box="[1158,1332,1417,1441]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" value="1995-04-21" valueMax="1995-04-30" valueMin="1995-04-21">
<collectingDate box="[1158,1332,1417,1441]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" value="1995-04-21" valueMax="1995-04-30" valueMin="1995-04-21">21-30.IV.1995</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName pageId="12" pageNumber="11">E. Giesbert</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode box="[306,384,1450,1474]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2565891009" box="[403,1440,1449,1474]" collectingDate="1995-04-21" collectingDateMax="1995-04-30" collectingDateMin="1995-04-21" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="E. Giesbert" country="Panama" isTailEnumeration="true" location="El Llano" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" specimenCount="3" specimenCount-male="3" stateProvince="Panama" typeStatus="paratype">
<typeStatus box="[403,530,1450,1474]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Paratypes</typeStatus>
, 
<specimenCount box="[542,639,1449,1474]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="male">3 males</specimenCount>
, 2 same data as holotype except 
<date box="[1039,1108,1450,1474]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" value="1993-05-14" valueMax="1993-05-22" valueMin="1993-05-14">14-22</date>
.V.1993 (1 
<collectionCode box="[1238,1314,1450,1474]" country="USA" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/jekt-x82m" name="Florida State Collection of Arthropods, The Museum of Entomology" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="Museum">FSCA</collectionCode>
, 1 
<collectionCode box="[1348,1428,1450,1474]" country="Brazil" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
);
</materialsCitation>
<materialsCitation ID-GBIF-Occurrence="2565891001" box="[192,826,1481,1506]" collectingDate="1995-04-21" collectingDateMax="1995-04-30" collectingDateMin="1995-04-21" collectionCode="FSCA" collectorName="E. Giesbert" country="Panama" isTailEnumeration="true" location="El Llano" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" specimenCount="3" specimenCount-male="3" stateProvince="Panama" typeStatus="paratype">
1 same data as holotype except 
<date box="[579,610,1481,1505]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" value="1992-04-26">26</date>
.IV.1992 (
<collectionCode box="[727,814,1482,1506]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">ACMT</collectionCode>
).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1440,1529,1617]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,323,1529,1553]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Remarks.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Wappes &amp; Santos-Silva, 2019" authorityName="Wappes &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2019" box="[328,613,1529,1553]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elllanocarti" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[328,613,1529,1553]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Odontocera elllanocarti</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[619,711,1530,1553]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
differs from 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1885" box="[863,1028,1529,1553]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fuscicornis">
<emphasis box="[863,1028,1529,1553]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">O. fuscicornis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(see photograph of the 
<typeStatus box="[1306,1410,1529,1553]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">holotype</typeStatus>
in 
<bibRefCitation author="Bezark, L. G." box="[192,347,1561,1586]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" refId="ref12352" refString="Bezark, L. G. 2019. A photographic Catalog of the Cerambycidae of the New World. Available at https: // apps 2. cdfa. ca. gov / publicApps / plant / bycidDB / wsearch. asp? w = n. (Last accessed January 2019.)" type="url" year="2019">Bezark 2019</bibRefCitation>
) as follows: prothorax slender; elytra without oblique dark band basally. In 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1885" box="[1274,1440,1561,1585]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="fuscicornis">
<emphasis box="[1274,1440,1561,1585]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">O. fuscicornis</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
the prothorax is more rounded and the elytra have an oblique dark band basally.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="11" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="12.[192,1441,1641,1857]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[192,343,1641,1665]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Etymology.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authorityName="Wappes &amp; Santos-Silva" authorityYear="2019" box="[349,627,1641,1665]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Odontocera" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="12" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elllanocarti">
<emphasis box="[349,627,1641,1665]" italics="true" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Odontocera elllanocarti</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is named after El Llano–Carti road in 
<collectingCountry box="[1078,1178,1642,1665]" name="Panama" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">Panama</collectingCountry>
(treated as a latinized noun in the nominative singular standing in apposition to the generic name). This road (collection site of the 
<typeStatus box="[269,374,1705,1729]" pageId="12" pageNumber="11">holotype</typeStatus>
) traverses a hilly ridge-top which years ago was lined with woody plants that flowered with the advent of the Spring rains. This produced a food source for many thousands of pollen-feeding cerambycids representing dozens of species, many of which were undescribed. A collector fortunate enough to be there at just the right time and with the help of a long-handled tropic net could feast on the offering.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>