<document ID-DOI="10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52" ID-ISSN="1807-0205" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4637231" ID-ZooBank="60CCFC22-D858-40F3-9B24-F3251F441270" approvalRequired="41" approvalRequired_for_document="1" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="4" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="30" approvalRequired_for_treatments="6" checkinTime="1616691947841" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto de L., Nearns, Eugenio H., Botero, Juan Pablo, Santos-Silva, Antonio &amp; Martins, David dos Santos" docDate="2020" docId="523F87CDFFD1FFBC6D55FD94E1AEBEC9" docLanguage="en" docName="PapAvZoo.60.e20206052.pdf" docOrigin="Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia (Pap. Avulsos Zool., S. Paulo) 60" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52" docStyle="DocumentStyle:6844D5473582683DD13A9A75B001759F:PapAvulsosZool.2018-.journal_article" docStyleId="6844D5473582683DD13A9A75B001759F" docStyleName="PapAvulsosZool.2018-.journal_article" docTitle="Pseudobeta casariae Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins 2020, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" masterDocId="AE06FFB5FFD7FFB46C6EFF8EE558BF5A" masterDocTitle="New species and new record in Lamiinae from Espírito Santo (Brazil) (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae)" masterLastPageNumber="12" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" updateTime="1616692281469" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-NC-4.0" zenodo-license-figures="CC-BY-NC-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species and new record in Lamiinae from Espírito Santo (Brazil) (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto de L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Nearns, Eugenio H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Botero, Juan Pablo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Martins, David dos Santos</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="series">
<mods:title>Pap. Avulsos Zool., S. Paulo</mods:title>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2020-10-20</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>60</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>12</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1807-0205</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">4637231</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">60CCFC22-D858-40F3-9B24-F3251F441270</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:523F87CDFFD1FFBC6D55FD94E1AEBEC9" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/523F87CDFFD1FFBC6D55FD94E1AEBEC9" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<subSubSection box="[315,648,538,563]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="6.[315,648,506,595]" box="[315,648,538,563]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<heading box="[315,648,538,563]" centered="true" fontSize="10" level="2" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" reason="5">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[315,648,538,563]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<taxonomicName authority="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins, 2020" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" box="[315,554,538,563]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="casariae" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[315,554,538,563]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Pseudobeta casariae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[559,648,538,563]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="6.[315,648,506,595]" box="[409,555,570,595]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[409,555,570,595]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
(
<figureCitation box="[416,491,570,595]" captionStart="Figure 3" captionStartId="6.[170,229,2074,2099]" captionTargetBox="[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetId="figure-277@6.[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetPageId="6" captionText="Figure 3. Pseudobeta casariae sp. nov.: (A) Dorsal habitus, holotype male;(B) Lateral habitus,holotype male; (C) Head,frontal view,holotype male; (D) Procoxae, holotype male." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637237" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637237/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Figs. 3</figureCitation>
A‑3E)
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[170,794,634,787]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[170,509,634,659]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
Description: 
<typeStatus box="[324,434,634,659]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Holotype</typeStatus>
male:
</emphasis>
Integument mostly dark brown, nearly black on some areas; mouthparts and anteclypeus dark reddish-brown (
<figureCitation box="[513,589,698,723]" captionStart="Figure 3" captionStartId="6.[170,229,2074,2099]" captionTargetBox="[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetId="figure-277@6.[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetPageId="6" captionText="Figure 3. Pseudobeta casariae sp. nov.: (A) Dorsal habitus, holotype male;(B) Lateral habitus,holotype male; (C) Head,frontal view,holotype male; (D) Procoxae, holotype male." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637237" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637237/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Fig. 3E</figureCitation>
); basal ¾ of antennomere III brown; about basal ¾ of antennomeres IV-X and of tarsomere V orangish-brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[868,1495,218,787]" lastBlockId="7.[94,720,218,1395]" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="8" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[869,938,218,243]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Head:</emphasis>
Frons (
<figureCitation box="[1016,1094,218,243]" captionStart="Figure 3" captionStartId="6.[170,229,2074,2099]" captionTargetBox="[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetId="figure-277@6.[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetPageId="6" captionText="Figure 3. Pseudobeta casariae sp. nov.: (A) Dorsal habitus, holotype male;(B) Lateral habitus,holotype male; (C) Head,frontal view,holotype male; (D) Procoxae, holotype male." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637237" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637237/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Fig. 3D</figureCitation>
) slightly transverse; finely, shallowly, sparsely punctate; with pale-yellow pubescence nearly obscuring integument, yellower on narrow lateral band close to genae, and wide central area between eyes (this area narrowed toward its inferior area);with narrow,longitudinal glabrous band on each side, from about middle of eyes to clypeus, and glabrous median groove. Vertex and area behind upper eye lobes with dense yellow pubescence, except glabrous median groove. Area behind low- er eye lobes with dense yellow pubescence on wide area close to eyes, except oblique glabrous band about middle,which reaches prothorax but does not reach eye; area close to prothorax, from oblique glabrous band to ventral surface, glabrous, finely, sparsely punctate superiorly, transversely striate inferiorly. Genae slightly shorter than lower eye lobe; with dense yellow pubescence, slightly paler toward clypeus, except glabrous apex. Postclypeus finely, somewhat sparsely punctate centrally, smooth laterally; with pale yellow pubescence on wide central area, with long, erect golden setae interspersed laterally, glabrous on smooth area. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior half, oblique, somewhat depressed at anterior half; with pale-yellow pubescence on posterior half, partially obscuring integument, and long, abundant golden setae on anterior half, and short fringe of golden setae on anterior margin. Antennal tubercles abruptly elevated, well-separated, with inner apex forming moderately elevated horn with blunt apex; pubescence mostly pale-yellow, yellower on some areas. Gulamentum transversely striate centrally, smooth on remaining surface; glabrous except short, sparse pale-yellow pubescence on intermaxillary process. Area of connection of eye lobes as wide as upper eye lobe. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.28 times length of scape (0.23 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.78 length of scape (0.67 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 2.3 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at basal third of antennomere VII. Scape gradually widened toward apex; wide central area coarsely, transversely rugose laterally and ventrally; with yellowish-white pubescence obscuring integument, except brownish pubescent macula on dorsal and lateral surfaces of posterior third (not reaching apex) (outer apex nearly glabrous, probably due to debridement). Pedicel and lighter area of antennomeres with yellowish-white pubescence, gradually finer, less conspicuous toward XI; dark apical area of antennomere III with yellowish-brown pubescence; dark area of antennomeres IV-X with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument (appearing to be darker due to integument color), gradually sparser, less conspicuous toward X; antennomere III slightly sinuous. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.81; pedicel = 0.16; IV = 0.82; V = 0.80; VI = 0.74; VII = 0.74;VIII = 0.69; IX = 0.69; X = 0.67; XI = 0.70.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637237" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4637237" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637237/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" startId="6.[170,229,2074,2099]" targetBox="[170,1493,816,2044]" targetPageId="6">
<paragraph blockId="6.[170,1494,2074,2131]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName authority="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins, 2020" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" box="[256,420,2074,2099]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="casariae" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[256,420,2074,2099]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Pseudobeta casariae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[424,489,2074,2099]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
: (A) Dorsal habitus, holotype male;(B) Lateral habitus,holotype male; (C) Head,frontal view,holotype male; (D) Procoxae, holotype male.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="7.[93,720,1434,2131]" lastBlockId="7.[792,1419,218,2131]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[94,185,1434,1459]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Thorax:</emphasis>
Prothorax transverse and cylindrical, 1.45 wider than long; sides with somewhat small, rounded gibbosity close to anterior constriction, and small protuberance about middle (anterior margin abruptly expanded). Pronotum transversely tumid between anterior and posterior fifths; tumid area with irregular, slightly elevated gibbosities laterally, and longitudinal gibbosity centrally (this gibbosity prolonged toward anterior margin, but less elevated than on tumid area); posterior area of tumid area with oblique, slightly elevated carina on each side, fused centrally; tumid area with yellow pubescence,with yellowish-white pubescence interspersed (posterior area with oblique carinae more yellowish-white centrally); anterior and posterior fifths mostly with yellowish-white pubescence, except narrow yellow pubescent band centrally on anterior fifth; area between oblique carinae on tumid area and posterior margin with coarse, sparse, glabrous punctures. Sides of prothorax coarsely, transversely rugose, especially centrally; with yellowish-white pubescence, with yellow pubescence interspersed, except area close to anterior margin and part of area close to procoxae; with long, erect dark setae posteriorly close to pronotum. Prosternum with abundant yellow pubescence laterally, and almost glabrous centrally. Prosternal process with dense yellow pubescence. Mesoventrite nearly glabrous, except yellowish-white pubescence close to mesocoxal cavities and apices. Mesoventral process with yellowish-white pubescence obscuring integument, except narrow, longitudinal central band partially glabrous. Mesanepisternum, mesepimeron, metanepisternum, and metaventrite with dense yellowish-white pubescence, with patches of yellow pubescence on some areas. Scutellum with yellowish-white pubescence close to margins, and yellowish-brown pubescence centrally, except glabrous, transverse band on anterocentral area. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[851,928,634,659]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Elytra:</emphasis>
Nearly parallel-sided on anterior ¾,uniformly rounded on posterior quarter; humerus tumid, slightly projected forward and sideward, with small glabrous tubercle at apex; coarsely, somewhat sparsely punctate on basal quarter (punctures near base scabrous), nearly absent on remaining surface; sides of basal quarter with yellowish-brown pubescence, with whitish pubescence interspersed (whitish pubescence more abundant toward central area); punctures on basal quarter with minute yellow seta arising from each one; central area of anterior quarter with dense white pubescence; remaining surface with dense white pubescence, with irregular patches of pale-yellow pubescence, except almost zig-zag, cross band of pale-yellow pubescence beyond middle. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[882,943,1082,1107]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Legs:</emphasis>
Procoxae with distinct, uncinate projection (
<figureCitation box="[799,880,1114,1139]" captionStart="Figure 3" captionStartId="6.[170,229,2074,2099]" captionTargetBox="[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetId="figure-277@6.[170,1493,816,2044]" captionTargetPageId="6" captionText="Figure 3. Pseudobeta casariae sp. nov.: (A) Dorsal habitus, holotype male;(B) Lateral habitus,holotype male; (C) Head,frontal view,holotype male; (D) Procoxae, holotype male." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637237" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637237/files/figure.png" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Fig. 3E</figureCitation>
). Profemora wide basally, slightly widened toward apex; meso- and metafemora narrower basally, and slightly wider toward apex than profemora (especially metafemora); dorsally with dense yellowish pubescence (profemora with brownish pubescent patch near apex), and remaining surface with dense yellowish-white pubescence. Protibiae gradually widened toward apex; mesotibiae somewhat abruptly widened dorsally from basal third, with wide, distinct sulcus laterally from apex of anterior third to near apex (gradually shallower toward apex); metatibiae gradually, strongly widened on anterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[838,860,1464,1490]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">⅔</emphasis>
, slightly narrowed toward apex on posterior third, with wide, distinct sulcus laterally from apex of anterior third to near apex (gradually shallower toward apex, especially inferiorly); protibiae with yellowish-white pubescence partially obscuring integument, with short yellow setae interspersed, except dense, somewhat bristly yellow pubescence on posterior quarter of dorsal surface, posterior third of ventral surface, and entire apex; mesotibiae with pale-yellow pubescence dorsally on anterior third, yellowish-white pubescence laterally and ventrally on anterior third and almost entire ventral surface of posterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[860,882,1816,1842]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">⅔</emphasis>
, dense, bristly yellow pubescence on dorsal surface of posterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[975,997,1848,1874]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">⅔</emphasis>
and apex of ventral surface, and short, decumbent, sparse yellow setae on sides of posterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1390,1412,1880,1906]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">⅔</emphasis>
; metatibiae with yellowish-white pubescence on basal third (yellower dorsally), yellowish-white pubescence ventrally to about middle, yellowish-white pubescence dorsally to posterior third, dense, somewhat bristly yellow pubescence dorsally on posterior third, ventrally on about posterior half and entire apex, and short, decumbent yellow setae on sides of posterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1225,1247,2104,2130]" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">⅔</emphasis>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[170,794,218,339]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[170,294,218,243]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Abdomen:</emphasis>
Ventrites with dense grayish-white pubescence, except apex of ventrite V with yellowish pubescence; apex of ventrite V nearly truncate, slightly, widely emarginate centrally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[170,795,378,563]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[170,286,378,403]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Variation:</emphasis>
Sides of basal quarter of elytra with yellow pubescence much more abundant than in the 
<typeStatus box="[688,791,410,435]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">holotype</typeStatus>
, without whitish pubescence interspersed, except a few white pubescent maculae near apex of this area; white pubescence of elytra with yellowish-brown patches of pubescence interspersed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[169,795,602,755]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[170,648,602,627]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
Dimensions in mm (
<typeStatus box="[407,518,602,627]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">holotype</typeStatus>
/ 
<typeStatus box="[525,637,602,627]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">paratype</typeStatus>
):
</emphasis>
Total length, 18.90/20.00; prothoracic length, 2.95/3.25; anterior prothoracic width, 4.10/4.50; posterior prothoracic width, 4.25/4.65;humeral width,6.70/7.30; elytral length, 13.70/14.25.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="8.[170,794,794,947]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[170,347,794,819]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Type material:</emphasis>
<materialsCitation collectingDate="1988-11-01" collectionCode="RFCVRD, RNV, MZSP" collectorName="Jose Simplicio dos Santos" country="Brazil" location="Linhares" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Espirito Santo" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[362,465,794,819]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Holotype</typeStatus>
male from 
<collectingCountry box="[616,698,794,819]" name="Brazil" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">BRAZIL</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<collectingRegion country="Brazil" name="Espirito Santo" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Espírito Santo</collectingRegion>
:
</emphasis>
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:523F87CDFFD1FFBC6D55FD94E1AEBEC9:DF496000FFDFFFBC6C9BFCB4E40BBC09" box="[245,339,826,851]" country="Brazil" name="Linhares" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" stateProvince="Espirito Santo">Linhares</location>
(
<collectionCode box="[350,445,826,851]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">RFCVRD</collectionCode>
, 2218) [= 
<collectionCode box="[551,605,826,851]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">RNV</collectionCode>
], 
<date box="[619,736,826,851]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" value="1988-11-01">
<collectingDate box="[619,736,826,851]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" value="1988-11-01">01.XI.1988</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName pageId="8" pageNumber="9">José Simplício dos Santos</collectorName>
col. (
<collectionCode box="[455,520,858,883]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
, formerly 
<collectionCode box="[629,682,858,883]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">RNV</collectionCode>
)
</materialsCitation>
. 
<typeStatus box="[696,794,858,883]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Paratype</typeStatus>
male, same data as 
<typeStatus box="[397,498,890,915]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">holotype</typeStatus>
except, # 2941, 
<date box="[686,794,890,915]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" value="1992-10-20">20.X.1992</date>
(
<collectionCode box="[176,230,922,947]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">RNV</collectionCode>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="8.[170,795,986,1075]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[170,306,986,1011]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Etymology:</emphasis>
This species is name for Professor Sônia A. Casari (MZSP) for her support and contributions to the study of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Linnaeus" authorityYear="1758" box="[265,390,1050,1075]" class="Magnoliopsida" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Plantae" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="order">Coleoptera</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="9" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="8.[170,795,1114,2131]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[170,280,1114,1139]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Remarks:</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Zajciw, 1972" authorityName="Zajciw" authorityYear="1972" box="[288,562,1114,1139]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[288,414,1114,1139]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Pseudobeta</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Zajciw, D." box="[422,562,1114,1139]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="219 - 220" refId="ref9239" refString="Zajciw, D. 1972. Descricao de um genero novo e uma especie nova de longicorneos neotropicos (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae). Revista Brasileira de Biologia, 32 (2): 219 - 220." type="journal article" year="1972">Zajciw, 1972</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
(a synonym used as a replacement name for 
<taxonomicName authority="Dillon &amp; Dillon, 1945" authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[450,741,1146,1171]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Amaranthaceae" genus="Beta" kingdom="Plantae" order="Caryophyllales" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[450,498,1146,1171]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Beta</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S." box="[507,741,1146,1171]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="1 - 186" refId="ref8417" refString="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S. 1945. The tribe Onciderini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae). Part I. Scientific Publications of the Reading Public Museum, 5: 1 - 186." type="journal article" year="1945">Dillon &amp; Dillon, 1945</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
) is a problematic genus because the generic limits are not clear, and its separation from 
<taxonomicName authority="Monne, 2005" authorityName="Monne" authorityYear="2005" box="[515,794,1210,1235]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Midamiella" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[515,636,1210,1235]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Midamiella</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Monne, M. A." box="[645,794,1210,1235]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="1 - 759" refId="ref8777" refString="Monne, M. A. 2005. Catalogue of the Cerambycidae (Coleoptera) of the Neotropical Region. Part II. Subfamily Lamiinae. Zootaxa, 1023: 1 - 759." type="journal article" year="2005">Monné, 2005</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
(replacement name for 
<taxonomicName authority="Dillon &amp; Dillon, 1945" authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[431,765,1242,1267]" genus="Midamus" kingdom="Animalia" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[431,531,1242,1267]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Midamus</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S." box="[537,765,1242,1267]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="1 - 186" refId="ref8417" refString="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S. 1945. The tribe Onciderini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae). Part I. Scientific Publications of the Reading Public Museum, 5: 1 - 186." type="journal article" year="1945">Dillon &amp; Dillon, 1945</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
) is questionable.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[170,795,1114,2131]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<bibRefCitation author="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S." box="[208,450,1306,1331]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="1 - 186" refId="ref8417" refString="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S. 1945. The tribe Onciderini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae). Part I. Scientific Publications of the Reading Public Museum, 5: 1 - 186." type="journal article" year="1945">Dillon &amp; Dillon (1945)</bibRefCitation>
separated 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[576,624,1306,1331]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Amaranthaceae" genus="Beta" kingdom="Plantae" order="Caryophyllales" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[576,624,1306,1331]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Beta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
from 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[693,793,1306,1331]" genus="Midamus" kingdom="Animalia" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[693,793,1306,1331]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Midamus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
in the alternative of couplet “29”:“Head with front transverse,” leading to 
<emphasis box="[369,423,1370,1395]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[369,417,1370,1395]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Amaranthaceae" genus="Beta" kingdom="Plantae" order="Caryophyllales" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">Beta</taxonomicName>
;
</emphasis>
“Head with front subquadrate or elongate,” leading to 
<emphasis box="[411,517,1402,1427]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[411,514,1402,1427]" genus="Midamus" kingdom="Animalia" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" rank="genus">Midamus</taxonomicName>
.
</emphasis>
However, the difference between transverse and subquadrate may be nonexistent. In addition, according to 
<bibRefCitation author="Zajciw, D." box="[512,662,1466,1491]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="219 - 220" refId="ref9239" refString="Zajciw, D. 1972. Descricao de um genero novo e uma especie nova de longicorneos neotropicos (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae, Lamiinae). Revista Brasileira de Biologia, 32 (2): 219 - 220." type="journal article" year="1972">Zajciw (1972)</bibRefCitation>
the frons is subquadrate in 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Zajciw" authorityYear="1972" box="[344,470,1498,1523]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[344,470,1498,1523]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Pseudobeta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(the 
<typeStatus box="[526,576,1498,1523]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">type</typeStatus>
species of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[697,745,1498,1523]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Amaranthaceae" genus="Beta" kingdom="Plantae" order="Caryophyllales" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[697,745,1498,1523]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Beta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Zajciw" authorityYear="1972" box="[170,296,1530,1555]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[170,296,1530,1555]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Pseudobeta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
are synonyms). In fact, 
<bibRefCitation author="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S." box="[556,794,1530,1555]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="1 - 186" refId="ref8417" refString="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S. 1945. The tribe Onciderini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae). Part I. Scientific Publications of the Reading Public Museum, 5: 1 - 186." type="journal article" year="1945">Dillon &amp; Dillon (1945)</bibRefCitation>
compared 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[297,345,1562,1587]" class="Magnoliopsida" family="Amaranthaceae" genus="Beta" kingdom="Plantae" order="Caryophyllales" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[297,345,1562,1587]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Beta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
with 
<emphasis box="[421,527,1562,1587]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[421,521,1562,1587]" genus="Midamus" kingdom="Animalia" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" rank="genus">Midamus</taxonomicName>
:
</emphasis>
“Somewhat related to 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[170,270,1594,1619]" genus="Midamus" kingdom="Animalia" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[170,270,1594,1619]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Midamus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
in the broad front, small eyes, short genae and cylindrical pronotum; distinct in having the eyes broad- er, more oblong; antennal tubercles more prominent; pronotum transverse, sides not excavated, distinctly tuberculate, disk with two tubercles; elytra more tapering, apices acute, base punctate, humeri more elevated; metatibiae subequal in length to metafemora.” These differences are at least partially incorrect. For example, the prothorax is transverse in the two species currently placed in 
<emphasis box="[285,411,1882,1907]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Monne" authorityYear="2005" box="[285,407,1882,1907]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Midamiella" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Midamiella</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
and according to 
<bibRefCitation author="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S." pageId="8" pageNumber="9" pagination="1 - 186" refId="ref8417" refString="Dillon, L. S. &amp; Dillon, E. S. 1945. The tribe Onciderini (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae). Part I. Scientific Publications of the Reading Public Museum, 5: 1 - 186." type="journal article" year="1945">Dillon &amp; Dillon (1945)</bibRefCitation>
, in the description of 
<emphasis box="[495,600,1914,1939]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Dillon &amp; Dillon" authorityYear="1945" box="[495,597,1914,1939]" genus="Midamus" kingdom="Animalia" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" rank="genus">Midamus</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
the pronotum is transverse. We believe that 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Zajciw" authorityYear="1972" box="[474,600,1946,1971]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[474,600,1946,1971]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Pseudobeta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is the best genus to include the new species, however, a comprehensive review of this genus and 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Monne" authorityYear="2005" box="[446,567,2010,2035]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Midamiella" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis box="[446,567,2010,2035]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Midamiella</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is necessary.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[170,795,1114,2131]" lastBlockId="8.[869,1493,218,403]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authority="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins, 2020" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" box="[208,428,2042,2067]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="casariae" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis box="[208,428,2042,2067]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Pseudobeta casariae</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[436,521,2042,2067]" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Galileo &amp; Martins, 1990" authorityName="Galileo &amp; Martins" authorityYear="1990" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ferruginea">
<emphasis box="[662,795,2042,2067]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">P. ferruginea</emphasis>
Galileo &amp; Martins, 1990
</taxonomicName>
, but differs as follows: dorsal pubescence mostly yellow and white; sides of prothorax not distinctly widened centrally; antennomere III at most as wide as posterior margin of the prothorax; frons transverse. In 
<emphasis box="[973,1114,282,307]" italics="true" pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Galileo &amp; Martins" authorityYear="1990" box="[973,1110,282,307]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Pseudobeta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ferruginea">P. ferruginea</taxonomicName>
,
</emphasis>
the dorsal pubescence is mostly orangish, sides of prothorax are distinctly widened centrally, antennomere III wider than posterior margin of the prothorax, and the frons is elongate.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>