<document ID-DOI="10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52" ID-ISSN="1807-0205" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4637231" ID-ZooBank="60CCFC22-D858-40F3-9B24-F3251F441270" approvalRequired="41" approvalRequired_for_document="1" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="4" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="30" approvalRequired_for_treatments="6" checkinTime="1616691947841" checkinUser="carolina" docAuthor="Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto de L., Nearns, Eugenio H., Botero, Juan Pablo, Santos-Silva, Antonio &amp; Martins, David dos Santos" docDate="2020" docId="523F87CDFFD6FFB06CC1FA94E643BD49" docLanguage="en" docName="PapAvZoo.60.e20206052.pdf" docOrigin="Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia (Pap. Avulsos Zool., S. Paulo) 60" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52" docStyle="DocumentStyle:6844D5473582683DD13A9A75B001759F:PapAvulsosZool.2018-.journal_article" docStyleId="6844D5473582683DD13A9A75B001759F" docStyleName="PapAvulsosZool.2018-.journal_article" docTitle="Xylergates quinquetuberculatus Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins 2020, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" masterDocId="AE06FFB5FFD7FFB46C6EFF8EE558BF5A" masterDocTitle="New species and new record in Lamiinae from Espírito Santo (Brazil) (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae)" masterLastPageNumber="12" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" updateTime="1616692281469" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-NC-4.0" zenodo-license-figures="CC-BY-NC-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species and new record in Lamiinae from Espírito Santo (Brazil) (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Nascimento, Francisco Eriberto de L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Nearns, Eugenio H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Botero, Juan Pablo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Santos-Silva, Antonio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Martins, David dos Santos</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2020</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="series">
<mods:title>Pap. Avulsos Zool., S. Paulo</mods:title>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2020-10-20</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>60</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>12</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11606/1807-0205/2020.60.52</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1807-0205</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">4637231</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">60CCFC22-D858-40F3-9B24-F3251F441270</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:523F87CDFFD6FFB06CC1FA94E643BD49" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/523F87CDFFD6FFB06CC1FA94E643BD49" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="1.[175,637,1306,1363]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<taxonomicName authority="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins, 2020" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" box="[175,542,1306,1331]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quinquetuberculatus" status="sp. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[175,542,1306,1331]" italics="true" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Xylergates quinquetuberculatus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[548,637,1306,1331]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(
<figureCitation box="[339,411,1338,1363]" captionStart="Figure 1" captionStartId="2.[170,229,2074,2099]" captionTargetBox="[198,1464,204,2044]" captionTargetId="figure-1@2.[198,1464,204,2044]" captionTargetPageId="2" captionText="Figure 1.(A-D)Nyssodrysina infima (Bates,1885),male:(A) Dorsal habitus;(B)Ventralhabitus;(C) Lateral habitus;(D)Head,frontal view.(E-H)Xylergates quinquetuberculatus sp.nov.,holotype female:(E) Head,frontal view;(F) Dorsal habitus;(G) Ventral habitus;(H) Lateral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637233" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637233/files/figure.png" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Figs. 1</figureCitation>
E‑1H)
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="1" pageNumber="2" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="1.[94,719,1402,1587]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[94,447,1402,1427]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
Description: 
<typeStatus box="[244,354,1402,1427]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Holotype</typeStatus>
female:
</emphasis>
Integument mostly dark brown, almost black; mouthparts reddish-brown except dark brown palpomeres; basal 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[438,460,1464,1490]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">⅔</emphasis>
of antennomeres III-VII brown, gradually lighter toward VII; about basal half of antennomeres VIII-XI orangish, and remaining surface brown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[93,720,1626,2131]" lastBlockId="1.[792,1420,218,1683]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[94,163,1626,1651]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Head:</emphasis>
Frons (
<figureCitation box="[250,325,1626,1651]" captionStart="Figure 1" captionStartId="2.[170,229,2074,2099]" captionTargetBox="[198,1464,204,2044]" captionTargetId="figure-1@2.[198,1464,204,2044]" captionTargetPageId="2" captionText="Figure 1.(A-D)Nyssodrysina infima (Bates,1885),male:(A) Dorsal habitus;(B)Ventralhabitus;(C) Lateral habitus;(D)Head,frontal view.(E-H)Xylergates quinquetuberculatus sp.nov.,holotype female:(E) Head,frontal view;(F) Dorsal habitus;(G) Ventral habitus;(H) Lateral habitus." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637233" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637233/files/figure.png" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Fig. 1E</figureCitation>
) finely, abundantly punctate; with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument; with two long, erect yellowish-brown setae on each side close to eyes. Median groove distinct from clypeus to area posterior to the upper eye lobes (obliterated by the pronotum). Area between antennal tubercles and upper eye lobes depressed, with fine transverse sulcus (crossing the median groove). Vertex and area behind upper eye lobes finely, abundantly punctate, punctures poorly marked close to prothorax; with yellowish-brown pubescence partially obscuring integument (forming nearly golden, slight delimited macula on each side of vertex close to eyes), absent close to prothorax, sparser on triangular-shaped area close to prothorax. Area behind lower eye lobes finely punctate close to eye, smooth close to prothorax, slightly longitudinally striate at limit between these two regions;with pale yellowish-brown pubescence close to eye, except triangular, nearly glabrous area after middle, smooth close to prothorax. Genae about as long as lower eye lobe;finely,densely punctate,except smooth apex; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, longer, slightly denser close to smooth area. Postclypeus nearly smooth on wide central area, smooth laterally; with somewhat bristly yellowish-brown pubescence on wide central area, with long, erect, sparse yellowish-brown setae interspersed, glabrous laterally. Labrum with yellowish-white pubescence posteriorly, with sparse yellowish-brown setae interspersed, nearly glabrous anteriorly. Antennal tubercles moderately elevated; with yellowish-white pubescence anteriorly,nearly golden posteriorly. Gulamentum smooth, shining, glabrous posteriorly, depressed, opaque anteriorly; with a few long, erect brownish setae close to anterior margin. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.22 times length of scape (0.25 times distance between outer margins of eyes); in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.51 length of scape (0.59 times distance between outer margins of eyes). Antennae 2.0 times elytral length,reaching elytral apex near apex of antennomere V. Scape with yellowish-white pubescence, with several small, irregular glabrous areas, except apical area with yellowish-brown pubescence,especially dorsally;with a few long, erect yellowish-brown setae ventrally near apex. Pedicel with yellowish-brown pubescence and whitish pubescence interspersed; with a few short, erect, thick dark setae ventrally. Antennomere III with dense yellowish-white pubescence on basal 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[893,915,1176,1202]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">⅔</emphasis>
(whiter depending on light intensity), shorter yellowish-white pubescence on posterior third (slightly conspicuous, appearing to be darker due to integument color); with a few short, erect, thick dark setae ventrally. Antennomere IV with two yellowish-white pubescent rings, one basally, another starting about middle (whiter depending on light intensity); with short, erect, thick dark seta ventrally about middle, and a few similar setae at apex; dark areas with pubescence as on dark area of ventrite III; remaining antennomeres with yellowish-white pubescence on lighter area, shorter, less conspicuous on dark area; with a few short, erect, thick dark setae on ventral apex, except antennomeres X-XI. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 1.23; pedicel = 0.13; IV = 0.94; V = 0.77; VI = 0.65; VII = 0.57; VIII = 0.52; IX = 0.48; X = 0.38; XI = 0.40.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[794,1419,1722,2131]" lastBlockId="3.[794,1420,218,339]" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[794,884,1722,1747]" pageId="1" pageNumber="2">Thorax:</emphasis>
Prothorax transverse, 1.6 wider than long; sides with acute tubercle near posterior third, gradually widened from anterolateral angles to lateral tubercle, distinctly narrowed, parallel-sided on posterior quarter. Pronotum with five tubercles, two almost conical on each side of anterior third, two rounded and blunt on each side about middle, more distant from each other than anterior ones, another slightly elongated on center of posterior area; with transverse row of coarse, deep punctures near posterior margin, coarse, shallow punctures on sides of anterior half, and near anterior margin; remaining surface nearly smooth; wide central area with yellowish-brown pubescence except on top of anterior tubercles, and remaining surface with yellowish-white pubescence (whiter depending on light intensity); with a few long, erect brownish setae on sides of posterior area.Sides of prothorax coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate on central area, almost impunctate on remaining surface; with dense yellowish-white pubescence centrally close to pronotum, yellowish-brown on remaining surface, distinctly sparser, toward postcoxal process. Prosternum and prosternal process densely micropunctate; with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument; narrowest area of prosternal process 0.35 times width of procoxal cavity. Mesoventrite with yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument, except denser, yellowish-brown pubescence on apex of sides. Mesanepisternum and mesepimeron with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, denser on mesanepisternum close to mesepimeron and superiorly close to elytra. Apex of mesoventral process almost as wide as mesocoxal cavity. Metanepisternum with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument on anterior half, dense, yellowish-white with yellowish-brown pubescence interspersed on posterior half. Metaventrite with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence on sides, with small, irregular glabrous areas interspersed, darker and sparser close to anterior half of metanepisternum, abundant, shorter, yellowish-white on central area (whiter depending on light intensity). Scutellum with dense yellowish-brown pubescence centrally (this area widened toward apex),and shorter,spars- er pubescence of same color on remaining surface (appearing to be darker due to integument color). 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[642,718,1178,1203]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Elytra:</emphasis>
Parallel-sided on anterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[395,417,1208,1234]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">⅔</emphasis>
, gradually convergent on posterior third; apex truncate, slightly oblique toward sutural angle; humeri rounded, somewhat projected forward; humeral carina irregular, somewhat distinct on anterior half; with oblique, moderately distinct carina dorsally from near humerus to beyond middle, with sparse tubercles dorsally; surface somewhat irregular, moderately coarsely punctate on anterior 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[513,535,1432,1458]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">⅔</emphasis>
, finely, sparsely punctate on posterior third; elytral pubescence mostly yellowish-brown with yellowish-white pubescence interspersed, except V-shaped band on center of dorsal anterior third, wide, longitudinal white pubescent band about middle, obliquely narrowed on its anterior margin, narrowly projected forward along suture, arched, projected sideward on its posterior apex, oblique, wide dark pubescent band close to apex of white band, and transverse, irregular white pubescent band on posterior quarter, tubercles on anterior two thirds surrounded by dark yellowish-brown pubescence; entire surface with short, sparse, suberect black setae. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[512,574,1818,1843]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Legs:</emphasis>
Femora pedunculate-clavate; with distinctly short yellowish-white pubescence not obscuring integument on peduncle, dense yellowish-white pubescence on club, yellower on some areas, with small, circular glabrous areas interspersed. Tibiae with dense yellowish-white pubescence obscuring integument, with small, circular glabrous areas interspersed, except two rings with sparser, shorter yellowish-brown pubescence, one slightly before middle, another on posterior third (ventral surface of protib- iae with dense brownish pubescence on posterior half). Tarsomeres I-II with dense yellowish-white pubescence, and remaining segments with predominantly brown pubescence.
</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4637233" ID-Zenodo-Dep="4637233" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/4637233/files/figure.png" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" startId="2.[170,229,2074,2099]" targetBox="[198,1464,204,2044]" targetPageId="2">
<paragraph blockId="2.[170,1493,2074,2131]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">
Figure 1.(A-D) 
<taxonomicName authority="(Bates, 1885)" baseAuthorityName="Bates" baseAuthorityYear="1885" box="[301,577,2074,2099]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Nyssodrysina" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="infima">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[301,462,2074,2099]" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Nyssodrysina infima</emphasis>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Bates, H. W." box="[471,571,2074,2099]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" pagination="249 - 436" refId="ref8198" refString="Bates, H. W. 1885. Biologia Centrali-Americana, Insecta, Coleoptera, suppl. to Longicornia. London. v. 5, p. 249 - 436." type="journal article" year="1885">Bates,1885</bibRefCitation>
)
</taxonomicName>
,male:(A) Dorsal habitus;(B)Ventral habitus;(C) Lateral habitus;(D)Head,frontal view.(E-H) 
<taxonomicName authority="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins, 2020" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quinquetuberculatus" status="sp.nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" italics="true" pageId="2" pageNumber="3">Xylergates quinquetuberculatus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[274,338,2106,2131]" pageId="2" pageNumber="3" rank="species">sp.nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
,holotype female:(E) Head,frontal view;(F) Dorsal habitus;(G) Ventral habitus;(H) Lateral habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="3.[794,1418,378,787]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[794,918,378,403]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Abdomen:</emphasis>
Apex of last tergite strongly notched. Ventrite V trunco-conical, distinctly longer than IV, surpassing elytral apex, with apex truncate, sides spiniform. Ventrite I with dense yellowish-white pubescence on posterior area of sides, remaining surface of sides with short, slightly conspicuous yellowish-brown pubescence, remaining surface with whitish pubescence; ventrites II-IV with dense yellowish-white pubescence laterally, with small glabrous areas interspersed, remaining surface with whitish pubescence; ventrite V with dense yellowish-white pubescence, with small glabrous areas interspersed, except inverted V-shaped central area with sparser whitish pubescence.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[793,1418,826,947]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[794,1176,826,851]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Dimensions in mm (
<typeStatus box="[1052,1165,826,851]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">holotype</typeStatus>
):
</emphasis>
Total length, 11.20; prothoracic length,2.00; anterior prothoracic width,2.40; posterior prothoracic width, 2.60; maximum prothoracic width, 3.20; humeral width, 4.10; elytral length, 7.90.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="3.[794,1419,986,1075]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[794,968,986,1011]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Type material:</emphasis>
<materialsCitation collectingDate="2016-11-30" collectionCode="MZSP" collectorName="Martins &amp; Fiuza" country="Brazil" location="Linhares" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" specimenCount="1" stateProvince="Espirito Santo" typeStatus="holotype">
<typeStatus box="[978,1081,986,1011]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Holotype</typeStatus>
female from 
<collectingCountry box="[1243,1325,986,1011]" name="Brazil" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">BRAZIL</collectingCountry>
, 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<collectingRegion country="Brazil" name="Espirito Santo" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Espírito Santo</collectingRegion>
:
</emphasis>
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:523F87CDFFD6FFB06CC1FA94E643BD49:DF496000FFD4FFB76F1DFC74E689BB49" box="[883,977,1018,1043]" country="Brazil" name="Linhares" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" stateProvince="Espirito Santo">Linhares</location>
(Reserva Natural Vale, Col. 1190), 
<date box="[794,911,1050,1075]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2016-11-30">
<collectingDate box="[794,911,1050,1075]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2016-11-30">30.XI.2016</collectingDate>
</date>
, 
<collectorName box="[918,1002,1050,1075]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Martins</collectorName>
&amp; 
<collectorName box="[1027,1084,1050,1075]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Fiuza</collectorName>
col.(
<collectionCode box="[1136,1201,1050,1075]" country="Brazil" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/9yp6-zxp9" name="Sao Paulo, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de Sao Paulo" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="Museum">MZSP</collectionCode>
,formerly INCAPER).
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="3.[793,1418,1114,1171]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[794,929,1114,1139]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Etymology:</emphasis>
The epithet refers to the number of pronotal tubercles.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="3.[793,1419,1210,1843]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[794,904,1210,1235]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Remarks:</emphasis>
By the general appearance, especially the pattern of the elytral pubescence, 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quinquetuberculatus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Xylergates quinquetuberculatus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
is similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Giorgi &amp; Corbett, 2005" authorityName="Giorgi &amp; Corbett" authorityYear="2005" box="[1021,1414,1274,1299]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="capixaba">
<emphasis box="[1021,1146,1274,1299]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">X. capixaba</emphasis>
<bibRefCitation author="Giorgi, J. A. &amp; Corbett, D." box="[1156,1414,1274,1299]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" pagination="5 - 8" refId="ref8560" refString="Giorgi, J. A. &amp; Corbett, D. 2005. Sinopse do genero Xylergates (Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Acanthocinini). Iheringia, Zoologia, 95 (1): 5 - 8." type="journal article" year="2005">Giorgi &amp; Corbett, 2005</bibRefCitation>
</taxonomicName>
, but differs as follows: antennomere IV biannulate; pronotum with five tubercles; white pubescent band on center of the elytra narrower and with sides regular; oblique dark band on elytra beyond middle projected upward from sides toward suture; white pubescent band on posterior quarter of the elytra narrow and projected upward from sides to suture. In 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Giorgi &amp; Corbett" authorityYear="2005" box="[1056,1180,1498,1523]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="capixaba">
<emphasis box="[1056,1180,1498,1523]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">X. capixaba</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
(see photographs on 
<bibRefCitation author="Bezark, L. G." box="[795,937,1530,1555]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" refId="ref8266" refString="Bezark, L. G. 2020. A photographic Catalog of the Cerambycidae of the World. New World Cerambycidae Catalog. Available at: http: // bezbycids. com / byciddb / wdefault. asp? w = n. Access in: 08 / 2020." type="url" year="2020">Bezark,2020</bibRefCitation>
), antennomere IV not biannulate, pronotum with three tubercles, white pubescent band on center of the elytra is distinctly wider and with sides irregular, oblique dark band on elytra beyond middle is projected downward from sides toward suture, white pubescent band on posterior quarter of the elytra wide and project- ed downward from sides to suture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[793,1419,1210,1843]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" box="[831,1169,1754,1779]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quinquetuberculatus">
<emphasis box="[831,1169,1754,1779]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Xylergates quinquetuberculatus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
can be included in the alternative of couplet “3” from 
<bibRefCitation author="Giorgi, J. A. &amp; Corbett, D." box="[1149,1417,1786,1811]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" pagination="5 - 8" refId="ref8560" refString="Giorgi, J. A. &amp; Corbett, D. 2005. Sinopse do genero Xylergates (Cerambycidae, Lamiinae, Acanthocinini). Iheringia, Zoologia, 95 (1): 5 - 8." type="journal article" year="2005">Giorgi &amp; Corbett (2005)</bibRefCitation>
(translated, modified):
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[794,1420,1882,2131]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
3(2). Elytra with a small projected spine on outer margin of the apex; scutellum unicolorous, with brownish pubescence; elytra with distinct narrow white pubescent lines. 
<collectingCountry box="[1168,1254,1946,1971]" name="Venezuela" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Venezuela</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[1262,1341,1946,1971]" name="Colombia" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Colombia</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[1349,1415,1946,1971]" name="Ecuador" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Ecuador</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[851,932,1978,2003]" name="Suriname" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Suriname</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[946,1010,1978,2003]" name="Guyana" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Guyana</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[1023,1149,1978,2003]" name="French Guiana" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">French Guiana</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[1163,1209,1978,2003]" name="Brazil" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Brazil</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion box="[1224,1263,1978,2003]" country="Brazil" name="Acre" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Acre</collectingRegion>
, Amazonas, Pará, 
<collectingRegion box="[850,931,2010,2035]" country="Brazil" name="Rondonia" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Rondônia</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[939,1042,2010,2035]" country="Brazil" name="Mato Grosso" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Mato Grosso</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[1049,1137,2010,2035]" country="Brazil" name="Maranhao" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Maranhão</collectingRegion>
), 
<collectingCountry box="[1149,1188,2010,2035]" name="Peru" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Peru</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[1196,1251,2010,2035]" name="Bolivia" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Bolivia</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion box="[1262,1302,2010,2035]" country="Bolivia" name="Beni" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Beni</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[1310,1363,2010,2035]" country="Bolivia" name="Pando" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Pando</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion country="Bolivia" name="Santa Cruz" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Santa Cruz</collectingRegion>
).................................................................. 
<taxonomicName authority="Bates, 1864" authorityName="Bates" authorityYear="1864" box="[1243,1417,2042,2067]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="lacteus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1243,1318,2042,2067]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">X.lacteus</emphasis>
Bates,1864
</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[794,1420,1882,2131]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">— Elytra not spiniform on outer margin of the apex;scutellum bicolorous; elytra lacking narrow pubescent lines................................................3’</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[170,796,218,531]" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
3’(3). Elytra with wide,arched white pubescent band on anterior half;elytra with longitudinal dark band on posterior half; white pubescent band on posterior quarter of the elytra projected downward from sides to suture. 
<collectingCountry box="[290,356,314,339]" name="Ecuador" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Ecuador</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[363,427,314,339]" name="Guyana" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Guyana</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[435,554,314,339]" name="French Guiana" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">French Guiana</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[561,638,314,339]" name="Colombia" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Colombia</collectingCountry>
(Amazonas), 
<collectingCountry box="[750,796,314,339]" name="Brazil" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Brazil</collectingCountry>
(Amazonas,Pará, 
<collectingRegion box="[372,453,346,371]" country="Brazil" name="Rondonia" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Rondônia</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingRegion box="[460,565,346,371]" country="Brazil" name="Mato Grosso" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Mato Grosso</collectingRegion>
), 
<collectingCountry box="[576,615,346,371]" name="Peru" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Peru</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[622,677,346,371]" name="Bolivia" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Bolivia</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion box="[686,741,346,371]" country="Bolivia" name="Pando" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Pando</collectingRegion>
)........ ..................................................................... 
<taxonomicName authority="Gilmour, 1962" authorityName="Gilmour" authorityYear="1962" box="[588,794,378,403]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="elaineae">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[588,675,378,403]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">X.elaineae</emphasis>
Gilmour,1962
</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[170,796,218,531]" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
— Elytra lacking wide, arched white pubescent band on anterior half; elytra with oblique dark band on posterior half; white pubescent band on posterior quarter of the elytra projected upward from sides to suture. 
<collectingCountry box="[287,333,506,531]" name="Brazil" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Brazil</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingRegion box="[342,458,506,531]" country="Brazil" name="Espirito Santo" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Espírito Santo</collectingRegion>
)............... 
<taxonomicName authority="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins, 2020" authorityName="Nascimento &amp; Nearns &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva &amp; Martins" authorityYear="2020" box="[544,728,506,531]" class="Insecta" family="Cerambycidae" genus="Xylergates" kingdom="Animalia" order="Coleoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quinquetuberculatus" status="sp.nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[544,728,506,531]" italics="true" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">X.quinquetuberculatus</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[733,795,506,531]" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" rank="species">sp.nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>