<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5720448" ID-GBIF-Dataset="96fae295-c48f-470e-822a-f32408b3a16d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="190572889" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5720448" checkinTime="1633677820725" checkinUser="conny" docAuthor="Don E. Wilson &amp; Russell A. Mittermeier" docDate="2011" docId="EC7D87A1FFF4FF8BE2E0F95CC7D8F33C" docLanguage="en" docName="hbmw_2_Manidae_0082.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 2 Hoofed Mammals, Barcelona: Lynx Edicions" docTitle="Manis temminckii Smuts 1832" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="101" masterDocId="1044FFD9FFF1FF8DE721FF8CC448FF83" masterDocTitle="Manidae" masterLastPageNumber="103" masterPageNumber="95" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" updateTime="1637670409515" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Manidae</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Don E. Wilson</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Russell A. Mittermeier</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2011</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:dateOther type="pubDate">2011-08-31</mods:dateOther>
<mods:publisher>Lynx Edicions</mods:publisher>
<mods:place>
<mods:placeTerm>Barcelona</mods:placeTerm>
</mods:place>
</mods:originInfo>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Handbook of the Mammals of the World – Volume 2 Hoofed Mammals</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>95</mods:start>
<mods:end>103</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>book chapter</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5720458</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">96fae295-c48f-470e-822a-f32408b3a16d</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5720458</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5720448" ID-GBIF-Taxon="190572889" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5720448" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:EC7D87A1FFF4FF8BE2E0F95CC7D8F33C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EC7D87A1FFF4FF8BE2E0F95CC7D8F33C" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="101" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<paragraph blockId="5.[1471,2418,1744,1873]" box="[1473,2279,1744,1790]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<heading box="[1473,2279,1744,1790]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<subSubSection box="[1473,1506,1744,1790]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="multiple">6.</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[1523,1886,1744,1790]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="vernacular_name">Ground Pangolin</subSubSection>
<subSubSection box="[1938,2279,1744,1790]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="nomenclature">
<taxonomicName authorityName="Smuts" authorityYear="1832" box="[1938,2279,1744,1790]" class="Mammalia" family="Manidae" genus="Manis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Pholidota" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="temminckii">
<emphasis box="[1938,2279,1744,1790]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Manis temminckii</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</subSubSection>
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[1471,2418,1744,1873]" lastBlockId="5.[2086,2673,1917,2340]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="vernacular_name">
<heading pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<emphasis box="[1473,1549,1808,1829]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">French:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1559,1784,1808,1829]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Pangolin de Temminck</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis box="[1805,1896,1808,1829]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">German:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1905,2119,1808,1829]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Steppenschuppentier</vernacularName>
/ 
<emphasis box="[2140,2231,1808,1829]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Spanish:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[2241,2417,1808,1829]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Pangolin terrestre</vernacularName>
<emphasis box="[1472,1718,1847,1868]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Other common names:</emphasis>
<vernacularName box="[1726,1940,1847,1868]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Temminck’s Pangolin</vernacularName>
, 
<vernacularName box="[1953,2094,1847,1868]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<collectingRegion box="[1953,2002,1847,1868]" country="South Africa" name="Western Cape" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Cape</collectingRegion>
Pangolin
</vernacularName>
</heading>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="reference_group">
<emphasis box="[2086,2241,1917,1946]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Taxonomy.</emphasis>
<taxonomicName authority="Smuts, 1832" authorityName="Smuts" authorityYear="1832" box="[2255,2666,1917,1946]" class="Mammalia" family="Manidae" genus="Manis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Pholidota" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="temminckii">Manis temminckii Smuts, 1832</taxonomicName>
, Latakou (= Litakun), near Kuruman, 
<collectingRegion box="[2087,2434,2000,2025]" country="South Africa" name="Northern Cape" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Northern Cape Province</collectingRegion>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[2451,2628,2000,2025]" name="South Africa" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">South Africa</collectingCountry>
. Sometimes included in the genus/subgenus Smutsia. Monotypic.
</subSubSection>
</paragraph>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="distribution">
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5720472" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5720472" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5720472/files/figure.png" inLine="true" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" targetBox="[1469,2063,1924,2340]" targetPageId="5">
<paragraph blockId="5.[2086,2673,1917,2340]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<emphasis box="[2086,2262,2109,2142]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Distribution.</emphasis>
Widely but patchily distributed in open areas ranging from E 
<collectingCountry box="[2598,2672,2149,2182]" name="Chad" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Chad</collectingCountry>
and N 
<collectingCountry box="[2201,2568,2188,2221]" name="Central African Republic" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Central African Republic</collectingCountry>
to extreme W 
<collectingCountry box="[2234,2355,2227,2260]" name="Ethiopia" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Ethiopia</collectingCountry>
, then south through most of E Africa to N 
<collectingCountry box="[2423,2605,2275,2300]" name="South Africa" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">South Africa</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry name="Namibia" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Namibia</collectingCountry>
, and C 
<collectingCountry box="[2274,2377,2315,2340]" name="Angola" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Angola</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="5.[1472,2676,2346,3439]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<emphasis box="[1472,1718,2346,2379]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Descriptive notes.</emphasis>
Head—body 45-55 cm, tail 40-52 cm; weight 5-17 kg (but specimens above 20 kg have been reported). A round shield-shaped pangolin with broad scales. There is a linear correlation between body weight and total body length. One pair of pectoral mammae. Adult males larger than females and up to twice as heavy. Head conical and rostrum thin and shorter than in the Giant Pangolin (
<taxonomicName authorityName="Illiger" authorityYear="1815" box="[2403,2564,2503,2536]" class="Mammalia" family="Manidae" genus="Manis" kingdom="Animalia" order="Pholidota" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" phylum="Chordata" rank="species" species="gigantea">M. gigantea</taxonomicName>
), giving a V-shape to the head in dorsal view. Nose pad color similar to the brown skin (may reach dark purple). Auditory orifice without ear pinna. Eyes small and iris dark. Massive scaled armor covering the upper face and the whole body except the belly and innerside of legs; skin and scales constitute one-fourth to one-third of total body mass. Hairs brown rufous, very thin and short on belly (less than 0-3 cm); very sparsely distributed on other skin surfaces. No hairs project between scales. 13 dorsal scale rows. Scales on the distal part of the body at least twice as wide as the first rows of post-scapular scales; from base to tip, scales show a longitudinal, rufous brown to golden color gradient. Scales three-cusped; the main, distal cusp is still visible in old adults, despite general abrasion. Tail shorter than head and body. On tail, medio-dorsal row of scales interrupted half way to tip; injuveniles and subadults, posterior margin is three-cusped (can also be observed on back), whereas cusps—and original shape—tend to disappear with age because of natural abrasion. Ventral part of tail concave, entirely covered by scales. Legs massive, especially hindlegs. Forelegs much shorter than hindlegs. Five long and slightly curved claws on forefeet, especially the third one; walk with weight on outer edge of claws, with claws facing backwards. The five claws on hindfeet kept shorter by soil abrasion (plantigrade posture) than in arboreal species; hind claws only slightly curved. Skull reaching 7-5-9 cm long, pear-shaped, and shorter than in Giant Pangolin. 19-21 caudal vertebrae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="101" pageId="5" pageNumber="100" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="5.[1472,2676,2346,3439]" lastBlockId="6.[98,1306,280,3265]" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="101" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">
<emphasis box="[1473,1584,3288,3321]" pageId="5" pageNumber="100">Habitat.</emphasis>
Various types of woodlands and savannas, often with dense undergrowth (e.g. bushveld and thornbush, in southern Africa). Can also be found in floodplain grassland and farmed areas, except in eastern Africa. May reach elevations up to 1700 m. Range of suitable niche likely conditioned by the abundance of specific groups of termites and ants preyed upon, which may explain its absence in north-eastern and western Africa. 
<collectingRegion box="[314,367,320,353]" country="Cameroon" name="North" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Not</collectingRegion>
presentin forested areas of high rainfall, where the Giant Pangolin lives. Often lives near water sources.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="food_feeding">
<paragraph blockId="6.[98,1306,280,3265]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
<emphasis box="[100,373,398,431]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Food and Feeding.</emphasis>
Almost strictly myrmecophagous; genera preyed upon include Acantholepis, Anoplepsis, Camponotus, Crematogaster, Monsmorium, Myrmicania, Paltothyreus, Pheidole, Polyrhachis, Tapenonian, Technomyremex, Xiphomyremex (ants), and to a lesser extent, Odontotermes, Microcerotermes, Microtermes, Amitermes and Ancistotermes (termites). May be locally highly selective on species ingested; prefers eggs and larvae, probably because they are softer. Larvae of dung beetles can also be eaten. Macrosmatic, continuously sniffing while foraging; search for food is generally nocturnal, but can become diurnal depending on the activity cycles of prey. Opportunistic foraging, searching ground litter and soil fissures for ants and termites; digging to reach prey is not as frequent and deep as in other terrestrial pangolins. Mounds of termites and ants are opened using its powerful forefoot claws, notably the third one. Holes, tunnels, and fissures are sniffed and the sticky tongueis inserted where a large quantity of prey is located. Ant and termite colonies, which are not completely destroyed, usually recover well from raids of the Ground Pangolin. Sometimes also takes pieces of mound, wood, or dung in its forefeet and rolls onto its back to catch prey while manipulating the item. A series of nights is spent foraging in an area of several kilometers, for up to six hours a night, before moving to another area. Feces are dark, sausage-shaped, and have a strong smell; they contain a lot of soil and chitinous remains of prey. The lingual system is dramatically adapted to preying on ants and termites. The tongue reaches 25-40 cm long and 5 mm wide; when feeding, 10-15 cm are protracted and retracted from a pouch located within the throat (similarly to the Giant Pangolin). The tongue is covered with colorless, viscous saliva secreted by large pharyngeal and cervical salivary glands that extend almost to the shoulder. The thin, flat mandibles and weak temporo-mandibular joints seriously limit jaw movements. The tongue is attached ventral to the larynx and trachea, to a characteristically modified xiphisternum (xiphoid process). Xiphoid cartilages form two elongated bars that extend from sternum to pelvic region.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="breeding">
<paragraph blockId="6.[98,1306,280,3265]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
<emphasis box="[100,234,1460,1493]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Breeding.</emphasis>
Males have testes in a fold of skin located in the groin (i.e. not descended into a scrotum). Exact breeding season not clearly delimited. Tails of male and female are entwined when copulating. Gestation takes about 130-150 days. Fetuses of ¢.8 g and 110 g were found in pregnant females in May and July, respectively; no pregnant females were observed between December and February. A single young is born per year, although twins have been reported. At birth, measures 15-18 cm and weighs 340-425 g; eyes are open. From around four weeks, carried clinging to mother’s back or tail (slipping onto her belly when in danger), and can start ingesting living prey. Young is carried until it reaches c.3 kg. Females mate while nursing young. In captivity, females were seen protecting their offspring through bipedal attack; at rest, young is held close to belly and curled under mother’s tail as a protection.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="activity">
<paragraph blockId="6.[98,1306,280,3265]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
<emphasis box="[99,336,1892,1925]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Activity patterns.</emphasis>
A poorly known species. Solitary, terrestrial, and mostly nocturnal. Activity starts late in the afternoon or at dusk, and the pangolins forage all night, sometimes until morning. During the day, they opportunistically rest in terrestrial shelters, termite mounds, or Aardvark (Orycteropus afer) and spring hare (Pedetes spp.) burrows, preferably connected to ant or termite colonies; they rarely dig their own burrows. Typical burrows have a 20-25 cm diameter entrance and 3-5 m long horizontal tunnels, c.1 m below entrance level. The same burrow is occupied several days in a row, and then left for another one. Can walk quadrupedally or bipedally. In quadrupedal walk, feet alternate and tail drags discontinuously on the ground. Bipedal walk is often used when foraging, with tail maintained above the ground for balance and forelegs held in a kangaroo-like carriage. Pelvis is more vertical and tuber coxae more prominent than in other pangolins, allowing regular use of bipedal walk. Sleeps curled up with scales open; when disturbed, scales are pulled down with much force. When walking, reacts to alarming noise by putting head between hindlegs, so to present the dorsal part of the scaled armoras a first defensive posture. In case of imminent danger, rolls into a ball. A female was observed lying on her back in the shade, exposing her belly moistened by urine to cool down body temperature. Capable of climbing, helped by the lateral, sharp scales ofthe tail. Can create a depression on the ground to collect rainwater by gyrating backwards in a tightcircle.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph blockId="6.[98,1306,280,3265]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
<emphasis box="[101,811,2640,2673]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Movements, Home range and Social organization.</emphasis>
Movements of individuals remain unknown. Marks rocks with urine. Density in Kruger National Park (
<collectingCountry box="[1054,1232,2679,2712]" name="South Africa" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">South Africa</collectingCountry>
) was estimated at 0-24 ind/km?.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="conservation">
<paragraph blockId="6.[98,1306,280,3265]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
<emphasis box="[101,446,2758,2791]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Status and Conservation.</emphasis>
CITES Appendix II. Classified as Least Concern on The [UCN Red List because widespread, locally abundant, protected, and distributed in numerous protected areas. Nevertheless, likely to decline locally because of hunting, pesticides— to which it is extremely sensitive—and electric fences. Hunted for meat and scales. Scales are exported from Maputaland (
<collectingCountry box="[663,844,2915,2948]" name="South Africa" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">South Africa</collectingCountry>
) to 
<collectingCountry box="[907,1089,2915,2948]" name="Mozambique" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Mozambique</collectingCountry>
for traditional clothing. In East Africa, burning scalesis believed to keep lions away. In 
<collectingCountry box="[1112,1240,2954,2987]" name="Tanzania" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Tanzania</collectingCountry>
, the Ground Pangolin is named “Bwana mganga” (doctor), each portion ofits body having specific healing power. In 
<collectingCountry box="[532,678,3033,3066]" name="Zimbabwe" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Zimbabwe</collectingCountry>
, seeing a Ground Pangolin is a good omen and it is traditional to offerit to local or spiritual authorities. Supposed to be close to extinction in 
<collectingCountry box="[292,548,3111,3144]" name="South Africa" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Orange Free State</collectingCountry>
(
<collectingCountry box="[572,751,3111,3144]" name="South Africa" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">South Africa</collectingCountry>
) and probably exterminated in several parts ofits range.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="101" type="reference_group">
<paragraph blockId="6.[98,1306,280,3265]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">
<emphasis box="[102,255,3198,3223]" pageId="6" pageNumber="101">Bibliography.</emphasis>
Botha &amp; Gaudin (2007), van Ee (1966), Heath (1992b), Heath &amp; Coulson (1997, 1998), Hoffmann (2008c), Jacobsen et al. (1991), Kingdon (1997), Kyle (2000), Stuart (1980).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>