<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302" ID-GBIF-Dataset="758f5696-6157-4383-8c42-21466df0f3bb" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030276" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-117-29" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F8E59EAB-64AD-46A5-9B37-FB1C64B4CB87" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-117-29" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 117" ModsDocTitle="Five new species of the genus Cryptopimpla Taschenberg (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) with a key to species known from China" checkinTime="1451250191811" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Sheng, Mao-Ling" docDate="2011" docId="84E1DB8965FDD2AF48F7F36DBACACA61" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 117: 29-49" docOrigin="ZooKeys 117" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302" docTitle="Cryptopimpla maculifacialis Sheng, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="F8E59EAB-64AD-46A5-9B37-FB1C64B4CB87" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="40" masterDocId="B014FF916931FFFEFF8AEA382515FFBC" masterDocTitle="Five new species of the genus Cryptopimpla Taschenberg (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) with a key to species known from China" masterLastPageNumber="49" masterPageNumber="29" pageId="9" pageNumber="38" updateTime="1643716313934" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Five new species of the genus Cryptopimpla Taschenberg (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) with a key to species known from China</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sheng, Mao-Ling</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>117</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>29</mods:start>
<mods:end>49</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.117.1302</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-117-29</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">BB38479A-4AB2-4A61-A748-B0E716EEAC1C</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030276" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F8E59EAB-64AD-46A5-9B37-FB1C64B4CB87" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/84E1DB8965FDD2AF48F7F36DBACACA61" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="40" pageId="9" pageNumber="38">
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="38" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="38">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F8E59EAB-64AD-46A5-9B37-FB1C64B4CB87" authority="Sheng" class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cryptopimpla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cryptopimpla maculifacialis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="9" pageNumber="38" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculifacialis">Cryptopimpla maculifacialis Sheng</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="9" pageNumber="38">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 16-19
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="38" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="38">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="38">The specific name is derived from the face, which has a dark fleck.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="9" pageNumber="38" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="38">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="9" pageNumber="38">
Holotype: female, CHINA: Shuangjiang Forest Farm, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ji’an">Ji'an</normalizedToken>
, Jiangxi Province, 15 June 2008, leg. Yi Kuang. Paratypes: 1 male, CHINA: Matubei, 320m, Quannan, Jiangxi Province, 6 May 2009, leg. Shi-Chang Li. 1 male, CHINA: Wokou, 320m, Quannan, Jiangxi Province, 13 May 2009, leg. Shi-Chang Li. 1 male, CHINA: 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="39" start="start">Citangbei</pageBreakToken>
, 378m, Quannan, Jiangxi Province, 27 May 2009, leg. Shi-Chang Li. 1 male, CHINA: Shuangjiang Forest Farm, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Ji’an">Ji'an</normalizedToken>
, Jiangxi Province, 1 June 2009, leg. Da-Lin Li.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="39" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="39">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="39">Mesosoma with fine leathery texture. Ovipositor sheath shorter than first tergum. Face white with median longitudinal black band. Flagellomeres 10 to 16 white. Scutellum yellowish white. Basal-median portion of first tergum white to yellowish white.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="40" pageId="10" pageNumber="39" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="39">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="39">Female. Body length about 8.3 mm. Fore wing length about 6.2 mm. Ovipositor sheath length about 1.6 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="39">Head. Face (Fig. 17) slightly convergent ventrally, approximately 1.7 times as wide as long, median portion evenly convex, with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.1 to 0.3 times diameter of puncture; lateral portion with punctures almost contacting each other as transverse wrinkles, upper margin with small median tubercle. Clypeus approximately 2.2 times as wide as long, smooth, evenly convex, basal portion with sparse, fine punctures, apical portion almost impunctate; apical margin thick, convex, with relatively long hairs. Mandible strong, with weak, fine punctures, distance between punctures 0.5 to 2.0 times diameter of puncture. Upper tooth sharp, longer than lower tooth. Malar space, gena, vertex and frons with fine leathery texture. Malar space approximately 0.5 times as long as basal width of mandible, with indistinct punctures. Gena slightly convergent posteriorly, with distinct punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 1.5 times diameter of puncture. Vertex (Fig. 18) with punctures slightly denser than on gena. Interocellar area slightly convex. Postocellar line approximaly 1.1 times as long as ocular-ocellar line. Frons almost flat, with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.1 to 0.5 times diameter of puncture, almost contacting each other transversely. Upper median portion, below median ocellus, concave. Antenna with 34 flagellomeres, each flagellomere longer than wide; ratio of length from first to fifth flagellomeres: 6.4:4.4:4.2:4.0:3.7. Occipital carina complete, lower end joining hypostomal carina above base of mandible.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="40" pageId="10" pageNumber="39">
Mesosoma. Mesosoma with fine leathery texture. Anterior margin of pronotum with elongate punctures, lateral concavity with short transverse wrinkles, posterior portion with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 0.5 times diameter of puncture. Mesoscutum evenly convex, with punctures as on posterior portion of pronotum. Without notaulus. Scutellum slightly convex, with sparse, shallow, irregular punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 3.0 times diameter of puncture, without lateral carina. Postscutellum transverse, with weak punctures, anterior portion with transverse concavity and deep lateral pit. Mesopleuron (Fig. 19) with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.2 to 1.0 times diameter of puncture. Upper end of epicnemial carina reaching level of lower third of front margin of mesopleuron, distant from front margin of mesopleuron. Mesopleural fovea deep. Without speculum. Metapleuron with denser, finer punctures than mesopleuron. Front portion of submetapleural carina convex, as a broad lobe. Without juxtacoxal carina. Wings brownish hyaline. Vein 1cu-a distal of 1/M, distance between them approximately 0.4 times length of 1cu-a. Areolet quadrate, vein 3rs-m distinctly longer than 2rs-m, receiving vein 2m-cu approximately at 0.7 distance from vein 2rs-m to 3rs-m. Vein 2-Cu slightly longer than 2cu-a. Hind wing vein 1/cu about 2 times as long as cu-a. Legs comparatively robust. Ratio of length of hind tarsomeres 10.0:4.6:3.2:1.7:2.1. Claws simple. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="40" start="start">Propodeum</pageBreakToken>
evenly convex, with dense, fine, indistinct punctures. Posterior transverse carina complete and strong. Pleural carina weak. Propodeal spiracle almost round.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">Metasoma. First tergum approximately 1.6 times as long as apical width, evenly narrowed towards base, rough, with dense, indistinct punctures, lateral portion with short longitudinal wrinkles, median dorsal carina indistinct, basal portion of dorsolateral carina present, spiracle small, weakly convex, slightly before middle of tergum. Second tergum about 0.9 times as long as apical width, with dense punctures, distance between punctures 0.1 to 0.5 times diameter of puncture, apical margin narrowly smooth, basal margin with transverse thyridium, spiracle distinctly convex. Third tergum with finer punctures than second tergum. Fourth tergum almost smooth, indistinctly punctate. Following terga smooth, with more or less clear fine transverse lines. Ovipositor sheath approximately 0.5 times as long as hind tibia, 0.9 times as long as first tergum. Ovipositor evenly upcurved and compressed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">Color. (Fig. 16). Black, except the following. White portions: ventral profile of scape and pedicel, flagellomeres 10 to 16 and apical portion of 9, face except upper narrow margin and median longitudinal band and short elongate spot below antennal socket, clypeus except apical half yellowish brown, mandible except teeth, maxillary palpus except apical 2 segments yellowish brown, labial palpus except apical segment yellowish brown, upper-posterior corner of pronotum, elongate spot on latero-anterior portion of mesoscutum, subalar ridge, scutellum, ventral profile of front coxa and trochanter, ventral profile of middle coxa, basal-median portion of tergum 1, apical bands of terga 1 to 3, narrow apical margins of terga 4 to 7. Legs reddish brown. Basal-ventral sides of front and middle femora, dorsal sides of basal portions of front and middle tibiae, basal portion of hind tibia and tarsomeres 1 to 4 white. Apex of hind coxa, hind trochantellus, apical portion of hind femur, apical half of hind tibia, and hind tarsomere 5 black. Stigma dark brown. Veins brownish black.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">Male. Body length 8.5 to 8.8 mm. Fore wing length 6.3 to 6.5 mm. Antenna with 33 to 34 flagellomeres. Face yellow with irregular transverse black band to almost entirely black.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="40" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">The face of one male specimen is almost enitrely black, with only very narrow sublateral yellow lines. Tergum 1 of male with basal and apical portions white to unevenly brownish yellow with two small longitudinal black spots.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="40" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">
Similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cryptopimpla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cryptopimpla flavifacialis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavifacialis">Cryptopimpla flavifacialis</taxonomicName>
Sheng, but can be distinguished from the latter in having the first tergum approximately 1.6 times as long as apical width, mesosoma with fine leathery texture, metapleuron with denser and finer punctures than mesopleuron, face white with median longitudinal black band, flagellomeres 10 to 16 white, scutellum yellowish white, basal median portion of tergum 1 white to yellowish white. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cryptopimpla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cryptopimpla flavifacialis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="flavifacialis">Cryptopimpla flavifacialis</taxonomicName>
: first tergum 1.8 to 1.9 times as long as apical width, mesosoma with smooth texture, metapleuron with punctures as on mesopleuron, face yellow, without median longitudinal black band, median to subapical portion of flagella yellowish brown, without white portion, scutellum black, basal portion of tergum 1 black.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="11" pageNumber="40">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="40">
Figures 16-19. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Ichneumonidae" genus="Cryptopimpla" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cryptopimpla maculifacialis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="40" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="maculifacialis">Cryptopimpla maculifacialis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Female 16 Body, lateral view 17 Face 18 Vertex 19 Mesopleuron.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>