<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6236515" ID-GBIF-Dataset="532d37fe-3808-427a-8c44-bd65f15e1b6d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134690" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6236515" ModsDocAuthor="Cover, S. P. &amp; Deyrup, M." ModsDocDate="2007" ModsDocID="21276" ModsDocOrigin="http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/15367" ModsDocTitle="A new ant genus from the southwestern United States." checkinTime="1243372115870" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Cover, S. P. &amp; Deyrup, M." docDate="2007" docId="A293A03F12EA84F0538AEA2E4908A907" docLanguage="en" docName="21276" docOrigin="Advances in ant systematics (Hymenoptera: Formicidae): Homage to E. O. Wilson - 50 years of contributions. (Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 80)" docSource="http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/15367" docTitle="Dolopomyrmex Cover &amp; Deyrup, 2007, new genus" docType="treatment" docVersion="10" lastPageNumber="92" masterDocId="AC6E6FD308147B85F14480D310486867" masterDocTitle="A new ant genus from the southwestern United States." masterLastPageNumber="99" masterPageNumber="89" pageNumber="90" updateTime="1645591647184" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new ant genus from the southwestern United States.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cover, S. P.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Deyrup, M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Editor</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Snelling, R. R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Editor</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fisher, B. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Editor</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ward, P. S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2007</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="title">
<mods:title>Advances in ant systematics (Hymenoptera: Formicidae): Homage to E. O. Wilson - 50 years of contributions.</mods:title>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>80</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>89</mods:start>
<mods:end>99</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/15367</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">21276</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6236515" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100134690" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6236515" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A293A03F12EA84F0538AEA2E4908A907" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A293A03F12EA84F0538AEA2E4908A907" lastPageNumber="92" pageNumber="90">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="90">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:223486" authority="Cover &amp; Deyrup, 2007" authorityName="Cover &amp; Deyrup" authorityYear="2007" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Dolopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Dolopomyrmex Cover &amp; Deyrup" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="90" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Dolopomyrmex</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="genus">new genus</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="90">Figures 1 - 3</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="90">Diagnosis of Worker. Monomorphic subterranean myrmicine ants with the following combination of characters:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">1) Palp formula 3,2</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">2) Mandible with 4 teeth and strongly oblique cutting margin, the largest gap between mandibular teeth separating the basal tooth from the third subapical tooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">3) Clypeus ecarinate. Median clypeal seta absent, instead anterior margin with pair of long, ventrally curved setae, one on each side of the midpoint, flanked laterally by fringe of 5 - 6 long, forward-projecting setae on each side of the clypeal margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">4) Median portion of clypeus narrow, strongly elevated, antennal insertions closely approximated.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">5) Frontal lobes small, subtriangular, fully covering condylar bulbs of antennae. Frontal carinae absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">6) Eyes vestigial or entirely absent, when present, consisting only of the remnant of a single ommatidium.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">7) Antennae 11 segmented, with an enormous 3 segmented apical club longer than the remainder of the funiculus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">8) Mesosoma elongate, in profile, compressed laterally at promesonotal juncture with propodeum giving it a distinctive hourglass shape in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">9) Metanotal impression present, propodeum lacking teeth or spines, in profile dorsally convex, with flat posterior face in side view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">10) Propodeal spiracle circular, of moderate size. Metapleural gland well-developed. Metapleural lobes small, rounded and inconspicuous.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="90">11) Petiole with short, indistinct peduncle, node low, rounded, suborbicular in dorsal view. Subpetiolar process absent. Spiracle circular, located laterally on the anterior slope of the node.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">12) Postpetiole low and rounded in profile, lacking a ventral projection or tooth, suborbicular in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">
13) Tergite and sternite of the fourth abdominal segment meeting to produce an angulate corner on each side of the postpetiole seen in dorsal view, as in the unrelated myrmicine genus 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:24885" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Pheidole" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Pheidole Westwood" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pheidole</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">14) Sting simple, robust.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">15) Outer surfaces of middle and hind tibiae and tarsomeres with abundant stiff, spine-like, erect to suberect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">Diagnosis of Queen. As in worker except:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">1) Enormous in comparison with worker caste. ML always&gt; TL of largest workers.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">2) Mandible with strongly oblique cutting margin and 4 teeth that decrease progressively in size from apical to basal.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">3) Submedian ventrally curved setae on anterior clypeal margin not clearly separable from other setae present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">4) Ventral surface of head with abundant, curved, delicate erect setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">5) Compound eyes large, with scattered very short, stubble-like, erect setae. Ocelli welldeveloped but small.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">6) Antennae 11 segmented as in worker, 3 segmented apical club present, but less pronounced.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">7) Body in general somewhat flattened, probably as an adaptation for subterranean life.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">8) Mesosoma massive, with full complement of sclerites associated with the presence of wings.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">9) Petiolar node subrectangular, wider than long, in dorsal view. Postpetiole subelliptic in dorsal view.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">10) Spine-like erect setae abundant on outer surface of hind tibia, especially abundant on the outer tibial surface of the middle leg.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">Diagnosis of Male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">1) Palpal formula 2,1. Palps very short.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">2) Mandible strap-like, with strongly oblique cutting margin and 4 teeth, decreasing progressively in size from the apex. Rarely, 1 - 2 teeth may be absent, leaving only the apical and subapical teeth present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">3) As in worker caste, clypeus ecarinate, median clypeal seta absent, paired submedian ventrally curved setae present.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">4) Median portion of clypeus narrow, elevated, antennal insertions closely approximated.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">5) Frontal lobes small, only partly covering the condylar bulbs, frontal carinae absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">6) Compound eyes large, with short erect setae as in queen. Ocelli well-developed but small.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">7) Antennae 11 segmented, with large 3 segmented club. First antennal segment greatly enlarged to form distinct scape longer than the apical club.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">8) Mesosoma massive, alate, wing venation as in Fig. 3. Propodeum lacking teeth or spines, spiracle lenticular, metapleural lobes very small.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">9) Petiolar node low and rounded in profile, peduncle absent. Petiolar spiracles located at the tips of large, laterally projecting connules.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">10) Postpetiole unique, as in Fig. 3. Attachment to fourth abdominal segment extraordinarily broad, spiracles as in petiole, located at the tips of large, laterally projecting connules.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="91">11) Erect or suberect setae present on outer surfaces of middle and hind tibiae, but neither stiff and spine-like, nor as abundant as in the female castes.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="91">
Type species: 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:223487" authority="Cover &amp; Deyrup, 2007" authorityName="Cover &amp; Deyrup" authorityYear="2007" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Dolopomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Dolopomyrmex pilatus Cover &amp; Deyrup" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="91" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pilatus">Dolopomyrmex pilatus Cover &amp; Deyrup</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="etymology">
<paragraph pageNumber="92">Etymology: Dolops, Dolopos (ancient Greek,lurker in ambush) + myrmex, myrmekos (Greek,ant).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>