<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e8e04fdf-7ade-4df5-9a33-951aa243f7b3" ID-GBIF-Taxon="139438644" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-724-101" ID-ZBK="5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:31953FC2-6002-496D-8CE1-F24EA7E67D0C" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-724-101" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 724" ModsDocTitle="Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)" checkinTime="1513881619487" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Rong, Hua &amp; Li, Houhun" docDate="2017" docId="CF47C6C437BF38B4B532C3398BF33CDB" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 724: 101-118" docOrigin="ZooKeys 724" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262" docTitle="Locastra nigrilineata Rong &amp; Li, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="31953FC2-6002-496D-8CE1-F24EA7E67D0C" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="105" masterDocId="A540DC10FF9A2C5FFFF07461FF83FF84" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="118" masterPageNumber="101" pageId="2" pageNumber="103" updateTime="1643574149427" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the genus Locastra Walker, 1859 from China, with descriptions of four new species (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae, Epipaschiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Rong, Hua</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Houhun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>724</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>101</mods:start>
<mods:end>118</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.724.13262</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-724-101</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5CC0385F61974831A05B10F28324C82C</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="139438644" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:31953FC2-6002-496D-8CE1-F24EA7E67D0C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CF47C6C437BF38B4B532C3398BF33CDB" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="105" pageId="2" pageNumber="103">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="103" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="103">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/31953FC2-6002-496D-8CE1-F24EA7E67D0C" class="Insecta" family="Pyralidae" genus="Locastra" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Locastra nigrilineata" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="103" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="nigrilineata">Locastra nigrilineata</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="103">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 4, 9, 14
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="104" pageId="2" pageNumber="103" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="103">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="103">
Holotype: ♂ - CHINA, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Lao’an">Lao'an</normalizedToken>
(
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="555" value="30.33">30.33°N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="5555" value="119.4">119.4°E</geoCoordinate>
), Mt. Tianmu, Zhejiang, 555 m, 5.VII.2014, coll. Aihui Yin, Xuemei Hu and Qingyun Wang, slide No. RH15430.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="104" pageId="2" pageNumber="103">
Paratypes: (17♂, 3♀) - Guizhou: 1♂, Neila, Limingguan, Libo County, 800 m, 18.VII.2015, coll. Meiqing Yang and Gaeun Lee, slide No. RH15425; 1♂, Limingguan, Libo County, 820 m, 21.VII.2015, coll. Meiqing Yang and Gaeun Lee, slide No. RH15428; Hainan: 1♀, Diaoluoshan Nature Reserves, 922 m, 26.V.2015, coll. Peixin Cong, Wei Guan and Sha Hu, slide No. RH16152; Jiangxi: 1♀, Mt. Jiulian, 21.VII.2006, coll. Jiasheng Xu and Weichun Li; Zhejiang: 2♂, Mt. Tianmu, 325 m, 26.VI.2013, coll. Aihui Yin and Xiuchun Wang; 5♂, Huangtanyu, Mt. Jiulong, 467 m, 3-9.VII.2013, coll. Aihui Yin and Xiuchun Wang; 1♂, Yanping, Mt. Jiulong, 530 m, 4.VII.2013, coll. Aihui Yin and Xiuchun Wang; 2♂, Zhangkengkou, Mt. Jiulong, 623 m, 5.VII.2013, coll. Aihui Yin and Xiuchun Wang; 3♂, Jiufu, Mt. Longtang, 520 m, 26.VII.2014, coll. Aihui Yin, Xuemei Hu and Qingyun Wang, slide No. RH15247; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="104" start="start">1</pageBreakToken>
♂, Mt. Tianmu, 335 m, 20.VII.2015, coll. Aihui Yin, Kang Lou and Tao Wang, slide No. RH15429; 1♀, Laofoyan, Shuangxikou, Jiangshan, 424 m, 7.VIII.2016, coll. Qingyun Wang, Meiqing Yang and Ping Liu; 1♂, Linkeng, Yongjia, 387 m, 24.VIII.2016, coll. Qingyun Wang, Meiqing Yang and Ping Liu, slide No. RH16455.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="104" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="104">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="104">
This species is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. subtrapezia" pageId="3" pageNumber="104" rank="species" species="subtrapezia">L. subtrapezia</taxonomicName>
sp. n. in both forewing pattern and male genitalia. It can be distinguished by the long scape extension apically reaching the mesothorax; in male genitalia by the straight posterior margin of the juxta and the very short cornutus approx 1/14 length of the phallus. In 
<taxonomicName genus="L." lsidName="L. subtrapezia" pageId="3" pageNumber="104" rank="species" species="subtrapezia">L. subtrapezia</taxonomicName>
sp. n., the extremely short sub-globose scape extension 
<normalizedToken originalValue="doesn’t">doesn't</normalizedToken>
apically reach the patagium; the posterior margin of the juxta is concave medially and the long cornutus is approx 2/7 length of the phallus.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="105" pageId="3" pageNumber="104" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="104">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="105" pageId="3" pageNumber="104">
Adult (Fig. 4) wingspan 41.0-46.0 mm. Head earthy yellow in male, yellowish white in female. Male labial palpus white on inner side, grayish green mixed with reddish fuscous on outer side; first segment half length of second; second segment reaching vertex apically, inner side with dense long hair-like scales white on basal half and grayish green on distal half; third segment approx 1/6 length of second, tapering. Female labial palpus slightly porrect, widened distally, white on inner side, reddish fuscous mixed with black on outer side; first segment approx 1/4 length of second; second segment with inner side bearing long white hair-like scales on distal half; third segment approx 1/5 length of second, tapering. Maxillary palpus compressed, short, white mixed with reddish fuscous and grayish green. Antenna with ventral surface yellowish fuscous, with short pale gray cilia longer in male than in female; dorsal surface dirty white mixed with fuscous; scape extension strongly developed, reaching mesothorax, dirty white mixed with reddish fuscous, also with grayish green basally, with long dirty white mixed with reddish fuscous hair-like scales ventrally and apically. Thorax and tegula dirty white mixed with black. Forewing with basal area dirty white mottled reddish fuscous, grayish green with reddish fuscous on anterior 1/4, mixed with black along dorsum; median area blackish gray, grayish green on anterior 1/4; distal area grayish green mixed with black; antemedian line black, wavy, extending from basal 1/3 of costal margin slightly oblique outward to before middle of dorsum; postmedian line slightly darker than median area, ill defined, serrate, from 2/3 of costal margin directed obliquely inward to anterior 1/5 from costa, then outward to M3, inward to CuP, finally straight to 5/6 of dorsum and forming a right angle with dorsum, edged with grayish white along outer margin; glandular swelling yellowish fuscous; longitudinal black line from base to before antemedian line below lower margin of cell, interrupted with white and black tuft beyond middle; discocellular spot small, indistinct, represented by black mixed with reddish fuscous tuft; terminal line dirty white, with uniform black rectangular spots evenly spaced along its inner side, interrupted with dirty white on veins. Hindwing gray, darkening from base toward apex; postmedian line dark gray, edged with dirty white along outer margin, ill-defined, extending from M1 slightly arched outward to 1A. Cilia of both wings pale pink, interrupted with black on extension of veins. Legs white on inner side; on outer side, fore femur dirty white mixed with reddish fuscous and grayish green, tibia and tarsus grayish green mixed with black, mid 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="105" start="start">femur</pageBreakToken>
grayish green mixed with black, tibia dirty white mixed with grayish green, with dense long pale pink hair-like scales, tarsus black mixed with grayish green, hind femur grayish green mixed with black and reddish fuscous, tibia pale pink mixed with black, with dense long pale pink hair-like scales, tarsus black mixed with grayish green, all tarsi white at apex of each tarsomere. Abdomen black, mixed with white and grayish green, 3rd to 6th segments white posteriorly on dorsal surface.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Male genitalia (Fig. 9). Uncus sub-rectangular, approximately 1.8 times longer than wide, slightly widened distally, distal 1/3 with dense short setae dorsally. Gnathos lateral arms slender, joined from 3/5; distal process hooked. Valva approximately twice as long as maximum width, with dense long hairs; costa straight, reaching before apex of valva; ventral margin obtuse, curved band from ventrobasal corner to base of juxta approximately 1.3 times length of ventral margin. Vinculum approximately twice as long as uncus. Juxta horizontally extended outward in triangle proximally, basal 3/5 separated, lateral arms straight and parallel from near proximal base; distal 2/5 merged sub-rectangularly, straight on posterior margin; posterolateral lobe almost membranous, semicircular, with short hairs; slender lateral arm extending from basal 2/3 at right angle not reaching vinculum. Phallus membranous in basal 2/3, weakly sclerotized in distal 1/3, approximately 1.3 times length of valva; dorsal sclerotized plate sub-rounded, much smaller than ventral plate; cornutus very short, approx 1/14 length of phallus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Female genitalia (Fig. 14). Papillae anales shovel-shaped, narrowly rounded posteriorly, with dense fine hairs. Eighth segment sub-rectangular, with sparse long hairs posteriorly; tergite almost membranous anteriorly and posteriorly; sternite narrow, membranous medially. Apophyses anteriores approximately 1.2 times length of apophyses posteriores. Antrum annular. Ductus bursae with basal 3/5 straight, distal 2/5 S shaped, with longitudinal ridges. Corpus bursae sub-circular, approx 2/5 length of ductus bursae; signa long, ovate, with longitudinal ridge along central line.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="105" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">China (Guizhou, Hainan, Jiangxi, Zhejiang).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="105" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="105">The specific name is derived from the Latin nigr- and lineatus, referring to the forewing with black line from the base to before the antemedian line below the lower margin of the cell.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>