<document ENCODING="UTF8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6288452" ID-GBIF-Dataset="fb222747-aef6-419c-95c7-59bc8aa19625" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116598" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6288452" ModsDocAuthor=" &amp; Wheeler, W. M." ModsDocDate="1923" ModsDocID="3374" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3374/3374.pdf" ModsDocTitle="Ants of the genera Myopias and Acanthoponera." checkinTime="1264889117264" checkinUser="claudia" docAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." docDate="1923" docId="AF0A33F196129E8356E11C948D8D3C19" docLanguage="en" docName="3374_tx1.xml" docOrigin="Psyche 30" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3374/3374.pdf" docTitle="Acanthoponera (Anacanthoponera) leae Wheeler, 1923, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="183" masterDocId="31B58FA601A566F82737B7A205FCB538" masterDocTitle="Ants of the genera Myopias and Acanthoponera." masterLastPageNumber="192" masterPageNumber="175" pageNumber="181" updateTime="1645824868570" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Ants of the genera Myopias and Acanthoponera.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wheeler, W. M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Psyche</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1923</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>30</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>175</mods:start>
<mods:end>192</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/3374/3374.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">3374</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6288452" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100116598" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6288452" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:AF0A33F196129E8356E11C948D8D3C19" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF0A33F196129E8356E11C948D8D3C19" lastPageNumber="183" pageNumber="181">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="181">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:138751" authorityName="Wheeler" authorityYear="1923" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Acanthoponera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Acanthoponera (Anacanthoponera) leae Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="181" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leae" status="sp. nov." subGenus="Anacanthoponera">Acanthoponera (Anacanthoponera) leae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="181">(Fig. 3.)</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="181">Worker. Length 4 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="183" pageNumber="181">
Head subrectangular, a little longer than broad and very slightly narrower in front than behind, the posterior border 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="182">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="182">rather</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
deeply and broadly concave, the sides feebly and evenly convex, the median longitudinal costa, or carina, extending back over the front and vertex, very pronounced. Eyes rather small, moderately convex, their anterior orbits just behind the median transverse diameter of the head. Mandibles large and broad, their external border rather straight in the middle, the terminal border with only three distinct large apical teeth, the more basal denticles appearing as mere undulations. Clypeus sharply 
<normalizedToken originalValue="carínate">carinate</normalizedToken>
, its anterior border entire, broadly rounded and depressed; frontal area short and indistinct, with a median carina continuous with those of the clypeus and dorsal surface of the head; frontal carinae separated as in 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:138745" authorityName="Emery" authorityYear="1895" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Acanthoponera" genus.completionEvidence="missing, matching species" genus.innerRound="1" genus.outerRound="1" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Acanthoponera imbellis Emery" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="182" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="imbellis" subGenus.completionEvidence="missing, matching species" subGenus.innerRound="1" subGenus.outerRound="1">imbellis</taxonomicName>
, subparallel, scarcely reaching to the level of the anterior orbits, bordering a depressed area on each side for the accomodation of the antennae. Scapes of the latter reaching somewhat beyond the eyes; funicular joints 2-7 subequal, transverse but less so than in 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:138745" authorityName="Emery" authorityYear="1895" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Acanthoponera" genus.completionEvidence="missing, matching species" genus.innerRound="1" genus.outerRound="1" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Acanthoponera imbellis Emery" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="182" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="imbellis" subGenus.completionEvidence="missing, matching species" subGenus.innerRound="1" subGenus.outerRound="1">imbellis</taxonomicName>
, the three terminal joints forming an indistinct club, the last joint somewhat longer than the two preceding subequal joints together. Thorax in profile feebly rounded above, slightly more convex and broadest in the region of the pronotum, which is transversely subrectangular, with distinctly dentate anterior corners, the teeth being nearly as long as the width of their bases. Promesonotal suture subangular, distinct but not strongly impressed; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="mesoëpinotal">mesoepinotal</normalizedToken>
suture obsolete. Mesonotum short, broader than long, somewhat semicircular. Epinotum with nearly straight base which is distinctly longer than the abrupt, slightly concave declivity, the lateral angles between the two surfaces forming stout, broad, rather acute and erect teeth. The declivity is longitudinally grooved in the middle but not marginate on the sides below. Petiolar node cuneate in profile, about one and one-half times as high as long, narrowed above, its summit produced in the middle as a short, stout, erect spine; seen from above the node is somewhat hexagonal, broader than long, the median transverse diameter corresponding with the narrowed, transverse summit. At the anteroventral end of the petiole there is an acute, backwardly directed tooth. Postpetiole very large, longer than broad, narrowed in front, where its anterior surface is abruptly truncated and concave, its 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="183">
<pageStartToken pageNumber="183">sides</pageStartToken>
</pageStartToken>
convex, its anteroventral edge with a transverse tubercle. Gaster small and short, much smaller than the postpetiole, the first segment convex above, semicircular, scarcely longer than broad, enveloping the remaining segments which are very small and together form a downwardly directed cone. Sting small. Legs rather long and stout; tarsal claws simple.
</paragraph>
<caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="181">
Fig. 3. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:138751" authorityName="Wheeler" authorityYear="1923" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Acanthoponera" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Acanthoponera (Anacanthoponera) leae Wheeler" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="181" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="leae" status="sp. nov." subGenus="Anacanthoponera">Acanthoponera (Anacanthoponera) leae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
worker, a, head, from above; thorax and abdomen in profile.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageNumber="183">
Opaque; mandibles somewhat shining, finely striate and coarsely punctate, the striae and punctures more numerous near the apical border. Clypeus finely and indistinctly punctaterugulose. Head between and behind the frontal carinae coarsely and divergently longitudinally rugose, with coarse punctures, or foveolaee in the interrugal spaces; sides of head with the rows of foveolaee more distinct. Thorax, petiole, postpetiole and first gastric segment coarsely rugose and foveolate, the rugae vermiculate and reticulate on the pronotum and petiole, longitudinal on the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="mesoëpinotum">mesoepinotum</normalizedToken>
, including the epinotal declivity, mesopleurae, postpetiole and first gastric segment, most sharply on the two latter regions. Terminal gastric segments smoother and somewhat shining; scapes and legs subopaque, densely punctate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="183">Hairs yellow, fine, uneven, rather abundant and rather short, erect or suberect on the body; the appendages covered with abundant, fine, rather appressed hairs with fewer, interspersed, long, erect hairs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="183">
Deep castaneous brown; mandibles, scapes, tip of gaster and legs, excluding the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxœ">coxoe</normalizedToken>
, yellowish brown; apical borders of mandibles and median carina of head black.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="183">Described from two specimens taken by Mr. A. M. Lea in the National Park, near Sydney, New South Wales.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="183">
This very distinct species is interesting because, unlike the other known Australasian species of the genus, it approaches the Neotropical 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:24699" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Acanthoponera" genus.completionEvidence="missing, matching species" genus.innerRound="2" genus.outerRound="1" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Acanthoponera mucronata (Roger)" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="183" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mucronata">mucronata</taxonomicName>
in the armature of the petiole.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>