<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.605.9338" ID-GBIF-Dataset="36484b54-61c3-4542-9be7-f428b78f31ca" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127889410" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-605-53" ID-ZBK="755057764A2441A586441CC292519090" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:690B5097-63CA-44FB-9B8B-6EBFFA2EA9AA" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-605-53" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 605" ModsDocTitle="The first geophilid centipedes from Malesia: a new genus with two new species from Sumatra (Chilopoda, Geophilidae)" checkinTime="1468535301504" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Bonato, Lucio, Klarner, Bernhard, Widyastuti, Rahayu &amp; Scheu, Stefan" docDate="2016" docId="C459E81D49F5326F63E6B3308B1FEC7B" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 605: 53-71" docOrigin="ZooKeys 605" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.605.9338" docTitle="Sundageophilus poriger Bonato, Klarner, Widyastuti &amp; Scheu, 2016, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="690B5097-63CA-44FB-9B8B-6EBFFA2EA9AA" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="5" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="65" masterDocId="FFEEA250D07CFF871A73FE5AFFA1A958" masterDocTitle="The first geophilid centipedes from Malesia: a new genus with two new species from Sumatra (Chilopoda, Geophilidae)" masterLastPageNumber="71" masterPageNumber="53" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" updateTime="1643626576631" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The first geophilid centipedes from Malesia: a new genus with two new species from Sumatra (Chilopoda, Geophilidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bonato, Lucio</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Klarner, Bernhard</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Widyastuti, Rahayu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Scheu, Stefan</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>605</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>53</mods:start>
<mods:end>71</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.605.9338</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.605.9338</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-605-53</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">755057764A2441A586441CC292519090</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">755057764A2441A586441CC292519090</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127889410" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:690B5097-63CA-44FB-9B8B-6EBFFA2EA9AA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C459E81D49F5326F63E6B3308B1FEC7B" lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Taxon classification Animalia Geophilomorpha Geophilidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/690B5097-63CA-44FB-9B8B-6EBFFA2EA9AA" class="Chilopoda" family="Geophilidae" genus="Sundageophilus" higherTaxonomySource="treatment-meta" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sundageophilus poriger" order="Geophilomorpha" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="poriger">Sundageophilus poriger</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="8" pageNumber="61">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
A 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Geophilidae" genus="Sundageophilus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sundageophilus" order="Geophilomorpha" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Sundageophilus</taxonomicName>
species with cephalic plate ca. 1.3 times as long as wide; first maxillary telopodite composed of two articles; no distinct denticles on the trochanteroprefemur; tarsungulum with a single basal denticle; approximately 31 pairs of legs; ventral pore-fields from the first to the penultimate leg-bearing segment; ultimate metasternite ca. 1.5-1.6 times as wide as long, anteriorly ca. 2.6 times as wide as posteriorly, lateral margins almost straight; four coxal pores on each coxopleuron, of which two along the lateral margin of the metasternite; legs of the ultimate pair not swollen in the female, unknown in the male, composed of six articles including distinct trochanter and prefemur, without disto-ventral bulges and without additional dense ventral setae; pretarsus of the ultimate leg pair similar to the other leg claws.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="8" pageNumber="61" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Holotype. ♀ with gonopods developed, body length 5.8 mm, head width 190 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
; one leg of the ultimate pair damaged; originally entire, subsequently divided into three pieces, (i) head, (ii) forcipular segment, (iii) leg-bearing segments 1-31 and postpedal segments; collected Nov. 2013 by B. Klarner; in ethanol, LIPI macrosoilHJ2c13_chilo165.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Type locality. Indonesia, Sumatra, Harapan, jungle rubber agroforest, research site HJ2, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-1.8255554">01°49'32&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="103.29417">103°17'39&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, ca. 80 m a.s.l., from upper soil layer (0-5 cm).
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="62" pageId="8" pageNumber="61">
Other specimens examined. 1 ♀, from Bukit Duabelas, jungle rubber agroforest, research site BJ3, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-2.0630555">02°03'47&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="102.80112">102°48'04&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, ca. 90 m a.s.l., from upper soil layer (0-5 cm), same date and collector as holotype, PD5771; 1 specimen, sex unknown because both anterior and posterior parts missing, from Bukit Duabelas, jungle rubber agroforest, 
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="62" start="start">research</pageBreakToken>
site BJ5, 
<geoCoordinate direction="south" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="-2.1433334">02°08'36&quot;S</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="102.85139">102°51'05&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
, ca. 50 m a.s.l., from upper soil layer (0-5 cm), same date and collector as holotype, PD5770.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="62" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
&quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Geophilidae" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="poriger" order="Geophilomorpha" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="poriger">poriger</taxonomicName>
&quot; means &quot;bearing pores&quot; and refers to the presence of glandular pore-fields on the ventral side of the trunk.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Description of holotype (♀, LIPI macrosoilHJ2c13_chilo165). See also Figs 4, 5C.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Geophilidae" genus="Sundageophilus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sundageophilus poriger" order="Geophilomorpha" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="poriger">Sundageophilus poriger</taxonomicName>
sp. n.: A entire body, dorsal view B forcipular segment, ventral view C ultimate left leg, dorsal view. LM photos of holotype LIPI macrosoilHJ2c13_chilo165.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Chilopoda" family="Geophilidae" genus="Sundageophilus" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sundageophilus poriger" order="Geophilomorpha" pageId="9" pageNumber="62" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="poriger">Sundageophilus poriger</taxonomicName>
sp. n.: A head and forcipular segment, dorsal view, antennal articles 
<normalizedToken originalValue="II–XIV">II-XIV</normalizedToken>
omitted, areolation only partially drawn B head, ventral view, areolation only partially drawn C ultimate leg-bearing segment and postpedal segments, ventral view, ultimate legs partially omitted. Line drawings based on LM photos of PD5771 (A, B) and holotype LIPI macrosoilHJ2c13_chilo165 (C).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">General features. Body distinctly narrowing posteriorly. Legs relatively short, most of them ca. 0.2 mm long. Colour (in ethanol) almost uniformly pale yellow, but forcipular tarsungula darker.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
Cephalic capsule. Cephalic plate subrectangular, ca. 1.3 times as long as wide, ca. as wide as the forcipular tergite, the lateral margins slightly convex; scutes approximately isometric and up to 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
in the anterior half of the cephalic plate, indistinct in the posterior half; frontal line absent; setae up to ca. 30 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long. Clypeus ca. 1.3-1.4 times as wide as long, with lateral margins complete; uniformly areolate, the scutes being up to 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
wide, without a distinct clypeal area; two pairs of setae, closed to anterior margin, one anterior to the other. Intermediate part of labrum bearing ca. 8 short tubercles; lateral parts of labrum far apart from each other, separated from the clypeus by complete sulci.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
Antennae. Slender, ca. 3.7 times as long as the head width. Intermediate articles up to ca. 1.2 times as long as wide. Article XIV ca. 1.9 times as long as wide, ca. 2.1 times as long as article XIII and slightly narrower than the latter. Setae gradually denser and shorter from the basal articles to the distal ones, both ventrally and dorsally, in particular up to 25 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long on article I but less than 15 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long on article XIV. Apical sensilla ca. 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long, spear-like, without projections, only gently narrowing at around the mid-length. Club-like sensilla ca. 10 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long, only on article XIV, grouped on the distal parts of both the internal and external sides. Longitudinal rows of 1-3 proprioceptive spine-like sensilla at the bases of the antennal articles: two rows on articles 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
, approximately dorsal and ventral; three rows on articles 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–XIV">IV-XIV</normalizedToken>
, approximately dorsal, ventro-internal and ventro-external; rows reduced to 0-1 spine on antennal articles VI, X and XIV. A single sensillum, similar to the apical ones, ca. 5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long, on both dorso-external and ventro-internal position, close to the distal margin of articles V, IX and XIII.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">First maxillae. Coxosternite without setae. Coxal projection sub-triangular, longer than wide, with a seta. Telopodite composed of two articles, with a seta on the distal one. Lappets lacking.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="62">Second maxillae. Anterior margin of coxosternite entire and concave, without anterior projections. Coxosternite with few setae; neither statuminia nor other distinctly sclerotized parts associated with the metameric pores. Telopodite composed of three articles, only slightly narrowing towards the tip, with some distal setae; pretarsus in shape of an elongate claw, ca. 5 times as long as wide at the basis, sub-conic and slightly bent.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="64" pageId="9" pageNumber="62">
Forcipular segment. Tergite subtrapezoidal, ca. 1.8 times as wide as long, contiguous to the cephalic plate and partially covered by the tergite of the first leg-bearing segment, with lateral margins strongly converging anteriorly, posteriorly ca. 0.9 times as wide as the 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="63" start="start">subsequent</pageBreakToken>
tergite. Pleurites without distinctly sclerotized scapular ridges. Exposed part of the coxosternite ca. 1.1 times as wide as long; anterior margin slightly projecting anteriorly with intermediate part shallowly concave, with short sclerotized denticles; coxopleural sutures straight and subparallel for most of their length; chitin-lines indistinct. Basal distance between the forcipules ca. 0.2 of the maximum width of the coxosternite. Forcipular tro 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="64" start="start">chanteroprefemur</pageBreakToken>
ca. 1.5-1.6 times as long as wide, the internal side much shorter than the external side, without denticles, only a distal shallow bulge. Forcipular intermediate articles distinct, without denticles. Tarsungulum ca. 2.5-2.6 times as long as wide, both the external and the internal profiles uniformly curved, but for a mesal basal bulge bearing a sub-conic denticle. Poison calyx not elongate, in the forcipular intermediate articles.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="65" pageId="11" pageNumber="64">
Leg-bearing segments. 31 leg-bearing segments. Metatergite 1 slightly wider than the subsequent one, without pretergite. No paratergites. Metasternites longer than wide, without obvious 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“carpophagus”">&quot;carpophagus&quot;</normalizedToken>
pit, with pore-fields from the first to the penultimate leg-bearing segment. A single, sub-circular, posterior pore-field on each metas 
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="65" start="start">ternite</pageBreakToken>
. Leg claws simple, uniformly bent; at least a posterior accessory spine, much shorter than mid-length of the pretarsus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="65">
Ultimate leg-bearing segment. Pleuropretergite without sulci. Metatergite sub-trapezoid, ca. 1.1 times as wide as long, lateral margins convex and distinctly converging posteriorly, posterior margin slightly convex. Metasternite sub-trapezoid, ca. 1.5-1.6 times as wide as long, anteriorly ca. 2.6 times as wide as posteriorly, lateral margins almost straight and converging backwards; setae denser in the posterior part. Coxopleuron ca. 1.7-1.8 times as long as the metasternite; setae distributed uniformly. Coxal organs of each coxopleuron opening through four independent pores, of which two are approximately aligned along the lateral margin of the metasternite, the largest ca. 12 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
wide. The telopodite ca. seven times as long as wide, ca. 1.6 times as long and ca. 1.2 times as wide as the penultimate telopodite; six articles, not swollen; setae sparse, uniformly distributed, up to 50 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
long. Pretarsus claw-like, approximately as long as that of the penultimate legs, apparently without accessory spines.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="65">Postpedal segments. Genital pleurosternite entire. Gonopods appearing as a short bilobate lamina. Anal organs relatively large and anal pores exposed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="65">Intraspecific variability. The body length, which is 5.8 mm in the holotype, is estimated to be shorter in the other two specimens, which being damaged cannot be measured accurately. The two specimens with complete trunks are both females with 31 leg-bearing segments.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>