<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6288770" ID-GBIF-Dataset="80d9ecf3-9ff6-4f20-86aa-0910a641cb8e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135164" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6288770" ModsDocID="20597" checkinTime="1243371986070" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Wheeler, W. M." docDate="1922" docId="14A91C69EE4DCE3A67E15D2FD88821FD" docLanguage="en" docName="20597_2" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 45" docSource="http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097" docTitle="Crematogaster (Atopogyne) africana subsp. tibialis Wheeler, 1922, new subspecies" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="158" masterDocId="5A93796082A6378B06C46BB24D100B01" masterDocTitle="The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition." masterLastPageNumber="269" masterPageNumber="39" pageNumber="157" updateTime="1645826231149" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ants collected by the American Museum Congo Expedition.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wheeler, W. M.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1922</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>45</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>39</mods:start>
<mods:end>269</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://plazi.org:8080/dspace/handle/10199/17097</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">20597</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6288770" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135164" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6288770" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:14A91C69EE4DCE3A67E15D2FD88821FD" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/14A91C69EE4DCE3A67E15D2FD88821FD" lastPageNumber="158" pageNumber="157">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="157">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:227648" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Crematogaster" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Crematogaster (Atopogyne) africana tibialis Santschi" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="157" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="subSpecies" species="africana" subGenus="Atopogyne" subSpecies="tibialis">Crematogaster (Atopogyne) africana subspecies tibialis Santschi</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="subSpecies">new subspecies</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="157">&quot;Worker.- &quot;Length 3.5 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="158" pageNumber="157">
&quot;Pale castaneous. Epinotum, postpetiole, and posterior half of gaster of a deeper castaneous tint, passing to reddish brown. A spot on the vertex and the appendages dark brown, the tibiae and metatarsi blackish, the tarsi and the extremity of the thorax reticulate, the epinotum more finely, with some fine longitudinal rugae on the whole basal surface. Sides of the mesonotum regularly reticulatepunctate. Sides of the pronotum more shining and of the epinotum longitudinally striate. Petiole finely reticulate; gaster finely shagreened, almost smooth. The pubescence is rather well developed on the head, the gaster, and the appendages, sparse on the thorax. The hairs are very sparse, except around the mouth and at the tip of the gaster. Head square, with rather convex sides and straight posterior border. Eyes at the middle of the sides. Frontal area short, feebly impressed behind. Frontal carinae developed. Clypeus slightly convex, with rather arched anterior border. Mandibles striate-punctate, with four blackish teeth. The pronotum forms with the basal surface of the mesonotum a plane surface with a contour like that of 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:28122" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Crematogaster" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Crematogaster castanea Smith" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="158" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="castanea">C. castanea Smith</taxonomicName>
. Sides of the basal surface of the mesonotum blunt, not marginate, with the anterior eminence scarcely indicated. Promesonotal suture little or not at all impressed. Sides of the pronotum marginate. Declivity of mesonotum oblique, feebly concave from right to left, above with marginate sides. Mesoepinotal furrow moderately deep. Basal surface of epinotum trapezoidal, its length equal to its width anteriorly in the small worker. It is convex in front, more feebly behind. The spines are as short as a fifth of the interval between their bases, which is concave. They are directed backward and slightly outward. Declivity as long as two-thirds of the basal surface and forming with it an angle of about 145°. Petiole trapezoidal, as broad as long, and as broad as the epinotum. Last antennal joint reddish. A fine and dense striation disposed as in africana (Mayr) but more or less effaced on the front, vertex and occiput, where the reflection is more shining than silky. Epinotum transversely striate-rugose. Petiole smooth, postpetiole and gaster very finely shagreened, almost shining. The head is, moreover, punctate as in africana and much less smooth in the individuals with large head.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="158">&quot;The head, which varies in size independently of the rest of the body, which is almost invariable, is sometimes longer than broad and scarcely emarginate behind, sometimes broader than long, strongly concave behind and with convex sides. Eyes more posterior than in africana. Frontal area narrow, strongly impressed and shining. Mandibles punctate, feebly striate. Mesoepinotal impression stronger than in africana, the pronotum less marginate anteriorly. Mesonotum carinate, more elongate and with the declivous surface much less abrupt than in africana, with longer epinotal spines, even longer than in the variety variegata (Mayr) and a little farther apart. Petiole and postpetiole as in africana.&quot; (Santschi)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="158">Numerous workers taken at the village of Mosekowa between Walikale and Lubutu by Dr. Bequaert from the peculiar pouches of Macaranga saccifera (Part IV) growing in the Rain Forest. As only adult ants and no brood were found in the pouches, Dr. Bequaert does not regard them as true nests. The openings of the pouches were not closed with fibrous carton.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>