<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.833.30689" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b9551847-4eeb-4813-9b89-99e92cfb078b" ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200794" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-833-1" ID-ZBK="7716B2EA10C24F95A4A2702ACD17D57A" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2019" ModsDocID="1313-2970-833-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 833" ModsDocTitle="Discovery of Neonrosellavitiata (Darwin) and Newmanellaspinosus Chan &amp; Cheang (Balanomorpha, Tetraclitidae) from the Andaman Sea, eastern Indian Ocean" checkinTime="1555318561263" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Sukparangsi, Woranop, Pochai, Ashitapol, Wongkunanusorn, Chinnakit &amp; Salinee Khachonpisitsak," docDate="2019" docId="6D435D64A8C7C3EBB31085A3846FE796" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 833: 1-20" docOrigin="ZooKeys 833" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.833.30689" docTitle="Newmanella spinosus Chan &amp; Cheang 2016" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageNumber="1" masterDocId="FFCDF729FFE3FFC1FFCE06646E09FF9C" masterDocTitle="Discovery of Neonrosellavitiata (Darwin) and Newmanellaspinosus Chan &amp; Cheang (Balanomorpha, Tetraclitidae) from the Andaman Sea, eastern Indian Ocean" masterLastPageNumber="20" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" updateTime="1643460665945" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Discovery of Neonrosellavitiata (Darwin) and Newmanellaspinosus Chan &amp; Cheang (Balanomorpha, Tetraclitidae) from the Andaman Sea, eastern Indian Ocean</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Sukparangsi, Woranop</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Pochai, Ashitapol</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wongkunanusorn, Chinnakit</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Salinee Khachonpisitsak,</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2019</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>833</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>20</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.833.30689</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.833.30689</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-833-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">7716B2EA10C24F95A4A2702ACD17D57A</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">7716B2EA10C24F95A4A2702ACD17D57A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="156200794" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6D435D64A8C7C3EBB31085A3846FE796" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6D435D64A8C7C3EBB31085A3846FE796" lastPageNumber="1" pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Redescription of 
<taxonomicName authority="Chan &amp; Cheang, 2016" authorityName="Chan &amp; Cheang" authorityYear="2016" class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella spinosus" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosus">Newmanella spinosus Chan &amp; Cheang, 2016</taxonomicName>
Figs 5, 6, 7, 8
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<taxonomicName class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella radiata" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="radiata">Newmanella radiata</taxonomicName>
. 
<bibRefCitation author="Chan, BKK" journalOrPublisher="National Taiwan Ocean University Press, Keelung, Taiwan" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" title="Crustacean fauna of Taiwan: Barnacles, Vol 1 - Cirripedia: Thoracica excluding the Pyrgomatidae and Acastinae." year="2009">Chan et al. 2009</bibRefCitation>
: 199, fig. 170; 
<bibRefCitation author="Shuto, T" journalOrPublisher="Landscape and Ecological Engineering" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" pagination="157 - 163" title="Floating castles in the ocean: the barnacles of two giant fish aggregating devices from Okinawa, Japan." url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11355-012-0190-7" volume="9" year="2013">Shuto and Hayashi 2013</bibRefCitation>
: 159, fig. 3c (non 
<taxonomicName family="Tetraclitidae" genus="New." higherTaxonomySource="treatment-meta" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="New. radiata" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" rank="species" species="radiata">New. radiata</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Bruguière">Bruguiere</normalizedToken>
1789
</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<taxonomicName class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Newmanella</taxonomicName>
sp. 
<bibRefCitation author="Tsang, LM" journalOrPublisher="Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" pagination="324 - 329" title="Molecular phylogeny of the acorn barnacle family Tetraclitidae (Cirripedia: Balanomorpha: Tetraclitoidea): validity of shell morphology and arthropodal characteristics in the systematics of Tetraclitid barnacles." url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2014.09.015" volume="82" year="2015">Tsang et al. 2015</bibRefCitation>
: 325, fig. 1A, 327 fig. 2.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<taxonomicName class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella spinosus" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosus">Newmanella spinosus</taxonomicName>
Chan &amp; Cheang, 2016: 212-220, figs 9-15.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="type">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Type.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">NMNS-006535-00001, deposited in NMNS (not examined).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">17 specimens, southern Thailand, Andaman Sea in the eastern Indian Ocean, Phang-Nga Province, Na-Tai District, Na-Tai rocky shore, 20 Mar 2018, A Pochai leg. ZCBUU-CP-007-023.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Parietes and opercular plates green on external and internal surfaces. External shell plate with numerous radiating or longitudinal lines extending from apex to base. Scutal margin of tergum with serrated teeth and broad spur with cutting edges. Cirrus II with equal rami and slight curvature of both rami carrying triangular spines. Basis of cirri 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–VI">IV-VI</normalizedToken>
without spines. Greater curvature of both anterior ramus and posterior ramus of Cirrus IV with triangular spines. Mandible with five teeth, the third teeth bidentate, the fourth teeth with serrations and small teeth along the edge, and the fifth teeth sits on the middle of lower margin surrounded by other small spines. Labrum with four teeth on each cutting margin. Penis without basi-dorsal point.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Peduncle absent. Body length 2-3 cm. Shell green with longitudinal folds or lines from orifice toward base or radiating lines; low conic; composed of four shell plates including one carina, two laterals and one rostrum. Base calcareous with parietal tubes; three rows of irregular shape and size of parietal tubes (Fig. 5
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
). External shell plate with longitudinal fold or striation from apex to base; some exhibited decolouration or erosion of shell plate. Basal margin of each shell plate irregularly undulated (Fig. 5E). Internal shell plate smooth and white to pale green; interior part close to orifice green and with some white horizontal striations (Fig. 5F). Orifice pentagonal (Fig. 5G). External surface of opercular plates white with irregular green spots or lines (Fig. 5G). Internal surface of opercular plates mostly white with green, in particular scutum (Fig. 5H). Tergum smaller than scutum (Fig. 5I, J). Tergum triangular with clear spur protruding from basal margin; dorsal surface with horizontal lines; longitudinal furrow on dorsal side broad connected to spur. Spur of tergum broad with cutting edge tip. Scutal margin with serrated teeth. Basal margin of tergum with lateral depressor muscle crests thick (9-10 crests); tergal articular ridge with narrow width (Fig. 5I). Scutum triangular with height 1.3 times base. External surface of scutum with horizontal lines. Lateral depressor crest deep and numerous (5-8 crests) (Fig. 5J).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 5. Shell plate and operculum morphology of 
<taxonomicName class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella spinosus" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosus">Newmanella spinosus</taxonomicName>
Chan &amp; Cheang, 2016 A anterior view of shell B basal view of shell with body tissue C external and anterior view of shell without body tissue D internal and basal view of shell plates showing parietal tubes E external view of parietes F internal view of parietes G close-up on orifice and exterior opercular plates H internal view of operculum without intact tissues I internal view (left) and external view (right) of tergum J internal view (left) and external view (right) of scutum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Cirrus I with unequal rami; anterior ramus (21-segmented) length approx. twice as long as posterior ramus (10-segmented) (Fig. 6A); intermediate segments of posterior ramus normal or not protuberant (Fig. 6B); greater and lesser curvature of both rami without spines (Fig. 6C, D); basipod without spines; serrulated setae found in both anterior and posterior rami (Fig. 6F, G); protopod on the posterior side with plumose setae (Fig. 6H). Cirrus II with equal rami and similar length (both rami with 10-segmented) (Fig. 6I); greater curvature of posterior ramus with serrulated setae (Fig. 6J, K); lesser curvature of posterior ramus with hook-like triangular spines (Fig. 6L) and lesser curvature of anterior ramus with slender spines and serrulated setae (Fig. 6M); apex of posterior ramus with long serrulated setae (Fig. 6N, O); apex of anterior ramus with bi-pinnate setae (Fig. 6P). Cirrus III with unequal rami; posterior ramus (26-segments) longer than anterior ramus (22-segmented, approximately 1.2 times; both rami antenniform (Fig. 6Q); basipod with spines (Fig. 6R) and anterior side of basipod with serrulated setae (Fig. 6S); weak curvature of both rami with hook-like triangular spines (Fig. 6T, U); greater curvature of anterior ramus with short spines (Fig. 6V); Both rami with serrulated setae and bidentate setae (Fig. 6
<normalizedToken originalValue="W–Y">W-Y</normalizedToken>
). Cirrus 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–VI">IV-VI</normalizedToken>
with semi-equal and long rami (Fig. 7A, G, K); basis of cirrus 
<normalizedToken originalValue="IV–VI">IV-VI</normalizedToken>
without spines, only denticles observed (Fig. 7E, J, N). Cirrus IV, anterior ramus 20-segmented posterior ramus 21-segmented (Fig. 7A); Greater curvature of posterior ramus with slender spines (Fig. 7B, C); Greater curvature of anterior ramus with broad triangular spines (Fig. 7B, D); each segment carries two pairs of long serrulated setae and one pair of shorter simple setae (Fig. 7F). No spine on each segment at lesser curvature side. Cirrus V, anterior ramus 19-segmented posterior ramus 20-segmented (Fig. 7G); Greater curvature of posterior ramus with slender spines (Fig. 7H) while no spines on anterior ramus (Fig. 7I). Cirrus VI, anterior ramus 24-segmented, posterior ramus 26-segmented (Fig. 7K); greater curvature of both rami with slender spines (Fig. 7L, M).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 6. SEM showing cirral morphology of 
<taxonomicName class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella spinosus" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosus">Newmanella spinosus</taxonomicName>
Chan &amp; Cheang, 2016 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–H">A-H</normalizedToken>
cirrus I A overview of cirrus I morphology B close-up at proximal region of cirrus I C close-up on posterior ramus D close-up on anterior ramus E apex of anterior ramus F serrulated setae on anterior ramus G serrulated setae on posterior ramus H plumose setae on posterior side of protopod 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–P">I-P</normalizedToken>
cirrus II I overview of cirrus II morphology J proximal region of cirrus II K serrulated and bidentate setae on greater curvature of posterior ramus L hook-like triangular spines on lesser curvature of posterior ramus M spines (asterisks) on lesser curvature of anterior ramus N close-up on apex on posterior ramus O serrulated setae on posterior ramus P serrulated and bidentate setae on anterior ramus 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Q–Y">Q-Y</normalizedToken>
cirrus III Q overview of cirrus III morphology R slender spines on basipod S plumose setae on anterior side of basipod T hook-like triangular spines on lesser curvature of posterior ramus U hook-like triangular spines on lesser curvature of anterior ramus V greater curvature of anterior ramus with spines W serrulated setae and bidentate setae on posterior ramus X serrulated setae on anterior ramus Y bidentate setae on anterior ramus. Abbreviations: pr, protopod; bs, basipod; pos, posterior ramus; ant, anterior ramus. Scale bars in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 7. SEM showing cirral morphology of 
<taxonomicName class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella spinosus" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosus">Newmanella spinosus</taxonomicName>
Chan &amp; Cheang, 2016 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–F">A-F</normalizedToken>
cirrus IV A overview of cirrus IV morphology B close-up on proximal region of greater curvature C slender spines on greater curvature of posterior ramus D triangular spines on greater curvature of anterior ramus E close-up on basipod showing denticles without spine F lesser curvature of both rami showing two pairs of long serrulated setae and a pair of simple setae 
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–J">G-J</normalizedToken>
cirrus V G overview of cirrus V morphology H greater curvature of posterior ramus showing spines I greater curvature of both rami (the other side) without spine J close-up on basipod without spine (only denticles) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="K–N">K-N</normalizedToken>
Cirrus VI K overview of cirrus VI morphology L greater curvature of both rami M close-up on slender spines on greater curvature of anterior ramus N close-up on basipod without spine. Abbreviations: pr, protopod; bs, basipod; pos, posterior ramus; ant, anterior ramus. Scale bars in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Maxilla bi-lobate; both lobes covered with serrulated setae (Fig. 8A, B, C). Maxillule with V-shaped notch; two large spines and five smaller spines before notch; six pairs of long slender spines and following seven smaller spines closed to inferior angle after notch (Fig. 8D); cutting edge after notch carrying a cluster of serrulated setae (Fig. 8E). Mandible with five teeth; the first teeth largest; the second and the third teeth bidentate; the fourth teeth serrated; the fifth teeth only single in the middle of lower margin surrounded by small and slender spines; lower margin narrow with a pack of 12 spines (irregular length); no setae under inferior angle (Fig. 8F). Labrum with V-shaped notch; four teeth with densely packed simple setae on each side of cutting margin (Fig. 8
<normalizedToken originalValue="H–J">H-J</normalizedToken>
). Mandibular palp rectangular carrying densely packed serrulated setae on superior margin (Fig. 8
<normalizedToken originalValue="K–L">K-L</normalizedToken>
). Penis long and annulated without basi-dorsal point (Fig. 8M inset); a few simple setae scattered randomly along whole length; at the tip of penis carrying two clusters of simple and long setae (Fig. 8
<normalizedToken originalValue="M–P">M-P</normalizedToken>
).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Figure 8. SEM showing mouth parts of 
<taxonomicName class="Maxillopoda" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Newmanella" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Newmanella spinosus" order="Sessilia" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="spinosus">Newmanella spinosus</taxonomicName>
Chan &amp; Cheang, 2016 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–C">A-C</normalizedToken>
maxilla A overview of maxilla morphology showing upper lobe (ul) and lower lobe (ll) B serrulated setae on upper lobe C serrulated setae on lower lobe 
<normalizedToken originalValue="D–E">D-E</normalizedToken>
maxillule D overview of maxillule morphology E serrulated setae on inferior angle of maxillule F mandible (inset showing close up of third-fifth teeth of mandible) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–J">G-J</normalizedToken>
labrum G exterior view of labrum H interior view of labrum I teeth on labrum (left margin from H) J teeth on labrum (right margin from H) K mandibular palp L close-up on superior side showing serrulated setae on mandibular palp 
<normalizedToken originalValue="M–P">M-P</normalizedToken>
penis M overview of whole penis on side view and inset showing smooth dorsal side (dash line) on the base of the penis without basi-dorsal point N apex of penis carrying setae O penis with annulation P base of penis. Abbreviations: ul, upper lobe of maxilla; ll, lower lobe of maxilla. Scale bars in 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
The specimens were collected only during the lowest tide (March) of the year at the lowest tide littoral zone, the same habitat as 
<taxonomicName authority="Jones, 2010" authorityName="Jones" authorityYear="2010" class="Thecostraca" family="Tetraclitidae" genus="Neonrosella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Neonrosella vitiata" order="Balanomorpha" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vitiata">Neonrosella vitiata</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="1" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="1">
Western Pacific from Taiwan (type locality) and Philippines (
<bibRefCitation author="Chan, BKK" journalOrPublisher="Zootaxa" pageId="0" pageNumber="1" pagination="201 - 226" title="First discovery of a new species of Newmanella Ross, 1969 (Balanomorpha: Tetraclitidae) in the western Pacific, with a note on the new status of Neonrosella Jones, 2010." url="https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4098.2.1" volume="4098" year="2016">Chan and Cheang 2016</bibRefCitation>
) and Andaman Sea of eastern Indian Ocean (Phang-Nga Province, southern Thailand).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>