<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6285052" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c57fbb65-0453-4dee-a98f-2476dde849e4" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127808" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6285052" ModsDocID="4580" checkinTime="1243376393067" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Kempf, W. W." docDate="1966" docId="7DB9E98D5447D520BDF066D32CDA734A" docLanguage="en" docName="4580" docOrigin="Studia Entomologica (N. S.) 8" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/4580/4580.pdf" docTitle="Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="190" masterDocId="A60EEC1733A0D7C5B5AD52D191854726" masterDocTitle="A revision of the Neotropical fungus-growing ants of the genus Cyphomyrmex Mayr. Part II. Group of rimosus (Spinola) (Hym. Formicidae)." masterLastPageNumber="200" masterPageNumber="161" pageNumber="188" updateTime="1645813190549" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A revision of the Neotropical fungus-growing ants of the genus Cyphomyrmex Mayr. Part II. Group of rimosus (Spinola) (Hym. Formicidae).</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Kempf, W. W.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Studia Entomologica (N. S.)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1966</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>8</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>161</mods:start>
<mods:end>200</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/4580/4580.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">4580</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6285052" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100127808" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6285052" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:7DB9E98D5447D520BDF066D32CDA734A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7DB9E98D5447D520BDF066D32CDA734A" lastPageNumber="190" pageNumber="188">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="188">
11. 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:28550" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cyphomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="188" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vorticis">Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber</taxonomicName>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="188">(Figs. 1, 15, 34, 44)</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageNumber="188">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:28550" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cyphomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="188" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vorticis">Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber</taxonomicName>
, 1940: 409-10 (Worker; Bolivia: Santa Helena).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="188">Types. - Workers taken by W. M. Mann at Santa Helena, Bolivia, in August 1921. A single specimen (lectotype NAW) seen.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="188">Worker (lectotype). - Total length 3.8 mm; head length 0.88 mm; head width 0.85 mm; thorax length 1.28 mm; hind femur length 1.28 mm. Medium brown; dorsum of head, scapes, tibiae and gaster darker with ferruginous hues. Integument opaque; densely and minutely punctate-granulate.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="189" pageNumber="188">Head as shown in Fig. 1. Mandibles finely reticulaterugulose, somewhat shining; chewing border with a broader diastema between 2nd and 3rd basal tooth. Clypeus with flattened anterior apron, the border of which is gently convex and notched in the middle; on each side it bears a prominent tooth. Frontal lobes very broadly expanded, the anterior curvature stronger than the posterior one; upper surface with a depressed circular area above the antennal socket. Frontal carinae sigmoidal, not quite reaching occipital corner, their border somewhat elevated at place of greatest constriction. Front with a feeble tumulus at frontal area, followed by a transverse shallow depression. Carinae of vertex semicircular, having as center a prominent tubercle; from there they diverge both cephalad and caudad. Occipital corners strongly dentate, tooth curving slightly upward and outward. Occiput oblique, not perpendicular. Preocular carina curving mesad above eyes. Postocular carina beginning below eye and extending backwards to the prominent supraocular tooth. Eyes with about 11-12 facets across greatest diameter. Inferior border of cheeks strongly and irregularly crested. Scapes gradually incrassate toward apex, surpassing the occipital corner by more than their maximum width. All funicular segments longer than broad, segment I as long as II and III combined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="189">Thorax as shown in Fig. 15. Pronotum with small median, stronger lateral teeth; the latter connected with the feebly marked humeral angle by a blunt carina; antero-inferior tooth rectangular. Mesonotum with strong paired conical anterior teeth, followed by another pair of low elongate and blunt tubercles. Mesoepinotal constriction deep. Basal face of epinotum flanked by sharply carinate ridges in its entire length; space between ridges shallowly excavate. Declivous face laterally immarginate. Lateral blunt and oblique welt well developed, bearing the spiracle. Hind femora (Fig; 44) angular beneath in front of basal third, then gradually tapering toward apex; the postero-ventral border very slightly carinate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="189">Petiole and postpetiole as shown in Figs. 15 and 34. Petiolar node strikingly transverse without ridges or prominent posterodorsal laminule. Postpetiole even broader, with a pair of low diverging tubercles near entire posterior border, separated by a shallow median depression. Gaster anteriorly sharply marginate; tergum I without an antero-median impression and a distinct lateral margination.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="189">Pilosity inconspicuous, minute and appressed, not scale-like; more visible on appendages and sharp ridges of body where they become decumbent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="189">Female and male unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="189">
Distribution. - Although collected only twice, it is quite possible that 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:28550" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cyphomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="189" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vorticis">vorticis</taxonomicName>
is confined to the upper Amazon basin, in northwestern Brazil and northern Bolivia.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="189">Specimens examined: 3 workers; besides the lone lectotype (NAW) already mentioned above, two more workers from Brazil, Rondonia territory, Sao Pedro, Rio Jamari, O.P. Forattini leg. on July 11, 1960 (WWK).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="189">Discussion. - The Brazilian workers agree completely with the Bolivian type. Their measurements are the following: total length 3.6-3.9 mm; head length 0.83-0.88 mm; head width 0.78-0.83 mm; thorax length 1.20-1.31 mm; hind femur length 1.14-1.28 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="190">
The closest ally of 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:28550" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cyphomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="190" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vorticis">vorticis</taxonomicName>
is 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:28546" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cyphomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cyphomyrmex salvini Forel" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="190" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="salvini">salvini</taxonomicName>
, differing the former from the latter in the following features: Body hairs simple, never scale-like; frontal lobes strikingly different in shape, broadly rounded cephalad, the curvature gradually decreasing caudad (cf. Figs. 1 and 3); the sigmoidal frontal carinae always fade out before reaching the spinelike occipital lobe; basal face of epinotum strongly and sharply carinate in its entire length; posterior mesonotal tubercles low, not tooth-like nor conical; petiole not noticeably constricted at each side just in front of postpetiolar insertion.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageNumber="190">
Nothing is known as regards the biology of 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:28550" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cyphomyrmex" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Cyphomyrmex vorticis Weber" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="190" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="vorticis">vorticis</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>