<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" ID-GBIF-Dataset="e9e44d3d-42b4-4432-8746-68506bf9820e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047570" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-331-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 331" ModsDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" checkinTime="1451246961488" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Burks, Roger A., Masner, Lubomir, Johnson, Norman F. &amp; Austin, Andrew D." docDate="2013" docId="EF189C6574CD4F892E89363D2FD8B0BA" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 331: 1-266" docOrigin="ZooKeys 331" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152" docTitle="Oxyscelio mirellus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="127" lastPageNumber="128" masterDocId="FFA9506BFF9FFFABA36DFFB258419539" masterDocTitle="Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna" masterLastPageNumber="266" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" updateTime="1643530488545" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s. l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific fauna</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Burks, Roger A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Masner, Lubomir</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Johnson, Norman F.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Austin, Andrew D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>331</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>266</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.331.5152</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-331-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F456C9B2-3A15-4520-A0A2-6208722B52B0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152047570" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:EF189C6574CD4F892E89363D2FD8B0BA" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EF189C6574CD4F892E89363D2FD8B0BA" lastPageId="127" lastPageNumber="128" pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
<subSubSection pageId="124" pageNumber="125" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/466E4C8E-B0F7-4DD7-8FD7-A1A983FE1CB5" authority="Dodd" class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio mirellus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirellus">Oxyscelio mirellus (Dodd)</taxonomicName>
Figures 187-192; Morphbank64
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="124" pageNumber="125" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Sceliomorpha" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sceliomorpha mirella" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirella">Sceliomorpha mirella</taxonomicName>
Dodd, 1920: 349 (original description); 
<bibRefCitation pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Masner 1965</bibRefCitation>
: 96 (type information).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio mirellus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirellus">Oxyscelio mirellus</taxonomicName>
(Dodd): 
<bibRefCitation author="Dodd, AP" journalOrPublisher="Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="71 - 81" title="The genus Oxyscelio Kieffer, its synonymy and species, with a description of one new genus (Hymenoptera: Proctotrypoidea)." volume="42" year="1931">Dodd 1931</bibRefCitation>
: 76 (generic transfer); 
<bibRefCitation author="Galloway, ID" journalOrPublisher="Queensland Journal of Agricultural and Animal Sciences" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="83 - 114" title="The types of Australian species of the subfamily Scelioninae (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae)." volume="33" year="1976">Galloway 1976</bibRefCitation>
: 99 (type information); 
<bibRefCitation author="Masner, L" journalOrPublisher="Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada" pageId="245" pageNumber="246" pagination="1 - 87" title="Revisionary notes and keys to world genera of Scelionidae (Hymenoptera: Proctotrupoidea)." url="10.4039/entm10897fv" volume="97" year="1976">Masner 1976</bibRefCitation>
: 24 (description).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="126" lastPageNumber="127" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Female. Body length 4.2-4.55 mm (n=6).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Radicle color and shade: darker than scape. Pedicel color: same as scape. A3: longer than pedicel. A4: broader than long. A5: broader than long.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">Ventral clypeal margin: with slightly convex median lobe. Interantennal process: not elongate. Lower frons at dorsal margin of interantennal process: without transverse carina. Transverse curved rugae extending from frontal depression to eye: absent. Median longitudinal carina in frontal depression: absent. Ventral portion of frontal depression: with medially interrupted transverse carinae. Dorsal portion of frontal depression: without transverse carinae. Submedian carina: present. Frontal depression dorsally: hood-like, dorsally protruding. Upper frons major sculpture: umbilicate foveate; irregularly rugose. Upper frons microsculpture: absent. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Carina connecting occipital carina to hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: broadly angular, with rounded median peak. Occiput sculpture: irregularly sculptured. Extra carina ventral to occipital carina: present, complete. Gena length: shorter than eye. Major sculpture of gena anteroventrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of gena posteroventrally: umbilicate foveate; rugose. Microsculpture of gena anteroventrally: absent. Microsculpture of gena posteroventrally: absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="126" lastPageNumber="127" pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
Lateral pronotal area sculpture: with shallow irregular carinae, without microsculpture. Posterior border of central pronotal area: directed anteriorly, protruding at corner of epomial carina and transverse pronotal carina. Mesoscutum anteriorly: very steep and tall, descending at a right angle or protruding anteriorly. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Mesoscutal midlobe sculpture at midlength: not different from nearby sculpture. Major sculpture of mesoscutal mid 
<pageBreakToken pageId="125" pageNumber="126" start="start">lobe</pageBreakToken>
posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Median mesoscutal carina: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate; umbilicate punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: punctate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: punctate. Mesoscutellar rim: not expanded. Mesoscutellar rim medially: without notch. Mesofemoral depression: longitudinally striate dorsally and 
<pageBreakToken pageId="126" pageNumber="127" start="start">ventrally</pageBreakToken>
. Metascutellum shape: not emarginate, concave but elevated posteriorly. Metascutellar setae: absent. Metascutellum sculpture: with large smooth posterior fovea. Spines along tibiae: absent. Lateral propodeal carinae: broadly separated, not parallel anteriorly. Setae in metasomal depression: absent. Anterior sculpture of metasomal depression: absent. Median propodeal carina: absent. Postmarginal vein: absent, but marginal vein curving slightly at apex. Fore wing apex at rest: not reaching base of T5. Coxae color brightness: darker than femora.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="126" pageNumber="127">T1 horn: absent. Number of longitudinal carinae of T1 midlobe: 4. T1 lateral carina: protruding laterally, visible from ventral view. T2 sculpture: with longitudinal striae or rugae, setiferous puncta present between them. T2 sublateral longitudinal foveae: absent. T3 metasomal flanges: present. T4 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T4 metasomal flanges: present as slightly protruding sharp corners. T5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. T5 metasomal flanges: present as slightly protruding sharp corners. T6: broader than long. Major sculpture of T6: umbilicate punctate; longitudinally striate. Microsculpture of T6: absent. T6 medially: with medially truncate emargination, separated from apical rim. T6 metasomal flanges: present, very broadly rounded but with sharp apices. T6 raised peripheral rim: absent. S4 sculpture: longitudinally striate or rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 sculpture: longitudinally striate to rugose, setal pits spanning interspaces. S5 median carina: present. S6 peripheral carina: present, posteriorly complete. S6 apex in relation to T6: exposed to dorsal view by T6 emargination. S6 apex: truncate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="126" pageNumber="127">Male. Body length 3-3.9 mm (n=20). A3: longer than pedicel. A5 tyloid shape: narrow, linear. A6: broader than long. A11: as long as broad. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe anteriorly: granulate. Microsculpture of mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly: absent. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: umbilicate foveate. Major sculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: umbilicate foveate. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum centrally: absent. Microsculpture of mesoscutellum peripherally: absent. Fore wing apex at rest: reaching apex of T5. T1 midlobe longitudinal carinae: 4. T3 metasomal flanges: absent. T4 metasomal flanges: absent. T5 metasomal flanges: present as slightly protruding sharp corners. T6 metasomal flanges: present as slightly protruding acuminate flanges. T7: broadly and deeply emarginate, with rounded posterolateral margins.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="126" pageNumber="127">
<paragraph pageId="126" pageNumber="127">
Figures 187-192. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio mirellus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="126" pageNumber="127" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirellus">Oxyscelio mirellus</taxonomicName>
(Dodd), female (B.M. TYPE HYM. 9.511) 187 Head and mesosoma, lateral view 188 Head and mesosoma, dorsal view 189 Head, anterior view. Female (OSUC 462747) 190 Metasomal apex, dorsal view. Paratype male (OSUC 462750) 191 Antenna 192 Metasoma, dorsal view. Morphbank64
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="127" lastPageNumber="128" pageId="126" pageNumber="127" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="126" pageNumber="127">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="127" lastPageNumber="128" pageId="126" pageNumber="127">
Both sexes: Frontal depression deep, all carinae except dorsal separator interrupted medially, no carinae present above dorsal separator; submedian carina sharp. Hyperoccipital carina absent. Occipital carina complete, medially weakly convex or forming a vague median peak. Mesoscutellar rim not expanded, without median notch. Metascutellum scoop-like, projecting dorsally. Coxa darker than rest of leg. Postmarginal vein absent. Female: A3 not longer than pedicel. A4, A5, A6 broader than long. T4 with tiny metasomal flanges; T5, T6 with broad, flat metasomal flanges. T6 apically broadly and deeply emarginate, truncate medially. S6 exposed to dorsal view, truncate apically. Male: A3 longer than broad. A4, A11 broader than long. Mes 
<pageBreakToken pageId="127" pageNumber="128" start="start">oscutellum</pageBreakToken>
and mesoscutal midlobe posteriorly with broad foveae, not smooth medially. T5, T6 with sharp metasomal flanges. T7 with rounded postero-lateral lobes, broadly emarginate medially.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="127" pageNumber="128" type="link to distribution map">
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">Link to distribution map.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">[http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=5028]</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="127" pageNumber="128" type="associations">
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">Associations.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">
On flower of mallee: [
<taxonomicName genus="Myrtales" lsidName="Myrtales" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" rank="genus">Myrtales</taxonomicName>
: 
<taxonomicName genus="Myrtaceae" lsidName="Myrtaceae" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" rank="genus">Myrtaceae</taxonomicName>
]
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="127" pageNumber="128" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">Holotype, female, S. mirella: AUSTRALIA: WA, Yallingup, 1.XII-12.XII.1913, R. E. Turner, B.M. TYPE HYM. 9.511 (deposited in BMNH). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 1 female, 4 males, OSUC 435935 (ANIC); OSUC 462562, 462750-462752 (BMNH). Other material: AUSTRALIA: 6 females, 33 males, OSUC 462748 (ANIC); OSUC 449030-449031, 449037-449044, 449049-449055, 449058-449062 (BMNH); OSUC 462746-462747 (CNCI); OSUC 435936 (QDPC); OSUC 449045-449048, 449057 (UQIC); WAM Ent. Reg No. 70285 (WAMP); OSUC 449032-449036, 449056, 462749 (WINC).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="127" pageNumber="128" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="127" pageNumber="128">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Scelionidae" genus="Oxyscelio" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxyscelio mirellus" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="127" pageNumber="128" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="mirellus">Oxyscelio mirellus</taxonomicName>
is distinctive in having a very broadly and deeply emarginate T6 with broad metasomal flanges, in combination with short flagellomeres in both sexes. South Australian specimens are slightly smaller than those from Western Australia, but otherwise seemed conspecific.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>