<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472" ID-GBIF-Dataset="64686cef-cf34-47d6-9cf4-3bd4e0dc9160" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152049024" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-345-73" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6266B6AA-1976-40FE-83EB-D59D4A208237" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-345-73" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 345" ModsDocTitle="The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)" checkinTime="1451246762417" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Belokobylskij, Sergey A., Tang, Pu &amp; Chen, Xue-xin" docDate="2013" docId="C0015920F516B3F9FDEAEF7AA842C151" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 345: 73-96" docOrigin="ZooKeys 345" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472" docTitle="Ontsira robusta Belokobylskij, Tang &amp; Chen, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="6266B6AA-1976-40FE-83EB-D59D4A208237" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="87" masterDocId="FF94FFF6852CFFA9582EFF9DAB3CFF96" masterDocTitle="The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)" masterLastPageNumber="96" masterPageNumber="73" pageId="11" pageNumber="84" updateTime="1643696211464" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Chinese species of the genus Ontsira Cameron (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Doryctinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Belokobylskij, Sergey A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tang, Pu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chen, Xue-xin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>345</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>73</mods:start>
<mods:end>96</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.345.5472</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-345-73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5F4F3D22-2655-4E1B-A9D2-714D9E6F5991</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152049024" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6266B6AA-1976-40FE-83EB-D59D4A208237" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C0015920F516B3F9FDEAEF7AA842C151" lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="11" pageNumber="84">
<subSubSection pageId="11" pageNumber="84" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="84">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/6266B6AA-1976-40FE-83EB-D59D4A208237" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira robusta" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="11" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robusta">Ontsira robusta</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="11" pageNumber="84">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Fig. 3
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="85" pageId="11" pageNumber="84" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="84">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="84">Holotype: female, &quot;Korea, Kyonggi-do, Suwon-shi, Sodun-dong, Mt. Yogi, 23-29.VI.1994, Malaise trap&quot; (ZISP).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="85">
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="85" start="start">Paratypes</pageBreakToken>
. 1 female, &quot;Korea, Kyonggi-do, Suwon-shi, Sodun, Mt. Yogi, 16-23.VI.1994, Malaise trap&quot; (ZISP); 1 female, China, North-East, 195(7?), N 5703.10 (ZJUH).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="12" pageNumber="85" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="85">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="85">
After Latin 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“robustus”">&quot;robustus&quot;</normalizedToken>
, meaning 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“strong”">&quot;strong&quot;</normalizedToken>
, because of the first metasomal tergite short and wide.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="12" pageNumber="85" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="85">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="85">Female. Body length 6.0-7.2 mm; fore wing length 4.8-5.4 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="85">Head width 1.2-1.3 times as long as its median length, about 1.1 times as long as width of mesoscutum. Frons without carina, with shallow or very shallow median furrow. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex anteriorly, roundly narrowed posteriorly; transverse diameter of eye almost equal to temple. Ocellar triangle situated before middle of head (dorsal view), its anterior ocellus situated almost on middle level of eyes. Ocelli medium-sized, in triangle with base 1.2-1.3 times as long as its sides. POL 1.0-1.3 times Od, 0.4-0.5 times OOL. Eye rather densely and shortly setose, with very shallow or indistinct emargination opposite antennal sockets, 1.3-1.4 times as high as broad. Face along eyes without distinct carinae, with short and shallow elongate depressions above clypeus; width of face 1.15-1.20 times as long as height of eye and 1.3-1.4 times as long as height of face and clypeus combined. Diameter of antennal socket 1.1-1.4 times as long as distance between sockets and 1.4-1.6 times as long as distance between socket and eye. Malar suture indistinct. Malar space 0.40-0.45 times as long as height of eye, almost equal to basal width of mandible. Clypeus with wide flange ventrally. Clypeal suture complete, deep laterally and very shallow dorsally. Hypoclypeal depression round, its width 1.1-1.2 times as long as distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.45-0.50 times as long as width of face. Occipital carina ventrally fused with hypostomal carina at upper base of mandible. Maxillary palpi long, 1.1-1.2 times as long as head height.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="12" pageNumber="85">Antennae rather thick, weakly setiform, 36-37-segmented, 0.75-0.80 times as long as body. Scape 1.7-1.9 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment 2.7-3.0 times as long as its apical width, 1.15-1.30 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 1.7-1.9 times as long as wide, about 0.4 times as long as first flagellar segment, 0.7-0.8 times as long as apical segment; the apical segment distinctly pointed apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="86" pageId="12" pageNumber="85">
Mesosoma. Length about twice as long as its height. Pronotum weakly convex dorsally (lateral view), with fine pronotal carina in anterior 0.4. Median lobe of mesoscutum (dorsal view) rather distinctly protruding forward, with shallow and wide median furrow. Notauli deep anteriorly and shallow posteriorly, wide, densely coarsely crenulate-rugulose with granulation partly. Prescutellar depression rather deep, long, with one to three carinae, rather coarsely rugose entirely, about 0.5 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum weakly convex, without lateral carinae. Metanotum (dorsal view) with two strongly and curvedly convergent and fused posteriorly with large rugulose area lateral carinae, without median carinae; with short and obtuse metanotal tooth. Subalar depression shallow, wide, coarsely striate-rugose. Sternaulus deep, weakly curved or straight, oblique, densely and coarsely crenulate and with fine or very fine granulation, connected with prepectal carina anteriorly, running along anterior 0.6-0.7 of 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="86" start="start">lower</pageBreakToken>
part of mesopleuron. Metapleural flange rather short, wide, rounded apically. Propodeum with rather distinct, short, thick lateral tubercles.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="86">Wings. Fore wing 3.5-3.6 times as long as its maximum width. Radial vein arising behind middle of pterostigma, inner basal part of pterostigma 1.2-1.3 times as long as its inner apical part. Radial cell not shortened; metacarp 1.3 times as long as pterostigma. First radial abscissa 0.6-0.8 times as long as maximum width of pterostigma. Second radial abscissa 3.6-4.0 times as long as first abscissa, 0.6 times as long as the straight third abscissa, 1.3-1.5 times as long as first radiomedial vein. Second radiomedial cell 2.3-2.5 times as long as its maximum width, 1.1 times as long as brachial cell. First medial abscissa almost straight or weakly sinuate. Mediocubital vein weakly curved. Recurrent vein 3.0-3.3 times second abscissa of medial vein. Distance from nervulus to basal vein 0.7-1.0 times as long as nervulus. Parallel vein arising from posterior 0.25 of distal margin of brachial cell. Hind wing 4.7-5.2 times as long as its maximum width. First costal abscissa 0.6-0.7 times as long as second abscissa. First abscissa of mediocubital vein 1.5-1.8 times as long as second abscissa. Radial cell weakly narrowed posteriorly. Mediocubital cell large, widened toward apex, 6.5-6.7 times as long as wide, 0.45-0.50 times as long as whole length of wing. Recurrent vein straight or weakly curved, oblique, more or less distinctly postfurcal, unsclerotized but distinctly pigmented.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="86">Legs. Fore tibia with numerous slender spines arranged in rather narrow stripe. Hind coxa without dorsal tooth, 1.3-1.5 times as long as wide (with tubercle). Hind femur 3.5-3.6 times as long as wide. Hind tarsus 0.85-0.90 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.80-0.85 times as long as second-fifth segments combined. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.40-0.45 times as long as basitarsus, 1.20-1.25 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="86">Metasoma 1.1-1.2 times as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite with large dorsope, with small spiracular tubercles in basal 0.3, rather weakly and almost linearly widened from base to apex. Maximum width of first tergite 1.7 times its minimum width; length 0.9-1.1 times as long as its apical width. Second tergite without basomedian area, 0.5-0.6 times as long as its basal width, 0.85-0.90 times as long as third tergite. Second suture straight, shallow, complete. Third tergite without transverse furrow. Ovipositor sheath 0.8-1.1 times as long as body, 1.5-2.2 times as long as metasoma, 2.4-3.3 times as long as mesosoma, 1.1-1.4 times as long as fore wing.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="87" pageId="13" pageNumber="86">
Sculpture and pubescence. Vertex entirely or mostly more or less coarsely or (rarely) rather finely curvedly striate; frons entirely coarsely and partly undulately rugose-striate, with granulation between striae; face distinctly and rather densely transverse striate-rugose with dense and fine granulation, clypeus smooth with rugulosity below; temple rather coarsely or rather finely vertically striate, smooth on more or less narrow part near eye. Sides of pronotum entirely coarsely rugose, with crenulate median furrow. Mesoscutum densely and rather finely punctulate-rugulose entirely, with dense and rather fine granulation between rugae, coarsely rugose in wide area on medioposterior half. Scutellum mostly smooth. Mesopleuron rather coarsely or sometimes finely rugose, with two-three small smooth areas. Propodeum with rather distinctly delineated by carinae areas, entirely coarsely rugose-reticulate; basolateral areas large, entirely 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="87" start="start">coarsely</pageBreakToken>
rugose-reticulate with dense granulation at least in anterior half; areola long and narrow, 1.6-1.8 times as long as wide; dorsal carina long, 1.1-1.7 times as long as areola fork. Hind coxae almost entirely and densely rugose-reticulate with dense and fine granulation between rugae. Hind femur rugulose-areolate with dense fine granulation dorsally and laterally, almost smooth ventrally. First tergite densely, coarsely linearly or curvedly striate, rugose-reticulate in mediobasal 0.3-0.7, without distinct ground sculpture between striae. Second tergite sparsely striate in basal 0.2-0.3, sometimes (holotype) with three semicircular striae or with curved striae basomedially, smooth on remaining part. Remaining tergites smooth. Vertex with rather sparse, short and semi-erect setae; mesoscutum entirely with very dense, short and semi-erect pale setae. Hind tibia dorsally with short, dense and almost erect or semi-erect setae, length of these setae about 0.5 times as long as maximum width of hind tibia.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Colour. Body black, metasoma behind first tergite dark reddish brown, yellowish brown or reddish brown ventrally, sometimes metasoma light reddish brown medially. Antennae dark reddish brown to black. Palpi reddish brown or sometimes dark reddish brown. Legs reddish brown, partly yellowish, all tibiae basally yellow. Ovipositor sheath black. Fore wing membrane rather distinctly infuscate. Pterostigma brown, sometimes very shortly paler basally and apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Male unknown.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="87">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="87">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira robusta" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="robusta">Ontsira robusta</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (female). A habitus, lateral view B head, dorsal view C mesosoma, lateral view D head, front view E basal segments of antenna F fore and hind wings G metasoma, dorsal view H mesosoma, dorsal view. Scale bar 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="87" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="87">China (North East); Korea.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="87" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="87">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="87">
This new species is very similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira imperator" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="imperator">Ontsira imperator</taxonomicName>
(Haliday), but differs in having the vertex almost entirely or mostly and temple at most part distinctly striate, and the mesoscutum almost entirely, very densely and finely granulate with sparse punctation. It is also similar to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Ontsira" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ontsira rugivertex" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="87" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="rugivertex">Ontsira rugivertex</taxonomicName>
sp. n., but differs in having the antennae rather distinctly shorter than body, the first abscissa of mediocubital vein of hind wing longer, the hind femur wider, the second segment of hind tarsus shorter, the first tergite shorter and wider, the second tergite shorter, and the palpi dark.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>