<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" ID-GBIF-Dataset="907713bd-c7f2-4f8e-a75e-b7f9c958865f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648708" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-689-1" ID-ZBK="2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-689-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 689" ModsDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" checkinTime="1502744367222" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lackner, Tomas &amp; Leschen, Richard A. B." docDate="2017" docId="60269CC2017566A327E83CA9218312EF" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 689: 1-263" docOrigin="ZooKeys 689" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021" docTitle="Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava Kanaar 1989" docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageId="124" lastPageNumber="125" masterDocId="D302FFB6FFA66345FFBAFF89311EFFDE" masterDocTitle="A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" masterLastPageNumber="263" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="118" pageNumber="119" updateTime="1643479489822" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A monograph of the Australopacific Saprininae (Coleoptera, Histeridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lackner, Tomas</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Leschen, Richard A. B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>689</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>263</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.689.12021</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-689-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">2F40BF4AD35F4CC697D5976EC201E652</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="132648708" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:60269CC2017566A327E83CA9218312EF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/60269CC2017566A327E83CA9218312EF" lastPageId="124" lastPageNumber="125" pageId="118" pageNumber="119">
<subSubSection pageId="118" pageNumber="119" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="118" pageNumber="119">
<taxonomicName authority="Kanaar, 1989" authorityName="Kanaar" authorityYear="1989" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava" order="Coleoptera" pageId="118" pageNumber="119" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandiclava" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava Kanaar, 1989</taxonomicName>
Figs 439, 440-448, 449-457, 755
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus grandiclava" order="Coleoptera" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandiclava">
<pageBreakToken pageId="119" pageNumber="120" start="start">Saprinus</pageBreakToken>
grandiclava
</taxonomicName>
Kanaar, 1989: 285.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Indonesia: Papua: Jayapura.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="119" pageNumber="120">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">
Figure 439. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava" order="Coleoptera" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandiclava" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava</taxonomicName>
Kanaar, 1989 habitus, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Type material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus grandiclava" order="Coleoptera" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandiclava">Saprinus grandiclava</taxonomicName>
Kanaar, 1989: holotype, ♂, with extracted genitalia, glued on a separate triangular mounting card under the specimen, with the following labels: &quot;HOLLANDIA / NW. GUINEA&quot; (black-framed printed label); followed by: &quot;Museum Leiden / Collectie / Doesburg / rec. 1973&quot; (printed); followed by: &quot;HOLOTYPUS, ♂ / 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus" order="Coleoptera" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Saprinus</taxonomicName>
/ 
<taxonomicName lsidName="grandiclava" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" rank="species" species="grandiclava">grandiclava</taxonomicName>
/ P. Kanaar des. 1989&quot; (printed-written label) (NCB). Paratypes: 1 ♂, with identical labels as the Holotype, with an extra blue, margined label: &quot;Museum Leiden / 
<taxonomicName authority="Gyllenhal, 1808" authorityName="Gyllenhal" authorityYear="1808" class="Insecta" family="Corydiidae" genus="Histeroidea" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Histeroidea" order="Blattodea" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="superFamily" superFamily="Histeroidea">Histeroidea</taxonomicName>
/ collection / dr P. Kanaar&quot; (NCB); 4 ♀♀ paratypes, with extracted genitalia and identical labels to those of the Holotype (NCB). One of the female paratypes bears another light yellow label: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“10-118”">&quot;10-118&quot;</normalizedToken>
(pencil-written) added by the senior author; followed by another green label: &quot;Photographed by / B. Rhode&quot; (printed) (NCB).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Additional material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">
Indonesia. West Papua: 1 spec., road Nabire-Ilaga, km 62, 250 m, 24.vii.1991, M. Balke leg. (ZSM). PAPUA NEW GUINEA. 1 ♀, Huon Golf, Sattelberg, 1899, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Biró">Biro</normalizedToken>
leg. (HNHM).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Unknown.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Indonesia: Papua (former Irian Jaya). New to Papua New Guinea (Fig. 755).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">
This is the only species of the Australopacific 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" rank="subFamily" subFamily="Saprininae">Saprininae</taxonomicName>
that lacks sensory areas (or plaques) on the ventral side of the antennal club.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="124" lastPageNumber="125" pageId="119" pageNumber="120" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Re-description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="119" pageNumber="120">Body length: PEL: 4.00-4.50 mm; APW: 1.50-1.75 mm; PPW: 3.25 mm; EL: 2.75 mm; EW: 3.50-3.60 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="120" pageNumber="121">
<pageBreakToken pageId="120" pageNumber="121" start="start">Body</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 439), convex, pronotum dark brown with faint bronze metallic luster, elytra dark blue with metallic tinge; propygidium and pygidium black; legs, mouthparts and antennal scape castaneous brown to red; antennal club black.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="120" pageNumber="121">Antennal scape (Fig. 440) slightly thickened, coarsely punctate, with several short setae; antennal club (Figs 441-442) unusually large for the genus, shaped like an inverted heart, apical part distinctly depressed, covered with dense short sensilla intermingled with sparse longer erect setae; sensory structures of antennal club externally absent, vesicle(s) not examined.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="120" pageNumber="121">
<paragraph pageId="120" pageNumber="121">
Figures 440-448. 440 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava" order="Coleoptera" pageId="120" pageNumber="121" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandiclava" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava</taxonomicName>
Kanaar, 1989 head, dorsal view 441 antennal club, dorsal view 442 ditto, ventral view 443 clypeus + labrum, dorsal view 444 propygidium + pygidium 445 prosternum 446 mesoventrite 447 lateral disc of metaventrite + metepisternum 448 protibia, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="121" lastPageNumber="122" pageId="120" pageNumber="121">
Mandibles dorso-laterally rather coarsely punctate, rounded, mandibular apex acute, sub-apical tooth on left mandible obtuse; labrum (Fig. 443) finely and sparsely 
<pageBreakToken pageId="121" pageNumber="122" start="start">punctate</pageBreakToken>
, convex, with distinct median depression; labral pits present, labral setae broken off; other mouthparts not examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="121" pageNumber="122">Clypeus (Fig. 443) flattened, rugosely punctate; frontal stria widely interrupted medially, but not prolonged onto clypeus, supraorbital stria slightly carinate; frontal disc (Fig. 440) densely punctate, punctures separated by about their diameter; eyes convex, well visible from above.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="122" lastPageNumber="123" pageId="121" pageNumber="122">
Pronotal sides (Fig. 439) moderately narrowing anteriorly, apical angles obtuse, pronotal depressions deep, well-impressed; anterior incision for head shallow; marginal pronotal stria complete, carinate, visible along its entire length from dorsal view; pronotal disc laterally with a depressed band of deep dense elongate punctures originating approximately in pronotal depressions, but not reaching basal angles of pronotum, between it and pronotal margin a narrow smooth band present; rest of the pronotal disc with only scattered microscopic punctation; several rows of fine ovoid punctures present along pronotal base reaching ante-scutellar area in a form of a single row of 
<pageBreakToken pageId="122" pageNumber="123" start="start">fine</pageBreakToken>
punctures; pronotal hypomeron glabrous, with scattered punctation; scutellum small, visible.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Elytral epipleura with sparse fine punctures; marginal epipleural stria complete; marginal elytral stria well impressed, carinate, continued as complete (weakened) apical elytral stria. Humeral elytral stria well impressed on basal third, faintly connected to inner subhumeral stria, between it and first dorsal elytral stria a short complementary fragment of stria present; four dorsal elytral striae 1-4 well impressed, in fine punctures, all striae about the same length, approximately apically attaining elytral half; fourth dorsal elytral stria basally connected with complete sutural elytral stria that is apically connected with apical elytral stria; elytral disc on apical half (roughly) punctate, punctures separated by about twice their diameter, along elytral suture punctation reaches slightly further basally than along elytral flanks, punctures almost not entering elytral intervals; punctation becomes finer but denser apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Propygidium (Fig. 444) almost completely exposed, densely punctate, punctures separated by less than their diameter; pygidium (Fig. 444) with sparser punctation, punctures separated by about their own diameter; interspaces in both cases imbricate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Anterior margin of median portion of prosternum (Fig. 445) rounded laterally; marginal prosternal stria present only laterally; prosternal process between carinal prosternal striae slightly convex, on prosternal apophysis and near united apices of carinal prosternal striae depressed, sparsely and finely punctate; carinal prosternal striae carinate, parallel on basal two-thirds, on apical third slightly divergent and thence slightly convergent, united in front (Fig. 465); lateral prosternal striae carinate, strongly convergent, apically attaining carinal prosternal striae almost near their united apices.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Anterior margin of mesoventrite (Fig. 446) almost straight; discal marginal mesoventral stria well impressed, carinate, complete; disc with coarse and dense punctation, punctures of various sizes; meso-metaventral sutural stria indicated by a dense row of large punctures; intercoxal disc of metaventrite flattened; disc for the most part almost smooth, surface around apical corners and along lateral metaventral stria with scattered punctation, punctures of various sizes, along posterior margin and especially behind metacoxa several rows of larger punctures appear; lateral metaventral stria (Fig. 447) well impressed, carinate, almost straight, shortened; lateral disc of metaventrite (Fig. 447) slightly concave, with dense shallow large punctures of various sizes; metepisternum (Fig. 447) with similar punctures; metepisternal stria present only along fused metepimeron.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="122" pageNumber="123">Intercoxal disc of first abdominal ventrite completely striate laterally; disc along basal and lateral margins with shallow punctures of various sizes; rest of ventrite with scattered microscopic punctation.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="123" lastPageNumber="124" pageId="122" pageNumber="123">
Protibia (Fig. 448) slightly dilated, outer margin with six moderately large triangular teeth topped by small rounded denticle, teeth diminishing in size proximally; setae of outer row regular, short; protarsal groove deep; anterior protibial stria complete; setae of median row worn off; two tarsal denticles present near tarsal insertion; protibial spur large, bent, growing out from apical margin of protibia; outer part of posterior surface glabrous, separated from glabrous and narrow median part of posterior surface 
<pageBreakToken pageId="123" pageNumber="124" start="start">by</pageBreakToken>
a definite stria bearing a sparse row of setae; posterior protibial stria complete, apically with a short but dense row of setae; inner row of setae double, setae dense, though probably worn off partially.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="124" lastPageNumber="125" pageId="123" pageNumber="124">
Mesotibia slender, outer margin with a regular row of sparse short denticles slightly growing in size apically, another row of much shorter sparser denticles situated on anterior surface of mesotibia; setae of outer row regular, partially worn off, almost as long as denticles themselves; setae of median row shorter and finer; posterior mesotibial stria almost complete; anterior surface of mesotibia slightly rugulose; anterior mes 
<pageBreakToken pageId="124" pageNumber="125" start="start">otibial</pageBreakToken>
stria almost complete, terminating in two tiny denticles; mesotibial spur stout, short; apical margin of mesotibia anteriorly with two short denticles; claws of apical tarsomere slightly bent, shorter than half its length; metatibia slenderer and longer than mesotibia, in all aspects similar to it, but denticles on outer margin much shorter and sparser.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
Male genitalia. Eighth sternite (Fig. 449) apically with thin vela; apices with a tuft of short setae; eighth tergite (Fig. 450) faintly inwardly arcuate apically; eighth sternite and tergite fused laterally (Fig. 451). Ninth tergite with strongly sclerotized median line, apico-laterally with pores, basally strongly sclerotized. Tenth tergite (Fig. 452) basally and apically faintly inwardly arcuate; laterally strongly sclerotized. Spiculum gastrale on basal end sub-triangular, outwardly arcuate; apex inwardly arcuate (Figs 454-455). Aedeagus (Figs 456-457) bi-sinuate, apical third with pores and pseudopores; parameres narrowly separated on their apical half. Phallobase short, its length approximately equals 1/6 of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="paramere’s">paramere's</normalizedToken>
length.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
<paragraph pageId="124" pageNumber="125">
Figures 449-457. 449 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Saprinus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava" order="Coleoptera" pageId="124" pageNumber="125" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="grandiclava" subGenus="Saprinus">Saprinus (Saprinus) grandiclava</taxonomicName>
Kanaar, 1989 male terminalia: 8th sternite + 8th tergite, ventral view 450 ditto, dorsal view 451 ditto, lateral view 452 male terminalia: 9th + 10th tergites, dorsal view 453 ditto, lateral view 454 male terminalia: spiculum gastrale, ventral view 455 ditto, lateral view 456 male terminalia: aedeagus, dorsal view 457 ditto, lateral view
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>