<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.118.914" ID-GBIF-Dataset="8b1d50e6-599c-41ef-bd3a-d38b1f2a930f" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030306" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-118-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2011" ModsDocID="1313-2970-118-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 118" ModsDocTitle="Review of the genus Stephanospathius Belokobylskij, 1992 (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), with discussion of their tribal position" checkinTime="1451250184364" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Belokobylskij, Sergey A." docDate="2011" docId="9AE632774D8126BFD88A3DDB746974CF" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 118: 1-17" docOrigin="ZooKeys 118" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.118.914" docTitle="Stephanospathius ornatipes Kieffer 1911" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" masterDocId="FFD1286CA47C762EFFF1635BFFF53334" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Stephanospathius Belokobylskij, 1992 (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), with discussion of their tribal position" masterLastPageNumber="17" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" updateTime="1643555458986" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the genus Stephanospathius Belokobylskij, 1992 (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), with discussion of their tribal position</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Belokobylskij, Sergey A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2011</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>118</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>17</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.118.914</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.118.914</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-118-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">8C84074E-2752-4CBB-AF83-33D01460A127</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152030306" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:9AE632774D8126BFD88A3DDB746974CF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9AE632774D8126BFD88A3DDB746974CF" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://species-id.net/wiki/Stephanospathius_ornatipes" authority="Kieffer, 1911" authorityName="Kieffer" authorityYear="1911" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Stephanospathius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephanospathius ornatipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ornatipes">Stephanospathius ornatipes (Kieffer, 1911)</taxonomicName>
Figs 1-12
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName authority="Smith, 1859" authorityName="Smith" authorityYear="1859" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Stenophasmus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenophasmus ornatipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ornatipes">Stenophasmus ornatipes</taxonomicName>
<bibRefCitation author="Kieffer, JJ" journalOrPublisher="Bolletino della Societe Entomologica Italiana" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" pagination="116 - 121" title="Nouveaux Stephanides d'Afrique." volume="41" year="1911">Kieffer, 1911</bibRefCitation>
: 119.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Stephanospathius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephanospathius ornatipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ornatipes">Stephanospathius ornatipes</taxonomicName>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="Belokobylskij, SA" journalOrPublisher="Entomologicheskoe obozrenie" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" pagination="900 - 928" title="On the classification and phylogeny of the braconide wasps of subfamilies Doryctinae and Exothecinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae). Part I. On the classification, 1." volume="71" year="1992">Belokobylskij 1992</bibRefCitation>
: 919, 
<bibRefCitation author="Yu, DS" journalOrPublisher="Taxapad, Vancouver" pageId="12" pageNumber="13" title="World Ichneumonoidea 2004. Taxonomy, biology, morphology and distribution. CD / DVD." url="www.taxapad.com" year="2005">Yu et al. 2005</bibRefCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="examined material">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Examined material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Male (holotype), &quot;Kamerun, Conradt&quot;, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Syntypus”">&quot;Syntypus&quot;</normalizedToken>
(red), &quot; 
<taxonomicName authority="Smith, 1859" authorityName="Smith" authorityYear="1859" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Stenophasmus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenophasmus ornatipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ornatipes">Stenophasmus ornatipes</taxonomicName>
n. sp.&quot; (handwriting by Kieffer), &quot;Kieffer det.&quot; (handwriting), &quot;Holotypus 
<taxonomicName authority="Smith, 1859" authorityName="Smith" authorityYear="1859" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Stenophasmus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stenophasmus ornatipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ornatipes">Stenophasmus ornatipes</taxonomicName>
Kieffer&quot; (red), &quot; 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Stephanospathius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephanospathius ornatipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ornatipes">Stephanospathius ornatipes</taxonomicName>
(Kieffer), det. Belokobylskij, 1992&quot; (SDEI); 1 female, Republic of Congo, &quot;Musee du Conco, Mayumbe: Dinai, 19 - X - 1924, A. Collart&quot; (MRAC); 1 female, Republic of Congo, &quot;Musee du Conco, Mayumbe: Buhurumbe (?), 10 - X - 1924, A. Collart&quot; (ZISP); 1 female (without head and most part of legs), Republic of Congo, &quot;Musee du Conco, Eala, VII - 1936, J. Ghesquiere&quot; (MRAC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Description.</paragraph>
<subSection lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="8" pageId="4" pageNumber="5" type="female">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Female</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Body length 10.6-16.2 mm; fore wing length 7.4-10.8 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Head width 1.1-1.2 times its median length, 1.0-1.1 times its total length, 1.15-1.2 times its maximum height, 1.2-1.3 times maximum width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex anteriorly and distinctly roundly narrowed posteriorly or entirely roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 1.4-1.5 times longer than temple. Ocelli medium-sized, in triangle with base 1.3-1.4 times its sides, situated before middle of head. POL 1.5 times Od, 0.6-0.7 times OOL. Occiput with dense and white setae (dorsal view). Eye 1.25-1.3 times as high as broad. Malar space height 0.2-0.25 times height of eye, 0.5-0.7 times basal width of mandible. Face width 0.8-0.85 times height of eye and 1.0-1.1 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeus distinctly convex. Width of hypoclypeal depression 1.1-1.3 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.45-0.5 times width of face. Hypostomal flange very narrow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="5">Antennae slender, weakly setiform, more than 54-segmented (apical segments missing). Scape short and wide, apically curvedly cutting along outer side, 1.5-1.6 times longer than maximum width. First flagellar segment almost round in dissection, distinctly curved basally, 5.0-5.5 times longer than its apical width, 0.9-0.95 times as long as second segment. Most flagellar segments with fine median constriction. Subapical segments 3.3 times longer than their width.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="4" pageNumber="5">
Mesosoma 2.7-3.2 times longer than its height, 2.6 times longer than its maximum width. Median lobe of mesoscutum distinctly protruding forward and convex anteriorly. Mesoscutum 1.3-1.4 times longer than its maximum width. Notauli finely and 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="6" start="start">widely</pageBreakToken>
striate. Prescutellar depression shallow, rather narrow medially and wider laterally, with distinct median carina, almost smooth on rest part or sometimes with short sparse rugae, medially 0.2 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum flat, 1.1 times longer 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="7" start="start">than</pageBreakToken>
maximum width. Subalar depression almost entirely finely rugulose-reticulate, with distinct and short striae anteriorly.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Wings. Fore wing 5.0-5.3 times longer than its maximum width. Pterostigma 6.0-7.0 times longer than wide. Metacarp 1.4-1.7 times longer than pterostigma. First and second radial abscissae forming very obtuse angle. Second radial abscissa 3.0-3.5 times longer than first abscissa, 0.55-0.6 times as long as the almost straight third abscissa, 1.3-1.5 times longer than first radiomedial vein. Second radiomedial cell long and wide, 3.2-3.6 times longer than its maximum width, 0.85-1.0 times as long as the rather wide brachial cell. First medial abscissa distinctly concavely curved. Nervulus postfurcal, distance from nervulus to basal vein about 0.4 times nervulus length. Hind wing 7.5-8.0 times longer than wide. First costal abscissa 0.45-0.5 times as long as second abscissa. Recurrent vein short, straight or weakly curved, weakly postfurcal or antefurcal, pigmented.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Legs. Hind coxa elongate-oval, with long and rather narrow basoventral tooth, 2.5 times without tooth or 2.2-2.3 times with tooth longer than wide, tooth with dense and white pubescence. Hind femur 4.8-5.1 times longer than wide, 0.55-0.6 times as long as hind tibia. Hind tarsus 1.1 times longer than hind tibia. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.5 times as long as basitarsus, 4.0 times longer than fourth segment, 2.0 times longer than fifth segment (without pretarsus).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Metasoma 1.8-2.0 times longer than head and mesosoma combined. Petiole very weakly or weakly and evenly widened towards apex. Maximum width of first tergum almost equal to its width at level of spiracular tubercles, 1.8-2.0 times its minimum width; length of petiole 7.3-8.8 times its maximum width, 0.9-1.1 times length of mesosoma, 0.7-0.85 times length of head and mesosoma combined. Median length of second tergum 2.5-3.0 times its basal width, 1.3-1.4 times length of third tergum. Length of second and third terga combined 5.0 times basal width of second tergum, 0.6-0.7 times length of petiole.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="8" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
Sculpture and pubescence. Vertex, frons and temple smooth, temple below with distinct striation on narrow part; face almost entirely coarsely and densely rugose-reticulate, clypeus densely reticulate-rugose. Pronotum mostly smooth, its side below distinctly curvedly striate at narrow area. Mesoscutum smooth on median lobe, its lateral lobes finely and densely punctate, medially mesoscutum densely rugulose or rugulose-striate. Scutellum almost smooth or sparsely and finely punctate. Mesopleuron smooth in lower 0.8-0.9. Propodeum without delineated areas, with distinct and complete median and two weakly curvedly convergent posteriorly lateral longitudinal carinae, entirely coarsely and mostly transversely rugose-striate, sculpture medially sometimes distinctly fine. Metapleuron rugose-striate, but sometimes sculpture fine. Hind coxae densely transversely striate in dorsal half, finely rugulose-striate to almost smooth in ventral half. Hind femur dorsally very finely rugulose-reticulate, sometimes almost smooth, smooth on the most part. First tergum almost entirely densely transversely striate, often finely sculptured basally and almost smooth apically at short distance. Second tergum mostly smooth, rugose-striate in basal area. Remaining terga smooth. Vertex in posterior 0.2-0.3 with rather dense, long and semi-erect pale setae, remainder of vertex glabrous. Median lobe of mesoscutum sparsely and shortly setose, almost glabrous an 
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="8" start="start">teriorly</pageBreakToken>
; lateral lobes entirely with dense, semi-erect and mainly short pale setae, with additional sparse long setae along notauli and marginally. Metapleural lobe with short and dense pubescence. Hind tibia dorsally with numerous and dense short and sparse long semi-erect setae; length of long setae 0.5-0.9 times maximum width of hind tibia.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Colour. Head reddish brown or dark reddish brown, darkened dorsally, face sometimes mostly yellowish brown, malar space yellow or brownish yellow. Metasoma almost black. Petiole and second metasomal tergum reddish brown or dark reddish brown, often petiole black, remaining terga brownish yellow or light reddish brown, but infuscate medio-posteriorly. Palpi pale yellow. Fore and middle legs yellow or pale brownish yellow, fore tarsi infuscate, middle trochantellus and wide submedian part of femur more or less brown. Hind coxa, trochanter, trochantellus and femur dark reddish brown to almost black at least partly, tibia brownish yellow, but infuscate apically, tarsus yellowish brown; apical segments of all tarsi infuscate. Fore wing evenly and very faintly infuscate. Pterostigma entirely dark brown.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" pageId="7" pageNumber="8" type="male">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Male</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Body length 11.6 mm; fore wing length 6.6 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Head width 1.1 times its median length, equal to its total length, 1.15 times its maximum height, equal to maximum width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex anteriorly and distinctly roundly narrowed posteriorly. Transverse diameter of eye 1.3 times longer than temple. Ocelli medium-sized, in triangle with base 1.3 times its sides, situated before middle of head. POL 1.4 times Od, 0.75 times OOL. Occiput with very dense and white setae (dorsal view). Eye 1.3 times as high as broad. Malar space height 0.2 times height of eye, about 0.5 times basal width of mandible. Face width 0.85 times height of eye and 1.1 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeus distinctly convex. Width of hypoclypeal depression equal to distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.4 times width of face. Hypostomal flange very narrow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Antennae entirely missing.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Mesosoma 3.2 times longer than its height, about 3.0 times longer than its maximum width. Median lobe of mesoscutum distinctly protruding forward and convex anteriorly. Mesoscutum 1.4 times longer than maximum width. Notauli mostly almost smooth. Prescutellar depression shallow, rather narrow medially and wider laterally, with distinct median carina, almost entirely smooth, medially 0.2 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum flat, 1.1 times longer than maximum width. Subalar depression entirely rugose-striate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="8">Wings. Fore wing 4.8 times longer than its maximum width. Pterostigma 6.5 times longer than width. Metacarp 1.3 times longer than pterostigma. First and second radial abscissae forming very obtuse angle. Second radial abscissa 4.0 times longer than first abscissa, 0.6 times as long as the straight third abscissa, 1.5 times longer than first radiomedial vein. Second radiomedial cell long and wide, 3.3 times longer than its maximum width, 0.9 times as long as the wide brachial cell. First medial abscissa distinctly curved. Nervulus very weakly postfurcal. Hind wing 7.0 times longer than width. First costal abscissa 0.5 times as long as second abscissa. Recurrent vein short, straight, weakly postfurcal, pigmented.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="9" pageId="7" pageNumber="8">
Legs. Hind coxa without basoventral tooth, elongate-oval, 2.7 times longer than width. Hind femur 4.8 times longer than width, 0.55 times as long as hind tibia. Hind 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="9" start="start">tarsus</pageBreakToken>
almost as long as hind tibia. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.45 times as long as basitarsus, 3.3 times longer than fourth segment, 1.6 times longer than fifth segment (without pretarsus).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Metasoma 2.4 times longer than head and mesosoma combined. Petiole mostly almost parallel-sided, weakly and curvedly widened in apical 0.25. Maximum width of first tergum 0.85 times its width at level of spiracular tubercles, 1.6 times its minimum width; length of petiole 13.0 times its maximum width, 1.25 times length of mesosoma, 0.95 times length of head and mesosoma combined. Median length of second tergum 4.5 times its basal width, 1.4 times length of third tergum. Length of second and third terga combined almost 8.0 times basal width of second tergum, 0.65 times length of petiole</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Sculpture and pubescence. Vertex, frons and temple smooth; face almost entirely coarsely and densely striate-rugose, clypeus rugose. Pronotum mostly smooth, its side below distinctly striate at narrow area. Mesoscutum mostly smooth, its lateral lobes finely punctate, finely rugulose latero-marginally. Scutellum smooth. Mesopleuron smooth in lower 0.7. Propodeum without delineated areas, with distinct median and two weakly convergent posteriorly lateral longitudinal complete carinae, entirely coarsely and mostly transversely rugose-striate. Metapleuron coarsely rugose-striate. Hind coxae entirely densely transversely and semi-circularly striate. Hind femur dorsally finely rugulose-reticulate. First tergum entirely densely transversely striate, sometimes partly rugulose-striate. Second tergum basally finely and densely striate. Remaining terga smooth. Vertex in posterior 0.3 with rather dense, long and semi-erect pale setae, remainder of vertex glabrous. Median lobe of mesoscutum sparsely and shortly setose, glabrous anteriorly; lateral lobes almost entirely with dense, semi-erect and mainly short pale setae, with additional sparse long setae along notauli and marginally. Metapleural lobe with short and dense pubescence posteriorly. Hind tibia dorsally with numerous and dense short and sparse long semi-erect setae; length of long setae 0.4-0.7 times maximum width of hind tibia.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">Colour. Head and metasoma reddish brown to dark reddish brown, face laterally pale, malar space yellow. Petiole yellowish brown, remainder metasoma brownish yellow, but brown apically. Palpi pale yellow. Fore and middle legs yellow or brownish yellow. Hind coxa and trochanter reddish brown, femur brownish yellow, tibia and tarsus almost yellow; apical segments of all tarsi infuscate. Fore wing hyaline. Pterostigma entirely brown.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="9">
Figures 1-12. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Stephanospathius" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Stephanospathius ornatipes" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="8" pageNumber="9" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="ornatipes">Stephanospathius ornatipes</taxonomicName>
(Kieffer) (1-4, 6, 7, 9, 10, 12 - male; 5, 8, 11 - female) 1 head and mesosoma, lateral view 2 head and mesosoma, dorsal view 3 first tergite, lateral view 4, 5 first tergite, dorsal view 6 second-fifth tergites, dorsal view 7, 8 propodeum and propodeal bridge, posterior view 9 fore femur and tibia, inner view 10 hind coxa, trochanters and trochantellus and basal part of middle leg 11 hind coxa, trochanters and trochantellus 12 fore and hind wings.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSection>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>