<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6180693" ID-GBIF-Dataset="155cefd2-7fbd-4482-9f7d-bcc96d645bb7" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119428071" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6180693" checkinTime="1460423865124" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Pogue, Michael G." docDate="2012" docId="03F9878AE400FFAAF9F967A7FD2D32D2" docLanguage="en" docName="zt03153p031.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 3153" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@4241c298" docStyleName="zootaxa.2007.monograph" docTitle="Oruza albocostaliata (Packard) The White-Edge" docType="treatment" docVersion="7" lastPageNumber="7" masterDocId="FFC0FFF2E406FFACF96E6538FF963522" masterDocTitle="The Aventiinae, Boletobiinae, Eublemminae, Pangraptinae, Phytometrinae, and Scolecocampinae (Lepidoptera: Noctuoidea: Erebidae) of Great Smoky Mountains National Park, U. S. A." masterLastPageNumber="31" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" updateTime="1645342727231" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Aventiinae, Boletobiinae, Eublemminae, Pangraptinae, Phytometrinae, and Scolecocampinae (Lepidoptera: Noctuoidea: Erebidae) of Great Smoky Mountains National Park, U. S. A.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Pogue, Michael G.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3153</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>31</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.279582</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">155cefd2-7fbd-4482-9f7d-bcc96d645bb7</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">279582</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6180693" ID-GBIF-Taxon="119428071" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6180693" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03F9878AE400FFAAF9F967A7FD2D32D2" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F9878AE400FFAAF9F967A7FD2D32D2" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<subSubSection box="[151,775,671,697]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,775,671,730]" box="[151,775,671,697]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,775,671,697]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,775,671,697]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<number box="[151,166,671,697]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" value="1.0">1</number>
. 
<taxonomicName authority="(Packard) The White-Edge" authorityName="(Packard) The White-Edge" box="[180,775,671,697]" class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Oruza" kingdom="Animalia" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="albocostaliata">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[180,429,671,697]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Oruza albocostaliata</emphasis>
(Packard) The White-Edge
</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,775,671,730]" box="[151,320,706,730]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,226,706,730]" captionStart="FIGURES 1 – 32" captionStartId="7.[151,264,1090,1113]" captionTargetBox="[254,1321,193,1046]" captionTargetId="figure@7.[254,1321,193,1046]" captionTargetPageId="7" captionText="FIGURES 1 – 32. Adults. 1, Oruza albocostaliata, m, Maryland, Prince Georges Co., Aquasco, 12 June 1997, J. Glaser; 2, Metalectra discalis, m, Tennessee, Blount Co., Ace Gap Trailhead, GSMNP, 24 July 2000, M. G. Pogue, USNMENT 00154045; 3, Metalectra discalis, m, Maryland, Prince Georges Co., Adelphi, 17 Aug. 1969, D. C. Ferguson; 4, Metalectra quadrisignata, m, North Carolina, Jackson Co., Balsam, 3200 ft., 21 June 1974, D. C. Ferguson; 5, Metalectra quadrisignata, f, Maryland, Montgomery Co., Violette’s Lock, 29 July 1975, D. C. Ferguson; 6, Metalectra richardsi, m, Maryland, Montgomery Co., Colesville, 11 Aug. 1980, D. C. Ferguson; 7, Metalectra richardsi, m, South Carolina, Charleston Co., McClellanville, Wedge Plantation; 1 May 1972, D. C. Ferguson; 8, Metalectra tantillus, m, South Carolina, Charleston Co., McClellanville, Wedge Plantation; 23 Apr. 1974, D. C. Ferguson; 9, Metalectra tantillus, m, Florida, Putnam Co., Welaka, University Reserve, 7 Apr. 1971, D. C. Ferguson; 10, Dyspyralis illocata, f, Canada, Nova Scotia, Queens Co., Lake Kajimukujik, 20 July 1957, D. C. Ferguson; 11, Dyspyralis illocata, m, Canada, Nova Scotia, Queens Co., Lake Kajimukujik, 21 July 1957, D. C. Ferguson; 12, Dyspyralis nigellus, m, Maryland, Montgomery Co., Colesville, 8 July 1986, D. C. Ferguson; 13, Dyspyralis nigellus, m, Maryland, Baltimore Co., Soldiers Delight, 17 July 1993, J. Glaser; 14, Dyspyralis puncticosta, m, New Hampshire, Winnipesaukee, Long Island, 4 Aug. 1972, E. Jäckh; 15 Dyspyralis puncticosta, f, Arkansas, Washington Co., Devil’s Den State Park, 7 July 1966, R. W. Hodges; 16, Eublemma minima, m, Tennessee, Cocke Co., Foothills Parkway, GSMNP, 17 Sep. 2001, J. Brown, USN- MENT 00152848; 17, Eublemma minima, m, Texas, Cameron Co., Brownsville, 9 Nov. 1969, A. &amp; M. E. Blanchard; 18, Ledaea perditalis, m, Florida, Collier Co., Big Cypress Swamp Preserve, Turner Rd., 1.5 mi US Hwy 41, 18 Mar. 1997, M. G. Pogue; 19, Ledaea perditalis, m, Florida, Putnam Co., Welaka, University of Florida Preserve, 26 Mar. 1987, D. C. Ferguson; 20, Pangrapta decoralis, m, North Carolina, Swain Co., 8.3 mi NE GSMNP ent. on 441, Kephart Prong trail, 2825 ft., 10 June 2003, M. G. Pogue, USNMENT 00155798; 21, Pangrapta decoralis, m, Tennessee, Cocke Co., 2.6 mi from St. Rt. 321, Greenbrier entrance, 1620 ft., 27 July 2007, M. Pogue, D. Adamski, M. Metz, GSMNP 1209; 22, Pangrapta decoralis, f, North Carolina, Swain Co., 13.5 mi NE GSMNP ent. on 441, Thomas Divide trail, 4634 ft., 8 June 2003, M. G. Pogue, USNMENT 00155702; 23, Pangrapta decoralis, f, Tennessee, Sevier Co., Jake’s Creek trail, near Campsite  27, GSMNP, 22 July 2004, M. G. Pogue, USNMENT 00221776; 24, Pangrapta decoralis, f, Tennessee, Sevier Co., 1.3 mi W of Jct. 441 &amp; Clingmans Dome Rd., Road Prong trail, 5260 ft., 28 July 2003, M. G. Pogue, USNMENT 00156584; 25, Hemeroplanis habitalis, m, Florida, Highlands Co., Lake Placid, Archbold Biological Station, 19 Feb. 1985, D. C. Ferguson; 26, Hemeroplanis habitalis, m, Oklahoma, Murray Co., Arbuckle Mts., 1 km W Turner Falls, 19 – 30 July 1984, Don &amp; Mignon Davis; 27, Hemeroplanis habitalis, m, Florida, Hillsborough Co., Lutz, 10 May 1916; 28, Hemeroplanis obliqualis, m, Oklahoma, Sequoyah Co., Tenkiller Lake, 3 mi W Blackgum, 6 – 9 July 1979, D. &amp; M. Davis; 29, Spargaloma sexpunctata, m, Maryland, Montgomery Co., Colesville, 8 Aug. 1984, D. C. Ferguson; 30, Spargaloma sexpunctata, f, Maryland, Montgomery Co., Colesville, 6 Aug. 1984, D. C. Ferguson; 31, Hyperstrotia pervertens, m, Maryland, Dorchester Co., 3 mi E Hurlock, 17 May 2004, J. Glaser; 32, Hyperstrotia pervertens, f, New York, Erie Co., Sardinia, Richmond Gulf, 25 July 1940, L. R. Rupert." httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/279583/files/figure.png" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
Fig. 
<number box="[212,226,706,730]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" value="1.0">1</number>
</figureCitation>
, Map 
<number box="[298,313,706,730]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" value="2.0">2</number>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1436,773,1373]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,320,773,798]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Identification.</emphasis>
Forewing length 
<quantity box="[523,675,773,797]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.055" metricValueMax="1.1199999999999999" metricValueMin="0.99" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" unit="mm" value="10.55" valueMax="11.2" valueMin="9.9">9.9–11.2 mm</quantity>
. This species is easily recognizable by the cinnamon-colored forewing with a distinct white band along the costa that continues across the thorax. Antemedial line is white, curved and continues to the posterior margin. Reniform spot is an indistinct area of black scales. Postmedial line is white, slightly sinuate, and continues to posterior margin. Subterminal line consists of a series of somewhat triangular black spots that are between the wing veins and are bordered proximally by a white line. The size and shape of these black spots are somewhat variable. Terminal line consists of a series of tiny, black, triangular spots between the wing veins. Some black scales are randomly scattered over the forewing. Except for the white costa, the hind wing is similar in color and pattern to the forewing. A faint, black discal spot is present and is variable in size, sometimes with only a few scales. Postmedial line from the forewing continues across the entire hind wing. Terminal line in hind wing is the same as forewing.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1436,773,1373]" box="[197,507,1133,1158]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,360,1133,1158]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Flight period.</emphasis>
June to July.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1436,773,1373]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,428,1169,1194]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Collected localities.</emphasis>
North Carolina: Swain Co.: 
<quantity box="[752,844,1169,1193]" metricMagnitude="1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="9.144" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" unit="ft" value="300.0">300 feet</quantity>
above lake on Welch Ridge. Tennessee: Blount Co.: W Foothills Parkway at E end. (
<specimenCount box="[511,650,1205,1229]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" type="generic">
<number box="[511,525,1205,1229]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" value="3.0">3</number>
specimens
</specimenCount>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1436,773,1373]" box="[197,709,1241,1266]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,393,1241,1266]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Elevation range.</emphasis>
<quantity box="[400,554,1241,1265]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.146804" metricValueMax="5.24256" metricValueMin="3.051048" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" unit="ft" value="1360.5" valueMax="1720.0" valueMin="1001.0">1001–1720 ft</quantity>
. (
<quantity box="[571,701,1241,1265]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="4.145" metricValueMax="5.24" metricValueMin="3.05" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" unit="m" value="414.5" valueMax="524.0" valueMin="305.0">305–524 m</quantity>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1436,773,1373]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[197,449,1277,1302]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">General distribution.</emphasis>
This species ranges from Massachusetts to South Carolina, west to Missouri and Texas. It is common in wooded areas of southeastern Ohio.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,1436,773,1373]" box="[199,479,1349,1373]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[199,354,1349,1373]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">Larval hosts.</emphasis>
Unknown.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[151,699,2010,2032]" box="[151,699,2010,2032]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,234,2010,2031]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
MAP 
<number box="[215,229,2010,2031]" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" value="2.0">2</number>
.
</emphasis>
Collecting localities of 
<emphasis box="[477,699,2010,2032]" italics="true" pageId="6" pageNumber="7">
<taxonomicName box="[477,695,2010,2032]" class="Insecta" family="Noctuidae" genus="Oruza" kingdom="Animalia" order="Lepidoptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="7" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="albocostaliata">Oruza albocostaliata</taxonomicName>
.
</emphasis>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>