<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247" ID-GBIF-Dataset="4ab1486d-256b-467d-a0dc-cf6658ed74fa" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127864956" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-647-37" ID-ZBK="B8255BDA82A442DC82F75BF13ACF632A" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1C7553C2-DF16-437F-AC89-95E3BBF141EC" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-647-37" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 647" ModsDocTitle="Review of the genus Craspedolcus Enderlein sensu lato in China, with the description of a new genus and four new species (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Braconinae)" checkinTime="1485645102941" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Li, Yang, van Achterberg, Cornelis &amp; Chen, Xue-xin" docDate="2017" docId="F06E602F09F556D294B8078E88765460" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 647: 37-65" docOrigin="ZooKeys 647" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247" docTitle="Maculibracon luteonervis Li, Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="1C7553C2-DF16-437F-AC89-95E3BBF141EC" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="18" lastPageNumber="55" masterDocId="F361FF8F0F34FFAAFFC4FFA6FF871747" masterDocTitle="Review of the genus Craspedolcus Enderlein sensu lato in China, with the description of a new genus and four new species (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Braconinae)" masterLastPageNumber="65" masterPageNumber="37" pageId="14" pageNumber="51" updateTime="1643567205425" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Review of the genus Craspedolcus Enderlein sensu lato in China, with the description of a new genus and four new species (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Braconinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Yang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>van Achterberg, Cornelis</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Chen, Xue-xin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>647</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>37</mods:start>
<mods:end>65</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.647.11247</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-647-37</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">B8255BDA82A442DC82F75BF13ACF632A</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">B8255BDA82A442DC82F75BF13ACF632A</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127864956" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1C7553C2-DF16-437F-AC89-95E3BBF141EC" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F06E602F09F556D294B8078E88765460" lastPageId="18" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="14" pageNumber="51">
<subSubSection pageId="14" pageNumber="51" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="51">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/1C7553C2-DF16-437F-AC89-95E3BBF141EC" authority="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017" authorityName="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen" authorityYear="2017" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Maculibracon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Maculibracon luteonervis" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="51" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="luteonervis">Maculibracon luteonervis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="14" pageNumber="51">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 67, 68-79
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="52" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="52">
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="52" start="start">Type</pageBreakToken>
material.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="52">Holotype, ♀ (IZAS), &quot;[China:] Yunnan, Xishuangbanna, Menghun, 750 m, 1.VI.1958, Yiran Zhang, No. IOZ(E)1964632&quot;.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="52" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="52">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="52">
Scapus mainly yellowish brown, except for dark brown stripe on outer side, rather slender and less protruding ventrally (Fig. 74); head roundly narrowed posteriorly (Fig. 76); propodeum medio-posteriorly with smooth protuberance in lateral view (Fig. 78); medial area of first tergite low anteriorly (Fig. 78); wing membrane yellow with slightly infuscate apical area of fore wing wide and rather close to vein 1r-m; stigmal spot of fore wing up to anterior half of first discal cell, enclosing 0.6 of vein 1-SR+M (Figs 68, 69); pterostigma entirely yellow (Fig. 68); medio-basal area of second tergite nearly rhombic (Fig. 72); vein 1-SR+M of fore wing yellow; body and hind leg brownish yellow; length of ovipositor sheath 0.8 times fore wing and 0.8 times body. Similar to 
<taxonomicName authority="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017" authorityName="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen" authorityYear="2017" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Maculibracon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Maculibracon laertius" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laertius">Maculibracon laertius</taxonomicName>
(Cameron, 1903) because of the yellowish scapus in dorsal view, medium-sized stigmal sport of the fore wing, anteriorly low medial area of the first tergite and the wide apical infuscate area of the fore wing. The new species differs by having the apex of the pterostigma yellow (versus dark brown in 
<taxonomicName authority="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen, 2017" authorityName="Li, van Achterberg &amp; Chen" authorityYear="2017" class="Insecta" family="Braconidae" genus="Maculibracon" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Maculibracon laertius" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laertius">Maculibracon laertius</taxonomicName>
), ovipositor sheath 0.8 times fore wing (versus about 0.4 times), stigmal spot nearly square (versus obliquely narrowed) and head gradually roundly narrowed posteriorly in dorsal view (versus obliquely narrowed).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="17" lastPageNumber="54" pageId="15" pageNumber="52" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="52">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="52">Holotype, ♀, length of body 17.1 mm, of fore wing 16.7 mm, of ovipositor sheath 13.0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="53" pageId="15" pageNumber="52">
Head. Antenna incomplete, left antenna with 75 segments remaining; scapus rather stout, 1.5 times longer than wide and distinctly emarginated apically, slightly longer ventrally than dorsally in lateral view, with a narrow apical ledge at inner side and gradually narrowed basally (Fig. 74); third and fourth segments 1.4 and 1.0 times their maximum width, respectively; length of maxillary palp as long as the height of head; inner side of eye not emarginated but slightly sinuate (Fig. 75); face moderately convex but flattened medially and medio-dorsally with weak median crest, densely punctate, and with long erect setae; clypeus flat, punctate, dorsally with coarse curved carina and ventral margin thin and lamelliform, with few long setae ventrally; hypoclypeal depression 0.4 times as wide as minimum width of face (Fig. 75); frons shallowly concave behind antennal sockets, smooth, except for a rather shallow median groove (Fig. 75); 
<pageBreakToken pageId="16" pageNumber="53" start="start">vertex</pageBreakToken>
smooth, with few long setae and shiny; stemmaticum distinctly protruding; OOL:diameter of posterior ocellus:POL = 24:9:8; in dorsal view length of eye 1.9 times temple; temples gradually roundly narrowed behind eyes, with some long setae, almost smooth dorsally and sparsely punctate ventrally (Figs 76, 77); malar suture shallow, curved; length of malar space 0.8 times basal width of mandible; mandible twisted, both teeth robust and subequal.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="54">
<pageBreakToken pageId="17" pageNumber="54" start="start">Mesosoma</pageBreakToken>
. Length of mesosoma 2.1 times its height (Fig. 70); side of pronotum shiny and smooth; propleuron with spaced punctures; pronotum vertical anteriorly, with a shallow pronope and groove and narrow antescutal depression; mesopleuron smooth and glabrous, except for an oblique band with punctures and short setae; mesosternal sulcus smooth and narrow; metapleuron smooth and with long setae, convex; mesoscutum glabrous except some setae near notaulic courses, shiny and smooth; notauli smooth, only distinct anteriorly and medially shallowly impressed; scutellar sulcus present and with distinct fine crenulae; scutellum distinctly convex and smooth except for some punctures; side of scutellum smooth; metanotum medio-anteriorly with short carina, posteriorly evenly convex and smooth; propodeum distinctly remotely punctate, with long setae, evenly convex but medio-posteriorly with one smooth protuberance (Fig. 71), ribbed in lateral view (Fig. 78).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="54">Wings. Fore wing (Fig. 68): m-cu 0.8 times as long as 1-M; 1-SR+M angularly bent subbasally 1.4 times as long as 1-M; 3-SR weakly curved, and SR1 straight; r:3-SR:SR1 = 10:55:59; 2-SR:3-SR:r-m = 20:55:19; r-m largely sclerotised; 1-CU1 slightly widened and 0.18 times 2-CU1; cu-a weakly inclivous; CU1b nearly as wide as 3-CU1. Hind wing (Fig. 69): with 6 coarse subbasal bristles on C+SC+R and with 3 hamuli on R1; SR weakly curved basally and marginal cell parallel-sided apically; area near cu-a glabrous; 1r-m straight and 0.95 times as long as SC+R1; 2-SC+R twice longer than wide.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="54">Legs. Tarsal claws simple and with long bristly setae ventrally; length of femur, tibia and basitarsus of hind leg 5.3, 10.0 and 7.9 times their maximum width, respectively; hind tibia with dense and rather appressed setae; one hind tibial spur 0.2 times as long as hind basitarsus, the other is broken; inner side of hind tibia and tarsus densely bristly setose (Fig. 73).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="54">
Metasoma. Length of first tergite 1.5 times its apical width, dorso-lateral carinae strongly developed, medial area smooth except for high median carina and medial area steep anteriorly (Figs 72, 78); second tergite smooth (including deep oblique anterior grooves) except strong median carina connected to minute nearly rhombic medio-basal area, antero-lateral triangular areas large (Fig. 72); second metasomal suture strongly crenulate, laterally narrowed and weakly up curved; medially second tergite 1.4 times longer than third tergite; maximum width of third tergite 2.7 times its medial length; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="third–fifth">third-fifth</normalizedToken>
tergites smooth and without transverse subposterior groove and with long antero-lateral grooves; ovipositor sheath 0.78 times as long as fore wing and 0.76 times body; hypopygium ending just anterior of apex of metasoma (Fig. 67).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="17" pageNumber="54">Colour. Brownish yellow; antenna (scapus mainly yellowish brown, except for dark brown stripe on outer side) and mandible apically dark brown; ovipositor sheath blackish with yellow setae; stigmal spot medium-sized, up to anterior half of first discal cell, enclosing 0.6 of vein 1-SR+M (Fig. 68); veins yellow (included 1-SR+M) except dark brown basal half of 1-SR; pterostigma entirely yellow (Fig. 68); wing membrane yellow, with slightly infuscate apical area of fore wing wide and rather close to vein 1r-m (Figs 68, 69).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="18" pageNumber="55" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="55">
<pageBreakToken pageId="18" pageNumber="55" start="start">Distribution</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="55">*China (Yunnan).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="18" pageNumber="55" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="55">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="18" pageNumber="55">
Named after the yellow vein 1-SR+M of the fore wing, contrasting with the dark brown surrounding stigmal spot. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Luteus”">&quot;Luteus&quot;</normalizedToken>
is Latin for 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“yellow”">&quot;yellow&quot;</normalizedToken>
and 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“nervus”">&quot;nervus&quot;</normalizedToken>
for &quot;sinew, vein&quot;.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>