<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.810.29253" ID-GBIF-Dataset="c800b48c-aff8-46f5-a716-84e0cf16bd4e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154127006" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-810-45" ID-ZBK="5361B3677FA8495D81B27151B77D2CB4" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3C3184B8-A779-436B-87BA-B009F324F54E" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-810-45" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 810" ModsDocTitle="Onychocamptus Daday, 1903 from Thailand, with descriptions of two new species and two new records (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida, Laophontidae)" checkinTime="1545315434524" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Boonyanusith, Chaichat, Saetang, Thanida, Wongkamheng, Koraon &amp; Supiyanit Maiphae," docDate="2018" docId="D6D186ADB10BF7EC816CFE3536BA018B" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 810: 45-89" docOrigin="ZooKeys 810" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.810.29253" docTitle="Onychocamptus tratensis Boonyanusith, Saetang, Wongkamheng &amp; Maiphae, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="3C3184B8-A779-436B-87BA-B009F324F54E" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="60" masterDocId="FFA82031FFF8FFD4FFFA2124FFBAFFD4" masterDocTitle="Onychocamptus Daday, 1903 from Thailand, with descriptions of two new species and two new records (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida, Laophontidae)" masterLastPageNumber="89" masterPageNumber="45" pageId="7" pageNumber="52" updateTime="1643551894690" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Onychocamptus Daday, 1903 from Thailand, with descriptions of two new species and two new records (Crustacea, Copepoda, Harpacticoida, Laophontidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Boonyanusith, Chaichat</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Saetang, Thanida</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wongkamheng, Koraon</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Supiyanit Maiphae,</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>810</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>45</mods:start>
<mods:end>89</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.810.29253</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.810.29253</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-810-45</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">5361B3677FA8495D81B27151B77D2CB4</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">5361B3677FA8495D81B27151B77D2CB4</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="154127006" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3C3184B8-A779-436B-87BA-B009F324F54E" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D6D186ADB10BF7EC816CFE3536BA018B" lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="60" pageId="7" pageNumber="52">
<subSubSection pageId="7" pageNumber="52" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="52">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/3C3184B8-A779-436B-87BA-B009F324F54E" class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="7" pageNumber="52" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="7" pageNumber="52">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 22A, 23B
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="53" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="53">
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="53" start="start">Material</pageBreakToken>
examined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="53">Holotype. Adult female, dissected and mounted onto two slides (PSUZC-PK2003-01-PSUZC-PK2003-02). Allotype. One adult male, dissected and mounted onto two slides (PSUZC-PK2003-03-PSUZC-PK2003-04). Paratypes. One undissected adult female, mounted onto one slide, (PSUZC-PK2003-05). One undissected adult male, mounted onto one slide, (PSUZC-PK2003-06). One adult female, dissected and mounted onto two slides, (PSUZC-PK2003-07-PSUZC-PK2003-08).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="53">All specimens were collected by S Maiphae and T Saetang from type locality on 9 January 2017.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="53" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="53">Additional material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="53">Ten females and five males, all collected from type locality on 9 January 2017 and stored in 70% ethanol, deposited in crustacean reference collection, Zoological Museum, Kasetsart University (ZMKU_CP).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="53" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="53">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="53">
Samer-rach peat swamp, Trat Province, eastern Thailand, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="12.467777">12°28'04.0&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="102.35572">102°21'20.6&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
. Water temperature ranged between 28.83 °C, pH of 6.23, salinity 6.91 ppt, total dissolved solids 7.9 mg L-1, and dissolved oxygen 4.41 mg L-1.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="54" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="54">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="54" start="start">Etymology</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="54">
The specific name 
<taxonomicName genus="O" lsidName="O tratensis" pageId="9" pageNumber="54" rank="species" species="tratensis">tratensis</taxonomicName>
is derived from the name of Trat Province, where the species was collected. The name is a noun in the genitive singular, masculine.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="54" type="differential diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="54">Differential diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="54">
<taxonomicName family="Laophontidae" lsidName="" pageId="9" pageNumber="54" rank="family">Laophontidae</taxonomicName>
. Body gradually tapering posteriorly. One middle and two lateral rounded integumental window-like structures on cephalothorax. Second and third urosomite fused ventrally in female forming genital double-somite. Caudal rami cylindrical, both sides parallel, approximately 2.5 twice as long as wide, with one longitudinal row of minute spinules on inner margin near insertion of dorsal seta and horizontal row of minute spinules near insertion of inner terminal seta. Outer terminal seta (seta IV) fused at base with inner terminal seta. Allobasis of antenna without abexopodal seta. Endopodal lobe of P5 with two bipinnate and one plumose setae on inner margin and exopod of P5 with four plumose setae. Enp-2 of male P3 with apophysis on outer distal corner; apophysis reaching the tip of enp-3. Exopod of male P5 with three bipinnate setae, outer seta two times as long as supporting segment. P6 of the male reduced, with outer seta and inner bipinnate seta apically; inner seta approximately twice as long as outer one.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="58" pageId="9" pageNumber="54" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="54">Description of adult female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="54">
Body. Total body length, measured from tip of rostrum to posterior margin of caudal rami, 360-450 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
(mean 400 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
, n = 14; 420 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
in holotype); preserved specimen colourless. Body covered entirely with setules, cylindrical; gradually tapering posteriorly, with maximum width at posterior part of cephalothorax. Prosome 1.3 times as long as urosome (including caudal rami) (Fig. 9A). Rostrum small, completely fused to cephalothorax. Cephalothorax as long as wide, approximately 0.5 times the length of prosome length, with one middle and two lateral rounded integumental window-like structures on cephalothorax. Cephalothorax and all free thoracic somites with sensillum-bearing tubercles along posterior margin. Second and third urosomite fused ventrally (Fig. 9C, D), distinct dorsally. Genital field ribbon-shaped, with seta representing P6 at outer distal corner (Fig. 9C). The remnant of first abdominal somite (posterior half of genital double-somite) with lateral sensillum-bearing tubercles (Fig. 9C, D). Posterior margin of genital double-somite and fourth urosomites with outer sensillum-bearing tubercles; posterior half of genital double-somite and fourth urosomite with posterior setules dorsally (Fig. 9D) and small spinules ventrally (Fig. 9C) between sensillum-bearing tubercles. The penultimate urosomite with posterior setules dorsally and laterally, with one posterior row of spinules ventrally. Anal somite approximately 0.6 times longer than wide, with arch row of long spinules posterior to anal operculum (Fig. 9D), with ventrolateral row of minute spinules near insertion of caudal rami (Fig. 9C). Anal operculum poorly developed, with minute spinules along posterior margin (Fig. 9D).
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="54">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="54">
Figure 9. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="9" pageNumber="54" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A habitus, dorsal view B habitus, lateral view C urosome, ventral view D urosome, dorsal view E egg sac. Scale bars: 0.1 mm (A, B, E), 0.05 mm (C, D).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="55" pageId="9" pageNumber="54">
Caudal rami (Fig. 9C, D). Cylindrical, both sides parallel, 2.5 times as long as wide, with one longitudinal row of minute inner spinules near insertion of caudal seta (VII) and horizontal row of minute spinules near insertion of inner terminal seta (V). Anterolateral accessory seta (I) minute, inserted, close to anterolateral seta (II), both subapical. Posterolateral seta (III) inserted on minute pedestal. Outer terminal seta (IV) slender, fused at base with inner terminal seta (V), the letter longest, without fracture plane, approximately 0.9 times as long as body length. Inner accessory seta (VI) slender. Dorsal seta (VII) tri-articulate, inserted at quarter of rami. Length ratio 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="55" start="start">of</pageBreakToken>
caudal setae to ramus length, from seta I to seta VII of holotype: 0.5: 1.7: 2.5: 0.7: 13.3: 0.7: 2.0.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Egg sac (Fig. 9E). Ovigerous female with two egg sacs ventrally between pair of P5, each with eight eggs.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Antennule (Fig. 10A). Short, 5-segmented, large aesthetasc on third segment and small aesthetasc on fifth segment. Surface of all segments smooth, except for medial and distal rows of small spinules on first segment. Armature formula I-[1], II-[7+(1+aesthetasc)], III-[8+aesthetasc], IV-[1], V-[9+acrothek]. Aesthetasc on third segment fuse basally to one smooth seta. Apical acrothek consists of one aesthetasc fused basally to two slender smooth setae. Only seta on first segment bipinnate, all other setae smooth.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A antennule B, C antenna D, E 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male allotype D, E exopod of antenna. Scale bar: 0.05 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Antenna (Figs 10B, 22A). Comprising coxa, allobasis, 1-segmented endopod, and exopod. Coxa without ornamentation. Allobasis with one row of inner spinules, with 1-segmented exopod; the latter with two apical and two lateral bipinnate setae. Free endopod with two strong sharp spines accompanied by several strong, short spinules along outer margin, distal end with five elements; one slender seta, two geniculate setae, and two strong spines.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Mandible (Fig. 11A). Gnathobase with strong, chitinised teeth and dorsal pinnate seta along cutting edge. Mandibular palp short, 1-segmented, with five slender setae sub-equal in length.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
Figure 11. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A mandible B maxillule C maxilla D maxilliped. Scale bar: 0.05 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Maxillule (Fig. 11B). Composed of robust precoxa, coxa, basis, endopod fused to basis, and 1-segmented free exopod. Precoxal arthrite with six strong apical spines, with lateral spine. Coxa with cylindrical endite bearing two smooth setae. Basis with cylindrical endite bearing three setae. Endopod incorporated to basis, with three setae. Exopod free, 1-segmented, with two sub-equal apical setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Maxilla (Fig. 11C). Composed of syncoxa, allobasis, and 1-segmented endopod. Syncoxa with two endites; each endite with two apical pinnate setae, outer margin with spinules. Allobasis with apical drawn out into claw, with one anterior and one posterior seta. Endopod 1-segmented, with two smooth apical setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">Maxilliped (Fig. 11D). Subchelate, 3-segmented, comprising syncoxa, basis, and endopod. Syncoxa with one pinnate seta at outer distal corner. Basis with two transverse rows of outer spinules, one of which near base of endopod. Endopod drawn out into strong naked claw, with one small seta near base.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">P1 (Fig. 12A). Intercoxal sclerite naked. Precoxa small and triangular, with one row of spinules at distal margin (not shown). Coxa with one row of long outer spinules. Basis with one outer bipinnate spine and one inner plumose seta near insertion of endopod, with longitudinal row of anterior spinules medially, with long setules along inner margin. Both rami 2-segmented. Exopod reaching proximal third of enp-1; exp-1 with one bipinnate outer spine, with one row of outer spinules; exp-2 with three outer smooth spines and two apical geniculate setae, with row of outer spinules and inner setules. Enp-1 approximately 4.4 times as long as wide, with one row of outer and inner setules; enp-2 with one median strong outwardly curved claw-like smooth spine and one slender inner seta, with few outer spinules.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
Figure 12. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="10" pageNumber="55" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A P1 B P2. Scale bars: 0.05 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="12" lastPageNumber="57" pageId="10" pageNumber="55">
P2 (Fig. 12B). Intercoxal sclerite and precoxa as in P1. Coxa with two oblique parallel rows of long outer spinules (one on anterior and others on posterior surface), with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="56" start="start">one</pageBreakToken>
row of spinules at distal margin, and few spinules at inner margin. Basis with outer bipinnate spine, with spinules at base of spine, with one row of long spinules between exopod and endopod, and with one row of inner setules. Rami with 3-segmented exopod and 2-segmented endopod; endopod reaching tip of exp-2. Exp-1 with one 
<pageBreakToken pageId="12" pageNumber="57" start="start">outer</pageBreakToken>
bipinnate spine; exp-2 with one outer bipinnate spine and one inner plumose seta; exp-3 with three outer bipinnate spines, two apical elements (of which outer one spiniform seta with outer spinules and inner setules, inner element one plumose seta), and one inner plumose seta. All segments of exopod with several rows of strong outer spinules and inner setules, and only exp-1 with one row of outer setules. Enp-1 without armature, enp-2 with two apical and two inner plumose setae. All segments of endopod with one row of long outer and inner setules.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="13" lastPageNumber="58" pageId="12" pageNumber="57">
P3 (Fig. 13A). Intercoxal sclerite and precoxa as in P1. Coxa with two parallel rows of long spinules along outer margin (one on anterior and other on posterior surface). Basis 
<pageBreakToken pageId="13" pageNumber="58" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
one smooth outer seta; with spinules at base of seta and one row of inner setules. Segmentation of rami as in P2, endopod reaching to middle segment of exp-2. Exp-1 with one outer bipinnate spine; exp-2 with one outer bipinnate spine and one inner plumose seta; exp-3 with three outer bipinnate spines, two apical elements (of which outer one spiniform seta with outer spinules and inner setules, inner element one plumose seta), and one inner plumose seta. All segments of exopod with several rows of strong outer spinules and one row of inner setules, and exp-1 and exp-2 with one row of outer setules. Enp-1 without armature, enp-2 with one outer bipinnate seta, two apical, and three inner plumose setae. Outer and inner of all segments of endopod with long setules.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="58">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">
Figure 13. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="13" pageNumber="58" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female holotype. A P3 B P4 C P5. Scale bars: 0.05 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">P4 (Fig. 13B). Intercoxal sclerite and precoxa (not shown) as in P1. Coxa with one row of setules and several outer spinules. Basis with one smooth outer seta; with spinules at base of seta and one row of inner setules. Rami with 3-segmented exopod and 2-segmented endopod, endopod smaller than exopod. Exp-1 with one outer bipinnate spine; exp-2 with one outer bipinnate spine and one inner plumose seta; exp-3 with two outer bipinnate spines, two apical elements (of which outer one bipinnate spine, inner element one plumose seta), and one inner plumose seta. All segments of exopod with several rows of strong outer spinules and with fewer inner setules. Enp-1 without armature, enp-2 with one outer seta with plumose proximally and bipinnate distally, one apical plumose seta, and one inner plumose seta. Outer and inner of all segments of endopod with setules.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">Armature formula of P1-P4 as in Table 1.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">P5 (Figs 13C, 23B). Baseoendopod and exopod separated with setules as figured. Baseoendopod with basal seta and three inner setae on endopodal lobe; one proximal bipinnate seta, one middle bipinnate seta and one apical plumose seta, with one row of spinules at base of each seta, as well as with one distal row of spinules between distal seta of baseoendopod and exopod. Exopod with four plumose setae, with row of inner and outer setules, and with spinules at base of innermost seta.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="13" pageNumber="58" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">Description of adult male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">
Body (Fig. 14A, B). Total body length, measured from tip of rostrum to posterior margin of caudal rami, 340-360 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
(mean 350 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
, n = 3; 350 
<normalizedToken originalValue="µm">µm</normalizedToken>
in paratype); preserved specimen colourless. Prosome approximately 1.5 times as long as urosome. Cephalothorax as long as wide, 0.5 times the length of prosome. All free thoracic somites with sensillum-bearing tubercles along posterior margin, but fifth thoracic somite (first urosomite) with additional row of posterior setules dorsally. Second and third urosomite completely separated. Second urosomite with dorsal sensillum-bearing tubercles along posterior margin. Fourth urosomite without lateral protuberances, with one posterior row of dorsal setules and ventral spinules. Ornamentation on next three urosomites as in female. Anal somite approximately 0.5 times longer than wide. Anal operculum as in female.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="58">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">
Figure 14. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="13" pageNumber="58" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male allotype. A habitus, dorsal view B urosome, ventral view C antennule. Scale bars: 0.1 mm (A), 0.05 mm (B, C).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="58">Caudal rami (Fig. 14A, B). As in female.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="59" pageId="13" pageNumber="58">
Antennule (Fig. 14C). 8-segmented, large aesthetasc on fifth segment and small aesthetasc on eighth segment. First segment with proxim al setules and subdistal outer 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="59" start="start">spinules</pageBreakToken>
, second segment with one row of outer spinules, other segments smooth. Armature formula I-[1], II-[9], III-[3], IV-[2], V-[9+(1+aesthetasc)], VI-[0], VII-[1], VIII-[7+acrothek]. Aesthetasc on fifth segment robust. Apical acrothek consists of one aesthetasc fused basally with two slender smooth setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">Rostrum, antenna (coxa, allobasis, and endopod), mouthparts, and P1 as in female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">P2 (Fig. 15A). Intercoxal sclerite naked. Precoxa small and triangular, with one row of spinules at distal margin. Coxa with two rows of outer spinules. Basis with one outer bipinnate seta, with spinules at base of spine, and with one row of inner setules. Rami with 3-segmented exopod and 2-segmented endopod, endopod reaching to middle of exp-3. Armature and all ornamentation of endopod as in female. Enp-1 without armature, enp-2 with two apical plumose setae and two inner plumose setae. All segments of endopod with one row of outer spinules and one row of inner setules.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="59">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">
Figure 15. 
<taxonomicName class="Hexanauplia" family="Laophontidae" genus="Onychocamptus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Onychocamptus tratensis" order="Harpacticoida" pageId="14" pageNumber="59" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tratensis">Onychocamptus tratensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male allotype. A P2 B P3 C P4. Scale bar: 0.05 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">P3 (Fig. 15B). Intercoxal sclerite and precoxa as in P2. Coxa with two rows of outer spinules. Basis with one outer plumose seta; with spinules at base of seta and one row of inner setules. Both rami 3-segmented, endopod reaching to middle of exp-2. Exp-1 with one outer bipinnate spine; exp-2 with one outer bipinnate spine and one inner plumose seta, inner seta much shorter than in female; exp-3 with three outer bipinnate spines, two apical elements (both spiniform seta with outer spinules and inner setules), and one inner plumose seta, inner seta much shorter than in female. All segments of exopod with several rows of strong outer spinules and one row of inner setules except exp-3. Enp-1 without armature, enp-2 with outer distal apophysis exceeding the tip of enp-3, one inner plumose seta, and with one row of outer spinules and fewer inner setules; enp-3 with two inner plumose setae and two apical plumose setae, and with one row of spinules at base of outer seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">P4 (Fig. 15C). Intercoxal sclerite and precoxa as in P2. Coxa with one row of spinules along outer margin. Basis with one smooth seta on outer distal corner; ornamented with spinules at base of seta and one row of setules along inner margin. Rami with 3-segmented exopod and 2-segmented endopod. Exp-1 with one outer bipinnate spine; exp-2 with one outer bipinnate spine and one inner plumose seta, inner seta much shorter than in female; exp-3 with two outer bipinnate spines, two apical elements (of which outer one spiniform seta with outer spinules and inner setules, inner element one spiniform seta), and one inner plumose seta. Endopod reaching tip of exp-1; enp-1 without armature; enp-2 with one outer bipinnate seta, one apical plumose seta, and one inner plumose seta. All segments of exopod with several rows of strong spinules along outer margin, and with one row of setules along inner margin except exp-3. Armature and all ornamentation of endopod as in female, but presence of one row of spinules at base of apical seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">Armature formula of P1-P4 as in Table 1.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">P5 (Fig. 14B). With outer basal seta arising from long setophore; without endopodal lobe. Exopod with three plumose setae, outermost shortest, 2.5 times as long as segment, approximately 0.5 times as long as the middle seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="59">P6 (Fig. 14B). Reduced to one minute rectangular protuberance, with one outer and one inner bipinnate seta; inner seta approximately twice as long as outer one and reaching posterior margin of next urosomite.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="60" type="variability">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="60">
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="60" start="start">Variability</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="60">In male, variability was observed in the exopod of antenna, four specimens with four setae and one specimen with five setae (Fig. 10D, E). In female antenna, two strong spines of distal end of endopod not fused in six specimens and fused in only one specimen (Fig. 10C).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="15" pageNumber="60" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="60">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="60">This species is known from the type locality only. It was found in two months, January and September 2017.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>