<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.473.3037" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b5a6f009-a825-418a-a45a-d60f6e8d6a1a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152057849" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-473-137" ID-ZBK="AF49AD97E4E84604BBF0B57B9605B011" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2015" ModsDocID="1313-2970-473-137" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 473" ModsDocTitle="Rediscovery and redescription of the sharpshooter Kogigonaliaincarnata (Germar, 1821), comb. n. (Hemiptera, Cicadellidae, Cicadellini) from the Atlantic Forest of Brazil, with a key to the species of the genus" checkinTime="1451244806505" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Mejdalani, Gabriel, Cavichioli, Rodney R., Silva, Roberta Santos &amp; Quintas, Victor" docDate="2015" docId="72E8DF87D79581AD6C5777FF4F1D0DEF" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 473: 137-146" docOrigin="ZooKeys 473" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.473.3037" docTitle="Kogigonalia incarnata Germar 1821, comb. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="143" masterDocId="FFBDFFB47C01FFE8FFA5FFD2FFCFFFB2" masterDocTitle="Rediscovery and redescription of the sharpshooter Kogigonaliaincarnata (Germar, 1821), comb. n. (Hemiptera, Cicadellidae, Cicadellini) from the Atlantic Forest of Brazil, with a key to the species of the genus" masterLastPageNumber="146" masterPageNumber="137" pageId="1" pageNumber="138" updateTime="1643511314454" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Rediscovery and redescription of the sharpshooter Kogigonaliaincarnata (Germar, 1821), comb. n. (Hemiptera, Cicadellidae, Cicadellini) from the Atlantic Forest of Brazil, with a key to the species of the genus</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Mejdalani, Gabriel</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cavichioli, Rodney R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Silva, Roberta Santos</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Quintas, Victor</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2015</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>473</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>137</mods:start>
<mods:end>146</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.473.3037</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.473.3037</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-473-137</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">AF49AD97E4E84604BBF0B57B9605B011</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AF49AD97E4E84604BBF0B57B9605B011</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152057849" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:72E8DF87D79581AD6C5777FF4F1D0DEF" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/72E8DF87D79581AD6C5777FF4F1D0DEF" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="143" pageId="1" pageNumber="138">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="138" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">Taxon classification Animalia Hemiptera Cicadellidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="138" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">
<taxonomicName authority="Germar, 1821" authorityName="Germar" authorityYear="1821" class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Kogigonalia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kogigonalia incarnata" order="Hemiptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="138" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incarnata">Kogigonalia incarnata (Germar, 1821)</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="1" pageNumber="138">comb. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 1, 2, 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="138" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Tettigonia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Tettigonia incarnata" order="Hemiptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="138" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incarnata">Tettigonia incarnata</taxonomicName>
Germar, 1821: 69. Catalogued (as 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Amblyscarta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Amblyscarta incarnata" order="Hemiptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="138" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incarnata">Amblyscarta incarnata</taxonomicName>
) by 
<bibRefCitation author="Metcalf, ZP" journalOrPublisher="Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture, Washington, D. C." pageId="8" pageNumber="145" title="General catalogue of the Homoptera. Fascicle VI, Cicadelloidea. Part 1, Tettigellidae" year="1965">Metcalf (1965)</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="McKamey, SH" journalOrPublisher="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" pagination="1 - 394" title="Taxonomic catalogue of the leafhoppers (Membracoidea). Part 1. Cicadellinae." volume="78" year="2007">McKamey (2007)</bibRefCitation>
, and 
<bibRefCitation author="Wilson, MR" journalOrPublisher="Annales de la Societe Entomologique de France" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" title="National Museum Wales" url="http://naturalhistory.museumwales.ac.uk/sharpshooters/home.php" year="2009">Wilson et al. (2009)</bibRefCitation>
. Redescribed by 
<bibRefCitation author="Blanchard, E" journalOrPublisher="Paris, P. Dumeril" pageId="7" pageNumber="144" title="Histoire naturelle des insectes: Orthopteres, Nevropteres, Hemipteres, Hymenopteres, Lepidopteres et Dipteres. Tome troisieme." url="10.5962/bhl.title.59226" year="1840">Blanchard (1840</bibRefCitation>
: 190) and 
<bibRefCitation author="Signoret, V" journalOrPublisher="Annales de la Societe Entomologique de France" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" pagination="661 - 688" title="Revue iconographique des Tettigonides." volume="1" year="1853">Signoret (1853</bibRefCitation>
: 684, pl. 22, fig. 11). Four syntypes (two males, two females) from 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“Bahia”">&quot;Bahia&quot;</normalizedToken>
(northeastern Brazil) are deposited in the Museum 
<normalizedToken originalValue="für">fuer</normalizedToken>
Naturkunde, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Universität">Universitaet</normalizedToken>
Humboldt, Berlin; we have studied high-resolution images (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–b">a-b</normalizedToken>
, dorsal view of the body) of a male and a female syntype (see 
<bibRefCitation author="Wilson, MR" journalOrPublisher="Annales de la Societe Entomologique de France" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" title="National Museum Wales" url="http://naturalhistory.museumwales.ac.uk/sharpshooters/home.php" year="2009">Wilson et al. 2009</bibRefCitation>
). Two additional syntypes are deposited in the Germar collection in the Ivan Franko National University, Lviv (
<bibRefCitation author="Shydlovskyy, IV" journalOrPublisher="Ivan Franko LNU Publishing, Lviv" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" title="Homopteran insects from the collection of E. - F. Germar in the Zoological Museum of LNU (catalogue)" year="2005">Shydlovskyy and Holovachov 2005</bibRefCitation>
: 41, 
<bibRefCitation author="Holovachov, OV" journalOrPublisher="University Microfilms, Ann Arbor" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" title="Insects of E. - F. Germar in the collections of the Zoological Museum" url="http://zoomus.lviv.ua/en/germar_collection/" year="2008">Holovachov 2008</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="143" pageId="1" pageNumber="138" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">Length of male 10.4-11.3 mm (n = 3), female 10.8-11.9 mm (n = 3).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">Head (Fig. 1a), in dorsal view, well produced anteriorly, median length of crown approximately 7/10 interocular width and 4/10 transocular width; anterior margin broadly rounded; without carina at transition from crown to face; ocelli located on imaginary line between anterior eye angles, each approximately equidistant between adjacent eye angle and median line of crown; surface without sculpturing or setae; frontogenal sutures extending onto crown and attaining ocelli. Antennal ledges, in dorsal view, not protuberant; in lateral view, with anterior margins oblique and slightly concave. Frons swollen, muscle impressions distinct. Epistomal suture interrupted medially. Clypeus not produced; upper half continuing contour of frons, lower half more nearly horizontal; apex convex.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="138">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="138">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Kogigonalia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kogigonalia incarnata" order="Hemiptera" pageId="1" pageNumber="138" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incarnata">Kogigonalia incarnata</taxonomicName>
(Germar, 1821), comb. n. a crown, pronotum, and mesonotum, dorsal view. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="b–i">b-i</normalizedToken>
male terminalia: b pygofer, lateral view c valve and subgenital plates, ventral view d subgenital plate, lateral view e connective and styles, dorsal view f aedeagus, lateral view g aedeagus, ventral view h paraphyses, dorsal view i paraphyses, lateral view. APR = aedeagal ventral process; PEM = emargination of subgenital plate. Scale bars: a = 2 mm, b, h, i = 1 mm, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="c–g">c-g</normalizedToken>
= 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="139" pageId="1" pageNumber="138">
Thorax (Fig. 1a), in dorsal view, with pronotal width greater than transocular width; pronotum with lateral margins convergent anteriorly; posterior margin rectilinear or slightly concave; disk without sculpturing or setae; dorsopleural carinae declivous anteriorly, incomplete. Mesonotum with scutellum not transversely striate. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="139" start="start">Forewings</pageBreakToken>
coriaceous, venation (except on apical third) not very distinct; membrane well delimited, including first and second apical cells and distal portions of third and fourth apical cells; base of fourth apical cell located more proximally than base of third; with three closed anteapical cells, their bases located more proximally than apex of clavus. Hind wings with vein R2+3 incomplete. Hind legs with femoral setal formula 2:1:1; length of first tarsomere greater than combined length of second and third; with two parallel rows of small setae on plantar surface.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="140" pageId="2" pageNumber="139">
Color (Fig. 3
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
). Ground color of anterior dorsum (crown, pronotum, and mesonotum) yellow. Crown with dark brown to black median spear-shaped mark (size variable and may bear lateral extensions, sometimes covering much of coronal surface, with only lateroanterior portions remaining yellow); other variable minor dark brown to black 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="140" start="start">marks</pageBreakToken>
also present. Pronotum with conspicuous T-shaped dark brown to black mark, formed by median longitudinal stripe and posterior transverse stripe, anterior pronotal margin with transverse dark brown to black mark at base of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“T”">&quot;T&quot;</normalizedToken>
(pronotal marks varying from strong to faint or incomplete, sometimes covering much of pronotal surface, with only a pair of lateral areas remaining yellow); lateral portions of disk with variable brown or orange areas. Mesonotum with basal portion largely and variably dark brown to black; posterior portion of scutellum reddish-brown. Ground color of forewings reddish-brown; with or without three large orange or yellow areas, the first and largest on corium and clavus at basal third of wing, the second extending from costal area over clavus and forming transcommissural stripe, and the third extending from costal margin to outer margin of first apical cell (orange or yellow areas, when present, varying from distinct to faint); membrane brown. Face, thorax and legs, and venter of abdomen mostly yellow; frons with or without dark brown to black longitudinal stripe (continued from coronal spear-shaped mark); dorsum of abdomen red; male pygofer reddish.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="140">
Male genitalia with pygofer (Fig. 1b), in lateral view, strongly produced posteriorly; posterior margin narrowly rounded; without processes; macrosetae distributed mostly on posterior half and extending anteriorly along ventral margin. Valve (Fig. 1c), in ventral view, subrectangular. Subgenital plates (Fig. 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="c–d">c-d</normalizedToken>
) much shorter than pygofer; in ventral view, with basal half broad and apical half abruptly and strongly narrowed; transition from broad to narrow portion emarginated; basal half with uniseriate macrosetae; plate surface with scattered microsetae; plates separate from each other throughout their length. Styles (Fig. 1e), in dorsal view, with apophysis short, not extending as far posteriorly as apex of connective, narrowing gradually toward apex, without preapical lobe, with few preapical setae on outer margin. Connective (Fig. 1e), in dorsal view, a large trapezoidal plate; without median keel. Aedeagus (Fig. 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="f–g">f-g</normalizedToken>
) symmetrical; shaft, in ventral view, expanded apically; in lateral view, with strong, median ventral process on basal half; shaft apex with pair of membranous lobes; shaft surface with pair of areas covered by small spines, extending from median ventral process to lateroapical area, where spines are larger than more basal ones. Paraphyses (Fig. 1
<normalizedToken originalValue="h–i">h-i</normalizedToken>
), in dorsal view, with both stalk and rami elongate, the former articulated with connective, the latter with apical half curved dorsally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="143" pageId="3" pageNumber="140">
Females with abdominal sternite VII (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–b">a-b</normalizedToken>
), in ventral view, strongly produced posteriorly; posterior margin with elongate, median strong projection and pair of elongate, but shorter than median projection, lateral spiniform processes; median projection with slight preapical constriction; ventral surface of sternite VII with distinct median longitudinal carina. Internal sternite VIII, in dorsal view, without distinct median or lateral sclerites. First valvifers (Fig. 2d), in lateral view, with anterior and dorsal margins rounded, ventral margin emarginated, posterior margin truncate. Pygofer (Fig. 2c), in lateral view, strongly produced posteriorly; apex narrowly rounded; ventral margin slightly emarginated preapically; macrosetae distributed mostly on posterior portion and extending anteriorly along ventral margin. First valvulae, in ventral view, with basal portion expanded, without processes or projections; in lateral view (Fig. 2d), with apex acute; dorsal margin with approximately 10 preapical denticles (Fig. 2g); dorsal 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="141" start="start">sculptured</pageBreakToken>
area (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="e–f">e-f</normalizedToken>
) extended from basal portion to apex of blade, formed mostly by oblique linear processes; ventral sculptured area restricted to apical portion of blade, formed mostly by scale-like processes; ventral interlocking device (Fig. 2d) restricted to basal half of blade, its apical third curved dorsally. Second valvulae (Fig. 2h), in 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="142" start="start">lateral</pageBreakToken>
view, slightly expanded beyond basal curvature; basal hyaline area distinct; dorsal margin approximately rectilinear, with about 40 continuous teeth (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="i–k">i-k</normalizedToken>
) that are progressively smaller toward apex; most teeth subtriangular but posterior ones quadrate; 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="143" start="start">few</pageBreakToken>
irregular denticles on posterior portion of larger teeth and on ventroapical portion of blade; ventral blade margin convex; without preapical prominence; apex obtuse. Gonoplacs, in lateral view, with basal half narrow and apical half distinctly expanded; apex obtuse; blade with many minute spiniform processes and few macrosetae on apical portion and extending anteriorly along ventral margin.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="143">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="143">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Kogigonalia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kogigonalia incarnata" order="Hemiptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="143" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incarnata">Kogigonalia incarnata</taxonomicName>
(Germar, 1821), comb. n., female terminalia: a sternite VII, ventral view b sternite VII, lateral view c pygofer, lateral view d first valvifer and valvula, lateral view e dorsal sculptured area at basal portion f dorsal sculptured area at apical portion g apex h second valvula, lateral view i teeth at basal portion j teeth at median portion k teeth at apical portion. BHA = basal hyaline area; DEN = denticle; DSA = dorsal sculptured area; DUC = duct; LPR = lateral process of sternite VII; RAM = ramus; TOO = tooth; VID = ventral interlocking device; VLI = first valvifer. Scale bars: a, b, d, h = 2 mm, c = 1 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="143">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="143">
Figure 3. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–c">a-c</normalizedToken>
color variation in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Kogigonalia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kogigonalia incarnata" order="Hemiptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="143" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="incarnata">Kogigonalia incarnata</taxonomicName>
(Germar, 1821), comb. n., body, dorsal view: 
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–b">a-b</normalizedToken>
male and female syntypes, respectively, from the state of Bahia, northeastern Brazil (Museum 
<normalizedToken originalValue="für">fuer</normalizedToken>
Naturkunde, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Universität">Universitaet</normalizedToken>
Humboldt, Berlin) c female from Brazil 
<normalizedToken originalValue="d–f">d-f</normalizedToken>
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Kogigonalia" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Kogigonalia enola" order="Hemiptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="143" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="enola">Kogigonalia enola</taxonomicName>
Young, 1977, male holotype from French Guiana (United States National Museum, Washington, D.C.): d body, dorsal view e paraphyses, dorsal view f aedeagus, lateral view. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="a–d">a-d</normalizedToken>
reproduced, with permission, from 
<bibRefCitation author="Wilson, MR" journalOrPublisher="Annales de la Societe Entomologique de France" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" title="National Museum Wales" url="http://naturalhistory.museumwales.ac.uk/sharpshooters/home.php" year="2009">Wilson et al. (2009)</bibRefCitation>
<normalizedToken originalValue="e–f">e-f</normalizedToken>
redrawn from 
<bibRefCitation author="Young, DA" journalOrPublisher="Bulletin of North Carolina Agricultural Experiment Station" pageId="8" pageNumber="145" title="Taxonomic study of the Cicadellinae (Homoptera: Cicadellidae). Part 2. New World Cicadellini and the genus Cicadella." volume="239" year="1977">Young (1977)</bibRefCitation>
. Scale bars = 5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="143" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="143">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="143">
northeastern Brazil: state of Bahia: one female (MTD). southeastern Brazil: state of 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Espírito">Espirito</normalizedToken>
Santo: one male, Santa Teresa, 675 m, 1-2/IV/1969, Exp. Dep. Zool. col. (DZUP); Baixo Guandu, 17/IX/1966, C. Elias col. (DZUP); state of Rio de Janeiro: two males and one female, Casimiro de Abreu, Reserva 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Biológica">Biologica</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="União">Uniao</normalizedToken>
, 28-31/I/2013 (one male), 12/XII/2013-27/I/2014 (one male, one female), Lab. 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" order="Diptera" pageId="6" pageNumber="143" rank="order">Diptera</taxonomicName>
MN[RJ] col., Malaise trap (MNRJ); one male, Silva Jardim, III/1974, F. M. Oliveira col. (DZUP); one male, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Magé">Mage</normalizedToken>
, 3/III/1978, J. L. Nessimian col. (DZRJ). Brazil: one female, D. Swainson col. (DZUP); one specimen without abdomen (MTD).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>