<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4846" ID-GBIF-Dataset="afdfe364-6a28-40a5-bb64-4099233a98bd" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043507" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-294-75" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2247D429-CEB0-4BA8-BD51-D9FF89F995FD" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2013" ModsDocID="1313-2970-294-75" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 294" ModsDocTitle="Description and scanning electron microscopic observation of a new species of the genus Polycopetta (Crustacea, Ostracoda, Cladocopina) from an interstitial habitat in Japan" checkinTime="1451247356531" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Tanaka, Hayato &amp; Tsukagoshi, Akira" docDate="2013" docId="ADD61789A33C4519BD06EC256752ED5F" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 294: 75-91" docOrigin="ZooKeys 294" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4846" docTitle="Polycopetta quadrispinata Tanaka &amp; Tsukagoshi, 2013, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="2247D429-CEB0-4BA8-BD51-D9FF89F995FD" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="84" masterDocId="B728FFBDD240E41DFFE0FF99FF9BFFDE" masterDocTitle="Description and scanning electron microscopic observation of a new species of the genus Polycopetta (Crustacea, Ostracoda, Cladocopina) from an interstitial habitat in Japan" masterLastPageNumber="91" masterPageNumber="75" pageId="1" pageNumber="76" updateTime="1643692546905" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Description and scanning electron microscopic observation of a new species of the genus Polycopetta (Crustacea, Ostracoda, Cladocopina) from an interstitial habitat in Japan</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tanaka, Hayato</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tsukagoshi, Akira</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>294</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>75</mods:start>
<mods:end>91</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4846</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.294.4846</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-294-75</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">56902C37-22F2-4B8B-A96B-7FCE840582E0</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152043507" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2247D429-CEB0-4BA8-BD51-D9FF89F995FD" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/ADD61789A33C4519BD06EC256752ED5F" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="1" pageNumber="76">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="76" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="76">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2247D429-CEB0-4BA8-BD51-D9FF89F995FD" class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="1" pageNumber="76" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="1" pageNumber="76">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 213
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="76" type="type series">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="76">Type series.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="76">
Holotype: adult male (SUM-CO-2093), right valve length 357 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, height 301 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, left valve length 358 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, height 288 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
, soft parts mounted on a slide and valves preserved in a cardboard cell slide, Paratypes: 10 adult males (SUM-CO-2094-2103) and 11 adult females (SUM-CO-2104-2114). All specimens were collected on 24 June 2009.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="76" type="type locality">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="76">Type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="76">
The holotype specimen was collected from Mihomasaki beach, Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture, along the Pacific coast of central Japan, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="15" value="35.02028">35°01'13&quot;N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="15" value="138.52222">138°31'20&quot;E</geoCoordinate>
(Fig. 1B); in an interstitial environment at 40 cm below the shoreline sand surface. The substrate consisted mainly of clastic very coarse sand (median grain size is about 1.5 mm).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="1" pageNumber="76" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="76">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="77" pageId="1" pageNumber="76">
Carapace oval and anteriorly concave in lateral view. Carapace peripheral surface covered with shallow pits, except on posterodorsal area, and with scale-like sculptures in anterior area. Anterior end of both valves with one conspicuous spine. Posteroventral margin of right valve with four conspicuous spines in both sexes. In each valve, 73 simple pores, 23 pore systems involving a circular depression and two 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="77" start="start">contiguous</pageBreakToken>
pore systems. Male second podomere of the antennula with one ventral seta, third podomere with one ventral seta with serrated tip. Spermatozoa length approximately 750 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="2" pageNumber="77" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="77">Description of adult male.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="78" pageId="2" pageNumber="77">
Carapace (Figs 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–E">A-E</normalizedToken>
, 3-6). Carapace oval and anteriorly concave in lateral view. Yellowish white colour in living individuals. Carapace periphery surface covered with shallow pits except on posterodorsal area, and with scale-like sculptures on anterior area (Figs 2A, B, 3, 4). Anterior end of both valves with one conspicuous spine (Figs 2A, B, 3, 4). Mid-anterior to posteroventral margin covered with serration and fringe (Figs 2A, B, 3). Posteroventral margin of right valve with four conspicuous spines and fringe (Fig. 5A, B) and of left valve with fine serrations (Figs 2B, 3B). In each valve, 73 simple pores (Figs 4, 5C, D), 23 pore systems 
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="78" start="start">involving</pageBreakToken>
a circular depression with bifurcated seta (Figs 4, 5C) and two contiguous double pore systems with bifurcated seta (Figs 4, 5D). Adductor muscle scar consisting of three closely spaced scars (Fig. 5E). Marginal infold of each valve developed along anterior to posteroventral margins (Figs 2C, D, 6B, C, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="J–L">J-L</normalizedToken>
). Along hinge margin of right valve: anterodorsal bar and groove (Fig. 6A), anterior socket (Fig. 6E), median bar (Fig. 6F), posterior socket (Fig. 6G), and posteroventral groove (Fig. 6D, H). Along hinge margin of left valve: anterodorsal bar (Fig. 6I), anterior knob (Fig. 6M), median bar (Fig. 6N), posterior knob (Fig. 6O), and posterior bar (Fig. 6P).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="78">Frontal organ (Figs 7A, 8B). Spinous seta divided at mid-length. Distal half with long and proximal half with short setae, respectively (Fig. 8B).</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="79" pageId="3" pageNumber="78">
Antennula (Figs 7B, 8C). Uniramous, four articulated podomeres. First podomere rectangular in shape and tapering distally, with setulae on dorsal margin, lateral surface and at ventrodistal end, respectively. Second podomere about four-fifths as long as first podomere, with one annulated setulous seta at dorsoproximal end, one simple seta on ventrodistal end (Figs 7B, 8C), and setulae on dorsal margin, lateral surface, ventral middle margin and at ventrodistal end, respectively. Third podomere about one-fifth as long as first podomere, with one short simple seta at dorsodistal end and one seta 
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="79" start="start">with</pageBreakToken>
serrations at ventrodistal end (Figs 7B, 8C). Fourth podomere small, with four long setulous annulated setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="80" pageId="4" pageNumber="79">
Antenna (Figs 7D, D', 8D). Typically biramous, with exopodite and endopodite consisting of nine and three podomeres, respectively. Basis triangular and tapering distally. Exopodite: first podomere about 
<normalizedToken originalValue="one–third">one-third</normalizedToken>
as long as basis; podomere lengths decreasing in size from second to eighth, each podomere with one long plumose annulated seta, respectively; ninth (distal-most) podomere very small, with one long annulated, one medium annulated and one short bare setae at distal end. Endopodite (Figs 7D, D', 8D): first podomere about two-thirds as long as first podomere of exopodite; second podomere half as long as first podomere, with one setulous seta along dorsal 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="80" start="start">margin</pageBreakToken>
, one clavate process at proximal middle end (Fig. 7D') and five setae at distal end consisting of three long annulated, one medium annulated and one short annulated setulous. Third podomere one-fifth as long as first podomere, with one dorsal outgrowth (Figs 7D', 8D), and two long spinous annulated, one long annulated and one short setulous annulated setae at distal end.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="80">Upper lip (Fig. 10A). Semicircular in lateral view, with fine setae on surface (Fig. 13A).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="80">Mandibula (Fig. 10B). Coxal endite with four teeth. Basis with four plumose annulated setae on ventral margin, and one plumose annulated seta at mid-lateral surface. Exopodite pear-shaped, distal end jagged, with thin setae, and one simple seta. Endopodite consisting of two podomeres. First podomere with three annulated plumose setae on ventral margin and two annulated long setulous setae at dorsodistal end. Second podomere very small, bearing two plumose setae at distal end.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="81" pageId="5" pageNumber="80">
Maxillula (Fig. 10C, C', C&quot;). Precoxa (Fig. 10C') with seven annulated plumose setae and one stout setulous seta on ventral side. Coxa (Fig. 10C&quot;) with two short and two medium plumose setae on lateral surface near ventroproximal margin, two short and two medium plumose setae on lateral surface of ventral middle margin. Basis rectangular, dorsally-convex in lateral view, with one medium and one long 
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="81" start="start">plumose</pageBreakToken>
setae on ventral margin, and setulae along ventral margin. First podomere of endopodite with one long plumose seta at ventrodistal end. Second podomere three-fourths as long as first podomere, with two long and one medium annulated setulous setae on ventrodistal area, one short annulated and one medium setulous annulated seta at dorsodistal end. Third podomere small, with 4 long annulated setulous setae. Exopodite with four tufts along dorsal margin, and nine annulated setae at distal end.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="81">Fifth limb (Figs 10D, 11). Coxa bearing branchial plate (epipodite) with 15 long plumose setae, and four short setulous setae on dorsolateral area. Basis with three setulous and three plumose setae on dorsal and ventral margin, respectively. Endopodite consisting of two podomeres (Fig. 11). First podomere with one plumose seta. Second podomere rectangle, with one plumose seta. Exopodite with four setulous setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="82">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="82" start="start">Furca</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 12A, 13B). Furcal claws six and seven on left and right lamella, respectively, with row of setae on dorsal side.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="83" pageId="7" pageNumber="82">
Male copulatory organ and posterior body (Figs 12A, 13
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
). Arising from outer surface of body on left side of terminal trunk segment as long curved copulatory duct. 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="83" start="start">Tuft</pageBreakToken>
of stout setae at ventral right side (Fig. 12A, 13C). Posterior body including a lot of very long spermatozoa, approximately 750 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
long (Fig. 12A, 13D).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="83" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">Description of adult female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">Mandibula, maxillula, fifth limbs, and upper lip similar to those of adult male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">
Carapace (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="F–J">F-J</normalizedToken>
). Carapace length and height larger than adult males.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">Antennula (Fig. 7C). Uniramus, four articulated podomeres. First podomere similar to that of adult male. Second podomere about four-fifths as long as first podomere, with one annulated setulous seta at dorsoproximal end, and setulae on dorsal margin, lateral surface, ventral middle margin and at ventrodistal end, respectively. Third podomere about one-fifth as long as first podomere, with one short simple seta at dorsodistal end. Fourth podomere small, with five long setulous annulated setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">Antenna (Fig. 7E). Only second and third podomeres of endopodite different from those of adult male. Endopodite consisting of three podomeres. Second podomere half as long as first podomere, with one setulous seta along dorsal margin and five annulated setae at distal end. Third podomere one-fifth as long as first podomere with four annulated setae at distal end.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">Furca (Fig. 12B). Each lamella with seven claws.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="84" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" type="dimensions">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">Dimensions.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">See Table 1.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="83">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">
Table 1. Dimensions of valves of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. from type locality.&lt;br/&gt;
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="83">
<table pageId="8" pageNumber="83">
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="83">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">Length (μm)</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">Height (μm)</td>
</tr>
<tr pageId="8" pageNumber="83">
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">Mean</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">Observed range</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">N</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">Mean</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">Observed range</td>
<td colspan="1" pageId="8" pageNumber="83" rowspan="1">N</td>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<pageBreakToken pageId="9" pageNumber="84" start="start">Figure</pageBreakToken>
2. SEM images of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. valves. A and B male paratype (SUM-CO-2095) C and D male, paratype (SUM-CO-2096) E male, paratype (SUM-CO-2097) F female, paratype (SUM-CO-2105) G female paratype (SUM-CO-2106) H and I female, paratype (SUM-CO-2107) J female, paratype (SUM-CO-2108). A right external lateral view B left external lateral view C right internal lateral view D left internal lateral view E dorsal view F right external lateral view G left external lateral view H right internal lateral view I left internal lateral J dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 3. Valves of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093). A right internal view B left internal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 4. Distribution of pore systems and surface ornamentation of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. drawn from an SEM image. Male, paratype (SUM-CO-2095). A right external view B left external view. Solid circle, open circle and double circle indicate the positions of simple pores, pore systems involving a circular depression and contiguous pore systems, respectively.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 5. SEM images of the detailed structure of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. valves. A male, paratype (SUM-CO-2095) 
<normalizedToken originalValue="B–D">B-D</normalizedToken>
male, paratype (SUM-CO-2098) E male, paratype (SUM-CO-2094). A four spines at posteroventral margin of right valve B spines and fringe at posteroventral margin of right valve C pore system with circular depression D contiguous pore system E internal lateral view of adductor muscle scars of right valve. Arrowheads indicate simple pores.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 6. SEM images of internal view of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. valves. Male, paratype (SUM-CO-2096). 
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–H">A-H</normalizedToken>
right valve 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–P">I-P</normalizedToken>
left valve A anterodorsal bar and groove B anterior area of marginal infold C anteroventral area of marginal infold D posteroventral area of marginal infold E anterior socket of hinge structure F median bar of hinge structure G posterior socket of hinge structure H posteroventral groove I anterodorsal bar J anterior area of marginal infold K anteroventral area of marginal infold L posteroventral area of marginal infold M anterior knob of hinge structure N median bar of hinge structure O posterior knob of hinge structure P posterior bar. Scale bars indicate 20 
<normalizedToken originalValue="μm">μm</normalizedToken>
.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A, B and D male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093) C and E female, paratype (SUM-CO-2104). A frontal organ B male antennula C female antennula D male antenna D′ endopodite of male antenna without all setae E female antenna except the exopodite. Abbreviations: ba basis en endopodite ex exopodite.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 8. SEM images of male soft parts of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A left lateral view of whole body with left valve removed B left lateral view of frontal organ C right lateral view of distal area of antennula D left lateral view of antennal endopodite. Arrow indicates a seta with serrations at ventrodistal end. Arrowhead indicates a dorsal outgrowth of male antennal endopodite. Abbreviations: 1an antennula 2an antenna en endopodite fif fifth limb fo frontal organ lf left furcal lamella md mandibula mx maxillula.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 9. Light micrograph of male antennula of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. Arrow indicates seta with serrations at ventrodistal end.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 10. 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A and D male, paratype (SUM-CO-2094) B and C male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093). A right lateral view of upper lip B mandibula C maxillula C′precoxa of maxillula except setulae on setae C&quot; coxa of maxillula except setulae on setae D fifth limb. Arrowheads indicate tip of precoxal setae of maxillula. Abbreviations: ba basis cx coxa en endopodite ex exopodite pcx precoxa.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 11. SEM images of male fifth limb of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A left lateral view B enlarged view of figure 11A. Abbreviations: ba basis cx coxa en endopodite ex exopodite epi epipodite.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 12. Posterior body of 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. A male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093) B female, paratype (SUM-CO-2106). Arrowhead indicates the tuft of stout setae. Abbreviations: cd copulatory duct spe spermatozoa.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">
Figure 13. 
<taxonomicName class="Ostracoda" family="Polycopidae" genus="Polycopetta" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Polycopetta quadrispinata" order="Halocyprida" pageId="9" pageNumber="84" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="quadrispinata">Polycopetta quadrispinata</taxonomicName>
sp. n. SEM images of male soft parts of. A right lateral view of upper lip B left lateral view of posterior body, furcal lamellae and copulatory organ C right lateral view of the tuft of stout setae D fascicle of spermatozoa. Arrowhead indicates the tuft of stout setae. Abbreviations: cd copulatory duct lf left furcal lamella spe spermatozoa ul upper lip.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="84" type="occurrence">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">Occurrence.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">So far known only from type locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="84">Etymology. Specific name quadrispinata, an adjective derived from the Latin prefix quadri- (four) and Latin adjective spinatus (spiny), referring to the four spines on the posteroventral margin of the right valve in both sexes.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>