<document ENCODING="UTF8" ModsDocAuthor=" &amp; Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." ModsDocDate="1938" ModsDocID="5782" ModsDocOrigin="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5782/5782.pdf" ModsDocTitle="Five new species of ant, chiefly from New Guinea." checkinTime="1264825813356" checkinUser="claudia" docAuthor="Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K." docDate="1938" docId="A126EE5B7AEC4947A65DCD38176E169C" docLanguage="en" docName="5782_tx1.xml" docOrigin="Annals and Magazine of Natural History 1" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5782/5782.pdf" docTitle="Acanthoponera plaumanni Donisthorpe, 1938, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="141" masterDocId="1C9D5B545D3E88DF274EC2424FEF6CF6" masterDocTitle="Five new species of ant, chiefly from New Guinea." masterLastPageNumber="148" masterPageNumber="140" pageNumber="140" updateTime="1553872466124" updateUser="GgEditorBatch">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Five new species of ant, chiefly from New Guinea.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Donisthorpe, H. S. J. K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1938</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>140</mods:start>
<mods:end>148</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/5782/5782.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">5782</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A126EE5B7AEC4947A65DCD38176E169C" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A126EE5B7AEC4947A65DCD38176E169C">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="140">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:132378" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Acanthoponera" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName-HNS="Acanthoponera plaumanni Donisthorpe" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="140" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="plaumanni">Acanthoponera plaumanni</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="140">[worker]. Reddish yellow, legs and scapes lighter, eyes, masticatory border and teeth of mandibles black; whole body shining, and furnished with longer and shorter erect yellow hairs; gaster clothed with rather long decumbent pubescence.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageNumber="141" pageNumber="140">
Head subquadrate, posterior border considerably emarginate, posterior angles thick with a blunt projection on each side; sides of head to base of mandibles almost parallel. The sculpture consists of longitudinal raised ridges enclosing a network of large, shallow, shining pits. Mandibles large, with scattered shallow punctures, furnished with 8 or 9 rather small blunt teeth, except the two last apical ones which are longer, the one at apex being the longer and bluntly pointed; clypeus convex and evenly arched, anterior border slightly emarginate in centre; frontal area indistinct; frontal carinae slightly emarginate behind insertion of antennae and then continued 
<pageStartToken pageNumber="141">in</pageStartToken>
a thin ridge to base of head, forming the upper side of a long, shallow, shining scrobe to receive the whole of the scape; antennae moderate; scape not reaching posterior border of head by 1/3 of its length; funiculus with joints gradually increasing in length and breadth, forming a more or less 5-jointed club. Thorax narrowed to base; the sculpture on the dorsal surface and also on the sides of the pronotum is similar to that of the head, but the episternite and sternite of the mesothorax are smooth and shining with a few scattered shallow punctures; pronotum convex, broadest at anterior angles, which are rounded, and with a narrow neck in front for the reception of the head; mesonotum small, transverse, only slightly convex; pro-mesonotal suture semicircular, well marked; m,eso-epinotal suture only indicated by a furrow; epinotum with dorsal surface long, rather flat, furnished at base with two long, strong, projecting spines, which curve gradually, and very slightly inwards at apex; declivity abrupt, concave, smooth, shorter than the dorsal surface. Petiole armed above with a long sharp spine curving downwards, and beneath with a rounded projection ending posteriorly with a sharp tooth pointing backwards. The sculpture of the petiole is somewhat similar to that of head and thorax, only the apex of the spine and the projection beneath are very smooth and shining. Gaster covered with very small fine punctures, strangulation between post-petiole and rest of gaster considerable.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="141">Long. 8.3 mm.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="141">Described from a worker taken by Fritz Plaumann in Brazil, Nove Teutonia, lat. 27° 11' 8&quot; S., long. 52° 23' W., September 1935.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="141">I have looked up the descriptions of all the known species to date. This very fine insect is much larger than any of the others.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="distribution">
<paragraph pageNumber="141">The distribution of the genus is peculiar; it is found in Central and South America, Chili, East Australia, and New Zealand.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>