<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5631959" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d99f9bf3-131d-45af-886d-f55f1d82163a" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127663350" ID-ISSN="1175-5326" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5631959" ID-ZooBank="7C45A9A7-BFB2-4FF0-A5FA-CF461BABF5FE" checkinTime="1460578957140" checkinUser="plazi" docAuthor="Ewart, A. &amp; Popple, L. W." docDate="2013" docId="C84187D1810AFFBC5285947ED643FE89" docLanguage="en" docName="zt03620p042.pdf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 3620 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStylede.uka.ipd.idaho.easyIO.settings.Settings@4300e240" docStyleName="zootaxa.2013.journal_article" docTitle="Cicadettini" docType="treatment" docVersion="6" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="4" masterDocId="3478FFA98109FFB852129519D421FF95" masterDocTitle="New species of Drymopsalta Heath Cicadas (Cicadidae: Cicadettinae: Cicadettini) from Queensland and Northern Territory, Australia, with overview of genus" masterLastPageNumber="42" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" updateTime="1635667513264" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New species of Drymopsalta Heath Cicadas (Cicadidae: Cicadettinae: Cicadettini) from Queensland and Northern Territory, Australia, with overview of genus</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ewart, A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Popple, L. W.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2013</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>3620</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>42</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3620.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="GBIF-Dataset">d99f9bf3-131d-45af-886d-f55f1d82163a</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175-5326</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">283377</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">7C45A9A7-BFB2-4FF0-A5FA-CF461BABF5FE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5631959" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127663350" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5631959" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:C84187D1810AFFBC5285947ED643FE89" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C84187D1810AFFBC5285947ED643FE89" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="4" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<subSubSection box="[151,550,359,385]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,550,359,385]" box="[151,550,359,385]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,550,359,385]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,550,359,385]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Tribe 
<taxonomicName box="[226,364,359,385]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="tribe" tribe="Cicadettini">Cicadettini</taxonomicName>
Buckton, 
<number box="[492,550,359,385]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="1889.0">1889</number>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,430,2005]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,459,430,455]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Diagnosis of 
<taxonomicName box="[312,459,430,455]" class="Insecta" family="Cicadidae" genus="Drymopsalta" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hemiptera" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[312,459,430,455]" italics="true" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Drymopsalta</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
</emphasis>
(slightly extended after Moulds, 
<number box="[854,915,430,454]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2012.0">2012</number>
): Small cicadas, body length male &lt;
<quantity box="[1346,1432,430,454]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.2" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" unit="mm" value="12.0">12 mm</quantity>
, female &lt;
<quantity box="[250,331,466,490]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" unit="mm" value="15.0">15 mm</quantity>
; width of head, including compound eyes, wider than pronotum across lateral margins, and as wide as pronotal collar across lateral angles; width of pronotum across lateral margins as wide as abdomen across auditory capsules, and slightly wider than mesonotum between fore wings; pronotum in dorsal view parallel-sided. Metanotum visible at dorsal midline. Male abdomen slender and evenly tapered distally in dorsal and lateral views, widest across auditory capsules; epipleurites reflexed to ventral surface; tergite 
<number box="[1076,1090,610,634]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="1.0">1</number>
narrow along dorsal midline; sternites rounded and usually not all visible in lateral view, especially sternites VI and VII; abdominal venter with a darker medial fascia; sternite II with a black medial depression, the black extending slightly beyond the depression. Compound eyes clearly separated from pronotum along their outer ventral margins; distance between lateral ocelli approximately equal to distance between lateral ocellus and compound eyes; ventral margins of pronotum without lateral tooth; rostrum extending to posterior margins of mid coxae; cruciform elevation wider than long.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,430,2005]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Fore wing hyaline and relatively narrow with length/width ratios of 
<number box="[990,1078,826,850]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="3.05" valueMax="3.5" valueMin="2.6">2.6–3.5</number>
; fore wing slightly longer than body; pterostigma reddish-brown and relatively prominent; costal vein with marked anterior curvature between proximal join with thorax and node; relatively equal in width with minor but distinct thickening proximally to and adjacent to node; costal vein exhibits a very narrow sclerotised area along anterior margin, much thinner than costal vein thickness; costal and R+Sc veins fused, but clearly visible, with costal vein higher than R+Sc; forewings with 
<number box="[151,165,1006,1030]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="8.0">8</number>
apical cells of similar length to ulnar cells (some shorter and longer); subapical cells absent; ulnar cell 
<number box="[1313,1327,1006,1030]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="3.0">3</number>
angled to radial cell; basal cell relatively long and narrow; CuA and M veins fused before reaching basal cell so that length of the proximal section (vein M+CuA) of inner margin of radial cell is similar to, or slightly shorter than length of second section (vein M); the three distal vein sections of M that form the remaining inner margin of radial cell are unequal in length, but not strongly different; medial and cubital cell of similar size; radial cell typically shorter than distance from its apex to wing tip; veins CuP and 
<number box="[758,768,1186,1210]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="1.0">1</number>
A fused in part; distance between cross veins r and r-m approximately equal to, or slightly greater than distance between r-m and m; wing margin relatively evenly developed for its whole length; infuscation absent; cubital and medial cells of roughly similar size; basal membrane off-white to brownish, opaque.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,430,2005]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
<collectingCountry box="[201,257,1330,1354]" name="India" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Hind</collectingCountry>
wings hyaline with 
<number box="[497,511,1330,1354]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="5.0">5</number>
or 
<number box="[556,570,1330,1354]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="6.0">6</number>
apical cells; weak brown infuscation within anal cell 
<number box="[1203,1219,1330,1354]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="3.0">3</number>
; no infuscation on ambient vein; anal lobes broader than cubital cell 
<number box="[708,723,1369,1393]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="1.0">1</number>
; width of 
<number box="[837,851,1369,1393]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="1.0">1</number>
st cubital cell at distal end more than twice that of 
<number box="[1406,1420,1369,1393]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2.0">2</number>
nd cubital cell; anal lobe moderately broad with vein 
<number box="[726,738,1405,1429]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="3.0">3</number>
A curved, separate from wing margin; veins 
<collectingCountry box="[1250,1284,1406,1429]" name="Poland" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">RP</collectingCountry>
and M fused basally. Fore femora with 
<number box="[473,487,1441,1465]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="3.0">3</number>
prominent erect spines. Opercula broadly rhombohedral in shape, and usually somewhat acutely rounded distally (between medial and distal margins); distal and medial margins relatively straight, in some with weak convex curvature; meracanthus spike well developed; opercula developed asymmetrically around meracanthus; not completely reaching margin of tympanal cavity, but directed towards distomedial margin of cavity; male opercula with well separated inner margins; broad elongated dome extending from near distal margin into basal area.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,430,2005]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">
Timbals with 
<number box="[360,374,1657,1681]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="4.0">4</number>
long ribs; rib 
<number box="[542,556,1657,1681]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="4.0">4</number>
shorter than ribs 
<number box="[761,831,1657,1681]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2.0" valueMax="3.0" valueMin="1.0">1 to 3</number>
; ribs 
<number box="[898,966,1657,1681]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="2.0" valueMax="3.0" valueMin="1.0">1 to 3</number>
fused ventrally, but all 
<number box="[1242,1256,1657,1681]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="4.0">4</number>
long ribs fused dorsally with well developed basal spur; 
<specimenCount box="[609,748,1693,1717]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" type="intercalary">
<number box="[609,623,1693,1717]" pageId="3" pageNumber="4" value="3.0">3</number>
intercalary
</specimenCount>
ribs short and generally thin; dome on timbal plate elongated with parallel shallow grooves and ridges running across dome; basal dome prominent; anterior part of timbals mostly occupied by ribs.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[151,1437,430,2005]" lastBlockId="4.[151,1436,151,284]" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="5" pageId="3" pageNumber="4">Pygofer in ventral view widest across upper lobes, with weak tapering towards base; broadly sub-rectangular in ventral view; upper lobes flat, moderately developed, set well away from dorsal beak, subacutely rounded in lateral view; basal lobes undivided, broadly rounded and slightly obscured behind pygofer margin in lateral view, but clearly visible in dorsal view; dorsal beak conspicuous, extended, and acutely terminated as an apical spine, part of chitinized pygofer; median uncal lobe small, broadly duck-bill shaped; claspers prominent, narrow and erect, extended outside pygofer in lateral view, thickened and rounded apically, the outer face with an overhanging lip, restraining aedeagus; distally the claspers are approximately parallel to each other; aedeagus trifid with dorsal pseudoparameres which may be longer or shorter than endotheca, unfused, in dorsal view gently diverging, sclerotised ventral support; basal plate undulated in lateral view, broadly Y-shaped, apically broadened with ‘ears’, and with functional membraneous hinge.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>