<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7129" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ae62e183-b56a-4afe-8dad-70dd5160c3b3" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902092" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-1324-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1860-1324-1" ModsDocOrigin="Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift 61 (1)" ModsDocTitle="A new species of Sinophasma Günther, 1940 from Guangxi, China (Phasmida: Diapheromeridae: Necrosciinae)" checkinTime="1418151787395" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="George, Ho Wai-chun" docDate="2014" docId="9FC4F4E5EE0C9286330C8142D44E42DE" docLanguage="en" docName="DeutEntomolZeit 61(1): 23-25" docOrigin="Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift 61 (1)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7129" docTitle="Sinophasma damingshanensis Ho, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="23" masterDocId="4E38DA1EFF9EFFD6C939FFDB9725EA67" masterDocTitle="A new species of Sinophasma Guenther, 1940 from Guangxi, China (Phasmida: Diapheromeridae: Necrosciinae)" masterLastPageNumber="25" masterPageNumber="23" pageId="0" pageNumber="23" updateTime="1643521505838" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of Sinophasma Guenther, 1940 from Guangxi, China (Phasmida: Diapheromeridae: Necrosciinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>George, Ho Wai-chun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>61</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>23</mods:start>
<mods:end>25</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7129</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7129</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-1324-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127902092" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:9FC4F4E5EE0C9286330C8142D44E42DE" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9FC4F4E5EE0C9286330C8142D44E42DE" lastPageNumber="23" pageId="0" pageNumber="23">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="23" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/1083CC13-A904-4D1F-81F2-BC6AE050F016" authority="Ho" class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Sinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinophasma damingshanensis" order="Phasmida" pageId="0" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="damingshanensis">Sinophasma damingshanensis Ho</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="23">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1-6
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="23" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Description:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Male. Medium-sized. General colour of body, wings and legs green. Body slender and slim.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Head green, with six blackish longitudinal stripes reaching hind margin of head. Smooth, lacking granulation. Oval, longer and broader than pronotum, slightly constricted behind eyes posteriorly. Vertex flat, with an oval and shallow depression between bases of antennae. Occiput convex, with distinct median furrow, lateral furrows indistinct. Compound eyes light brown, rounded and prominent, about 1.5 times length of genae. Antennae dark brown, densely covered with setae; filiform, longer than forelegs; first segment flattened at base, rectangular, parallel-sided, about 1.5 times length of second segment, shorter than third segment; second and third segments cylindrical.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Pronotum rectangular, transverse and longitudinal sulci crossing before middle, anterior margin curved inward, hind margin slightly rounded. Mesonotum densely granulated, elongate, more than 4 times length of pronotum, slightly parallel-sided, median line distinct, with a long carina along lateral margins. Mesopleura and mesosternum with inconspicuous and dense granules. Metapleura and metasternum smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Abdomen dorsally green with brownish markings, ventral surface yellowish green. Smooth. Cylindrical and slender. Second to six terga parallel-sided, roughly equal in length. Seventh tergum gently expanded posteriorly. Eighth tergum trapezoid, gradually expanded posteriorly. Ninth tergum elongate and swollen, the longest, distinctly constricted medially, hind margin deeply emarginated; posterolateral angles elongate distinctly, apices obtuse; lateral margins raised. Anal segment rectangular, with a small horn medially; with ninth tergum vertically, longer than eighth tergum, reaching hind margin of anal segment; hind margin with four small emarginations, lateral angles elongate tuberculately. Poculum cup-shaped, hind margin rounded and broad. Cerci long and straight, cylindrical, apices rounded, not surpassing end of anal segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Tegmina brownish black, elevated angle blunt, with a yellow longitudinal stripe being laterad of elevation; oval, slightly as long as head, subtruncate posteriorly. Alae green, with dark brown longitudinal band, anal region dull rose; long, reaching posterior region of sixth tergum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Legs slender and long. Unarmed, covered with dense and short bristles. Coxae rufous brown. Femora and tibiae green, black apically. Tarsi orange brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Female. Similar to male, but distinctly larger and robust. General colour of body, wings and legs green. Body slender and cylindrical.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Head greenish brown to light brown, occiput with six black longitudinal bands segregated by light brown longitudinal stripes. Smooth. Oval, distinctly longer than wide. Vertex flat, with a small oval depression between bases of antennae, its diameter as long as second antennal segment. Occiput distinctly convex, with median and lateral furrows. Compound eyes light brown, oval, about 2.5 times length of genae. Antennae dark brown, filiform, longer than forelegs; first segment slightly flattened at base, about 1.8 times length of second segment, as long as third segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Pronotum green, shorter than head, gently expanded posteriorly, with transverse and longitudinal sulci crossing before middle, anterior margin curved inward, hind margin truncate. Mesonotum green, densely covered with yellow and small granules; about 4 times length of pronotum, median line indistinct. Mesopleura, mesosternum, metapleura and metasternum densely granulated as in mesonotum. Metanotum smooth, longer than median segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Abdomen dorsally and ventrally yellowish green. Smooth. Cylindrical, tapering posteriorly. Second to six terga roughly equal in length. Eighth tergum dilated into a slight and rounded lobe posterolaterally. Seventh sternum lacking preopercular organ. Anal segment slightly longer than ninth tergum, with small U-shaped notch on hind margin, lateral angles rounded. Supra-anal plate very small, hind margin rounded, exceeding hind margin of anal segment. Subgenital plate scoop-shaped, distinctly decurved in second half, strongly carinate laterally, apex pointed. Gonapophyses exposed, apex obtuse, reaching middle of ninth tergum. Cerci light brown, straight and cylindrical, apices pointed, surpassing hind margin of anal segment.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Tegmina brownish black, with light brown veins, elevated angle blunt, with a pale white longitudinal stripe being laterad of elevation; oval, longer than head, hind margin truncate. Alae green with dark brown longitudinal band, anal region dull rose; long, reaching middle of fifth tergum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Legs slender and long. Unarmed. Coxae buff brown. Profemora and protibiae rufous green. Mesofemora, mesotibiae, metafemora and metatibiae green. Apices of femora and tibiae black. Tarsi rufous brown.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Measurements. Length (mm): Holotype: ♂, body length 52.0, antennae 41.0, head 3.0, pronotum 2.0, mesonotum 9.5, metanotum including median segment 7.5, profemora 14.0, mesofemora 10.0, metafemora 15.0, protibiae 12.0, mesotibiae 9.0, metatibiae 14.0. Paratypes: ♂, body length 51.0-52.0, antennae 34.0-36.0, head 3.0-3.5, pronotum 2.0-2.2, mesonotum 9.5, metanotum including median segment 7.0, profemora 12.5-13.0, mesofemora 9.0-10.0, metafemora 14.0, protibiae 11.0-12.0, mesotibiae 9.0, metatibiae 13.0-14.0, tegmina 2.5-3.0, alae 22.0-25.0. Paratypes: ♀, body length 59.0-73.0, antennae 29.0-43.0, head 4.0-5.0, pronotum 2.5-3.0, mesonotum 11.5-14.0, metanotum including median segment 7.0, profemora 11.0-15.0, mesofemora 8.0-10.0, metafemora 12.0-15.0, protibiae 9.0-14.0, mesotibiae 7.0-9.0, metatibiae 10.0-14.0, tegmina 3.5-4.5, alae 25.0-28.0.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="23">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">
Figures 1-2. Habitus images of 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Sinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinophasma damingshanensis" order="Phasmida" pageId="0" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="damingshanensis">Sinophasma damingshanensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 1. Male, lateral view; 2. Female, lateral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="0" pageNumber="23">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">
Figures 3-6. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Sinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinophasma damingshanensis" order="Phasmida" pageId="0" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="damingshanensis">Sinophasma damingshanensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. from Guangxi, China. 3. Male, terminal end of abdomen, lateral view; 4. Male, terminal end of abdomen, dorsal view; 5. Female, terminal end of abdomen, lateral view; 6. Female, terminal end of abdomen, dorsal view. [scale bar = 5 mm]
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="23" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Type material:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">China: holotype: ♂, Damingshan, Wuming, Guangxi, 28-31.VII.2012, Ho Wai-Chun George (HKES). Paratypes: 12♂, 8♀, Damingshan, Wuming, Guangxi, China, 28-31.VII.2012, Ho Wai-Chun George (HKES).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="23" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Etymology:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">This species is named after the type-locality, Damingshan.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="23" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Distribution:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Guangxi, China.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="23" type="notes">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Notes:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">This species is found in evergreen broadleaf forests.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="23" type="differentiation">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">Differentiation:</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="23">
Small 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Sinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinophasma" order="Phasmida" pageId="0" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Sinophasma</taxonomicName>
species. This new species is separated from most species in the genus by its rectangular anal segment with a small horn medially in male and seventh sternum lacking preopercular organ in female. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Sinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinophasma damingshanensis" order="Phasmida" pageId="0" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="damingshanensis">Sinophasma damingshanensis</taxonomicName>
Ho, sp. n. [Guangxi, China] is related to 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Sinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Sinophasma unispinosum" order="Phasmida" pageId="0" pageNumber="23" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="unispinosum">Sinophasma unispinosum</taxonomicName>
Chen &amp; Chen, 1997 [Guangdong, China] but can be separated by its greenish colour, smaller size and slenderer body in both sexes; absence of preopercular organ and decurved subgenital plate in female; and posterolaterally tuberculate anal segment in male.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>