<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.235.4027" ID-GBIF-Dataset="16238707-ccb3-4aeb-b4e9-80750f9d0e1e" ID-GBIF-Taxon="152037615" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-235-73" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B29AE99A-81B2-431D-B9DB-221C28671864" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2012" ModsDocID="1313-2970-235-73" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 235" ModsDocTitle="Rare and new cumaceans (Crustacea, Peracarida) from the southern margin of the Cap Ferret Canyon (Bay of Biscay)" checkinTime="1451248610082" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Corbera, Jordi" docDate="2012" docId="520E13C5F25A40A72C26D809477FEC85" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 235: 73-85" docOrigin="ZooKeys 235" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.235.4027" docTitle="Ithyleucon sorbei Corbera, 2012, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="B29AE99A-81B2-431D-B9DB-221C28671864" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="3" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="81" masterDocId="F93BFFE7FFE46D2CFFF83A66FFFBFF9C" masterDocTitle="Rare and new cumaceans (Crustacea, Peracarida) from the southern margin of the Cap Ferret Canyon (Bay of Biscay)" masterLastPageNumber="85" masterPageNumber="73" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" updateTime="1643710807920" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Rare and new cumaceans (Crustacea, Peracarida) from the southern margin of the Cap Ferret Canyon (Bay of Biscay)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Corbera, Jordi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2012</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>235</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>73</mods:start>
<mods:end>85</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.235.4027</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.235.4027</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-235-73</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">24065841-D250-40A4-8A15-B155DC3C8F1D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="152037615" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B29AE99A-81B2-431D-B9DB-221C28671864" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/520E13C5F25A40A72C26D809477FEC85" lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="81" pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="77" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
<taxonomicName LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B29AE99A-81B2-431D-B9DB-221C28671864" class="Malacostraca" family="Leuconidae" genus="Ithyleucon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ithyleucon sorbei" order="Cumacea" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sorbei">Ithyleucon sorbei</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="4" pageNumber="77">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 24
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="77" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Leuconidae" genus="Pseudoleucon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Pseudoleucon" order="Cumacea" pageId="4" pageNumber="77" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Pseudoleucon</taxonomicName>
sp. A - 
<bibRefCitation author="Elizalde, M" journalOrPublisher="Publicaciones Especiales del Instituto Espanol de Oceanografia" pageId="9" pageNumber="82" pagination="247 - 258" title="Las comunidades suprabentonicas batiales del golfo de Vizcaya (margen sur del canon de Cap-Ferret): composicion faunistica y estructura." volume="11" year="1993">Elizalde et al. 1993</bibRefCitation>
, p. 253.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="77" type="material examined">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
Holotype: Cap Ferret Canyon, Bay of Biscay, ESSAIS II, stn TS13, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="44.56983">44°34.19'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="-2.2696667">2°16.18'W</geoCoordinate>
, 1097-1099 m, 17/05/89, preadult female (ICMU12101901), Jean-Claude Sorbe leg.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="77">
Paratypes: Same data as the holotype, 1 preadult female (ICMU12101903), 1 preadult female dissected in two slides (ICMU12101902), 2 preadult males (ICMU12101904 and ICMU12101905); ESSAIS I, stn TS12, 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="9" value="44.538334">44°32.30'N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="9" value="-2.2516665">2°15.10'W</geoCoordinate>
, 1024-1043 m, 22/04/89 1 immature male (ICMU12101906), Jean-Claude Sorbe leg.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="4" pageNumber="77" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="77">Carapace without ridges, frontal lobe with two teeth and others located posteriorly. Pseudorostral lobes extending anterodorsally, upturned, anterior margin serrate. Antenna 1 geniculate between peduncle articles 1 and 2, accessory flagellum extending beyond the mid-length of main flagellum. Female with exopods on pereopods 1-3; male with exopods on pereopods 1-4. Uropod peduncle shorter than rami; endopod bi-articulate, slightly shorter than exopod. Male with 2 pairs of pleopods.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="81" pageId="5" pageNumber="78" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="78">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="78" start="start">Description</pageBreakToken>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Preadult female 3.125 mm total length. Carapace (Fig. 2) slightly longer than a fourth of the total length; frontal lobe with two teeth and others (3-4) positioned posteriorly on the middorsal line. Pseudorostral lobes extending anterodorsally, upturned by an angle of about 90°, anterior margin serrate; antennal notch small, anterolateral angle acute with 0-3 serrations on the lower margin</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Antennula (Fig. 3A), peduncle 3-articulate, geniculate between articles 1 and 2; article 1 longer than the combined lengths of articles 2 and 3; article 2 shorter than article 3; main flagellum 3-articulate, shorter than the last peduncle article, with two aesthetascs and three long simple setae terminally; accessory flagellum longer than the main flagellum of article 1, with three long simple setae positioned terminally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="78">Antenna 2 (Fig. 3B) 3-articulate, with two pappose setae on article 1.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="79" start="start">Mandible</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 3C) base truncate, lacina mobilis with three teeth, two simple setae between lacina mobilis and pars molaris.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Maxillula (Fig. 3D) inner endite with five setae, one simple, three pappose and one bifid; outer endite with cuspidate setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Maxilla (Fig. 3E) with 3 endites; broad endite with 5 simple and several pappose setae terminally; narrow endites not extending beyond the distal margin of broad endite; inner narrow endite with 5 simple setae terminally; outer narrow endite with 4 simple setae terminally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Maxilliped 1 (Fig. 3F) reduced with only three articles, dactylus minute.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Maxilliped 2 (Fig. 3G) basis shorter than rest of appendage, with a pappose seta on distal inner corner; merus with a long seta; carpus longer than merus with several simple setae on inner margin; propodus shorter than carpus, with a pappose seta on distal outer corner and several setae on inner margin; dactylus with two simple setae terminally.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Maxilliped 3 (Fig. 4A) with well developed exopod, basis longer than rest of appendage, produced distally, with three long pappose setae on distal outer corner and three pappose setae on inner margin; merus with small pappose sete on inner margin and a long pappose seta on distal outer corner; carpus as long as merus, with pappose seta on inner margin and two simple setae on distal outer corner; propodus shorter than carpus with a pappose seta on inner margin; dactylus shorter than propodus.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Pereopod 1 (Fig. 4B) with well developed exopod, basis shorter than the following three articles combined, with three pappose setae on its inner margin and a longer one on distal corner; ischium with a small simple seta on inner margin; merus half the length of carpus, with small pappose setae; carpus as long as propodus, with short simple setae on both margins and four long simple setae distally; propodus with simple setae on both margins; dactylus shorter than propodus, with five long simple setae terminally and some smaller ones along the margins.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Pereopod 2 (Fig. 4C) with well-developed exopod, basis as long as rest of appendage, with three pappose setae on inner margin and a long one on distal outer corner; ischium very short; as long as carpus; carpus with simple setae on distal margin; propodus half length of dactylus; dactylus with a simple setae on each margin and four terminally (the longest longer than the article).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Pereopod 3 (Fig. 4D) with well-developed exopod, basis longer than the rest of appendage, with a simple seta on distal anterior corner; ischium with three simple and a pappose setae on distal corner; merus twice as long as ischium, with a simple seta on distal corner; carpus twice as long as merus, with two long simple setae (distally annulated) on distal corner; propodus longer than half length of carpus with a long simple seta (distally annulated) on distal corner.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="79">Pereopod 4 (Fig. 4E) basis as long as the rest of appendage, with simple and pappose setae on both margins; ischium with two long simple setae; merus with a simple seta on distal corner; carpus 1.5 times as long as merus, with two simple seta on the margin and two (distally annulated) on distal corner; propodus as long as merus, with a long simple seta (distally annulated) on distal corner.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="7" pageNumber="80">
<pageBreakToken pageId="7" pageNumber="80" start="start">Pereopod</pageBreakToken>
5 (Fig. 4F), basis as long as the three following article combined length; carpus twice as long as merus, with two simple setae (distally annulated) on distal corner; propodus as long as merus, with a long simple seta (distally annulated) on distal corner.
</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="8" lastPageNumber="81" pageId="7" pageNumber="80">
Uropod peduncle (Fig. 4G) slightly longer than the last pleonite and 0.66 times as long as exopod, with five small cuspidate setae on inner margin. Endopod 2-articulate; article 1, 1.6 times as long as article 2, with 10 cuspidate setae on inner margin; article 
<pageBreakToken pageId="8" pageNumber="81" start="start">2</pageBreakToken>
with six cuspidate setae on inner margin and one terminally. Exopod 2-articulate, slightly longer than endopod; article 2 with simple setae on the outer margin and upper face, five pappose setae on inner margin, and two long simple setae terminally.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">Preadult male 3.63 mm total length (Fig. 2B). Similar in most characteristics-apart from the sexual ones-to the female but with a shorter pseudorostrum, a lower number of teeth on the middorsal line and without antennal notch. However, the pseudorostrum of the immature male (pleopods reduced to a single bud with few terminal simple setae) is long as it is in females (Fig. 2C).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="81" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">The new species is named in honour of Jean-Claude Sorbe (Arcachon, France) in recognition of his extensive work studying suprabenthic communities.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="8" pageNumber="81" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">Bay of Biscay, N Atlantic between 1024 and 1099 m depth.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="81">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Leuconidae" genus="Ithyleucon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ithyleucon sorbei" order="Cumacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="81" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sorbei">Ithyleucon sorbei</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n. A preadult female holotype (ICMU12101901), whole animal in lateral view B preadult male paratype (ICMU12101904) C carapace of immature male paratype (ICMU12101906).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="81">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Leuconidae" genus="Ithyleucon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ithyleucon sorbei" order="Cumacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="81" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sorbei">Ithyleucon sorbei</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n. preadult female paratype (ICMU12101902): A antenna 1 B antenna 2 C left mandible D maxilla 1 E maxilla 2 F maxilliped 1 G maxilliped 2.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="8" pageNumber="81">
<paragraph pageId="8" pageNumber="81">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Leuconidae" genus="Ithyleucon" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Ithyleucon sorbei" order="Cumacea" pageId="8" pageNumber="81" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="sorbei">Ithyleucon sorbei</taxonomicName>
gen. et sp. n. preadult female paratype (ICMU12101902): A maxilliped 3 B pereopod 1 C pereopod 2 D pereopod 3 E pereopod 4 F pereopod 5 G uropod.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>