<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999" ID-GBIF-Dataset="3942c2db-fdc5-4428-bc87-0a337edc07d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="142664139" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-747-1" ID-ZBK="74DC1895C13148E6B0C28A2BF42FAFE3" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:ED25CC10-321D-44B1-98F3-E2E30CC99286" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-747-1" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 747" ModsDocTitle="Four new Gammarus species from Tibetan Plateau with a key to Tibetan freshwater gammarids (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)" checkinTime="1522305661575" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Hou, Zhonge &amp; Li, Shuqiang" docDate="2018" docId="6EC47CDBFD612986B52C6F733F3C557D" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 747: 1-40" docOrigin="ZooKeys 747" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999" docTitle="Gammarus gonggaensis Hou &amp; Li, 2018, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="ED25CC10-321D-44B1-98F3-E2E30CC99286" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" masterDocId="FFE0FFCB0045FF9EFF9D381EFF99FFED" masterDocTitle="Four new Gammarus species from Tibetan Plateau with a key to Tibetan freshwater gammarids (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)" masterLastPageNumber="40" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" updateTime="1643519075925" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Four new Gammarus species from Tibetan Plateau with a key to Tibetan freshwater gammarids (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Hou, Zhonge</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Li, Shuqiang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>747</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>40</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.747.21999</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-747-1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">74DC1895C13148E6B0C28A2BF42FAFE3</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">74DC1895C13148E6B0C28A2BF42FAFE3</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="142664139" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:ED25CC10-321D-44B1-98F3-E2E30CC99286" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6EC47CDBFD612986B52C6F733F3C557D" lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="10" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/ED25CC10-321D-44B1-98F3-E2E30CC99286" class="Malacostraca" family="FAMILIA" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="ORDO" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="9" pageNumber="10">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 12, 13, 14, 15, 16
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="10" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Holotype: male (IZCAS-I-A0065-1), 10.0 mm, Hepinggou, Baoxing County (
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="5555" value="30.3">30.3°N</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="east" orientation="longitude" precision="5555" value="102.7">102.7°E</geoCoordinate>
), Gongga Mountains, altitude 2110 m, June 15, 2001, collected by Jinzhong Fu and Yuezhao Wang. Paratype: female (IZCAS-I-A0065-2) 8.6 mm; paratypes: two males (IZCAS-I-A0065-3), same data as holotype.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="10" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">The specific name is derived from the type locality; adjective.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="9" pageNumber="10" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Antenna II with long setae along anterior and posterior margins of peduncle articles IV and V, calceoli absent; pereopods III and IV with long straight setae on posterior margin; inner ramus of uropod III less than half the length of outer ramus, both inner and outer rami with few marginal setae.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Description of holotype male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">(IZCAS-I-A0065-1), 10.0 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Head. (Fig. 12A): Eyes medium in size, oval.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Figure 12. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. A head B epimeral plates C urosomites (lateral view) D urosomites (dorsal view) E maxilla II F maxilliped G incisor of left mandible H palp of left mandible I left maxilla I J palp of right maxilla I K incisor of right mandible L upper lip M lower lip.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Antenna I (Fig. 15B): peduncle articles 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
in length ratio 1.0: 0.7: 0.5, bearing distal setae; flagellum with 17 articles, aesthetascs present; accessory flagellum with five articles.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Antenna II (Fig. 15A): gland cone reaching peduncle article III, peduncle article III with distal setae, article IV a little shorter than article V, both with five to six groups of long setae along anterior and posterior margins; flagellum with 12 articles, bearing some setae, calceoli absent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Upper lip (Fig. 12L): convex, with minute setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Mandible (Fig. 12G, H, K): incisor of left mandible with five teeth; lacinia mobilis with four teeth; second and third articles of palp in length ratio 1.1: 1.0, second article with 16 setae, third article with four A-setae, four B-setae, 19 D-setae and four E-setae apically. Incisor of right mandible with four teeth; lacinia mobilis bifurcate, with several small teeth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Lower lip (Fig. 12M): inner lobes lacking, outer lobes covered with thin setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Maxilla I (Fig. 12I, J): asymmetrical, left inner plate with 13 plumose setae, outer plate with eleven serrated spines, second article of left palp bearing ten slender spines; second article of right palp with five blunt spines and two stiff setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Maxilla II (Fig. 12E): inner plate with 12 plumose setae in an oblique row; inner and outer plates with long setae apically.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Maxilliped (Fig. 12F): inner plate with three apical spines and several plumose setae; outer plate with nine blade spines on medial margin and five long setae apically; palp with four articles.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Pereon. Gnathopod I (Fig. 13A, C): coxal plate weakly dilated distally, bearing three and one seta on anterior and posterior corners respectively; basis with setae on anterior and posterior margins; carpus and propodus in length ratio 0.6: 1.0; palm of propodus oblique, bearing one spine on medial margin, three pairs of spines on posterior margin and three spines on inner face; dactylus more than half of posterior margin in length, with on seta one outer margin.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Figure 13. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. A gnathopod I B gnathopod II C propodus of gnathopod I D propodus of gnathopod II.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Gnathopod II (Fig. 13B, D): coxal plate subrectangular, with three and one seta on anterior and posterior corners respectively; carpus parallel-sided; palm of propodus truncated, bearing one medial spine, five spines on posterior corner; dactylus beyond the palm margin, with one seta on outer margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Pereopod III (Fig. 14A): coxal plate with three and one seta on anterior and posterior corners respectively, merus to propodus with groups of long straight setae on posterior margins; carpus and propodus accompanied by five spines on posterior margins, dactylus stout.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Figure 14. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="9" pageNumber="10" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. A pereopod III B pereopod V C pereopod IV D pereopod VI E pereopod VII F dactylus of pereopod IV G dactylus of pereopod V.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Pereopod IV (Fig. 14C, F): coxal plate concave, bearing two and four setae on anterior corner and posterior margin, merus with six groups of long setae on posterior margin; carpus and propodus with four groups of spines accompanied by some setae; dactylus with one seta on anterior margin and two setae at hinge of nail.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Pereopod V (Fig. 14B, G): coxal plate bearing one seta on anterior lobe and two setae on posterior lobe; basis with three setae and three spines on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with one spine accompanied by setae, posterior margin with a row of nine setae; merus with three groups of setae on anterior margin, a spine accompanied by setae on anterodistal corner, two pairs of spines on posterior margin; carpus with two groups of spines on anterior and posterior margins each, anterodistal corner with a spine, posterodistal corner with a group of six spines; propodus with three pairs of spines on anterior margin, and three clusters of setae and spines on posterior margin; dactylus with one plumose seta on posterior margin and a seta at hinge of unguis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="9" pageNumber="10">Pereopod VI (Fig. 14D): coxal plate with two setae on posterior margin; basis narrowing distally, with two long setae and four spines on anterior margin, anterodistal corner with one spine accompanied by setae, posterior margin with a row of 13 setae, and inner surface with two setae on posterior corner; merus with three groups of spines on anterior margin and a pair of spines on posterior margin; carpus with three or two groups of spines on anterior and posterior margins; propodus with four pairs of spines on anterior margin, posterior margin with a seta and a spine accompanied by a seta; dactylus similar to that of pereopod V.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="9" pageNumber="10">
Pereopod VII (Fig. 14E): coxal plate with three plumose setae on anterior margin and three setae on posterior margin; basis with two setae and four spines on anterior margin, posterior margin with a row of 12 setae, inner surface with one spine accom 
<pageBreakToken pageId="10" pageNumber="11" start="start">panied</pageBreakToken>
by setae on posterior corner; merus and carpus with spines on anterior and posterior margins; propodus with three pairs of spines on anterior margin; dactylus similar to that of pereopod V.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Coxal gills (Fig. 14B, D, E): present on gnathopod II and pereopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–VII">III-VII</normalizedToken>
sac-like.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Pleon. Epimeral plates (Fig. 12B): plate I ventrally rounded, with seven setae on ventral margin and two setae on posterior margin; plate II with one seta and two spines on anterior corner, two setae on posterior margin, posterodistal corner blunt; plate III with three spines on ventral margin and two setae on posterior margin.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Pleopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
(Fig. 15
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–I">G-I</normalizedToken>
): peduncle with some marginal setae, bearing two retinacula accompanied by setae; inner and outer rami nearly the same length, both rami fringed with plumose setae.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Figure 15. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., male holotype. A antenna II B antenna I C uropod II D uropod I E uropod III F telson G pleopod I H pleopod II I pleopod III.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Urosome. Urosomites 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
(Fig. 12 C, D): non-humped, with four clusters of spines accompanied by setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Uropod I (Fig. 15D): peduncle with one basofacial spine, two spines on outer margin, two spines on outer distal corner, two spines on inner margin, and one spine on inner distal corner; outer ramus with one and two spines on outer and inner margins respectively; inner ramus with one spine on inner margin, both rami with five terminal spines.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Uropod II (Fig. 15C): peduncle with one spine on inner and outer margins each, one spine on inner and outer distal corners each; inner ramus with one spine on inner margin; outer ramus with one spine on outer margin, both rami with five terminal spines.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Uropod III (Fig. 15E): peduncle with one seta on surface, two marginal plumose setae, two distal plumose setae and two distal spines; inner ramus 0.4 times as long as outer ramus, bearing two distal spines accompanied by one long seta; proximal article of outer ramus with two-one-two spines on outer margin and two distal spines, inner margin with a few plumose setae, terminal article shorter than adjacent spines, with distal setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Telson (Fig. 15F): cleft, with two distal spines and one facial spine.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Description of paratype female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">(IZCAS-I-A0065-2), 8.6 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Pereon. Gnathopod I (Fig. 16A, B): propodus pyriform, palm slant, bearing four spines on posterior corner.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Figure 16. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n., female paratype. A gnathopod I B propodus of gnathopod I C gnathopod II D propodus of gnathopod II E uropod III F oostegite of gnathopod II.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Gnathopod II (Fig. 16C, D): palm of propodus transverse, with four spines on posterior corner.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
Oostegites (Fig. 16F): present on gnathopod II and pereopods 
<normalizedToken originalValue="III–V">III-V</normalizedToken>
, broad, with many long setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Urosome. Uropod III (Fig. 16E): peduncle with one marginal spine accompanied by setae, and three pairs of distal spines; inner ramus around half the length of outer ramus, bearing one marginal and three distal spines; proximal article of outer ramus with two groups of spines on outer margin, one spine on inner margin and three spines on distal margin, terminal article shorter than adjacent spines.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">This species was collected from a small brook flowing under a large stone, forming a pool with an area of one square meter.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="10" pageNumber="11">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="11" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="10" pageNumber="11">
The new species of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. kangdingensis" pageId="10" pageNumber="11" rank="species" species="kangdingensis">G. kangdingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. in pereopods III and IV having long setae on posterior margins; and inner 
<pageBreakToken pageId="11" pageNumber="12" start="start">ramus</pageBreakToken>
of uropod III 0.4 times the length of outer ramus. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. can be distinguished from 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. kangdingensis" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="species" species="kangdingensis">G. kangdingensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. kangdingensis" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="species" species="kangdingensis">G. kangdingensis</taxonomicName>
in parentheses) by antenna II peduncle having long setae along anterior and posterior margins, calceoli absent (peduncle with short setae, calceoli present); outer ramus of uropod III with a few plumose setae on inner margin, inner ramus with no plumose marginal setae (with a row of plumose setae on inner margins of inner and outer rami); terminal article of uropod III shorter than adjacent spines (longer than adjacent spines).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. emeiensis" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="species" species="emeiensis">G. emeiensis</taxonomicName>
Hou, Li &amp; Koenemann, 2002 in antenna II peduncle with long setae along anterior and posterior margins, calceoli absent, and pereopods III and IV with long setae on posterior margins. It differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. emeiensis" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="species" species="emeiensis">G. emeiensis</taxonomicName>
<bibRefCitation author="Hou, Z" journalOrPublisher="Beaufortia" pageId="17" pageNumber="18" pagination="37 - 43" title="Gammarusemeiensis, a new species of amphipod crustacean from Sichuan Province, China." volume="52" year="2002">Hou et al., 2002</bibRefCitation>
by uropod III inner ramus 0.4 times the length of outer ramus, while reaching 0.7 times in 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. emeiensis" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="species" species="emeiensis">G. emeiensis</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="11" pageNumber="12">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Gammaridae" genus="Gammarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Gammarus gonggaensis" order="Amphipoda" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="gonggaensis">Gammarus gonggaensis</taxonomicName>
sp. n. differs from 
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. altus" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="species" species="altus">G. altus</taxonomicName>
sp. n. (
<taxonomicName genus="G." lsidName="G. altus" pageId="11" pageNumber="12" rank="species" species="altus">G. altus</taxonomicName>
in parentheses) by anternna II peduncle with long setae, calceoli absent (with short setae, calceoli present); pereopods III and IV with long setae on posterior margin (with a few short setae); uropod III with plumose setae on inner margin of inner ramus (with no plumose setae), terminal article shorter than adjacent spines (longer than adjacent spines).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>