<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.808.28172" ID-GBIF-Dataset="04917f36-3693-4c99-81d9-c2d53ae87c5d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="154125294" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-808-23" ID-ZBK="6121F4634D7E42ECA10B27E8140B2B78" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-808-23" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 808" ModsDocTitle="Morphological characters of immature stages of Palaearctic species of Cleopomiarus and Miarus and their systematic value in Mecinini (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Curculioninae)" checkinTime="1545315464969" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Skuhrovec, Jiri, Gosik, Rafal, Caldara, Roberto, Tosevski, Ivo, Letowski, Jacek &amp; Szwaj, Ewelina" docDate="2018" docId="D82E06912FFFF16CC8211621679B5165" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 808: 23-92" docOrigin="ZooKeys 808" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.808.28172" docTitle="Cleopomiarus longirostris Gyllenhal 1838" docType="treatment" docVersion="3" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="39" masterDocId="1B57FFC6815CAE18FFF5FFEEFFA3FFD9" masterDocTitle="Morphological characters of immature stages of Palaearctic species of Cleopomiarus and Miarus and their systematic value in Mecinini (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Curculioninae)" masterLastPageNumber="92" masterPageNumber="23" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" updateTime="1643467364076" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Morphological characters of immature stages of Palaearctic species of Cleopomiarus and Miarus and their systematic value in Mecinini (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Curculioninae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Skuhrovec, Jiri</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Gosik, Rafal</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Caldara, Roberto</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tosevski, Ivo</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Letowski, Jacek</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Szwaj, Ewelina</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>808</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>23</mods:start>
<mods:end>92</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.808.28172</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.808.28172</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-808-23</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">6121F4634D7E42ECA10B27E8140B2B78</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">6121F4634D7E42ECA10B27E8140B2B78</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="154125294" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:D82E06912FFFF16CC8211621679B5165" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D82E06912FFFF16CC8211621679B5165" lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="36" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
<taxonomicName authority="Gyllenhal, 1838" authorityName="Gyllenhal" authorityYear="1838" class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Cleopomiarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cleopomiarus longirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostris">Cleopomiarus longirostris (Gyllenhal, 1838)</taxonomicName>
Figures 21, 22, 23-24, 25-26, 27, 28-30
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="36" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
11 L3 larvae: south-eastern France, Menton, July 2007, ex capsules of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Campanulaceae" genus="Campanula" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Campanula trachelium" order="Asterales" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="trachelium">Campanula trachelium</taxonomicName>
L., leg. and det. R. Caldara, all determined by association with reared adults.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
Measurements (in mm). Body length: 6.60-8.70 (mean 8.3). Body width (abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–III">I-III</normalizedToken>
) up to 2.44. Head width: 1.05-1.16 (mean 1.10).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">General. Body elongated, slender, curved, rounded in cross section (Fig. 21).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
Figure 21. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Cleopomiarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cleopomiarus longirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostris">Cleopomiarus longirostris</taxonomicName>
mature larva habitus.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">Colouration. Pale brown head with indistinct pattern around frontal sutures (Fig. 21). All thoracic and abdominal segments from distinctly white to slightly yellow (Fig. 21).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">Vestiture. Setae on body thin, orange, distinctly different in length (minute to very short or long to very long). Cuticle slightly asperate.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">Head capsule (Fig. 22). Head oval, slightly flattened laterally. Frontal sutures medium width, distinct. Two pairs of stemmata (st), anterior one in the form of a large pigmented spot; and posterior one in form of a very small pigmented spot, located on each side close des5. Des1-3 long; des4 short and des5 long to very long (Fig. 22). Fs1 long; fs2 absent; fs3 short; fs4 long; and long fs5 (Fig. 22). Les1 and les2 as long as des5; both ves very short. Epicranial area with three pes and two sensilla in line with des2.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
Figure 22. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Cleopomiarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cleopomiarus longirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostris">Cleopomiarus longirostris</taxonomicName>
mature larva head, frontal view. Abbreviations: des - dorsal epicranial s., fs - frontal epicranial s., les - lateral epicranial s., pes - postepicranial s., ves - ventral s., at - antenna, st - stemmata.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">Antennae bearing one medium size conical sensorium, and basal membranous article with four sensilla different in length, three behind conical sensorium, and one ahead of it (Fig. 23).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
Figures 23-24. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Cleopomiarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cleopomiarus longirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostris">Cleopomiarus longirostris</taxonomicName>
mature larva. 23 Antenna 24 Right mandible. Abbreviation: mds - mandible dorsal s.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">Clypeus (Fig. 25) approximately 2.5 times as wide as long with two short cls, cls2 distinctly longer than cls1, and one sensillum.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
<paragraph pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
Figures 25-26. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Cleopomiarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cleopomiarus longirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="13" pageNumber="36" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostris">Cleopomiarus longirostris</taxonomicName>
mature larva, mouthparts. 25 Labrum and clypeus 26 Epipharynx. Abbreviations: als - anteriolateral s., ams - anteromedial s., cls - clypeal s., lms - labral s., mes - median s., clss - clypeal sensillium, lr - labral rods.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="14" lastPageNumber="37" pageId="13" pageNumber="36">
Mouthparts. Labrum (Fig. 25) less than 2.5 times as wide as long, with three piliform lms, different in the length; lms1 located anteromedially, close to margin, lms2 located in the middle, and lms3 located posterolaterally; lms1 and lms2 of medium size, and lms3 distinctly shorter than the previous two; only lms2 distinctly reaches labral margin. Epipharynx (Fig. 26) with three long finger-like als, two als of identical in 
<pageBreakToken pageId="14" pageNumber="37" start="start">length</pageBreakToken>
, and the third one distinctly shorter and also located more close to labral rods (lr); with three ams in different length, ams1 and ams2 piliform and short, finger-like ams3 and enlarged in middle, and also located more close to lr; without mes; labral rods (lr) distinct, elongated, oval. Mandibles (Fig. 24) bifid; mds1 relatively long, piliform, located basally; mds2 medium size, piliform, located distinctly apically and laterally. Maxilla (Fig. 27) stipes with very long stps and both pfs; very short to minute mbs, and sensillum close to mbs; mala with six medium sized finger-like dms; five vms, different in length, three setae medium size, and two setae very short. Maxillary palpi: basal palpomere with one short mxps and two sensilla; distal palpomere with, cuticular apical processes; length ratio of basal and distal palpomeres 1:0.8. Prelabium (Fig. 27) with one relatively long prms; ligula with two very short to minute ligs; premental sclerite broad, ring-shaped. Labial palpi with two palpomeres; length ratio of basal and distal palpomeres 1:0.8; each of the palpomeres with one sensillum, distal palpomere with short, cuticular apical processes. Postlabium (Fig. 27) with very short pms1 located basally, very long pms2 located medially and short to medium size pms3 located apically; membranous area basolaterally distinctly asperate.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="14" pageNumber="37">
<paragraph pageId="14" pageNumber="37">
Figure 27. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Cleopomiarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cleopomiarus longirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="14" pageNumber="37" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostris">Cleopomiarus longirostris</taxonomicName>
larval mouthparts, maxillolabial complex, ventral view right maxilla. Abbreviations: dms - dorsal malar s., vms - ventral malar s., mpxs - maxillary palps s., mbs - basioventral s., pfs - palpiferal s., stps - stipital s., prms - premental s., pms - postmental s., ligs - ligular s.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="15" lastPageNumber="38" pageId="14" pageNumber="37">
Thorax. Prothorax (Fig. 28) with eight very long to long and one very short to minute prns, small pigmented dorsal sclerite present with four long prns, this sclerite subdivided in two triangular plates medially; two very long to long ps; and one short to very short eus. Meso- and metathorax (Fig. 28) with one long prs, three medium to long pds; one very long to long as; two very long and one very short to minute ss; one 
<pageBreakToken pageId="15" pageNumber="38" start="start">long</pageBreakToken>
eps; one long ps; and one short to very short eus. Each pedal area of the thoracic segments with 5-6 very long to long pda.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="15" pageNumber="38">
<paragraph pageId="15" pageNumber="38">
Figures 28-30. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Curculionidae" genus="Cleopomiarus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cleopomiarus longirostris" order="Coleoptera" pageId="15" pageNumber="38" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostris">Cleopomiarus longirostris</taxonomicName>
mature larva, habitus. 28 Lateral view of thoracic segments 29 Lateral view of abdominal segment I 30 Lateral view of abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="VI–X">VI-X</normalizedToken>
. Abbreviations: as - alar s., ds - dorsal s., eps - epipleural s., eus - eusternal s., lsts - laterosternal s., pda - pedal s., pds - postdorsal s., prns - pronotal s., prs - prodorsal s., ss - spiracular s., ps - pleural s., sts - sternal s., ts - terminal s., Th1-3 - number of thoracic segments, Ab1-10 - number of abdominal seg.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="16" lastPageNumber="39" pageId="15" pageNumber="38">
Abdomen. Abdominal segments 
<normalizedToken originalValue="I–VII">I-VII</normalizedToken>
(Figs 29-30) with one short prs; one long and two short to very short pds (order: short, long, short); one long and one minute ss; two very long to long eps; one relatively long ps; one short lsts; and two very short eus. Abdominal segment VIII (Fig. 30) with one very short to minute prs; one relatively long and two very short pds (order: very short, long, very short); one relatively long and 
<pageBreakToken pageId="16" pageNumber="39" start="start">one</pageBreakToken>
minute ss; two relatively long eps; one short ps; one short lsts; and two very short eus. Abdominal segment IX (Fig. 30) with three relatively long and one very short to minute ds; one relatively long and sometimes one minute ps; and two short to very short sts. Abdominal segment X (Fig. 30) with one very short seta (ts).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="16" pageNumber="39" type="biology_ecology">
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="39">Biology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="39">
We can confirm that larvae of this species feed on seed capsules of 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Campanulaceae" genus="Campanula" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Campanula trachelium" order="Asterales" pageId="16" pageNumber="39" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="trachelium">Campanula trachelium</taxonomicName>
L., where they pupate without producing galls. It is noteworthy that adults did not exit by making a hole in the capsules but remained inside with the rostrum folded in the ventral canal until these opened spontaneously and forcefully, blowing up the seeds. On the other hand, it would be impossible, especially for the female, to straighten up the very long rostrum inside the capsule due to the limited available space. This is a more advantageous behaviour and apparently opposite to that of 
<taxonomicName authority="Schilsky, 1906" authorityName="Schilsky" authorityYear="1906" class="Insecta" family="Brentidae" genus="Rhopalapion" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Rhopalapion longirostre" order="Coleoptera" pageId="16" pageNumber="39" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="longirostre">Rhopalapion longirostre</taxonomicName>
(Olivier, 1807), another species where the female rostrum is more than twice as long as the stout male rostrum. In this species, 
<bibRefCitation author="Wilhelm, G" journalOrPublisher="Biological Journal of the Linnean Society" pageId="57" pageNumber="80" pagination="642 - 660" title="Sexual dimorphism in head structures of the weevil Rhopalapionlongirostre (Olivier 1807) (Coleoptera: Curculionoidea): a response to ecological demands of egg deposition." url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1095-8312.2011.01751.x" volume="104" year="2011">Wilhelm et al. (2011)</bibRefCitation>
argued that the long rostrum is presumably an advantage for this weevil because its larvae can feed on plant parts with high energy density into buds (i.e., pollen grains) and that natural selection favours rostrum elongation. However, these authors reported that the elongated rostrum of females also bears a high risk when metamorphosed weevils attempt to leave their site of pupal development, which is the dry seed chambers, and therefore mortality during escaping may counteract selection for rostrum elongation, thus placing a limit on rostrum exaggeration. It is noteworthy that 
<taxonomicName genus="R." lsidName="R. longirostre" pageId="16" pageNumber="39" rank="species" species="longirostre">R. longirostre</taxonomicName>
does not possess a ventral canal, which allows it to retain the folded rostrum.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="16" pageNumber="39" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="39">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="16" pageNumber="39">
This species is only known from France, Italy, and Switzerland, where it is quite common. The adult is very closely related to 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. graminis" pageId="16" pageNumber="39" rank="species" species="graminis">C. graminis</taxonomicName>
, as also supported by preliminary molecular studies (I 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Toševski">Tosevski</normalizedToken>
, unpublished data), from which it differs only by the very long rostrum especially in the female and usually by the larger size (
<bibRefCitation author="Caldara, R" journalOrPublisher="Journal of Insect Biodiversity" pageId="54" pageNumber="77" pagination="1 - 47" title="Systematics of the Holarctic species of the weevil genus Cleopomiarus Pierce (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)." url="https://doi.org/10.12976/jib/2016.4.6" volume="4" year="2016">Caldara and Legalov 2016</bibRefCitation>
). Therefore, the larval differences between these two taxa, in 
<taxonomicName genus="C." lsidName="C. longirostris" pageId="16" pageNumber="39" rank="species" species="longirostris">C. longirostris</taxonomicName>
antennae bearing one medium size conical sensorium and four sensilla (Fig. 23), dorsal setae (except des4) extremely long (Fig. 22), prothorax with eight very long and one very short to minute prns (Fig. 28), are very important since they allow easy separation of these two species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>