<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.600.6709" ID-GBIF-Dataset="0010d985-7b7c-462b-b2d9-ec991e99dccb" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127876043" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-600-89" ID-ZBK="ABD7E90899B340CEADCC68EF71387FDA" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:747DBE94-0E6E-4E94-8A24-D0C927515082" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2016" ModsDocID="1313-2970-600-89" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 600" ModsDocTitle="Evemphyronsinense, a new genus and species infesting legume seedpods in China (Coleoptera, Attelabidae, Rhynchitinae)" checkinTime="1466665058129" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lv, Xiangyang, Alonso-Zarazaga, Miguel A., Xiao, Zhishu, Wang, Zhiliang &amp; Zhang, Runzhi" docDate="2016" docId="4242BC36BA03B509B5C9FB8623F76AAE" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 600: 89-101" docOrigin="ZooKeys 600" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.600.6709" docTitle="Evemphyron Alonso-Zarazaga, Lv &amp; Wang, gen. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="747DBE94-0E6E-4E94-8A24-D0C927515082" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="94" masterDocId="FFB9691FA5092D0A527DFFF9FFAEAF2F" masterDocTitle="Evemphyronsinense, a new genus and species infesting legume seedpods in China (Coleoptera, Attelabidae, Rhynchitinae)" masterLastPageNumber="101" masterPageNumber="89" pageId="1" pageNumber="90" updateTime="1643630121228" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Evemphyronsinense, a new genus and species infesting legume seedpods in China (Coleoptera, Attelabidae, Rhynchitinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lv, Xiangyang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Alonso-Zarazaga, Miguel A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Xiao, Zhishu</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Wang, Zhiliang</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Zhang, Runzhi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2016</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>600</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>89</mods:start>
<mods:end>101</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.600.6709</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.600.6709</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-600-89</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">ABD7E90899B340CEADCC68EF71387FDA</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">ABD7E90899B340CEADCC68EF71387FDA</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127876043" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:747DBE94-0E6E-4E94-8A24-D0C927515082" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4242BC36BA03B509B5C9FB8623F76AAE" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="94" pageId="1" pageNumber="90">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="90" type="multiple">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="90">Taxon classification Animalia Coleoptera Attelabidae</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="90" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="90">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/747DBE94-0E6E-4E94-8A24-D0C927515082" authority="Alonso-Zarazaga, Lv &amp; Wang" genus="Evemphyron" lsidName="Evemphyron" pageId="1" pageNumber="90" rank="genus">Evemphyron Alonso-Zarazaga, Lv &amp; Wang</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="1" pageNumber="90">gen. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 3-6, 7-10, 11-16, 17-19
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="90" type="type species">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="90">Type species.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="90">
<taxonomicName genus="Evemphyron" lsidName="Evemphyron sinense" pageId="1" pageNumber="90" rank="species" species="sinense">Evemphyron sinense</taxonomicName>
Alonso-Zarazaga, Lv &amp; Wang, sp. n.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="94" pageId="1" pageNumber="90" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="90">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="90">
A member of the tribe 
<taxonomicName lsidName="" pageId="1" pageNumber="90" rank="tribe" tribe="Deporaini">Deporaini</taxonomicName>
Voss, 1929 as currently understood (cf. 
<bibRefCitation author="Sawada, Y" journalOrPublisher="Humans and Nature" pageId="10" pageNumber="99" pagination="1 - 93" title="A systematic study of the family Rhynchitidae of Japan (Coleoptera, Curculionoidea)." volume="2" year="1993">Sawada 1993</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="90">Integument black to brownish, with green to dark bronze metallic shine, some areas on legs, antennae and underside a little lighter.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="91" pageId="1" pageNumber="90">
Vestiture yellow or brown, dense; scales arched to oblique, piliform, those on elytra with apex sometimes flagelliform; brown scales forming a chevron on declivity; scales on dorsum of elytra placed transversally or pointing to outer apical angle of elytra, clearly subparallel to striae only on apical half of 1st interstria, those on anterior half of pronotum, head and metarostrum suberect and pointing forward; scape and funicle with yellow piliform scales, black setae at most as long as scales; tarsomeres densely covered with black piliform scales; very short suberect, arched black setae visible only 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="91" start="start">on</pageBreakToken>
apical two thirds of elytral interstriae 9 and 10, rarely visible on other interstriae, and on underside of rostrum.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="91">Mouthparts. (Figs 7, 17-18) Mandibles with two teeth on outer margin, a short basal one and a long, sickle-shaped, outwardly-pointed, subapical one, this tooth caducous (in both sexes), leaving at most an obtuse tooth-like remainder after being shed (usually only in females); apex of right mandible with a small ventral cusp (usually quickly worn and obliterated in the apparently more aged specimens, like the outer basal teeth). Maxillary palpi well developed, projecting beyond apex of setose galea, 4-segmented, segments 1-3 transverse, segment 4 subconical, little shorter than wide at base, apex rounded, with eight longitudinal, rod-shaped sensilla. Prementum about as long as wide, asetose, tightly enclosed between deeply crescent-shaped anterior margin of postmentum, with a semicircular base, apex subtruncate, irregular; ligula densely setose, occupying entire apex of prementum; postmental apices almost reaching apices of ligular setae; labial palpi minute, 3-segmented, not protruding from notch in anterolateral corners of prementum and not projecting beyond its apex, first and second palpomeres each with one very long seta, third palpomere minute with two sensilla.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="92" start="start">Rostrum</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 5-6) elongate, in both sexes longer than pronotum, in side view with a strong lower lateral keel running more or less parallel to the ventral margin and a strong median ventral keel parallel to the other, leaving a sulcus between them. Lower margin of scrobe slightly prominent laterally at mesorostrum. Female metarostrum without dense patches of setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">
Antennae (Fig. 8) inserted a little behind middle in both sexes, more robust in male; scape shorter than mesorostral width; desmomeres circular in cross-section, 2nd desmomere longer than either scape or first desmomere, but shorter than length of both combined; club loose, slightly flattened, velvety, as long as last 
<normalizedToken originalValue="4½">41/2</normalizedToken>
desmomeres, two first segments transverse, last segment longer than any of the others, but as long as or slightly shorter than first and second together, obpyriform, pointed, asymmetrical, its front margin straight to slightly concave, its hind margin convex.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="92">Head moderately elongate, subglobose, very weakly constricted behind eyes in side view, but not in dorsal view. Eyes moderately convex, protruding from head outline, in dorsal view longer than minimum distance between them across forehead, in side view slightly oval.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="93" start="start">Pronotum</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 3-4) rather isodiametric, widest in basal quarter, densely punctulate, with rounded, non-carinate sides and base curved towards scutellum, an incomplete median keel present, fine but marked. Scutellum (Figs 3-4) subrectangular, slightly transverse, densely punctulate and with dense vestiture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">Elytra (Figs 3-4) oblong, dorsal surface flat to evidently concave behind scutellum, with rounded, developed humeri, bases obliquely converging towards scutellum, sides subparallel, falling almost vertically from 7th interstria to costal margin, elytral declivity very steep, elytral apices separately and widely rounded; ten striae formed by rows of strong, more or less rounded punctures, 9th and 10th striae confluent at metacoxal level; scutellar striole absent. Macropterous.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
Ventral areas. Prosternum short in both sexes, procoxae almost reaching front margin. Hypomera not touching at midline, sternellum large, separating both hypomera and forming part of prothoracic margin (Fig. 19). Procoxae projecting, subconical, tangential to one another. Male with rather large sex patch of setae on inner apex of procoxae. Mesocoxae separated by a distance of less than mesocoxal transverse diameter. Mesocoxal acetabuli open. Abdominal lobes absent, metacoxa reaching metanepisternum (Fig. 10). Tergites I-III fused. Sternites separated by a thin membrane, not visibly fused, sternite 1 barely longer than 2, sternite 5 as long as 4 in both sexes. Propygidium (tergite VI) almost completely covered by elytra, with sparse spicules not forming definite wing-folding patches. Pygidium (tergiteVII) almost vertical, not costate, ca. 1.25 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as wide as long, in dorsal view covered by elytra in both sexes, but clearly visible from behind. Tergite VIII in male without bunches of macrosetae, these irregularly placed along margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
Legs. Femora unarmed. Tibiae straight, moderately flattened, moderately widening towards apex, without mucrones or spurs in both sexes; meso- and metatibiae with an outer crenulate (bracteate) keel (
<bibRefCitation author="Holloway, BA" journalOrPublisher="New Zealand Journal of Zoology" pageId="9" pageNumber="98" pagination="445 - 450" title="Morphology of pronotal carinae and associate surface structures in New Zealand Anthribidae (Insecta: Coleoptera)." url="10.1080/03014223.1984.10428259" volume="11" year="1984">Holloway 1984</bibRefCitation>
), this also present but reduced (bracteae scattered) on apical dorsum of meso- and metafemora, represented by a glabrous line (Fig. 9); protibiae with outer margin rounded. First tarsomere subtriangular, little longer than wide in all legs. Claws elongate, inner tooth three quarters as long as outer.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">Male genitalia and terminalia. Penis (Figs 11-13) flattened, in dorsal view pedon apically pointed and mucronulate, tectum almost as wide as pedon, in side view ventral margin of pedon almost straight, weakly incurved at apex, temones moderately widening cephalad. Endophallus wider than tube of penis between the temones, endophallic armature consisting of sparse small denticles, these larger and condensed in an irregularly U-shaped patch between the base of the temones, around the gonopore, with a larger median projection near its anterior margin. Tegmen (Figs 14-15) with dorsal plate strongly projecting and tapering towards apex, this shortly recurved, with a few long and short macrochaetae, manubrium slightly asymmetrical, uniformly broadening to apex. Sternite IX fused to VIII, with apodeme strongly curving sinistro-anteriad near apex (Fig. 16).</paragraph>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
Figures 11-16. 
<taxonomicName genus="Evemphyron" lsidName="Evemphyron sinense" pageId="4" pageNumber="93" rank="species" species="sinense">Evemphyron sinense</taxonomicName>
, paratype male 11 Penis, dorsal view 12 Penis, lateral view 13 Penis, ventral view 14 Tegmen, dorsal view 15 Tegmen, lateral view 16 Sternite and tergite VIII (to the right) and sternite IX with apodeme turning sinistro-anterially at apex.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
Figures 17-19. 
<taxonomicName genus="Evemphyron" lsidName="Evemphyron sinense" pageId="4" pageNumber="93" rank="species" species="sinense">Evemphyron sinense</taxonomicName>
17 Apex of submentum, labium and maxilla 18 Detail of labial palpus 19 Detail of apex of hypomera and intervening sternellum.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="94" pageId="4" pageNumber="93">
Female genitalia and terminalia. Ovipositor with gonoxites very wide in anterior half, and obliquely narrowed to an elongate posterior half (
<normalizedToken originalValue="“subdivided”">&quot;subdivided&quot;</normalizedToken>
in 
<bibRefCitation author="Sawada, Y" journalOrPublisher="Humans and Nature" pageId="10" pageNumber="99" pagination="1 - 93" title="A systematic study of the family Rhynchitidae of Japan (Coleoptera, Curculionoidea)." volume="2" year="1993">
<normalizedToken originalValue="Sawada’s">Sawada's</normalizedToken>
(1993)
</bibRefCitation>
sense), styli cylindrical, ca. 4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
as long as wide. Spermatheca C-shaped, with 
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="94" start="start">cornu</pageBreakToken>
robust, apically rounded, a little longer than body, no visible nodulus or ramus, ductus spermathecae and ductus glandulae very close to each other at junction with spermatheca. Sternite VIII with plate slightly longer than wide at base, rounded at apex, manubrium strongly curving sinistro-anteriad near apex.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="94" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="94">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="94">
The genus name is based on the classical Greek prefix 
<normalizedToken originalValue="εὖ">εὖ</normalizedToken>
(well), latinized as ev- (as in 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Cicadellidae" genus="Evacanthus" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Evacanthus" order="Hemiptera" pageId="5" pageNumber="94" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Evacanthus</taxonomicName>
) and the present active participle of the verb 
<normalizedToken originalValue="ἐμφύρω">ἐμφύρω</normalizedToken>
(to confuse), 
<normalizedToken originalValue="ἐμφῦρον">ἐμφῦρον</normalizedToken>
(the confusing one). Gender neuter. Stem is Evemphyront-.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="5" pageNumber="94" type="chinese name">
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="94">Chinese name.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="94">
<normalizedToken originalValue="豆毛象属">豆毛象属</normalizedToken>
[
<normalizedToken originalValue="dòu">dou</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="máo">mao</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="xiàng">xiang</normalizedToken>
<normalizedToken originalValue="shǔ">shǔ</normalizedToken>
].
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>