<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.668.12181" ID-GBIF-Dataset="ae33e92d-1c8f-475f-90bb-d32eea2bf9de" ID-GBIF-Taxon="128527473" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-668-33" ID-ZBK="A930C073388A4507BABFB1D0FC82A5D6" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:811C54A4-0339-4043-809D-2E0715BA7C5A" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1313-2970-668-33" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 668" ModsDocTitle="A new species of the genus Nicippe from Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Pardaliscidae)" checkinTime="1492081469541" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Matsukami, Sachi, Nakano, Takafumi &amp; Tomikawa, Ko" docDate="2017" docId="D80890D3B6967A10A74BBD26044DF5CD" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 668: 33-47" docOrigin="ZooKeys 668" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.668.12181" docTitle="Nicippe recticaudata Matsukami, Nakano &amp; Tomikawa, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="811C54A4-0339-4043-809D-2E0715BA7C5A" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="35" masterDocId="FFF6FF97B913C060FF9DFFF1FFB2FF92" masterDocTitle="A new species of the genus Nicippe from Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Pardaliscidae)" masterLastPageNumber="47" masterPageNumber="33" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" updateTime="1643557770244" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A new species of the genus Nicippe from Japan (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Pardaliscidae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Matsukami, Sachi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Nakano, Takafumi</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Tomikawa, Ko</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>668</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>33</mods:start>
<mods:end>47</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.668.12181</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.668.12181</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-668-33</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZBK">A930C073388A4507BABFB1D0FC82A5D6</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">A930C073388A4507BABFB1D0FC82A5D6</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="128527473" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:811C54A4-0339-4043-809D-2E0715BA7C5A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D80890D3B6967A10A74BBD26044DF5CD" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/811C54A4-0339-4043-809D-2E0715BA7C5A" class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="1" pageNumber="34">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="reference_group">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe tumida" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tumida">Nicippe tumida</taxonomicName>
: 
<bibRefCitation author="Ren, X" journalOrPublisher="Science Press, Beijing" pageId="4" pageNumber="37" title="Fauna Sinica. Invertebrata vol. 43 Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea (II)." year="2012">Ren 2012</bibRefCitation>
: 349-351, fig. 154.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Material examined.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Holotype: male (8.4 mm), NSMT-Cr 25456 (Fig. 1A), off Cape Toi (31°14.54'N, 131°32.20'
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–">E-</normalizedToken>
31°14.94'N, 131°31.46'E; 265-367 m deep), Japan, collected by K. Tomikawa, 29 May 2006. Paratypes: female (8.5 mm), NSMT-Cr 25457 (Fig. 1B), male (8.5 mm), NSMT-Cr 25458, male (10.4 mm), KUZ Z1807, male (6.8 mm), KUZ Z1808, data same as for holotype.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Figure 1. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
sp. n., habitus, lateral views. A holotype, male, 8.4 mm, NSMT-Cr 25456 B paratype, female, 8.5 mm, NSMT-Cr 25457. Scale bars: 1.0 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Dorsal margin of urosomite 1 with 2 pointed teeth; posterior margin of merus of pereopod 4 with 5-6 setae; anterior margin of merus of pereopod 5 with 9-10 setae; telson with straight inner margin, tapering proximally.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Description of male</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
(holotype, NSMT-Cr 25456). Head (Fig. 2A) without any trace of eyes or ommatidia; rostrum pointed; lateral cephalic corners angularly produced. Pereon segments 1-4 subequal in length, slightly shorter than segment 5; segment 6-7 longest, about 1.3 times length of previous segment. Pleonites 1-3 in length ratio of 1.0: 1.3: 1.3. Posteroventral corners of epimeral plates 1-3 each with prominent small tooth (Fig. 4
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–I">G-I</normalizedToken>
); ventral submargins of epimeral plates 2 and 3 with 2 setae, respectively. Urosomites 1-3 in length ratio of 1.0: 1.0: 1.2; urosomite 1 with 2 pointed teeth extending beyond posterior margin of its segment (Fig. 4J); urosomites 2 and 3 dorsally smooth.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Antenna 1 (Fig. 2B): length 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
body length; peduncular articles 1-3 in length ratio of 1.0: 0.6: 0.3; posterodistal corner of peduncular article 1 with 2 long setae; accessory flagellum 3-articulate, article 1 long, length 4.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width; primary flagellum 38-articulate, length of article 1 longer than peduncular articles 2 and 3 combined, callynophore weakly developed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Antenna 2 (Fig. 2C): length 0.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
antenna 1, peduncular articles 3-5 in length ratio of 1.0: 1.1: 1.1; flagellum 29-articulate.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Figure 2. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 8.4 mm, NSMT-Cr 25456. A head, lateral view B antenna 1, lateral view, facial setae on accessory flagellum 1 omitted C antenna 2, lateral view D upper lip, anterior view E left mandible, medial view F distal part of left mandible, lateral view G distal part of right mandible, lateral view H lower lip, ventral view I maxilla 1, dorsal view J Maxilla 2, dorsal view K maxilliped, dorsal view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm (A, E, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="H–K">H-K</normalizedToken>
), 1.0 mm (B, C), 0.1 mm (D, F, G).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Mouthparts. Upper lip (Fig. 2D) with shallowly concave ventral margin, lobes symmetric. Mandibles (Fig. 2
<normalizedToken originalValue="E–G">E-G</normalizedToken>
): slightly asymmetric, incisor margins broad, straight, anterodosal corner rounded, anteroventral corner with a strong tooth; left lacinia mobilis (Fig. 2F) broad, about 0.8 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of incisor, multi-dentate; right incisor (Fig. 2G) with 2 teeth on proximal to anterodorsal corner; right lacinia absent; accessory setal row of left and right mandibles each with 2 robust setae, and a proximal tuft of seta; molar absent; mandibular palp 3-articulate with length ratio of 1.0: 3.6: 2.7, article 2 with 12 setae, article 3 with 5 posterolateral and 3 apical setae. Lower lip (Fig. 2H) with broad outer lobes, inner lobes coalesced. Maxilla 1 (Fig. 2I) with inner and outer plate and palp; inner plate small with apical seta; outer plate subrectangular with 7 spine-teeth and 1 stout plumose seta, the lateral one strongest and longest; left and right palps symmetric, palp 2-articulate, article 1 lacking marginal setae, article 2 expanded distally, with 8 robust and 8 slender setae on its apical margin. Maxilla 2 (Fig. 2J) with moderately slender inner and outer plates; inner plate bearing row of plumose setae on apical to medial margin; outer plate slightly longer than inner plate with apical plumose setae. Maxilliped (Fig. 2K) with inner and outer plates and palp; inner plate not reaching base of palp, with long plumose seta and short simple seta apically; outer plate narrowly rounded, reaching base of article 2 of palp, with setae along apical to medial margin; palp raptorial, 4-articulate, long, article 2 longest with inner marginal rows of setae, article 3 covered with 4 clusters of setae, article 4 slender with serrate inner margin.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 3A): coxa ovate with seta on anterodistal corner; basis long, expanded distally, anterior margin straight, posterior margin arched; ischium short, triangular, subequal in length to merus; carpus with short rounded lobe ventrally with long setae; propodus oval, about as wide as carpus, palm straight with long setae; dactylus slender, slightly curved, inner margin smooth with tooth near the base.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 3B): coxa rounded with seta on anterodistal corner, posteroproximal part with setae; compared to that of gnathopod 1, basis longer, more slender and straighter; carpal lobe stronger; dactylus similar, slightly shorter.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Pereopod 3 (Fig. 3C): coxa quadrate, posterior margin with setae; basis long with small setae on anterior and posterior margins; merus with 8 setae on posterior margin, 7 facial setae, and a cluster of setae comprising 3 setae on posterodistal corner; carpus and propodus with plumose and simple setae on posterior margin, and laterofacial setae; dactylus slender and weakly curved, length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
propodus.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Figure 3. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 8.4 mm, NSMT-Cr 25456. A gnathopod 1, lateral view B gnathopod 2, lateral view C pereopod 3, lateral view D pereopod 4, lateral view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Pereopod 4 (Fig. 3D): coxa rounded, ventral and posterior margins with setae; basis long with setae on anterior and posterior margins; merus with 5-6 setae on posterior margin, 7 laterofacial setae, and a cluster of setae comprising 3 setae on posterodistal corner; carpus and propodus with plumose and simple setae on posterior margin, and laterofacial setae; dactylus slender and weakly curved, length 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
propodus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Pereopod 5 (Fig. 4A): coxa bilobate, anterior lobe stronger and slightly longer with seta on ventral margin; basis posterior margin slightly convex with 2 small setae, posteroventral corner subquadrate with 2 minute setae; merus, carpus, and propodus in length ratio of 1.0: 0.8: 0.9; merus with 9 setae on anterior margin and 5 setae on submargin, anterodistal corner with 1 long and 3 relatively short setae; dactylus slender and almost straight, longer than on pereopods 3-4, 0.76 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
length of propodus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Pereopod 6 (Fig. 4B): coxa shallowly bilobate, anterior lobe slightly stronger; basis posterior margin slightly convex without setae, posteroventral corner subquadrate with seta.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Pereopod 7 (Fig. 4C): coxa ventral margin shallowly concave, anterior margin and ventral submargin each with 2 setae; basis expanded more strongly than pereopods 5-6, distally tapering, posteroproximal margin convex, anterodistal margin with setae, posteroventral corner slightly produced into a small rounded lobe, armed with 2 long setae.</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Figure 4. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 8.4 mm, NSMT-Cr 25456. A pereopod 5, medial view B 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 6, lateral view C 
<normalizedToken originalValue="coxa–ischium">coxa-ischium</normalizedToken>
of pereopod 7, lateral view D pleopod 2, medial view, some setae on rami omitted E retinacula and associate setae on peduncle of pleopod 2, medial view F bifid plumose setae (clothes-pin setae) on inner basal margin of inner ramus of pleopod 2, medial view 
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–I">G-I</normalizedToken>
epimeral plates 1-3, respectively, lateral views J dorsal margin of urosomite 1. Scale bars: 0.5 mm (
<normalizedToken originalValue="A–D">A-D</normalizedToken>
, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="G–I">G-I</normalizedToken>
), 0.1 mm (E, F, J).
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Coxal gills on gnathopod 2 and pereopods 3-5 broad, longer than those of bases; gill on pereopod 6 ovate, length 0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
basis; gill on pereopod 7 slender, length 0.2 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
basis.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Pleopods 1-3 (Fig. 4D) each with paired retinacula (Fig. 4E) on inner distal margin of peduncle, bifid setae (clothes-pin setae) (Fig. 4F) on inner basal margin of inner ramus; inner and outer rami of each pleopod consisting of 18 and 21 articles, respectively.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Uropods. Uropod 1 (Fig. 5A): peduncle slightly longer than rami, distolateral peduncular tooth very strong; outer ramus somewhat longer than inner ramus, outer and medial margins of outer ramus with 6 and 4 robust setae, respectively; outer and medial margins of inner ramus with 4 and 8 robust setae, respectively; both rami with stout setae apically. Uropod 2 (Fig. 5B): distolateral peduncular tooth short; outer ramus slightly longer than inner ramus, outer and medial margins with 6 and 7 robust setae, respectively; inner ramus with 6 outer and 4 medial robust setae, respectively; both rami with a stout seta apically. Uropod 3 (Fig. 5C): peduncle setose on outer margin, length 0.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
outer ramus; outer ramus 1-articulate, somewhat longer than inner ramus; outer and medial margins of inner ramus each with plumose seta; medial margins of both rami with traces of setae.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Telson (Fig. 5D) length 2.0 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, cleft for 88% of length in V-shape with straight inner margins of incision, each lobe with 4 setae laterally; apex of each lobe incised, lateral part of apex slightly longer than medial part, with small robust seta, lobes slightly tapering distally.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Figure 5. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
sp. n., holotype, male, 8.4 mm, NSMT-Cr 25456. A uropod 1, dorsal view B uropod 2, dorsal view C uropod 3, ventral view D telson, dorsal view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Description of female</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
(paratype, NSMT-Cr 25457).Antenna 1 (Fig. 6A): length 0.6 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
body length; article 1 of accessory flagellum short, length 2.4 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width; primary flagellum 43-articulate, callynophore weakly developed.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Figure 6. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype, female, 8.5 mm, NSMT-Cr 25457. A antenna 1, lateral view B antenna 2, lateral view C gnathopod 1, medial view D gnathopod 2, medial view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Antenna 2 (Fig. 6B): length 0.7 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
antenna 1; flagellum 18-articulate.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Gnathopod 1 (Fig. 6C): anterior and posterior submargins of basis with many setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Gnathopod 2 (Fig. 6D): anterior margin and posterior submargin of basis with many setae.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Pereopods 6 and 7 (Fig. 7A, B): similar to those of holotype; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="merus–propodus">merus-propodus</normalizedToken>
slender, with setae on anterior and posterior margins, and facial setae; dactylus slender, slightly curved inward.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Telson (Fig. 7C): length 1.9 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
width, cleft for 90% of length, incision wider than that of male, each lobe with 6-7 setae laterally.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Figure 7. 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
sp. n., paratype, female, 8.5 mm, NSMT-Cr 25457. A pereopod 6, lateral view B pereopod 7, lateral view, coxa lacking C telson, dorsal view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="variation">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Variation.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Callynophore on antenna 1 well developed (3 males, NMST-Cr 25458, KUZ Z1807, Z1808); peduncular article 5 of antenna 2 longer than 1.5 
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
article 4 (3 males, NMST-Cr 25458, KUZ Z1807, Z1808); posterior margin of merus of pereopod 4 with 5-6 setae; anterior margin of merus of pereopod 5 with 9-11 setae.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="coloration">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Coloration.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Color in life unknown; faded in preservative (Fig. 1).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">The specific name is a compound adjective derived from the Latin words rectus, and caudatus referring to the fact that the inner margin of the telson of this species is straight, a diagnostic character of the species.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="sequences and coi genetic distances">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Sequences and COI genetic distances.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">In total nine nucleotide sequences were determined: holotype (NSMT-Cr 25456), four sequences, 28S (LC214961; 1336 bp), H3 (LC214963; 328 bp), COI (LC214958; 658 bp), and 16S (LC214956; 407 bp); paratype (NSMT-Cr 25457), four sequences, 28S (LC214962; 1336 bp), H3 (LC214964; 328 bp), COI (LC214959; 658 bp), and 16S (LC214957; 407 bp); and paratype (KUZ Z1807), one sequence, COI (LC214960; 658 bp).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
The obtained three COI sequences (LC214958-LC214960) were completely identical to each other. Based on the 651 bp aligned sequences, the COI uncorrected p-distance between 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. recticaudata" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="recticaudata">N. recticaudata</taxonomicName>
and the eastern North Pacific &quot; 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
&quot; was 17.1%.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="1" pageNumber="34" type="remarks">
<paragraph pageId="1" pageNumber="34">Remarks.</paragraph>
<paragraph lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="35" pageId="1" pageNumber="34">
Although the present specimens showed two characteristics in the degree of callynophore of male antenna 1 and the length of peduncular article 5 of male antenna 2, the obtained genetic data revealed that these morphological variants (specimens with strongly developed callynophore and long peduncular article 5 of antenna 2, e.g., KUZ Z1807 vs specimens with weakly developed callynophore and short peduncular article 5 of antenna 2, e.g., NSMT-Cr 25456) shared completely identical COI sequences, and thus they were identified as the same species. The character states of the well developed callynophore of antenna 1 and the elongate peduncular article 5 
<pageBreakToken pageId="2" pageNumber="35" start="start">of</pageBreakToken>
antenna 2 were observed only in males of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. recticaudata" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="recticaudata">N. recticaudata</taxonomicName>
. Males with these characteristics might be regarded as fully mature individuals.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="35">
According to the conventional classification of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Nicippe</taxonomicName>
species, this species would be identified as 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
based on the possession of the two-dentate posterior margin of urosomite 1. However, 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe recticaudata" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="recticaudata">Nicippe recticaudata</taxonomicName>
clearly differs from the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“true”">&quot;true&quot;</normalizedToken>
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
defined by 
<bibRefCitation author="Bruzelius, RM" journalOrPublisher="Kongliga Svenska Vetenskaps-Akademiens Hanglingar Ny Foeljd" pageId="3" pageNumber="36" pagination="1 - 104" title="Bidrag till kaennedomen om skandinaviens AmphipodaGammaridea." url="https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.part.28297" volume="3" year="1859">Bruzelius (1859)</bibRefCitation>
and 
<bibRefCitation author="Sars, GO" journalOrPublisher="Universitetsforlaget, Bergen" pageId="4" pageNumber="37" title="An Account of the Crustacea of Norway with Short Descriptions and Figures of All the Species." url="https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.1164" year="1895">Sars (1895)</bibRefCitation>
in the following three characteristics (character states of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
in parentheses): posterior margin of merus of pereopods 4 with 5-6 setae (more than 10); anterior margin of merus of pereopod 5 with 9-10 setae (more than 20); and telson with straight inner margin, tapering proximally (sinuous inner margin, weakly expanding proximally). Moreover, the calculated COI genetic distance (17.1%) between 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. recticaudata" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="recticaudata">N. recticaudata</taxonomicName>
specimens and the 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
sample from California (Northeastern Pacific) revealed that the new species is genetically diverged from the Californian population of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
; 3.5-4% COI distances have been proposed as the threshold for amphipod species discrimination (
<bibRefCitation author="Witt, JDS" journalOrPublisher="Molecular Ecology" pageId="4" pageNumber="37" pagination="3037 - 3082" title="DNA barcoding reveals extraordinary cryptic diversity in an amphipod genus: implications for desert spring conservation." url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.02999.x" volume="15" year="2006">Witt et al. 2006</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Rock, J" journalOrPublisher="Heredity" pageId="4" pageNumber="37" pagination="102 - 111" title="Phylogeography and environmental diversification of a highly adaptable marine amphipod Gammarusduebeni." url="https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.hdy.6800971" volume="99" year="2007">Rock et al. 2007</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Hou, Z" journalOrPublisher="Current Zoology" pageId="4" pageNumber="37" pagination="158 - 164" title="Identifying Chinese species of Gammarus (Crustacea: Amphipoda) using DNA barcoding." volume="55" year="2009">Hou et al. 2009</bibRefCitation>
). The 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
individuals inhabiting Californian waters were once reported to possess the morphological characteristics resembling those of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. recticaudata" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="recticaudata">N. recticaudata</taxonomicName>
(
<bibRefCitation author="Barnard, JL" journalOrPublisher="Pacific Naturalist" pageId="3" pageNumber="36" pagination="36 - 43" title="The common pardaliscid Amphipoda of Southern California, with a revision of the family." volume="1" year="1959">Barnard 1959</bibRefCitation>
). Contrary to their morphological similarities, therefore, the present COI data highlighted that the population from Northwestern Pacific (
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. recticaudata" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="recticaudata">N. recticaudata</taxonomicName>
), and that inhabiting Northeastern Pacific (&quot; 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
&quot; in Californian waters) are different species. In summary, the present 
<taxonomicName lsidName="tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">tumida</taxonomicName>
-like Japanese population of 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Nicippe</taxonomicName>
is considered as distinctive, and thus was described as a new species of the genus.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="35">
A 
<taxonomicName class="Malacostraca" family="Pardaliscidae" genus="Nicippe" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Nicippe" order="Amphipoda" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Nicippe</taxonomicName>
specimen identified as 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
was recorded from the East China Sea (
<bibRefCitation author="Ren, X" journalOrPublisher="Science Press, Beijing" pageId="4" pageNumber="37" title="Fauna Sinica. Invertebrata vol. 43 Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea (II)." year="2012">Ren 2012</bibRefCitation>
). However, its description as well as figures clearly shows the diagnostic characteristics of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. recticaudata" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="recticaudata">N. recticaudata</taxonomicName>
, and thus the Chinese sample in 
<bibRefCitation author="Ren, X" journalOrPublisher="Science Press, Beijing" pageId="4" pageNumber="37" title="Fauna Sinica. Invertebrata vol. 43 Crustacea: Amphipoda: Gammaridea (II)." year="2012">Ren (2012)</bibRefCitation>
definitely belongs to the present new species. As well, 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
has been recorded from around the Japanese Archipelago, e.g., from Sea of Japan and Sea of Okhotsk (
<bibRefCitation author="Gurjanova, EF" journalOrPublisher="Akademiia Nauk SSSR" pageId="3" pageNumber="36" title="Bokoplavy morej SSSR i sopredel'nykh vod (Amphipoda-Gammandea)" volumeTitle="Opredeliteli po Faune SSSR" year="1951">Gurjanova 1951</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="Bulycheva, A" journalOrPublisher="Akademiia Nauk SSSR" pageId="3" pageNumber="36" title="Morskie bloxi morej SSSR I sopredel'nyx vod (Amphipoda-Talitroidea)" volumeTitle="Opredeliteli po Faune SSSR" year="1957">Bulycheva 1957</bibRefCitation>
). Because these previous records lacked the detailed descriptions related to the diagnostic characters of 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. recticaudata" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="recticaudata">N. recticaudata</taxonomicName>
, their identities remain unclear. A world-wide systematic revision is essential to elucidate the cryptic species diversity in 
<taxonomicName genus="N." lsidName="N. tumida" pageId="2" pageNumber="35" rank="species" species="tumida">N. tumida</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>