<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280235" ID-GBIF-Dataset="87b69b39-6c55-40e9-9ead-51ab3c9799d2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120172" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280235" ModsDocID="8538" checkinTime="1252707819910" checkinUser="donat" docAuthor="Bolton, B." docDate="2000" docId="A032C5D79AB45EBC16C80372371172F1" docLanguage="en" docName="8538_stumi_malagasy.xml" docOrigin="Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 65" docSource="http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409" docTitle="Strumigenys epulo Bolton, 2000, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="680" masterDocId="814699F489404C94E11A5DF23EE15AD8" masterDocTitle="The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck." masterLastPageNumber="1028" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="679" updateTime="1645796809576" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The ant tribe Dacetini. With a revision of the Strumigenys species of the Malgasy Region by Brian L. Fisher, and a revision of the Austral epopostrumiform genera by Steven O. Shattuck.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bolton, B.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>65</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>1028</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://hdl.handle.net/10199/15409</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">8538</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">AA3AF36F-DAE3-48E6-812F-8A9934C335BE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6280235" ID-GBIF-Taxon="100120172" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6280235" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:A032C5D79AB45EBC16C80372371172F1" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A032C5D79AB45EBC16C80372371172F1" lastPageNumber="680" pageNumber="679">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="679">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155859" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys epulo Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys epulo Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="679" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="epulo">Strumigenys epulo Fisher</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
(Fig. 402)
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="679">HOLOTYPE WORKER. TL 2.4, HL 0.55, HW 0.37, CI 67, ML 0.26, MI 48, SL 0.34, SI 93, PW 0.25, AL 0.63. Characters of epulo-complex. Mandibles in full-face view with outer margins shallowly and evenly convex, the width approximately constant from the level of the proximal preapical tooth to near the base. In full-face view, upper scrobe margin narrowly concave (pinched in) immediately behind frontal lobes. Behind this, upper scrobe margin divergent and shallowly convex, not bordered by a rim or flange except for a thin lamella immediately behind frontal lobes, the eyes clearly visible. Apices of the upper scrobe margins confluent with the sides of the occipital lobes through an even curve, without an angle separating the two. Maximum diameter of eye slightly larger than maximum width of scape, with 4 - 5 ommatidia in longest row. Scape narrow and subcylindrical, shallowly and gently curved; hairs on leading edge narrow, flattened or spoon-shaped apically. Cephalic dorsum clothed with inconspicuous, curved, narrow, filiform ground-pilosity, the upper scrobe margin fringed with hairs which are the same shape and size as those on the dorsum. Upper scrobe margin with two laterally projecting flagellate hairs, one just posterior to eye, the other apicoscrobal. Cephalic dorsum with 2 pairs of standing fine, flagellate hairs close to the occipital margin and a more anteriorly situated flagellate pair. A shorter filiform hair is located at the apex of the occipital lobe. Pronotal humeral hair long, flagellate. Mesonotum with two pairs of standing hairs, a flagellate pair on the anterior margin and a filiform pair immediately behind them that curve gently toward the midline. Dorsal alitrunk without ground-pilosity. Dorsum of alitrunk in outline convex anteriorly and more or less flat posteriorly; posterior portion of mesonotum only slightly depressed below the anterior margin of propodeum. Anterior mesonotum with a narrow flange above the mesothoracic spiracle. Propodeal tooth broadly triangular and directed posteriorly, without a distinct lamella on declivity. Dorsal surfaces of alitrunk, petiole node and postpetiole disc more or less smooth and shiny, declivity of promesonotum with fine punctures which appear almost effaced. Sides of alitrunk smooth.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="680">In dorsal view petiole node longer than broad, dorsolateral margin of peduncle with a lamellate flange that extends to the petiolar disc. In profile the petiole with a well developed ventral spongiform curtain that is deeper than the peduncle of the petiole. In dorsal view disc of postpetiole completely surrounded by spongiform tissue. Basigastral costulae very short, more or less restricted to limbus. Dorsal surfaces of petiole, postpetiole and gaster with filiform and flagellate hairs. Colour brownish yellow.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="680">PARATYPE WORKERS. TL 2.2 - 2.4, HL 0.51 - 0.56, HW 0.35 - 0.38, CI 67 - 71, ML 0.26 - 0.28, MI 46 - 53, SL 0.31 - 34, SI 85 - 90, PW 0.22 - 0.25, AL 0.57 - 0.64 (8 measured). As holotype.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="680">Holotype worker, Madagascar: 6.3 km. S Ambanizana, Andranobe, 15 Â° 41 ' S, 49 Â° 57 ' E, 25 m., 14. xi. 1993, sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood), rainforest, # 886 (10) - 4 (B. L. Fisher) (MCZ).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="680">Paratypes. 8 workers and 1 queen (dealate) with same data as holotype but coded (12) - 12, (41) - 13 (BMNH, SAM).</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="680">NON-PARATYPIC MATERIAL EXAMINED. Madagascar: 5.3 km. SSE Ambanizana, Andranobe, 425 m. (B. L. Fisher); 19 km. SSE Maroantsetra, 350 m. (P. S. Vtxrd).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="680">Measurements of this material extend the range shown by the type-series: HL 0.52 - 0.59, HW 0.35 - 0.39, CI 65 - 70, ML 0.26 - 0.32, MI 50 - 54, SL 0.33 - 0.36, SI 90 - 94 (6 measured). The material for 19 km. SSE Maroantsetra differs from the type-material by having additional pairs of short filiform hairs on the posterior half of the cephalic dorsum.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageNumber="680">
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:155859" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Strumigenys epulo Fisher" lsidName-HNS="Strumigenys epulo Fisher" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="680" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="epulo">S. epulo</taxonomicName>
is easily distinguished from other species in the 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Strumigenys" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="680" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="scotti-group">scotti-group</taxonomicName>
by the presence of flagellate hairs on the cephalic dorsum, pronotal humerus and anterior margin of mesonotum. The mostly smooth and shiny alitrunk dorsum, petiole and postpetiole also help distinguish this species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>