<document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5088410" ID-ISSN="1175­5334" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5088410" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:71226742-A1B8-4878-AAA2-773F710F98A7" approvalRequired="32" approvalRequired_for_originalDoi="1" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="1" approvalRequired_for_treatments="30" checkinTime="1625852368432" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="KNEBELSBERGER, THOMAS &amp; MILLER, MICHAEL A." docDate="2007" docId="03DC87B0FFEEFF9AFF5D3E9AFCE08608" docLanguage="en" docName="zt01522p068.pdf.imf" docOrigin="Zootaxa 1522 (1)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.1522.1.1" docStyle="DocumentStyle:C4791ACFF01C5C140D2C1A203DB3C9B0.2:Zootaxa.2007-2008.monograph" docStyleId="C4791ACFF01C5C140D2C1A203DB3C9B0" docStyleName="Zootaxa.2007-2008.monograph" docStyleVersion="2" docTitle="Phyllodromica iberica Published 2007, spec. nov." docType="treatment" docUuid="71226742-A1B8-4878-AAA2-773F710F98A7" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="14" masterDocId="FFE5FFC8FFE3FF97FFCA3F3FFF9D831F" masterDocTitle="Revision and phylogeny of the subaptera-group of Phyllodromica (Blattoptera: Blattellidae: Ectobiinae), including a parthenogenetic species and the evaluation of COI sequences for species identification (DNA barcoding)" masterLastPageNumber="68" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" updateTime="1625863838283" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Revision and phylogeny of the subaptera-group of Phyllodromica (Blattoptera: Blattellidae: Ectobiinae), including a parthenogenetic species and the evaluation of COI sequences for species identification (DNA barcoding)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>KNEBELSBERGER, THOMAS</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>MILLER, MICHAEL A.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Zootaxa</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2007</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2007-07-09</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>1522</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>68</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.1522.1.1</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.11646/zootaxa.1522.1.1</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1175­5334</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5087760</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">71CB20C3-57F1-46E0-AA10-58B9E64A774D</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5088410" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5088410" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:71226742-A1B8-4878-AAA2-773F710F98A7" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03DC87B0FFEEFF9AFF5D3E9AFCE08608" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<subSubSection box="[151,553,421,447]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1148,421,482]" box="[151,553,421,447]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<heading bold="true" box="[151,553,421,447]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" reason="1">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,553,421,447]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<taxonomicName authority="Published, 2007" authorityName="Published" authorityYear="2007" box="[151,419,421,447]" class="Insecta" family="Ectobiidae" genus="Phyllodromica" kingdom="Animalia" order="Blattodea" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="iberica" status="spec. nov.">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,419,421,447]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Phyllodromica iberica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[433,553,421,447]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" rank="species">spec. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</emphasis>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1148,421,482]" box="[151,1148,456,482]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
(
<figureCitation box="[159,299,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 1" captionStartId="28.[151,255,1780,1804]" captionTargetBox="[264,1323,187,1725]" captionTargetId="figure-96@28.[264,1323,187,1725]" captionTargetPageId="28" captionText="FIGURE 1. A–C P. iberica morph 1, habitus. (A) Male in dorsal view; (B) female in dorsal and (C) ventral view. D Oothek of P. quadracantha (lateral view). Abbreviations: a antenna, c cercus, fl coxa of foreleg, h head, hl coxa of hindleg, mes mesonotum, met metanotum, ml coxa of midleg, pm palpus maxillaris, pro pronotum, sub subgenital plate, T2–T10 tergites 2–10, tm tegmen. Same scale in A and B. Localities: (A–C) Sp 449a, (D) Sp 500." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087764" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087764/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Figs 1 A–C</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[310,381,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 3" captionStartId="30.[151,255,1620,1644]" captionTargetBox="[264,1323,194,1565]" captionTargetId="figure-193@30.[264,1323,194,1580]" captionTargetPageId="30" captionText="FIGURE 3. Phyllodromica iberica morph 1, male (holotype). A Thoracal nota. B–F Abdominal tergites 5–9. (B) Tergite 5 and (C) tergite 6 with membranous glands in the lateral region of the anterior margin of tergites (black arrows); (D) tergite 7, white arrow heads point to the shallow pouches appearing as crescent–shaped black shadows; (E) tergite 8; (F) tergite 9 on glass rod. G Terminalia with tergite 10 (sa), cerci and paraprocts. H Hook of left phallomere with the posterior end on the top. I Subgenital plate with remaining genital sclerites (without hook). Abbreviations: ap anterior process, bf bristle field, c cercus, cm central mound, cp conelike process, ll lateral lobe, m mound, mes mesonotum, met metanotum, ml median lobe, mp medio-anterior process, pml posterior median lobe, pro pronotum, r ridge between bristle fields, rp right paraproct, sa supraanal plate, se sinusoidal edge, sp shallow pits, tm tegmen, tr transversal ridge, tt transversal trough. Same scale for (B, C, G) and (D, E, H). Identification: Sp 292b/M3 (holotype)." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087768" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087768/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">3 A–I</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[393,463,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 4" captionStartId="31.[151,255,1624,1648]" captionTargetBox="[269,1318,199,1559]" captionTargetId="figure-162@31.[264,1323,194,1583]" captionTargetPageId="31" captionText="FIGURE 4. Phyllodromica iberica morph 1, male, SEM pictures of tergal glandular structures. A–C, G Tergite 7. (A) Latero-frontal view from slightly above, anterior wall of trough slightly hollowed out anteriorly (white arrows); (B) lateral view of the glandular region from slightly above; (C) glandular region in dorsal view; (G) bristles of bristle field. D– F, H, I Tergite 8. (D) Dorsal view of the whole tergite, median emargination in the distribution of the bristles (white arrow heads); (E) latero-frontal view from slightly above; (F) dorsal view of the conelike process; (H) porous surface of the central mound; (I) soft villi on the surface of the conelike process. Abbreviations: bf bristle field, cm central mound, cp conelike process, m mound, r ridge, se sinusoidal edge, sp shallow pit, tt transversal trough. Identification: (A–C, E– I) Sp 270a/M4, (D) Sp 85/11." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087770" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087770/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">4 A–I</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[474,545,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 5" captionStartId="32.[151,255,1606,1630]" captionTargetBox="[264,1323,184,1555]" captionTargetId="figure-149@32.[264,1323,184,1565]" captionTargetPageId="32" captionText="FIGURE 5. Phyllodromica iberica morph 1, A–E, male. (A) Tergite 7 and (B) tergite 8 of a male specimen differing from the holotype in its colouration; (C) membrane glands of the left lateral region on the anterior border of tergite 6; (D) right paraproct; (E) distal end of tibia of the right mid leg (bearing 5 distal spines) in posterior view. F–I, female. (F, H) Different colour pattern of pronotum; (G, I) tergite 5. Abbreviations: mg membrane glands, mp medio-anterior process of right paraproct, rp right paraproct, sp spinelike process of right paraproct, tar tarsus, tib tibia. Same scale for (C, D) and (F–I). Identification: (A, B) Sp 330/3, (C, D) Sp 292b/M3 (holotype), (E) Sp 510/M1, (F, G) Sp 292b/W1, (H, I) Sp 292b/W2." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087772" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087772/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">5 A–I</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[557,627,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 6" captionStartId="33.[151,255,1614,1638]" captionTargetBox="[264,1323,194,1564]" captionTargetId="figure-170@33.[264,1323,194,1573]" captionTargetPageId="33" captionText="FIGURE 6. Phyllodromica iberica morph 2, male. A Thoracal nota. B–F Abdominal tergites 5–9. (B) Tergite 5; (C) tergite 6 with a narrow transversal torus (white arrow heads) bearing bristles (white spots) in extraordinary density; (D) tergite 7, white arrow heads point to the shallow pouches appearing as crescent–shaped black shadows; (E) tergite 8; (F) tergite 9 on glass rod. G Terminalia with tergite 10 (sa), cerci and paraprocts. H Hook of left phallomere with the posterior end on the top. I Subgenital plate with remaining genital sclerites (without hook). Abbreviations: ap anterior process, bf bristle field cm central mound, cp conelike process, m mound, ml median lobe, mp medio-anterior process of right paraproct, r ridge between bristle fields, rp right paraproct, sa supraanal plate, se sinusoidal edge, sp shallow pit, tt transversal trough. Same scale for (B, C, G) and (D, E, H). Identification: Sp 267c/M2." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087774" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087774/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">6 A–I</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[639,721,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 7" captionStartId="34.[151,255,1603,1627]" captionTargetBox="[269,1318,186,1545]" captionTargetId="figure-215@34.[264,1323,180,1565]" captionTargetPageId="34" captionText="FIGURE 7. Phyllodromica iberica morph 2, male, SEM pictures of tergite 6 and the tergal glandular structures. A–C Tergite 6. (A) Latero-frontal view from slightly above, white arrows point to two shallow longitudinal depressions posteriorly of the torus (to); (B) dorsal view of the whole tergite; (C) transversal torus with bristles (between arrows) of the right half of the tergite. As a result of the preparation procedure for SEM the posterior margin of the tergite and its emargination in the middle (in B) appear narrower than under natural conditions. D, E Tergite 7. (D) Lateral view of tergite from slightly above; (E) glandular region in dorsal view. F–H Tergite 8. (F) Dorsal view of the whole tergite with median emargination in the distribution of the bristles (white arrow heads); (G) latero-frontal view from slightly above; (H) lateral view of the anterior part of the tergite. Abbreviations: bf bristle field, cm central mound, cp conelike process, m mound, se sinusoidal edge, sp shallow pit, to transversal torus, tr transversal ridge, tt transversal trough. Same scale for (A, B) and (D, F, G). Identification: (A–C) Sp 267b/M6, (D–H) Sp 267b/M4." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087776" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087776/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">7 A–H</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[732,803,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 8" captionStartId="35.[151,255,1618,1642]" captionTargetBox="[264,1323,194,1565]" captionTargetId="figure-136@35.[264,1323,194,1578]" captionTargetPageId="35" captionText="FIGURE 8. A–E Phyllodromica iberica morph 2, male. (A–D) Different colour patterns of tergite 6; (E) helmet sclerite. F, G Phyllodromica iberica morph 2, female. (F) Thoracal nota; (G) abdominal tergite 5. H Right front leg of Phyllodromica iberica morph 1, male in frontal view. I Right front leg of Phyllodromica quadracantha, male in frontal view. Abbreviations: fr “frontal” part of helmet sclerite, cox coxa, fem femur, hs helmet sclerite re “rear” of helmet sclerite, tib tibia, tm tegmen. Same scale for (A–D), (F, G) and (H, I). Identification: (A) Sp 266/2, (B) Sp 365/3, (C) Sp 365a/M14, (D) Sp 365a/M8, (E) Sp 267c/M1, (F, G) Sp 267c/W2, (H) Sp 510/M11, (I) Sp 203d/M1 (holotype).." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087778" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087778/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">8 A–I</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[815,885,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 9" captionStartId="36.[151,255,1623,1647]" captionTargetBox="[264,1323,194,1565]" captionTargetId="figure-163@36.[264,1323,194,1585]" captionTargetPageId="36" captionText="FIGURE 9. Phyllodromica iberica morph 3, male. A Thoracal nota. B–F Abdominal tergites 5–9. (B) Tergite 5; (C) tergite 6; (D) tergite 7 and (E) tergite 8 with glandular structures in the anterior part of the tergites; (F) tergite 9. G Terminalia with tergite 10 (sa), cerci and paraprocts. H Hook of left phallomere with the posterior end on the top. I Subgenital plate with remaining genital sclerites (without hook). Abbreviations: a apodemes of subgenital plate, ap anterior process, bf bristle field, c cercus, cl claw of hook, cs cleft sclerite, ea endophallic apodeme, hs helmet sclerite, ml median lobe, rp right paraproct, R3 sclerite of the right phallomere, s stylus, sa supraanal plate, sh shaft, st stalk, sub subgenital plate, tt transversal trough, v velum. Same scale for (B, C, G) and (D, E, H). Identification: Sp 380/M2." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087782" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087782/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">9 A–I</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[897,993,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 10" captionStartId="37.[151,255,1611,1635]" captionTargetBox="[295,1292,200,1559]" captionTargetId="figure-203@37.[264,1323,194,1573]" captionTargetPageId="37" captionText="FIGURE 10. Phyllodromica iberica morph 3. A–F male, SEM pictures of different tergal glandular structures in dorsal view. (A, B), (E, F) Two different forms of glandular structures of tergites 7 and 8 of two specimens; white arrow heads in A point to the bulge-like cuticule limitations of the antero-lateral borders of the bristle fields which is absent in the other form (white arrow heads in E); on tergite 8 bristles are also present in the central region of the tergite (white arrow heads in B, F); (C, D) Medio-anterior part of tergite 8 of two further specimens showing variously developed conelike processes. The unnatural shape of the tergite in B (compared with F) is due to an mounting artefact. G, H female. (G) Thoracal nota; (H) abdominal tergite 5. Abbreviations: a artificial structures (originated during SEM preparation procedure), bf bristle field, cp conelike process, r ridge between bristle fields, tt transversal trough. Same scale for (A, E), (B, F) and (C, D). Identification: (A, B) Sp 388/M1, (E, F) Sp 512/M1, (C) Sp 186/M7, (D) Sp 361/M2, (G, H) Sp 380/W1." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087784" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087784/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">10 A–H</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[1005,1097,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 11" captionStartId="38.[151,255,1615,1639]" captionTargetBox="[264,1323,194,1565]" captionTargetId="figure-190@38.[264,1323,194,1578]" captionTargetPageId="38" captionText="FIGURE 11. Phyllodromica iberica morph 3, male. A Tergite 8; B-E Tergite 6; in C, enlargement of the left half of the tergite depicted in B with narrow transversal torus-like structure (between white arrows) bearing bristles (white spots) in enhanced density; in D, lack of torus-like structure, only bristles (white spots) in enhanced density. D, E Tergite 6, two examples of different tergite colouration. F–H Abdominal tergites 6–8 of one specimen. (F) Tergite 6; (G) tergite 7, bristle fields antero-lateral without bulge-like cuticule limitations (white arrows); (H) tergite 8, conelike process nearly completely missing. I–L Abdominal tergites 6–8 of one specimen. (I) Tergite 6; (K) tergite 7, white arrows point to the shallow pouches appearing as crescent–shaped black shadows; (L) tergite 8, well developed conelike process. Same scale for (A, G, H, K, L) and (B, D, E, F, I). Identification: (A) Sp 395/M1, (B, C) Sp 148b/M1, (D) Sp 460/M1, (E) Sp 387a/M1, (F, G, H) Sp 270a/M1, (I, K, L) Sp 335/5." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087788" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087788/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">11 A–L</figureCitation>
, 
<figureCitation box="[1109,1139,456,482]" captionStart="FIGURE 17" captionStartId="44.[151,255,1798,1822]" captionTargetBox="[294,1267,311,1652]" captionTargetId="figure-154@44.[294,1353,198,1785]" captionTargetPageId="44" captionText="FIGURE 17. Distribution of the bisexual species of the subaptera-group: Phyllodromica iberica morph 1, 2 and 3, and P. quadracantha; these species only occur on the Iberian Peninsula. In cases where two different symbols partly overlap, two P. iberica morphs are found at the same locality; in one case all three morphs occur together (Fig. 15, Sp 510 ca. 1° W, 40° N). P. iberica morph 3 symbols labeled with a “+” (Fig. 15, Sp 335) or an “ ” (Fig. 15, Sp 186, 270, 469 and 512) indicate the presence of morphological variations. At some localities no males have been found (“sad face” symbol) but females with spermathecae containing sperms and/or with oothecae containing male and female offspring. Both facts indicate the presence of a bisexual species of unknown specifity." figureDoi="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5087798" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5087798/files/figure.png" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">17</figureCitation>
)
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1017,530,553]" box="[151,1017,530,553]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<taxonomicName box="[151,422,530,553]" class="Insecta" family="Ectobiidae" genus="Phyllodromica" kingdom="Animalia" order="Blattodea" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="subaptera">
<emphasis box="[151,422,530,553]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Phyllodromica subaptera</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, morph #1, #2 and #3. —Knebelsberger &amp; Bohn, 2003.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,596,1303]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<materialsCitation collectingDate="2003-04-21" collectionCode="T, ZSM" collectorName="Piedrabuena &amp; W Ciudad Real" country="Spain" elevation="700" location="Los Pozuelos de Calatrava" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="1" specimenCount-male="1" typeStatus="holotype">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[151,265,597,623]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<typeStatus box="[151,265,597,623]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Holotype</typeStatus>
</emphasis>
: 
<specimenCount box="[280,300,596,616]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="male">♂</specimenCount>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[314,383,597,623]" name="Spain" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Spain</collectingCountry>
, Prov. Ciudad Real, btw. 
<location LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03DC87B0FFEEFF9AFF5D3E9AFCE08608:8EAA607DFFEEFF9AFD6D3D6AFC408170" box="[679,989,597,623]" country="Spain" name="Los Pozuelos de Calatrava" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Los Pozuelos de Calatrava</location>
&amp; 
<collectorName box="[1026,1170,597,623]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Piedrabuena</collectorName>
(
<collectorName box="[1186,1372,597,623]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">W Ciudad Real</collectorName>
), 
<quantity metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="7.0" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" unit="m" value="700.0">
<elevation metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="7.0" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" unit="m" value="700.0">700 m</elevation>
</quantity>
, 
<date box="[188,321,637,663]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="2003-04-21">
<collectingDate box="[188,321,637,663]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" value="2003-04-21">21.IV.2003</collectingDate>
</date>
, leg. 
<collectionCode box="[383,402,637,663]" name="Tavera, Department of Geology and Geophysics" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">T</collectionCode>
. Knebelsberger (on two slides, Sp 292b/M3); deposited in 
<collectionCode box="[1091,1155,637,663]" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/4b7r-7sec" name="Bavarian State Collection of Zoology" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="Museum">ZSM</collectionCode>
.
</materialsCitation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,596,1303]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<materialsCitation collectingDate="2003-04-21" collectionCode="T, ZSM" collectorName="Piedrabuena &amp; W Ciudad Real" country="Spain" elevation="700" location="Los Pozuelos de Calatrava" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCount="5" specimenCount-male="5" typeStatus="paratype">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[198,323,677,703]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<typeStatus box="[198,323,677,703]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Paratypes</typeStatus>
</emphasis>
: 
<specimenCount box="[341,385,676,703]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="male">5 ♂</specimenCount>
, same data as holotype. Sp 292b/M1 (frozen DNA; parts of body in 98 % ethanol); Sp 292b/M2 (frozen DNA; parts of body in 98 % ethanol); Sp 292b/M4 (on two slides); Sp 292b/M5 (on two slides), Sp 292b/M6 (on two slides)
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,596,1303]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<materialsCitation accessionNumber="AM600686, AM600685" collectionCode="DNATAX, ZSM, AM, T" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" specimenCode="DNATAX02859, DNATAX02860" specimenCount="3" typeStatus="paratype">
<typeStatus box="[198,300,797,823]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Paratype</typeStatus>
DNA and associated parts of body are stored in the 
<collectionCode box="[924,1042,797,823]" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/cnpp-emg5" name="DNA-TAX" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">DNATAX</collectionCode>
collection of 
<collectionCode box="[1208,1268,797,823]" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/4b7r-7sec" name="Bavarian State Collection of Zoology" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="Museum">ZSM</collectionCode>
under storage numbers 
<specimenCode box="[270,461,837,863]" collectionCode="DNATAX" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/cnpp-emg5" name="DNA-TAX" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">DNATAX02859</specimenCode>
(
<typeStatus box="[488,592,837,863]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Paratype</typeStatus>
Sp 292b/M2) and 
<specimenCode box="[857,1049,837,863]" collectionCode="DNATAX" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/cnpp-emg5" name="DNA-TAX" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">DNATAX02860</specimenCode>
(
<typeStatus box="[1075,1179,837,863]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Paratype</typeStatus>
Sp 292b/M1). The sequences were submitted to GenBank under the accession numbers: 
<accessionNumber box="[1021,1156,877,903]" httpUri="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/AM600686" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<collectionCode box="[1021,1068,877,903]" country="Australia" name="Australian Museum" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="Museum">AM</collectionCode>
600686
</accessionNumber>
(
<specimenCode box="[1177,1373,877,903]" collectionCode="DNATAX" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/cnpp-emg5" name="DNA-TAX" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">DNATAX02859</specimenCode>
) and 
<accessionNumber box="[151,286,917,943]" httpUri="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/AM600685" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<collectionCode box="[151,198,917,943]" country="Australia" name="Australian Museum" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="Museum">AM</collectionCode>
600685
</accessionNumber>
(
<specimenCode box="[301,500,917,943]" collectionCode="DNATAX" country="Germany" httpUri="http://grbio.org/cool/cnpp-emg5" name="DNA-TAX" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">DNATAX02860</specimenCode>
). The remaining 
<specimenCount box="[697,830,917,943]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="generic" typeStatus="paratypes">3 paratypes</specimenCount>
(Sp 292b/M4-6) are deposited in the private collection of 
<collectionCode box="[235,254,957,983]" name="Tavera, Department of Geology and Geophysics" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">T</collectionCode>
. Knebelsberger
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,596,1303]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[198,333,997,1023]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Etymology</emphasis>
: The name of the species refers to its distribution covering a large area of the Iberian peninsula.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="13" pageNumber="14" type="discussion">
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,596,1303]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[198,312,1077,1103]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">Remarks</emphasis>
: Within 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Published" authorityYear="2007" box="[420,534,1077,1102]" class="Insecta" family="Ectobiidae" genus="Phyllodromica" kingdom="Animalia" order="Blattodea" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="iberica">
<emphasis box="[420,534,1077,1102]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">P. iberica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
three morphotypes (morphs) can be distinguished and will be described in detail. The 
<typeStatus box="[285,387,1117,1143]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">holotype</typeStatus>
and 
<typeStatus box="[445,546,1117,1143]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">paratype</typeStatus>
specimens of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Published" authorityYear="2007" box="[716,828,1117,1142]" class="Insecta" family="Ectobiidae" genus="Phyllodromica" kingdom="Animalia" order="Blattodea" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="iberica">
<emphasis box="[716,828,1117,1142]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">P. iberica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
were selected from morph #1 which has the widest distribution.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="13.[151,1436,596,1303]" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">
The females of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Published" authorityYear="2007" box="[386,499,1197,1222]" class="Insecta" family="Ectobiidae" genus="Phyllodromica" kingdom="Animalia" order="Blattodea" pageId="13" pageNumber="14" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="iberica">
<emphasis box="[386,499,1197,1222]" italics="true" pageId="13" pageNumber="14">P. iberica</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
cannot be distinguished by external features. At the localities Po 19, 24; Sp 4, 5a, 14a, 88, 89, 90, 91, 94, a, 108, 112, 116, 136, 170, 333, 384 and 393 bisexual females were found, but not the appertaining males; their specificity remains to be clarified.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>