<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/asp.80.e71943" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b37641da-3532-4e85-9cac-bde7dfde11a2" ID-GBIF-Taxon="193873985" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1864-8312-80-99" ID-Pensoft-UUID="96FF9F9F633C5CD3ABD59188D27558EA" ID-ZooBank="F730F684CC13432B848089D91999F601" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:NomEnClAturAlACts/A26D6FDD-D726-4A41-B553-FE5F086B205D" ModsDocID="1864-8312-80-99" checkinTime="1646454833799" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Lepeco, Anderson &amp; Goncalves, Rodrigo Barbosa" docDate="2022" docId="968498ABE2EC55A08754EFE6BF79B0D2" docLanguage="en" docName="ArthropodSystPhyl 80: 99-115" docOrigin="Arthropod Systematics &amp; amp; Phylogeny 80" docPubDate="2022-03-04" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/asp.80.e71943" docTitle="Augochlora (Augochlora) intermedia Lepeco &amp; Gonçalves 2022, sp. nov." docType="treatment" docVersion="3" id="96FF9F9F633C5CD3ABD59188D27558EA" lastPageNumber="99" masterDocId="96FF9F9F633C5CD3ABD59188D27558EA" masterDocTitle="Bayesian and parsimony phylogeny of Augochlora bees (Hymenoptera: Apoidea) based on morphology: insights for their biogeography and natural history" masterLastPageNumber="115" masterPageNumber="99" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" updateTime="1646459041732" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bayesian and parsimony phylogeny of Augochlora bees (Hymenoptera: Apoidea) based on morphology: insights for their biogeography and natural history</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Lepeco, Anderson</mods:namePart>
<mods:nameIdentifier type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7467-5244</mods:nameIdentifier>
<mods:affiliation>Departamento de Zoologia, Universidade Federal do Parana, Cx. Postal 19020, 81531 - 980, Curitiba, PR, Brazil</mods:affiliation>
<mods:nameIdentifier type="email">al.lepeco@gmail.com</mods:nameIdentifier>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Goncalves, Rodrigo Barbosa</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>Departamento de Zoologia, Universidade Federal do Parana, Cx. Postal 19020, 81531 - 980, Curitiba, PR, Brazil</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Arthropod Systematics &amp; amp; Phylogeny</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2022</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2022-03-04</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>80</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>99</mods:start>
<mods:end>115</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/asp.80.e71943</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/asp.80.e71943</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1864-8312-80-99</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">F730F684CC13432B848089D91999F601</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-UUID">96FF9F9F633C5CD3ABD59188D27558EA</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="193873985" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:NomEnClAturAlACts/A26D6FDD-D726-4A41-B553-FE5F086B205D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/968498ABE2EC55A08754EFE6BF79B0D2" lastPageNumber="99" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
3.2.1. 
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/NomenclaturalActs/A26D6FDD-D726-4A41-B553-FE5F086B205D" authority="Lepeco &amp; Gonçalves, 2022" authorityName="Lepeco &amp; Gonçalves" authorityYear="2022" class="Insecta" family="Apoidea" genus="Augochlora" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Augochlora (Augochlora) intermedia" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="intermedia" status="sp. nov." subGenus="Augochlora">Augochlora (Augochlora) intermedia</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="99">sp. nov.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
<figureCitation captionStart="Figure 3" captionStartId="F3" captionText="Figure 3. Augochlora intermedia sp. nov. Female (holotype): A) frontal view of head, B) anterior view of head, C) dorsal view of mesosoma and metasoma; male (paratype): D) frontal view of head; E) dorsal view of mesosoma and metasoma. Scale bar: 1.0 mm, all at same scale." figureDoi="10.3897/asp.80.e71943.figure3" httpUri="https://binary.pensoft.net/fig/653665" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Figure 3A-E</figureCitation>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
Holotype female (DZUP), &quot; DZUP\568723&quot; &quot;LIMA San 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Bartolomé">Bartolome</normalizedToken>
\ 26.VII.75\ Coll: R. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="García”">Garcia&quot;</normalizedToken>
&quot;RG: 537&quot;. Paratypes (DZUP), male &quot; DZUP\568724&quot; &quot;LIMA San 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Bartolomé">Bartolome</normalizedToken>
\ 17.VII.75\ Coll: R. 
<normalizedToken originalValue="García”">Garcia&quot;</normalizedToken>
&quot;RG: 537&quot;; female &quot; DZUP\568725&quot; &quot;Lima (Peru)\ 1.6.1939\ leg. Weyrauch&quot; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“WKW\3773”">&quot;WKW\3773&quot;</normalizedToken>
; one female and two males pinned together &quot; DZUP\568726&quot; &quot;LIMA, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Perú">Peru</normalizedToken>
\ I-1949\ P. Aguilar&quot; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“FC.64A”">&quot;FC.64A&quot;</normalizedToken>
; female &quot; DZUP\568727&quot; &quot;LIMA, 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Perú">Peru</normalizedToken>
\ I-1949\ P. Aguilar L.&quot; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="“FC-64A”">&quot;FC-64A&quot;</normalizedToken>
; female &quot; DZUP\568728&quot; &quot;No. 606-35\ Hda. Nanipol\ Jequetepeque\ 21-XII-1934&quot; &quot;J. Lamas coll.&quot;; (RPSP) one female &quot; RPSP\ 15.2461&quot; &quot;Peru, Cajamarca, San\ Miguel, Florida, 06 51S\ 79 07 288W 20.vi.2008\ on 
<taxonomicName class="Magnoliopsida" family="Loasaceae" genus="Nasa" kingdom="Plantae" lsidName="Nasa olmosiana" order="Cornales" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Tracheophyta" rank="species" species="olmosiana">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Nasa olmosiana</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
&quot;.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
Females of the new species can be readily distinguished from most other 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Smith" authorityYear="1853" class="Insecta" family="Apoidea" genus="Augochlora" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Augochlora" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Augochlora</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
by the distinctly contiguous coarse punctuation, especially on tergal marginal area, in combination with the mandible with a small preapical tooth produced far from mandibular apex. In addition, females can be separated from other 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Smith" authorityYear="1853" class="Insecta" family="Apoidea" genus="Augochlora" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Augochlora" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Augochlora</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
s. str. species by the T5 pseudo-pygidial area covered by scale-like appressed setae (similarly with 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Eickwort" authorityYear="1969" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Oxystoglossella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxystoglossella" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Oxystoglossella</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species). From 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Eickwort" authorityYear="1969" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Oxystoglossella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxystoglossella" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Oxystoglossella</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species it can be separated by the darkened basal area of labrum and hind coxa angulate on ventral transition between anterior and posterior surfaces. Males are diagnosed by the combination of: F1 as long as F2; hind basitarsus black; metapostnotum shorter than scutellum; T1 with reduced impunctate area medially adjacent to apical dark band (similarly with 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Eickwort" authorityYear="1969" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Oxystoglossella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxystoglossella" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Oxystoglossella</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species); T2 with premarginal setae almost reaching apex on sublateral surfaces (similarly with 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Eickwort" authorityYear="1969" class="Insecta" family="Halictidae" genus="Oxystoglossella" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oxystoglossella" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Oxystoglossella</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
species); and outer lobe of gonostylus ventral process with setae shorter than inner lobe.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Description. Holotype Female.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Measurements (in mm).</emphasis>
Distance between eye notches: 1.8; head length: 2.2; clypeus width: 0.6; clypeus length: 0.5; clypeoantennal distance: 0.4; clypeus ocellar distance: 1.3; intertegular distance: 1.6; T1 width: 2.1; T2 width: 2.3; body length: 8. - 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Head</emphasis>
. Labrum basal surface black; basal elevation transverse. Mandible mostly black, apex brown; medial portion minimum width about 0.7x basal width; pre-apical tooth small and rounded, relatively distant from apical tooth apex; distal part of aductor ridge not swollen, but conspicuous in frontal view. Clypeus mostly green with golden reflection, apical black band as long as OD; mostly densely punctate (I&lt;PD), punctures large, medially with an impunctate longitudinal path, imbricate among punctures. Supraclypeal area green with golden reflection; mostly contiguously punctate, sparser towards clypeus, imbricate among punctures. Lower paraocular area green with golden reflection; contiguously punctate; long setae (3 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. Antennae: mostly black, flagellum ventrally brownish. Frons green with golden reflection; contiguously punctate; not protuberant above antennal sockets. Preoccipital carina not enlarged near post-gena. Gena with golden reflection. Post-gena darkened; microreticulate, some scattered weak punctures; setae length &lt;3 OD. Hypostomal carina not projected anteriorly. - 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Mesosoma</emphasis>
. Pronotum dorsolateral angle obtuse, not strongly projected. Fore leg: entirely dark brown, longer setae length = 3 OD. Mesoscutum green; mostly contiguously punctate, anterior portion crowded punctate to imbricate; with long dark setae (2 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. Scutellum green; without strong medial furrow; contiguously punctate; with long dark setae (3 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. Mesepisternum green with golden reflection; mostly contiguously punctate, anterior portion crowded punctate; with long setae (3 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. Mid leg: entirely dark brown, longer setae length = 3 OD; trochanter ventral margin straight; femur posterior surface flat; mesofemoral brush yellowish. Tegula dark brown. Metanotum longer setae length = 2 OD. Metepisternum green; contiguously punctate, becoming crowded to rugose above metapleural pit. Hind leg: mostly dark brown, except for green anterior surface of coxa; transition between anterior and posterior surfaces of coxa ventrally making a strong angulation; without black setae on tibia and basitarsus. Metapostnotum green; as long as 0.7x scutellum length; with almost straight radiating carinae, slightly imbricate in between. Propodeum green with golden reflection; with long setae (3 OD) intermixed with tiny setae; posterior surface mostly imbricate with some scattered distinct punctures, lateral surfaces crowded to contiguously punctate near metepisternum. - 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Metasoma</emphasis>
. T1 anterior surface densely punctate (I = 0.5 PD), loosely imbricate among punctures; with long setae (2 OD) intermixed with tiny decumbent setae. T1 dorsal surface contiguously punctate, mostly with small and deep punctures, larger punctures on lateral surfaces; mostly green, apical black band shorter than OD; apex not inflexed. T2 green; densely punctate (I = 0.5 PD), mostly with small and deep punctures, smooth in between, larger punctures on lateral surfaces; marginal zone with punctate portion 4x longer than apical brown band on sublateral surfaces. T3 green; densely punctate (I = 0.5 PD), loosely imbricate in between; apex of tiny setae surpassing apex of T3 sublaterally. T4 green; weakly punctate, imbricate in between. T5 light brown; pseudo-pygidial area medially without scale-like decumbent setae, colliculate. Pygidial plate dark brown, apex rounded. S1 brown; very slightly prominent medially, without distinct projection; long setae (&lt;5 OD) medially, margin with tiny decumbent setae. S2 brown; sparsely punctate, microreticulate in between; long setae (&lt;4 OD) on posterior half. S3-5 as S2. S6 dark brown.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Description. Paratype male.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Measurements (in mm).</emphasis>
Distance between eye notches: 1.6; head length: 2.1; clypeus width: 0.6; clypeus length: 0.5; clypeoantennal distance: 0.4; clypeocellar distance: 1.2; intertegular distance: 1.3; T1 width: 1.4; T2 width: 1.5; scape length: 0.6; body length: 9. - 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Head</emphasis>
. Labrum basal surface light yellowish. Mandible dark brown. Clypeus mostly green with golden reflection, apex yellowish, apical border exposed, yellowish; densely punctate, I = 0.5 PD, punctures large and shallow, loosely imbricate in between. Supraclypeal area green with golden reflection; mostly contiguously punctate, sparser towards clypeus, loosely imbricate among punctures. Paraocular area green with golden reflection; densely punctate, I &lt;0.5 PD, smooth in between; long setae (2 OD) and short setae intermixed. Antennae: mostly black, flagellum ventrally yellowish; F1 as long as F2; F3 as long as wide; remaining flagellomeres progressively longer. Frons mostly green, with golden and blue iridescences intermixed; mostly contiguously punctate, crowded punctate near mid ocellus. Gena green with golden reflection. Post-gena darkened, with golden reflections; loosely imbricate, some scattered weak punctures; sparse long setae (&lt;4 OD). - 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Mesosoma.</emphasis>
Pronotum dorsolateral angle obtuse, not strongly projected. Fore leg: mostly brown, except for green coxae anteriorly and femur outer surface; trochanter and femur not strongly swollen. Mesoscutum green; densely punctate (I = 0.5 PD), mostly loosely imbricate in between, anteriorly microrreticulate among punctures; with long dark setae (2 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. Scutellum green with golden reflection; medial furrow inconspicuous; densely punctate (I &lt;0.5 PD), punctures coarse; with long dark setae (2 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. Mesepisternum green with golden reflection; mostly densely punctate (I &lt;0.5 PD), anterior portion crowded punctate; with long setae (3 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. Mid leg: coxa mostly dark brown, except for green femur posterior surface; longer setae length = 2 OD; femur not strongly swollen. Tegula dark brown. Metanotum longer setae length = 2 OD. Metepisternum green with golden reflection; contiguously punctate, becoming crowded to rugose above metapleural pit. Hind leg: coxa mostly dark brown, except for coxae posterior surface green and trochanter and femur with faint blusih iridescences; femur outer surface with tiny setae among longer setae; basitarsus about 6x longer than maximum width, parallel sided. Metapostnotum green; about as long as metapostnotum; gently depressed transversally; mostly with sinuous radiating carinae, posteriorly rugose. Propodeum densely punctate (I &lt;0.5 PD), loosely imbricate in between; with long setae (2 OD) intermixed with tiny setae. - 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Metasoma</emphasis>
. T1 anterior surface sparsely punctate, punctures deep, loosely imbricate in between; only with long setae (2 OD). T1 dorsal surface mostly contiguously punctate, becoming densely punctate (I = 0.5 PD) towards apex, coarser punctures on lateral surfaces; mostly green with golden reflection, apical black band = 0.5 OD; apex not inflexed. T2 mostly green with golden reflection; mostly contiguously punctate, becoming sparser towards apex; marginal zone with punctate portion 3x longer than apical brown band on sublateral surfaces; T3 mostly green with golden reflection, apex darkened; punctate (I = PD), smooth in between. T4 mostly green with golden reflection, apex darkened; punctate (I = PD), smooth in between. T5 mostly green with golden reflection, apex darkened; sparsely punctate, punctures weak, smooth in between. T6 brown, with faint green reflection; weakly punctate. T7 light brown. S1 brown; with a slight longitudinal sulcus medially. long setae (&lt;2 OD) medially, margin with tiny decumbent setae. S2 mostly brown, apical portion yellowish; sparsely punctate, microreticulate in between; with short setae (= OD), more abundant near apex. S3-4 as S2. S5 apical portion not depressed; covered with tiny setaccurrihout medial glabrous path. S6 brown; with tiny setae, more abundant near apex. S7 lateral apodemes longer than half S8 width. S8 anterior projection more than four times longer than apical width; posterior margin acuminate. 
<emphasis bold="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Genitalia</emphasis>
: gonobase 2.0 times wider than long; gonobase ventral arms slightly curved on apex. Gonocoxite about 2.0 times longer than wide. Gonostylus, dorsal surface glabrous. Ventral process of gonostylus: inner lobe slender; with long and short setae intermixed; outer lobe with short setae with length = 0.7 inner lobe size. Gonapophysis ventral prong well produced and broad; dorsal bridge margin weakly projected; ventral bridge absent; apodeme narrow and strongly hooked.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">
Nominative feminine of 
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">intermedius</emphasis>
, meaning in the middle, a reference to intermixed features of 
<taxonomicName authorityName="Smith" authorityYear="1853" class="Insecta" family="Apoidea" genus="Augochlora" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Augochlora" order="Hymenoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="99" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<emphasis italics="true" pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Augochlora</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
subgenera found in this species.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Specimens were collected in Lima and La Libertad departments (Peru), western of Andean Mountains.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="99" type="comments">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">Comments.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="99">The holotype and a couple of paratypes have bluish reflections while remaining specimens are mostly green with few reddish reflections, besides this color variation the specimens have very similar body ornamentation and imperceptible differences in size.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>