<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.733.23126" ID-GBIF-Dataset="d1b8f315-e6cb-4d0e-8c35-77f8ef5786a7" ID-GBIF-Taxon="150742472" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1313-2970-733-119" ID-ZBK="58E27898-D720-4EDD-9715-D8018EB6D596" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A06D06E6-52F1-44F0-84A9-CC648422D095" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2018" ModsDocID="1313-2970-733-119" ModsDocOrigin="ZooKeys 733" ModsDocTitle="An early and mysterious histerid inquiline from Cretaceous Burmese amber (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" checkinTime="1517522972497" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Caterino, Michael S. &amp; Maddison, David R." docDate="2018" docId="6BCC66B66A4B898C31F34698E4552B75" docLanguage="en" docName="ZooKeys 733: 119-129" docOrigin="ZooKeys 733" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.733.23126" docTitle="Amplectister tenax Caterino &amp; Maddison, sp. n." docType="treatment" docUuid="A06D06E6-52F1-44F0-84A9-CC648422D095" docUuidSource="ZooBank" docVersion="4" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="125" masterDocId="6130EA5514325769A835FF8DFF94FF86" masterDocTitle="An early and mysterious histerid inquiline from Cretaceous Burmese amber (Coleoptera, Histeridae)" masterLastPageNumber="129" masterPageNumber="119" pageId="2" pageNumber="121" updateTime="1643517497023" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>An early and mysterious histerid inquiline from Cretaceous Burmese amber (Coleoptera, Histeridae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Caterino, Michael S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Maddison, David R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>ZooKeys</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2018</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>733</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>119</mods:start>
<mods:end>129</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.733.23126</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.733.23126</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1313-2970-733-119</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">58E27898-D720-4EDD-9715-D8018EB6D596</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="150742472" LSID="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A06D06E6-52F1-44F0-84A9-CC648422D095" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6BCC66B66A4B898C31F34698E4552B75" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="125" pageId="2" pageNumber="121">
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="121" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="121">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/A06D06E6-52F1-44F0-84A9-CC648422D095" authority="Caterino &amp; Maddison" authorityName="Caterino &amp; Maddison" authorityYear="2018" class="Insecta" family="Histeridae" genus="Amplectister" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Amplectister tenax" order="Coleoptera" pageId="2" pageNumber="121" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="tenax">Amplectister tenax Caterino &amp; Maddison</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="2" pageNumber="121">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="2" pageNumber="121" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="121">Type material.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="121">Holotype specimen, of unknown sex; type locality: Northern Myanmar: probably Hukawng Valley, collected in 2016; deposited in Oregon State Arthropod Collection, specimen OSAC_0002900057. The specimen was purchased by DRM from Yanling Ying in January 2017. Most of his specimens are from the Noije Bum mine or nearby, Kachin State; a few are from around Nam Sakhaw in Sagaing Division (NW of Haungpa); fewer are from elsewhere in other areas in Kachin State.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="125" pageId="2" pageNumber="121" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="121">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="2" pageNumber="121">Many body surfaces encrusted with thin off-white granular substance and/or thin film of air; textures and surface sculpture difficult to assess. An oblique planar fracture below the anterior part of the body distorts some observations of ventral anterior structures.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="122">
<pageBreakToken pageId="3" pageNumber="122" start="start">Total</pageBreakToken>
body (pronotum + elytra) length: 1.41 mm; maximum (humeral) width: 1.02 mm (for all measurements see Table 1). Body surfaces all apparently finely granulate, matte, possibly finely reticulate, not shiny; dorsal surface lacking obvious punctures; ventral surfaces distinctly punctate on most surfaces.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="122">Frons broad, anteriorly prominent (Figs 5-6); eyes present, large, located on sides of head; longitudinal supraocular ridges projecting anterad eyes, continued mediad by prominent, slightly oblique frontal ridges over antennal and mandibular insertions, frontal ridges possibly continuous medially (obscured); frontoclypeal suture not apparent (probably absent, but obscured); epistoma convex along longitudinal midline; labrum evenly rounded apically, convex, without major setae (though with short setal fringe around edges appressed to mandibles); mandibles apically acute, incisor edges short, neither with secondary tooth, left mandible overlapping right in repose; outer surface of mandibles weakly concave in basal half; head mostly retracted, ventral mouthparts not visible. Antennal scape short, expanded slightly to apex, bearing two elongate setae near apex; pedicel about one-third length of scape, subcylindrical; antennal funicle apparently with 6 more or less transverse antennomeres, gradually widening distad, with antennomere 8 nearly as wide as club; antennal club slightly elongate oval, weakly truncate apically, setose, bearing specialized setose patch on inner apical surface (Fig. 7), outer surface may be lightly sclerotized; antennal annuli not apparent.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="122">Pronotum (Figs 3, 5) rather broad, with deep anterior emargination; sides broadly rounded, distinctly widened from obtuse basal corners, widest about one-fourth from base, converging arcuately to rounded anterior corners; central part of pronotal disk convex, lateral margins depressed to broadly explanate, particularly in anterior corners, edges flattened, slightly reflexed.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="4" pageNumber="123">
<pageBreakToken pageId="4" pageNumber="123" start="start">Scutellum</pageBreakToken>
present, small, triangular; elytra (Fig. 3) broad, apparently asymmetrical (possibly optical distortion), the right tapered to a narrower apex than left, moderately flattened, lacking distinct striae but with weak serial depressions, posterolateral corners broadly rounded, apices truncate; each elytron with prominent marginal carina delimiting epipleuron extended from humeral corner around posterior corner, though not attaining apical midline; epipleuron (Fig. 4) with secondary carina extending from humeral corner about two-thirds epipleural length, there merging with lower elytral margin; elytral margin not carinate; metathoracic wings present (protruding slightly beneath posterolateral corner of left elytron).
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="5" pageNumber="124">
<pageBreakToken pageId="5" pageNumber="124" start="start">Propygidium</pageBreakToken>
(Fig. 3) exposed, wide, short, bearing numerous stiff setae (this is the only exposed sclerite for which this is true); pygidium subtriangular, with rounded sides and apex, disk depressed with a continuously elevated marginal carina; pygidium slightly opened, but genitalia obscured by air bubbles, sex undeterminable.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
<pageBreakToken pageId="6" pageNumber="125" start="start">Prosternum</pageBreakToken>
(Figs 2, 7) elevated at middle, anteriorly incised on either side of keel for passage of antennal funicle, with deep rounded depressions along keel and behind prosternal lobe for reception of antennal club; prosternal keel shallowly emarginate at base, keel elevated, with two prominent carinae, parallel from base to near apex, converging slightly above antennal cavities, distinctly depressed between; very short lateral carinae descend from inner anterior edge of profemur to join keel carinae behind antennal cavity; prosternal lobe minimal, forming broad flange delimiting front of antennal cavities, weakly emarginate where mandibles rest. Hypomeron broadly expanded laterally, with oblique longitudinal carina from anterior corner to near outer corner of profemoral insertion.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">Mesoventrite (Figs 2, 7) broad, anterior margin sinuate, weakly but distinctly produced at middle; mesometaventral suture apparently impressed (obscured); metaventrite with prominent, oblique postmesocoxal carinae extending from inner corners of mesocoxae to middle of metacoxa; middle of mesoventrite increasingly depressed posterad; laterally, mesepimeron, metepisternum, and metepimeron all distinct, apparently covered with large punctures (somewhat obscured), as is lateral portion of metaventrite.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">Abdominal venter (Fig. 2) deeply concave medially; sides of first ventrite elevated behind metacoxae, forming a distally setose lateral flange; subsequent ventrites transversely depressed, with abdomen deeply arched to pygidial apex.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">Legs (Figs 8-10): Procoxa moderately and obliquely transverse; protrochanter subquadrate, with inner corner prominent, setose; profemur narrowed to apex, with anterior, upper edge straight, inner edge weakly excavate for reception of protibia, inner posterior edge weakly expanded bearing few prominent setae; protibia narrow at base, widened weakly to apex, with two small apical spurs at inner corner, laterally with weakly bispinose apex, three to four weak denticles bearing small spines basad along margin, inner edge with series of ~8 fine spines; tarsal groove of anterior face of protibia poorly if at all developed; protarsomeres 1-4 short, subequal, bearing pair of ventral spines, apical tarsomere about three times length of tarsomere 4, with two ventral spines along midline, with pair of regular tarsal claws. Mesocoxa rounded; mesofemur narrowed to apex, with few prominent setae along anterior inner edge; mesotibia narrow, with weak apical spurs, outer edge slightly rounded, with single prominent spine at outer apical margin; outer posterior edge weakly grooved to receive tarsus; tarsus as for protarsus. Metacoxae rounded, widely separated; metatrochanter small, obscured, inserted at posterolateral corner of coxa; metafemur broad and thick, with prominent carinae along inner medial, outer medial, and dorsal margins (narrowly triangular in cross-section), inner surface weakly concave for reception of inner edge of metatibia; metatibia broad and flat, inner margin straight and bearing series of fine spines, outer margin rounded, smooth, inner surface with diffuse cluster of stiff setae about one-third from tibial base; metatarsus segmented as for meso- and protarsus, apparently received along apical half of outer edge of medial tibial face.</paragraph>
<caption ID-Table-UUID="A827AC6FCB219AF223993BD9E49E1B02" httpUri="http://table.plazi.org/id/A827AC6FCB219AF223993BD9E49E1B02" pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">Table 1. Body measurements in millimeters.</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
<table pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
<tr pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
<th colspan="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="125" rowspan="1">Measurement</th>
<th colspan="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="125" rowspan="1">mm</th>
</tr>
</table>
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">Figures 2-5. Photographs of holotype. 2 Ventral view 3 Dorsal view 4 Lateral view 5 Frontal view.</paragraph>
</caption>
<caption pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">Figures 6-10. Drawings from holotype. 6 Frontal view 7 Prosternum and antennae 8 Prothoracic leg, anterior view 9 Mesothoracic leg, anterior view 10 Metathoracic leg, anterior view.</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="6" pageNumber="125" type="derivation of specific epithet">
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">Derivation of specific epithet.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="6" pageNumber="125">
The species name means tenacious, referring to its grasp, from the Latin 
<taxonomicName lsidName="tenax" pageId="6" pageNumber="125" rank="species" species="tenax">tenax</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>