<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566" ID-GBIF-Dataset="eefaafbb-9c99-458a-b139-c4f7943c6303" ID-GBIF-Taxon="127856743" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1860-1324-1" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2014" ModsDocID="1860-1324-1" ModsDocOrigin="Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift 61 (1)" ModsDocTitle="A review of the genus Oosternum Sharp of the West Indies (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae: Sphaeridiinae)" checkinTime="1418151709527" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Deler-Hernandez, Albert, Cala-Riquelme, Franklyn &amp; Fikacek, Martin" docDate="2014" docId="909AAC28DCF9817DE419A429A69D5644" docLanguage="en" docName="DeutEntomolZeit 61(1): 43-63" docOrigin="Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift 61 (1)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566" docTitle="Oosternum pecki Deler-Hernandez, Cala-Riquelme &amp; Fikacek, 2014, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="5" lastPageNumber="43" masterDocId="FFECFFA4FFFEFFE7FFD46645CE45FFFA" masterDocTitle="A review of the genus Oosternum Sharp of the West Indies (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae: Sphaeridiinae)" masterLastPageNumber="63" masterPageNumber="43" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" updateTime="1643528765522" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of the genus Oosternum Sharp of the West Indies (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae: Sphaeridiinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Deler-Hernandez, Albert</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cala-Riquelme, Franklyn</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Fikacek, Martin</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2014</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>61</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>43</mods:start>
<mods:end>63</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/dez.61.7566</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1860-1324-1</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="127856743" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:909AAC28DCF9817DE419A429A69D5644" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/909AAC28DCF9817DE419A429A69D5644" lastPageNumber="43" pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/425E2398-6C4F-4966-A966-E7B1DD0C8207" class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Oosternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oosternum pecki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pecki">Oosternum pecki</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="0" pageNumber="43">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 15-1626334649525961
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="type-locality">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Type-locality.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Dominican Republic, Barahona: 
<geoCoordinate direction="north" orientation="latitude" precision="1" value="17.985237">
17°59
<normalizedToken originalValue="’06.85”">'06.85&quot;</normalizedToken>
N
</geoCoordinate>
, 
<geoCoordinate direction="west" orientation="longitude" precision="1" value="-71.21591">
71°12
<normalizedToken originalValue="’57.29”">'57.29&quot;</normalizedToken>
W
</geoCoordinate>
, 7 Km NW Paraiso, 200 m.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="type-specimens">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Type-specimens</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
(19 spec.). Holotype male, dry mounted, with genitalia mounted in Euparal on a microslide pinned below the specimen. Original label: &quot;DOM REP: Barahona: 7 Km NW Paraiso, 27.xi/04.xii.1991, Masner &amp; Peck, elevation 200 m, rainforest remnant, intercept tp. [printed] / Holotype, Oosternum pecki sp. n., 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Deler-Hernández">Deler-Hernandez</normalizedToken>
&amp; 
<normalizedToken originalValue="Fikáček">Fikacek</normalizedToken>
det. 2013 [red, printed]&quot; (CNC). Paratypes: DOMINICAN REPUBLIC: Barahona: same data as holotype (18 spec., CNC, NMPC, BSC-E, CMN, SEMC).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Diagnosis.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Body widest ca at midlength. Lateral margin of pronotum angulate. Pronotal punctation double-sized, dense consisting of moderately large round and rasp-like punctures. Pronotal interstices without microsculpture. Mesal part of prosternum not divided from lateral portions. Lateral margin of antennal grooves rounded. Elytral interval 2 narrower than interval 3, lower than intervals 1 and 3, reaching elytral apex. Elytral intervals 5, 7 and 9 distinctly higher than adjacent intervals. Elytral interstices shiny, without microsculpture. Preepisternal plate wide, subrhomboid, 2.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, largely overlapping over metaventrite. Interstices of median part of metaventrite without microsculpture. Anterolateral ridges of metaventrite not meeting together mesally. Parameres 1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than phallobase, bearing two long setae apically. Median lobe ca. as long as parameres, nearly parallel-sided basally, narrowing apicad in apical 0.2, apex rounded. Membranous lateral projections of median lobe absent.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Description.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Habitus. Body elongate oval, gradually narrowing posteriad; total lenght/total width ratio = 1.6. Length: 1.45-1.5 mm, length of holotype: 1.41 mm; width: 0.89-0.97 mm, width of holotype: 0.89 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Coloration. Coloration of dorsal side reddish brown. Ventral side brown to reddish brown. Femora, tibiae and antennal club pale reddish brown, tarsi and antennomeres 1-6 yellowish.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Head. Clypeus with sparse punctation consisting of fine punctures, each puncture bearing fine decumbent seta; setae pale; interstices without microsculpture; anterior margin of clypeus truncate. Frons with dense punctation consisting of small punctures of same shape medially and laterally; interstices without microsculpture. Eyes moderately large. Mentum 1.9
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
wider than long, anterior margin slightly emarginate; anteromedian part not distinctly impressed; with sparse punctation, punctation consisting of minute, nearly indistinct punctures bearing minute setae; interstices with fine microsculpture consisting of transverse ridges. Submentum without poriferous disc-like fields. Maxillary palpus with palpomeres 2 and 4 ca. 1.2
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than palpomere 3. Antenna with 9 antennomeres; scapus shorter than antennomeres 2-6 combined.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Prothorax. Pronotum evenly convex, forming continuous curve with elytra in lateral view. Lateral margin of pronotum angulate, with narrow marginal bead. Pronotal punctation double-sized, dense, slightly denser than on frons, consisting of transverse punctures anteriorly and large round punctures posteriorly; all punctures bearing long setae; interstices without microsculpture. Median portion of prosternum not elevated and demarcated from lateral portions, median carina of prosternum narrow projecting more anteriad mesally than anterior margin of median portion, with anterior portion elevated into small tooth in lateral view. Postero-mesal projection with deep notch. Antenal grooves moderately large. Lateral margin of antennal grooves rounded.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Mesothorax. Scutellar shield bearing a few small rasp-like punctures; interstices without microsculpture. Elytral series 1-5 and 8 arising basally, series 6-7 and 9 joint subbasally. Serial punctures small; transverse; sparsely arranged, with minute setae (indistinct under binocular microscope). Elytral interval 2 narrower than interval 3, lower than intervals 1 and 3, reaching elytral apex, intervals 5, 7 and 9 distinctly higher than adjacent intervals. Elytral interstices shiny, without microsculpture. Preepisternal plate wide, subrhomboid, 2.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide, widely attached to metaventrite; posterior part of preepisternal elevation much overlapping over anterior margin of metaventrite; median part flat; bearing densely arranged, large, shallow setiferous punctures; interstices without microsculpture.
</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Metathorax. Metaventrite distinctly shorter than preepisternal elevation of mesothorax, median portion markedly differing from lateral portion in punctation and microsculpture; punctation of median portion sparse, consisting of small rounded punctures, interstices without microsculpture, shiny. Anterolateral ridges bent posteriad along lateral margin of metaventrite, concave laterally, not meeting together mesally. Anterior margin of metaventrite not crenulate. Lateral margin with additional slightly concave ridge.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Abdomen. Ventrite 1 without additional longitudinal ridges laterally. Ventrites 2-5 without longitudinal ridges; posterior margin of all ventrites lacking denticles.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
Male genitalia. Aedeagus 0.57 mm long, parameres 1.1
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than phallobase. Parameres continuously narrowing apicad, bearing two long setae apically. Phallobase wide, 1.6
<normalizedToken originalValue="×">x</normalizedToken>
longer than wide. Median lobe ca. as long as parameres, nearly parallel-sided basally, narrowing apicad in apical 0.2, apex rounded. Membranous lateral projections of median lobe absent. Gonopore present.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Etymology.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
The new species is dedicated to Professor Stuart Peck (Carleton University, Canada) whose collecting trips accumulated a huge material of the West Indian 
<taxonomicName family="Hydrophilidae" lsidName="" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" rank="family">Hydrophilidae</taxonomicName>
, including many 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Oosternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oosternum" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">Oosternum</taxonomicName>
specimens used for this study.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Distribution.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Hydrophilidae" genus="Oosternum" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Oosternum pecki" order="Coleoptera" pageId="0" pageNumber="43" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="pecki">Oosternum pecki</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is a Hispaniolan endemic species currently known only from the type locality situated in the southern part of the Dominican Republic (Barahona province) (Fig. 61).
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="0" pageNumber="43" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Habitat.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="0" pageNumber="43">Based on the label data, the type specimens were collected in a remnant of the rain forest using a flight intercept trap.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>