<document ID-DOI="10.1206/0003-0090(2000)245&lt;0001:ARAROT&gt;2.0.CO;2" ID-ISSN="0003-0090" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5348675" approvalRequired="913" approvalRequired_for_taxonomicNames="14" approvalRequired_for_textStreams="877" approvalRequired_for_treatments="22" checkinTime="1630204009989" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="PLATNICK, NORMAN I." docDate="2000" docId="03B887CEB497FF09C668708FE39FF99D" docLanguage="en" docName="B245.pdf" docOrigin="Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 2000 (245)" docSource="http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/0003-0090%282000%29245%3C0001%3AARAROT%3E2.0.CO%3B2" docStyle="DocumentStyle:2B34016C1EBFE58B07368F9517618743.1:BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type1" docStyleId="2B34016C1EBFE58B07368F9517618743" docStyleName="BulAmeMusNatHis.2000-2010.journal_article.0cover.type1" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Centsymplia PLATNICK 2000, new genus" docType="treatment" docVersion="2" lastPageId="206" lastPageNumber="207" masterDocId="FF81FFB6B45BFFC7C576746FE37BFF9E" masterDocTitle="A Relimitation And Revision Of The Australasian Ground Spider Family Lamponidae (Araneae: Gnaphosoidea)" masterLastPageNumber="328" masterPageNumber="1" pageId="204" pageNumber="205" updateTime="1630470717368" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC-BY-4.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A Relimitation And Revision Of The Australasian Ground Spider Family Lamponidae (Araneae: Gnaphosoidea)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>PLATNICK, NORMAN I.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="pubDate">
<mods:number>2000-01-27</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>2000</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>245</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>328</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1206/0003-0090%282000%29245%3C0001%3AARAROT%3E2.0.CO%3B2</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.1206/0003-0090(2000)245&lt;0001:ARAROT&gt;2.0.CO;2</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">0003-0090</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5348675</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:03B887CEB497FF09C668708FE39FF99D" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B887CEB497FF09C668708FE39FF99D" lastPageId="206" lastPageNumber="207" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">
<subSubSection box="[798,1090,1248,1272]" pageId="204" pageNumber="205" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph blockId="204.[798,1090,1248,1272]" box="[798,1090,1248,1272]" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">
<heading box="[798,1090,1248,1272]" centered="true" fontSize="9" level="2" pageId="204" pageNumber="205" reason="2">
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2000" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2000" box="[798,947,1248,1272]" class="Arachnida" family="Lamponidae" genus="Centsymplia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="204" pageNumber="205" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus" status="new genus">
<emphasis bold="true" box="[798,947,1248,1272]" italics="true" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">Centsymplia</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[964,1090,1248,1271]" pageId="204" pageNumber="205" rank="genus">new genus</taxonomicNameLabel>
</heading>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="204" pageNumber="205" type="materials_examined">
<paragraph blockId="204.[680,1210,1300,1763]" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">
<typeStatus box="[709,767,1300,1323]" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">TYPE</typeStatus>
SPECIES: 
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2000" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2000" box="[887,1141,1300,1323]" class="Arachnida" family="Lamponidae" genus="Centsymplia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="204" pageNumber="205" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="glorious" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[887,1141,1300,1323]" italics="true" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">Centsymplia glorious</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="204" pageNumber="205" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="204" pageNumber="205" type="etymology">
<paragraph blockId="204.[680,1210,1300,1763]" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">ETYMOLOGY: The generic name is an arbitrary combination of letters, considered feminine in gender.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="204" pageNumber="205" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph blockId="204.[680,1210,1300,1763]" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">DIAGNOSIS: Members of this genus are most easily recognized by their odd genitalic characters: males have a tiny median apophysis (fig. 506) and long, twisted retrolateral tibial apophysis (fig. 507); females have a long, triangular epigynum (fig. 508) with the ducts restricted to its posterior portion (fig. 509).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection lastPageId="206" lastPageNumber="207" pageId="204" pageNumber="205" type="description">
<paragraph blockId="204.[680,1210,1300,1763]" lastBlockId="205.[670,1199,214,1762]" lastPageId="205" lastPageNumber="206" pageId="204" pageNumber="205">DESCRIPTION: Medium spiders, total length 4.6–6.1. Carapace brown, pars cephalica lightest, pars thoracica with few rows of slightly darkened maculations radiating from thoracic groove, with setae largely restricted to ocular area; thoracic groove long, longitudinal. Eight eyes in two rows, anterior medians largest, circular, dark, laterals subequal in size, oval, light, posterior medians smallest, irregularly oval, flattened, light; from above, anterior eye row slightly recurved, posterior row slightly procurved, from front, anterior row slightly procurved, posterior row strongly procurved; anterior medians separated by more than their radius, closer to anterior laterals; posterior medians separated by more than their diameter, farther from posterior laterals; anterior and posterior laterals separated by less than their radius; median ocular quadrangle slightly wider in back than in front, wider in front than long. Chelicerae, sternum, and mouthparts brown; chilum wide, triangular, accompanied by second, dumbbell­shaped posterior chilum (extremely narrow sclerite separating bases of chelicerae posteriorly); chelicerae with distinct, orange lateral boss, anterior surface with depressed, relatively unsclerotized oval area near promargin; promargin with row of long setae originating in line along base of fang, seta closest to fang bent near base at almost 908 angle, extending behind other promarginal setae to near midline; promargin with three teeth, median one largest, proximal one smallest; retromargin with two large, widely separated teeth. Labium elongate, base narrowed at about one­third of labial length, posterior margin truncate, anterior margin medially invaginated, surface not depressed medially. Endites obliquely depressed, with poorly demarcated, deep, wide groove along margin near labium, groove wider anteriorly than posteriorly; serrula long, with single row of teeth. Sternum not elevated, with flat, rebordered lateral margins, not expanded anteriorly, with triangular extensions to and between coxae; surface not tuberculate, with slight elevations opposite, and depressions between, coxae. One epimeric sclerite on each side, above each coxa, reaching sternal triangles only by narrow strips of weakly sclerotized cuticle (strongest strip between coxae II and III), not fused to carapace. Pedicel consisting of small, diamond­shaped sclerite bearing short dorsal and ventral tri­ angular ledges; anteroventral edge of sclerite reaching posterior tip of sternum.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[670,1199,214,1762]" pageId="205" pageNumber="206">Anterior edge of abdomen of male with complete sclerotic ring formed by strong epigastric scutum plus weaker dorsal abdominal scutum covering entire front edge of abdomen, reaching to about seven­eighths of abdominal length, females with dorsal scutum represented only by small semicircular plate above pedicel, restricted to anterior surface of abdomen; cuticle with short, recumbent setae; epigastric scutum accompanied posterolaterally by pair of oval, deeply invaginated sclerites bearing clearly elevated anterior rim; sclerites separated by membranous lobe, anterior rim of sclerites fitting under epigastric scutum; colulus represented only by setae on slight sclerotization; tiny transverse sclerite, well removed from spinnerets, marking position of small posterior spiracle. Anterior lateral spinnerets tubular, separated by almost their diameter, cuticle representing distal, second spinneret segment restricted to semicircle surrounding major ampullate gland spigots (piriform gland spigots surrounded only by soft cuticle); posterior median spinnerets of males large, tubular, of females with anteriorly expanded tips, bases occupied by three enormously widened cylindrical gland spigots; posterior lateral spinnerets two­segmented, those of female with one enormously widened cylindrical gland spigot.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="205.[670,1199,214,1762]" lastBlockId="206.[104,633,1134,1539]" lastPageId="206" lastPageNumber="207" pageId="205" pageNumber="206">Leg spination reduced only on anterior legs; typical leg spination pattern (only surfaces with spines listed): femora I, II d1­0­0, p0­0­1; III, IV d1­0­0; tibiae III, IV p0­1­1, v2­1p­2, r0­1­1; metatarsi III, IV p1­0­0, v2­ 1p­0, r1­0­0. Most leg surfaces with coated with short setae; males with all coxae and trochanters dorsally tuberculate; anterior coxae with slightly protuberant posterolateral corners; trochanters slightly notched; anterior metatarsi and tarsi with divided scopulae, composed of laterally directed setae; posterior metatarsi with thick, dark, distal preening brushes; tarsi III, IV with entire scopulae; tarsi with two dentate claws, claw tufts composed of few lateral pads of closely appressed setae; trichobothria in two rows on metatarsi and tarsi. Female palpal femur, patella, tibia, and tarsus with strong prolateral spines; female palpal tarsus with long, basally dentate claw.</paragraph>
<caption ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5349074" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5349074" httpUri="https://zenodo.org/record/5349074/files/figure.png" pageId="206" pageNumber="207" startId="206.[130,178,1021,1042]" targetBox="[106,1210,212,998]" targetPageId="206">
<paragraph blockId="206.[104,1208,1021,1069]" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">
Figs. 506–509. 
<taxonomicName authority="PLATNICK, 2000" authorityName="PLATNICK" authorityYear="2000" box="[316,544,1022,1043]" class="Arachnida" family="Lamponidae" genus="Centsymplia" kingdom="Animalia" order="Araneae" pageId="206" pageNumber="207" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="glorious" status="new species">
<emphasis box="[316,544,1022,1043]" italics="true" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">Centsymplia glorious</emphasis>
</taxonomicName>
, 
<taxonomicNameLabel box="[561,693,1021,1042]" pageId="206" pageNumber="207" rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[706,752,1021,1042]" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">506.</emphasis>
Left male palp, ventral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[1088,1134,1021,1042]" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">507.</emphasis>
Same, retrolateral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[293,339,1048,1069]" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">508.</emphasis>
Epigynum, ventral view. 
<emphasis bold="true" box="[619,665,1048,1069]" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">509.</emphasis>
Same, dorsal view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
<paragraph blockId="206.[104,633,1134,1539]" pageId="206" pageNumber="207">Male palp with long retrolateral tibial apophysis; cymbial surface excavated opposite tibial apophysis; tegulum expanded at proventral corner, bearing tiny, vestigial median apophysis opposing small terminal apophysis; embolus originating prolaterally, long, wide, accompanied distally by membranous conductor. Epigynum with anterior hood and shallow atrium; spermathecae accompanied medially by pair of longitudinal ducts, all restricted to posterior portion of epigynum.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>