<document ID-DOI="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jor.26.15289" ID-GBIF-Dataset="b3a14b71-e2d0-4eaa-a938-f86eb8335141" ID-GBIF-Taxon="157251651" ID-Pensoft-Pub="1937-2426-2-181" ModsDocAuthor="" ModsDocDate="2017" ModsDocID="1937-2426-2-181" ModsDocOrigin="Journal of Orthoptera Research 26 (2)" ModsDocTitle="Contribution to the knowledge of Oriental Phasmatodea I: A taxonomic study of the genus Parasinophasma (Phasmatodea: Necrosciinae)" checkinTime="1558621696502" checkinUser="pensoft" docAuthor="Ho, George Wai-Chun" docDate="2017" docId="6189068BA314B213EB018F903D84E89A" docLanguage="en" docName="JourOrthoptRes 26(2): 181-194" docOrigin="Journal of Orthoptera Research 26 (2)" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jor.26.15289" docTitle="Parasinophasma laifanae Ho, 2017, sp. n." docType="treatment" docVersion="4" lastPageNumber="184" masterDocId="A640FFA9B322CA7E1C100B45B519FFFD" masterDocTitle="Contribution to the knowledge of Oriental Phasmatodea I: A taxonomic study of the genus Parasinophasma (Phasmatodea: Necrosciinae)" masterLastPageNumber="194" masterPageNumber="181" pageId="3" pageNumber="184" updateTime="1643480484260" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Contribution to the knowledge of Oriental Phasmatodea I: A taxonomic study of the genus Parasinophasma (Phasmatodea: Necrosciinae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Ho, George Wai-Chun</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of Orthoptera Research</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2017</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>26</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>2</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>181</mods:start>
<mods:end>194</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jor.26.15289</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jor.26.15289</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Pensoft-Pub">1937-2426-2-181</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-GBIF-Taxon="157251651" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:6189068BA314B213EB018F903D84E89A" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6189068BA314B213EB018F903D84E89A" lastPageNumber="184" pageId="3" pageNumber="184">
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">
<taxonomicName LSID="http://zoobank.org/5FC56E3D-2230-4EC5-A639-863553275CAD" class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Parasinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parasinophasma laifanae" order="Phasmatodea" pageId="3" pageNumber="184" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laifanae">Parasinophasma laifanae</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel pageId="3" pageNumber="184">sp. n.</taxonomicNameLabel>
Figs 8-14, 44-51
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="type material">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Type material.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Holotype ♂, Fung Wong Shan, Lantau Island, Hong Kong, 20.VIII.2016, George Ho Wai-Chun (HKES); Paratypes 1♂ and 1♀, Fung Wong Shan, Lantau Island, Hong Kong, 20.VIII.2016, George Ho Wai-Chun (HKES); 5♂, 2♀ and 17 eggs (naturally laid by 1 paratype ♀), Fung Wong Shan, Lantau Island, Hong Kong, 16.IX.2016, George Ho Wai-Chun (HKES); 1♂, Fung Wong Shan, Lantau Island, Hong Kong, 4.VIII.2017, George Ho Wai-Chun (HKES); 2♂, 1♀ and 3 eggs (naturally laid by paratype ♀), Fung Wong Shan, Lantau Island, Hong Kong, 7.IX.2017, George Ho Wai-Chun (HKES); 1♂, Fung Wong Shan, Lantau Island, Hong Kong, 9.X.2017, George Ho Wai-Chun (HKES); 1♂, Fung Wong Shan, Lantau Island, Hong Kong, 4.XI.2017, George Ho Wai-Chun (HKES).</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="diagnosis">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Diagnosis.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Parasinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parasinophasma laifanae" order="Phasmida" pageId="3" pageNumber="184" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laifanae">Parasinophasma laifanae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. guangdongense" pageId="3" pageNumber="184" rank="species" species="guangdongense">P. guangdongense</taxonomicName>
Chen &amp; He, 2008, but can be distinguished by non-elongate ninth abdominal tergum and notched posterior margin on poculum in male. The female of 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. laifanae" pageId="3" pageNumber="184" rank="species" species="laifanae">P. laifanae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. is similar to 
<taxonomicName genus="P." lsidName="P. henanense" pageId="3" pageNumber="184" rank="species" species="henanense">P. henanense</taxonomicName>
(Bi &amp; Wang, 1998), but can be easily separated by tubercle-like praeopercular organ on seventh abdominal sternum and basal elevations on anterodorsal, posterodorsal, anteroventral and posteroventral carinae of mesofemora and metafemora.
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Description.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Male (Figs 8-9, 14, 44-46, 50): Medium-sized, more slender than female. Head oblong, longer than wide, lacking granulation. Vertex flat, lacking ocelli. Occiput distinctly convex, with distinct median and lateral longitudinal furrows. Compound eyes big and rounded, length about two times that of genae. Antennae filiform, densely covered with short bristles; scapus flattened basally, longer than pedicellus; third segment almost as long as scapus. Pronotum with small and inconspicuous granulations, rectangular, longer than wide, shorter than head; anterior margin weakly curved inwards, nearly truncate, posterior margin rounded, transverse and longitudinal sulci crossing before middle point. Mesonotum sparsely covered with small granules, parallel-sided, median longitudinal carina distinct. Mesopleurae and mesosternum with small and inconspicuous granulation. Metapleurae and metasternum lacking granulation. Abdomen smooth, lacking granulation. Second to seventh tergites parallel-sided. Eighth tergum expanded posteriorly, as long as ninth tergum. Ninth tergum with distinct posterolateral angles. Anal segment shorter than ninth tergum, medially tapering posteriorly, posterior margin bifurcated. Epiproct small and indistinct, posterior margin truncate. Poculum cup-shaped, posterior margin notched and reaching anterior area of anal segment. Cerci with a small spine-like appendage near middle area; cylindrical, tapering posteriorly, apices curved inwards and reaching posterior margin of anal segment. Vomer minute, apical part fork-like, nearly symmetric, distinctly constricted apically, apex distinctly emarginated forming two slightly apically pointed lateral elevations, left elevation slightly larger than right elevation in anteroventral view. Legs sparsely covered with short bristles. Unarmed. Profemora distinctly curved basally. All tibiae roughly as long as corresponding femora. Tegmina small and oval, shorter than head, posterior margin truncate. Alae long, posterior apices reaching anterior margin of sixth abdominal tergum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Coloration: General color of body brown. Scapus and pedicellus light brown, other antennal segments dark brown. Mesonotum marked with a black line on each side of lateral margins. Abdomen brown with blackish maculations. Profemora and protibiae dark brown with black maculations. Protarsi brown. Mesofemora, mesotibiae, mesotarsi, metafemora, metatibiae and metatarsi green with blackish apices. Tegmina light brown, with black and green maculations. Alae grayish brown with black maculations.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Female (Figs 10-11, 47-49, 51): Medium-sized. Body slender, distinctly larger and more robust than male. Head oblong, longer than wide, lacking granulation. Vertex flat. Occiput conically convex, with distinct median longitudinal furrow, lateral longitudinal furrows indistinct. Compound eyes rounded, length about three times that of genae. Antennae filiform, sparsely covered with short bristles; scapus flattened, longer than pedicellus; pedicellus as long as third segment. Pronotum with small and inconspicuous granulation, rectangular, longer than wide, shorter than head; anterior margin curved inwards, posterior margin rounded, transverse and longitudinal sulci crossing before middle point. Mesonotum covered with a few small black granules; roughly as long as combined length of metanotum and median segment, parallel-sided, median longitudinal line distinct, post-median area with a pair of obscurely elevated humps. Mesopleurae, mesosternum, metapleurae and metasternum sparsely covered with a few small granules. Abdomen cylindrical, lacking granulation. Second to sixth sternites with a small elevation posteromedially. Seventh sternum with distinct tubercle-like praeopercular organ posteromedially. Eighth tergum longer than anal segment. Ninth tergum shorter than eighth tergum. Anal segment longer than ninth tergum, with a small V-shaped emargination on posterior margin. Supra-anal plate small, posterior margin truncate. Subgenital plate scoop-shaped, apex pointed and reaching anterior area of anal segment. Gonapophyses not exposed, apex reaching posterior apex of subgenital plate. Cerci short, cylindrical, tapering apically and reaching posterolateral angles of anal segment. Legs sparsely covered with short bristles. Unarmed. Profemora distinctly curved basally. Anterodorsal, posterodorsal, anteroventral and posteroventral carinae of mesofemora and metafemora weakly elevated basally. Tegmina oval, tapering anteriorly, posterior margin subtruncate, longer than pronotum. Alae long, posterior apices just reaching anterior margin of sixth abdominal tergum.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Coloration: General color of body grayish brown. Legs grayish brown with black maculations. Tegmina and alae grayish brown with pale brown and black maculations. Anal region of alae gray, with brown spots.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Measurements.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">(mm) Holotype ♂, Body length: 68, head: 4, antennae: 50, pronotum: 3, mesonotum: 10.5, metanotum including median segment: 10, profemora: 18.5, mesofemora: 12, metafemora: 18, protibiae: 17, mesotibiae: 10.5, metatibiae: 17, tegmina: 4, alae: 34. Paratypes ♂, Body length: 64-72, head: 4, antennae: 48-52, pronotum: 3, mesonotum: 10-11, metanotum including median segment: 9-10, profemora: 18-20, mesofemora: 11.5-12, metafemora: 16.5-19.5, protibiae: 17-19, mesotibiae: 10-11, metatibiae: 17-18, tegmina: 4, alae: 33-35. Paratypes ♀, Body length: 87-92, head: 6, antennae: 45-47, pronotum: 4, mesonotum: 12-14, metanotum including median segment: 12-13, profemora: 18, mesofemora: 10-11, metafemora: 15-16, protibiae: 16-17, mesotibiae: 8.5-9, metatibiae: 14-15, tegmina: 6, alae: 42-44.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Eggs (Figs 12-13): Capsule black with minute granulations, strongly carinate; oval, tapering posteriorly, posterior pole rounded. Micropylar plate oval, anterior apex pointed, posterior apex rounded. Micropylar cup placed at posterior apex of micropylar plate. Median line short, about one-fourth of the length of micropylar plate, placed after micropylar cup. Operculum black with minute granulations, gently convex medially, marginally thickened.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="description">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Measurements.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">(mm) Length: 3, width: 1.4, height: 1.6.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="distribution">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Distribution.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Hong Kong.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="habitat">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Habitats.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">This species inhabits the middle level of evergreen broadleaf forests.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection pageId="3" pageNumber="184" type="etymology">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">Etymology.-</paragraph>
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">
This new species is named in honor of Lee Lai-Fan (the co-discoverer of this new species from Hong Kong) for her constant support during the 
<normalizedToken originalValue="author’s">author's</normalizedToken>
phasmid research.
</paragraph>
<caption pageId="3" pageNumber="184">
<paragraph pageId="3" pageNumber="184">
Figure 8-14. 
<taxonomicName class="Insecta" family="Diapheromeridae" genus="Parasinophasma" higherTaxonomySource="CoL" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Parasinophasma laifanae" order="Phasmida" pageId="3" pageNumber="184" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="laifanae">Parasinophasma laifanae</taxonomicName>
sp. n. 8. ♂, apex of abdomen, lateral view; 9. ♂, apex of abdomen, dorsal view; 10. ♀, apex of abdomen, lateral view; 11. ♀, apex of abdomen, dorsal view; 12. Egg, lateral view; 13. Egg, dorsal view; 14. ♂, vomer, ventral view.
</paragraph>
</caption>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>