<document ENCODING="UTF-8" ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284662" ID-GBIF-Dataset="5f96e565-1778-4154-8f67-81830690657d" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135914" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284662" ModsDocID="6751" checkinTime="1243377290804" checkinUser="christiana" docAuthor="Brown, W. L." docDate="1975" docId="AADFCED4B124B8FA81F7613620FBDE19" docLanguage="en" docName="6751" docOrigin="Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station 15" docSource="http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf" docTitle="Cerapachys luteoviger Brown, 1975, new species" docType="treatment" docVersion="9" lastPageNumber="70" masterDocId="5EF94453F8BE2CD657C7B1F34B08FD04" masterDocTitle="Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini." masterLastPageNumber="115" masterPageNumber="1" pageNumber="70" updateTime="1645811814098" updateUser="ExternalLinkService">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Contributions toward a reclassification of the Formicidae. V. Ponerinae, tribes Platythyreini, Cerapachyini, Cylindromyrmecini, Acanthostichini, and Aenictogitini.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Brown, W. L.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Search: Agriculture; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>1975</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>15</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>1</mods:start>
<mods:end>115</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://antbase.org/ants/publications/6751/6751.pdf</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="HNS-PUB">6751</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ZooBank">45422C7B-83F2-4F5A-9EE4-74C51F2C2BFE</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<treatment ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6284662" ID-GBIF-Taxon="125135914" ID-Zenodo-Dep="6284662" LSID="urn:lsid:plazi:treatment:AADFCED4B124B8FA81F7613620FBDE19" httpUri="http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AADFCED4B124B8FA81F7613620FBDE19" lastPageNumber="70" pageNumber="70">
<subSubSection type="nomenclature">
<paragraph pageNumber="70">
[57] 
<taxonomicName LSID-HNS="urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:27936" class="Insecta" family="Formicidae" genus="Cerapachys" kingdom="Animalia" lsidName="Cerapachys luteoviger Brown" lsidName-HNS="Cerapachys luteoviger Brown" order="Hymenoptera" pageNumber="70" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="species" species="luteoviger">Cerapachys luteoviger</taxonomicName>
<taxonomicNameLabel rank="species">new species</taxonomicNameLabel>
</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="description">
<paragraph pageNumber="70">(Figs. 54 - 57, 90, 91, 93)</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Holotype worker: TL 4.0, HL 0.82, HW 0.67 (CI 82), ML 0.10, scape L 0.53, greatest diameter of eye 0.20, WL 1.06, petiolar node L 0.37, W 0.49, postpetiole L 0.46, W 0.62 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Paratype workers (9 from type colony): TL 3.9 - 4.0, HL 0.80 - 0.81, HW 0.65 - 0.68 (CI 81 - 84), ML 0.09 - 0.10, scape L 0.46 - 0.51, greatest diameter of eye 0.18 - 0.20, WL 1.01 - 1.04, petiolar node L 0.36 - 0.38, W 0.44 - 0.48, postpetiole L 0.42 - 0.46, W 0.57 - 0.60 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Head, mandibles, and antennae shown in figs. 54, 55, 90, and 93. Posterior border straight to feebly convex when head is viewed full face. Median carina or tubercle of clypeus not well developed, not toothlike seen in full-face view (fig. 55). Trunk short and high, evenly convex above, parallel-sided, with transverse pronotal carina complete and forming subrectangular humeri as seen from above. Declivity of propodeum with carinate lateral margins, incomplete above in the middle.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Petiolar node distinctive in shape, as shown in figs. 56, 57, and 91; anterodorsal border concavely marginate (fig. 91). The body is smooth and shining, with spaced piligerous punctures as shown in the figures, except for petiole and base of first gastric tergum, which are more crowded with coarse punctures or foveolae (fig. 56), and postpetiole, which is densely covered with coarse and fine continguous to subcontiguous piligerous punctures and very abundant longer and shorter decumbent hairs, consequently, its general surface only weakly shining. Posterior half of gaster smooth and shining, with only scattered, fine punctures. Propodeal declivity and anterior face of petiolar node smooth, shining, densely punctulate, and with a very fine appressed pubescence. Antennae and legs with moderate decumbent pubescence and some longer decumbent hairs (longer erect hairs also on scapes). Longer erect and suberect hairs of body moderately abundant, more abundant on postpetiole and gaster. Pygidium densely punctate, with a smooth, shining median strip; spinules in a single row on each side of apex. Inner genual plate of hind coxae sharp and forming a crescentic margin, but not expanded as a lobe.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Color light ferruginous red, with posterior sides of trunk darker, more brownish. Apical segment of antenna light yellow, contrasting with the red of the rest of the body and appendages.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Queen (ergatoid): TL 4.5, HL 0.87, HW 0.73, (CI 84), ML 0.08, scape L 0.55, greatest diameter of eye 0.19, WL 1.21, petiolar node L 0.45, W 0.54, postpetiole L 0.52, W 0.78 mm.</paragraph>
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Though this individual is very like the accompanying workers except in its notably larger size and bulkier body (especially the gaster), even Wilson, the original collector, noted that in life it seemed to be the &quot; ergatoid queen. &quot; I can find no distinct ocelli, though ocellar pits would be difficult to distinguish from the punctate sculpture. There is a distinct indentation on the mid-vertex, about where an anterior median ocellus would normally be found. The sculpture is perhaps a little more distinct than in the workers, and the petiolar summit is at least as sharply rounded as in the worker. The hairs of the pilosity are fine and tend to be more sharply erect than in the worker. Color as in worker.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="materials_examined">
<paragraph pageNumber="70">Holotype (MCZ) taken from a small colony with the ergatoid queen from a piece of &quot; Passalus-stage &quot; rotten wood lying on the ground in forest at Gilimale, 16 - 20 km NE of Ratnapura, Sri Lanka (Ceylon), 18 - 21 July 1955, E. O. Wilson No. 1326. Wilson noted that the ants were very &quot; nervous and active &quot; in life. Paratypes in MCZ, BMNH — London, MHN — Geneva, and ANIC — Canberra.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
<subSubSection type="discussion">
<paragraph pageNumber="70">This species is a member of the dohertyi group of the Indo-Melanesian area. Its closest relatives are 2 - 3 undescribed species from this general area, but it differs from all of these in details of head shape and sculpture, in the shape of the petiolar node apex, and in the color pattern; the yellow ovoidal apical segment of the antenna is characteristic and gives the ant its name.</paragraph>
</subSubSection>
</treatment>
</document>